<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 02:35:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale simulation of neutral particle flows in the plasma edge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08575v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The plasma edge flow, situated at the intricate boundary between plasma and neutral particles, plays a pivotal role in the design of nuclear fusion devices such as divertors and pumps. Traditional numerical simulation methods, such as the direct simulation Monte Carlo approach and the discrete velocity method, are hindered by extensive computation times when dealing with near-continuum flow conditions. This paper presents a general synthetic iterative scheme to deterministically simulate the plasma edge flows. By alternately solving the kinetic equations and macroscopic synthetic equations, our method substantially decreases the number of iterations, while maintains asymptotic-preserving properties even when the spatial cell size is much larger than the mean free path. Consequently, our approach achieves rapid convergence and high accuracy in plasma edge flow simulations, particularly in near-continuum flow regimes. This advancement provides a robust and efficient computational tool, essential for the advancement of next-generation nuclear fusion reactors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08575v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Wen, Yanbing Zhang, Lei Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combustion Instabilities in Complex Chamber Geometries of Solid Propellant Rocket Motors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-frequency combustion instabilities can lead to significant fluctuations in chamber pressure, affecting the structural integrity and performance of solid rocket motors. Since these instabilities manifest as acoustic oscillations during combustion, a mathematical model has been developed to calculate the chamber modes, providing an accurate method for predicting the acoustic behaviour of the combustion chamber. A novel method for discretising the Laplacian operator is introduced, which allows the calculation of the acoustic modes of complex chamber geometries. This approach uses an efficient numerical algorithm designed for unstructured mesh configurations. Several computational examples are presented to demonstrate the application of the model to complex geometries typical of solid rocket motors. In addition, an analytical procedure is developed in these examples to aid the design process, providing engineers with critical data to optimise the stability and performance of propulsion systems. This research provides valuable insights into the analysis of combustion instabilities, with broad implications for the design and optimisation of propulsion systems in aerospace engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08731v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan M. Tiz\'on, Antoni M. Barredo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linearization Routines for the Parameter Space Concept to determine Crystal Structures without Fourier Inversion (Centrosymmetric cases in two and three-dimensional parameter space)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present detailed elaboration and first generally applicable linearization routines of the \textit{Parameter Space Concept} (PSC) for determining 1-dimensionally projected structures of $m$ independent scatterers. This crystal determination approach does not rely on Fourier inversion but rather considers all structure parameter combinations consistent with available diffraction data in a parameter space of dimension $m$. The method utilizes $m$ structure factor amplitudes or intensities represented by piece-wise analytic hyper-surfaces, to define the acceptable parameter regions. By employing the isosurfaces, the coordinates of the point scatterers are obtained through the intersection of multiple isosurfaces. This approach allows for the detection of all possible solutions for the given structure factor amplitudes in a single derivation. Taking the resonant contrast into account, the spatial resolution achieved by the presented method may exceed that of traditional Fourier inversion, and the algorithms can be significantly optimized by exploiting the symmetry properties of the isosurfaces. The applied 1-dimensional projection demonstrates the efficiency of the PSC linearization approach based on fewer reflections than Fourier sums. The Monte-Carlo simulations, using the projections of various random two- and three-atom structure examples, are presented to illustrate the universal applicability of the proposed method. Furthermore, ongoing efforts aim to enhance the efficiency of data handling and to overcome current constraints, promising further advancements in the capabilities and accuracy of the PSC framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08845v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muthu Vallinayagam, Melanie Nentwich, Dirk C. Meyer, Matthias Zschornak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple scales analysis of a nonlinear timestepping instability in simulations of solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07286v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The susceptibility of timestepping algorithms to numerical instabilities is an important consideration when simulating partial differential equations (PDEs). Here we identify and analyze a pernicious numerical instability arising in pseudospectral simulations of nonlinear wave propagation resulting in finite-time blow-up. The blow-up time scale is independent of the spatial resolution and spectral basis but sensitive to the timestepping scheme and the timestep size. The instability appears in multi-step and multi-stage implicit-explicit (IMEX) timestepping schemes of different orders of accuracy and has been found to manifest in simulations of soliton solutions of the Korteweg-de Vries (KdV) equation and traveling wave solutions of a nonlinear generalized Klein-Gordon equation. Focusing on the case of KdV solitons, we show that modal predictions from linear stability theory are unable to explain the instability because the spurious growth from linear dispersion is small and nonlinear sources of error growth converge too slowly in the limit of small timestep size. We then develop a novel multi-scale asymptotic framework that captures the slow, nonlinear accumulation of timestepping errors. The framework allows the solution to vary with respect to multiple time scales related to the timestep size and thus recovers the instability as a function of a slow time scale dictated by the order of accuracy of the timestepping scheme. We show that this approach correctly describes our simulations of solitons by making accurate predictions of the blow-up time scale and transient features of the instability. Our work demonstrates that studies of long-time simulations of nonlinear waves should exercise caution when validating their timestepping schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07286v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin A. Hyatt, Daniel Lecoanet, Evan H. Anders, Keaton J. Burns</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biodynamic Analysis of Alpine Skiing with a Skier-Ski-Snow Interaction Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08056v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study establishes a skier-ski-snow interaction (SSSI) model that integrates a 3D full-body musculoskeletal model, a flexible ski model, a ski-snow contact model, and an air resistance model. An experimental method is developed to collect kinematic and kinetic data using IMUs, GPS, and plantar pressure measurement insoles, which are cost-effective and capable of capturing motion in large-scale field conditions. The ski-snow interaction parameters are optimized for dynamic alignment with snow conditions and individual turning techniques. Forward-inverse dynamics simulation is performed using only the skier's posture as model input and leaving the translational degrees of freedom (DOFs) between the pelvis and the ground unconstrained. The effectiveness of our model is further verified by comparing the simulated results with the collected GPS and plantar pressure data. The correlation coefficient between the simulated ski-snow contact force and the measured plantar pressure data is 0.964, and the error between the predicted motion trajectory and GPS data is 0.7%. By extracting kinematic and kinetic parameters from skiers of different skill levels, quantitative performance analysis helps quantify ski training. The SSSI model with the parameter optimization algorithm of the ski-snow interaction allows for the description of skiing characteristics across varied snow conditions and different turning techniques, such as carving and skidding. Our research advances the understanding of alpine skiing dynamics, informing the development of training programs and facility designs to enhance athlete performance and safety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08056v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan Gao (Department of Engineering Mechanics, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China), Huitong Jin (Department of Engineering Mechanics, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China), Jianqiao Guo (MOE Key Laboratory of Dynamics and Control of Flight Vehicle, School of Aerospace Engineering, Beijing Institute of Technology, Beijing, China), Gexue Ren (Department of Engineering Mechanics, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China), Chun Yang (Department of Engineering Mechanics, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Neural Networks with Complementary Soft and Hard Constraints for Solving Complex Boundary Navier-Stokes Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08122v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Soft- and hard-constrained Physics Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) have achieved great success in solving partial differential equations (PDEs). However, these methods still face great challenges when solving the Navier-Stokes equations (NSEs) with complex boundary conditions. To address these challenges, this paper introduces a novel complementary scheme combining soft and hard constraint PINN methods. The soft-constrained part is thus formulated to obtain the preliminary results with a lighter training burden, upon which refined results are then achieved using a more sophisticated hard-constrained mechanism with a primary network and a distance metric network. Specifically, the soft-constrained part focuses on boundary points, while the primary network emphasizes inner domain points, primarily through PDE loss. Additionally, the novel distance metric network is proposed to predict the power function of the distance from a point to the boundaries, which serves as the weighting factor for the first two components. This approach ensures accurate predictions for both boundary and inner domain areas. The effectiveness of the proposed method on the NSEs problem with complex boundary conditions is demonstrated by solving a 2D cylinder wake problem and a 2D blocked cavity flow with a segmented inlet problem, achieving significantly higher accuracy compared to traditional soft- and hard-constrained PINN approaches. Given PINN's inherent advantages in solving the inverse and the large-scale problems, which are challenging for traditional computational fluid dynamics (CFD) methods, this approach holds promise for the inverse design of required flow fields by specifically-designed boundary conditions and the reconstruction of large-scale flow fields by adding a limited number of training input points. The code for our approach will be made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08122v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuyu Zhou, Tianyu Li, Chenxi Lan, Rongyu Du, Guoguo Xin, Pengyu Nan, Hangzhou Yang, Guoqing Wang, Xun Liu, Wei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BOSON$^{-1}$: Understanding and Enabling Physically-Robust Photonic Inverse Design with Adaptive Variation-Aware Subspace Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08210v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nanophotonic device design aims to optimize photonic structures to meet specific requirements across various applications. Inverse design has unlocked non-intuitive, high-dimensional design spaces, enabling the discovery of high-performance devices beyond heuristic or analytic methods. The adjoint method, which calculates gradients for all variables using just two simulations, enables efficient navigation of this complex space. However, many inverse-designed structures, while numerically plausible, are difficult to fabricate and sensitive to variations, limiting their practical use. The discrete nature with numerous local-optimal structures also pose significant optimization challenges, often causing gradient-based methods to converge on suboptimal designs. In this work, we formulate inverse design as a fabrication-restricted, discrete, probabilistic optimization problem and introduce BOSON-1, an end-to-end, variation-aware subspace optimization framework to address the challenges of manufacturability, robustness, and optimizability. To overcome optimization difficulty, we propose dense target-enhanced gradient flows to mitigate misleading local optima and introduce a conditional subspace optimization strategy to create high-dimensional tunnels to escape local optima. Furthermore, we significantly reduce the runtime associated with optimizing across exponential variation samples through an adaptive sampling-based robust optimization, ensuring both efficiency and variation robustness. On three representative photonic device benchmarks, our proposed inverse design methodology BOSON^-1 delivers fabricable structures and achieves the best convergence and performance under realistic variations, outperforming prior arts with 74.3% post-fabrication performance. We open-source our codes at https://github.com/ScopeX-ASU/BOSON.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08210v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pingchuan Ma, Zhengqi Gao, Amir Begovic, Meng Zhang, Haoyu Yang, Haoxing Ren, Zhaoran Rena Huang, Duane Boning, Jiaqi Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat transfer in a planer diverging channel with a slot jet inlet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article delves into a numerical exploration of two-dimensional, incompressible, laminar flow within a confined diverging jet. The study aims to understand how variations in the inlet opening fraction and Reynolds number affect the heat transfer and flow patterns. The research employs the finite volume method with a collocated mesh to solve the governing equations. Across a broad spectrum of inlet opening fractions (0.2, 0.4, and 0.6) and Reynolds numbers (ranging from 500 to 900), the findings reveal that increasing the inlet opening fraction of the jet in the diverging channel can lead to a remarkable (53%) improvement in heat transfer while simultaneously reducing pressure loss by 90%. This outcome holds the potential to conserve energy by requiring less pumping power. Notably, this investigation is pioneering and offers novel and valuable insights into enhancing heat transfer through the utilization of a diverging channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08573v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Insiat Islam Rabby, Mohammad Ali Rob Sharif, Mohammad Tarequl Islam, Md. Rakidul Islam, Md. Mahidul Alam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Space-local memory in generalized master equations: Reaching the thermodynamic limit for the cost of a small lattice simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08598v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The exact quantum dynamics of lattice models can be computationally intensive, especially when aiming for large system sizes and extended simulation times necessary to converge transport coefficients. By leveraging finite memory times to access long-time dynamics using only short-time data, generalized master equations (GMEs) can offer a route to simulating the dynamics of lattice problems efficiently. However, such simulations are limited to small lattices whose dynamics exhibit finite-size artifacts that contaminate transport coefficient predictions. To address this problem, we introduce a novel approach that exploits finite memory in time \textit{and} space to efficiently predict the many-body dynamics of dissipative lattice problems involving short-range interactions. This advance enables one to leverage the short-time dynamics of small lattices to simulate arbitrarily large systems over long times. We demonstrate the strengths of this method by focusing on nonequilibrium polaron relaxation and transport in the dispersive Holstein model, successfully simulating lattice dynamics in one and two dimensions free from finite-size effects, reducing the computational expense of such simulations by multiple orders of magnitude. Our method is broadly applicable and provides an accurate and efficient means to investigate nonequilibrium relaxation with microscopic resolution over mesoscopic length and time scales that are relevant to experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08598v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srijan Bhattacharyya, Thomas Sayer, Andr\'es Montoya-Castillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Dissipation Preserving Physics Informed Neural Network for Allen-Cahn Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08760v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates a numerical solution of Allen-Cahn equation with constant and degenerate mobility, with polynomial and logarithmic energy functionals, with deterministic and random initial functions, and with advective term in one, two, and three spatial dimensions, based on the physics-informed neural network (PINN). To improve the learning capacity of the PINN, we incorporate the energy dissipation property of the Allen-Cahn equation as a penalty term into the loss function of the network. To facilitate the learning process of random initials, we employ a continuous analogue of the initial random condition by utilizing the Fourier series expansion. Adaptive methods from traditional numerical analysis are also integrated to enhance the effectiveness of the proposed PINN. Numerical results indicate a consistent decrease in the discrete energy, while also revealing phenomena such as phase separation and metastability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08760v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa K\"ut\"uk, Hamdullah Y\"ucel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Transformation Toward Improving the Machine-Learned NLTE Models of ICF Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08789v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The integration of machine learning techniques into Inertial Confinement Fusion (ICF) simulations has emerged as a powerful approach for enhancing computational efficiency. By replacing the costly Non-Local Thermodynamic Equilibrium (NLTE) model with machine learning models, significant reductions in calculation time have been achieved. However, determining how to optimize machine learning-based NLTE models in order to match ICF simulation dynamics remains challenging, underscoring the need for physically relevant error metrics and strategies to enhance model accuracy with respect to these metrics. Thus, we propose novel physics-informed transformations designed to emphasize energy transport, use these transformations to establish new error metrics, and demonstrate that they yield smaller errors within reduced principal component spaces compared to conventional transformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08789v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Sang Cho, Paul E. Grabowski, Kowshik Thopalli, Thathachar S. Jayram, Michael J. Barrow, Jayaraman J. Thiagarajan, Rushil Anirudh, Hai P. Le, Howard A. Scott, Joshua B. Kallman, Branson C. Stephens, Mark E. Foord, Jim A. Gaffney, Peer-Timo Bremer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational Self-Assembly of a Six-Fold Chiral Quasicrystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01984v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quasicrystals are unique materials characterized by long-range order without periodicity. They are observed in systems such as metallic alloys, soft matter, and particle simulations. Unlike periodic crystals, which are invariant under real-space symmetry operations, quasicrystals possess symmetry that requires description by a space group in reciprocal space. In this study, we report the self-assembly of a six-fold chiral quasicrystal using molecular dynamics simulations of a two-dimensional particle system. The particles interact via the Lennard-Jones-Gauss pair potential and are subjected to a periodic substrate potential. We confirm the presence of chiral symmetry through diffraction patterns and order parameters, revealing unique local motifs in both real and reciprocal space. The quasicrystal's properties, including the tiling structure and symmetry and the extent of diffuse scattering, are strongly influenced by substrate potential depth and temperature. Our results provide insights into the mechanisms of chiral quasicrystal formation and the role and potential of external fields in tailoring quasicrystal structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01984v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nydia Roxana Varela-Rosales, Michael Engel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning models with different cheminformatics data sets to forecast the power conversion efficiency of organic solar cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23444v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Random Forest (RF) and Gradient Boosting Regression Trees (GBRT) regression models along with three cheminformatics data sets (RDkit, Mordred, Morgan) have been used to predict the power conversion efficiency (PCE) of organic solar cells (OSCs). The data consists of cheinformatics descriptors of the electron donor used in 433 OSCs for which the experimental PCE (target variable) is reported in the literature. The donor is either a polymer or a small organic molecule, and the acceptor the fullerene derivatives PCBM or PC71BM. Unlike previous methods, our ML approach considers the type of donor and the acceptor by adding four extra donor's features using the one-hot encoder tool. It is demonstrated that this additional information improves the prediction performance up to 34%. We have also exploited this feature to theoretically forecast the PCE of new OSCs by evaluating the ML model for a different acceptor. It is predicted that more than 50% of the OCSs obtained by exchanging the acceptor would have higher experimental PCE. The prediction accuracy of a given ML approach is analyzed for different PCE intervals. RF using RDkit descriptors resulted in the best ML approach with a Pearson's correlation coefficient for the training and testing sets equal to 0.96 and 0.62, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23444v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omar A. Alvarez-Gonzaga, Ulises A. Vergara-Beltran, Juan I. Rodriguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid finite element implementation of two-potential constitutive modeling of dielectric elastomers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07900v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dielectric elastomers are increasingly studied for their potential in soft robotics, actuators, and haptic devices. Under time-dependent loading, they dissipate energy via viscous deformation and friction in electric polarization. However, most constitutive models and finite element (FE) implementations consider only mechanical dissipation because mechanical relaxation times are much larger than electric ones. Accounting for electric dissipation is crucial when dealing with alternating electric fields. Ghosh et al. (2021) proposed a fully coupled three-dimensional constitutive model for isotropic, incompressible dielectric elastomers. We critically investigate their numerical scheme for solving the initial boundary value problem (IBVP) describing the time-dependent behavior. We find that their fifth-order explicit Runge-Kutta time discretization may require excessively small or unphysical time steps for realistic simulations due to the stark contrast in mechanical and electric relaxation times. To address this, we present a stable implicit time-integration algorithm that overcomes these constraints. We implement this algorithm with a conforming FE discretization to solve the IBVP and present the mixed-FE formulation implemented in FEniCSx. We demonstrate that the scheme is robust, accurate, and capable of handling finite deformations, incompressibility, and general time-dependent loading. Finally, we validate our code against experimental data for VHB 4910 under complex time-dependent electromechanical loading, as studied by Hossain et al. (2015).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07900v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamalendu Ghosh, Bhavesh Shrimali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning tight-binding approach for large-scale electronic simulations at finite temperatures with $ab$ $initio$ accuracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.04638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.04638v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Simulating electronic behavior in materials and devices with realistic large system sizes remains a formidable task within the $ab$ $initio$ framework due to its computational intensity. Here we show DeePTB, an efficient deep learning-based tight-binding approach with $ab$ $initio$ accuracy to address this issue. By training on structural data and corresponding $ab$ $initio$ eigenvalues, the DeePTB model can efficiently predict tight-binding Hamiltonians for unseen structures, enabling efficient simulations of large-size systems under external perturbations such as finite temperatures and strain. This capability is vital for semiconductor band gap engineering and materials design. When combined with molecular dynamics, DeePTB facilitates efficient and accurate finite-temperature simulations of both atomic and electronic behavior simultaneously. This is demonstrated by computing the temperature-dependent electronic properties of a gallium phosphide system with $10^6$ atoms. The availability of DeePTB bridges the gap between accuracy and scalability in electronic simulations, potentially advancing materials science and related fields by enabling large-scale electronic structure calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.04638v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-51006-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Commun. 15, 6772 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qiangqiang Gu, Zhanghao Zhouyin, Shishir Kumar Pandey, Peng Zhang, Linfeng Zhang, Weinan E</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Griffiths phase and beyond: A large deviations study of the magnetic susceptibility of the two-dimensional bond-diluted Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02889v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Griffiths phase in systems with quenched disorder occurs below the ordering transition of the pure system down to the ordering transition of the actual disordered system. While it does not exhibit long-range order, large fluctuations in the disorder degrees of freedom result in exponentially rare, long-range ordered states and hence the occurrence of broad distributions in response functions. Inside the Griffiths phase of the two-dimensional bond-diluted Ising model the distribution of the magnetic susceptibility is expected to have such a broad, exponential tail. A large-deviations Monte Carlo algorithm is used to sample this distribution and the exponential tail is extracted over a wide range of the support down to very small probabilities of the order of $10^{-300}$. We study the behavior of the susceptibility distribution across the full phase diagram, from the paramagnetic state through the Griffiths phase to the ferromagnetically ordered system and down to the zero-temperature point. We extract the rate function of large-deviation theory as well as its finite-size scaling behavior and we reveal interesting differences and similarities between the cases. A connection between the fraction of ferromagnetic bonds in a given disorder sample and the size of the magnetic susceptibility is demonstrated numerically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02889v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.054112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 110, 054112 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lambert M\"unster, Alexander K. Hartmann, Martin Weigel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-equilibrium quantum Monte Carlo algorithm for stabilizer Renyi entropy in spin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19577v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum magic, or nonstabilizerness, provides a crucial characterization of quantum systems, regarding the classical simulability with stabilizer states. In this work, we propose a novel and efficient algorithm for computing stabilizer R\'enyi entropy, one of the measures for quantum magic, in spin systems with sign-problem free Hamiltonians. This algorithm is based on the quantum Monte Carlo simulation of the path integral of the work between two partition function ensembles and it applies to all spatial dimensions and temperatures. We demonstrate this algorithm on the one and two dimensional transverse field Ising model at both finite and zero temperatures and show the quantitative agreements with tensor-network based algorithms. Furthermore, we analyze the computational cost and provide both analytical and numerical evidences for it to be polynomial in system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19577v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zejun Liu, Bryan K. Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing structural features of two-dimensional particle systems through Voronoi topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00553v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a new approach toward characterizing local structural features of two-dimensional particle systems. The approach can accurately identify and characterize defects in high-temperature crystals, distinguish a wide range of nominally disordered systems, and robustly describe complex structures such as grain boundaries. This paper also introduces two-dimensional functionality into the open-source software program VoroTop which automates this analysis. This software package is built on a recently-introduced multithreaded version of VORO++, enabling the analysis of systems with billions of particles on high-performance computer architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00553v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-651X/ad8ad9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Model. Simul. Mater. Sci. Eng. 32 085022 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Emanuel A. Lazar, Jiayin Lu, Chris H. Rycroft, Deborah Schwarcz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ACCEL$^2$ project: simulating Lyman-$\alpha$ forest in large-volume hydrodynamical simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04473v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cosmological information is usually extracted from the Lyman-$\alpha$ forest correlations using only either large-scale information interpreted through linear theory or using small-scale information interpreted by means of expensive hydrodynamical simulations. A complete cosmological interpretation of the 3D correlations at all measurable scales is challenged by the need of more realistic models including the complex growth of non-linear small scales that can only be studied within large hydrodynamical simulations. Past work were often limited by the trade off between the simulated cosmological volume and the resolution of the low-density intergalactic medium from which the Lyman-$\alpha$ signal originates. We conduct a suite of hydrodynamical simulations of the intergalactic medium, including one of the largest Lyman-$\alpha$ simulations ever performed in terms of volume (640 $h^{-1}\mathrm{Mpc}$), alongside simulations in smaller volumes with resolutions up to 25 $h^{-1}\mathrm{kpc}$, which will be further improved to show resolution convergence in future studies. We compare the 3D Lyman-$\alpha$ power spectra predicted by those simulations to different non-linear models. The inferred Lyman-$\alpha$ bias and redshift space distortion (RSD) parameters, $b_\alpha$ and $\beta_\alpha$ are in remarkable agreement with those measured in SDSS and DESI data. We find that, contrary to intuition, the convergence of large-scale modes of the 3D Lyman-$\alpha$ power spectra, which determines $\beta_\alpha$, is primarily influenced by the resolution of the simulation box through mode coupling, rather than the box size itself. Finally, we study the BAO signal encoded in the 3D Lyman-$\alpha$ power spectra. For the first time with a hydrodynamical simulation, we clearly detect the BAO signal, however we only marginally detect its damping, associated with the non-linear growth of the structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04473v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae2255</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 534, Issue 3, November 2024, Pages 2674-2693</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sol\`ene Chabanier, Corentin Ravoux, Lucas Latrille, Jean Sexton, \'Eric Armengaud, Julian Bautista, Tyann Dumerchat, Zarija Luki\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat-plane based double-counting free and parameter free many-body DFT+U</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08391v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Burgess et al. have recently introduced the BLOR corrective exchange-correlation functional that is, by construction, the unique simplified rotationally-invariant DFT+U functional that enforces the flat-plane condition separately on each effective orbital of a localized subspace. Detached from the Hubbard model, functionals of this type are both double-counting correction free and, when optimized in situ using appropriate error quantifiers, effectively parameter free. In this work, the extension of the BLOR functional to address many-body errors (mBLOR) is derived. The mBLOR functional is built to enforce the flat-plane condition on the entire subspace, rather than on each orbital individually. In this way inter-orbital errors are corrected on the same footing as the single-particle ones. Focusing on exact test cases with strong inter-orbital interactions, the BLOR and mBLOR functionals were benchmarked against contemporary DFT+U functionals using the total energy extensivity condition on stretched homo-nuclear p-block dimers that represent various self-interaction and static-correlation error regimes. The BLOR functional outperformed all other DFT+$U$ functionals tested, which often act to increase total-energy errors, yet it still yielded large errors in some systems. mBLOR instead yielded low energy errors across all four strongly-correlated dimers, while being constructed using only semi-local approximation ingredients. As mBLOR would not otherwise introduce a band-gap correction in the manner that is a desirable feature of DFT+U, we developed a cost-free technique to reintroduce it automatically by moving the functional's unusual explicit derivative discontinuity into the potential. With this in place, mBLOR is the only known DFT$+U$ functional that opens the bandgap of stretched neutral homo-nuclear dimers without the aid of unphysical spin-symmetry breaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08391v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrew C. Burgess, David D. O'Regan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing many-body methods on the potential energy surface of the (H$_2$)$_2$ hydrogen dimer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03410v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The anisotropic potential energy surface of the (H$_2$)$_2$ dimer represents a challenging problem for many-body methods. Here, we determine the potential energy curves of five different dimer configurations (T, Z, X, H, L) using the lattice regularized diffusion Monte Carlo (LRDMC) method and a number of approximate functionals within density functional theory (DFT), including advanced orbital-dependent functionals based on the random phase approximation (RPA). We assess their performance in describing the potential wells, bond distances and relative energies. The repulsive potential wall is studied by looking at the relative stability of the different dimer configurations as a function of an applied force acting along the intermolecular axis. It is shown that most functionals within DFT break down at finite compression, even those that give an accurate description around the potential well minima. Only by including exchange within RPA a qualitatively correct description along the entire potential energy curve is obtained. Finally, we discuss these results in the context of solid molecular hydrogen at finite pressures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03410v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0235728</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 161, 184107 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Damian Contant, Michele Casula, Maria Hellgren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Numerical Fluxes on High Order Semidiscrete WENO-DeC Finite Volume Schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07422v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The numerical flux determines the performance of numerical methods for solving hyperbolic partial differential equations (PDEs). In this work, we compare a selection of 8 numerical fluxes in the framework of nonlinear semidiscrete finite volume (FV) schemes, based on Weighted Essentially Non-Oscillatory (WENO) spatial reconstruction and Deferred Correction (DeC) time discretization. The methodology is implemented and systematically assessed for order of accuracy in space and time up to seven. The numerical fluxes selected in the present study represent the two existing classes of fluxes, namely centred and upwind. Centred fluxes do not explicitly use wave propagation information, while, upwind fluxes do so from the solution of the Riemann problem via a wave model containing $A$ waves. Upwind fluxes include two subclasses: complete and incomplete fluxes. For complete upwind fluxes, $A=E$, where $E$ is the number of characteristic fields in the exact problem. For incomplete upwind ones, $A&lt;E$. Our study is conducted for the one- and two-dimensional Euler equations, for which we consider the following numerical fluxes: Lax-Friedrichs (LxF), First-Order Centred (FORCE), Rusanov (Rus), Harten-Lax-van Leer (HLL), Central-Upwind (CU), Low-Dissipation Central-Upwind (LDCU), HLLC, and the flux computed through the exact Riemann solver (Ex.RS). We find that the numerical flux has an effect on the performance of the methods. The magnitude of the effect depends on the type of numerical flux and on the order of accuracy of the scheme. It also depends on the type of problem; that is, whether the solution is smooth or discontinuous, whether discontinuities are linear or nonlinear, whether linear discontinuities are fast- or slowly-moving, and whether the solution is evolved for short or long time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07422v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Micalizzi, Eleuterio F. Toro</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
