<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo Physics-informed neural networks for multiscale heat conduction via phonon Boltzmann transport equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The phonon Boltzmann transport equation (BTE) is widely used for describing multiscale heat conduction (from nm to $\mu$m or mm) in solid materials. Developing numerical approaches to solve this equation is challenging since it is a 7-dimensional integral-differential equation. In this work, we propose Monte Carlo physics-informed neural networks (MC-PINNs), which do not suffer from the {\emph{``curse of dimensionality''}}, to solve the phonon BTE to model the multiscale heat conduction in solid materials. MC-PINNs use a deep neural network to approximate the solution to the BTE, and encode the BTE as well as the corresponding boundary/initial conditions using the automatic differentiation. In addition, we propose a novel two-step sampling approach to address inefficiency and inaccuracy issues in the widely used sampling methods in PINNs. In particular, we first randomly sample a certain number of points in the temporal-spatial space (Step I), and then draw another number of points randomly in the solid angular space (Step II). The training points are constructed using the tensor product of the data drawn from the above two steps. The two-step sampling strategy enables MC-PINNs (1) to model the heat conduction from ballistic to diffusive regimes, and (2) is more memory-efficient compared to conventional numerical solvers or existing PINNs for BTE. A series of numerical examples including quasi-one-dimensional (quasi-1D) steady/unsteady heat conduction in a film, and the heat conduction in a quasi-two- and three-dimensional square domain, are conducted to justify the effectiveness of the MC-PINN for heat conduction spanning diffusive and ballistic regimes. Finally, we compare the computational time and memory usage of the MC-PINN and a state-of-art numerical methods to demonstrate the potential of the MC-PINN for large scale problems in real-world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10965v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingyi Lin (Institute of Interdisciplinary Research for Mathematics and Applied Science, School of Mathematics and Statistics, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, China), Chuang Zhang (Department of Physics, School of Sciences, Hangzhou Dianzi University, Hangzhou, China), Xuhui Meng (Institute of Interdisciplinary Research for Mathematics and Applied Science, School of Mathematics and Statistics, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, China), Zhaoli Guo (Institute of Interdisciplinary Research for Mathematics and Applied Science, School of Mathematics and Statistics, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, China)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreflecting Boundary Condition for the free Schr\"{o}dinger equation for hyperrectangular computational domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10208v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we discuss the efficient ways of implementing the transparent boundary condition (TBC) and its various approximations for the free Schr\"{o}dinger equation on a hyperrectangular computational domain in $\field{R}^d$ with periodic boundary conditions along the $(d-1)$ unbounded directions. In particular, we consider Pad\'e approximant based rational approximation of the exact TBC and a spatially local form of the exact TBC obtained under its high-frequency approximation. For the spatial discretization, we use a Legendre-Galerkin spectral method with a boundary-adapted basis to ensure the bandedness of the resulting linear system. Temporal discretization is then addressed with two one-step methods, namely, the backward-differentiation formula of order 1 (BDF1) and the trapezoidal rule (TR). Finally, several numerical tests are presented to demonstrate the effectiveness of the methods where we study the stability and convergence behaviour empirically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10208v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samardhi Yadav, Vishal Vaibhav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pfaffian quantum Monte Carlo: solution to Majorana sign ambiguity and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10311v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Determinant quantum Monte Carlo (DQMC), formulated in complex-fermion representation, has played a key role in studying strongly-correlated fermion systems. However, its applicability is limited due to the requirement of particle-number conservation after Hubbard-Stratonovich transformation. In going beyond the conventional DQMC, one encouraging development occurred when Majorana fermions were introduced for QMC [1,2]. But in previous Majorana-based QMC, Boltzmann weight is determined often with a sign ambiguity. Here we successfully resolved this ambiguity by deriving a closed-form Pfaffian formula for the weight, enabling efficient calculation of the weight with its sign in polynomial time. We call it ''Pfaffian quantum Monte Carlo'' (PfQMC), which can be applied to generic interacting fermion models. We have successfully employed PfQMC to explore how robust Majorana edge modes in Kitaev chain are against strong interactions. By offering greater flexibility, PfQMC can potentially enhance existing sign-mitigating and approximation methods and help address challenging issues such as the ground-state properties of the doped Hubbard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10311v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ze-Yao Han, Zhou-Quan Wan, Hong Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Underwater Topography with FINN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10649v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spatiotemporal partial differential equations (PDEs) find extensive application across various scientific and engineering fields. While numerous models have emerged from both physics and machine learning (ML) communities, there is a growing trend towards integrating these approaches to develop hybrid architectures known as physics-aware machine learning models. Among these, the finite volume neural network (FINN) has emerged as a recent addition. FINN has proven to be particularly efficient in uncovering latent structures in data. In this study, we explore the capabilities of FINN in tackling the shallow-water equations, which simulates wave dynamics in coastal regions. Specifically, we investigate FINN's efficacy to reconstruct underwater topography based on these particular wave equations. Our findings reveal that FINN exhibits a remarkable capacity to infer topography solely from wave dynamics, distinguishing itself from both conventional ML and physics-aware ML models. Our results underscore the potential of FINN in advancing our understanding of spatiotemporal phenomena and enhancing parametrization capabilities in related domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10649v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Co\c{s}ku Can Horuz, Matthias Karlbauer, Timothy Praditia, Sergey Oladyshkin, Wolfgang Nowak, Sebastian Otte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-matrix representation of optical scattering response: Suggestion for a data format</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10727v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The transition matrix, frequently abbreviated as T-matrix, contains the complete information in a linear approximation of how a spatially localized object scatters an incident field. The T-matrix is used to study the scattering response of an isolated object and describes the optical response of complex photonic materials made from ensembles of individual objects. T-matrices of certain common structures, potentially, have been repeatedly calculated all over the world again and again. This is not necessary and constitutes a major challenge for various reasons. First, the resources spent on their computation represent an unsustainable financial and ecological burden. Second, with the onset of machine learning, data is the gold of our era, and it should be freely available to everybody to address novel scientific challenges. Finally, the possibility of reproducing simulations could tremendously improve if the considered T-matrices could be shared. To address these challenges, we found it important to agree on a common data format for T-matrices and to enable their collection from different sources and distribution. This document aims to develop the specifications for storing T-matrices and associated metadata. The specifications should allow maximum freedom to accommodate as many use cases as possible without introducing any ambiguity in the stored data. The common format will assist in setting up a public database of T-matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10727v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nigar Asadova, Karim Achouri, Kristian Arjas, Baptiste Augui\'e, Roland Aydin, Alexandre Baron, Dominik Beutel, Bernd Bodermann, Kaoutar Boussaoud, Sven Burger, Minseok Choi, Krzysztof M. Czajkowski, Andrey B. Evlyukhin, Atefeh Fazel-Najafabadi, Ivan Fernandez-Corbaton, Puneet Garg, David Globosits, Ulrich Hohenester, Hongyoon Kim, Seokwoo Kim, Philippe Lalanne, Eric C. Le Ru, J\"org Meyer, Jungho Mun, Lorenzo Pattelli, Lukas Pflug, Carsten Rockstuhl, Junsuk Rho, Stefan Rotter, Brian Stout, P\"aivi T\"orm\"a, Jorge Olmos Trigo, Frank Tristram, Nikolaos L. Tsitsas, Renaud Vall\'ee, Kevin Vynck, Thomas Weiss, Peter Wiecha, Thomas Wriedt, Vassilios Yannopapas, Maxim A. Yurkin, Grigorios P. Zouros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the structural phase field crystal approach for modeling solid-liquid-vapor phase transformations in pure materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10992v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a recent class of phase field crystal (PFC) models, the density order parameter is coupled to powers of its mean field. This effectively introduces a phenomenology of higher-order direct correlation functions acting on long wavelengths, which is required for modelling solid-liquid-vapor systems. The present work generalizes these models by incorporating, into a single-field theory, higher-order direct correlations, systematically constructed in reciprocal space to operate across long {\it and} short wavelengths. The correlation kernels introduced are also readily adaptable to describe distinct crystal structures. We examine the three-phase equilibrium properties and phase diagrams of the proposed model, and reproduce parts of the aluminum phase diagram as an example of its versatile parametrization. We assess the dynamics of the model, showing that it allows robust control of the interface energy between the vapor and condensed phases (liquid and solid). We also examine the dynamics of solid-vapor interfaces over a wide range of parameters and find that dynamical artifacts reported in previous PFC models do not occur in the present formalism. Additionally, we demonstrate the capacity of the proposed formalism for computing complex microstructures and defects such as dislocations, grain boundaries, and voids in solid-liquid-vapor systems, all of which are expected to be crucial for investigating rapid solidification processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10992v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel L. Coelho, Duncan Burns, Emily Wilson, Nikolas Provatas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Shadow Tomography of Molecular Excited States from Enforcing $N$-representability Conditions by Semidefinite Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Excited-state properties of highly correlated systems are key to understanding photosynthesis, luminescence, and the development of novel optical materials, but accurately capturing their interactions is computationally costly. We present an algorithm that combines classical shadow tomography with physical constraints on the two-electron reduced density matrix (2-RDM) to treat excited states. The method reduces the number of measurements of the many-electron 2-RDM on quantum computers by (i) approximating the quantum state through a random sampling technique called shadow tomography and (ii) ensuring that the 2-RDM represents an $N$-electron system through imposing $N$-representability constraints by semidefinite programming. This generalizes recent work on the $N$-representability-enhanced shadow tomography of ground-state 2-RDMs. We compute excited-state energies and 2-RDMs of the H$_4$ chain and analyze the critical points along the photoexcited reaction pathway from gauche-1,3-butadiene to bicyclobutane via a conical intersection. The results show that the generalized shadow tomography retains critical multireference correlation effects while significantly reducing the number of required measurements, offering a promising avenue for the efficient treatment of electronically excited states on quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11025v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irma Avdic, David A. Mazziotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shadow Ansatz for the Many-Fermion Wave Function in Scalable Molecular Simulations on Quantum Computing Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11026v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Here we show that shadow tomography can generate an efficient and exact ansatz for the many-fermion wave function on quantum devices. We derive the shadow ansatz -- a product of transformations applied to the mean-field wave function -- by exploiting a critical link between measurement and preparation. Each transformation is obtained by measuring a classical shadow of the residual of the contracted Schr\"odinger equation (CSE), the many-electron Schr\"odinger equation (SE) projected onto the space of two electrons. We show that the classical shadows of the CSE vanish if and only if the wave function satisfies the SE and, hence, that randomly sampling only the two-electron space yields an exact ansatz regardless of the total number of electrons. We demonstrate the ansatz's advantages for scalable simulations -- fewer measurements and shallower circuits -- by computing H$_{3}$ on simulators and a quantum device.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11026v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Wang, Irma Avdic, David A. Mazziotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Topology Replica Exchange of Expanded Ensembles (MT-REXEE) for Multidimensional Alchemical Calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Relative free energy calculations are now widely used in academia and industry, but the accuracy is often limited by poor sampling of the complexes conformational ensemble. To address this, we have developed a novel method termed Multi-Topology Replica Exchange of Expanded Ensembles (MT-REXEE). This method enables parallel expanded ensemble calculations, facilitating iterative relative free energy computations while allowing conformational exchange between parallel transformations. These iterative transformations are adaptable to any set of systems with a common backbone or central substructure. We demonstrate that the MT-REXEE method maintains thermodynamic cycle closure to the same extent as standard expanded ensemble for both solvation free energy and relative binding free energy. The transformations tested involve simple systems that incorporate diverse heavy atoms and multi-site perturbations of a small molecule core resembling multi-site $\lambda$ dynamics, without necessitating modifications to the MD code, which in our initial implementation is GROMACS. We outline a systematic approach for topology set-up and provide instructions on how to perform inter-replicate coordinate modifications. This work shows that MT-REEXE can be used to perform accurate and reproducible free energy estimates and prompts expansion to more complex test systems and other molecular dynamics simulation infrastructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11038v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anika J. Friedman, Wei-Tse Hsu, Michael R. Shirts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shotgun crystal structure prediction using machine-learned formation energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.02158v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Stable or metastable crystal structures of assembled atoms can be predicted by finding the global or local minima of the energy surface within a broad space of atomic configurations. Generally, this requires repeated first-principles energy calculations, which is often impractical for large crystalline systems. Here, we present significant progress toward solving the crystal structure prediction problem: we performed noniterative, single-shot screening using a large library of virtually created crystal structures with a machine-learning energy predictor. This shotgun method (ShotgunCSP) has two key technical components: transfer learning for accurate energy prediction of pre-relaxed crystalline states, and two generative models based on element substitution and symmetry-restricted structure generation to produce promising and diverse crystal structures. First-principles calculations were performed only to generate the training samples and to refine a few selected pre-relaxed crystal structures. The ShotunCSP method is computationally less intensive than conventional methods and exhibits exceptional prediction accuracy, reaching 93.3% in benchmark tests with 90 different crystal structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.02158v5</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Liu (The Institute of Statistical Mathematics), Hiromasa Tamaki (Panasonic Holdings Corporation), Tomoyasu Yokoyama (Panasonic Holdings Corporation), Kensuke Wakasugi (Panasonic Holdings Corporation), Satoshi Yotsuhashi (Panasonic Holdings Corporation), Minoru Kusaba (The Institute of Statistical Mathematics), Artem R. Oganov (Skolkovo Innovation Center), Ryo Yoshida (The Institute of Statistical Mathematics, The Graduate University for Advanced Studies)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manufactured Solutions for an Electromagnetic Slot Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14573v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The accurate modeling of electromagnetic penetration is an important topic in computational electromagnetics. Electromagnetic penetration occurs through intentional or inadvertent openings in an otherwise closed electromagnetic scatterer, which prevent the contents from being fully shielded from external fields. To efficiently model electromagnetic penetration, aperture or slot models can be used with surface integral equations to solve Maxwell's equations. A necessary step towards establishing the credibility of these models is to assess the correctness of the implementation of the underlying numerical methods through code verification. Surface integral equations and slot models yield multiple interacting sources of numerical error and other challenges, which render traditional code-verification approaches ineffective. In this paper, we provide approaches to separately measure the numerical errors arising from these different error sources for the method-of-moments implementation of the electric-field integral equation with a slot model. We demonstrate the effectiveness of these approaches for a variety of cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14573v3</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jcp.2024.113343</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Brian A. Freno, Neil R. Matula, Robert A. Pfeiffer, Evelyn A. Dohme, Joseph D. Kotulski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diff-PIC: Revolutionizing Particle-In-Cell Simulation for Advancing Nuclear Fusion with Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02693v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sustainable energy is a crucial global challenge, and recent breakthroughs in nuclear fusion ignition underscore the potential of harnessing energy extracted from nuclear fusion in everyday life, thereby drawing significant attention to fusion ignition research, especially Laser-Plasma Interaction (LPI). Unfortunately, the complexity of LPI at ignition scale renders theory-based analysis nearly impossible -- instead, it has to rely heavily on Particle-in-Cell (PIC) simulations, which is extremely computationally intensive, making it a major bottleneck in advancing fusion ignition. In response, this work introduces Diff-PIC, a novel paradigm that leverages conditional diffusion models as a computationally efficient alternative to PIC simulations for generating high-fidelity scientific data. Specifically, we design a distillation paradigm to distill the physical patterns captured by PIC simulations into diffusion models, demonstrating both theoretical and practical feasibility. Moreover, to ensure practical effectiveness, we provide solutions for two critical challenges: (1) We develop a physically-informed conditional diffusion model that can learn and generate meaningful embeddings for mathematically continuous physical conditions. This model offers algorithmic generalization and adaptable transferability, effectively capturing the complex relationships between physical conditions and simulation outcomes; and (2) We employ the rectified flow technique to make our model a one-step conditional diffusion model, enhancing its efficiency further while maintaining high fidelity and physical validity. Diff-PIC establishes a new paradigm for using diffusion models to overcome the computational barriers in nuclear fusion research, setting a benchmark for future innovations and advancements in this field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02693v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuan Liu, Chunshu Wu, Shihui Cao, Mingkai Chen, James Chenhao Liang, Ang Li, Michael Huang, Chuang Ren, Dongfang Liu, Ying Nian Wu, Tong Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on higher-order and nonlinear limiting approaches for continuously bounds-preserving discontinuous Galerkin methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12965v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In (Dzanic, J. Comp. Phys., 508:113010, 2024), a limiting approach for high-order discontinuous Galerkin schemes was introduced which allowed for imposing constraints on the solution continuously (i.e., everywhere within the element). While exact for linear constraint functionals, this approach only imposed a sufficient (but not the minimum necessary) amount of limiting for nonlinear constraint functionals. This short note shows how this limiting approach can be extended to allow exactness for general nonlinear quasiconcave constraint functionals through a nonlinear limiting procedure, reducing unnecessary numerical dissipation. Some examples are shown for nonlinear pressure and entropy constraints in the compressible gas dynamics equations, where both analytic and iterative approaches are used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12965v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tarik Dzanic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plasma stratification in AC discharges in noble gases at low currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05926v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A hybrid kinetic-fluid model is used to study plasma stratification in alternating current (AC) discharges in noble gases at low plasma densities. Self-consistent coupled solutions of a nonlocal kinetic equation for electrons, a drift-diffusion equation of ions, and a Poisson equation for the electric field are obtained for a positive column and the entire discharge with near-electrode sheaths. A simplified two-level excitation-ionization model neglects the nonlinear effects due to stepwise ionization, gas heating, and Coulomb interactions among electrons. Standing striations are obtained for the reduced values of electric fields, E/p, corresponding to the inelastic energy balance of electrons in a range of driving frequencies. An analog of Novak law (striation length proportional to the excitation threshold of atoms and inversely proportional to the mean square root of the electric field), is observed in simulations, indicating the nonlocal nature of standing striations in AC discharges at low plasma densities. Stratified plasma operates in a dynamic regime for various driving frequencies. In this regime, ions respond to the time-averaged electric field, whereas electrons react to the instantaneous electric field. The disparity of time scales between ambipolar diffusion, which occurs at the ion time scale, and electron kinetics in the coordinate-energy phase space, which occurs at the free electron diffusion time scale, produces complicated fluxes in the phase space (due to electron heating, energy loss in collisions, and ionization processes) that are responsible for the stratification. Our paper emphasizes the need for the kinetic approach to analyze stratification phenomena in AC discharge of noble gases. It promotes an efficient method for the kinetic treatment of electrons that is an alternative to the commonly used PIC method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05926v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir I. Kolobov, Robert R. Arslanbekov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
