<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Scaled-up prediction of steady Navier-Stokes equation with component reduced order modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21534v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scaling up new scientific technologies from laboratory to industry often involves demonstrating performance on a larger scale. Computer simulations can accelerate design and predictions in the deployment process, though traditional numerical methods are computationally intractable even for intermediate pilot plant scales. Recently, component reduced order modeling method is developed to tackle this challenge by combining projection reduced order modeling and discontinuous Galerkin domain decomposition. However, while many scientific or engineering applications involve nonlinear physics, this method has been only demonstrated for various linear systems. In this work, the component reduced order modeling method is extended to steady Navier-Stokes flow, with application to general nonlinear physics in view. Large-scale, global domain is decomposed into combination of small-scale unit component. Linear subspaces for flow velocity and pressure are identified via proper orthogonal decomposition over sample snapshots collected at small scale unit component. Velocity bases are augmented with pressure supremizer, in order to satisfy inf-sup condition for stable pressure prediction. Two different nonlinear reduced order modeling methods are employed and compared for efficient evaluation of nonlinear advection: 3rd-order tensor projection operator and empirical quadrature procedure. The proposed method is demonstrated on flow over arrays of five different unit objects, achieving $23$ times faster prediction with less than $4\%$ relative error up to $256$ times larger scale domain than unit components. Furthermore, a numerical experiment with pressure supremizer strongly indicates the need of supremizer for stable pressure prediction. A comparison between tensorial approach and empirical quadrature procedure is performed, which suggests a slight advantage for empirical quadrature procedure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21534v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung Whan Chung, Youngsoo Choi, Pratanu Roy, Thomas Roy, Tiras Y. Lin, Du T. Nguyen, Christopher Hahn, Eric B. Duoss, Sarah E. Baker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable physics-guided data-driven component model reduction for steady Navier-Stokes flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21583v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Computational physics simulation can be a powerful tool to accelerate industry deployment of new scientific technologies. However, it must address the challenge of computationally tractable, moderately accurate prediction at large industry scales, and training a model without data at such large scales. A recently proposed component reduced order modeling (CROM) tackles this challenge by combining reduced order modeling (ROM) with discontinuous Galerkin domain decomposition (DG-DD). While it can build a component ROM at small scales that can be assembled into a large scale system, its application is limited to linear physics equations. In this work, we extend CROM to nonlinear steady Navier-Stokes flow equation. Nonlinear advection term is evaluated via tensorial approach or empirical quadrature procedure. Application to flow past an array of objects at moderate Reynolds number demonstrates $\sim23.7$ times faster solutions with a relative error of $\sim 2.3\%$, even at scales $256$ times larger than the original problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21583v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung Whan Chung, Youngsoo Choi, Pratanu Roy, Thomas Roy, Tiras Y. Lin, Du T. Nguyen, Christopher Hahn, Eric B. Duoss, Sarah E. Baker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Simulations of Tropical Cyclones using Adaptive Mesh Refinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21607v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tropical cyclones (TCs) are powerful, natural phenomena that can severely impact populations and infrastructure. Enhancing our understanding of the mechanisms driving their intensification is crucial for mitigating these impacts. To this end, researchers are pushing the boundaries of TC simulation resolution down to scales of just a few meters. However, higher resolution simulations come with significant computational challenges, increasing both time and energy costs. Adaptive mesh refinement (AMR) is a technique widely used in computational fluid dynamics but has seen limited application in atmospheric simulations. This study explores the use of h-adaptive grids using the spectral element discretization technique to accelerate TC simulations while allowing very high resolutions in certain parts of the domain. By applying AMR to a rapidly intensifying TC test case, we demonstrate that AMR can replicate the results of uniform grid simulations in terms of mean and local wind speed maxima while dramatically reducing computational costs. We show that AMR can speed up dry TC simulations by a factor of 2 - 13 for the set of tested refinement criteria. Additionally, we show that TC intensity changes as resolution is increased and that AMR can deliver high-resolution simulations at the cost of coarser static simulations. Our findings indicate that AMR and spectral element methods are promising tools for enhancing TC simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21607v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yassine Tissaoui, Stephen R. Guimond, Francis X. Giraldo, Simone Marras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure numerical simulations using fully homomorphic encryption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Data privacy is a significant concern in many environments today. This is particularly true if sensitive information, e.g., engineering, medical, or financial data, is to be processed on potentially insecure systems, as it is often the case in cloud computing. Fully homomorphic encryption (FHE) offers a potential solution to this problem, as it allows for secure computations on encrypted data. In this paper, we investigate the viability of using FHE for privacy-preserving numerical simulations of partial differential equations. We first give an overview of the CKKS scheme, a popular FHE method for computations with real numbers. This is followed by an introduction of our Julia packages OpenFHE.jl and SecureArithmetic.jl, which provide a Julia wrapper for the C++ library OpenFHE and offer a user-friendly interface for secure arithmetic operations. We then present a performance analysis of the CKKS scheme within OpenFHE, focusing on the error and efficiency of different FHE operations. Finally, we demonstrate the application of FHE to secure numerical simulations by implementing two finite difference schemes for the linear advection equation using the SecureArithmetic.jl package. Our results show that FHE can be used to perform cryptographically secure numerical simulations, but that the error and efficiency of FHE operations must be carefully considered when designing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21824v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arseniy Kholod, Yuriy Polyakov, Michael Schlottke-Lakemper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking the Million-Electron and 1 EFLOP/s Barriers: Biomolecular-Scale Ab Initio Molecular Dynamics Using MP2 Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The accurate simulation of complex biochemical phenomena has historically been hampered by the computational requirements of high-fidelity molecular-modeling techniques. Quantum mechanical methods, such as ab initio wave-function (WF) theory, deliver the desired accuracy, but have impractical scaling for modelling biosystems with thousands of atoms. Combining molecular fragmentation with MP2 perturbation theory, this study presents an innovative approach that enables biomolecular-scale ab initio molecular dynamics (AIMD) simulations at WF theory level. Leveraging the resolution-of-the-identity approximation for Hartree-Fock and MP2 gradients, our approach eliminates computationally intensive four-center integrals and their gradients, while achieving near-peak performance on modern GPU architectures. The introduction of asynchronous time steps minimizes time step latency, overlapping computational phases and effectively mitigating load imbalances. Utilizing up to 9,400 nodes of Frontier and achieving 59% (1006.7 PFLOP/s) of its double-precision floating-point peak, our method enables us to break the million-electron and 1 EFLOP/s barriers for AIMD simulations with quantum accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21888v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Stocks, Jorge L. Galvez Vallejo, Fiona C. Y. Yu, Calum Snowdon, Elise Palethorpe, Jakub Kurzak, Dmytro Bykov, Giuseppe M. J. Barca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Design Method with Enhanced Sampling for Complex Open Crystals: Application to Novel Zeolite Self-Assembly in a Coarse-Grained Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22111v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optimizing the synthesis of zeolites and exploring novel frameworks offer pivotal opportunities and challenges in materials design. While inverse design proves highly effective for simpler crystals, its application to intricate structures like zeolites poses severe challenges. Here, we introduce an innovative inverse design workflow tailored to efficiently reproduce target zeolite frameworks in a binary coarse-grained model using enhanced sampling molecular dynamics simulations. This workflow integrates an evolutionary parameter optimization strategy with a variant of the seeding approach. Using this method, we successfully reproduce Z1 and SGT zeolites, and Type-I clathrates, find new optimal parameters for known phases, such as the SOD and CFI, and even discover novel frameworks, such as Z5. This is done within a simple coarse-grained model for a tetrahedra-forming component and a structure-directing agent. Our methodology not only enables the screening of synthesis protocols but also facilitates the discovery of hypothetical zeolites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22111v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaohong Wang, Alberto P\'erez de Alba Ort\'iz, Marjolein Dijkstra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competition between simple and complex contagion on temporal networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22115v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Behavioral adoptions are influenced by peers in different ways. While some individuals may change after a single incoming influence, others need multiple cumulated attempts. These two mechanism, known as the simple and the complex contagions, often occur together in social phenomena alongside personal factors determining individual adoptions. Here we aim to identify, which of these contagion mechanism dominate a spreading process propagated by time-varying interactions. We consider three types of spreading scenarios: ones pre-dominated by simple or complex contagion, and mixed dynamics where the dominant mechanism changes during the unfolding of the spreading process. We propose different methods to analytically identify the transitions between these three scenarios and compare them with numerical simulations. This work offers new insights into social contagion dynamics on temporal networks, without assuming prior knowledge about individual's contagion mechanism driving their adoption decisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22115v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elsa Andres, Romualdo Pastor-Satorras, Michele Starnini, M\'arton Karsai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On resolving meso-scale calculations of pore-collapse-generated hotspots in energetic crystals for consistency with atomistic models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22174v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Meso-scale calculations of pore collapse and hotspot formation in energetic crystals provide closure models to macro-scale hydrocodes for predicting the shock sensitivity of energetic materials. To this end, previous works obtained atomistics-consistent material models for two common energetic crystals, HMX and RDX, such that pore collapse calculations adhered closely to molecular dynamics (MD) results on key features of energy localization, particularly the profiles of the collapsing pores, appearance of shear bands, and the transition from viscoplastic to hydrodynamic collapse. However, some important aspects such as the temperature distributions in the hotspot were not as well captured. One potential issue was noted but not resolved adequately in those works, namely the grid resolution that should be employed in the meso-scale calculations for various pore sizes and shock strengths. Conventional computational mechanics guidelines for selecting meshes as fine as possible, balancing computational effort, accuracy and grid independence, were shown not to produce physically consistent features associated with shear localization. Here, we examine the physics of pore collapse, shear band evolution and structure, and hotspot formation, for both HMX and RDX; we then evaluate under what conditions atomistics-consistent models yield physically correct (considering MD as ground truth) hotspots for a range of pore diameters, from nm to microns, and for a wide range of shock strengths. The study provides insights into the effects of pore size and shock strength on pore collapse and hotspots, identifying aspects such as size-independent behaviors, and proportion of energy contained in shear as opposed to jet impact-heated regions of the hotspot. Areas for further improvement of atomistics-consistent material models are also indicated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22174v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chukwudubem Okafor, Jacob Herrin, Catalin R. Picu, Tommy Sewell, John Brennan, James Larentzos, H. S. Udaykumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QMol-grid: A MATLAB package for quantum-mechanical simulations in atomic and molecular systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17938v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The QMol-grid package provides a suite of routines for performing quantum-mechanical simulations in atomic and molecular systems, currently implemented in one spatial dimension. It supports ground- and excited-state calculations for the Schrodinger equation, density-functional theory, and Hartree-Fock levels of theory as well as propagators for field-free and field-driven time-dependent Schrodinger equation (TDSE) and real-time time-dependent density-functional theory (TDDFT), using symplectic-split schemes. The package is written using MATLAB's object-oriented features and handle classes. It is designed to facilitate access to the wave function(s) (TDSE) and the Kohn-Sham orbitals (TDDFT) within MATLAB's environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17938v3</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francois Mauger, Cristel Chandre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Train Multiplication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19747v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the Tensor Train Multiplication (TTM) algorithm for the elementwise multiplication of two tensor trains with bond dimension $\chi$. The computational complexity and memory requirements of the TTM algorithm scale as $\chi^3$ and $\chi^2$, respectively. This represents a significant improvement compared with the conventional approach, where the computational complexity scales as $\chi^4$ and memory requirements scale as $\chi^3$.We benchmark the TTM algorithm using flows obtained from artificial turbulence generation and numerically demonstrate its improved runtime and memory scaling compared with the conventional approach. The TTM algorithm paves the way towards GPU accelerated tensor network simulations of computational fluid dynamics problems with large bond dimensions due to its dramatic improvement in memory scaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19747v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexios A Michailidis, Christian Fenton, Martin Kiffner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Half-Heusler TiXSn (X=Pd, Pt and Ni): electronic, vibrational, and defect properties from first-principles calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09186v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The knowledge of Half-Heusler compounds have attracted much attention as materials for thermoelectric applications. In this work, we investigate, using first-principles calculations, the electronic, vibrational, and defect properties of TiXSn (X=Ni, Pd, Pt) half-Heusler compounds. The knowledge of such properties is vital for the understanding and improvement of thermoelectric transport properties of these materials. The band gap of the three compounds increase with the atomic number of the group 10 elements, in agreement with previous findings. The electronic effective masses of the three compounds are similar, while the heavy hole effective mass of TiPtSn is larger than those of the other two materials. Our calculations of the phonon dispersion included the calculation of the LO-TO splitting indicating that TiNiSn has a stronger ionic character and polar scattering of charge carriers by optical phonons in the case of low doping. Calculation of the formation energy of Ni interstitial defect in TiNiSn is very low, in agreement with previous results. Surprisingly, for the Pd interstitial in TiPdSn the formation energy is negative, suggesting that the full-Heusler structure can be more stable than the half-Heusler one. On the other hand, the formation energy of an interstitial in TiPtSn is significantly higher, suggesting smaller effects on both electronic structure and transport properties. The formation energy of all substitutional defects investigated are substantially higher than that of interstitial ones, suggesting that they should occur in very low concentrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09186v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateus Corradini Lopes, Alex Antonelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWAP algorithm for lattice spin models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04981v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We adapted the SWAP molecular dynamics algorithm for use in lattice Ising spin models. We dressed the spins with a randomly distributed length and we alternated long-range spin exchanges with conventional single spin flip Monte Carlo updates, both accepted with a stochastic rule which respects detailed balance. We show that this algorithm, when applied to the bidimensional Edwards-Anderson model, speeds up significantly the relaxation at low temperatures and manages to find ground states with high efficiency and little computational cost. The exploration of spin models should help in understanding why SWAP accelerates the evolution of particle systems and shed light on relations between dynamics and free-energy landscapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04981v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.L043301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 110, L043301 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Greivin Alfaro-Miranda, Leticia F. Cugliandolo, Marco Tarzia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advanced surrogate model for electron-scale turbulence in tokamak pedestals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09474v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive an advanced surrogate model for predicting turbulent transport at the edge of tokamaks driven by electron temperature gradient (ETG) modes.Our derivation is based on a recently developed sensitivity-driven sparse grid interpolation approach for uncertainty quantification and sensitivity analysis at scale, which informs the set of parameters that define the surrogate model as a scaling law.Our model reveals that ETG-driven electron heat flux is influenced by the safety factor $q$, electron beta $\beta_e$, and normalized electron Debye length $\lambda_D$, in addition to well-established parameters such as the electron temperature and density gradients. To assess the trustworthiness of our model's predictions beyond training, we compute prediction intervals using bootstrapping. The surrogate model's predictive power is tested across a wide range of parameter values, including within-distribution testing parameters (to verify our model) as well as out-of-bounds and out-of-distribution testing (to validate the proposed model). Overall, validation efforts show that our model competes well with, or can even outperform, existing scaling laws in predicting ETG-driven transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09474v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/S0022377824001314</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ionut-Gabriel Farcas, Gabriele Merlo, Frank Jenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting solvation free energies with an implicit solvent machine learning potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00183v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) potentials are a powerful tool in molecular modeling, enabling ab initio accuracy for comparably small computational costs. Nevertheless, all-atom simulations employing best-performing graph neural network architectures are still too expensive for applications requiring extensive sampling, such as free energy computations. Implicit solvent models could provide the necessary speed-up due to reduced degrees of freedom and faster dynamics. Here, we introduce a Solvation Free Energy Path Reweighting (ReSolv) framework to parametrize an implicit solvent ML potential for small organic molecules that accurately predicts the hydration free energy, an essential parameter in drug design and pollutant modeling. With a combination of top-down (experimental hydration free energy data) and bottom-up (ab initio data of molecules in a vacuum) learning, ReSolv bypasses the need for intractable ab initio data of molecules in explicit bulk solvent and does not have to resort to less accurate data-generating models. On the FreeSolv dataset, ReSolv achieves a mean absolute error close to average experimental uncertainty, significantly outperforming standard explicit solvent force fields. Compared to the explicit solvent ML potential, ReSolv offers a computational speedup of four orders of magnitude and attains closer agreement with experiments. The presented framework paves the way toward deep molecular models that are more accurate yet computationally cheaper than classical atomistic models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00183v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastien R\"ocken, Anton F. Burnet, Julija Zavadlav</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
