<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 04:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal free-energy density functional for warm dense matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Finite-temperature orbital-free density functional theory (FT-OFDFT) holds significant promise for simulating warm dense matter due to its favorable scaling with both system size and temperature. However, the lack of the numerically accurate and transferable noninteracting free energy functionals results in a limit on the application of FT-OFDFT for warm dense matter simulations. Here, a nonlocal free energy functional, named XWMF, was derived by line integrals for FT-OFDFT simulations. Particularly, a designed integral path, wherein the electronic density varies from uniform to inhomogeneous, was employed to accurately describe deviations in response behavior from the uniform electron gas. The XWMF has been benchmarked by a range of warm dense matter systems including the Si, Al, H, He, and H-He mixture. The simulated results demonstrate that FT-OFDFT within XWMF achieves remarkable performance for accuracy and numerical stability. It is worth noting that XWMF exhibits a low computational cost for large-scale ab~initio simulations, offering exciting opportunities for the realistic simulations of warm dense matter systems covering a broad range of temperatures and pressures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12527v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Ma, Min Chen, Yu Xie, Qiang Xu, Wenhui Mi, Yanchao Wang, Yanming Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-task learning for molecular electronic structure approaching coupled-cluster accuracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12229v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) plays an important role in quantum chemistry, providing fast-to-evaluate predictive models for various properties of molecules. However, as most existing ML models for molecular electronic properties use density function theory (DFT) databases as the ground truth in training, their prediction accuracy cannot go beyond the DFT. In this work, we developed a unified ML method for electronic structures of organic molecules using the gold-standard CCSD(T) calculations as training data. Tested on hydrocarbon molecules, our model outperforms the DFT with the widely-used B3LYP functional in both computation costs and prediction accuracy of various quantum chemical properties. We apply the model to aromatic compounds and semiconducting polymers on both ground state and excited state properties, demonstrating its accuracy and generalization capability to complex systems that are hard to calculate using CCSD(T)-level methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12229v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Tang, Brian Xiao, Wenhao He, Pero Subasic, Avetik R. Harutyunyan, Yao Wang, Fang Liu, Haowei Xu, Ju Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Ground and Excited States via Single Reference Coupled-Cluster Theory and Algebraic Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12238v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The exploration of the root structure of coupled cluster equations holds both foundational and practical significance for computational quantum chemistry. This study provides insight into the intricate root structures of these non-linear equations at both the CCD and CCSD level of theory. We utilize computational techniques from algebraic geometry, specifically the monodromy and parametric homotopy continuation methods, to calculate the full solution set. We compare the computed CC roots against various established theoretical upper bounds, shedding light on the accuracy and efficiency of these bounds. We hereby focus on the dissociation processes of four-electron systems such as (H$_2$)$_2$ in both D$_{2{\rm h}}$ and D$_{\infty {\rm h}}$ configurations, H$_4$ symmetrically distorted on a circle, and lithium hydride. We moreover investigate the ability of single-reference coupled cluster solutions to approximate excited state energies. We find that multiple CC roots describe energies of excited states with high accuracy. Remarkably, our investigations reveal that for systems like lithium hydride, CC not only provides high-accuracy approximations to several excited state energies but also to the states themselves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12238v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svala Sverrisd\'ottir, Fabian M. Faulstich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large scale scattering using fast solvers based on neural operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend a recently proposed machine-learning-based iterative solver, i.e. the hybrid iterative transferable solver (HINTS), to solve the scattering problem described by the Helmholtz equation in an exterior domain with a complex absorbing boundary condition. The HINTS method combines neural operators (NOs) with standard iterative solvers, e.g. Jacobi and Gauss-Seidel (GS), to achieve better performance by leveraging the spectral bias of neural networks. In HINTS, some iterations of the conventional iterative method are replaced by inferences of the pre-trained NO. In this work, we employ HINTS to solve the scattering problem for both 2D and 3D problems, where the standard iterative solver fails. We consider square and triangular scatterers of various sizes in 2D, and a cube and a model submarine in 3D. We explore and illustrate the extrapolation capability of HINTS in handling diverse geometries of the scatterer, which is achieved by training the NO on non-scattering scenarios and then deploying it in HINTS to solve scattering problems. The accurate results demonstrate that the NO in HINTS method remains effective without retraining or fine-tuning it whenever a new scatterer is given. Taken together, our results highlight the adaptability and versatility of the extended HINTS methodology in addressing diverse scattering problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12380v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongren Zou, Adar Kahana, Enrui Zhang, Eli Turkel, Rishikesh Ranade, Jay Pathak, George Em Karniadakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent convergent close coupling method for molecular ionization in laser fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12455v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a time-dependent multi-configurational numerical technique for calculating ionization by short laser pulses of many-electron molecules. The method is based on the expansion of the wave function of a molecule into the eigenstates of the molecular ion. We classify this method as time-dependent convergent close coupling (TDCCC) because it uses the same symmetry for channel functions as the well-known convergent close coupling (CCC) method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12455v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladislav V. Serov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The hBN defects database: a theoretical compilation of color centers in hexagonal boron nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12749v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Color centers in hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) have become an intensively researched system due to their potential applications in quantum technologies. There has been a large variety of defects being fabricated, yet, for many of them, the atomic origin remains unclear. The direct imaging of the defect is technically very challenging, in particular since, in a diffraction-limited spot, there are many defects and then one has to identify the one that is optically active. Another approach is to compare the photophysical properties with theoretical simulations and identify which defect has a matching signature. It has been shown that a single property for this is insufficient and causes misassignments. Here, we publish a density functional theory (DFT)-based searchable online database covering the electronic structure of hBN defects (257 triplet and 211 singlet configurations), as well as their photophysical fingerprint (excited state lifetime, quantum efficiency, transition dipole moment and orientation, polarization visibility, and many more). All data is open-source and publicly accessible at https://h-bn.info and can be downloaded. It is possible to enter the experimentally observed defect signature and the database will output possible candidates which can be narrowed down by entering as many observed properties as possible. The database will be continuously updated with more defects and new photophysical properties (which can also be specifically requested by any users). The database therefore allows one to reliably identify defects but also investigate which defects might be promising for magnetic field sensing or quantum memory applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12749v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chanaprom Cholsuk, Ashkan Zand, Asli Cakan, Tobias Vogl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stable poro-mechanical formulation for Material Point Methods leveraging overlapping meshes and multi-field ghost penalisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12814v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Material Point Method (MPM) is widely used to analyse coupled (solid-water) problems under large deformations/displacements. However, if not addressed carefully, MPM u-p formulations for poro-mechanics can be affected by two major sources of instability. Firstly, inf-sup condition violation can arise when the spaces for the displacement and pressure fields are not chosen correctly, resulting in an unstable pressure field. Secondly, the intrinsic nature of particle-based discretisation makes the MPM an unfitted mesh-based method, which can affect the system's condition number and solvability, particularly when background mesh elements are poorly populated. This work proposes a solution to both problems. The inf-sup condition is avoided using two overlapping meshes, a coarser one for the pressure and a finer one for the displacement. This approach does not require stabilisation of the primary equations since it is stable by design and is particularly valuable for low-order shape functions. As for the system's poor condition number, a face ghost penalisation method is added to both the primary equations, which constitutes a novelty in the context of MPM mixed formulations. This study frequently makes use of the theories of functional analysis or the unfitted Finite Element Method (FEM). Although these theories may not directly apply to the MPM, they provide a robust and logical basis for the research. These rationales are further supported by three numerical examples, which encompass both elastic and elasto-plastic cases and drained and undrained conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12814v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuliano Pretti, Robert E. Bird, Nathan D. Gavin, William M. Coombs, Charles E. Augarde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical Sample Complexity of Neural Network Mixed State Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.01840v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum state reconstruction using Neural Quantum States has been proposed as a viable tool to reduce quantum shot complexity in practical applications, and its advantage over competing techniques has been shown in numerical experiments focusing mainly on the noiseless case. In this work, we numerically investigate the performance of different quantum state reconstruction techniques for mixed states: the finite-temperature Ising model. We show how to systematically reduce the quantum resource requirement of the algorithms by applying variance reduction techniques. Then, we compare the two leading neural quantum state encodings of the state, namely, the Neural Density Operator and the positive operator-valued measurement representation, and illustrate their different performance as the mixedness of the target state varies. We find that certain encodings are more efficient in different regimes of mixedness and point out the need for designing more efficient encodings in terms of both classical and quantum resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.01840v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haimeng Zhao, Giuseppe Carleo, Filippo Vicentini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Class of Phase Space Representations for the Exact Population Dynamics of Two-State Quantum Systems and the Relation to Triangle Window Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04868v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Isomorphism of the two-state system is heuristic in understanding the dynamical or statistical behavior of the simplest yet most quantum system that has no classical counterpart. We use the constraint phase space developed in J. Chem. Phys. 2016, 145, 204105; 2019, 151, 024105 and J. Phys. Chem. Lett. 2021, 12, 2496-2501, non-covariant phase space functions, time-dependent weight functions, and time-dependent normalization factors to construct a novel class of phase space representations of the exact population dynamics of the two-state quantum system. The equations of motion of the trajectory on constraint phase space are isomorphic to the time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation. The contribution of each trajectory to the integral expression for the population dynamics is always positive semi-definite. We also prove that the triangle window function approach, albeit proposed as a heuristic empirical model in J. Chem. Phys. 2016, 145, 144108, is related to a special case of the novel class and leads to an isomorphic representation of the exact population dynamics of the two-state quantum system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04868v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/1674-0068/cjcp2403033</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chinese Journal of Chemical Physics, 37, 230-254 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiangsong Cheng, Xin He, Jian Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
