<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 05:00:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Extreme Value Statistics of Community Detection in Complex Networks with Reduced Network Extremal Ensemble Learning (RenEEL)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Arguably, the most fundamental problem in Network Science is finding structure within a complex network. One approach is to partition the nodes into communities that are more densely connected than one expects in a random network. "The" community structure then corresponds to the partition that maximizes Modularity, an objective function that quantifies this idea. Finding the maximizing partition, however, is a computationally difficult, NP-Complete problem. We explore using a recently introduced machine-learning algorithmic scheme to find the structure of benchmark networks. The scheme, known as RenEEL, creates an ensemble of $K$ partitions and updates the ensemble by replacing its worst member with the best of $L$ partitions found by analyzing a simplified network. The updating continues until consensus is achieved within the ensemble. We perform an empirical study of three real-world networks to explore how the Modularity of the consensus partition depends on the values of $K$ and $L$ and relate the results to the extreme value statistics of record-breaking. We find that increasing $K$ is generally more effective than increasing $L$ for finding the best partition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00977v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tania Ghosh, R. K. P. Zia, Kevin E. Bassler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Petrov-Galerkin model reduction for thermochemical nonequilibrium gas mixtures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: State-specific thermochemical collisional models are crucial to accurately describe the physics of systems involving nonequilibrium plasmas, but they are also computationally expensive and impractical for large-scale, multi-dimensional simulations. Historically, computational cost has been mitigated by using empirical and physics-based arguments to reduce the complexity of the governing equations. However, the resulting models are often inaccurate and they fail to capture the important features of the original physics. Additionally, the construction of these models is often impractical, as it requires extensive user supervision and time-consuming parameter tuning. In this paper, we address these issues through an easily-implementable and computationally-efficient model reduction pipeline based on the Petrov-Galerkin projection of the nonlinear kinetic equations. Our approach is justified by the observation that kinetic systems in thermal nonequilibrium tend to exhibit low-rank dynamics that rapidly drive the state towards a low-dimensional subspace. Furthermore, despite the nonlinear nature of the governing equations, we observe that the dynamics of these systems evolve on subspaces that can be accurately identified using the linearized equations about thermochemical equilibrium, which significantly reduce the cost associated with the construction of the model. The approach is demonstrated on a rovibrational collisional model for the O$_2$-O system, and a vibrational collisional model for the combined O$_2$-O and O$_2$-O$_2$ systems. Our method achieves high accuracy, with relative errors of less than 1% for macroscopic quantities (i.e., moments) and 10% for microscopic quantities (i.e., energy levels population), while also delivering excellent compression rates and speedups, outperforming existing state-of-the-art techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01673v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Zanardi, Alberto Padovan, Daniel J. Bodony, Marco Panesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variance-reduced random batch Langevin dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The random batch method is advantageous in accelerating force calculations in particle simulations, but it poses a challenge of removing the artificial heating effect in application to the Langevin dynamics. We develop an approach to solve this issue by estimating the force variance, resulting in a variance-reduced random batch Langevin dynamics. Theoretical analysis shows the high-order local truncation error of the time step in the numerical discretization scheme, in consistent with the fluctuation-dissipation theorem. Numerical results indicate that the method can achieve a significant variance reduction since a smaller batch size provides accurate approximation, demonstrating the attractive feature of the variance-reduced random batch method for Langevin dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01762v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenli Xu, Yue Zhao, Qi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Constrained Graph Neural Networks for Spatio-Temporal Prediction of Drop Impact on OLED Display Panels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study aims to predict the spatio-temporal evolution of physical quantities observed in multi-layered display panels subjected to the drop impact of a ball. To model these complex interactions, graph neural networks have emerged as promising tools, effectively representing objects and their relationships as graph structures. In particular, MeshGraphNets (MGNs) excel in capturing dynamics in dynamic physics simulations using irregular mesh data. However, conventional MGNs often suffer from non-physical artifacts, such as the penetration of overlapping objects. To resolve this, we propose a physics-constrained MGN that mitigates these penetration issues while maintaining high level of accuracy in temporal predictions. Furthermore, to enhance the model's robustness, we explore noise injection strategies with varying magnitudes and different combinations of targeted components, such as the ball, the plate, or both. In addition, our analysis on model stability in spatio-temporal predictions reveals that during the inference, deriving next time-step node positions by predicting relative changes (e.g., displacement or velocity) between the current and future states yields superior accuracy compared to direct absolute position predictions. This approach consistently shows greater stability and reliability in determining subsequent node positions across various scenarios. Building on this validated model, we evaluate its generalization performance by examining its ability to extrapolate with respect to design variables. Furthermore, the physics-constrained MGN serves as a near real-time emulator for the design optimization of multi-layered OLED display panels, where thickness variables are optimized to minimize stress in the light-emitting materials. It outperforms conventional MGN in optimization tasks, demonstrating its effectiveness for practical design applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01848v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiyong Kim, Jangseop Park, Nayong Kim, Younyeol Yu, Kiseok Chang, Chang-Seung Woo, Sunwoong Yang, Namwoo Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-implicit Lax-Wendroff kinetic scheme for multi-scale phonon transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01945v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fast and accurate predictions of the spatiotemporal distributions of temperature are crucial to the multi-scale thermal management and safe operation of microelectronic devices. To realize it, an efficient semi-implicit Lax-Wendroff kinetic scheme is developed for numerically solving the transient phonon Boltzmann transport equation (BTE) from the ballistic to diffusive regime. The phonon BTE at the cell center is discretized under the framework of finite volume method, where the trapezoidal and midpoint rules are used to deal with the temporal integration of phonon scattering and convection terms, respectively. For the reconstruction of the interfacial distribution function, the phonon BTE at the cell interface is discretized in the form of finite difference method and solved numerically, where second-order upwind and central scheme are used to deal with the spatial interpolation and gradient of interfacial distribution function, respectively. The macroscopic governing equations are invoked for the evolution of macroscopic fields at both the cell center and interface, where the macroscopic flux is obtained by taking the moment of the interfacial distribution function. Numerical results show that the present scheme could accurately predict the steady/unsteady heat conduction in solid materials from the ballistic to diffusive regime, and its time and cell size are not limited by the relaxation time and phonon mean free path. The present work could provide a useful tool for the efficient predictions of the macroscopic spatiotemporal distributions in the multi-scale thermal engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01945v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuang Peng, Songze Chen, Hong Liang, Chuang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-multiplexed Reservoir Computing with Quantum-Dot Lasers: Does more complexity lead to better performance?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02032v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reservoir computing with optical devices offers an energy-efficient approach for time-series forecasting. Quantum dot lasers with feedback are modelled in this paper to explore the extent to which increased complexity in the charge carrier dynamics within the nanostructured semiconductor can enhance the prediction performance. By tuning the scattering interactions, the laser's dynamics and response time can be finely adjusted, allowing for a systematic investigation. It is found that both system response time and task requirements need to be considered to find optimal operation conditions. Further, lasers with pronounced relaxation oscillations outperform those with strongly damped dynamics, even if the underlying charge carrier dynamics is more complex. This demonstrates that optimal reservoir computing performance relies not only on internal complexity but also on the effective utilization of these dynamics through the output sampling process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02032v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huifang Dong, Lina Jaurigue, Kathy L\"udge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-learned nodal structures of Fermion systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A major challenge in quantum physics is the accurate simulation of fermionic systems, particularly those involving strong correlations. While effective for bosonic systems, traditional quantum Monte Carlo methods encounter the notorious sign problem when applied to Fermions, often resulting in biased outcomes through the fixed-node approximation. This work demonstrates the potential of machine learning techniques to address these limitations by allowing nodal structures to be learned through gradient descent optimization iterations and the variational algorithm. Using a neural network to represent the wave function, we focus on quantum dots containing up to 30 electrons. The results show a significant reduction in the variational bias, achieving greater accuracy and a lower ground state energy than diffusion Monte Carlo with the fixed-node approximation. Our approach paves the way for precise and accurate property predictions in fermionic strongly correlated systems, advancing fundamental understanding and applications in quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02257v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Freitas, B. Abreu, S. A. Vitiello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic feature selection and weighting using Differentiable Information Imbalance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Feature selection is a common process in many applications, but it is accompanied by uncertainties such as: What is the optimal dimensionality of an interpretable, reduced feature space to retain a maximum amount of information? How to account for different units of measure in features? How to weight different features according to their importance? To address these challenges, we introduce the Differentiable Information Imbalance (DII), an automatic data analysis method to rank information content between sets of features. Based on the nearest neighbors according to distances in the ground truth feature space, the method finds a low-dimensional subset of the input features, within which the pairwise distance relations are most similar to the ground truth. By employing the Differentiable Information Imbalance as a loss function, the relative feature weights of the inputs are optimized, simultaneously performing unit alignment and relative importance scaling, while preserving interpretability. Furthermore, this method can generate sparse solutions and determine the optimal size of the reduced feature space. We illustrate the usefulness of this approach on two prototypical benchmark problems: (1) Identifying a small set of collective variables capable of describing the conformational space of a biomolecule, and (2) selecting a subset of features for training a machine-learning force field. The results highlight the potential of the Differentiable Information Imbalance in addressing feature selection challenges and optimizing dimensionality in various applications. The method is implemented in the Python library DADApy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00851v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romina Wild, Vittorio Del Tatto, Felix Wodaczek, Bingqing Cheng, Alessandro Laio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A highly efficient Voigt program for line profile computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Evaluation of the Voigt function, a convolution of a Lorentzian and a Gaussian profile, is essential in various fields such as spectroscopy, atmospheric science, and astrophysics. Efficient computation of the function is crucial, especially in applications where the function may be called for an enormous number of times. In this paper, we present a highly efficient novel algorithm and its Fortran90 implementation for the practical evaluation of the Voigt function with accuracy in the order of 1.0e-6. The algorithm uses improved fits based on Chebyshev subinterval polynomial approximation for functions in two variables. The algorithm significantly outperforms widely-used competitive algorithms in the literature, in terms of computational speed, making it highly suitable for real-time applications and large-scale data processing tasks. The substantial improvement in efficiency positions the present algorithm and computer code as a valuable tool in relevant scientific domains. The algorithm has been adopted and implemented in the Meudon PDR code at Paris Observatory and is recommended for similar applications and simulation packages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00917v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mofreh R. Zaghloul, Jacques Le Bourlot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Global Analysis of Experimental Dynamics through Low-Dimensional Linear Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00989v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dynamical systems theory has long provided a foundation for understanding evolving phenomena across scientific domains. Yet, the application of this theory to complex real-world systems remains challenging due to issues in mathematical modeling, nonlinearity, and high dimensionality. In this work, we introduce a data-driven computational framework to derive low-dimensional linear models for nonlinear dynamical systems directly from raw experimental data. This framework enables global stability analysis through interpretable linear models that capture the underlying system structure. Our approach employs time-delay embedding, physics-informed deep autoencoders, and annealing-based regularization to identify novel low-dimensional coordinate representations, unlocking insights across a variety of simulated and previously unstudied experimental dynamical systems. These new coordinate representations enable accurate long-horizon predictions and automatic identification of intricate invariant sets while providing empirical stability guarantees. Our method offers a promising pathway to analyze complex dynamical behaviors across fields such as physics, climate science, and engineering, with broad implications for understanding nonlinear systems in the real world.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00989v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel A. Moore, Brian P. Mann, Boyuan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combining graph deep learning and London dispersion interatomic potentials: A case study on pnictogen chalcohalides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01197v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine-learning interatomic potential models based on graph neural network architectures have the potential to make atomistic materials modeling widely accessible due to their computational efficiency, scalability, and broad applicability. The training datasets for many such models are derived from density-functional theory calculations, typically using a semilocal exchange-correlation functional. As a result, long-range interactions such as London dispersion are often missing in these models. We investigate whether this missing component can be addressed by combining a graph deep learning potential with semiempirical dispersion models. We assess this combination by deriving the equations of state for layered pnictogen chalcohalides BiTeBr and BiTeI and performing crystal structure optimizations for a broader set of V-VI-VII compounds with various stoichiometries, many of which possess van der Waals gaps. We characterize the optimized crystal structures by calculating their X-ray diffraction patterns and radial distribution function histograms, which are also used to compute Earth mover's distances to quantify the dissimilarity between the optimized and corresponding experimental structures. We find that dispersion-corrected graph deep learning potentials generally (though not universally) provide a more realistic description of these compounds due to the inclusion of van der Waals attractions. In particular, their use results in systematic improvements in predicting not only the van der Waals gap but also the layer thickness in layered V-VI-VII compounds. Our results demonstrate that the combined potentials studied here, derived from a straightforward approach that neither requires fine-tuning the training nor refitting the potential parameters, can significantly improve the description of layered polar crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01197v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0237101</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 161, 174106 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>\c{C}etin K{\i}l{\i}\c{c}, S\"umeyra G\"uler-K{\i}l{\i}\c{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-the-fly reparametrization of pairwise dispersion interactions for accurate and efficient molecular dynamics: Phase diagram of white phosphorus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01298v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate estimation of the contribution from dispersion interactions to the total energy is important for many molecular systems and low-dimensional solids. In this work we demonstrate how the recently developed linear-scaling many-body dispersion correction method can be efficiently applied in molecular dynamics simulations while keeping high accuracy. This is achieved by reparametrization of the effective pairwise dispersion interactions on the fly during the simulation. We demonstrate this method by computing order-disorder and solid-liquid transitions of the phase diagram of white phosphorus (P$_4$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01298v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heikki Muhli, Tapio Ala-Nissila, Miguel A. Caro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A gamma variate generator with shape parameter less than unity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01415v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Algorithms for generating random numbers that follow a gamma distribution with shape parameter less than unity are proposed. Acceptance-rejection algorithms are developed, based on the generalized exponential distribution. The squeeze technique is applied to our method, and then piecewise envelope functions are further considered. The proposed methods are excellent in acceptance efficiency and promising in speed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01415v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seiji Zenitani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LES-SINDy: Laplace-Enhanced Sparse Identification of Nonlinear Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01719v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sparse Identification of Nonlinear Dynamical Systems (SINDy) is a powerful tool for the data-driven discovery of governing equations. However, it encounters challenges when modeling complex dynamical systems involving high-order derivatives or discontinuities, particularly in the presence of noise. These limitations restrict its applicability across various fields in applied mathematics and physics. To mitigate these, we propose Laplace-Enhanced SparSe Identification of Nonlinear Dynamical Systems (LES-SINDy). By transforming time-series measurements from the time domain to the Laplace domain using the Laplace transform and integration by parts, LES-SINDy enables more accurate approximations of derivatives and discontinuous terms. It also effectively handles unbounded growth functions and accumulated numerical errors in the Laplace domain, thereby overcoming challenges in the identification process. The model evaluation process selects the most accurate and parsimonious dynamical systems from multiple candidates. Experimental results across diverse ordinary and partial differential equations show that LES-SINDy achieves superior robustness, accuracy, and parsimony compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01719v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyang Zheng, Guang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Element Simulations of particles interacting via capillary forces using MercuryDPM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02042v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the implementation of two advanced capillary bridge approximations within the Discrete Element Method (DEM) framework of the open-source code MercuryDPM. While MercuryDPM already includes a simplified version of the Willett approximation, our work involves implementing both the classical Willett approximation and the recently published Bagheri approximation in MercuryDPM. Through detailed descriptions and illustrative simulations using a two-particle collision model, we demonstrate the enhanced accuracy and capabilities of these approximations in capturing the complex dynamics of wet granular matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02042v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meysam Bagheri, Sudeshna Roy, Thorsten Poeschel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of noise-induced modulations on the timing stability of passively mode-locked semiconductor laser subject to optical feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02049v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that passively mode-locked lasers subject to feedback from a single external cavity can exhibit large timing fluctuations on short time scales despite having a relatively small long-term timing jitter, meaning that the commonly used von Linde and K\'{e}f\'{e}lian techniques of experimentally estimating the timing jitter can lead to large errors in the estimation of the arrival time of pulses. We also show that adding a second feedback cavity of the appropriate length can significantly suppress noise-induced modulations that are present in the single feedback system. This reduces the short time scale fluctuations of the interspike interval time and at the same time improves the variance of the fluctuation of the pulse arrival times on long time scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02049v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lina Jaurigue, Kathy L\"udge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solute diffusion calculation in Fe-Si and Fe-Cr-Si multicomponent alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02053v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Diffusion plays a key role in microstructure evolution at multicomponent alloys: diffusion controls the kinetics of phase transformations and alloy homogenization. This study aims at developing computationally efficient approaches to estimate the solute diffusion coefficients in two-component systems. We consider silicon as the solute example because it is highly used in industrial steels. We demonstrate that the silicon jump frequency may be calculated with the bond potential instead of the more computationally expensive machine learning potential in Fe-Si and Fe-Cr-Si alloys. We show that the silicon jump frequency can be estimated from thermodynamic simulations for the bond potential without kinetic simulations. The silicon correlation factor slightly depends on silicon concentration and can be approximately estimated by the analytical nine-frequency model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02053v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timofei Miryashkin, Ivan Novoselov, Alexey Yanilkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building robust surrogate models of laser-plasma interactions using large scale PIC simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02079v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As the repetition rates of ultra-high intensity lasers increase, simulations used for the prediction of experimental results may need to be augmented with machine learning to keep up. In this paper, the usage of gaussian process regression in producing surrogate models of laser-plasma interactions from particle-in-cell simulations is investigated. Such a model retains the characteristic behaviour of the simulations but allows for faster on-demand results and estimation of statistical noise. A demonstrative model of Bremsstrahlung emission by hot electrons from a femtosecond timescale laser pulse in the $10^{20} - 10^{23}\;\mathrm{Wcm}^{-2}$ intensity range is produced using 800 simulations of such a laser-solid interaction from 1D hybrid-PIC. While the simulations required 84,000 CPU-hours to generate, subsequent training occurs on the order of a minute on a single core and prediction takes only a fraction of a second. The model trained on this data is then compared against analytical expectations. The efficiency of training the model and its subsequent ability to distinguish types of noise within the data are analysed, and as a result error bounds on the model are defined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02079v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Smith, Christopher Ridgers, Kate Lancaster, Chris Arran, Stuart Morris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised detection of semantic correlations in big data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02126v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In real-world data, information is stored in extremely large feature vectors. These variables are typically correlated due to complex interactions involving many features simultaneously. Such correlations qualitatively correspond to semantic roles and are naturally recognized by both the human brain and artificial neural networks. This recognition enables, for instance, the prediction of missing parts of an image or text based on their context. We present a method to detect these correlations in high-dimensional data represented as binary numbers. We estimate the binary intrinsic dimension of a dataset, which quantifies the minimum number of independent coordinates needed to describe the data, and is therefore a proxy of semantic complexity. The proposed algorithm is largely insensitive to the so-called curse of dimensionality, and can therefore be used in big data analysis. We test this approach identifying phase transitions in model magnetic systems and we then apply it to the detection of semantic correlations of images and text inside deep neural networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02126v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santiago Acevedo, Alex Rodriguez, Alessandro Laio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>eTraj.jl: Trajectory-Based Simulation for Strong-Field Ionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02133v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dynamics of light-matter interactions in the realm of strong-field ionization has been a focal point and has attracted widespread interest. We present the eTraj.jl program package, designed to implement established classical/semiclassical trajectory-based methods to determine the photoelectron momentum distribution resulting from strong-field ionization of both atoms and molecules. The program operates within a unified theoretical framework that separates the trajectory-based computation into two stages: initial-condition preparation and trajectory evolution. For initial-condition preparation, we provide several methods, including the Strong-Field Approximation with Saddle-Point Approximation (SFA-SPA), SFA-SPA with Non-adiabatic Expansion (SFA-SPANE), and the Ammosov-Delone-Krainov theory (ADK), with atomic and molecular variants, as well as the Weak-Field Asymptotic Theory (WFAT) for molecules. For trajectory evolution, available options are Classical Trajectory Monte-Carlo (CTMC), which employs purely classical electron trajectories, and the Quantum Trajectory Monte-Carlo (QTMC) and Semi-Classical Two-Step model (SCTS), which include the quantum phase during trajectory evolution. The program is a versatile, efficient, and out-of-the-box solution for trajectory-based simulations for strong-field ionization. It is designed with user-friendliness in mind and is expected to serve as a valuable and powerful tool for the community of strong-field physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02133v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyu Zhu, Hongcheng Ni, Jian Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Density Functional Theory for Static Correlation in Large Molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02254v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A critical challenge for density functional theory (DFT) in practice is its limited ability to treat static electron correlation, leading to errors in its prediction of charges, multiradicals, and reaction barriers. Recently, we combined one- and two-electron reduced density matrix theories with DFT to obtain a universal $O(N^3)$ generalization of DFT for static correlation. In this Letter, we enhance the theory's treatment of large molecules by renormalizing the trace of the two-electron identity matrix in the correction using Cauchy-Schwarz inequalities of the electron-electron repulsion matrix. We apply the resulting functional theory to linear hydrogen chains as well as the prediction of the singlet-triplet gap and equilibrium geometries of a series of acenes. This renormalization of the generalized DFT retains the $O(N^{3})$ computational scaling of DFT while enabling the accurate treatment of static correlation for a broad range of molecules and materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02254v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, L040802 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Gibney, Jan-Niklas Boyn, David A. Mazziotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multidimensional coherent spectroscopy of correlated lattice systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02389v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multidimensional coherent spectroscopy (MDCS) has been established in quantum chemistry as a powerful tool for studying the nonlinear response and nonequilibrium dynamics of molecular systems. More recently, the technique has also been applied to correlated electron materials, where the interplay of localized and itinerant states makes the interpretation of the spectra more challenging. Here we use the Keldysh contour representation of effective models and nonequilibrium dynamical mean field theory to systematically study the MDCS signals of prototypical correlated lattice systems. By analyzing the current induced by sequences of ultrashort laser pulses we demonstrate the usefulness of MDCS as a diagnostic tool for excitation pathways and coherent processes in correlated solids. We also show that this technique allows to extract detailed information on the nature and evolution of photo-excited nonequilibrium states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02389v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiyu Chen, Philipp Werner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty-biased molecular dynamics for learning uniformly accurate interatomic potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01416v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficiently creating a concise but comprehensive data set for training machine-learned interatomic potentials (MLIPs) is an under-explored problem. Active learning, which uses biased or unbiased molecular dynamics (MD) to generate candidate pools, aims to address this objective. Existing biased and unbiased MD-simulation methods, however, are prone to miss either rare events or extrapolative regions -- areas of the configurational space where unreliable predictions are made. This work demonstrates that MD, when biased by the MLIP's energy uncertainty, simultaneously captures extrapolative regions and rare events, which is crucial for developing uniformly accurate MLIPs. Furthermore, exploiting automatic differentiation, we enhance bias-forces-driven MD with the concept of bias stress. We employ calibrated gradient-based uncertainties to yield MLIPs with similar or, sometimes, better accuracy than ensemble-based methods at a lower computational cost. Finally, we apply uncertainty-biased MD to alanine dipeptide and MIL-53(Al), generating MLIPs that represent both configurational spaces more accurately than models trained with conventional MD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01416v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41524-024-01254-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>npj Comput. Mater. 10, 83 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Zaverkin, David Holzm\"uller, Henrik Christiansen, Federico Errica, Francesco Alesiani, Makoto Takamoto, Mathias Niepert, Johannes K\"astner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More quantum chemistry with fewer qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16873v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum computation is one of the most promising new paradigms for the simulation of physical systems composed of electrons and atomic nuclei, with applications in chemistry, solid-state physics, materials science, and molecular biology. This requires a truncated representation of the electronic structure Hamiltonian using a finite number of orbitals. While it is, in principle, obvious how to improve on the representation by including more orbitals, this is usually unfeasible in practice (e.g., because of the limited number of qubits available) and severely compromises the accuracy of the obtained results. Here, we propose a quantum algorithm that improves on the representation of the physical problem by virtue of second-order perturbation theory. In particular, our quantum algorithm evaluates the second-order energy correction through a series of time-evolution steps under the unperturbed Hamiltonian. An important application is to go beyond the active-space approximation, allowing to include corrections of virtual orbitals, known as multireference perturbation theory. Here, we exploit that the unperturbed Hamiltonian is diagonal for virtual orbitals and show that the number of qubits is independent of the number of virtual orbitals. This gives rise to more accurate energy estimates without increasing the number of qubits. Moreover, we demonstrate numerically for realistic chemical systems that the total runtime has highly favorable scaling in the number of virtual orbitals compared to previous work. Numerical calculations confirm the necessity of the multireference perturbation theory energy corrections to reach accurate ground state energy estimates. Our perturbation theory quantum algorithm can also be applied to symmetry-adapted perturbation theory. As such, we demonstrate that perturbation theory can help to reduce the quantum hardware requirements for quantum chemistry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16873v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.043021</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Res. 6, 043021 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jakob G\"unther, Alberto Baiardi, Markus Reiher, Matthias Christandl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collocation methods for nonlinear differential equations on low-rank manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18721v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce new methods for integrating nonlinear differential equations on low-rank manifolds. These methods rely on interpolatory projections onto the tangent space, enabling low-rank time integration of vector fields that can be evaluated entry-wise. A key advantage of our approach is that it does not require the vector field to exhibit low-rank structure, thereby overcoming significant limitations of traditional dynamical low-rank methods based on orthogonal projection. To construct the interpolatory projectors, we develop a sparse tensor sampling algorithm based on the discrete empirical interpolation method (DEIM) that parameterizes tensor train manifolds and their tangent spaces with cross interpolation. Using these projectors, we propose two time integration schemes on low-rank tensor train manifolds. The first scheme integrates the solution at selected interpolation indices and constructs the solution with cross interpolation. The second scheme generalizes the well-known orthogonal projector-splitting integrator to interpolatory projectors. We demonstrate the proposed methods with applications to several tensor differential equations arising from the discretization of partial differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18721v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alec Dektor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-Rank Irreducible Cartesian Tensors for Equivariant Message Passing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14253v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ability to perform fast and accurate atomistic simulations is crucial for advancing the chemical sciences. By learning from high-quality data, machine-learned interatomic potentials achieve accuracy on par with ab initio and first-principles methods at a fraction of their computational cost. The success of machine-learned interatomic potentials arises from integrating inductive biases such as equivariance to group actions on an atomic system, e.g., equivariance to rotations and reflections. In particular, the field has notably advanced with the emergence of equivariant message passing. Most of these models represent an atomic system using spherical tensors, tensor products of which require complicated numerical coefficients and can be computationally demanding. Cartesian tensors offer a promising alternative, though state-of-the-art methods lack flexibility in message-passing mechanisms, restricting their architectures and expressive power. This work explores higher-rank irreducible Cartesian tensors to address these limitations. We integrate irreducible Cartesian tensor products into message-passing neural networks and prove the equivariance and traceless property of the resulting layers. Through empirical evaluations on various benchmark data sets, we consistently observe on-par or better performance than that of state-of-the-art spherical and Cartesian models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14253v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Zaverkin, Francesco Alesiani, Takashi Maruyama, Federico Errica, Henrik Christiansen, Makoto Takamoto, Nicolas Weber, Mathias Niepert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Ground State Properties: Constant Sample Complexity and Deep Learning Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18489v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A fundamental problem in quantum many-body physics is that of finding ground states of local Hamiltonians. A number of recent works gave provably efficient machine learning (ML) algorithms for learning ground states. Specifically, [Huang et al. Science 2022], introduced an approach for learning properties of the ground state of an $n$-qubit gapped local Hamiltonian $H$ from only $n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$ data points sampled from Hamiltonians in the same phase of matter. This was subsequently improved by [Lewis et al. Nature Communications 2024], to $\mathcal{O}(\log n)$ samples when the geometry of the $n$-qubit system is known. In this work, we introduce two approaches that achieve a constant sample complexity, independent of system size $n$, for learning ground state properties. Our first algorithm consists of a simple modification of the ML model used by Lewis et al. and applies to a property of interest known beforehand. Our second algorithm, which applies even if a description of the property is not known, is a deep neural network model. While empirical results showing the performance of neural networks have been demonstrated, to our knowledge, this is the first rigorous sample complexity bound on a neural network model for predicting ground state properties. We also perform numerical experiments that confirm the improved scaling of our approach compared to earlier results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18489v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Wanner, Laura Lewis, Chiranjib Bhattacharyya, Devdatt Dubhashi, Alexandru Gheorghiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smallest [5,6]fullerene as building blocks for 2D networks with superior stability and enhanced photocatalytic performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15421v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The assembly of molecules to form covalent networks can create varied lattice structures with distinct physical and chemical properties from conventional atomic lattices. Using the smallest stable [5,6]fullerene units as building blocks, various 2D C$_{24}$ networks can be formed with superior stability and strength compared to the recently synthesised monolayer polymeric C$_{60}$. Monolayer C$_{24}$ harnesses the properties of both carbon crystals and fullerene molecules, such as stable chemical bonds, suitable band gaps and large surface area, facilitating photocatalytic water splitting. The electronic band gaps of C$_{24}$ are comparable to TiO$_2$, providing appropriate band edges with sufficient external potential for overall water splitting over the acidic and neutral pH range. Upon photoexcitation, strong solar absorption enabled by strongly bound bright excitons can generate carriers effectively, while the type-II band alignment between C$_{24}$ and other 2D monolayers can separate electrons and holes in individual layers simultaneously. Additionally, the number of surface active sites of C$_{24}$ monolayers are three times more than that of their C$_{60}$ counterparts in a much wider pH range, providing spontaneous reaction pathways for hydrogen evolution reaction. Our work provides insights into materials design using tunable building blocks of fullerene units with tailored functions for energy generation, conversion and storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15421v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqi Wu, Bo Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical structure factors of Warm Dense Matter from Time-Dependent Orbital-Free and Mixed-Stochastic-Deterministic Density Functional Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23599v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the first calculations of the inelastic part of the dynamical structure factor (DSF) for warm dense matter (WDM) using Time-Dependent Orbital-Free Density Functional Theory (TD-OF-DFT) and Mixed-Stochastic-Deterministic (mixed) Kohn Sham TD-DFT (KS TD-DFT). WDM is an intermediate phase of matter found in planetary cores and laser-driven experiments, where the accurate calculation of the DSF is critical for interpreting X-ray Thomson scattering (XRTS) measurements. Traditional TD-DFT methods, while highly accurate, are computationally expensive, motivating the exploration of TD-OF-DFT and mixed TD-KS-DFT as more efficient alternatives. We applied these methods to experimentally measured WDM systems, including solid-density aluminum and beryllium, compressed beryllium, and carbon-hydrogen mixtures. Our results show that TD-OF-DFT requires a dynamical kinetic energy potential in order to qualitatively capture the plasmon response. Additionally, it struggles with capturing bound electron contributions and accurately modeling plasmon dynamics without the inclusion of a dynamic kinetic energy potential. In contrast, mixed TD-KS-DFT offers greater accuracy in distinguishing bound and free electron effects, aligning well with experimental data, though at a higher computational cost. This study highlights the trade-offs between computational efficiency and accuracy, demonstrating that TD-OF-DFT remains a valuable tool for rapid scans of parameter space, while mixed TD-KS-DFT should be preferred for high-fidelity simulations. Our findings provide insight into the future development of DFT methods for WDM and suggest potential improvements for TD-OF-DFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23599v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander J. White</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
