<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 05:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Many-Body Coarse-Grained Molecular Dynamics with the Atomic Cluster Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations provide detailed insight into atomic-scale mechanisms but are inherently restricted to small spatio-temporal scales. Coarse-grained molecular dynamics (CGMD) techniques allow simulations of much larger systems over extended timescales. In theory, these techniques can be quantitatively accurate, but common practice is to only target qualitatively correct behaviour of coarse-grained models. Recent advances in applying machine learning methodology in this setting are now being applied to create also quantitatively accurate CGMD models. We demonstrate how the Atomic Cluster Expansion parameterization (Drautz, 2019) can be used in this task to construct highly efficient, interpretable and accurate CGMD models. We focus in particular on exploring the role of many-body effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04661v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangshuai Wang, Gabor Csanyi, Christoph Ortner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calibrated Physics-Informed Uncertainty Quantification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neural PDEs offer efficient alternatives to computationally expensive numerical PDE solvers for simulating complex physical systems. However, their lack of robust uncertainty quantification (UQ) limits deployment in critical applications. We introduce a model-agnostic, physics-informed conformal prediction (CP) framework that provides guaranteed uncertainty estimates without requiring labelled data. By utilising a physics-based approach, we are able to quantify and calibrate the model's inconsistencies with the PDE rather than the uncertainty arising from the data. Our approach uses convolutional layers as finite-difference stencils and leverages physics residual errors as nonconformity scores, enabling data-free UQ with marginal and joint coverage guarantees across prediction domains for a range of complex PDEs. We further validate the efficacy of our method on neural PDE models for plasma modelling and shot design in fusion reactors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04406v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vignesh Gopakumar, Ander Gray, Lorenzo Zanisi, Timothy Nunn, Stanislas Pamela, Daniel Giles, Matt J. Kusner, Marc Peter Deisenroth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity Analysis of Normalizing Constant Estimation: from Jarzynski Equality to Annealed Importance Sampling and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given an unnormalized probability density $\pi\propto\mathrm{e}^{-V}$, estimating its normalizing constant $Z=\int_{\mathbb{R}^d}\mathrm{e}^{-V(x)}\mathrm{d}x$ or free energy $F=-\log Z$ is a crucial problem in Bayesian statistics, statistical mechanics, and machine learning. It is challenging especially in high dimensions or when $\pi$ is multimodal. To mitigate the high variance of conventional importance sampling estimators, annealing-based methods such as Jarzynski equality and annealed importance sampling are commonly adopted, yet their quantitative complexity guarantees remain largely unexplored. We take a first step toward a non-asymptotic analysis of annealed importance sampling. In particular, we derive an oracle complexity of $\widetilde{O}\left(\frac{d\beta^2{\mathcal{A}}^2}{\varepsilon^4}\right)$ for estimating $Z$ within $\varepsilon$ relative error with high probability, where $\beta$ is the smoothness of $V$ and $\mathcal{A}$ denotes the action of a curve of probability measures interpolating $\pi$ and a tractable reference distribution. Our analysis, leveraging Girsanov theorem and optimal transport, does not explicitly require isoperimetric assumptions on the target distribution. Finally, to tackle the large action of the widely used geometric interpolation of probability distributions, we propose a new normalizing constant estimation algorithm based on reverse diffusion samplers and establish a framework for analyzing its complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04575v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Guo, Molei Tao, Yongxin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A symmetric boundary integral formulation for time-domain acoustic-elastic scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04767v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A symmetric boundary integral formulation for the transient scattering of acoustic waves off homogeneous elastic obstacles is analyzed. Both the acoustic scattered field and the elastodynamic excited field are represented through a direct integral representation, resulting in a coupled system of interior/exterior integral equations that is symmetrized through the introduction of an auxiliary mortar variable. The analysis of each system and of its Galerkin discretization is done through the passage to the Laplace domain, which allows for the use of convolution quadrature for time discretization. Since the operators of the acustic and elastic Calder\'on calculus appear independently of each other, the formulation is well suited for non-intrusive numerical impementations (i.e. existing codes for acoustic and elastic problems can be used without any modification). Numerical examples are provided for two-dimensional examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04767v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tonatiuh S\'anchez-Vizuet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking electron capture processes in classical molecular dynamics simulations for spectral line broadening in plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04808v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Plasma spectroscopy is a fundamental tool for diagnosing laboratory and astrophysical plasmas. Accurate interpretation of spectra depends upon precise modeling and comprehension of Stark-broadening and other mechanisms affecting spectral lines. In this context, computer simulations have emerged as invaluable tools, offering \textit{idealized experiments} with well-defined conditions. Molecular dynamics simulations, in particular, excel at replicating the particle interactions within the plasma and their impact on the state of a radiating atom or ion. However, these simulations present challenges in tracking electron capture processes, since setting an unambiguous criterion to distinguish between bound and free electrons is not trivial. In this paper we introduce a new algorithm that, within a classical framework, precisely identifies the scenario in which an electron is captured by an ion and then follows a stable orbit around it. The algorithm's applicability extends to emitters with charges Z &gt;= 1. Importantly, the procedure enables the correct identification of valid time-histories of the electric microfield perturbing the emitting ion, which will be used for subsequent line shape calculations. As a result, our simulations naturally and accurately incorporate the effects of both strong collisions and electron capture phenomena on spectral line broadening.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04808v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Gonz\'alez-Herrero, G. P\'erez-Callejo, R. Florido, M. A. Gigosos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative phase retrieval algorithm for space-variant PSF in optical systems with aberrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04897v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Iterative phase retrieval algorithms are widely used in digital optics for their efficiency and simplicity. Conventionally, these algorithms do not consider aberrations as they assume an ideal, aberration-free optical system. Here, we propose modified iterative phase retrieval algorithms that take into account the space-invariant and space-variant point spread function of the optical system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04897v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Brault, Corinne Fournier, Tatiana Latychevskaia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying the Liouville-Lanczos Method of Time-Dependent Density-Functional Theory to Warm Dense Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04921v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ab initio modeling of dynamic structure factors (DSF) and related density response properties in the warm dense matter (WDM) regime is a challenging computational task. The DSF, convolved with a probing X-ray beam and instrument function, is measured in X-ray Thomson scattering (XRTS) experiments, which allows for the study of electronic structure properties at the microscopic level. Among the various ab initio methods, linear response time-dependent density functional theory (LR-TDDFT) is a key framework for simulating the DSF. The standard approach in LR-TDDFT for computing the DSF relies on the orbital representation. A significant drawback of this method is the unfavorable scaling of the number of required empty bands as the wavenumber increases, making LR-TDDFT impractical for modeling XRTS measurements over large energy scales, such as in backward scattering geometry. We consider and test an alternative approach that employs the Liouville-Lanczos (LL) method for simulating the DSF. This approach does not require empty states and allows the DSF at large momentum transfer values and over a broad frequency range to be accessed. We compare the results obtained from the LL method with those from the standard LR-TDDFT within the projector augmented-wave formalism for isochorically heated aluminum and warm dense hydrogen. Additionally, we utilize exact path integral Monte Carlo (PIMC) results for the imaginary-time density-density correlation function (ITCF) of warm dense hydrogen to rigorously benchmark the LL approach. We discuss the application of the LL method for calculating DSFs and ITCFs at different wavenumbers, the effects of pseudopotentials, and the role of Lorentzian smearing. The successful validation of the LL method under WDM conditions makes it a valuable addition to the ab initio simulation landscape, supporting experimental efforts and advancing WDM theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04921v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhandos A. Moldabekov, Sebastian Schwalbe, Thomas Gawne, Thomas R. Preston, Jan Vorberger, Tobias Dornheim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Hamiltonian Systems and Physics-Informed Neural Networks: Hamilton-Dirac Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15485v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The effectiveness of the Physics Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) for learning the dynamics of constrained Hamiltonian systems is demonstrated using the Dirac theory of constraints for regular systems with holonomic constraints and systems with non-standard Lagrangians. By utilizing Dirac brackets, we derive the Hamilton-Dirac equations and minimize their residuals, incorporating also energy conservation and the Dirac constraints, using appropriate regularization terms in the loss function. The resulting PINNs, referred to as Hamilton-Dirac Neural Networks (HDNNs), successfully learn constrained dynamics without deviating from the constraint manifold. Two examples with holonomic constraints are presented: the nonlinear pendulum in Cartesian coordinates and a two-dimensional, elliptically restricted harmonic oscillator. In both cases, HDNNs exhibit superior performance in preserving energy and constraints compared to traditional explicit solvers. To demonstrate applicability in systems with singular Lagrangians, we computed the guiding center motion in a strong magnetic field starting from the guiding center Lagrangian. The imposition of energy conservation during the neural network training proved essential for accurately determining the orbits of the guiding center. The HDNN architecture enables the learning of parametric dependencies in constrained dynamics by incorporating a problem-specific parameter as an input, in addition to the time variable. Additionally, an example of semi-supervised, data-driven learning of guiding center dynamics with parameter inference is presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15485v3</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.111.025301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 111, 025301 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios A. Kaltsas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broadening the Scope of Neural Network Potentials through Direct Inclusion of Additional Molecular Attributes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15073v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Most state-of-the-art neural network potentials do not account for molecular attributes other than atomic numbers and positions, which limits its range of applicability by design. In this work, we demonstrate the importance of including additional electronic attributes in neural network potential representations with a minimal architectural change to TensorNet, a state-of-the-art equivariant model based on Cartesian rank-2 tensor representations. By performing experiments on both custom-made and public benchmarking datasets, we show that this modification resolves the input degeneracy issues stemming from the use of atomic numbers and positions alone, while enhancing the model's predictive accuracy across diverse chemical systems with different charge or spin states. This is accomplished without tailored strategies or the inclusion of physics-based energy terms, while maintaining efficiency and accuracy. These findings should furthermore encourage researchers to train and use models incorporating these additional representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15073v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillem Simeon, Antonio Mirarchi, Raul P. Pelaez, Raimondas Galvelis, Gianni De Fabritiis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Window Muffin Tin Orbitals (EWMTO) and Energy Window Linear Muffin Tin orbitals (EWLMTO) within the Atomic Sphere Approximation (ASA)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15299v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work we propose two new, closely related, efficient basis sets for the electronic structure problem. The basis sets are based on the Muffin Tin Orbital (MTO) idea that the eigenstates of the Khon Sham (KS) Hamiltonian may we be expanded in terms of eigenstates of the spherically averaged KS Hamiltonian inside the so called Muffin Tin (MT) spheres and Bessel functions in the interstitial multiplied by appropriate spherical Harmonics. Here we use the fact that the solution to the finding the ground state electron density is most often found through an iterative process: where generically on the order of over twenty iterations are taken till the ground state electron density and energy converges to the lowest values allowed by the correlation and exchange functional. We use eigenstate information from the previous iteration loop to choose the energies of the basis set elements used to study the KS Hamiltonian. Furthermore within the Atomic Sphere Approximation (ASA) the energies of the Bessel functions do not matter, as they are cancelled out other than for boundary conditions, and are chosen at zero energy. This is an efficient method aimed at studying the electronic structure of materials with large unit cells especially if they are of close packed form where ASA is particularly accurate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15299v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Garry Goldstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parton Distribution Functions in the Schwinger Model with Tensor Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16996v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Parton distribution functions (PDFs) describe universal properties of bound states and allow us to calculate scattering amplitudes in processes with large momentum transfer. Calculating PDFs involves the evaluation of matrix elements with a Wilson line in a light-cone direction. In contrast to Monte Carlo methods in Euclidean spacetime, these matrix elements can be directly calculated in Minkowski-space using the Hamiltonian formalism. The necessary spatial- and time-evolution can be efficiently applied using established tensor network methods. We present PDFs in the Schwinger model calculated with matrix product states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16996v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.466.0024</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of The 41st International Symposium on Lattice Field Theory -- PoS(LATTICE2024), volume 466, 024 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mari Carmen Ba\~nuls, Krzysztof Cichy, C. -J. David Lin, Manuel Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CaNS-Fizzy: A GPU-accelerated finite difference solver for turbulent two-phase flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04189v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: CaNS-Fizzy -- Fizzy for short -- is a GPU-accelerated numerical solver for massively-parallel Direct Numerical Simulations (DNS) of incompressible two-phase flows. A DNS enables direct access to all flow quantities, resolved in time and space at all relevant continuum scales. The resulting numerical experiments provide complete data sets for the analysis of the detailed mechanisms underlying the flow, particularly the interaction between the chaotic and multi-scale dynamics of turbulence and the interface movement and deformation. The insights gained can guide the design and operation of various applications, such as boiling heat transfer, liquid-liquid extraction, gas-liquid reactors, absorption and stripping columns, distillation columns, liquid combustion appliances, in all of which the rate of heat and mass transfer between phases is proportional to the interfacial area. Fizzy's two-phase capabilities were implemented using the efficient, GPU-accelerated Navier-Stokes solver CaNS as base.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04189v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Lupo, P. Wellens, P. Costa</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
