<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 02:08:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Comparison of Surrogate Constitutive Models for Viscoplastic Creep Simulation of HT-9 Steel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mechanistic microstructure-informed constitutive models for the mechanical response of polycrystals are a cornerstone of computational materials science. However, as these models become increasingly more complex - often involving coupled differential equations describing the effect of specific deformation modes - their associated computational costs can become prohibitive, particularly in optimization or uncertainty quantification tasks that require numerous model evaluations. To address this challenge, surrogate constitutive models that balance accuracy and computational efficiency are highly desirable. Data-driven surrogate models, that learn the constitutive relation directly from data, have emerged as a promising solution. In this work, we develop two local surrogate models for the viscoplastic response of a steel: a piecewise response surface method and a mixture of experts model. These surrogates are designed to adapt to complex material behavior, which may vary with material parameters or operating conditions. The surrogate constitutive models are applied to creep simulations of HT-9 steel, an alloy of considerable interest to the nuclear energy sector due to its high tolerance to radiation damage, using training data generated from viscoplastic self-consistent (VPSC) simulations. We define a set of test metrics to numerically assess the accuracy of our surrogate models for predicting viscoplastic material behavior, and show that the mixture of experts model outperforms the piecewise response surface method in terms of accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22667v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pieterjan Robbe, Andre Ruybalid, Arun Hegde, Christophe Bonneville, Habib N Najm, Laurent Capolungo, Cosmin Safta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of Variance Reduction and Population Control in Monte Carlo Neutron Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Monte Carlo methods are widely used for neutron transport simulations at least partly because of the accuracy they bring to the modeling of these problems. However, the computational burden associated with the slow convergence rate of Monte Carlo poses a significant challenge to running large-scale simulations. The continued improvement in high-performance computing capabilities has put exascale time-dependent Monte Carlo neutron transport simulations within reach. Variance reduction techniques have become an essential component to the efficiency of steady-state simulations, and population control techniques are an integral part of time-dependent simulations, but combining them can create algorithmic conflicts. This study investigates the performance of steady-state variance reduction techniques when extended to time-dependent problems and examines how variance reduction and population control techniques combine to impact the effectiveness of time-dependent simulations. Simulations were conducted using various combinations of these techniques across multiple test problems to assess their performance. While this study does not examine all possible variance reduction and population control combinations, the findings emphasize the importance of carefully selecting algorithms to simulate large-scale time-dependent problems effectively. Notably, using weight windows with weight-based combing for population control can significantly hinder simulation performance, whereas pairing weight windows with uniform combing can provide the efficiencies necessary for successfully computing the results of massive problems. Further performance gains were observed when steady-state weight windows were replaced with time-dependent versions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22943v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Northrop, Ilham Variansyah, Todd Palmer, Camille Palmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-preserving random batch Ewald method for constant-potential simulation of electrochemical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24742v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Constant potential molecular dynamics simulation plays important role for applications of electrochemical systems, yet the calculation of charge fluctuation on electrodes remains a computational bottleneck. We propose a highly scalable, symmetry-preserving random batch Ewald (SRBE) algorithm to address this challenge. The SRBE algorithm deterministically computes the low-frequency components along the direction perpendicular to electrodes, while efficiently approximating the remaining components using random batch sampling. This approach simultaneously reduces charge and force fluctuations while satisfying the symmetry-preserving mean field condition in anisotropic systems with large aspect ratios. Numerical experiments on electrode/ionic liquid systems validate the high accuracy of the SRBE method in capturing dynamic charging processes and equilibrium electric double layer structures. The SRBE method achieves parallel efficiency improvements of up to two orders of magnitude compared with conventional FFT-based algorithms. These findings highlight its strong potential for enabling large-scale electrochemical simulations and its broad applicability to practical problems in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24742v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weihang Gao, Qi Zhou, Qianru Zhang, Zhenli Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FESTIM v2.0: Upgraded framework for multi-species hydrogen transport and enhanced performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24760v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: FESTIM is an open-source finite element framework for modelling the transport of hydrogen isotopes in materials. It provides a flexible and extensible tool for simulating diffusion, trapping, surface interactions, and other processes that govern hydrogen behaviour. This paper presents FESTIM v2.0, a major release that broadens both the physical scope and the software infrastructure of the framework. On the physics side, the formulation adopts a modular structure that supports multi-species transport, advanced trapping and reaction schemes, isotope exchange, decay, and advection. Interface and boundary conditions have been generalised, and interoperability with external solvers enables multiphysics workflows, including coupling with fluid dynamics and neutron transport codes. On the software side, FESTIM v2.0 has been migrated to DOLFINx, the next-generation FEniCS platform, providing improved performance, interoperability, and long-term sustainability. Taken together, these advances position FESTIM v2.0 as a versatile platform for investigating hydrogen transport in materials across scientific and engineering applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24760v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Dark, R\'emi Delaporte-Mathurin, J{\o}rgen S. Dokken, Huihua Yang, Chirag Khurana, Kaelyn Dunnell, Gabriele Ferrero, Vladimir Kulagin, Samuele Meschini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Numerical Simulation Model for Laser Material Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22666v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High power lasers are used for a variety of manufacturing processes on time and length scales that cover many orders of magnitude and on different materials. The variety of processes achievable through laser-material interaction results from numerous coupled, nonlinear physical phenomena. Simulation models can be used to gain process understanding, explain experimentally observed phenomena, and optimize or design processes. However, the inherent complexity and diversity of the phenomena make modeling a challenging task.
  Within this chapter, a universal model is presented that accurately simulates a broad spectrum of processes, including welding, additive manufacturing, cutting, ablation, drilling, and surface structuring, encompassing both continuous wave and ultrashort pulsed lasers and their interaction with various materials. Starting from the fundamental principles of conservation of mass, momentum, and energy, a continuum mechanical framework is introduced that captures the main multiphysical effects. A numerical solution using the Finite Volume Method is presented and validated against benchmark problems where detailed experimental data are available. Macroscopic examples with continuous wave lasers include keyhole drilling and collapse under stationary illumination as well as melt pool dynamics and pore formation in copper welding. At the microscopic level, copper ablation with femtosecond pulses is simulated.
  Finally, a set of real-world applications is shown, where the model helps to explain and optimize industrial phenomena and defects. Examples include deep penetration welding of steel with dynamic beam shaping, multilayer additive manufacturing via powder bed fusion, and ultrashort pulsed drilling of micro vias in dielectric materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22666v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Otto, Michele Buttazzoni, Carlos Dur\'an, Tobias Florian, Constantin Zenz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-hyperuniform Critical States of Active Topological Defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22911v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological defects are fundamental to the collective dynamics of non-equilibrium systems and in active matter, mediating spontaneous flows, dynamic self-organization, and emergent pattern formation. Here, we reveal critical states in active nematics, marked by slowed defect density relaxation, amplified fluctuations, and heightened sensitivity to activity. Near criticality, defect interactions become long-ranged, scaling with system size, and the system enters an anti-hyperuniform regime with giant number fluctuations of topological defects and defect clustering. This transition reflects a dual scaling behavior: fluctuations are uniform at small scales but become anti-hyperuniform at larger scales, \tm{as supported by experimental measurements on large-field-of-view endothelial monolayers. We find that these anti-hyperuniform states with multiscale defect density fluctuations are robust to varying parameters, introducing frictional damping, and changing boundary conditions.} Finally, we show that the observed anti-hyperuniformity originates from defect clustering, distinguishing this transition from defect-unbinding or phase separation processes. Beyond fundamental implications for non-equilibrium systems, these results may inform biological contexts where topological defects are integral to processes such as morphogenesis and collective cellular self-organization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22911v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6633/ae075e</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Simon Guldager Andersen, Tianxiang Ma, Makito F. Katsume, Kexin Li, Xiao Liu, Martin Cramer Pedersen, Amin Doostmohammadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IsingFormer: Augmenting Parallel Tempering With Learned Proposals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23043v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) underlies both statistical physics and combinatorial optimization, but mixes slowly near critical points and in rough landscapes. Parallel Tempering (PT) improves mixing by swapping replicas across temperatures, yet each replica still relies on slow local updates to change its configuration. We introduce IsingFormer, a Transformer trained on equilibrium samples that can generate entire spin configurations resembling those from the target distribution. These uncorrelated samples are used as proposals for global moves within a Metropolis step in PT, complementing the usual single-spin flips. On 2D Ising models (sampling), IsingFormer reproduces magnetization and free-energy curves and generalizes to unseen temperatures, including the critical region. Injecting even a single proposal sharply reduces equilibration time, replacing thousands of local updates. On 3D spin glasses (optimization), PT enhanced with IsingFormer finds substantially lower-energy states, demonstrating how global moves accelerate search in rugged landscapes. Finally, applied to integer factorization encoded as Ising problems, IsingFormer trained on a limited set of semiprimes transfers successfully to unseen semiprimes, boosting success rates beyond the training distribution. Since factorization is a canonical hard benchmark, this ability to generalize across instances highlights the potential of learning proposals that move beyond single problems to entire families of instances. The IsingFormer demonstrates that Monte Carlo methods can be systematically accelerated by neural proposals that capture global structure, yielding faster sampling and stronger performance in combinatorial optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23043v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saleh Bunaiyan, Corentin Delacour, Shuvro Chowdhury, Kyle Lee, Kerem Y. Camsari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A FFT-based GMRES for fast solving of Poisson equation in concatenated geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23180v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fast Fourier Transform (FFT)-based solvers for the Poisson equation are highly efficient, exhibiting $O(N\log N)$ computational complexity and excellent parallelism. However, their application is typically restricted to simple, regular geometries due to the separability requirement of the underlying discrete operators. This paper introduces a novel domain decomposition method that extends the applicability of FFT-based solvers to complex composite domains geometries constructed from multiple sub-regions. The method transforms the global problem into a system of sub-problems coupled through Schur complements at the interfaces. A key challenge is that the Schur complement disrupts the matrix structure required for direct FFT-based inversion. To overcome this, we develop a FFT-based preconditioner to accelerate the Generalized Minimal Residual (GMRES) method for the interface system. The central innovation is a novel preconditioner based on the inverse of the block operator without the Schur complement, which can be applied efficiently using the FFT-based solver. The resulting preconditioned iteration retains an optimal complexity for each step. Numerical experiments on a cross-shaped domain demonstrate that the proposed solver achieves the expected second-order accuracy of the underlying finite difference scheme. Furthermore, it exhibits significantly improved computational performance compared to a classic sparse GMRES solver based on Eigen libeary. For a problem with $10^5$ grid points, our method achieves a speedup of over 40 times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23180v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zichao Jiang, Jiacheng Lian, Zhuolin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PHASE: Physics-Integrated, Heterogeneity-Aware Surrogates for Scientific Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large-scale numerical simulations underpin modern scientific discovery but remain constrained by prohibitive computational costs. AI surrogates offer acceleration, yet adoption in mission-critical settings is limited by concerns over physical plausibility, trustworthiness, and the fusion of heterogeneous data. We introduce PHASE, a modular deep-learning framework for physics-integrated, heterogeneity-aware surrogates in scientific simulations. PHASE combines data-type-aware encoders for heterogeneous inputs with multi-level physics-based constraints that promote consistency from local dynamics to global system behavior. We validate PHASE on the biogeochemical (BGC) spin-up workflow of the U.S. Department of Energy's Energy Exascale Earth System Model (E3SM) Land Model (ELM), presenting-to our knowledge-the first scientifically validated AI-accelerated solution for this task. Using only the first 20 simulation years, PHASE infers a near-equilibrium state that otherwise requires more than 1,200 years of integration, yielding an effective reduction in required integration length by at least 60x. The framework is enabled by a pipeline for fusing heterogeneous scientific data and demonstrates strong generalization to higher spatial resolutions with minimal fine-tuning. These results indicate that PHASE captures governing physical regularities rather than surface correlations, enabling practical, physically consistent acceleration of land-surface modeling and other complex scientific workflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23453v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dawei Gao, Dali Wang, Zhuowei Gu, Qinglei Cao, Xiao Wang, Peter Thornton, Dan Ricciuto, Yunhe Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Canonical Transformation for the Spectra of Fluxional Molecule CH5+</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23731v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Protonated methane, CH5+, is a highly fluxional molecule with large spatial motions of the hydrogen atoms. The molecule's anharmonic effects and the scrambling of the hydrogen atoms significantly affect the excitation spectrum of the molecule. The neural canonical transformation (NCT) approach, which we previously developed to solve the vibrational spectra of molecules and solids, is a powerful method that effectively treats nuclear quantum effects and anharmonicities. Using NCT with wavefunctions in atomic coordinates rather than normal coordinates, we successfully calculate the ground and excited states of CH5+. We found that the wavefunctions for the ground state, as well as for low- and high-energy excited states, show preferences for the three stationary points on the potential energy surface. Furthermore, the dynamics of all these states are characterized by continuous hydrogen swapping. This work extends the applicability of the NCT approach for calculating excited states to fluxional molecules without fixed geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23731v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruisi Wang, Qi Zhang, Lei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Network Markov Chain Monte Carlo: Efficient Sampling of Three-Dimensional Spin Glasses and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sampling the three-dimensional (3D) spin glass -- i.e., generating equilibrium configurations of a 3D lattice with quenched random couplings -- is widely regarded as one of the central and long-standing open problems in statistical physics. The rugged energy landscape, pronounced critical slowing down, and intrinsic ergodicity breaking render standard Monte Carlo methods severely inefficient, particularly for large systems at low temperatures. In this work, we introduce the Tensor Network Markov Chain Monte Carlo (TNMCMC) approach to address the issue. It generates large-scale collective updates in MCMC using tensor networks on the 2D slices of the 3D lattice, greatly improving the autocorrelation time and offering orders-of-magnitude speed-ups over conventional MCMC in generating unbiased samples of the Boltzmann distribution. We conduct numerical experiments on 3D spin glasses up to system size $64\times 64\times 64$ using a single CPU, and show that TNMCMC dramatically suppresses critical slowing down in large disordered systems, which usually require a supercomputer to perform MCMC simulations. Furthermore, we apply our approach to the 3-state Potts model up to system size $64\times 64\times 64$ using a single CPU, and show that the TNMCMC approach efficiently traverses the exponential barriers of the strong first-order transition, whereas conventional MCMC fails. Our results reveal that TNMCMC opens a promising path toward tackling long-standing, formidable three-dimensional problems in statistical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23945v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Chen, Jing Liu, Youjin Deng, Pan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GeoFunFlow: Geometric Function Flow Matching for Inverse Operator Learning over Complex Geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inverse problems governed by partial differential equations (PDEs) are crucial in science and engineering. They are particularly challenging due to ill-posedness, data sparsity, and the added complexity of irregular geometries. Classical PDE-constrained optimization methods are computationally expensive, especially when repeated posterior sampling is required. Learning-based approaches improve efficiency and scalability, yet most are designed for regular domains or focus on forward modeling. Here, we introduce {\em GeoFunFlow}, a geometric diffusion model framework for inverse problems on complex geometries. GeoFunFlow combines a novel geometric function autoencoder (GeoFAE) and a latent diffusion model trained via rectified flow. GeoFAE employs a Perceiver module to process unstructured meshes of varying sizes and produces continuous reconstructions of physical fields, while the diffusion model enables posterior sampling from sparse and noisy data. Across five benchmarks, GeoFunFlow achieves state-of-the-art reconstruction accuracy over complex geometries, provides calibrated uncertainty quantification, and delivers efficient inference compared to operator-learning and diffusion model baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24117v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sifan Wang, Zhikai Wu, David van Dijk, Lu Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Review of Light-Field Imaging in Biomedical Sciences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Light-field imaging is an emerging paradigm in biomedical optics, offering the unique ability to capture volumetric information in a single snapshot by encoding both the spatial and angular components of light. Unlike conventional three-dimensional (3D) imaging modalities that rely on mechanical or optical scanning, light-field imaging enables high-speed volumetric acquisition, making it particularly well-suited for capturing rapid biological dynamics. This review outlines the theoretical foundations of light-field imaging and surveys its core implementations across microscopy, mesoscopy, and endoscopy. Special attention is given to the fundamental trade-offs between imaging speed, spatial resolution, and depth of field, as well as recent advances that address these limitations through compressive sensing, deep learning, and meta-optics. By positioning light-field imaging within the broader landscape of biomedical imaging technologies, we highlight its unique strengths, existing challenges, and future potential as a scalable and versatile tool for biological discovery and clinical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24191v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruixuan Zhao, Xuanwen Hua, Woongjae Baek, Zhaoqiang Wang, Shu Jia, Liang Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph-Based Learning of Free Surface Dynamics in Generalized Newtonian Fluids using Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24264v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we propose a graph neural network (GNN) model for efficiently predicting the flow behavior of non-Newtonian fluids with free surface dynamics. The numerical analysis of non-Newtonian fluids presents significant challenges, as traditional algorithms designed for Newtonian fluids with constant viscosity often struggle to converge when applied to non-Newtonian cases, where rheological properties vary dynamically with flow conditions. Among these, power-law fluids exhibit viscosity that decreases exponentially as the shear rate increases, making numerical simulations particularly difficult. The complexity further escalates in free surface flow scenarios, where computational challenges intensify. In such cases, particle-based methods like smoothed particle hydrodynamics (SPH) provide advantages over traditional grid-based techniques, such as the finite element method (FEM). Building on this approach, we introduce a novel GNN-based numerical model to enhance the computational efficiency of non-Newtonian power-law fluid flow simulations. Our model is trained on SPH simulation data, learning the effects of particle accelerations in the presence of SPH interactions based on the fluid's power-law parameters. The GNN significantly accelerates computations while maintaining reliable accuracy in benchmark tests, including dam-break and droplet impact simulations. The results underscore the potential of GNN-based simulation frameworks for efficiently modeling non-Newtonian fluid behavior, paving the way for future advancements in data-driven fluid simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24264v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyo-Jin Kim, Jaekwang Kim, Hyung-Jun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct numerical simulation of two-phase flows with surfactant-induced surface viscous effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24722v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Direct numerical simulations of interfacial flows with surfactant-induced complexities involving surface viscous stresses are performed within the framework of the Level Contour Reconstruction Method (LCRM); this hybrid front-tracking/level-set approach leverages the advantages of both methods. In addition to interface-confined surfactant transport that results in surface diffusion and Marangoni stresses, the interface, endowed with shear and dilatational viscosities; these act to resist deformation arising from velocity gradients in the plane of the two-dimensional manifold of the interface, and interfacial compressibility effects, respectively. By adopting the Boussinesq-Scriven constitutive model, We provide a mathematical formulation of these effects that accurately captures the interfacial mechanics, which is then implemented within the LCRM-based code by exploiting the benefits inherent to the underlying front-tracking/level-sets hybrid approach. We validate our numerical predictions against a number of benchmark cases that involve drops undergoing deformation when subjected to a flow field or when rising under the action of buoyancy. The results of these validation studies highlight the importance of adopting a rigorous approach in modelling the interfacial dynamics. We also present results that demonstrate the effects of surface viscous stresses on interfacial deformation in unsteady parametric surface waves and atomisation events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24722v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debashis Panda, Seungwon Shin, Abdullah M. Abdal, Lyes Kahouadji, Jalel Chergui, Damir Juric, Omar K. Matar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SymBoltz.jl: a symbolic-numeric, approximation-free and differentiable linear Einstein-Boltzmann solver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24740v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: SymBoltz is a new Julia package that solves the linear Einstein-Boltzmann equations. It features a symbolic-numeric interface for specifying equations, is free of approximation switching schemes and is compatible with automatic differentiation. Cosmological models are built from replaceable physical components in a way that scales well in model space. The modeler should simply write down their equations, and SymBoltz solves them and eliminates much of the friction in the process. SymBoltz enables up to 100x shorter model definitions compared to browsing equivalent files in CLASS. Symbolic knowledge enables powerful automation of tasks, such as separating computational stages like the background and perturbations, generating the Jacobian matrix and its sparsity pattern, and interpolating arbitrary expressions from the solution. Modern implicit solvers integrate the full stiff equations at all times, reducing slowdowns by taking long time steps, reusing the Jacobian and LU-factorizing it over several time steps, and using fast linear system solvers. Automatic differentiation gives exact derivatives of any output with respect to any input, which is important for gradient-based Markov chain Monte Carlo methods in large parameter spaces, training of emulators, Fisher forecasting and sensitivity analysis. These features are useful in their own rights, but also reinforce each other in a synergy. Results agree with established codes like CLASS and CAMB. With more work, SymBoltz can grow into an integrated symbolic-numeric cosmological modeling environment with a large library of models that delivers differentiable output as fast as other codes. SymBoltz is available at https://github.com/hersle/SymBoltz.jl with single-command installation and extensive documentation, and welcomes questions, suggestions and contributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24740v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Herman Sletmoen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DRIFT-Net: A Spectral--Coupled Neural Operator for PDEs Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24868v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning PDE dynamics with neural solvers can significantly improve wall-clock efficiency and accuracy compared with classical numerical solvers. In recent years, foundation models for PDEs have largely adopted multi-scale windowed self-attention, with the scOT backbone in \textsc{Poseidon} serving as a representative example.
  However, because of their locality, truly globally consistent spectral coupling can only be propagated gradually through deep stacking and window shifting. This weakens global coupling and leads to error accumulation and drift during closed-loop rollouts. To address this, we propose \textbf{DRIFT-Net}. It employs a dual-branch design comprising a spectral branch and an image branch. The spectral branch is responsible for capturing global, large-scale low-frequency information, whereas the image branch focuses on local details and nonstationary structures. Specifically, we first perform controlled, lightweight mixing within the low-frequency range. Then we fuse the spectral and image paths at each layer via bandwise weighting, which avoids the width inflation and training instability caused by naive concatenation. The fused result is transformed back into the spatial domain and added to the image branch, thereby preserving both global structure and high-frequency details across scales. Compared with strong attention-based baselines, DRIFT-Net achieves lower error and higher throughput with fewer parameters under identical training settings and budget. On Navier--Stokes benchmarks, the relative $L_{1}$ error is reduced by 7\%--54\%, the parameter count decreases by about 15\%, and the throughput remains higher than scOT. Ablation studies and theoretical analyses further demonstrate the stability and effectiveness of this design. The code is available at https://github.com/cruiseresearchgroup/DRIFT-Net.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24868v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayi Li, Flora D. Salim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing three dimensional modeling of adsorption physics in porous media for gas separation towards a new design of fixed bed adsorbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25062v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new three-dimensional (3D) multiphase computational fluid dynamics (CFD) model for adsorption physics in porous media is developed and validated. The model is constituted at a macroscopic scale that integrates new volumetric source terms in the multi-species gas transport and energy conservation equations. These new terms, for the first time, take into account the impact of pores adsorption occupation rate (PAOR), or gas loading. Transient 3D simulations are performed at an atmospheric pressure of about 1.02 bar for different CO2-He gas mixture feed-in compositions (100%, 50%, and 15% CO2). The 3D model validation is conducted through quantitative comparisons with experimental data from the literature for CO2 adsorption on porous Zeolite-13X beads in a cylindrical fixed-bed. Results demonstrate the new model's ability to accurately predict the breakthrough curves and the thermal front propagation inside the bed. Finally, the new CFD model is applied to investigate CO2 capture in a new 3D design of fixed-bed adsorbers of equivalent adsorbent material volume. The new design outperformed the reference cylindrical design thanks to its new geometry with higher surface area. This allows to shorten the adsorption periods in pressure and temperature swing adsorption processes and thus increase the overall gas separation process productivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25062v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamad Najib Nadamani, Mostafa Safdari Shadloo, Talib Dbouk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>gCAMB: A GPU-accelerated Boltzmann solver for next-generation cosmological surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inferring cosmological parameters from Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) data requires repeated and computationally expensive calculations of theoretical angular power spectra using Boltzmann solvers like CAMB. This creates a significant bottleneck, particularly for non-standard cosmological models and the high-accuracy demands of future surveys. While emulators based on deep neural networks can accelerate this process by several orders of magnitude, they first require large, pre-computed training datasets, which are costly to generate and model-specific. To address this challenge, we introduce gCAMB, a version of the CAMB code ported to GPUs, which preserves all the features of the original CPU-only code. By offloading the most computationally intensive modules to the GPU, gCAMB significantly accelerates the generation of power spectra, saving massive computational time, halving the power consumption in high-accuracy settings and, among other purposes, facilitating the creation of extensive training sets needed for robust cosmological analyses. We make the gCAMB software available to the community at https://github.com/lstorchi/CAMB/tree/gpuport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25110v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Storchi, P. Campeti, M. Lattanzi, N. Antonini, E. Calore, P. Lubrano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discretization form of the continuity condition at the polar axis, with application to the gyrokinetic simulation in a magnetic fusion torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03657v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new computational method to solve the hyperbolic (Vlasov) equation and the elliptic (Poisson-like) equation at the polar axis is proposed. It is shown that the value of a scalar function at the polar axis can be predicted by its neighbouring values based on the continuity condition. This continuity condition systematically solves the pole problems including the singular factor 1/r in the hyperbolic equation and the inner boundary in the elliptic equation. The proposed method is applied to the global gyrokinetic simulation of the tokamak plasma with the magnetic axis included.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03657v4</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiannan Wu, Zihao Wang, Shaojie Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Systems of Linear Equations: HHL from a Tensor Networks Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05290v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work presents a new approach for simulating the HHL linear systems of equations solver algorithm with tensor networks. First, a novel HHL in the qudits formalism, the generalization of qubits, is developed, and then its operations are transformed into an equivalent classical HHL, taking advantage of the non-unitary operations that they can apply. The main novelty of this proposal is to perform a classical simulation of the HHL as efficiently as possible to benchmark the algorithm steps according to its input parameters and the input matrix. The algorithm is applied to three classical simple simulation problems, comparing it with an exact inversion algorithm, and its performance is compared against an implementation of the original HHL simulated in the Qiskit framework, providing both codes. It is also applied to study the sensitivity of the HHL algorithm with respect to its hyperparameter values, reporting the existence of saturation points and maximal performance values. The results show that this approach can achieve a promising performance in computational efficiency to simulate the HHL process without quantum noise, providing a higher bound for its performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05290v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Mata Ali, I\~nigo Perez Delgado, Marina Ristol Roura, Aitor Moreno Fdez. de Leceta, Sebasti\'an V. Romero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron volt energy resolution with ptychography using a broadband continuum spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00703v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ptychography is a scanning coherent diffraction imaging technique successfully applied in the electron, visible and x-ray regimes. One of the distinct features of ptychography with respect to other coherent diffraction techniques is its capability of dealing with partial spatial and temporal coherence via the reconstruction algorithm. Here we focus on the temporal and clarify theoretically and with simulations the constraints which affect the energy resolution limits of the ptychographic algorithms. Based on this, we design and perform simulations for a broadband ptychography in the hard x-ray regime, which enables an energy resolution down to 1 eV. We benchmark the simulations against experimental ptychographic data from a nickel test sample, by extracting the x-ray absorption near edge spectrum with energy resolution of 5 eV using a continuum spectrum of 20 eV bandwidth. We review the results, discuss the limitations, and provide guidelines for future broadband ptychography experiments, its prospective applications and potential impact on achieving diffraction limited resolutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00703v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Cipiccia, Wiebe Stolp, Luca Fardin, Ralf Ziesche, Ingo Manke, Matthieu Boone, Chris Armstrong, Alessandro Olivo, Darren Batey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant Measures in Time-Delay Coordinates for Unique Dynamical System Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00589v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While invariant measures are widely employed to analyze physical systems when a direct study of pointwise trajectories is intractable, e.g., due to chaos or noise, they cannot uniquely identify the underlying dynamics. Our first result shows that, in contrast to invariant measures in state coordinates, e.g., $[x(t), y(t), z(t)]$, the invariant measure expressed in time-delay coordinates, e.g., $[x(t), x(t-\tau),\ldots, x(t-(m-1)\tau)]$, can identify the dynamics up to a topological conjugacy. Our second result resolves the remaining ambiguity: by combining invariant measures constructed from multiple delay frames with distinct observables, the system is uniquely identifiable, provided that a suitable initial condition is satisfied. These guarantees require informative observables and appropriate delay parameters ($m,\tau$), which can be limiting in certain settings. We support our theoretical contributions through a series of physical examples demonstrating how invariant measures expressed in delay-coordinates can be used to perform robust system identification in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00589v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ppys-lx68</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jonah Botvinick-Greenhouse, Robert Martin, Yunan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensionless learning based on information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03927v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dimensional analysis is one of the most fundamental tools for understanding physical systems. However, the construction of dimensionless variables, as guided by the Buckingham-$\pi$ theorem, is not uniquely determined. Here, we introduce IT-$\pi$, a model-free method that combines dimensionless learning with the principles of information theory. Grounded in the irreducible error theorem, IT-$\pi$ identifies dimensionless variables with the highest predictive power by measuring their shared information content. The approach is able to rank variables by predictability, identify distinct physical regimes, uncover self-similar variables, determine the characteristic scales of the problem, and extract its dimensionless parameters. IT-$\pi$ also provides a bound of the minimum predictive error achievable across all possible models, from simple linear regression to advanced deep learning techniques, naturally enabling a definition of model efficiency. We benchmark IT-$\pi$ across different cases and demonstrate that it offers superior performance and capabilities compared to existing tools. The method is also applied to conduct dimensionless learning for supersonic turbulence, aerodynamic drag on both smooth and irregular surfaces, magnetohydrodynamic power generation, and laser-metal interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03927v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Yuan, Adri\'an Lozano-Dur\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An adaptive, data-driven multiscale approach for dense granular flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13458v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The accuracy of coarse-grained continuum models of dense granular flows is limited by the lack of high-fidelity closure models for granular rheology. One approach to addressing this issue, referred to as the hierarchical multiscale method, is to use a high-fidelity fine-grained model to compute the closure terms needed by the coarse-grained model. The difficulty with this approach is that the overall model can become computationally intractable due to the high computational cost of the high-fidelity model. In this work, we describe a multiscale modeling approach for dense granular flows that utilizes neural networks trained using high-fidelity discrete element method (DEM) simulations to approximate the constitutive granular rheology for a continuum incompressible flow model. Our approach leverages an ensemble of neural networks to estimate predictive uncertainty that allows us to determine whether the rheology at a given point is accurately represented by the neural network model. Additional DEM simulations are only performed when needed, minimizing the number of additional DEM simulations required when updating the rheology. This adaptive coupling significantly reduces the overall computational cost of the approach while controlling the error. In addition, the neural networks are customized to learn regularized rheological behavior to ensure well-posedness of the continuum solution. We first validate the approach using two-dimensional steady-state and decelerating inclined flows. We then demonstrate the efficiency of our approach by modeling three-dimensional sub-aerial granular column collapse for varying initial column aspect ratios, where our multiscale method compares well with the computationally expensive computational fluid dynamics (CFD)-DEM simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13458v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cma.2025.118294</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>B. Siddani, Weiqun Zhang, Andrew Nonaka, John Bell, Ishan Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A coupled HDG discretization for the interaction between acoustic and elastic waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15106v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose and analyze an HDG scheme for the Laplace-domain interaction between a transient acoustic wave and a bounded elastic solid embedded in an unbounded fluid medium. Two mixed variables (the stress tensor and the velocity of the acoustic wave) are included while the symmetry of the stress tensor is imposed weakly by considering the antisymmetric part of the strain tensor (the spin or vorticity tensor) as an additional unknown. Convergence of the method is demonstrated and theoretical rates are obtained; numerical results suggesting optimal order of convergence and superconvergence of the traces are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15106v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Artaza-Covarrubias, Tonatiuh S\'anchez-Vizuet, Manuel Solano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Resonant Spectroscopy Simulations Using Multi-Shifted Bi-Conjugate Gradient</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09551v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Resonant spectroscopies, which involve intermediate states with finite lifetimes, provide essential insights into collective excitations in quantum materials that are otherwise inaccessible. However, theoretical understanding in this area is often limited by the numerical challenges of solving Kramers-Heisenberg-type response functions for large-scale systems. To address this, we introduce a multi-shifted biconjugate gradient algorithm that exploits the shared structure of Krylov subspaces across spectra with varying incident energies, effectively reducing the computational complexity to that of linear spectroscopies. Both mathematical proofs and numerical benchmarks confirm that this algorithm substantially accelerates spectral simulations, achieving constant complexity independent of the number of incident energies, while ensuring accuracy and stability. This development provides a scalable, versatile framework for simulating advanced spectroscopies in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09551v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gfdn-pyr2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 115113 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Prakash Sharma, Luogen Xu, Fei Xue, Yao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into Ionic Diffusion in C-S-H Gel Pore from Molecular Dynamics Simulations: Spatial Distributions, Energy Barriers, and Structural Descriptor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23089v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding transport behavior in nanoconfined environments is critical to many natural and engineering systems, including cementitious materials, yet its molecular-level mechanisms remain poorly understood. Here, molecular dynamics (MD) simulations were used to investigate Na, Cl, and water diffusion inside a 4 nm calcium-silicate-hydrate (C-S-H) pore channel over temperatures ranging from 300 K to 360 K. Spatially resolved analysis revealed strong suppression of diffusivity near the solid-liquid interface and gradual recovery toward the pore center. Arrhenius analysis further quantified the spatial variation of activation energy barriers and intrinsic mobilities across the pore channel, showing distinct confinement effects. The spatially resolved structural analysis uncovers a mechanistic transition from structure-controlled to hydrodynamics-controlled transport regimes with increasing distance from the pore surface. A structural descriptor, total coordination strength (TCS), was introduced, providing a predictive link between local liquid structure and molecular mobility within approximately 1 nm of the interface. Beyond approximately 1 nm, suppressed diffusivities were well captured by an empirical model inspired by the Darcy-Brinkman framework. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first MD study to comprehensively resolve the spatial heterogeneity of transport, thermal kinetics, and structure within cementitious nanopores. These findings deepen the fundamental understanding of nanoscale transport phenomena and suggest that tailoring the nanochannel structure and interfacial chemistry of cementitious gels, for example surface coordination environments, pore size distributions, and adsorption sites, may offer a promising strategy to suppress ionic ingress and enhance the durability of cement-based materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23089v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiqiang Chen, Kai Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EAC-Net: Predicting real-space charge density via equivariant atomic contributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04052v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Charge density is central to density functional theory (DFT), as it fully defines the ground-state properties of a material system. Obtaining it with high accuracy is a computational bottleneck. Existing machine learning models are constrained by trade-offs among accuracy, efficiency, and generalization. Here, we introduce the Equivariant Atomic Contribution Network (EAC-Net), which couples atoms and grids to integrate the strengths of grid-based and basis-function frameworks. EAC-Net achieves high accuracy (typically below 1% error), enhanced efficiency, and strong generalization across complex systems. Building on this framework, we develop EAC-mp, a universal charge density model covering the periodic table. The model demonstrates robust zero-shot performance across diverse systems, and generalizes beyond the training distribution, supporting downstream applications such as band structure calculations. By linking local chemical environments to charge densities, EAC-Net provides a scalable framework for accelerating electronic structure prediction and enabling high-throughput materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04052v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuejian Qin, Taoyuze Lv, Zhicheng Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insertion space in repulsive active matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08131v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For equilibrium hard spheres the stochastic geometry of the insertion space, the room to accommodate another sphere, relates exactly to the equation of state. We begin to extend this idea to active matter, analyzing insertion space for repulsive active particles in one and two dimensions using both on- and off-lattice models. In 1D we derive closed-form expressions for the mean insertion cavity size, cavity number, and total insertion volume, all in excellent agreement with simulations. Strikingly, activity increases the total insertion volume and tends to keep the insertion space more connected. These results provide the first quantitative foundation for the stochastic geometry of active matter, and opens up a new route to building a thermodynamics of active systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08131v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke K. Davis, Karel Proesmans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimer-driven multiple reentrant localization with composite potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21338v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent studies have revealed reentrant localization transitions in quasi-periodic one-dimensional lattices, where the competition between dimerized hopping and staggered disorder plays a central role. Yet the extent to which such reentrant localization persists under more general conditions, such as additional periodic potentials, modified quasi-periodic modulations remains unclear. Here we investigate localization phenomena in a one-dimensional lattice subject to a periodic potential and an additional quasi-periodic modulation. Using both eigenstate-based indicators and experimentally accessible dynamical observables, we identify robust reentrant, or multiple, localization transitions. We show that these transitions are uniquely stabilized by the dimer structure of the unit cell, where the competition between the onsite periodic potential and the quasi-periodic modulation becomes most pronounced. By systematically varying the periodicity parameter $\alpha$ and the quasi-periodic frequency $\beta$, we find that the robust multiple reentrant localization behavior disappears for any deviation from the dimer configuration, confirming its essential role. Our results suggest that the interplay between these competing factors drives the multiple reentrant localization transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21338v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Jie Chang, Dong Ruan, Gui-Lu Long</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
