<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 04:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Investigation of Preferential Flow Paths in Enzymatically Induced Calcite Precipitation supported by Bayesian Model Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The usability of enzymatically induced calcium carbonate precipitation (EICP) as a method for altering porous-media properties, soil stabilization, or biocementation depends on our ability to predict the spatial distribution of the precipitated calcium carbonate in porous media. While current REV-scale models are able to reproduce the main features of laboratory experiments, they neglect effects like the formation of preferential flow paths and the appearance of multiple polymorphs of calcium carbonate with differing properties. We show that extending an existing EICP model by the conceptual assumption of a mobile precipitate, amorphous calcium carbonate (ACC), allows for the formation of preferential flow paths when the initial porosity is heterogeneous. We apply sensitivity analysis and Bayesian inference to gain an understanding of the influence of characteristic parameters of ACC that are uncertain or unknown and compare two variations of the model based on different formulations of the ACC detachment term to analyse the plausibility of our hypothesis. An arbitrary Polynomial Chaos (aPC) surrogate model is trained based on the full model and used to reduce the computational cost of this study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17314v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rebecca Kohlhaas, Johannes Hommel, Felix Weinhardt, Holger Class, Sergey Oladyshkin, Bernd Flemisch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-property directed generative design of inorganic materials through Wyckoff-augmented transfer learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16784v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accelerated materials discovery is an urgent demand to drive advancements in fields such as energy conversion, storage, and catalysis. Property-directed generative design has emerged as a transformative approach for rapidly discovering new functional inorganic materials with multiple desired properties within vast and complex search spaces. However, this approach faces two primary challenges: data scarcity for functional properties and the multi-objective optimization required to balance competing tasks. Here, we present a multi-property-directed generative framework designed to overcome these limitations and enhance site symmetry-compliant crystal generation beyond P1 (translational) symmetry. By incorporating Wyckoff-position-based data augmentation and transfer learning, our framework effectively handles sparse and small functional datasets, enabling the generation of new stable materials simultaneously conditioned on targeted space group, band gap, and formation energy. Using this approach, we identified previously unknown thermodynamically and lattice-dynamically stable semiconductors in tetragonal, trigonal, and cubic systems, with bandgaps ranging from 0.13 to 2.20 eV, as validated by density functional theory (DFT) calculations. Additionally, we assessed their thermoelectric descriptors using DFT, indicating their potential suitability for thermoelectric applications. We believe our integrated framework represents a significant step forward in generative design of inorganic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16784v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuya Yamazaki, Wei Nong, Ruiming Zhu, Kostya S. Novoselov, Andrey Ustyuzhanin, Kedar Hippalgaonkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discontinuous Galerkin Representation of the Maxwell-J\"uttner Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16827v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kinetic simulations of relativistic gases and plasmas are critical for understanding diverse astrophysical and terrestrial systems, but the accurate construction of the relativistic Maxwellian, the Maxwell-J\"uttner (MJ) distribution, on a discrete simulation grid is challenging. Difficulties arise from the finite velocity bounds of the domain, which may not capture the entire distribution function, as well as errors introduced by projecting the function onto a discrete grid. Here we present a novel scheme for iteratively correcting the moments of the projected distribution applicable to all grid-based discretizations of the relativistic kinetic equation. In addition, we describe how to compute the needed nonlinear quantities, such as Lorentz boost factors, in a discontinuous Galerkin (DG) scheme through a combination of numerical quadrature and weak operations. The resulting method accurately captures the distribution function and ensures that the moments match the desired values to machine precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16827v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grant Johnson, Ammar Hakim, James Juno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling Material Injection Into Porous Structures With the Theory of Porous Media Under Non-isothermal Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16968v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, the Theory of Porous Media (TPM) is employed to model percutaneous vertebroplasty, a medical procedure in which acrylic cement is injected into cancellous vertebral bone. Previously, isothermal macroscale models have been derived to describe this material injection and the mechanical interactions which arise. However, the temperature of the injected cement is typically below the human body temperature, necessitating the extension of these models to the non-isothermal case. Following the modelling principles of the TPM and considering local thermal non-equilibrium conditions, our model introduces three energy balances as well as additional constitutive relations. If restricted to local thermal equilibrium conditions, our model equations are in agreement with other examples of TPM-based models. We observe that our model elicits physically reasonable behaviour in numerical simulations which employ parameter values and initial and boundary conditions relevant for our application. Noting that we neglect capillary effects, we claim our model to be thermodynamically consistent despite the employment of simplifying assumptions during its derivation, such as the Coleman and Noll procedure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16968v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan-S\"oren L. V\"olter (University of Stuttgart), Zubin Trivedi (University of Stuttgart), Tim Ricken (University of Stuttgart), Oliver R\"ohrle (University of Stuttgart)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Non-Ideal Single Vortex Flows Using the Differentiable Vortex Particle Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17012v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study extends the differentiable vortex particle method (DVPM) beyond idealized flow scenarios to encompass more realistic, non-ideal conditions, including viscous flow and flow subjected to non-conservative body forces. We establish the Lamb-Oseen vortex as a benchmark case, representing a fundamental viscous single vortex flow in fluid mechanics. This selection offers significant analytical advantages, as the Lamb-Oseen vortex possesses an exact analytical solution derived from the Navier-Stokes (NS) equations, thereby providing definitive ground truth data for training and validation purposes. Through rigorous evaluation across a spectrum of Reynolds numbers, we demonstrate that DVPM achieves superior accuracy in modeling the Lamb-Oseen vortex compared to conventional convolutional neural networks (CNNs) and physics-informed neural networks (PINNs). Our results substantiate DVPM's robust capabilities in modeling non-ideal single vortex flows, establishing its distinct advantages over contemporary deep learning methodologies in fluid dynamics applications. The dataset and source code are publicly available on GitHub at the following link: https://github.com/jh36714753/Learning_Non-Ideal_Single_Vortex_Flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17012v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqi Ji, Gang Du, Penghao Duan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Efficiency trends in HPC: what high-energy and astrophysicists need to know</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17283v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The growing energy demands of HPC systems have made energy efficiency a critical concern for system developers and operators. However, HPC users are generally less aware of how these energy concerns influence the design, deployment, and operation of supercomputers even though they experience the consequences. This paper examines the implications of HPC's energy consumption, providing an overview of current trends aimed at improving energy efficiency. We describe how hardware innovations such as energy-efficient processors, novel system architectures, power management techniques, and advanced scheduling policies do have a direct impact on how applications need to be programmed and executed on HPC systems. For application developers, understanding how these new systems work and how to analyse and report the performances of their own software is critical in the dialog with HPC system designers and administrators. The paper aims to raise awareness about energy efficiency among users, particularly in the high energy physics and astrophysics domains, offering practical advice on how to analyse and optimise applications to reduce their energy consumption without compromising on performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17283v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Estela Suarez, Jorge Amaya, Martin Frank, Oliver Freyermuth, Maria Girone, Bartosz Kostrzewa, Susanne Pfalzner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient inverse design of large-area metasurfaces for incoherent light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.10701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.10701v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Incoherent light is ubiquitous, yet designing optical devices that can handle its random nature is very challenging, since directly averaging over many incoherent incident beams can require a huge number of scattering calculations. We show how to instead solve this problem with a reciprocity technique which leads to three orders of magnitude speedup: one Maxwell solve (using any numerical technique) instead of thousands. This improvement enables us to perform efficient inverse design, large scale optimization of the metasurface for applications such as light collimators and concentrators. We show the impact of the angular distribution of incident light on the resulting performance, and show especially promising designs for the case of "annular" beams distributed only over nonzero angles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.10701v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsphotonics.2c01015</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rapha\"el Pestourie, Wenjie Yao, Boubacar Kant\'e, Steven G. Johnson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of barren plateaus and scaling of gradients in the energy optimization of isometric tensor network states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.00161v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vanishing gradients can pose substantial obstacles for high-dimensional optimization problems. Here we consider energy minimization problems for quantum many-body systems with extensive Hamiltonians and finite-range interactions, which can be studied on classical computers or in the form of variational quantum eigensolvers on quantum computers. Barren plateaus correspond to scenarios where the average amplitude of the energy gradient decreases exponentially with increasing system size. This occurs, for example, for quantum neural networks and for brickwall quantum circuits when the depth increases polynomially in the system size. Here we prove that the variational optimization problems for matrix product states, tree tensor networks, and the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz are free of barren plateaus. The derived scaling properties for the gradient variance provide an analytical guarantee for the trainability of randomly initialized tensor network states (TNS) and motivate certain initialization schemes. In a suitable representation, unitary tensors that parametrize the TNS are sampled according to the uniform Haar measure. We employ a Riemannian formulation of the gradient based optimizations which simplifies the analytical evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.00161v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-024-05217-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun. Math. Phys. 406, (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Barthel, Qiang Miao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matsubara-Frequency-Resolved Spin Exchange-Correlation Kernel for the Three-Dimensional Uniform Electron Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11864v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The spin Coulomb drag effect, arising from the exchange of momentum between electrons of opposite spins, plays a crucial role in the spin transport of interacting electron systems and can be characterized by the exchange-correlation (XC) kernel in the spin channel $K_{\rm XC}^-(q,\omega)$. Using the state-of-the-art Variational Diagrammatic Monte Carlo approach, we compute the Matsubara-frequency-resolved spin XC kernel $K_{\rm XC}^-(q,i\omega_n)$ for the three-dimensional uniform electron gas at sufficiently low temperatures with high precision. In the long-wavelength limit, we identified a singular behavior of the form $A(i\omega_n)/q^2$, confirming the theoretically predicted ultranonlocal behavior associated with spin Coulomb drag. Analysis of this structure in the low frequency region enables precise determination of two crucial parameters characterizing the spin Coulomb drag effect: the spin mass enhancement factor and spin diffusion relaxation time. We observe a significant trend of increasing enhancement of the spin mass factor with decreasing electron density, and provide clear evidence for the suppression of spin diffusion at low temperatures. These quantitative findings advance our understanding of Coulomb interaction effects on spin transport and provide essential parameters for time-dependent density functional theory and spintronics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11864v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyi Li, Pengcheng Hou, Youjin Deng, Kun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Machine Learning Seismology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18397v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Scientific machine learning (SciML) is an interdisciplinary research field that integrates machine learning, particularly deep learning, with physics theory to understand and predict complex natural phenomena. By incorporating physical knowledge, SciML reduces the dependency on observational data, which is often limited in the natural sciences. In this article, the fundamental concepts of SciML, its applications in seismology, and prospects are described. Specifically, two popular methods are mainly discussed: physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) and neural operators (NOs). PINNs can address both forward and inverse problems by incorporating governing laws into the loss functions. The use of PINNs is expanding into areas such as simultaneous solutions of differential equations, inference in underdetermined systems, and regularization based on physics. These research directions would broaden the scope of deep learning in natural sciences. NOs are models designed for operator learning, which deals with relationships between infinite-dimensional spaces. NOs show promise in modeling the time evolution of complex systems based on observational or simulation data. Since large amounts of data are often required, combining NOs with physics-informed learning holds significant potential. Finally, SciML is considered from a broader perspective beyond deep learning: statistical (or mathematical) frameworks that integrate observational data with physical principles to model natural phenomena. In seismology, mathematically rigorous Bayesian statistics has been developed over the past decades, whereas more flexible and scalable deep learning has only emerged recently. Both approaches can be considered as part of SciML in a broad sense. Theoretical and practical insights in both directions would advance SciML methodologies and thereby deepen our understanding of earthquake phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18397v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomohisa Okazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A physics-informed transformer neural operator for learning generalized solutions of initial boundary value problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09009v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Initial boundary value problems arise commonly in applications with engineering and natural systems governed by nonlinear partial differential equations (PDEs). Operator learning is an emerging field for solving these equations by using a neural network to learn a map between infinite dimensional input and output function spaces. These neural operators are trained using a combination of data (observations or simulations) and PDE-residuals (physics-loss). A major drawback of existing neural approaches is the requirement to retrain with new initial/boundary conditions, and the necessity for a large amount of simulation data for training. We develop a physics-informed transformer neural operator (named PINTO) that efficiently generalizes to unseen initial and boundary conditions, trained in a simulation-free setting using only physics loss. The main innovation lies in our new iterative kernel integral operator units, implemented using cross-attention, to transform the PDE solution's domain points into an initial/boundary condition-aware representation vector, enabling efficient learning of the solution function for new scenarios. The PINTO architecture is applied to simulate the solutions of important equations used in engineering applications: advection, Burgers, and steady and unsteady Navier-Stokes equations (three flow scenarios). For these five test cases, we show that the relative errors during testing under challenging conditions of unseen initial/boundary conditions are only one-fifth to one-third of other leading physics informed operator learning methods. Moreover, our PINTO model is able to accurately solve the advection and Burgers equations at time steps that are not included in the training collocation points. The code is available at https://github.com/quest-lab-iisc/PINTO</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09009v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumanth Kumar Boya, Deepak Subramani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schr\"odinger Bridges for Systems of Interacting Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09328v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A Schr\"odinger bridge is the most probable time-dependent probability distribution that connects an initial probability distribution $w_{i}$ to a final one $w_{f}$. The problem has been solved and widely used for the case of simple Brownian evolution (non-interacting particles). It is related to the problem of entropy regularized Wasserstein optimal transport. In this article, we generalize Brownian bridges to systems of interacting particles. We derive some equations for the forward and backward single particle ``wave-functions'' which allow to compute the most probable evolution of the single-particle probability between the initial and final distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09328v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henri Orland</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
