<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 03:03:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Unifying same- and different-material particle charging through stochastic scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23775v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Triboelectric charging of insulating particles through contact is critical in diverse physical and engineering processes, from dust storms and volcanic eruptions to industrial powder handling. However, repeated experiments revealed counterintuitive charge patterns, including variable impact charge under identical conditions, charge sign reversal with repeated impacts, and bipolar charging of differently sized particles. Existing computational models cannot predict these patterns; they either rely on oversimplified heuristics or require inaccessible detailed surface properties. We present a physics-based stochastic particle charging (SPC) model integrating experimentally characterized charging statistics into multiphase simulations. The model unifies same-material (particle-particle) and different-material (particle-wall) charging in a single framework, grounded in a stochastic closure by the mean, variance, skewness, and minimum impact charge of a single reference experiment. Implemented in a Lagrangian-Eulerian CFD solver, the SPC model takes less than 0.01% of the CPU time when simulating 300 000 insulating particles, charging during millions of same- and different-material contacts, transported by turbulent wall-bounded flows. By scaling the statistical parameters of the reference impact to each collision, the new model reproduces the complex charging patterns observed in experiments without requiring surface-level first-principles inputs. The SPC model offers a physically grounded route to massive-scale simulations of electrostatic effects across many fields of particle-laden flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23775v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holger Grosshans, Gizem Ozler, Simon Janta\v{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-Embedded Neural Solvers for One-Dimensional Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Physics-informed neural networks (PINN) have been widely used in computational physics to solve partial differential equations (PDEs). In this study, we propose an energy-embedding-based physics-informed neural network method for solving the one-dimensional time-independent Schr\"{o}dinger equation to obtain ground- and excited-state wave functions, as well as energy eigenvalues by incorporating an embedding layer to generate process-driven data. The method demonstrates high accuracy for several well-known potentials, such as the infinite potential well, harmonic oscillator potential, Woods-Saxon potential, and double-well potential. Further validation shows that the method also performs well in solving the radial Coulomb potential equation, showcasing its adaptability and extensibility. The proposed approach can be extended to solve other partial differential equations beyond the Schr\"{o}dinger equation and holds promise for applications in high-dimensional quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24194v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Qiang Wu, Xuan Liu, Hanlin Li, Fuqiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variation of Bose surface by Filling in Cooper pair Bose metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Cooper pair Bose metal (CPBM) is a non-superfluid quantum phase in which uncondensed fermion pairs form a "Bose surface" in momentum space. We investigate the CPBM in the two-dimensional spin-anisotropic attractive Hubbard model by tuning the next-nearest-neighbor (NNN) hopping t', carrier filling n, and spin anisotropy alpha, using large-scale constrained-path quantum Monte Carlo simulations. A moderate NNN hopping (t'/t = 0.2) substantially enlarges the CPBM region: the phase extends into weaker anisotropy regimes and coexists with a commensurate charge-density wave (CDW) near half-filling (n &gt; 0.95), where CDW order would otherwise dominate at t' = 0. Interestingly, t' suppresses the overall CDW peak amplitude and introduces a geometric correlation between the orientations of the Fermi and Bose surfaces: for weak Fermi-surface rotations, the Bose surface remains aligned with the lattice axes, while larger distortions drive both surfaces to rotate in tandem. Momentum-resolved pairing distributions reveal that the bosonic pairing channels are jointly controlled by t' and carrier filling n. For small t', d_xy-wave correlations dominate across the entire filling range. In contrast, for larger t', the dominant pairing symmetry varies with n, reflecting a nontrivial interplay between frustration and density. These findings establish carrier filling and NNN hopping as complementary levers for manipulating CPBM stability and provide concrete criteria for identifying non-superfluid bosonic matter in cold-atom and correlated-electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24405v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahao Su, Ji Liu, Jianyu Li, Zhangkai Cao, Tao Ying, Ho-Kin Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential Effects of Loading Terminal Locations on Surface Trajectories of Oil Spill Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an investigation comparing the potential impacts of offshore and onshore crude oil loading sites on surface trajectories of spilled oil particles in the regions near the Port of Corpus Christi, Texas. Oil transport is established in a two step procedure. First, the circulation and flow characteristics of seawater throughout the coastal ocean are established for various flow conditions, including current and proposed channel depth, seasonality changes, and extreme weather events. Then, spilled oil is modeled as distinct particles released at either the proposed onshore or offshore loading locations. The particle trajectories are tracked and used to assess the spread into diverse coastal ecosystems with extensive plant, sea, and land life. The models indicate that the extent of spread of these simulated oil spills to ecologically significant regions is greater when initiated at the onshore loading site than at the offshore site.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24610v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoshana Reich, Edward Buskey, Clint Dawson, Eirik Valseth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FDTD with Auxiliary Bath Fields for Condensed-Phase Polaritonics: Fundamentals and Implementation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding condensed-phase polariton experiments requires accurately accounting for both realistic cavity geometries and the interplay between polaritons and material dark modes arising from microscopic molecular interactions. The finite-difference time-domain (FDTD) approach numerically propagates classical Maxwell's equations in the time domain, offering a versatile scheme for modeling polaritons in realistic cavities. However, the simple dielectric functions routinely used in FDTD often fail to describe molecular details. Consequently, standard FDTD calculations, to date, cannot accurately describe processes involving the complex coupling between polaritons and dark modes, such as polariton relaxation, transport, and condensation. For more faithful simulations of the energy flow between the polaritons and dark modes, herein, local bath degrees of freedom coupled to the material polarization are explicitly included in FDTD to describe the dark-mode dynamics. This method -- FDTD with auxiliary bath fields (FDTD-Bath) -- is implemented in the open-source MEEP package by adding a Lorentz-Bath material susceptibility, where explicit bath modes are coupled to conventional Lorentz oscillators. With this Lorentz-Bath susceptibility, linear polariton spectra and Rabi-splitting-dependent polariton relaxation rates in planar Fabry--P\'erot cavities are reproduced more accurately than those with the conventional Lorentz susceptibility. Supported by a user-friendly Python interface and efficient MPI parallelism, the FDTD-Bath approach implemented in MEEP is ready to model a wide range of polariton phenomena involving realistic cavity geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23963v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao E. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-theoretic machine learning for time-varying mode decomposition of separated airfoil wakes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We perform an information-theoretic mode decomposition for separated wakes around a wing. The current data-driven approach based on a neural network referred to as deep sigmoidal flow enables the extraction of an informative component from a given flow field snapshot with respect to a target variable at a future time stamp, thereby capturing the causality as a time-varying modal structure. We consider three examples of separated flows around a NACA0012 airfoil, namely, 1. laminar periodic wake at post-stall angles of attack, 2. strong vortex-airfoil interactions, and 3. a turbulent wake in a spanwise-periodic domain. The present approach reveals informative vortical structures associated with a time-varying lift response. For the periodic shedding cases, the informative structures vary in time corresponding to the fluctuation level from their mean values. With the second example of vortex-airfoil interactions, how the effect of vortex gust on a wing emerges in the lift response over time is identified in an interpretable manner. Furthermore, for the case of turbulent wake, the present model highlights structures near the wing and vortex cores as informative components based solely on the information metric without any prior knowledge of aerodynamics and length scales. This study provides causality-based insights into a range of unsteady aerodynamic problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24132v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Fukami, Ryo Araki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Method for Analytical Solutions in the Lattice Boltzmann Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Analytical solutions to the lattice Boltzmann Equation make it possible to study the method itself, explore the properties of its collision operator, and identify implementations of boundary conditions. In this paper, we propose a method to find analytical solutions where the macroscopic flow profile is known. We test this method on bulk Couette flow aligned and inclined to the simulation lattice with the quadratic and entropic equilibrium distributions. Our method indeed provides an analytical solution to these flows when using the quadratic distribution. When the flow is aligned to the lattice, our method provides an analytical solution using the entropic distribution for practical relaxation times and shear rates. We show that a small even order truncation of the formal solution is optimal for accuracy-compute-time trade-off. In the inclined case, our method does not conserve momentum, by a small relative error, when using the entropic distribution. We also discover that entropic lattice Boltzmann method is not compatible with the angled Couette flow. We discuss the application of our method to more complicated flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24170v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Larson, Alexander J. Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photostriction-tunable Polarization and Structural Dynamics in Interlayer Sliding Ferroelectrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24186v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional ferroelectrics with robust polarization offer promising opportunities for non-volatile memory, field-effect transistors, and optoelectronic devices. However, the impact of lattice deformation on polarization and photoinduced structural response remains poorly understood. Here, we employ first-principles calculations to demonstrate photodoping-induced lattice expansion in rhombohedrally stacked bilayer MoS2, revealing a strong coupling between photodoping carrier and lattice structure. We identify a pronounced photostrictive response in sliding ferroelectrics, wherein electron-hole excitation leads to substantial in-plane expansion, increased interlayer spacing, and enhanced ferroelectric polarization. This strain-induced modulation drives significant bandgap renormalization. The photostriction-tunable polarization and structural dynamics arise from the strong electromechanical coupling inherent to the non-centrosymmetric rhombohedral stacking. The findings provide critical insights into the nonthermal lattice expansion governing sliding ferroelectrics at atomic-scale timescales, while simultaneously laying the groundwork for next-generation electronic and memory technologies by leveraging lattice-tunable polarization switching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24186v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Yang, Jianxin Yu, Jia Zhang, Sheng Meng, Jin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Quantum Heuristics: Non-Variational QWOA for Weighted Maxcut</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present benchmarking results for the non-variational Quantum Walk Optimisation Algorithm (non-variational QWOA) applied to the weighted maxcut problem, using classical simulations for problem sizes up to $n = 31$. The amplified quantum state, prepared using a quadratic number of alternating unitaries, achieves a constant average-case measurement probability for globally optimal solutions across these problem sizes. This behaviour contrasts with that of classical heuristics, which, for NP-hard optimisation problems, typically exhibit solve probabilities that decay as problem size increases. Performance comparisons with two local-search heuristics on the same benchmark instances suggest that the non-variational QWOA may offer a meaningful advantage by scaling more favourably with problem size. These results provide supporting evidence for the potential of this quantum heuristic to achieve quantum advantage, though further work is needed to assess whether the observed performance scaling persists at larger problem sizes, and to confirm whether similar performance trends are observed for the other problem classes to which the non-variational QWOA is designed to generalise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24191v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tavis Bennett, Aidan Smith, Edric Matwiejew, Jingbo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoupling Local Electrostatic Potential and Temperature-Driven Atomistic Forming Mechanisms in TaOx/HfO2-Based ReRAMs using Reactive Molecular Dynamics Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Resistive random access memories (ReRAMs) with a bilayer TaOx/HfO2 stack structure have been shown to possess uniquely promising resistive switching characteristics. However, the key atomistic forming mechanisms and the physical processes that govern the behavior of this kind of device remain to be clarified. Here, we present a detailed analysis of the physical mechanisms underlying its forming at the atomistic level through molecular dynamics (MD) simulations using an extended charge equilibration scheme to describe the effects of applied voltage with the charge transfer ionic potential formalism. The displacement of the tantalum ions was found to be the highest, followed by that of the hafnium ions, in response to a sufficiently high applied voltage across the electrodes, whereas the oxygen ions had a relatively minor voltage-driven response. This led to the formation of a tantalum-depleted, oxygen-rich zone near the positive top electrode acting as the anode and the clustering of oxygen vacancies that nucleated into the filament near the negative bottom electrode, or the cathode. This process resulted in partial shielding of the bulk dielectric from the applied voltage. We found a minimum threshold voltage was required to initiate vacancy clustering to form the filament. Filament growth during forming is attributed to a localized mechanism, driven by thermally activated generation of oxygen vacancy defects, which get stabilized by the local electric fields near the edge of the nucleated filament at the cathode.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24468v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simanta Lahkar, Valeria Bragaglia, Behnaz Bagheri, Donato Francesco Falcone, Matteo Galetta, Marilyne Sousa, Aida Todri-Sanial</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jacobian-free Multigrid Preconditioner for Discontinuous Galerkin Methods applied to Numerical Weather Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24504v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Discontinuous Galerkin (DG) methods are promising high order discretizations for unsteady compressible flows. Here, we focus on Numerical Weather Prediction (NWP). These flows are characterized by a fine resolution in $z$-direction and low Mach numbers, making the system stiff. Thus, implicit time integration is required and for this a fast, highly parallel, low-memory iterative solver for the resulting algebraic systems. As a basic framework, we use inexact Jacobian-Free Newton-GMRES with a preconditioner.
  For low order finite volume discretizations, multigrid methods have been successfully applied to steady and unsteady fluid flows. However, for high order DG methods, such solvers are currently lacking. %The lack of efficient solvers suitable for contemporary computer architectures inhibits wider adoption of DG methods. This motivates our research to construct a Jacobian-free precondtioner for high order DG discretizations. The preconditioner is based on a multigrid method constructed for a low order finite volume discretization defined on a subgrid of the DG mesh. We design a computationally efficient and mass conservative mapping between the grids. As smoothers, explicit Runge-Kutta pseudo time iterations are used, which can be implemented in parallel in a Jacobian-free low-memory manner.
  We consider DG Methods for the Euler equations and for viscous flow equations in 2D, both with gravity, in a well balanced formulation. Numerical experiments in the software framework DUNE-FEM on atmospheric flow problems show the benefit of this approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24504v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Birken, Andreas Dedner, Robert Kl\"ofkorn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PySEQM 2.0: Accelerated Semiempirical Excited State Calculations on Graphical Processing Units</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24807v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the implementation of electronic excited states for semi-empirical quantum chemical methods at the configuration interaction singles (CIS) and time-dependent Hartree-Fock (TDHF) level of theory in the PySEQM software. Built on PyTorch, this implementation leverages GPU acceleration to significantly speed up molecular property calculations. Benchmark tests demonstrate that our approach can compute excited states for molecules with nearly a thousand atoms in under a minute. Additionally, the implementation also includes a machine learning interface to enable parameters re-optimization and neural network training for future machine learning applications for excited state dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24807v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishikh Athavale, Nikita Fedik, William Colglazier, Anders M. N. Niklasson, Maksim Kulichenko, Sergei Tretiak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel methodology to obtain transonic solutions for dissipative flows around compact objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24839v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A novel methodology to obtain global transonic solutions around compact objects is reported here. A unified methodology to obtain accretion as well as wind solutions around these objects has been presented. Flows around compact objects are dissipative, and the conservation equations are therefore stiff. In such conditions, obtaining of sonic point(s) and hence, the transonic solution is not trivial. The conserved equations of motion fail to integrate in the presence of realistic viscosity, thereby making it difficult to obtain a global solution. This inhibits one from getting an actual picture of an astrophysical flow. The current work addresses this long-standing issue of obtaining solutions for both accretion and wind. The methodology developed utilises the inner boundary conditions and takes recourse to implicit-explicit (ImEx) integration schemes, to obtain general global transonic accretion and wind solutions. This is the first time such an attempt has been made. Current work considers the different cooling processes like bremsstrahlung, synchrotron and their inverse-Comptonizations, which are found to affect the thermodynamics of the flow. This methodology could successfully generate all topologies of global solutions, multiple sonic point regime, as well as shocks. A broad parameter space study has been done in this work. In an upcoming part II of the paper, a detailed discussion on the spectra and luminosity of the accretion and wind solutions has been presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24839v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilpa Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum DeepONet: Neural operators accelerated by quantum computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15683v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the realm of computational science and engineering, constructing models that reflect real-world phenomena requires solving partial differential equations (PDEs) with different conditions. Recent advancements in neural operators, such as deep operator network (DeepONet), which learn mappings between infinite-dimensional function spaces, promise efficient computation of PDE solutions for a new condition in a single forward pass. However, classical DeepONet entails quadratic complexity concerning input dimensions during evaluation. Given the progress in quantum algorithms and hardware, here we propose to utilize quantum computing to accelerate DeepONet evaluations, yielding complexity that is linear in input dimensions. Our proposed quantum DeepONet integrates unary encoding and orthogonal quantum layers. We benchmark our quantum DeepONet using a variety of PDEs, including the antiderivative operator, advection equation, and Burgers' equation. We demonstrate the method's efficacy in both ideal and noisy conditions. Furthermore, we show that our quantum DeepONet can also be informed by physics, minimizing its reliance on extensive data collection. Quantum DeepONet will be particularly advantageous in applications in outer loop problems which require exploring parameter space and solving the corresponding PDEs, such as uncertainty quantification and optimal experimental design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15683v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengpeng Xiao, Muqing Zheng, Anran Jiao, Xiu Yang, Lu Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Challenges in the Theory and Atomistic Simulation of Metal Electrodeposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16704v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Electrodeposition is a fundamental process in electrochemistry, and has applications in numerous industries, such as corrosion protection, decorative finishing, energy storage, catalysis, and electronics. While there is a long history of using electrodeposition, its application for controlled nanostructure growth is limited. The establishment of an atomic-scale understanding of the electrodeposition process and dynamics is crucial to enable the controlled fabrication of metal nanoparticles and other nanostructures. Significant advancements in molecular simulation capabilities and the electronic structure theory of electrified solid-liquid interfaces bring theory closer to realistic applications, but a gap remains between realistic applications, theoretical understanding of dynamics, and atomistic simulation. In this review we briefly summarize the current state-of-the-art computational techniques available for the simulation of electrodeposition and electrochemical growth on surfaces, and identify the remaining open challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16704v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shayantan Chaudhuri, Reinhard J. Maurer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin fluctuations steer the electronic behavior in the FeSb$_{3}$ skutterudite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15961v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Skutterudites are promising materials for thermoelectric and spintronics applications. Here we explore spin fluctuations in the FeSb$_{3}$ skutterudite and their effect on its electronic structure using Hubbard-corrected density-functional theory calculations. We identify multiple magnetic and charge-disproportionated configurations, with an antiferromagnetic metallic ground state. Paramagnetic fluctuations modeled through a special quasirandom spin structure open a 61 meV gap, consistent with experiments. This state features non-degenerate spin channels and band-avoided crossings, resembling a Luttinger-compensated ferrimagnet with topological features. Mapping the electronic structure to a Heisenberg Hamiltonian fails to explain the low N\'eel temperature ($\lesssim$10 K), suggesting that factors such as stoichiometry and magnetic exchange frustration may play an important role, calling for more detailed experimental investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15961v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Di Lucente, Flaviano Jos\'e dos Santos, Nicola Marzari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Materials Foundation Model via Hybrid Invariant-Equivariant Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05771v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine learning interatomic potentials (MLIPs) can predict energy, force, and stress of materials and enable a wide range of downstream discovery tasks. A key design choice in MLIPs involves the trade-off between invariant and equivariant architectures. Invariant models offer computational efficiency but may not perform as well, especially when predicting high-order outputs. In contrast, equivariant models can capture high-order symmetries, but are computationally expensive. In this work, we propose HIENet, a hybrid invariant-equivariant materials interatomic potential model that integrates both invariant and equivariant message passing layers, while provably satisfying key physical constraints. HIENet achieves state-of-the-art performance with considerable computational speedups over prior models. Experimental results on both common benchmarks and downstream materials discovery tasks demonstrate the efficiency and effectiveness of HIENet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05771v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keqiang Yan, Montgomery Bohde, Andrii Kryvenko, Ziyu Xiang, Kaiji Zhao, Siya Zhu, Saagar Kolachina, Do\u{g}uhan Sar{\i}t\"urk, Jianwen Xie, Raymundo Arroyave, Xiaoning Qian, Xiaofeng Qian, Shuiwang Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal Field Generation Based on Hybrid Mamba-Transformer with Physics-informed Fine-tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11578v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This research confronts the challenge of substantial physical equation discrepancies encountered in the generation of spatiotemporal physical fields through data-driven trained models. A spatiotemporal physical field generation model, named HMT-PF, is developed based on the hybrid Mamba-Transformer architecture, incorporating unstructured grid information as input. A fine-tuning block, enhanced with physical information, is introduced to effectively reduce the physical equation discrepancies. The physical equation residuals are computed through a point query mechanism for efficient gradient evaluation, then encoded into latent space for refinement. The fine-tuning process employs a self-supervised learning approach to achieve physical consistency while maintaining essential field characteristics. Results show that the hybrid Mamba-Transformer model achieves good performance in generating spatiotemporal fields, while the physics-informed fine-tuning mechanism further reduces significant physical errors effectively. A MSE-R evaluation method is developed to assess the accuracy and realism of physical field generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11578v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peimian Du, Jiabin Liu, Xiaowei Jin, Wangmeng Zuo, Hui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
