<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 03:26:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Mapped infinite elements in practice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This contribution is a technical description of details for implementing infinite elements. The novelty is the closed, analytic form used for most quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05568v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Marx</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomized Quasi-Monte Carlo Sampling in The Random Ray Method for Neutron Transport Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a random ray method of neutral particle transport simulation, each iteration begins by sampling a set of rays before proceeding to solve the characteristic transport equation along the linear paths the rays follow. Historically, traditional pseudorandom number generators have always been used when sampling ray starting points and directions. In the present work, we experiment with using a randomized Quasi-Monte Carlo sampling technique in place of the traditionally fully random technique with the goal of reducing the variance of simulation results. To evaluate the numerical and runtime performance of the new sampling scheme, it is implemented in the random ray solver of the OpenMC particle transport application and tested on the 2D C5G7 benchmark simulation. The new scheme delivered over a 10% reduction in the average pin-cell error and up to an 8% overall speedup compared to the state-of-the-art, owing both to numerical reductions in uncertainty as well as practical reductions in shared memory contention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06150v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Pasmann, John Tramm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Batch Power Iteration Approach for the Iterative Quasi-Monte Carlo Method Using a Randomized-Halton Sequence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06154v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Iterative Quasi-Monte Carlo (iQMC) method is a recently developed hybrid method for neutron transport simulations. iQMC replaces standard quadrature techniques used in deterministic linear solvers with Quasi-Monte Carlo simulation for accurate and efficient solutions to the neutron transport equation. Previous iQMC studies utilized a fixed-seed approach wherein particles were reset to the same initial position and direction of travel at the start of every transport sweep. While the QMC samples offered greatly improved uniformity compared to pseudo-random samples, the fixed-seed approach meant that some regions of the problem were under-sampled and resulted in errors similar to ray effects observed in discrete ordinates methods.
  This work explores using randomized-Quasi Monte Carlo techniques (RQMC) to generate unique sets of QMC samples for each transport sweep and gain a much-improved sampling of the phase space. The use of RQMC introduces some stochastic noise to iQMC's iterative process, which was previously absent. To compensate, we adopt a ``batch'' approach similar to typical Monte Carlo k-eigenvalue problems, where the iQMC source is converged over $N_\text{inactive}$ batches, then results from $N_\text{active}$ batches are recorded and used to calculate the average and standard deviation of the solution.
  The RQMC batch method was implemented in the Monte Carlo Dynamic Code (MC/DC) and is shown to be a large improvement over the fixed-seed method. The batch method was able to provide iteratively stable and more accurate solutions with nearly two orders of magnitude reduction in the number of particle histories per batch. Notably, despite introducing some stochastic noise to the solution, the RQMC batch approach converges both the k-effective and mean scalar flux error at the theoretical QMC convergence rate of $O(N^{-1})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06154v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Pasmann, Ilham Variansyah, C. T. Kelley, Ryan G. McClarren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrostatic interactions between anisotropic particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05760v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the electrostatic interactions between two charged anisotropic conductors using a combination of asymptotic and numerical methods. For widely separated particles, we employ the method of reflections to analyze the interactions. Although the formulation applies to conductors of arbitrary shapes, it is specifically implemented for spheroid-sphere systems to capture anisotropy effects in a simple configuration. In near-contact cases with axisymmetric configurations, the lubrication approximation is used to extend the analysis. Additionally, we develop a Boundary Integral Method (BIM) to study particle interactions at arbitrary separations, validating the results with asymptotic solutions for both near and far fields. We derive analytical expressions for the electrostatic force and torque on a spheroid due to another spheroid in the far-field regime. When combined with hydrodynamic effects, the electrostatic torque competes with the hydrodynamically favourable alignments of a pair of settling spheroids in certain regions while reinforcing them in others. Consequently, the inclusion of electrostatic effects may influence the instability observed in dilute suspensions of spheroids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05760v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harshit Joshi, Anubhab Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development and Comparison of Model-Based and Data-Driven Approaches for the Prediction of the Mechanical Properties of Lattice Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05762v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Lattice structures have great potential for several application fields ranging from medical and tissue engineering to aeronautical one. Their development is further speeded up by the continuing advances in additive manufacturing technologies that allow to overcome issues typical of standard processes and to propose tailored designs. However, the design of lattice structures is still challenging since their properties are considerably affected by numerous factors. The present paper aims to propose, discuss, and compare various modeling approaches to describe, understand, and predict the correlations between the mechanical properties and the void volume fraction of different types of lattice structures fabricated by fused deposition modeling 3D printing. Particularly, four approaches are proposed: (i) a simplified analytical model; (ii) a semi-empirical model combining analytical equations with experimental correction factors; (iii) an artificial neural network trained on experimental data; (iv) numerical simulations by finite element analyses. The comparison among the various approaches, and with experimental data, allows to identify the performances, advantages, and disadvantages of each approach, thus giving important guidelines for choosing the right design methodology based on the needs and available data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05762v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11665-024-10199-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Materials Engineering and Performance, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Pasini, Oscar Ramponi, Stefano Pandini, Luciana Sartore, Giulia Scalet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles Investigation of CaV$_2$TeO$_8$: A Multifunctional Heteroanionic Oxychalcogenide for Photocatalytic and Thermoelectric Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The development of industrial growth raises global energy demand. Novel materials with promising unorthodox features satiate and demand for sustainable, non-toxic, and cost-effective energy. A first-principles investigation were carried out to ground state and transport properties of CaV$_2$TeO$_8$ towards energy harvesting and photocatalytic applications was carried out. In groundstate the CaV$_2$TeO$_8$ showed good mechanically stable with a volume of \(1138.235 \, \text{\AA}^3\) and a high elastic modulus of \(215.73 \, \text{GPa}\). Further, the electronic properties of \(\mathrm{CaV_2TeO_8}\), PBE-GGA exchange-correlation was utilized, demonstrates direct and indirect transitions with a wide bandgap of 2.7 and 2.8 eV, indicating its semiconducting nature. Photoinduced charge carriers were investigated through Deformation Potential Theory (DPT) to estimate the mobility of charge carriers, excitonic radius, and effective mass. Axial anisotropic strain in band degeneracy and shifts in the S-Y and Y-\Gamma transitions offer a \(3.17 \, \text{\AA}\) Frenkel-type strongly bound exciton with a high carrier mobility of \(2409.91 \, \text{cm}^2 \, \text{V}^{-1} \, \text{s}^{-1}\) electrons and \(316.46 \, \text{cm}^2 \, \text{V}^{-1} \, \text{s}^{-1}\) holes respectively. To estimate the feasibility of \(\mathrm{CaV_2TeO_8}\) in photocatalysis, we examined the conduction and valence band edges under harsh pH conditions within PBE-GGA exchange-correlation functionals. The band edges of \(\mathrm{CaV_2TeO_8}\) show the halfway reaction for hydrogen evolution with reference to the Normal Hydrogen Electrode (NHE). Moreover, the Boltzmann equation interface was used to investigate the transport and thermoelectric properties. A high Seebeck coefficient in \(\mathrm{CaV_2TeO_8}\) at \(300 \, \text{K}\) directs a thermoelectric figure of merit of \(0.94\).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05774v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Thamizharasan, R. D. Eithiraj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Speedup for Nonreversible Markov Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05868v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum algorithms can potentially solve a handful of problems more efficiently than their classical counterparts. In that context, it has been discussed that Markov chains problems could be solved significantly faster using quantum computing. Indeed, previous work suggests that quantum computers could accelerate sampling from the stationary distribution of reversible Markov chains. However, in practice, certain physical processes of interest are nonreversible in the probabilistic sense and reversible Markov chains can sometimes be replaced by more efficient nonreversible chains targeting the same stationary distribution. This study uses modern quantum algorithmic techniques and Markov chain theory to sample from the stationary distribution of nonreversible Markov chains with faster worst-case runtime and without requiring the stationary distribution to be computed up to a multiplicative constant. Such an up-to-exponential quantum speedup goes beyond the predicted quadratic quantum acceleration for reversible chains and is likely to have a decisive impact on many applications ranging from statistics and machine learning to computational modeling in physics, chemistry, biology and finance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05868v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Claudon, Jean-Philip Piquemal, Pierre Monmarch\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Design of 3D Nanophotonic Devices with Structural Integrity Using Auxiliary Thermal Solvers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05900v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: 3D additive manufacturing enables the fabrication of nanophotonic structures with subwavelength features that control light across macroscopic scales. Gradient-based optimization offers an efficient approach to design these complex and non-intuitive structures. However, expanding this methodology from 2D to 3D introduces complexities, such as the need for structural integrity and connectivity. This work introduces a multi-objective optimization method to address these challenges in 3D nanophotonic designs. Our method combines electromagnetic simulations with an auxiliary heat-diffusion solver to ensure continuous material and void connectivity. By modeling material regions as heat sources and boundaries as heat sinks, we optimize the structure to minimize the total temperature, thereby penalizing disconnected regions that cannot dissipate thermal loads. Alongside the optical response, this heat metric becomes part of our objective function. We demonstrate the utility of our algorithm by designing two 3D nanophotonic devices. The first is a focusing element. The second is a waveguide junction, which connects two incoming waveguides for two different wavelengths into two outgoing waveguides, which are rotated by 90{\deg} to the incoming waveguides. Our approach offers a design pipeline that generates digital blueprints for fabricable nanophotonic materials, paving the way for practical 3D nanoprinting applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05900v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Kuster, Yannick Augenstein, Roberto Narv\'aez Hern\'andez, Carsten Rockstuhl, Thomas Jebb Sturges</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of sustainable energy materials via the machine-learned material space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05903v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Does a machine learning model actually gain an understanding of the material space? We answer this question in the affirmative on the example of the OptiMate model, a graph attention network trained to predict the optical properties of semiconductors and insulators. By applying the UMAP dimensionality reduction technique to its latent embeddings, we demonstrate that the model captures a nuanced and interpretable representation of the materials space, reflecting chemical and physical principles, without any user-induced bias. This enables clustering of almost 10,000 materials based on optical properties and chemical similarities. Beyond this understanding, we demonstrate how the learned material space can be used to identify more sustainable alternatives to critical materials in energy-related technologies, such as photovoltaics. These findings demonstrate the dual utility of machine learning models in materials science: Accurately predicting material properties while providing insights into the underlying materials space. The approach demonstrates the broader potential of leveraging learned materials spaces for the discovery and design of materials for diverse applications, and is easily applicable to any state-of-the-art machine learning model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05903v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Malte Grunert, Max Gro{\ss}mann, Erich Runge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimOS: A Python Framework for Simulations of Optically Addressable Spins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05922v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an open-source simulation framework for optically detected magnetic resonance, developed in Python. The framework allows users to construct, manipulate, and evolve multipartite quantum systems that consist of spins and electronic levels. We provide an interface for efficient time-evolution in Lindblad form as well as a framework for facilitating simulation of spatial and generalized stochastic dynamics. Further, symbolic operator construction and propagation is supported for simple model systems making the framework also ideal for use in classroom instruction of magnetic resonance. Designed to be backend-agnostic, the library leverages existing Python libraries as computational backends. We introduce the most important functionality and illustrate the syntax on a series of examples. These include systems such as the nitrogen-vacancy center in diamond and photo-generated spin-correlated radical pairs for which our library offers system-specific sub-modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05922v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura A. V\"olker, John M. Abendroth, Christian L. Degen, Konstantin Herb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity of Tensor Product Functions in Representing Antisymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tensor product function (TPF) approximations have been widely adopted in solving high-dimensional problems, such as partial differential equations and eigenvalue problems, achieving desirable accuracy with computational overhead that scales linearly with problem dimensions. However, recent studies have underscored the extraordinarily high computational cost of TPFs on quantum many-body problems, even for systems with as few as three particles. A key distinction in these problems is the antisymmetry requirement on the unknown functions. In the present work, we rigorously establish that the minimum number of involved terms for a class of TPFs to be exactly antisymmetric increases exponentially fast with the problem dimension. This class encompasses both traditionally discretized TPFs and the recent ones parameterized by neural networks. Our proof exploits the link between the antisymmetric TPFs in this class and the corresponding antisymmetric tensors and focuses on the Canonical Polyadic rank of the latter. As a result, our findings uncover a fundamental incompatibility between antisymmetry and low-rank TPFs in high-dimensional contexts and offer new insights for further developments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05958v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuyang Wang, Yukuan Hu, Xin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SECRET: Stochasticity Emulator for Cosmic Ray Electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06011v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The spectrum of cosmic-ray electrons depends sensitively on the history and spatial distribution of nearby sources. Given our limited observational handle on cosmic-ray sources, any model remains necessarily probabilistic. Previously, predictions were performed in a Monte Carlo fashion, summing the contributions from individual, simulated sources to generate samples from the statistical ensemble of possible electron spectra. Such simulations need to be re-run if the cosmic-ray transport parameters (e.g. diffusion coefficient, maximum energy) are changed, rendering any parameter study computationally expensive. In addition, a proper statistical analysis of observations and comparison with such probabilistic models requires the joint probability distribution of the full spectrum instead of only samples. Note that parametrising this joint distribution is rendered difficult by the non-Gaussian statistics of the cosmic-ray fluxes. Here, we employ machine learning to compute the joint probability distribution of cosmic-ray electron fluxes. Specifically, we employ masked autoregressive density estimation (MADE) for a representation of the high-dimensional joint probability distribution. In a first step, we train the network on a Monte Carlo simulation for a fixed set of transport parameters, thus significantly accelerating the generation of samples. In a second step, we extend this setup to SECRET (Stochasticity Emulator for Cosmic Ray Electrons), allowing to reliably interpolate over the space of transport parameters. We make the MADE and SECRET codes available at https://git.rwth-aachen.de/pmertsch/secret .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06011v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolas Frediani (RWTH Aachen), Michael Kr\"amer (RWTH Aachen), Philipp Mertsch (RWTH Aachen), Kathrin Nippel (RWTH Aachen)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Phase Dataset for Ti and Ti-6Al-4V</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06116v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Titanium and its alloys are technologically important materials that display a rich phase behaviour. In order to enable large-scale, realistic modelling of Ti and its alloys on the atomistic scale, Machine Learning Interatomic Potentials (MLIPs) are crucial, but rely on databases of atomic configurations. We report databases of such configurations that represent the {\alpha}, \b{eta}, {\omega} and liquid phases of Ti and the Ti-6Al-4V alloy, where we provide total energy, force and stress values evaluated by Density Functional Theory (DFT) using the PBE exchange-correlation functional. We have also leveraged and extended a data reduction strategy, via non-diagonal supercells, for the vibrational properties of Ti and sampling of atomic species within bulk crystalline data for Ti-6Al-4V. These configurations may be used to fit MLIP models that can accurately model the phase behaviour of Ti and Ti-6Al-4V across a broad range of thermodynamic conditions. To validate models, we assembled a set of benchmark protocols, which can be used to rapidly develop and evaluate MLIP models. We demonstrated the utility of our databases and validation tools by fitting models based on the Gaussian Approximation Potential (GAP) and Atomic Cluster Expansion (ACE) frameworks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06116v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor S. Allen, Albert P. Bart\'ok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal multipole center for subwavelength acoustic scatterers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06168v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The multipole expansion is a powerful framework for analyzing how subwavelength-size objects scatter waves in optics or acoustics. The calculation of multipole moments traditionally uses the scatterer's center of mass as the reference point. The theoretical foundation of this heuristic convention remains an open question. Here, we challenge this convention by demonstrating that a different, optimal multipole center can yield superior results. The optimal center is crucial -- it allows us to accurately express the scattering response while retaining a minimum number of multipole moments. Our analytical technique for finding the optimal multipole centers of individual scatterers, both in isolation and within finite arrays, is validated through numerical simulations. Our findings reveal that such an optimized positioning significantly reduces quadrupole contributions, enabling more accurate monopole-dipole approximations in acoustic calculations. Our approach also improves the computational efficiency of the T-matrix method, offering practical benefits for metamaterial design and analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06168v1</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita Ustimenko, Carsten Rockstuhl, Alexander V. Kildishev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Force-Field Approach for Itinerant Electron Magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06171v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review the recent development of machine-learning (ML) force-field frameworks for Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert (LLG) dynamics simulations of itinerant electron magnets, focusing on the general theory and implementations of symmetry-invariant representations of spin configurations. The crucial properties that such magnetic descriptors must satisfy are differentiability with respect to spin rotations and invariance to both lattice point-group symmetry and internal spin rotation symmetry. We propose an efficient implementation based on the concept of reference irreducible representations, modified from the group-theoretical power-spectrum and bispectrum methods. The ML framework is demonstrated using the s-d models, which are widely applied in spintronics research. We show that LLG simulations based on local fields predicted by the trained ML models successfully reproduce representative non-collinear spin structures, including 120$^\circ$, tetrahedral, and skyrmion crystal orders of the triangular-lattice s-d models. Large-scale thermal quench simulations enabled by ML models further reveal intriguing freezing dynamics and glassy stripe states consisting of skyrmions and bi-merons. Our work highlights the utility of ML force-field approach to dynamical modeling of complex spin orders in itinerant electron magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06171v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng Zhang, Yunhao Fan, Kotaro Shimizu, Gia-Wei Chern</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Providing Machine Learning Potentials with High Quality Uncertainty Estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05250v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Computational chemistry has come a long way over the course of several decades, enabling subatomic level calculations particularly with the development of Density Functional Theory (DFT). Recently, machine-learned potentials (MLP) have provided a way to overcome the prevalent time and length scale constraints in such calculations. Unfortunately, these models utilise complex and high dimensional representations, making it challenging for users to intuit performance from chemical structure, which has motivated the development of methods for uncertainty quantification. One of the most common methods is to introduce an ensemble of models and employ an averaging approach to determine the uncertainty. In this work, we introduced Bayesian Neural Networks (BNNs) for uncertainty aware energy evaluation as a more principled and resource efficient method to achieve this goal. The richness of our uncertainty quantification enables a new type of hybrid workflow where calculations can be offloaded to a MLP in a principled manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05250v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeynep Sumer, James L. McDonagh, Clyde Fare, Ravikanth Tadikonda, Viktor Zolyomi, David Bray, Edward Pyzer-Knapp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Krylov Methods for Molecular Hamiltonians: Reduced Memory Cost and Complexity Scaling via Tensor Hypercontraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12708v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a matrix product operator (MPO) construction based on the tensor hypercontraction (THC) format for ab initio molecular Hamiltonians. Such an MPO construction dramatically lowers the memory requirement and cost scaling of Krylov subspace methods. These can find low-lying eigenstates while avoiding local minima and simulate quantum time evolution with high accuracy. In our approach, the molecular Hamiltonian is represented as a sum of products of four MPOs, each with a bond dimension of only $2$. Iteratively applying the MPOs to the current quantum state in matrix product state (MPS) form, summing and re-compressing the MPS leads to a scheme with the same asymptotic memory cost as the bare MPS and reduces the computational cost scaling compared to the Krylov method based on a conventional MPO construction. We provide a detailed theoretical derivation of these statements and conduct supporting numerical experiments to demonstrate the advantage. We also propose that our method is compatible with parallel computing, which is essential for calculating large-size systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12708v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Maxine Luo, Christian B. Mendl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-Generalized-Gradient Approximation made Magnetic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15201v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Jacob's ladder of density functional theory (DFT) proposes the compelling view that by extending the form of successful approximations -- being guided by exact conditions and selected (least empirical) norms -- upper rungs will do better than the lower, thus allowing to balance accuracy and computational effort. Meta-generalized-gradient-approximations (MGGAs) belong to the last rung of the semi-local approximations before hybridization with non-local wave function theories. Among the MGGAs, the Strongly Constrained and Appropriately Normed Approximation (SCAN) greatly improves upon GGAs from the lower rung. But the over magnetized solutions of SCAN make GGAs more reliable for magnetism. Here, we provide a solution that satisfies the most pressing {\em desiderata} for density functional approximations for ferromagnetic, antiferromagnetic and non-collinear states. The approach is available in an implementation in the \textsc{Crystal} electronic structure package.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15201v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacques K. Desmarais, Alessandro Erba, Giovanni Vignale, Stefano Pittalis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-learned design principles for enhanced red emission from nitride quantum wells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23591v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Significant effort has been devoted toward mitigating polarization fields in nitride LEDs, as they are viewed as detrimental to light emission, albeit with limited success for red emission. Here, we show that such fields can unusually enhance the optical oscillator strength of red-emitting nitride quantum wells. This insight is enabled by machine-learned models trained on multi-scale quantum-mechanical simulations, allowing for a global exploration of the quantum-well design space at greatly reduced computational cost. Larger polarization fields correlate with higher wave-function overlaps for red emission, a consequence of the quantum-confined Stark effect enabling thinner quantum wells. This finding has implications for designing efficient red nitride LEDs, which are crucial for miniaturizing polychromatic LED pixels to the micron scale for extended-reality and biomedical applications. More broadly, this work highlights the power of machine learning in accelerating the discovery of unconventional paradigms for semiconductor design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23591v4</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick Pant, Rob Armitage, Emmanouil Kioupakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wettability and Color Change of Copper by Controlling Area Fraction of Laser Ablated Surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17324v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this research, wettability control by area fraction of laser ablated surface of copper is presented. The functional surfaces with full wettability control from highly hydrophilic to super-hydrophobic were created on copper by nanosecond (ns) and picosecond (ps) laser irradiation. The area fraction and color change were evaluated by digital image processing of microscopic images of the laser-ablated copper surface. The control of the wetting angle from almost 0 degrees to 132 degrees was achieved for both ps and ns pulses by controlling the area fraction of the laser-ablated surface. Cassie, Cassie-Baxter, and Wenzel models were adopted to explain the experimental results. For the first time, the wettability and color of copper were controlled by controlling the area fraction of the laser-ablated surface. It is expected that the current results make an impact on the heat exchanger technology of water heat sinks, cooling units, atmospheric water generators, and fog harvesting and impact numerous applications from power plants to solar thermal water systems devices where highly-hydrophilic to super hydrophobic copper can be applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17324v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mantas Gaidys, Stella Maragkaki, Alexandros Mimidis, Antonis Papadopoulos, Andreas Lemonis, Evangelos Skoulas, Andrius \v{Z}emaitis, Emmanuel Stratakis, Mindaugas Gedvilas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Deterministic Dynamical Low-rank Approach for Charged Particle Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09484v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Deterministically solving charged particle transport problems at a sufficient spatial and angular resolution is often prohibitively expensive, especially due to their highly forward peaked scattering. We propose a model order reduction approach which evolves the solution on a low-rank manifold in time, making computations feasible at much higher resolutions and reducing the overall run-time and memory footprint.
  For this, we use a hybrid dynamical low-rank approach based on a collided-uncollided split, i.e., the transport equation is split through a collision source method. Uncollided particles are described using a ray tracer, facilitating the inclusion of boundary conditions and straggling, whereas collided particles are represented using a moment method combined with the dynamical low-rank approximation. Here the energy is treated as a pseudo-time and a rank adaptive integrator is chosen to dynamically adapt the rank in energy. We can reproduce the results of a full-rank reference code at a much lower rank and thus computational cost and memory usage. The solution further achieves comparable accuracy with respect to TOPAS MC as previous deterministic approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09484v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pia Stammer, Tiberiu Burlacu, Niklas Wahl, Danny Lathouwers, Jonas Kusch</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
