<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.comp-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph</link>
    <description>physics.comp-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.comp-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 02:32:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Lagrangian Homotopy Analysis Method using the Least Action Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14730v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Homotopy Analysis Method (HAM) is a powerful technique which allows to derive approximate solutions of both ordinary and partial differential equations. We propose to use a variational approach based on the Least Action Principle (LAP) in order to improve the efficiency of the HAM when applied to Lagrangian systems. The extremization of the action is achieved by varying the HAM parameter, therefore controlling the accuracy of the approximation. As case studies we consider the harmonic oscillator, the cubic and the quartic anharmonic oscillators, and the Korteweg-de Vries partial differential equation. We compare our results with those obtained using the standard approach, which is based on the residual error square method. We see that our method accelerates the convergence of the HAM parameter to the exact value in the cases in which the exact solution is known. When the exact solution is not analytically known, we find that our method performs better than the standard HAM for the cases we have analyzed. Moreover, our method shows better performance when the order of the approximation is increased and when the nonlinearity of the equations is stronger.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14730v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gervais Nazaire Chendjou Beukam, Jean Pierre Nguenang, Stefano Ruffo, Andrea Trombettoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NAS-PINNv2: Improved neural architecture search framework for physics-informed neural networks in low-temperature plasma simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Limited by the operation and measurement conditions, numerical simulation is often the only feasible approach for studying plasma behavior and mechanisms. Although artificial intelligence methods, especially physics-informed neural network (PINN), have been widely applied in plasma simulation, the design of the neural network structures still largely relies on the experience of researchers. Meanwhile, existing neural architecture search methods tailored for PINN have encountered failures when dealing with complex plasma governing equations characterized by variable coefficients and strong nonlinearity. Therefore, we propose an improved neural architecture search-guided method, namely NAS-PINNv2, to address the limitations of existing methods. By analyzing the causes of failure, the sigmoid function is applied to calculate the architecture-related weights, and a new loss term is introduced. The performance of NAS-PINNv2 is verified in several numerical experiments including the Elenbaas-Heller equation without and with radial velocity, the drift-diffusion-Poisson equation and the Boltzmann equation. The results again emphasize that larger neural networks do not necessarily perform better, and the discovered neural architecture with multiple neuron numbers in a single hidden layer imply a more flexible and sophisticated design rule for fully connected networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15160v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Wang, Linlin Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explainable autoencoder for neutron star dense matter parameter estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a physics-informed autoencoder designed to encode the equation of state of neutron stars into an interpretable latent space. In particular the input will be encoded in the mass, radius, and tidal deformability values of a neutron star. Unlike traditional black-box models, our approach incorporates additional loss functions to enforce explainability in the encoded representations. This method enhances the transparency of machine learning models in physics, providing a robust proof-of-concept tool to study compact stars data. Our results demonstrate that the proposed autoencoder not only accurately estimates the EoS parameters and central density/pressure but also offers insights into the physical connection between equation of state and observable physical quantities. This framework conceptualizes the physical differential equations themselves as the ``encoders", allowing interpretability of the latent space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15222v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Di Clemente, Matteo Scialpi, Micha{\l} Bejger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The immersed boundary method: an accelerated SIMPLE approach for moving bodies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel and scalable approach to accelerate a direct-forcing IBM for moving boundary simulations. Building upon the SIMPLE approach, we keep the pressure and forces coupled, formulate the pressure-forces corrections system, solve for pressure-forces corrections, then perform a projection-correction step for velocities followed by a correction step for pressure and forces. To solve the pressure-forces system, we apply a block reduction and suggest an efficient preconditioning approach that is based on using the Laplacian as a preconditioner for the resulting Schur complement. The Laplacian, being independent of the coordinates of the immersed body, is factorized only once (using an efficient direct method) and is then reused throughout the simulation. We present a rigorous proof of the spectral equivalence of the Laplacian and the Schur complement, thereby showing that the preconditioner's efficiency is independent of the grid resolution.
  The performance of the method is validated through simulations of the flow around a periodically oscillating sphere in a three-dimensional box. The methodology is then applied to analyze flows generated by arrays of 7 and 14 sub-spheres modeling porous spheres of different porosities. We show good scalability of the algorithm in terms of computational time and memory consumptions. That is, the iteration count for the preconditioned pressure-forces system is nearly constant, regardless of the grid resolution, Reynolds number, and the number of spheres. The developed approach enables accurate moving boundary simulations to be performed on standard workstations, thereby enhancing accessibility of the simulations to the CFD community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15314v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Yovel, Eran Treister, Yuri Feldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation of Micro-Void Development within Large Scale Additively Manufactured Polymer Composite Deposition Beads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15349v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite the growing level of technology advancement that characterizes extrusion-deposition additive manufacturing technology, there remains a significant knowledge gap in fully understanding the process-structure-property relationship involved in this technology. The ability to effectively and efficiently control the manufacturing process provides an opportunity for optimizing the complex microstructure of the polymer composite prints which can lead to significant improvement of the associated print properties and in-service part performance. Modeling the polymer melt flow extrusion-deposition process is important in understanding the development of the inherent microstructural formation. The current research presents a computational-based approach for investigating process-induced micro-voids and their impact on print properties. We develop a multiscale FEA simulation tool to predict the global and local flow-fields during the polymer-melt flow process to investigate underlying mechanisms that may promote the micro-void development within the bead microstructure and determine potential process related factors that can be controlled to mitigate micro-void formation and growth. The research also presents a computational based method for assessing the impact of micro-voids on the effective print properties. The direct implication of reduced part voidage levels is the development of high-quality functional components for specialized applications such as light weight &amp; high strength integrity composites widely used in a variety of industries particularly the automobile, aerospace, renewable energy and defense industries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15349v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aigbe E. Awenlimobor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faults Unveiled: An In-depth MATLAB Simulation Study of Transmission Line Anomalies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15823v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study aims to create a MATLAB simulation model to examine three-phase symmetrical and unsymmetrical faults that frequently occur in long transmission line systems. The types of faults considered include single line to ground fault (L-G), double line to ground fault (L-L-G), triple line to ground fault (L-L-L-G), and line to line fault (L-L). The analysis of these faults and their impact on simulation outputs such as voltage and current are investigated. The research utilizes MATLAB software to simulate the transmission line model. The simulation model provides a valuable tool for studying the behaviour of different fault types and understanding their effects on the electrical system. The results obtained from the simulation experiments can aid in developing effective fault detection and protection strategies for transmission lines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15823v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milind A. Patwardhan, D. P. Chopade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards nonlinear thermohydrodynamic simulations via the Onsager-Regularized Lattice Boltzmann Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present theoretical analyses of the recently proposed Onsager-Regularized (OReg) lattice Boltzmann (LB) method [Jonnalagadda et al., Phys. Rev. E 104, 015313 (2021)] to demonstrate its ability to mitigate spurious errors associated with the insufficient isotropy of standard first-neighbor lattices without the inclusion of any external correction terms. As an illustration, we theoretically show that, with the so-called guided equilibrium, the OReg scheme inherently compensates for the insufficient lattice isotropy of the standard D2Q9 lattice by automatically adjusting the lattice viscosity; these theoretical results are verified numerically through simulations of the rotated decaying shear wave and isothermal shocktube problems. The present work lays the theoretical foundation of a generic framework which, with appropriately constrained equilibrium representations, can enable fully local, correction-free nonlinear thermohydrodynamic LB simulations on standard lattices, thereby facilitating scalable simulations of physically challenging fluid flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16000v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirudh Jonnalagadda, Amit Agrawal, Atul Sharma, Walter Rocchia, Sauro Succi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A non-history dependent temporal superposition algorithm for the finite line source solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16027v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulations of the operation of fields of borehole heat exchangers involve a wide spectrum of time scales, and hourly simulations for decades are required for the evaluation of the heat transfer in the subsurface due to these systems. Most current models rely on time and space superposition of fundamental analytical solutions of the heat equation to build the solution for complex borehole fields configurations and loading conditions. These procedures are robust and accurate but do not have favorable scaling properties, and the problems can become quickly computationally intractable as the size increases. In this context, acceleration algorithms for temporal superposition are key to overcome this limitation. This paper presents developments on the so-called "non-history dependent" acceleration scheme and its application to the point and line source solutions, which are commonly used as building blocks in borehole field simulations.
  The results obtained show promising properties as the computational complexity of the proposed algorithm is linear in the number of time steps, and near double precision accuracy can be achieved by refining the discretizations used to compute the integrals arising from the scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16027v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Lazzarotto, Marc Basquens, Massimo Cimmino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Fidelity Machine Learning Applied to Steady Fluid Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14870v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A machine learning method to predict steady external fluid flows using elliptic input features is introduced. Using data from as few as one high-fidelity simulation, the proposed method produces models generalizable under changes to boundary geometry by using solutions to elliptic boundary value problems over the flow domain as the model input, instead of Cartesian coordinates of the domain. Training data is generated through pointwise evaluation of flow features at points selected through a quad-tree adaptive sampling method to concentrate training points in areas with large field gradients. Models are trained within a training window around the body, while predictions are smoothly extended to freestream conditions using a Partition-of-Unity extension. Predictive capabilities of the machine learning model are demonstrated in steady-state flow of incompressible fluid around a cylinder and a Joukowski airfoil. The predicted flow field is used to warm-start CFD simulations to achieve acceleration in solver convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14870v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1080/10618562.2022.2154758</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Computational Fluid Dynamics, 36(7), 618-640 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kazuko W. Fuchi, Eric M. Wolf, David S. Makhija, Christopher R. Schrock, Philip S. Beran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous Superconducting and Topological Properties in Mg-Li Electrides at High Pressures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15518v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electrides as a unique class of emerging materials exhibit fascinating properties and hold important significance for understanding the matter under extreme conditions, which is characterized by valence electrons localized into the interstitial space as quasi-atoms (ISQs). In this work, using crystal structure prediction and first-principles calculations, we identified seven stable phases of Mg-Li that are electride with novel electronic properties under high pressure. Among them, MgLi10 is a semiconductor with a band gap of 0.22 eV; and Pm-3m MgLi is superconductor with a superconducting transition temperature of 22.8 K. The important role played by the localization degree of ISQ in the superconducting transition temperature of these electrides is revealed by systematic comparison of Mg-Li with other Li-rich electride superconductors. Furthermore, we proved that Pm-3m MgLi and Pnma MgLi also have distinct topological behavior with metallic surface states and the non-zero $Z_2$ invariant. The simultaneous coexistence of superconductivity, electronic band topology and electride property in the same structure of Pm-3m MgLi and Pnma MgLi demonstrates the feasibility of realizing multi-quantum phases in a single material, which will stimulate further research in these interdisciplinary fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15518v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jpcc.4c06309</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Chem. C 129, 689-698 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. Wang, H. Song, Q. Hao, G. Yang, H. Wang, L. Zhang, Y. Chen, X. Chen, Hua Y. Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure induced Structure Change and Anomalies in Thermodynamic Quantities and Transport Properties in Liquid Lithium Hydride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understand the nature of liquid structure and its evolution under different conditions is a major challenge in condensed physics and materials science. Here, we report a pressure-induced structure change spanning a wide pressure range in liquid-state lithium hydride (LiH) by first-principles molecular dynamic simulations. This behavior can be described as a continuous crossover from low pressure liquid with Li$^+$-H$^-$ duality symmetry to high pressure one with broken of duality symmetry. The thermodynamic quantities such as heat capacity and ionic transport properties such as diffusivity are also saliently impacted. It is important to stress that such behavior is firstly predicted for this category of materials, which is ubiquitous in universe as well as in industry applications. Lastly, a comprehensive high-pressure high-temperature phase diagram of LiH is constructed, which embodies rich physics in this previously-thought-simple ionic compound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15532v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.024102</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 024102 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>X. Z. Yan, Y. M. Chen, Hua Y. Geng, Y. F. Wang, Y. Sun, L. L. Zhang, H. Wang, Y. L. Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Mechanical Strain on Magnetic and Structural Properties of 2D Materials: A Monte Carlo study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15626v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The inherent flexibility of two dimensional materials allows for efficient manipulation of their physical properties through strain application, which is essential for the development of advanced nanoscale devices. This study aimed to understand the impact of mechanical strain on the magnetic properties of two dimensional materials using Monte Carlo simulations. The effects of several strain states on the magnetic properties were investigated using the Lennard Jones potential and bond length-dependent exchange interactions. The key parameters analyzed include the Lindemann coefficient, radial distribution function, and magnetization in relation to temperature and magnetic field. The results indicate that applying biaxial tensile strain generally reduces the critical temperature. In contrast, the biaxial compressive strain increased Tc within the elastic range, but decreased at higher strain levels. Both compressive and tensile strains significantly influence the ferromagnetic properties and structural ordering, as evidenced by magnetization hysteresis. Notably, pure shear strain did not induce disorder, leaving the magnetization unaffected. In addition, our findings suggest the potential of domain-formation mechanisms. This study provides comprehensive insights into the influence of mechanical strain on the magnetic behavior and structural integrity of 2D materials, offering valuable guidance for future research and advanced material design applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15626v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0227208</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>This article published in J. Chem. Phys. 161, 124705 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aytac Celik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of cooperation promoted by higher-order strategy updates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15698v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cooperation is fundamental to human societies, and the interaction structure among individuals profoundly shapes its emergence and evolution. In real-world scenarios, cooperation prevails in multi-group (higher-order) populations, beyond just dyadic behaviors. Despite recent studies on group dilemmas in higher-order networks, the exploration of cooperation driven by higher-order strategy updates remains limited due to the intricacy and indivisibility of group-wise interactions. Here we investigate four categories of higher-order mechanisms for strategy updates in public goods games and establish their mathematical conditions for the emergence of cooperation. Such conditions uncover the impact of both higher-order strategy updates and network properties on evolutionary outcomes, notably highlighting the enhancement of cooperation by overlaps between groups. Interestingly, we discover that the strategical mechanism alternating optimality and randomness -- selecting an outstanding group and then imitating a random individual within this group -- can prominently promote cooperation. Our analyses further unveil that, compared to pairwise interactions, higher-order strategy updates generally improve cooperation in most higher-order networks. These findings underscore the pivotal role of higher-order strategy updates in fostering collective cooperation in complex social systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15698v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dini Wang, Peng Yi, Yiguang Hong, Jie Chen, Gang Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transient Finite Element Simulation of Accelerator Magnets Using Thermal Thin Shell Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermal transient responses of superconducting magnets can be simulated using the finite element (FE) method. Some accelerator magnets use cables whose electric insulation is significantly thinner than the bare electric conductor. The FE discretisation of such geometries with high-quality meshes leads to many degrees of freedom. This increases the computational time, particularly since non-linear material properties are involved. In this work, we propose to use a thermal thin-shell approximation (TSA) to improve the computational efficiency when solving the heat diffusion equation in two dimensions. We apply the method to compute the thermal transient response of superconducting accelerator magnets used for CERN's Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and High-Luminosity LHC. The TSA collapses thin electrical insulation layers into lines while accurately representing the thermal gradient across the insulation's thickness. The TSA is implemented in the multipole module of the open-source Finite Element Quench Simulator (FiQuS), which can generate the multipole magnet models programmatically from input text files. First, the TSA approach is verified by comparison to classical FE simulations with meshed surface insulation regions for a simple block of four cables and a detailed model of the MBH dipole. The results show that the TSA approach reduces the computational time significantly while preserving the accuracy of the solution. Second, the quench heater (QH) delay computed with the TSA method is compared to measurements for the MBH magnet. To this end, the thermal transient simulation is coupled to a magnetostatic solution to account for magneto-resistive effects. Third, the TSA's full capabilities are showcased in non-linear magneto-thermal simulations of several LHC and HL-LHC superconducting magnet models. The full source code, including all input files, is publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15871v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik Schnaubelt, Andrea Vitrano, Mariusz Wozniak, Emmanuele Ravaioli, Arjan Verweij, Sebastian Sch\"ops</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidential Physics-Informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15908v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel class of Physics-Informed Neural Networks that is formulated based on the principles of Evidential Deep Learning, where the model incorporates uncertainty quantification by learning parameters of a higher-order distribution. The dependent and trainable variables of the PDE residual loss and data-fitting loss terms are recast as functions of the hyperparameters of an evidential prior distribution. Our model is equipped with an information-theoretic regularizer that contains the Kullback-Leibler divergence between two inverse-gamma distributions characterizing predictive uncertainty. Relative to Bayesian-Physics-Informed-Neural-Networks, our framework appeared to exhibit higher sensitivity to data noise, preserve boundary conditions more faithfully and yield empirical coverage probabilities closer to nominal ones. Toward examining its relevance for data mining in scientific discoveries, we demonstrate how to apply our model to inverse problems involving 1D and 2D nonlinear differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15908v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai Siong Tan, Kuancheng Wang, Rafe McBeth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Icarus 3.0: Dynamic Heliosphere Modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15923v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Space weather predictions are necessary to avoid damage caused by intense geomagnetic storms. Such strong storms are usually caused by a co-rotating interaction region (CIR) passing at Earth or by the arrival of strong coronal mass ejections (CMEs). To mitigate the damage, the effect of propagating CMEs in the solar wind must be estimated accurately at Earth and other locations. Modelling solar wind accurately is crucial for space weather predictions, as it is the medium for CME propagation. The Icarus heliospheric modelling tool is upgraded to handle dynamic inner heliospheric driving instead of using steady boundary conditions. The ideal magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) solver and the automated grid-adaptivity are adjusted to the latest MPI-AMRVAC version. The inner boundary conditions, prescribed at 0.1 AU for the heliospheric model, are updated time-dependently throughout the simulation. The coronal model is computed repeatedly for selected magnetograms. The particle sampling within MPI-AMRVAC is extended to handle stretched spherical grid information. The solar wind obtained in the simulation is dynamic and shows significant variations throughout the evolution. When comparing the results with the observations, the dynamic solar wind results are more accurate than previous results obtained with purely steady boundary driving. The CMEs propagated through the dynamic solar wind background produce more similar signatures in the time-series data than in the steady solar wind. Dynamic boundary driving in Icarus results in a more self-consistent solar wind evolution in the inner heliosphere. The obtained space weather modelling tool for dynamic solar wind and CME simulations is better suited for space weather forecasting than a steady solar wind model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15923v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tinatin Baratashvili, Beatrice Popescu Braileanu, Fabio Bacchini, Rony Keppens, Stefaan Poedts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin fluctuations steer electronic behavior and altermagnetism in the FeSb$_{3}$ skutterudite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15961v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Skutterudites are promising materials for thermoelectric and spintronics applications. Here we explore spin fluctuations in the FeSb$_{3}$ skutterudite and their effect on its electronic structure using Hubbard-corrected density-functional theory calculations. We identify multiple magnetic and charge-disproportionated configurations, with an antiferromagnetic metallic ground state. Paramagnetic fluctuations modeled through a special quasirandom spin structure open a 61 meV gap, consistent with experiments. This state features non-degenerate spin channels and band-avoided crossings, hinting at a potential altermagnetic transition with topological features. Mapping the electronic structure to a Heisenberg Hamiltonian fails to explain the low N\'eel temperature ($\lesssim$10 K), highlighting the role of magnetic exchange frustration and the need for more in-depth experimental investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15961v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Di Lucente, Flaviano Jos\'e dos Santos, Nicola Marzari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-shot capable surface acoustic wave dispersion measurement of a layered plate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16001v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Established techniques for characterizing a layer on a substrate system via surface acoustic wave (SAW) dispersion measurement are often slow due to the need for scanning excitation or detection positions. We present a method for determining discrete points on the SAW mode at equidistant wavenumbers that requires only a single measurement, overcoming these speed limitations. A pulsed laser, shaped into an array of equidistant lines, generates elastic waves on the sample surface. A vibrometer detects the resulting surface displacement next to the line array. The periodic excitation arrangement results in constructive interference of the SAW at wavelengths corresponding to integer fractions of the line spacing. This leads to distinct peaks in the response spectrum, whose higher orders we term spatial harmonics of the SAW. The known line spacing determines the wavelengths, allowing the peak frequencies to be mapped to discrete points on the SAW dispersion curve, effectively sampling the SAW at specific equidistant wavenumbers. By solving an inverse problem, a model can be fit to the experimental data to obtain properties of the layered system. We demonstrate this technique on copper-clad epoxy laminate and roll-cladded aluminum alloy plates and compare our results with dispersion relation scans and micrography. Additionally, we analyze the method's sensitivity to elastic parameters and layer thickness. This approach offers a viable alternative to established SAW scanning methods, particularly in scenarios where the trade-off of lower wavenumber sampling density is acceptable to achieve exceptionally fast measurements while avoiding moving parts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16001v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georg Watzl, Stefan Eder, Martin Ryzy, Mike Hettich, Edgar Scherleitner, Martin Schagerl, Clemens Gr\"unsteidl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond traditional box-covering: Determining the fractal dimension of complex networks using a fixed number of boxes of flexible diameter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16030v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a novel box-covering algorithm for analyzing the fractal properties of complex networks. Unlike traditional algorithms that impose a predefined box size, our approach assigns nodes to boxes identified by the nearest local hubs without rigid distance constraints. This flexibility directly relates to the recently proposed scaling theory of fractal complex networks and is clearly consistent with the idea of hidden metric spaces in which network nodes are embedded. It also allows us to determine the box dimension of various real and model-based complex networks more accurately, including those previously unrecognized as fractal, such as the Internet at the level of autonomous systems. We show that our algorithm not only significantly reduces computational complexity compared to the classical greedy coloring method but also enables more precise determination of various scaling exponents describing the structure of fractal networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16030v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Lepek, Kordian Makulski, Agata Fronczak, Piotr Fronczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic correlations with time dependent quantum Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16072v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we solve quantum many-body problem by propagating ensembles of trajectories and guiding waves in physical space. We introduce the 'effective potential' correction within the recently proposed time-dependent quantum Monte Carlo methodology to incorporate the nonlocal quantum correlation effects between the electrons. The associated correlation length is calculated by adaptive kernel density estimation over the walker distribution. The general formalism is developed and tested on one-dimensional Helium atom in laser field of different intensity and carrier frequency. Good agreement with exact results for the atomic ionization is obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16072v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan P. Christov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum frequency resampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16283v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In signal processing, resampling algorithms can modify the number of resources encoding a collection of data points. Downsampling reduces the cost of storage and communication, while upsampling interpolates new data from limited one, e.g. when resizing a digital image. We present a toolset of quantum algorithms to resample data encoded in the probabilities of a quantum register, using the quantum Fourier transform to adjust the number of high-frequency encoding qubits. We discuss advantage over classical resampling algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16283v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Tumbiolo, Simone Roncallo, Chiara Macchiavello, Lorenzo Maccone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tailored Forecasting from Short Time Series via Meta-learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16325v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) models can be effective for forecasting the dynamics of unknown systems from time-series data, but they often require large amounts of data and struggle to generalize across systems with varying dynamics. Combined, these issues make forecasting from short time series particularly challenging. To address this problem, we introduce Meta-learning for Tailored Forecasting from Related Time Series (METAFORS), which uses related systems with longer time-series data to supplement limited data from the system of interest. By leveraging a library of models trained on related systems, METAFORS builds tailored models to forecast system evolution with limited data. Using a reservoir computing implementation and testing on simulated chaotic systems, we demonstrate METAFORS' ability to predict both short-term dynamics and long-term statistics, even when test and related systems exhibit significantly different behaviors and the available data are scarce, highlighting its robustness and versatility in data-limited scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16325v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Declan A. Norton, Edward Ott, Andrew Pomerance, Brian Hunt, Michelle Girvan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering High-Strength Alloys via Physics-Transfer Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07526v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Predicting the strength of materials requires considering various length and time scales, striking a balance between accuracy and efficiency. Peierls stress measures material strength by evaluating dislocation resistance to plastic flow, reliant on elastic lattice responses and crystal slip energy landscape. Computational challenges due to the non-local and non-equilibrium nature of dislocations prohibit Peierls stress evaluation from state-of-the-art material databases. We propose a data-driven framework that leverages neural networks trained on force field simulations to understand crystal plasticity physics, predicting Peierls stress from material parameters derived via density functional theory computations, which are otherwise computationally intensive for direct dislocation modeling. This physics transfer approach successfully screen the strength of metallic alloys from a limited number of single-point calculations with chemical accuracy. Guided by these predictions, we fabricate high-strength binary alloys previously unexplored, utilizing high-throughput ion beam deposition techniques. The framework extends to problems facing the accuracy-performance dilemma in general by harnessing the hierarchy of physics of multiscale models in materials sciences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07526v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingjie Zhao, Hongbo Zhou, Zian Zhang, Zhenxing Bo, Baoan Sun, Minqiang Jiang, Zhiping Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
