<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SC</link>
    <description>cs.SC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Predictive Modeling of Flexible EHD Pumps using Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07488v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel approach to predicting the pressure and flow rate of flexible electrohydrodynamic pumps using the Kolmogorov-Arnold Network. Inspired by the Kolmogorov-Arnold representation theorem, KAN replaces fixed activation functions with learnable spline-based activation functions, enabling it to approximate complex nonlinear functions more effectively than traditional models like Multi-Layer Perceptron and Random Forest. We evaluated KAN on a dataset of flexible EHD pump parameters and compared its performance against RF, and MLP models. KAN achieved superior predictive accuracy, with Mean Squared Errors of 12.186 and 0.001 for pressure and flow rate predictions, respectively. The symbolic formulas extracted from KAN provided insights into the nonlinear relationships between input parameters and pump performance. These findings demonstrate that KAN offers exceptional accuracy and interpretability, making it a promising alternative for predictive modeling in electrohydrodynamic pumping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07488v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanhong Peng, Miao He, Fangchao Hu, Zebing Mao, Xia Huang, Jun Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM4ED: Large Language Models for Automatic Equation Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07761v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Equation discovery is aimed at directly extracting physical laws from data and has emerged as a pivotal research domain. Previous methods based on symbolic mathematics have achieved substantial advancements, but often require the design of implementation of complex algorithms. In this paper, we introduce a new framework that utilizes natural language-based prompts to guide large language models (LLMs) in automatically mining governing equations from data. Specifically, we first utilize the generation capability of LLMs to generate diverse equations in string form, and then evaluate the generated equations based on observations. In the optimization phase, we propose two alternately iterated strategies to optimize generated equations collaboratively. The first strategy is to take LLMs as a black-box optimizer and achieve equation self-improvement based on historical samples and their performance. The second strategy is to instruct LLMs to perform evolutionary operators for global search. Experiments are extensively conducted on both partial differential equations and ordinary differential equations. Results demonstrate that our framework can discover effective equations to reveal the underlying physical laws under various nonlinear dynamic systems. Further comparisons are made with state-of-the-art models, demonstrating good stability and usability. Our framework substantially lowers the barriers to learning and applying equation discovery techniques, demonstrating the application potential of LLMs in the field of knowledge discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07761v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengge Du, Yuntian Chen, Zhongzheng Wang, Longfeng Nie, Dongxiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scene-Driven Multimodal Knowledge Graph Construction for Embodied AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03783v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Embodied AI is one of the most popular studies in artificial intelligence and robotics, which can effectively improve the intelligence of real-world agents (i.e. robots) serving human beings. Scene knowledge is important for an agent to understand the surroundings and make correct decisions in the varied open world. Currently, knowledge base for embodied tasks is missing and most existing work use general knowledge base or pre-trained models to enhance the intelligence of an agent. For conventional knowledge base, it is sparse, insufficient in capacity and cost in data collection. For pre-trained models, they face the uncertainty of knowledge and hard maintenance. To overcome the challenges of scene knowledge, we propose a scene-driven multimodal knowledge graph (Scene-MMKG) construction method combining conventional knowledge engineering and large language models. A unified scene knowledge injection framework is introduced for knowledge representation. To evaluate the advantages of our proposed method, we instantiate Scene-MMKG considering typical indoor robotic functionalities (Manipulation and Mobility), named ManipMob-MMKG. Comparisons in characteristics indicate our instantiated ManipMob-MMKG has broad superiority in data-collection efficiency and knowledge quality. Experimental results on typical embodied tasks show that knowledge-enhanced methods using our instantiated ManipMob-MMKG can improve the performance obviously without re-designing model structures complexly. Our project can be found at https://sites.google.com/view/manipmob-mmkg</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03783v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Song Yaoxian, Sun Penglei, Liu Haoyu, Li Zhixu, Song Wei, Xiao Yanghua, Zhou Xiaofang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Computation of Inter-Core Bounds Through Exact Abstractions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06387v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Real-time systems (RTSs) are at the heart of numerous safety-critical applications. An RTS typically consists of a set of real-time tasks (the software) that execute on a multicore shared-memory platform (the hardware) following a scheduling policy. In an RTS, computing inter-core bounds, i.e., bounds separating events produced by tasks on different cores, is crucial. While efficient techniques to over-approximate such bounds exist, little has been proposed to compute their exact values. Given an RTS with a set of cores C and a set of tasks T , under partitioned fixed-priority scheduling with limited preemption, a recent work by Foughali, Hladik and Zuepke (FHZ) models tasks with affinity c (i.e., allocated to core c in C) as a Uppaal timed automata (TA) network Nc. For each core c in C, Nc integrates blocking (due to data sharing) using tight analytical formulae. Through compositional model checking, FHZ achieved a substantial gain in scalability for bounds local to a core. However, computing inter-core bounds for some events of interest E, produced by a subset of tasks TE with different affinities CE, requires model checking the parallel composition of all TA networks Nc for each c in CE, which produces a large, often intractable, state space. In this paper, we present a new scalable approach based on exact abstractions to compute exact inter-core bounds in a schedulable RTS, under the assumption that tasks in TE have distinct affinities. We develop a novel algorithm, leveraging a new query that we implement in Uppaal, that computes for each TA network Nc in NE an abstraction A(Nc) preserving the exact intervals within which events occur on c, therefore drastically reducing the state space. The scalability of our approach is demonstrated on the WATERS 2017 industrial challenge, for which we efficiently compute various types of inter-core bounds where FHZ fails to scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06387v2</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Aristide Foughali, Marius Miku\v{c}ionis, Maryline Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
