<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SC</link>
    <description>cs.SC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 04:00:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Extensions of the Cylindrical Algebraic Covering Method for Quantifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03070v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The cylindrical algebraic covering method was originally proposed to decide the satisfiability of a set of non-linear real arithmetic constraints. We reformulate and extend the cylindrical algebraic covering method to allow for checking the truth of arbitrary non-linear arithmetic formulas, adding support for both quantifiers and Boolean structure. Furthermore, we also propose a variant to perform quantifier elimination on such formulas. After introducing the algorithm, we elaborate on various extensions, optimizations and heuristics. Finally, we present an experimental evaluation of our implementation and provide a comparison with state-of-the-art SMT solvers and quantifier elimination tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03070v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jasper Nalbach, Gereon Kremer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Syntax and Semantics of einsum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20020v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 2011, einsum was introduced to NumPy as a practical and convenient notation for tensor expressions in machine learning, quantum circuit simulation, and other fields. It has since been implemented in additional Python frameworks such as PyTorch and TensorFlow, as well as in other programming languages such as Julia. Despite its practical success, the einsum notation still lacks a solid theoretical basis, and is not unified across the different frameworks, limiting opportunities for formal reasoning and systematic optimization. In this work, we discuss the terminology of tensor expressions and provide a formal definition of the einsum language. Based on this definition, we formalize and prove important equivalence rules for tensor expressions and highlight their relevance in practical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20020v2</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurice Wenig, Paul G. Rump, Mark Blacher, Joachim Giesen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
