<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SC</link>
    <description>cs.SC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Grammar-based Ordinary Differential Equation Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02630v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The understanding and modeling of complex physical phenomena through dynamical systems has historically driven scientific progress, as it provides the tools for predicting the behavior of different systems under diverse conditions through time. The discovery of dynamical systems has been indispensable in engineering, as it allows for the analysis and prediction of complex behaviors for computational modeling, diagnostics, prognostics, and control of engineered systems. Joining recent efforts that harness the power of symbolic regression in this domain, we propose a novel framework for the end-to-end discovery of ordinary differential equations (ODEs), termed Grammar-based ODE Discovery Engine (GODE). The proposed methodology combines formal grammars with dimensionality reduction and stochastic search for efficiently navigating high-dimensional combinatorial spaces. Grammars allow us to seed domain knowledge and structure for both constraining, as well as, exploring the space of candidate expressions. GODE proves to be more sample- and parameter-efficient than state-of-the-art transformer-based models and to discover more accurate and parsimonious ODE expressions than both genetic programming- and other grammar-based methods for more complex inference tasks, such as the discovery of structural dynamics. Thus, we introduce a tool that could play a catalytic role in dynamics discovery tasks, including modeling, system identification, and monitoring tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02630v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karin L. Yu, Eleni Chatzi, Georgios Kissas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confluence of Conditional Rewriting Modulo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01847v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Sets of equations E play an important computational role in rewriting-based systems R by defining an equivalence relation =E inducing a partition of terms into E-equivalence classes on which rewriting computations, denoted -&gt;R/E and called *rewriting modulo E*, are issued. This paper investigates *confluence of -&gt;R/E*, usually called *E-confluence*, for *conditional* rewriting-based systems, where rewriting steps are determined by conditional rules. We rely on Jouannaud and Kirchner's framework to investigate confluence of an abstract relation R modulo an abstract equivalence relation E on a set A. We show how to particularize the framework to be used with conditional systems. Then, we show how to define appropriate finite sets of *conditional pairs* to prove and disprove E-confluence. In particular, we introduce *Logic-based Conditional Critical Pairs* which do not require the use of (often infinitely many) E-unifiers to provide a finite representation of the *local peaks* considered in the abstract framework. We also introduce *parametric Conditional Variable Pairs* which are essential to deal with conditional rules in the analysis of E-confluence. Our results apply to well-known classes of rewriting-based systems. In particular, to *Equational (Conditional) Term Rewriting Systems*.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01847v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salvador Lucas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
