<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.class-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.class-ph</link>
    <description>physics.class-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.class-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotical dynamics of askew-polarized spinning top under the radiation reaction torque</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02970v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rotary dynamics of polarized composite particles as dipole rigid bodies is considered. It is described the Euler equations singularly perturbed by the radiation reaction torque. The Schott term is taken into account, and the reduction procedure lowering higher derivatives is applied. Asymptotic methods of nonlinear mechanics are used to analyze the rotary dynamics of askew-polarized spinning top. Numerical estimates are relevant to the hypothetical DAST-nanocrystals that might possess a huge dipole moment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02970v2</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjp/s13360-024-05104-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The European Physical Journal Plus 139, 423 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Askold Duviryak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinearity-induced symmetry breaking in a system of two parametrically driven Kerr-Duffing oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01377v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the classical dynamics of a system comprising a pair of Kerr-Duffing nonlinear oscillators, which are coupled through a nonlinear interaction and subjected to a parametric drive. Using the rotating wave approximation (RWA), we analyze the steady-state solutions for the amplitudes of the two oscillators. For the case of almost identical oscillators, we investigate separately the cases in which only one oscillator is parametrically driven and in which both oscillators are simultaneously driven. In the latter regime, we demonstrate that even when the parametric drives acting on the two oscillators are identical, the system can transition from a stable symmetric solution to a broken-symmetry solution as the detuning is varied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01377v2</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Hellbach, D. De Bernardis, M. Saur, I. Carusotto, W. Belzig, G. Rastelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
