<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.class-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.class-ph</link>
    <description>physics.class-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.class-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 02:47:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Envelope vector solitons in nonlinear flexible mechanical metamaterials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ a combination of analytical and numerical techniques to investigate the dynamics of lattice envelope vector soliton solutions propagating within a one-dimensional chain of flexible mechanical metamaterial. To model the system, we formulate discrete equations that describe the longitudinal and rotational displacements of each individual rigid unit mass using a lump element approach. By applying the multiple-scales method in the context of a semi-discrete approximation, we derive an effective nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation that characterizes the evolution of rotational and slowly varying envelope waves from the aforementioned discrete motion equations. We thus show that this flexible mechanical metamaterial chain supports envelope vector solitons where the rotational component has the form of either a bright or a dark soliton. In addition, due to nonlinear coupling, the longitudinal displacement displays kink-like profiles thus forming the 2-components vector soliton. These findings, which include specific vector envelope solutions, enrich our knowledge on the nonlinear wave solutions supported by flexible mechanical metamaterials and open new possibilities for the control of nonlinear waves and vibrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09871v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Demiquel, Vassos Achilleos, Georgios Theocharis, Vincent Tournat</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
