<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.class-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.class-ph</link>
    <description>physics.class-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.class-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Local Elastic Lattices with $\mathcal{PT}$-Symmetry and Time Modulation: From Perfect Trapping to the Wave Boomerang Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wave motion is fundamentally constrained by the dispersion properties of the medium, often making it challenging -- or even impossible -- to guide wave packets along desired trajectories, particularly when wave inversion is required. The paper illustrates how one-dimensional (1D) and two-dimensional (2D) non-Hermitian elastic lattices with time-varying non-local feedback interactions offer unprecedented wave guidance. By relaxing the constraint of Hermiticity while preserving $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetry of the nonlocal interactions, it is herein built a framework where the dispersion transitions from positive to negative group velocity, passing through an intermediate regime characterized by a perfectly flat band across all momenta. This effect, realized within the unbroken $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric phase, is further enhanced by the time modulation of lattice parameters, thereby unlocking functionalities such as perfect trapping, where a wave packet is intentionally stopped, and the wave boomerang effect, where the wave packet is reversed or guided back to its initial position. The framework presented in this paper unlocks opportunities that extend beyond wave guidance, including information processing through dispersion engineering in elastic media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20401v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Riva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature as Joules per Bit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12119v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In statistical mechanics, entropy is defined as a fundamental quantity. However, its unit, J/K, involves that of temperature, which is only subsequently defined - and defined in terms of entropy. This circularity arises with the introduction of Boltzmann's constant into the very expression of entropy. The J/K carried by the constant prevents entropy from finding a unit of its own while simultaneously obfuscating its informational nature. Following the precepts of information theory, we argue that entropy is well measured in bits and coincides with information capacity at thermodynamic equilibrium. Consequently, not only is the temperature of a system in equilibrium expressed in J/bit, but it acquires a clear meaning: It is the cost in energy to increase its information capacity by 1 bit. Viewing temperature as joules per bit uncovers the strong duality exhibited by Gibbs long ago between available capacity and free energy. It also simplifies Landauer's cost and clarifies that it is a cost of displacement, not of erasure. Replacing the kelvin with the bit as an SI unit would remove Boltzmann's constant from the seven defining constants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12119v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1119/5.0198820</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Charles Alexandre B\'edard, Sophie Berthelette, Xavier Coiteux-Roy, Stefan Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
