<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.AP</link>
    <description>stat.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 04:01:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrosophic Birnbaum-Saunders distribution with applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Classical statistics deals with determined and precise data analysis. But in reality, there are many cases where the information is not accurate and a degree of impreciseness, uncertainty, incompleteness, and vagueness is observed. In these situations, uncertainties can make classical statistics less accurate. That is where neutrosophic statistics steps in to improve accuracy in data analysis. In this article, we consider the Birnbaum-Saunders distribution (BSD) which is very flexible and practical for real world data modeling. By integrating the neutrosophic concept, we improve the BSD's ability to manage uncertainty effectively. In addition, we provide maximum likelihood parameter estimates. Subsequently, we illustrate the practical advantages of the neutrosophic model using two cases from the industrial and environmental fields. This paper emphasizes the significance of the neutrosophic BSD as a robust solution for modeling and analysing imprecise data, filling a crucial gap left by classical statistical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17884v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mansooreh Razmkhah, Mohammad Arashi, Andriette Bekker, Filipe J. Marques</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the effect of non-resonant background variation on the CARS data analysis and classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17829v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: : Non-resonant background (NRB) plays a significant role in coherent anti-Stokes Raman scattering (CARS) spectroscopic applications. All the recent works primarily focused on removing the NRB using different deep learning methods, and only one study explored the effect of NRB. Hence, in this work, we systematically investigated the impact of NRB variation on Raman signal retrieval. The NRB is simulated as a linear function with different strengths relative to the resonant Raman signal, and the variance also changed for each NRB strength. The resonant part of nonlinear susceptibility is extracted from real experimental Raman data; hence, the simulated CARS data better approximate the experimental CARS spectra. Then, the corresponding Raman signal is retrieved by four different methods: maximum entropy method (MEM), Kramers-Kronig (KK), convolutional neural network (CNN), and long short-term memory (LSTM) network. Pearson correlation measurements and principal component analysis combined with linear discriminant analysis (PCA-LDA) modelling revealed that MEM and KK methods have an edge over LSTM and CNN for higher NRB strengths. It is also demonstrated that normalizing the input data favors LSTM and CNN predictions. In contrast, background removal from the predictions significantly influenced Pearson correlation but not the classification accuracies for MEM and KK. This comprehensive study is done for the first time to the best of our knowledge and has the potential to impact the CARS spectroscopy and microscopy applications in different areas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17829v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajendhar Junjuri, Tobias Meyer-Zedler, J\"urgen Popp, Thomas Bocklitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shrinkage Estimators for Beta Regression Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18047v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The beta regression model is a useful framework to model response variables that are rates or proportions, that is to say, response variables which are continuous and restricted to the interval (0,1). As with any other regression model, parameter estimates may be affected by collinearity or even perfect collinearity among the explanatory variables. To handle these situations shrinkage estimators are proposed. In particular we develop ridge regression and LASSO estimators from a penalized likelihood perspective with a logit link function. The properties of the resulting estimators are evaluated through a simulation study and a real data application</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18047v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Firinguetti, Manuel Gonz\'alez-Navarrete, Romer Machaca-Aguilar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Counting Stations to City-Wide Estimates: Data-Driven Bicycle Volume Extrapolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Shifting to cycling in urban areas reduces greenhouse gas emissions and improves public health. Street-level bicycle volume information would aid cities in planning targeted infrastructure improvements to encourage cycling and provide civil society with evidence to advocate for cyclists' needs. Yet, the data currently available to cities and citizens often only comes from sparsely located counting stations. This paper extrapolates bicycle volume beyond these few locations to estimate bicycle volume for the entire city of Berlin. We predict daily and average annual daily street-level bicycle volumes using machine-learning techniques and various public data sources. These include app-based crowdsourced data, infrastructure, bike-sharing, motorized traffic, socioeconomic indicators, weather, and holiday data. Our analysis reveals that the best-performing model is XGBoost, and crowdsourced cycling and infrastructure data are most important for the prediction. We further simulate how collecting short-term counts at predicted locations improves performance. By providing ten days of such sample counts for each predicted location to the model, we are able to halve the error and greatly reduce the variability in performance among predicted locations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18454v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silke K. Kaiser, Nadja Klein, Lynn H. Kaack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving estimation for asymptotically independent bivariate extremes via global estimators for the angular dependence function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.13237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.13237v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modelling the extremal dependence of bivariate variables is important in a wide variety of practical applications, including environmental planning, catastrophe modelling and hydrology. The majority of these approaches are based on the framework of bivariate regular variation, and a wide range of literature is available for estimating the dependence structure in this setting. However, such procedures are only applicable to variables exhibiting asymptotic dependence, even though asymptotic independence is often observed in practice. In this paper, we consider the so-called `angular dependence function'; this quantity summarises the extremal dependence structure for asymptotically independent variables. Until recently, only pointwise estimators of the angular dependence function have been available. We introduce a range of global estimators and compare them to another recently introduced technique for global estimation through a systematic simulation study, and a case study on river flow data from the north of England, UK.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.13237v4</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. J. R. Murphy-Barltrop, J. L. Wadsworth, E. F. Eastoe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussian Saha's ionization in Rindler spacetime and the equivalence principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07644v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the non-Gaussian effects of the Saha equation in Rindler space via Tsallis statistics. By considering a system with cylindrical geometry, we deduce the non-Gaussian Saha ionization equation for a partially ionized hydrogen plasma that expands with uniform acceleration. We demonstrate conditions for the validity of the equivalence principle within the realms of both Boltzmann-Gibbs and Tsallis statistics. In the non-Gaussian framework, our findings reveal that the effective binding energy exhibits a quadratic dependence on the frame acceleration, in contrast to the linear dependence predicted by Boltzmann-Gibbs statistics. We show that an accelerated observer shall notice a more pronounced effect on the effective binding energy for $a&gt;0$ and a more attenuated one when $a&lt;0$. We also ascertain that an accelerated observer will measure values of $q$ smaller than those measured in the rest frame. Besides, assuming the equivalence principle, we examine the effects of the gravitational field on the photoionization of hydrogen atoms and pair production. We show that both photoionization and pair production are more intensely suppressed in regions with a strong gravitational field in a non-Gaussian context than in the Boltzmann-Gibbs framework. Lastly, constraints on the gravitational field and the electron and positron chemical potentials are derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07644v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. L. Sales, F. C. Carvalho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp variance estimator and causal bootstrap in stratified randomized experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16667v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The design-based finite-population asymptotic theory provides a normal approximation for the sampling distribution of the average treatment effect estimator in stratified randomized experiments. The asymptotic variance could be estimated by a Neyman-type conservative variance estimator. However, the variance estimator can be overly conservative, and the asymptotic theory may fail in small samples. To solve these issues, we propose a sharp variance estimator for the weighted difference-in-means in stratified randomized experiments. Furthermore, we propose two causal bootstrap procedures to more accurately approximate the sampling distribution of the weighted difference-in-means estimator. The first causal bootstrap procedure is based on rank-preserving imputation and we prove its second-order refinement over normal approximation. The second causal bootstrap procedure is based on constant-treatment-effect imputation and is applicable in paired experiments. We prove its validity even when the assumption of constant treatment effect is violated for the true potential outcomes. Our analysis is randomization-based or design-based by conditioning on the potential outcomes, with treatment assignment being the sole source of randomness. Numerical studies and two real data applications demonstrate advantages of our proposed methods in finite samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16667v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyang Yu, Ke Zhu, Hanzhong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coarse graining correlation matrices according to macrostructures: Financial markets as a paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05364v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze correlation structures in financial markets by coarse graining the Pearson correlation matrices according to market sectors to obtain Guhr matrices using Guhr's correlation method according to Ref. [P. Rinn {\it et. al.}, Europhysics Letters 110, 68003 (2015)]. We compare the results for the evolution of market states and the corresponding transition matrices with those obtained using Pearson correlation matrices. The behavior of market states is found to be similar for both the coarse grained and Pearson matrices. However, the number of relevant variables is reduced by orders of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05364v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Mija\'il Mart\'inez-Ramos, Parisa Majari, Andres R. Cruz-Hern\'andez, Hirdesh K. Pharasi, Manan Vyas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Geometry Analysis of EMF Exposure of Idle Users and Network Performance with Dynamic Beamforming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01190v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel mathematical framework based on stochastic geometry to investigate the electromagnetic field exposure (EMFE) of both active and idle users located at a specific distance from each other, in cellular networks with dynamic beamforming. Accurate antenna gain modeling, encompassing both the main and side lobes, becomes crucial in this context. To address this need, the multi-cosine antenna pattern is introduced. The marginal distribution of EMFE for each user type is derived. The paper then examines network performance by introducing a new metric designed to ensure minimal downlink coverage for active users while keeping EMFE for idle users below a specified limit. This metric addresses questions such as, "What is the probability that idle users at a distance of $x$~m from an active user will experience EMFE below a specific limit while the active user meets a specific coverage requirement, and how many antenna elements are needed at the base station to increase this probability of, let us say, 20\%?".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01190v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quentin Gontier, Charles Wiame, Joe Wiart, Fran\c{c}ois Horlin, Christo Tsigros, Claude Oestges, Philippe De Doncker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking mortality risk prediction from electrocardiograms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17002v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Several recent high-impact studies leverage large hospital-owned electrocardiographic (ECG) databases to model and predict patient mortality. MIMIC-IV, released September 2023, is the first comparable public dataset and includes 800,000 ECGs from a U.S. hospital system. Previously, the largest public ECG dataset was Code-15, containing 345,000 ECGs collected during routine care in Brazil. These datasets now provide an excellent resource for a broader audience to explore ECG survival modeling. Here, we benchmark survival model performance on Code-15 and MIMIC-IV with two neural network architectures, compare four deep survival modeling approaches to Cox regressions trained on classifier outputs, and evaluate performance at one to ten years. Our results yield AUROC and concordance scores comparable to past work (circa 0.8) and reasonable AUPRC scores (MIMIC-IV: 0.4-0.5, Code-15: 0.05-0.13) considering the fraction of ECG samples linked to a mortality (MIMIC-IV: 27\%, Code-15: 4\%). When evaluating models on the opposite dataset, AUROC and concordance values drop by 0.1-0.15, which may be due to cohort differences. All code and results are made public.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17002v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Platon Lukyanenko, Joshua Mayourian, Mingxuan Liu, John K. Triedman, Sunil J. Ghelani, William G. La Cava</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
