<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.AP</link>
    <description>stat.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 02:50:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Climatic Factors on Respiratory Pharmaceutical Demand: A Comparison of Forecasting Models for Greece</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Climate change is increasingly recognized as a driver of health-related outcomes, yet its impact on pharmaceutical demand remains largely understudied. As environmental conditions evolve and extreme weather events intensify, anticipating their influence on medical needs is essential for designing resilient healthcare systems.
  This study examines the relationship between climate variability and the weekly demand for respiratory prescription pharmaceuticals in Greece, based on a dataset spanning seven and a half years (390 weeks). Granger causality spectra are employed to explore potential causal relationships. Following variable selection, four forecasting models are implemented: Prophet, a Vector Autoregressive model with exogenous variables (VARX), Random Forest with Moving Block Bootstrap (MBB-RF), and Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) networks.
  The MBB-RF model achieves the best performance in relative error metrics while providing robust insights through variable importance rankings. The LSTM model outperforms most metrics, highlighting its ability to capture nonlinear dependencies. The VARX model, which includes Prophet-based exogenous inputs, balances interpretability and accuracy, although it is slightly less competitive in overall predictive performance.
  These findings underscore the added value of climate-sensitive variables in modeling pharmaceutical demand and provide a data-driven foundation for adaptive strategies in healthcare planning under changing environmental conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10642v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viviana Schisa, Matteo Farn\`e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Velocity Vector Fields using Transport Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10898v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurately estimating latent velocity vector fields of atmospheric winds is crucial for understanding weather phenomena. Direct measurement of atmospheric winds is costly, especially in the upper atmosphere, so researchers attempt to estimate atmospheric winds by observing the movement patterns of clouds and other features in satellite images of the atmosphere. These Derived Motion Winds use feature tracking algorithms to search for movement within small windows in space and time. Consequently, these algorithms cannot leverage information from broader-scale features and cannot ensure that the collection of wind vectors over space and time represents a physically realistic velocity field. In this work, we use spatial-temporal Gaussian processes to model the evolution of a scalar quantity transported over time by fluid flow. Our framework simultaneously estimates covariance parameters and latent velocities by maximizing the likelihood. Specifically, flows are represented using time-dependent residual neural networks, and velocities are subsequently derived through closed-form formulas. Performance evaluations using weather model data demonstrate our method's accuracy and efficiency. We apply our methods to GOES-16 images, demonstrating computational efficiency and the ability to produce wind estimates where Derived Motion Winds fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10898v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youssef Fahmy, Maria Laura Battagliola, Joseph Guinness</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Age-stratified clustering of multiple long-term conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Background: Most people with any long-term condition have multiple long-term conditions, but our understanding of how conditions cluster is limited. Many clustering studies identify clusters in the whole population, but the clusters that occur in people of different ages may be distinct. The aim of this paper was to explore similarities and differences in clusters found in different age-groups.
  Method: We present a method for finding similar clusters in multiple age-groups, referred to as cluster sets, using Latent Class Analysis (LCA) and Chebyshev distance metric. We analyse a primary care electronic health record (EHR) dataset recording the presence of 40 long-term conditions (LTCs) in 570,355 people aged 40-99 years with at least one of these conditions, analysing in five-year age-groups.
  Findings: We find that the 600 clusters found separately in 12 age-strata can be summarised by 342 cluster sets with 263 cluster sets only being found in a single age-group (singleton cluster sets), and 79 cluster sets being present in multiple age-groups. We observe that 31 conditions of the 40 conditions studied appear in cluster sets with the respective condition being the only condition present with a very high prevalence of more than 0.9 whereas the remaining cluster sets typically contain two to four conditions present with a high prevalence of more than 0.7.
  Interpretation: Multimorbidity profiles in different age-groups are often distinct (singleton cluster sets observed only in that age-group), but similar clusters with small variations in their composition are also found in multiple age-groups. This demonstrates the age dependency of MLTC clusters and presents a case for age-stratified clustering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10952v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Chakraborty, Bruce Guthrie, Sohan Seth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dependency-Aware Shrinkage Priors for High Dimensional Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10715v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In high dimensional regression, global local shrinkage priors have gained significant traction for their ability to yield sparse estimates, improve parameter recovery, and support accurate predictive modeling. While recent work has explored increasingly flexible shrinkage prior structures, the role of explicitly modeling dependencies among coefficients remains largely unexplored. In this paper, we investigate whether incorporating such structures into traditional shrinkage priors improves their performance. We introduce dependency-aware shrinkage priors, an extension of continuous shrinkage priors that integrates correlation structures inspired by Zellner's g prior approach. We provide theoretical insights into how dependence alters the prior and posterior structure, and evaluate the method empirically through simulations and real data. We find that modeling dependence can improve parameter recovery when predictors are strongly correlated, but offers only modest gains in predictive accuracy. These findings suggest that prior dependence should be used selectively and guided by the specific inferential goals of the analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10715v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Enrique Aguilar, Paul-Christian B\"urkner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covariance Symmetries Classification in Multitemporal/Multipass PolSAR Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11137v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A polarimetric synthetic aperture radar (PolSAR) system, which uses multiple images acquired with different polarizations in both transmission and reception, has the potential to improve the description and interpretation of the observed scene. This is typically achieved by exploiting the polarimetric covariance or coherence matrix associated with each pixel, which is processed to meet a specific goal in Earth observation. This paper presents a design framework for selecting the structure of the polarimetric covariance matrix that accurately reflects the symmetry associated with the analyzed pixels. The proposed methodology leverages both polarimetric and temporal information from multipass PolSAR images to enhance the retrieval of information from the acquired data. To accomplish this, it is assumed that the covariance matrix (of the overall acquired data) is given as the Kronecker product of the temporal and polarimetric covariances. An alternating maximization algorithm, known as the flip-flop method, is then developed to estimate both matrices while enforcing the symmetry constraint on the polarimetric covariance. Subsequently, the symmetry structure classification is formulated as a multiple hypothesis testing problem, which is solved using model order selection techniques. The proposed approach is quantitatively assessed on simulated data, showing its advantages over its competitor, which does not exploit temporal correlations. For example, it reaches accuracies of 94.6% and 92.0% for the reflection and azimuth symmetry classes, respectively, while the competitor achieves 72.5% and 72.6% under the same simulation conditions. Finally, the effectiveness of the proposed framework is further demonstrated using measured RADARSAT-2 data, corroborating the results obtained from the simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11137v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dehbia Hanis, Luca Pallotta, Augusto Aubry, Aichouche Belhadj-Aissa, Antonio De Maio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JaxSGMC: Modular stochastic gradient MCMC in JAX</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11190v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present JaxSGMC, an application-agnostic library for stochastic gradient Markov chain Monte Carlo (SG-MCMC) in JAX. SG-MCMC schemes are uncertainty quantification (UQ) methods that scale to large datasets and high-dimensional models, enabling trustworthy neural network predictions via Bayesian deep learning. JaxSGMC implements several state-of-the-art SG-MCMC samplers to promote UQ in deep learning by reducing the barriers of entry for switching from stochastic optimization to SG-MCMC sampling. Additionally, JaxSGMC allows users to build custom samplers from standard SG-MCMC building blocks. Due to this modular structure, we anticipate that JaxSGMC will accelerate research into novel SG-MCMC schemes and facilitate their application across a broad range of domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11190v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.softx.2024.101722</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SoftwareX, Volume 26, 2024, 101722, ISSN 2352-7110</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Thaler, Paul Fuchs, Ana Cukarska, Julija Zavadlav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Generative Framework for Causal Estimation via Importance-Weighted Diffusion Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11444v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Estimating individualized treatment effects from observational data is a central challenge in causal inference, largely due to covariate imbalance and confounding bias from non-randomized treatment assignment. While inverse probability weighting (IPW) is a well-established solution to this problem, its integration into modern deep learning frameworks remains limited. In this work, we propose Importance-Weighted Diffusion Distillation (IWDD), a novel generative framework that combines the pretraining of diffusion models with importance-weighted score distillation to enable accurate and fast causal estimation-including potential outcome prediction and treatment effect estimation. We demonstrate how IPW can be naturally incorporated into the distillation of pretrained diffusion models, and further introduce a randomization-based adjustment that eliminates the need to compute IPW explicitly-thereby simplifying computation and, more importantly, provably reducing the variance of gradient estimates. Empirical results show that IWDD achieves state-of-the-art out-of-sample prediction performance, with the highest win rates compared to other baselines, significantly improving causal estimation and supporting the development of individualized treatment strategies. We will release our PyTorch code for reproducibility and future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11444v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinran Song, Tianyu Chen, Mingyuan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanistic inference of stochastic gene expression from structured single-cell data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Single-cell gene expression measurements encode variability spanning molecular noise, cellular heterogeneity, and technical artifacts. Mechanistic models provide a principled framework to disentangle these sources and extract insight, but inferring underlying dynamics from standard sequencing count data faces fundamental limitations. Structured datasets with temporal, spatial, or multimodal features offer constraints that help resolve these ambiguities, but demand more complex models and advanced inference strategies, including machine learning techniques with associated tradeoffs. This review highlights recent progress in the judicious integration of structured single-cell data, stochastic model development, and innovative inference strategies to extract gene-level insights. These approaches lay the foundation for mechanistic understanding of regulatory networks and multicellular systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11460v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher E. Miles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Multivariate Track Geometry Degradation Modelling and its use in Condition-Based Inspection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.14240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.14240v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Effective maintenance of railway infrastructure is crucial for safe and comfortable transportation. Among the various degradation modes, track geometry deformation due to repeated loading significantly impacts operational safety. Detecting and maintaining acceptable track geometry involves the use of track recording vehicles (TRVs) that inspect and record geometric parameters. This study aims to develop a novel track geometry degradation model that considers multiple indicators and their correlations, accounting for both imperfect manual and mechanized tamping. A multivariate Wiener model is formulated to capture the characteristics of track geometry degradation. To address data limitations, a hierarchical Bayesian approach with Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulation is employed. This research contributes to the analysis of a multivariate predictive model, which considers the correlation between the degradation rates of multiple indicators, providing insights for rail operators and new track-monitoring systems. The model's performance is validated through a real-world case study on a commuter track in Queensland, Australia, using actual data and independent test datasets. Additionally, the study demonstrates the application of the proposed multivariate degradation model in developing a condition-based inspection policy for track geometry, potentially reducing the number of TRV runs while maintaining abnormal detection levels and failure rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.14240v2</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huy Truong-Ba, Sinda Rebello, Michael E. Cholette, Venkat Reddy, Pietro Borghesani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Privacy risk from synthetic data: practical proposals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04257v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes and compares measures of identity and attribute disclosure risk for synthetic data. Data custodians can use the methods proposed here to inform the decision as to whether to release synthetic versions of confidential data. Different measures are evaluated on two data sets. Insight into the measures is obtained by examining the details of the records identified as posing a disclosure risk. This leads to methods to identify, and possibly exclude, apparently risky records where the identification or attribution would be expected by someone with background knowledge of the data. The methods described are available as part of the \textbf{synthpop} package for \textbf{R}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04257v3</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gillian M Raab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auditing Fairness by Betting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.17570v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide practical, efficient, and nonparametric methods for auditing the fairness of deployed classification and regression models. Whereas previous work relies on a fixed-sample size, our methods are sequential and allow for the continuous monitoring of incoming data, making them highly amenable to tracking the fairness of real-world systems. We also allow the data to be collected by a probabilistic policy as opposed to sampled uniformly from the population. This enables auditing to be conducted on data gathered for another purpose. Moreover, this policy may change over time and different policies may be used on different subpopulations. Finally, our methods can handle distribution shift resulting from either changes to the model or changes in the underlying population. Our approach is based on recent progress in anytime-valid inference and game-theoretic statistics-the "testing by betting" framework in particular. These connections ensure that our methods are interpretable, fast, and easy to implement. We demonstrate the efficacy of our approach on three benchmark fairness datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.17570v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Chugg, Santiago Cortes-Gomez, Bryan Wilder, Aaditya Ramdas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local-Polynomial Estimation for Multivariate Regression Discontinuity Designs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08941v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a multivariate local-linear estimator for multivariate regression discontinuity designs in which treatment is assigned by crossing a boundary in the space of running variables. The dominant approach uses the Euclidean distance from a boundary point as the scalar running variable; hence, multivariate designs are handled as uni-variate designs. However, the bandwidth selection with the distance running variable is suboptimal and inefficient for the underlying multivariate problem. We handle multivariate designs as multivariate. In this study, we develop a novel asymptotic normality for multivariate local-polynomial estimators. Our estimator is asymptotically valid and can capture heterogeneous treatment effects over the boundary. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our estimator through numerical simulations. Our empirical illustration of a Colombian scholarship study reveals a richer heterogeneity of the treatment effect that is hidden in the original estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08941v2</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masayuki Sawada, Takuya Ishihara, Daisuke Kurisu, Yasumasa Matsuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization Error Propagation: Revisiting Layer-Wise Post-Training Quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09629v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Layer-wise PTQ is a promising technique for compressing large language models (LLMs), due to its simplicity and effectiveness without requiring retraining. However, recent progress in this area is saturating, underscoring the need to revisit its core limitations and explore further improvements. We address this challenge by identifying a key limitation of existing layer-wise PTQ methods: the growth of quantization errors across layers significantly degrades performance, particularly in low-bit regimes. To address this fundamental issue, we propose Quantization Error Propagation (QEP), a general, lightweight, and scalable framework that enhances layer-wise PTQ by explicitly propagating quantization errors and compensating for accumulated errors. QEP also offers a tunable propagation mechanism that prevents overfitting and controls computational overhead, enabling the framework to adapt to various architectures and resource budgets. Extensive experiments on several LLMs demonstrate that QEP-enhanced layer-wise PTQ achieves substantially higher accuracy than existing methods. Notably, the gains are most pronounced in the extremely low-bit quantization regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09629v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yamato Arai, Yuma Ichikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whitened Score Diffusion: A Structured Prior for Imaging Inverse Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10311v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Conventional score-based diffusion models (DMs) may struggle with anisotropic Gaussian diffusion processes due to the required inversion of covariance matrices in the denoising score matching training objective \cite{vincent_connection_2011}. We propose Whitened Score (WS) diffusion models, a novel SDE-based framework that learns the Whitened Score function instead of the standard score. This approach circumvents covariance inversion, extending score-based DMs by enabling stable training of DMs on arbitrary Gaussian forward noising processes. WS DMs establish equivalence with FM for arbitrary Gaussian noise, allow for tailored spectral inductive biases, and provide strong Bayesian priors for imaging inverse problems with structured noise. We experiment with a variety of computational imaging tasks using the CIFAR and CelebA ($64\times64$) datasets and demonstrate that WS diffusion priors trained on anisotropic Gaussian noising processes consistently outperform conventional diffusion priors based on isotropic Gaussian noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10311v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Alido, Tongyu Li, Yu Sun, Lei Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
