<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.AP</link>
    <description>stat.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Absolute Risk Prediction for Cannabis Use Disorder Using Bayesian Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Introduction: Substance use disorders (SUDs) have emerged as a pressing public health crisis in the United States, with adolescent substance use often leading to SUDs in adulthood. Effective strategies are needed to prevent this progression. To help in filling this need, we develop a novel and the first-ever absolute risk prediction model for cannabis use disorder (CUD) for adolescent or young adult cannabis users.
  Methods: We train a Bayesian machine learning model that provides a personalized CUD absolute risk for adolescent or young adult cannabis users using data from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health. Model performance is assessed using 5-fold cross-validation (CV) with area under the curve (AUC) and ratio of the expected to observed number of cases (E/O). External validation of the final model is conducted using two independent datasets.
  Results: The proposed model has five risk factors: biological sex, delinquency, and scores on personality traits of conscientiousness, neuroticism, and openness. For predicting CUD risk within five years of first cannabis use, AUC and E/O, computed via 5-fold CV, were 0.68 and 0.95, respectively. For the same type of prediction in external validation, AUC values were 0.64 and 0.75, with E/O values of 0.98 and 1, indicating good discrimination and calibration performances of the model.
  Discussion and Conclusion: The proposed model is the first absolute risk prediction model for an SUD. It can aid clinicians in identifying adolescent/youth substance users at a high risk of developing CUD in future for clinically appropriate interventions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09156v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tingfang Wang, Joseph M. Boden, Swati Biswas, Pankaj K. Choudhary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grey system model on time scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09358v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Grey System Theory (GST) is a powerful mathematical framework employed for modeling systems with uncertain or incomplete information. This paper proposes an integration of the GST with time scales, a generalized approach that encompasses both discrete and continuous time models. The proposed model, called the Grey System Model on Time Scales (GST-T), offers a robust solution for analyzing hybrid systems where events occur on varying time domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09358v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanli Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid, Comprehensive Search of Crystalline Phases from X-ray Diffraction in Seconds via GPU-Accelerated Bayesian Variational Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09308v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In analysis of X-ray diffraction data, identifying the crystalline phase is important for interpreting the material. The typical method is identifying the crystalline phase from the coincidence of the main diffraction peaks. This method identifies crystalline phases by matching them as individual crystalline phases rather than as combinations of crystalline phases, in the same way as the greedy method. If multiple candidates are obtained, the researcher must subjectively select the crystalline phases. Thus, the identification results depend on the researcher's experience and knowledge of materials science. To solve this problem, we have developed a Bayesian estimation method to identify the combination of crystalline phases, taking the entire profile into account. This method estimates the Bayesian posterior probability of crystalline phase combinations by performing an approximate exhaustive search of all possible combinations. It is a method for identifying crystalline phases that takes into account all peak shapes and phase combinations. However, it takes a few hours to obtain the analysis results. The aim of this study is to develop a Bayesian method for crystalline phase identification that can provide results in seconds, which is a practical calculation time. We introduce variational sparse estimation and GPU computing. Our method is able to provide results within 10 seconds even when analysing $2^{50}$ candidate crystalline phase combinations. Furthermore, the crystalline phases identified by our method are consistent with the results of previous studies that used a high-precision algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09308v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryo Murakami, Kenji Nagata, Yoshitaka Matsushita, Masahiko Demura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data mining the functional architecture of the brain's circuitry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09684v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The brain is a highly complex organ consisting of a myriad of subsystems that flexibly interact and adapt over time and context to enable perception, cognition, and behavior. Understanding the multi-scale nature of the brain, i.e., how circuit- and moleclular-level interactions build up the fundamental components of brain function, holds incredible potential for developing interventions for neurodegenerative and psychiatric diseases, as well as open new understanding into our very nature. Historically technological limitations have forced systems neuroscience to be local in anatomy (localized, small neural populations in single brain areas), in behavior (studying single tasks), in time (focusing on specific stages of learning or development), and in modality (focusing on imaging single biological quantities). New developments in neural recording technology and behavioral monitoring now provide the data needed to break free of local neuroscience to global neuroscience: i.e., understanding how the brain's many subsystem interact, adapt, and change across the multitude of behaviors animals and humans must perform to thrive. Specifically, while we have much knowledge of the anatomical architecture of the brain (i.e., the hardware), we finally are approaching the data needed to find the functional architecture and discover the fundamental properties of the software that runs on the hardware. We must take this opportunity to bridge between the vast amounts of data to discover this functional architecture which will face numerous challenges from low-level data alignment up to high level questions of interpretable mathematical models of behavior that can synthesize the myriad of datasets together.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09684v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam S. Charles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kairosis: A method for dynamical probability forecast aggregation informed by Bayesian change point detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00785v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new method, "kairosis", for aggregating probability forecasts made over a time period of a single outcome determined at the end of that period. Informed by work on Bayesian change-point detection, we begin by constructing for each time during the period a posterior probability that the forecasts before and after this time are distributed differently. The resulting posterior probability mass function is integrated to give a cumulative mass function, which is used to create a weighted median forecast. The effect is to construct an aggregate in which the most heavily weighted forecasts are those which have been made since the probable most recent change in the forecasts' distribution. Kairosis outperforms standard methods, and is especially suitable for geopolitical forecasting tournaments because it is observed to be robust across disparate questions and forecaster distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00785v3</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zane Hassoun, Ben Powell, Niall MacKay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Necessary and sufficient conditions for posterior propriety for generalized linear mixed models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.00665v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Generalized linear mixed models (GLMMs) are commonly used to analyze correlated discrete or continuous response data. In Bayesian GLMMs, the often-used improper priors may yield undesirable improper posterior distributions. Thus, verifying posterior propriety is crucial for valid applications of Bayesian GLMMs with improper priors. Here, we consider the popular improper uniform prior on the regression coefficients and several proper or improper priors, including the widely used gamma and power priors on the variance components of the random effects. We also construct an approximate Jeffreys' prior for objective Bayesian analysis of GLMMs. For the two most widely used GLMMs, namely, the binomial and Poisson GLMMs, we provide easily verifiable sufficient conditions compared to the currently available results. We also derive the necessary conditions for posterior propriety for the general exponential family GLMMs. Finally, we use examples involving one-way and two-way random effects models to demonstrate the theoretical results derived here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.00665v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yalin Rao, Vivekananda Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact phylodynamic likelihood via structured Markov genealogy processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17032v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider genealogies arising from a Markov population process in which individuals are categorized into a discrete collection of compartments, with the requirement that individuals within the same compartment are statistically exchangeable. When equipped with a sampling process, each such population process induces a time-evolving tree-valued process defined as the genealogy of all sampled individuals. We provide a construction of this genealogy process and derive exact expressions for the likelihood of an observed genealogy in terms of filter equations. These filter equations can be numerically solved using standard Monte Carlo integration methods. Thus, we obtain statistically efficient likelihood-based inference for essentially arbitrary compartment models based on an observed genealogy of individuals sampled from the population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17032v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron A. King, Qianying Lin, Edward L. Ionides</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the optimal prediction of extreme events in heavy-tailed time series with applications to solar flare forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11887v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The prediction of extreme events in time series is a fundamental problem arising in many financial, scientific, engineering, and other applications. We begin by establishing a general Neyman-Pearson-type characterization of optimal extreme event predictors in terms of density ratios. This yields new insights and several closed-form optimal extreme event predictors for additive models. These results naturally extend to time series, where we study optimal extreme event prediction for both light- and heavy-tailed autoregressive and moving average models. Using a uniform law of large numbers for ergodic time series, we establish the asymptotic optimality of an empirical version of the optimal predictor for autoregressive models. Using multivariate regular variation, we obtain an expression for the optimal extremal precision in heavy-tailed infinite moving averages, which provides theoretical bounds on the ability to predict extremes in this general class of models. We address the important problem of predicting solar flares by applying our theory and methodology to a state-of-the-art time series consisting of solar soft X-ray flux measurements. Our results demonstrate the success and limitations in solar flare forecasting of long-memory autoregressive models and long-range-dependent, heavy-tailed FARIMA models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11887v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Verma, Stilian Stoev, Yang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional Singular Value Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03619v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Heterogeneous functional data commonly arise in time series and longitudinal studies. To uncover the statistical structures of such data, we propose Functional Singular Value Decomposition (FSVD), a unified framework encompassing various tasks for the analysis of functional data with potential heterogeneity. We establish the mathematical foundation of FSVD by proving its existence and providing its fundamental properties. We then develop an implementation approach for noisy and irregularly observed functional data based on a novel alternating minimization scheme and provide theoretical guarantees for its convergence and estimation accuracy. The FSVD framework also introduces the concepts of intrinsic basis functions and intrinsic basis vectors, representing two fundamental structural aspects of random functions. These concepts enable FSVD to provide new and improved solutions to tasks including functional principal component analysis, factor models, functional clustering, functional linear regression, and functional completion, while effectively handling heterogeneity and irregular temporal sampling. Through extensive simulations, we demonstrate that FSVD-based methods consistently outperform existing methods across these tasks. To showcase the value of FSVD in real-world datasets, we apply it to extract temporal patterns from a COVID-19 case count dataset and perform data completion on an electronic health record dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03619v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianbin Tan, Pixu Shi, Anru R. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
