<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB</link>
    <description>cs.DB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 02:43:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>$\textit{Dirigo}$: A Method to Extract Event Logs for Object-Centric Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07490v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Real-world processes involve multiple object types with intricate interrelationships. Traditional event logs (in XES format), which record process execution centred around the case notion, are restricted to a single-object perspective, making it difficult to capture the behaviour of multiple objects and their interactions. To address this limitation, object-centric event logs (OCEL) have been introduced to capture both the objects involved in a process and their interactions with events. The object-centric event data (OCED) metamodel extends the OCEL format by further capturing dynamic object attributes and object-to-object relations. Recently OCEL 2.0 has been proposed based on OCED metamodel. Current research on generating OCEL logs requires specific input data sources, and resulting log data often fails to fully conform to OCEL 2.0. Moreover, the generated OCEL logs vary across different representational formats and their quality remains unevaluated. To address these challenges, a set of quality criteria for evaluating OCEL log representations is established. Guided by these criteria, $\textit{Dirigo}$ is proposed -- a method for extracting event logs that not only conforms to OCEL 2.0 but also extends it by capturing the temporal aspect of dynamic object-to-object relations. Object-role Modelling (ORM), a conceptual data modelling technique, is employed to describe the artifact produced at each step of $\textit{Dirigo}$. To validate the applicability of $\textit{Dirigo}$, it is applied to a real-life use case, extracting an event log via simulation. The quality of the log representation of the extracted event log is compared to those of existing OCEL logs using the established quality criteria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07490v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia Wei (Queensland University of Technology), Chun Ouyang (Queensland University of Technology), Arthur ter Hofstede (Queensland University of Technology), Ying Wang (Beijing Jiaotong University), Lei Huang (Beijing Jiaotong University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Data Markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07267v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Data is the new oil of the 21st century. The growing trend of trading data for greater welfare has led to the emergence of data markets. A data market is any mechanism whereby the exchange of data products including datasets and data derivatives takes place as a result of data buyers and data sellers being in contact with one another, either directly or through mediating agents. It serves as a coordinating mechanism by which several functions, including the pricing and the distribution of data as the most important ones, interact to make the value of data fully exploited and enhanced. In this article, we present a comprehensive survey of this important and emerging direction from the aspects of data search, data productization, data transaction, data pricing, revenue allocation as well as privacy, security, and trust issues. We also investigate the government policies and industry status of data markets across different countries and different domains. Finally, we identify the unresolved challenges and discuss possible future directions for the development of data markets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07267v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayao Zhang, Yuran Bi, Mengye Cheng, Jinfei Liu, Kui Ren, Qiheng Sun, Yihang Wu, Yang Cao, Raul Castro Fernandez, Haifeng Xu, Ruoxi Jia, Yongchan Kwon, Jian Pei, Jiachen T. Wang, Haocheng Xia, Li Xiong, Xiaohui Yu, James Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overhead-free User-side Recommender Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07589v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditionally, recommendation algorithms have been designed for service developers. But recently, a new paradigm called user-side recommender systems has been proposed. User-side recommender systems are built and used by end users, in sharp contrast to traditional provider-side recommender systems. Even if the official recommender system offered by the provider is not fair, end users can create and enjoy their own user-side recommender systems by themselves. Although the concept of user-side recommender systems is attractive, the problem is they require tremendous communication costs between the user and the official system. Even the most efficient user-side recommender systems require about 5 times more costs than provider-side recommender systems. Such high costs hinder the adoption of user-side recommender systems. In this paper, we propose overhead-free user-side recommender systems, RecCycle, which realizes user-side recommender systems without any communication overhead. The main idea of RecCycle is to recycle past recommendation results offered by the provider's recommender systems. The ingredients of RecCycle can be retrieved ``for free,'' and it greatly reduces the cost of user-side recommendations. In the experiments, we confirm that RecCycle performs as well as state-of-the-art user-side recommendation algorithms while RecCycle reduces costs significantly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07589v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryoma Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spider 2.0: Evaluating Language Models on Real-World Enterprise Text-to-SQL Workflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07763v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Real-world enterprise text-to-SQL workflows often involve complex cloud or local data across various database systems, multiple SQL queries in various dialects, and diverse operations from data transformation to analytics. We introduce Spider 2.0, an evaluation framework comprising 632 real-world text-to-SQL workflow problems derived from enterprise-level database use cases. The databases in Spider 2.0 are sourced from real data applications, often containing over 1,000 columns and stored in local or cloud database systems such as BigQuery and Snowflake. We show that solving problems in Spider 2.0 frequently requires understanding and searching through database metadata, dialect documentation, and even project-level codebases. This challenge calls for models to interact with complex SQL workflow environments, process extremely long contexts, perform intricate reasoning, and generate multiple SQL queries with diverse operations, often exceeding 100 lines, which goes far beyond traditional text-to-SQL challenges. Our evaluations indicate that based on o1-preview, our code agent framework successfully solves only 17.0% of the tasks, compared with 91.2% on Spider 1.0 and 73.0% on BIRD. Our results on Spider 2.0 show that while language models have demonstrated remarkable performance in code generation -- especially in prior text-to-SQL benchmarks -- they require significant improvement in order to achieve adequate performance for real-world enterprise usage. Progress on Spider 2.0 represents crucial steps towards developing intelligent, autonomous, code agents for real-world enterprise settings. Our code, baseline models, and data are available at https://spider2-sql.github.io.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07763v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangyu Lei, Jixuan Chen, Yuxiao Ye, Ruisheng Cao, Dongchan Shin, Hongjin Su, Zhaoqing Suo, Hongcheng Gao, Wenjing Hu, Pengcheng Yin, Victor Zhong, Caiming Xiong, Ruoxi Sun, Qian Liu, Sida Wang, Tao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>City Foundation Models for Learning General Purpose Representations from OpenStreetMap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00583v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pre-trained Foundation Models (PFMs) have ushered in a paradigm-shift in Artificial Intelligence, due to their ability to learn general-purpose representations that can be readily employed in a wide range of downstream tasks. While PFMs have been successfully adopted in various fields such as Natural Language Processing and Computer Vision, their capacity in handling geospatial data and answering urban questions remains limited. This can be attributed to the intrinsic heterogeneity of geospatial data, which encompasses different data types, including points, segments and regions, as well as multiple information modalities, such as a spatial position, visual characteristics and textual annotations. The proliferation of Volunteered Geographic Information initiatives, and the ever-increasing availability of open geospatial data sources, like OpenStreetMap, which is freely accessible globally, unveil a promising opportunity to bridge this gap. In this paper, we present CityFM, a self-supervised framework to train a foundation model within a selected geographical area of interest, such as a city. CityFM relies solely on open data from OSM, and produces multimodal representations of entities of different types, incorporating spatial, visual, and textual information. We analyse the entity representations generated using our foundation models from a qualitative perspective, and conduct quantitative experiments on road, building, and region-level downstream tasks. We compare its results to algorithms tailored specifically for the respective applications. In all the experiments, CityFM achieves performance superior to, or on par with, the baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00583v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Balsebre, Weiming Huang, Gao Cong, Yi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Access for Conjunctive Queries with Negations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.15800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.15800v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a conjunctive query $Q$ and a database $D$, a direct access to the answers of $Q$ over $D$ is the operation of returning, given an index $k$, the $k$-th answer for some order on its answers. While this problem is #P-hard in general with respect to combined complexity, many conjunctive queries have an underlying structure that allows for a direct access to their answers for some lexicographical ordering that takes polylogarithmic time in the size of the database after a polynomial time precomputation. Previous work has precisely characterised the tractable classes and given fine-grained lower bounds on the precomputation time needed depending on the structure of the query.
  In this paper, we generalise these tractability results to the case of signed conjunctive queries, that is, conjunctive queries that may contain negative atoms. Our technique is based on a class of circuits that can represent relational data. We first show that this class supports tractable direct access after a polynomial time preprocessing. We then give bounds on the size of the circuit needed to represent the answer set of signed conjunctive queries depending on their structure. Both results combined together allow us to prove the tractability of direct access for a large class of conjunctive queries. On the one hand, we recover the known tractable classes from the literature in the case of positive conjunctive queries. On the other hand, we generalise and unify known tractability results about negative conjunctive queries -- that is, queries having only negated atoms. In particular, we show that the class of $\beta$-acyclic negative conjunctive queries and the class of bounded nest set width negative conjunctive queries admit tractable direct access.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.15800v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florent Capelli, Nofar Carmeli, Oliver Irwin, Sylvain Salvati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Privacy-Preserving Medical Record Linkage: A Three-Party MPC Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21605v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Record linkage is a crucial concept for integrating data from multiple sources, particularly when datasets lack exact identifiers, and it has diverse applications in real-world data analysis. Privacy-Preserving Record Linkage (PPRL) ensures this integration occurs securely, protecting sensitive information from unauthorized access. This is especially important in sectors such as healthcare, where datasets include private identity information (IDAT) governed by strict privacy laws. However, maintaining both privacy and efficiency in large-scale record linkage poses significant challenges. Consequently, researchers must develop advanced methods to protect data privacy while optimizing processing performance. This paper presents a novel and efficient PPRL method based on a secure 3-party computation (MPC) framework. Our approach allows multiple parties to compute linkage results without exposing their private inputs and significantly improves the speed of linkage process compared to existing privacy-preserving solutions. We demonstrated that our method preserves the linkage quality of the state-of-the-art PPRL method while achieving up to 14 times faster performance. For example, linking a record against a database of 10,000 records takes just 8.74 seconds in a realistic network with 700 Mbps bandwidth and 60 ms latency. Even on a slower internet connection with 100 Mbps bandwidth and 60 ms latency, the linkage completes in 28 seconds, highlighting the scalability and efficiency of our solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21605v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\c{S}eyma Selcan Ma\u{g}ara, Noah Dietrich, Ali Burak \"Unal, Mete Akg\"un</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
