<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB</link>
    <description>cs.DB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Qr-Hint: Actionable Hints Towards Correcting Wrong SQL Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe a system called Qr-Hint that, given a (correct) target query Q* and a (wrong) working query Q, both expressed in SQL, provides actionable hints for the user to fix the working query so that it becomes semantically equivalent to the target. It is particularly useful in an educational setting, where novices can receive help from Qr-Hint without requiring extensive personal tutoring. Since there are many different ways to write a correct query, we do not want to base our hints completely on how Q* is written; instead, starting with the user's own working query, Qr-Hint purposefully guides the user through a sequence of steps that provably lead to a correct query, which will be equivalent to Q* but may still "look" quite different from it. Ideally, we would like Qr-Hint's hints to lead to the "smallest" possible corrections to Q. However, optimality is not always achievable in this case due to some foundational hurdles such as the undecidability of SQL query equivalence and the complexity of logic minimization. Nonetheless, by carefully decomposing and formulating the problems and developing principled solutions, we are able to provide provably correct and locally optimal hints through Qr-Hint. We show the effectiveness of Qr-Hint through quality and performance experiments as well as a user study in an educational setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04352v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihao Hu, Amir Gilad, Kristin Stephens-Martinez, Sudeepa Roy, Jun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aleph Filter: To Infinity in Constant Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Filter data structures are widely used in various areas of computer science to answer approximate set-membership queries. In many applications, the data grows dynamically, requiring their filters to expand along with the data that they represent. However, existing methods for expanding filters cannot maintain stable performance, memory footprint, and false positive rate at the same time. We address this problem with Aleph Filter, which makes the following contributions. (1) It supports all operations (insertions, queries, deletes, etc.) in constant time, no matter how much the data grows. (2) Given any rough estimate of how much the data will ultimately grow, Aleph Filter provides far superior memory vs. false positive rate trade-offs, even if the estimate is off by orders of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04703v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niv Dayan, Ioana Bercea, Rasmus Pagh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster Algorithms for Fair Max-Min Diversification in $\mathbb{R}^d$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The task of extracting a diverse subset from a dataset, often referred to as maximum diversification, plays a pivotal role in various real-world applications that have far-reaching consequences. In this work, we delve into the realm of fairness-aware data subset selection, specifically focusing on the problem of selecting a diverse set of size $k$ from a large collection of $n$ data points (FairDiv).
  The FairDiv problem is well-studied in the data management and theory community. In this work, we develop the first constant approximation algorithm for FairDiv that runs in near-linear time using only linear space. In contrast, all previously known constant approximation algorithms run in super-linear time (with respect to $n$ or $k$) and use super-linear space. Our approach achieves this efficiency by employing a novel combination of the Multiplicative Weight Update method and advanced geometric data structures to implicitly and approximately solve a linear program. Furthermore, we improve the efficiency of our techniques by constructing a coreset. Using our coreset, we also propose the first efficient streaming algorithm for the FairDiv problem whose efficiency does not depend on the distribution of data points. Empirical evaluation on million-sized datasets demonstrates that our algorithm achieves the best diversity within a minute. All prior techniques are either highly inefficient or do not generate a good solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04713v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3654940</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIGMOD 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yash Kurkure, Miles Shamo, Joseph Wiseman, Sainyam Galhotra, Stavros Sintos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BOLD v4: A Centralized Bioinformatics Platform for DNA-based Biodiversity Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: BOLD, the Barcode of Life Data System, supports the acquisition, storage, validation, analysis, and publication of DNA barcodes, activities requiring the integration of molecular, morphological, and distributional data. Its pivotal role in curating the reference library of DNA barcodes, coupled with its data management and analysis capabilities, make it a central resource for biodiversity science. It enables rapid, accurate identification of specimens and also reveals patterns of genetic diversity and evolutionary relationships among taxa. Launched in 2005, BOLD has become an increasingly powerful tool for advancing understanding of planetary biodiversity. It currently hosts 17 million specimen records and 14 million barcodes that provide coverage for more than a million species from every continent and ocean. The platform has the long-term goal of providing a consistent, accurate system for identifying all species of eukaryotes. BOLD's integrated analytical tools, full data lifecycle support, and secure collaboration framework distinguish it from other biodiversity platforms. BOLD v4 brought enhanced data management and analysis capabilities as well as novel functionality for data dissemination and publication. Its next version will include features to strengthen its utility to the research community, governments, industry, and society-at-large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05696v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujeevan Ratnasingham, Catherine Wei, Dean Chan, Jireh Agda, Josh Agda, Liliana Ballesteros-Mejia, Hamza Ait Boutou, Zak Mohammad El Bastami, Eddie Ma, Ramya Manjunath, Dana Rea, Chris Ho, Angela Telfer, Jaclyn McKeowan, Miduna Rahulan, Claudia Steinke, Justin Dorsheimer, Megan Milton, Paul D. N. Hebert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniTS: A Universal Time Series Analysis Framework with Self-supervised Representation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.13804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.13804v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine learning has emerged as a powerful tool for time series analysis. Existing methods are usually customized for different analysis tasks and face challenges in tackling practical problems such as partial labeling and domain shift. To achieve universal analysis and address the aforementioned problems, we develop UniTS, a novel framework that incorporates self-supervised representation learning (or pre-training). The components of UniTS are designed using sklearn-like APIs to allow flexible extensions. We demonstrate how users can easily perform an analysis task using the user-friendly GUIs, and show the superior performance of UniTS over the traditional task-specific methods without self-supervised pre-training on five mainstream tasks and two practical settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.13804v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyu Liang, Chen Liang, Zheng Liang, Hongzhi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Effective Next POI Prediction: Spatial and Semantic Augmentation with Remote Sensing Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04271v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The next point-of-interest (POI) prediction is a significant task in location-based services, yet its complexity arises from the consolidation of spatial and semantic intent. This fusion is subject to the influences of historical preferences, prevailing location, and environmental factors, thereby posing significant challenges. In addition, the uneven POI distribution further complicates the next POI prediction procedure. To address these challenges, we enrich input features and propose an effective deep-learning method within a two-step prediction framework. Our method first incorporates remote sensing data, capturing pivotal environmental context to enhance input features regarding both location and semantics. Subsequently, we employ a region quad-tree structure to integrate urban remote sensing, road network, and POI distribution spaces, aiming to devise a more coherent graph representation method for urban spatial. Leveraging this method, we construct the QR-P graph for the user's historical trajectories to encapsulate historical travel knowledge, thereby augmenting input features with comprehensive spatial and semantic insights. We devise distinct embedding modules to encode these features and employ an attention mechanism to fuse diverse encodings. In the two-step prediction procedure, we initially identify potential spatial zones by predicting user-preferred tiles, followed by pinpointing specific POIs of a designated type within the projected tiles. Empirical findings from four real-world location-based social network datasets underscore the remarkable superiority of our proposed approach over competitive baseline methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04271v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan Jiang, Haitao Yuan, Jianing Si, Minxiao Chen, Shangguang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IsoPredict: Dynamic Predictive Analysis for Detecting Unserializable Behaviors in Weakly Isolated Data Store Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04621v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents the first dynamic predictive analysis for data store applications under weak isolation levels, called Isopredict. Given an observed serializable execution of a data store application, Isopredict generates and solves SMT constraints to find an unserializable execution that is a feasible execution of the application. Isopredict introduces novel techniques that handle divergent application behavior; solve mutually recursive sets of constraints; and balance coverage, precision, and performance. An evaluation on four transactional data store benchmarks shows that Isopredict often predicts unserializable behaviors, 99% of which are feasible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04621v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3656391</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. ACM Program. Lang., Vol. 8, No. PLDI, Article 161. Publication date: June 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chujun Geng, Spyros Blanas, Michael D. Bond, Yang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TimeCSL: Unsupervised Contrastive Learning of General Shapelets for Explorable Time Series Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05057v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Unsupervised (a.k.a. Self-supervised) representation learning (URL) has emerged as a new paradigm for time series analysis, because it has the ability to learn generalizable time series representation beneficial for many downstream tasks without using labels that are usually difficult to obtain. Considering that existing approaches have limitations in the design of the representation encoder and the learning objective, we have proposed Contrastive Shapelet Learning (CSL), the first URL method that learns the general-purpose shapelet-based representation through unsupervised contrastive learning, and shown its superior performance in several analysis tasks, such as time series classification, clustering, and anomaly detection. In this paper, we develop TimeCSL, an end-to-end system that makes full use of the general and interpretable shapelets learned by CSL to achieve explorable time series analysis in a unified pipeline. We introduce the system components and demonstrate how users interact with TimeCSL to solve different analysis tasks in the unified pipeline, and gain insight into their time series by exploring the learned shapelets and representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05057v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyu Liang, Chen Liang, Zheng Liang, Hongzhi Wang, Bo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHORUS: Foundation Models for Unified Data Discovery and Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09610v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We apply foundation models to data discovery and exploration tasks. Foundation models include large language models (LLMs) that show promising performance on a range of diverse tasks unrelated to their training. We show that these models are highly applicable to the data discovery and data exploration domain. When carefully used, they have superior capability on three representative tasks: table-class detection, column-type annotation and join-column prediction. On all three tasks, we show that a foundation-model-based approach outperforms the task-specific models and so the state of the art. Further, our approach often surpasses human-expert task performance. We investigate the fundamental characteristics of this approach including generalizability to several foundation models and the impact of non-determinism on the outputs. All in all, this suggests a future direction in which disparate data management tasks can be unified under foundation models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09610v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moe Kayali, Anton Lykov, Ilias Fountalis, Nikolaos Vasiloglou, Dan Olteanu, Dan Suciu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IEPile: Unearthing Large-Scale Schema-Based Information Extraction Corpus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14710v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) demonstrate remarkable potential across various domains; however, they exhibit a significant performance gap in Information Extraction (IE). Note that high-quality instruction data is the vital key for enhancing the specific capabilities of LLMs, while current IE datasets tend to be small in scale, fragmented, and lack standardized schema. To this end, we introduce IEPile, a comprehensive bilingual (English and Chinese) IE instruction corpus, which contains approximately 0.32B tokens. We construct IEPile by collecting and cleaning 33 existing IE datasets, and introduce schema-based instruction generation to unearth a large-scale corpus. Experimental results on LLaMA, Baichuan and Qwen demonstrate that using IEPile can enhance the performance of LLMs for IE, especially the zero-shot generalization. We open-source the resource and pre-trained models, hoping to provide valuable support to the NLP community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14710v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Honghao Gui, Lin Yuan, Hongbin Ye, Ningyu Zhang, Mengshu Sun, Lei Liang, Huajun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Process Modeling With Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07541v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the realm of Business Process Management (BPM), process modeling plays a crucial role in translating complex process dynamics into comprehensible visual representations, facilitating the understanding, analysis, improvement, and automation of organizational processes. Traditional process modeling methods often require extensive expertise and can be time-consuming. This paper explores the integration of Large Language Models (LLMs) into process modeling to enhance the accessibility of process modeling, offering a more intuitive entry point for non-experts while augmenting the efficiency of experts. We propose a framework that leverages LLMs for the automated generation and iterative refinement of process models starting from textual descriptions. Our framework involves innovative prompting strategies for effective LLM utilization, along with a secure model generation protocol and an error-handling mechanism. Moreover, we instantiate a concrete system extending our framework. This system provides robust quality guarantees on the models generated and supports exporting them in standard modeling notations, such as the Business Process Modeling Notation (BPMN) and Petri nets. Preliminary results demonstrate the framework's ability to streamline process modeling tasks, underscoring the transformative potential of generative AI in the BPM field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07541v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Humam Kourani, Alessandro Berti, Daniel Schuster, Wil M. P. van der Aalst</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
