<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB</link>
    <description>cs.DB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 04:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Triadic First-Order Logic Queries in Temporal Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17215v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motif counting is a fundamental problem in network analysis, and there is a rich literature of theoretical and applied algorithms for this problem. Given a large input network $G$, a motif $H$ is a small "pattern" graph indicative of special local structure. Motif/pattern mining involves finding all matches of this pattern in the input $G$. The simplest, yet challenging, case of motif counting is when $H$ has three vertices, often called a "triadic" query. Recent work has focused on "temporal graph mining", where the network $G$ has edges with timestamps (and directions) and $H$ has time constraints.
  Inspired by concepts in logic and database theory, we introduce the study of "thresholded First Order Logic (FOL) Motif Analysis" for massive temporal networks. A typical triadic motif query asks for the existence of three vertices that form a desired temporal pattern. An "FOL" motif query is obtained by having both existential and thresholded universal quantifiers. This allows for query semantics that can mine richer information from networks. A typical triadic query would be "find all triples of vertices $u,v,w$ such that they form a triangle within one hour". A thresholded FOL query can express "find all pairs $u,v$ such that for half of $w$ where $(u,w)$ formed an edge, $(v,w)$ also formed an edge within an hour".
  We design the first algorithm, FOLTY, for mining thresholded FOL triadic queries. The theoretical running time of FOLTY matches the best known running time for temporal triangle counting in sparse graphs. We give an efficient implementation of FOLTY using specialized temporal data structures. FOLTY has excellent empirical behavior, and can answer triadic FOL queries on graphs with nearly 70M edges is less than hour on commodity hardware. Our work has the potential to start a new research direction in the classic well-studied problem of motif analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17215v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omkar Bhalerao, Yunjie Pan, C. Seshadhri, Nishil Talati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unfolding Data Quality Dimensions in Practice: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17507v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data quality describes the degree to which data meet specific requirements and are fit for use by humans and/or downstream tasks (e.g., artificial intelligence). Data quality can be assessed across multiple high-level concepts called dimensions, such as accuracy, completeness, consistency, or timeliness. While extensive research and several attempts for standardization (e.g., ISO/IEC 25012) exist for data quality dimensions, their practical application often remains unclear. In parallel to research endeavors, a large number of tools have been developed that implement functionalities for the detection and mitigation of specific data quality issues, such as missing values or outliers. With this paper, we aim to bridge this gap between data quality theory and practice by systematically connecting low-level functionalities offered by data quality tools with high-level dimensions, revealing their many-to-many relationships. Through an examination of seven open-source data quality tools, we provide a comprehensive mapping between their functionalities and the data quality dimensions, demonstrating how individual functionalities and their variants partially contribute to the assessment of single dimensions. This systematic survey provides both practitioners and researchers with a unified view on the fragmented landscape of data quality checks, offering actionable insights for quality assessment across multiple dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17507v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasileios Papastergios, Lisa Ehrlinger, Anastasios Gounaris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SHINE: A Scalable HNSW Index in Disaggregated Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Approximate nearest neighbor (ANN) search is a fundamental problem in computer science for which in-memory graph-based methods, such as Hierarchical Navigable Small World (HNSW), perform exceptionally well. To scale beyond billions of high-dimensional vectors, the index must be distributed. The disaggregated memory architecture physically separates compute and memory into two distinct hardware units and has become popular in modern data centers. Both units are connected via RDMA networks that allow compute nodes to directly access remote memory and perform all the computations, posing unique challenges for disaggregated indexes.
  In this work, we propose a scalable HNSW index for ANN search in disaggregated memory. In contrast to existing distributed approaches, which partition the graph at the cost of accuracy, our method builds a graph-preserving index that reaches the same accuracy as a single-machine HNSW. Continuously fetching high-dimensional vector data from remote memory leads to severe network bandwidth limitations, which we overcome by employing an efficient caching mechanism. Since answering a single query involves processing numerous unique graph nodes, caching alone is not sufficient to achieve high scalability. We logically combine the caches of the compute nodes to increase the overall cache effectiveness and confirm the efficiency and scalability of our method in our evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17647v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Widmoser, Daniel Kocher, Nikolaus Augsten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eco-Friendly AI: Unleashing Data Power for Green Federated Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17241v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The widespread adoption of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML) comes with a significant environmental impact, particularly in terms of energy consumption and carbon emissions. This pressing issue highlights the need for innovative solutions to mitigate AI's ecological footprint. One of the key factors influencing the energy consumption of ML model training is the size of the training dataset. ML models are often trained on vast amounts of data continuously generated by sensors and devices distributed across multiple locations. To reduce data transmission costs and enhance privacy, Federated Learning (FL) enables model training without the need to move or share raw data. While FL offers these advantages, it also introduces challenges due to the heterogeneity of data sources (related to volume and quality), computational node capabilities, and environmental impact.
  This paper contributes to the advancement of Green AI by proposing a data-centric approach to Green Federated Learning. Specifically, we focus on reducing FL's environmental impact by minimizing the volume of training data. Our methodology involves the analysis of the characteristics of federated datasets, the selecting of an optimal subset of data based on quality metrics, and the choice of the federated nodes with the lowest environmental impact. We develop a comprehensive methodology that examines the influence of data-centric factors, such as data quality and volume, on FL training performance and carbon emissions. Building on these insights, we introduce an interactive recommendation system that optimizes FL configurations through data reduction, minimizing environmental impact during training. Applying this methodology to time series classification has demonstrated promising results in reducing the environmental impact of FL tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17241v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Sabella, Monica Vitali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CQE under Epistemic Dependencies: Algorithms and Experiments (extended version)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17487v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate Controlled Query Evaluation (CQE) over ontologies, where information disclosure is regulated by epistemic dependencies (EDs), a family of logical rules recently proposed for the CQE framework. In particular, we combine EDs with the notion of optimal GA censors, i.e. maximal sets of ground atoms that are entailed by the ontology and can be safely revealed. We focus on answering Boolean unions of conjunctive queries (BUCQs) with respect to the intersection of all optimal GA censors - an approach that has been shown in other contexts to ensure strong security guarantees with favorable computational behavior. First, we characterize the security of this intersection-based approach and identify a class of EDs (namely, full EDs) for which it remains safe. Then, for a subclass of EDs and for DL-Lite_R ontologies, we show that answering BUCQs in the above CQE semantics is in AC^0 in data complexity by presenting a suitable, detailed first-order rewriting algorithm. Finally, we report on experiments conducted in two different evaluation scenarios, showing the practical feasibility of our rewriting function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17487v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Marconi, Flavia Ricci, Riccardo Rosati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric Private Information Retrieval (SPIR) on Graph-Based Replicated Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17736v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the problem of symmetric private information retrieval (SPIR) on replicated databases modeled by a simple graph. In this model, each vertex corresponds to a server, and a message is replicated on two servers if and only if there is an edge between them. We consider the setting where the server-side common randomness necessary to accomplish SPIR is also replicated at the servers according to the graph, and we call this as message-specific common randomness. In this setting, we establish a lower bound on the SPIR capacity, i.e., the maximum download rate, for general graphs, by proposing an achievable SPIR scheme. Next, we prove that, for any SPIR scheme to be feasible, the minimum size of message-specific randomness should be equal to the size of a message. Finally, by providing matching upper bounds, we derive the exact SPIR capacity for the class of path and regular graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17736v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreya Meel, Sennur Ulukus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ResidualPlanner+: a scalable matrix mechanism for marginals and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.08175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.08175v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Noisy marginals are a common form of confidentiality protecting data release and are useful for many downstream tasks such as contingency table analysis, construction of Bayesian networks, and even synthetic data generation. Privacy mechanisms that provide unbiased noisy answers to linear queries (such as marginals) are known as matrix mechanisms.
  We propose ResidualPlanner and ResidualPlanner+, two highly scalable matrix mechanisms. ResidualPlanner is both optimal and scalable for answering marginal queries with Gaussian noise, while ResidualPlanner+ provides support for more general workloads, such as combinations of marginals and range queries or prefix-sum queries. ResidualPlanner can optimize for many loss functions that can be written as a convex function of marginal variances (prior work was restricted to just one predefined objective function). ResidualPlanner can optimize the accuracy of marginals in large scale settings in seconds, even when the previous state of the art (HDMM) runs out of memory. It even runs on datasets with 100 attributes in a couple of minutes. Furthermore, ResidualPlanner can efficiently compute variance/covariance values for each marginal (prior methods quickly run out of memory, even for relatively small datasets).
  ResidualPlanner+ provides support for more complex workloads that combine marginal and range/prefix-sum queries (e.g., a marginal on race, a range query on age, and a combined race/age tabulation that answers age range queries for each race). It even supports custom user-defined workloads on different attributes. With this added flexibility, ResidualPlanner+ is not necessarily optimal, however it is still extremely scalable and outperforms the prior state-of-the-art (HDMM) on prefix-sum queries both in terms of accuracy and speed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.08175v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingtai Xiao, Guanlin He, Levent Toksoz, Zeyu Ding, Danfeng Zhang, Daniel Kifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum Inner Product is Query-Scaled Nearest Neighbor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06882v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Maximum Inner Product Search (MIPS) for high-dimensional vectors is pivotal across databases, information retrieval, and artificial intelligence. Existing methods either reduce MIPS to Nearest Neighbor Search (NNS) while suffering from harmful vector space transformations, or attempt to tackle MIPS directly but struggle to mitigate redundant computations due to the absence of the triangle inequality. This paper presents a novel theoretical framework that equates MIPS with NNS without requiring space transformation, thereby allowing us to leverage advanced graph-based indices for NNS and efficient edge pruning strategies, significantly reducing unnecessary computations. Despite a strong baseline set by our theoretical analysis, we identify and address two persistent challenges to further refine our method: the introduction of the Proximity Graph with Spherical Pathway (PSP), designed to mitigate the issue of MIPS solutions clustering around large-norm vectors, and the implementation of Adaptive Early Termination (AET), which efficiently curtails the excessive exploration once an accuracy bottleneck is reached. Extensive experiments reveal the superiority of our method over existing state-of-the-art techniques in search efficiency, scalability, and practical applicability. Compared with state-of-the-art graph based methods, it achieves an average 35% speed-up in query processing and a 3x reduction in index size. Notably, our approach has been validated and deployed in the search engines of Shopee, a well-known online shopping platform. Our code and an industrial-scale dataset for offline evaluation will also be released to address the absence of e-commerce data in public benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06882v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tingyang Chen, Cong Fu, Kun Wang, Xiangyu Ke, Yunjun Gao, Wenchao Zhou, Yabo Ni, Anxiang Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stitching Inner Product and Euclidean Metrics for Topology-aware Maximum Inner Product Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14861v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Maximum Inner Product Search (MIPS) is a fundamental challenge in machine learning and information retrieval, particularly in high-dimensional data applications. Existing approaches to MIPS either rely solely on Inner Product (IP) similarity, which faces issues with local optima and redundant computations, or reduce the MIPS problem to the Nearest Neighbor Search under the Euclidean metric via space projection, leading to topology destruction and information loss. Despite the divergence of the two paradigms, we argue that there is no inherent binary opposition between IP and Euclidean metrics. By stitching IP and Euclidean in the design of indexing and search algorithms, we can significantly enhance MIPS performance. Specifically, this paper explores the theoretical and empirical connections between these two metrics from the MIPS perspective. Our investigation, grounded in graph-based search, reveals that different indexing and search strategies offer distinct advantages for MIPS, depending on the underlying data topology. Building on these insights, we introduce a novel graph-based index called Metric-Amphibious Graph (MAG) and a corresponding search algorithm, Adaptive Navigation with Metric Switch (ANMS). To facilitate parameter tuning for optimal performance, we identify three statistical indicators that capture essential data topology properties and correlate strongly with parameter tuning. Extensive experiments on 12 real-world datasets demonstrate that MAG outperforms existing state-of-the-art methods, achieving up to 4x search speedup while maintaining adaptability and scalability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14861v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tingyang Chen, Cong Fu, Xiangyu Ke, Yunjun Gao, Yabo Ni, Anxiang Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conflict Detection for Temporal Knowledge Graphs:A Fast Constraint Mining Algorithm and New Benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11053v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Temporal facts, which are used to describe events that occur during specific time periods, have become a topic of increased interest in the field of knowledge graph (KG) research. In terms of quality management, the introduction of time restrictions brings new challenges to maintaining the temporal consistency of KGs. Previous studies rely on manually enumerated temporal constraints to detect conflicts, which are labor-intensive and may have granularity issues. To address this problem, we start from the common pattern of temporal facts and propose a pattern-based temporal constraint mining method, PaTeCon. Unlike previous studies, PaTeCon uses graph patterns and statistical information relevant to the given KG to automatically generate temporal constraints, without the need for human experts. In this paper, we illustrate how this method can be optimized to achieve significant speed improvement. We also annotate Wikidata and Freebase to build two new benchmarks for conflict detection. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our pattern-based automatic constraint mining approach is highly effective in generating valuable temporal constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11053v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianhao Chen, Junyang Ren, Wentao Ding, Haoyuan Ouyang, Wei Hu, Yuzhong Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Querying Graph-Relational Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16089v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For applications that store structured data in relational databases, there is an impedance mismatch between the flat representations encouraged by relational data models and the deeply nested information that applications expect to receive. In this work, we present the graph-relational database model, which provides a flexible, compositional, and strongly-typed solution to this "object-relational mismatch." We formally define the graph-relational database model and present a static and dynamic semantics for queries. In addition, we discuss the realization of the graph-relational database model in EdgeQL, a general-purpose SQL-style query language, and the Gel system, which compiles EdgeQL schemas and queries into PostgreSQL queries. Gel facilitates the kind of object-shaped data manipulation that is frequently provided inefficiently by object-relational mapping (ORM) technologies, while achieving most of the efficiency that comes from writing complex PostgreSQL queries directly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16089v2</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Sullivan, Zhibo Chen, Elvis Pranskevichus, Robert J. Simmons, Victor Petrovykh, Alja\v{z} Mur Er\v{z}en, Yury Selivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
