<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB</link>
    <description>cs.DB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble Threshold Calibration for Stable Sensitivity Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02116v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precise recall control is critical in large-scale spatial conflation and entity-matching tasks, where missing even a few true matches can break downstream analytics, while excessive manual review inflates cost. Classical confidence-interval cuts such as Clopper-Pearson or Wilson provide lower bounds on recall, but they routinely overshoot the target by several percentage points and exhibit high run-to-run variance under skewed score distributions. We present an end-to-end framework that achieves exact recall with sub-percent variance over tens of millions of geometry pairs, while remaining TPU-friendly. Our pipeline starts with an equigrid bounding-box filter and compressed sparse row (CSR) candidate representation, reducing pair enumeration by two orders of magnitude. A deterministic xxHash bootstrap sample trains a lightweight neural ranker; its scores are propagated to all remaining pairs via a single forward pass and used to construct a reproducible, score-decile-stratified calibration set. Four complementary threshold estimators - Clopper-Pearson, Jeffreys, Wilson, and an exact quantile - are aggregated via inverse-variance weighting, then fused across nine independent subsamples. This ensemble reduces threshold variance compared to any single method. Evaluated on two real cadastral datasets (approximately 6.31M and 67.34M pairs), our approach consistently hits a recall target within a small error, decreases redundant verifications relative to other calibrations, and runs end-to-end on a single TPU v3 core.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02116v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John N. Daras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GeoSQL-Eval: First Evaluation of LLMs on PostGIS-Based NL2GeoSQL Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25264v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have shown strong performance in natural language to SQL (NL2SQL) tasks within general databases. However, extending to GeoSQL introduces additional complexity from spatial data types, function invocation, and coordinate systems, which greatly increases generation and execution difficulty. Existing benchmarks mainly target general SQL, and a systematic evaluation framework for GeoSQL is still lacking. To fill this gap, we present GeoSQL-Eval, the first end-to-end automated evaluation framework for PostGIS query generation, together with GeoSQL-Bench, a benchmark for assessing LLM performance in NL2GeoSQL tasks. GeoSQL-Bench defines three task categories-conceptual understanding, syntax-level SQL generation, and schema retrieval-comprising 14,178 instances, 340 PostGIS functions, and 82 thematic databases. GeoSQL-Eval is grounded in Webb's Depth of Knowledge (DOK) model, covering four cognitive dimensions, five capability levels, and twenty task types to establish a comprehensive process from knowledge acquisition and syntax generation to semantic alignment, execution accuracy, and robustness. We evaluate 24 representative models across six categories and apply the entropy weight method with statistical analyses to uncover performance differences, common error patterns, and resource usage. Finally, we release a public GeoSQL-Eval leaderboard platform for continuous testing and global comparison. This work extends the NL2GeoSQL paradigm and provides a standardized, interpretable, and extensible framework for evaluating LLMs in spatial database contexts, offering valuable references for geospatial information science and related applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25264v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuyang Hou, Haoyue Jiao, Ziqi Liu, Lutong Xie, Guanyu Chen, Shaowen Wu, Xuefeng Guan, Huayi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EMR-AGENT: Automating Cohort and Feature Extraction from EMR Databases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00549v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Machine learning models for clinical prediction rely on structured data extracted from Electronic Medical Records (EMRs), yet this process remains dominated by hardcoded, database-specific pipelines for cohort definition, feature selection, and code mapping. These manual efforts limit scalability, reproducibility, and cross-institutional generalization. To address this, we introduce EMR-AGENT (Automated Generalized Extraction and Navigation Tool), an agent-based framework that replaces manual rule writing with dynamic, language model-driven interaction to extract and standardize structured clinical data. Our framework automates cohort selection, feature extraction, and code mapping through interactive querying of databases. Our modular agents iteratively observe query results and reason over schema and documentation, using SQL not just for data retrieval but also as a tool for database observation and decision making. This eliminates the need for hand-crafted, schema-specific logic. To enable rigorous evaluation, we develop a benchmarking codebase for three EMR databases (MIMIC-III, eICU, SICdb), including both seen and unseen schema settings. Our results demonstrate strong performance and generalization across these databases, highlighting the feasibility of automating a process previously thought to require expert-driven design. The code will be released publicly at https://github.com/AITRICS/EMR-AGENT/tree/main. For a demonstration, please visit our anonymous demo page: https://anonymoususer-max600.github.io/EMR_AGENT/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00549v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kwanhyung Lee, Sungsoo Hong, Joonhyung Park, Jeonghyeop Lim, Juhwan Choi, Donghwee Yoon, Eunho Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting Answers to Unions of Conjunctive Queries: Natural Tractability Criteria and Meta-Complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.10634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.10634v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the problem of counting answers to unions of conjunctive queries (UCQs) under structural restrictions on the input query. Concretely, given a class C of UCQs, the problem #UCQ(C) provides as input a UCQ Q in C and a database D and the problem is to compute the number of answers of Q in D.
  Chen and Mengel [PODS'16] have shown that for any recursively enumerable class C, the problem #UCQ(C) is either fixed-parameter tractable or hard for one of the parameterised complexity classes W[1] or #W[1]. However, their tractability criterion is unwieldy in the sense that, given any concrete class C of UCQs, it is not easy to determine how hard it is to count answers to queries in C. Moreover, given a single specific UCQ Q, it is not easy to determine how hard it is to count answers to Q.
  In this work, we address the question of finding a natural tractability criterion: The combined conjunctive query of a UCQ $\varphi_1 \vee \dots \vee \varphi_\ell$ is the conjunctive query $\varphi_1 \wedge \dots \wedge \varphi_\ell$. We show that under natural closure properties of C, the problem #UCQ(C) is fixed-parameter tractable if and only if the combined conjunctive queries of UCQs in C, and their contracts, have bounded treewidth. A contract of a conjunctive query is an augmented structure, taking into account how the quantified variables are connected to the free variables. If all variables are free, then a conjunctive query is equal to its contract; in this special case the criterion for fixed-parameter tractability of #UCQ(C) thus simplifies to the combined queries having bounded treewidth.
  Finally, we give evidence that a closure property on C is necessary for obtaining a natural tractability criterion: We show that even for a single UCQ Q, the meta problem of deciding whether #UCQ({Q}) can be solved in time $O(|D|^d)$ is NP-hard for any fixed $d\geq 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.10634v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Focke, Leslie Ann Goldberg, Marc Roth, Stanislav \v{Z}ivn\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Handling Heterophily in Recommender Systems with Wavelet Hypergraph Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14399v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recommender systems are pivotal in delivering personalised user experiences across various domains. However, capturing the heterophily patterns and the multi-dimensional nature of user-item interactions poses significant challenges. To address this, we introduce FWHDNN (Fusion-based Wavelet Hypergraph Diffusion Neural Networks), an innovative framework aimed at advancing representation learning in hypergraph-based recommendation tasks. The model incorporates three key components: (1) a cross-difference relation encoder leveraging heterophily-aware hypergraph diffusion to adapt message-passing for diverse class labels, (2) a multi-level cluster-wise encoder employing wavelet transform-based hypergraph neural network layers to capture multi-scale topological relationships, and (3) an integrated multi-modal fusion mechanism that combines structural and textual information through intermediate and late-fusion strategies. Extensive experiments on real-world datasets demonstrate that FWHDNN surpasses state-of-the-art methods in accuracy, robustness, and scalability in capturing high-order interconnections between users and items.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14399v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darnbi Sakong, Thanh Tam Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
