<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 01:47:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of the Electromagnetic Dalitz Transition $h_c \rightarrow e^+e^-\eta_c$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using $(27.12\pm 0.14)\times10^8$ $\psi(3686)$ decays and data samples of $e^+e^-$ collisions with $\sqrt{s}$ from 4.130 to 4.780~GeV collected with the BESIII detector, we report the first observation of the electromagnetic Dalitz transition $h_c\to e^+e^-\eta_c$ with a statistical significance of $5.4\sigma$. We measure the ratio of the branching fractions $\frac{\mathcal{B}(h_c\rightarrow e^+e^-\eta_c)}{\mathcal{B}(h_c\rightarrow \gamma \eta_c)}$ separately for the $h_c$ samples produced via $\psi(3686)\to\pi^0h_c$ and $e^+e^-\to\pi^+\pi^-h_c$. The average ratio is determined to be $(0.59\pm0.10(\text{stat.})\pm0.04(\text{syst.}))\%$, where the uncertainty includes both statistical and systematic components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00136v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> BESIII Collaboration, M. Ablikim, M. N. Achasov, P. Adlarson, S. Ahmed, M. Albrecht, R. Aliberti, A. Amoroso, M. R. An, Q. An, X. H. Bai, Y. Bai, O. Bakina, R. Baldini Ferroli, I. Balossino, Y. Ban, K. Begzsuren, N. Berger, M. Bertani, D. Bettoni, F. Bianchi, J. Bloms, A. Bortone, I. Boyko, R. A. Briere, H. Cai, X. Cai, A. Calcaterra, G. F. Cao, N. Cao, S. A. Cetin, J. F. Chang, W. L. Chang, G. Chelkov, D. Y. Chen, G. Chen, H. S. Chen, M. L. Chen, S. J. Chen, X. R. Chen, Y. B. Chen, Z. J Chen, W. S. Cheng, G. Cibinetto, F. Cossio, X. F. Cui, H. L. Dai, X. C. Dai, A. Dbeyssi, R. E. de Boer, D. Dedovich, Z. Y. Deng, A. Denig, I. Denysenko, M. Destefanis, F. De Mori, Y. Ding, C. Dong, J. Dong, L. Y. Dong, M. Y. Dong, X. Dong, S. X. Du, Y. L. Fan, J. Fang, S. S. Fang, Y. Fang, R. Farinelli, L. Fava, F. Feldbauer, G. Felici, C. Q. Feng, J. H. Feng, M. Fritsch, C. D. Fu, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. G. Gao, I. Garzia, P. T. Ge, C. Geng, E. M. Gersabeck, A Gilman, K. Goetzen, L. Gong, W. X. Gong, W. Gradl, M. Greco, L. M. Gu, M. H. Gu, S. Gu, Y. T. Gu, C. Y Guan, A. Q. Guo, L. B. Guo, R. P. Guo, Y. P. Guo, A. Guskov, T. T. Han, W. Y. Han, X. Q. Hao, F. A. Harris, N H\"usken, K. L. He, F. H. Heinsius, C. H. Heinz, T. Held, Y. K. Heng, C. Herold, M. Himmelreich, T. Holtmann, Y. R. Hou, Z. L. Hou, H. M. Hu, J. F. Hu, T. Hu, Y. Hu, G. S. Huang, L. Q. Huang, X. T. Huang, Y. P. Huang, Z. Huang, T. Hussain, W. Ikegami Andersson, W. Imoehl, M. Irshad, S. Jaeger, S. Janchiv, Q. Ji, Q. P. Ji, X. B. Ji, X. L. Ji, Y. Y. Ji, H. B. Jiang, X. S. Jiang, J. B. Jiao, Z. Jiao, S. Jin, Y. Jin, T. Johansson, N. Kalantar-Nayestanaki, X. S. Kang, R. Kappert, M. Kavatsyuk, B. C. Ke, I. K. Keshk, A. Khoukaz, P. Kiese, R. Kiuchi, R. Kliemt, L. Koch, O. B. Kolcu, B. Kopf, M. Kuemmel, M. Kuessner, A. Kupsc, M. G. Kurth, W. K\"uhn, J. J. Lane, J. S. Lange, P. Larin, A. Lavania, L. Lavezzi, Z. H. Lei, H. Leithoff, M. Lellmann, T. Lenz, C. Li, C. H. Li, Cheng Li, D. M. Li, F. Li, G. Li, H. Li, H. Li, H. B. Li, H. J. Li, H. J. Li, J. L. Li, J. Q. Li, J. S. Li, Ke Li, L. K. Li, Lei Li, P. R. Li, S. Y. Li, W. D. Li, W. G. Li, X. H. Li, X. L. Li, Xiaoyu Li, Z. Y. Li, H. Liang, H. Liang, H. Liang, Y. F. Liang, Y. T. Liang, G. R. Liao, L. Z. Liao, J. Libby, C. X. Lin, B. J. Liu, C. X. Liu, D. Liu, F. H. Liu, Fang Liu, Feng Liu, H. B. Liu, H. M. Liu, Huanhuan Liu, Huihui Liu, J. B. Liu, J. L. Liu, J. Y. Liu, K. Liu, K. Y. Liu, Ke Liu, L. Liu, M. H. Liu, P. L. Liu, Q. Liu, Q. Liu, S. B. Liu, Shuai Liu, T. Liu, W. M. Liu, X. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. B. Liu, Z. A. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, X. C. Lou, F. X. Lu, F. X. Lu, H. J. Lu, J. D. Lu, J. G. Lu, X. L. Lu, Y. Lu, Y. P. Lu, C. L. Luo, M. X. Luo, P. W. Luo, T. Luo, X. L. Luo, S. Lusso, X. R. Lyu, F. C. Ma, H. L. Ma, L. L. Ma, M. M. Ma, Q. M. Ma, R. Q. Ma, R. T. Ma, X. X. Ma, X. Y. Ma, F. E. Maas, M. Maggiora, S. Maldaner, S. Malde, Q. A. Malik, A. Mangoni, Y. J. Mao, Z. P. Mao, S. Marcello, Z. X. Meng, J. G. Messchendorp, G. Mezzadri, T. J. Min, R. E. Mitchell, X. H. Mo, Y. J. Mo, N. Yu. Muchnoi, H. Muramatsu, S. Nakhoul, Y. Nefedov, F. Nerling, I. B. Nikolaev, Z. Ning, S. Nisar, S. L. Olsen, Q. Ouyang, S. Pacetti, X. Pan, Y. Pan, A. Pathak, P. Patteri, M. Pelizaeus, H. P. Peng, K. Peters, J. Pettersson, J. L. Ping, R. G. Ping, R. Poling, V. Prasad, H. Qi, H. R. Qi, K. H. Qi, M. Qi, T. Y. Qi, T. Y. Qi, S. Qian, W. B. Qian, Z. Qian, C. F. Qiao, L. Q. Qin, X. P. Qin, X. S. Qin, Z. H. Qin, J. F. Qiu, S. Q. Qu, K. H. Rashid, K. Ravindran, C. F. Redmer, A. Rivetti, V. Rodin, M. Rolo, G. Rong, Ch. Rosner, M. Rump, H. S. Sang, A. Sarantsev, Y. Schelhaas, C. Schnier, K. Schoenning, M. Scodeggio, D. C. Shan, W. Shan, X. Y. Shan, J. F. Shangguan, M. Shao, C. P. Shen, P. X. Shen, X. Y. Shen, H. C. Shi, R. S. Shi, X. Shi, X. D Shi, J. J. Song, W. M. Song, Y. X. Song, S. Sosio, S. Spataro, K. X. Su, P. P. Su, F. F. Sui, G. X. Sun, H. K. Sun, J. F. Sun, L. Sun, S. S. Sun, T. Sun, W. Y. Sun, W. Y. Sun, X Sun, Y. J. Sun, Y. K. Sun, Y. Z. Sun, Z. T. Sun, Y. H. Tan, Y. X. Tan, C. J. Tang, G. Y. Tang, J. Tang, J. X. Teng, V. Thoren, Y. T. Tian, I. Uman, B. Wang, C. W. Wang, D. Y. Wang, H. J. Wang, H. P. Wang, K. Wang, L. L. Wang, M. Wang, M. Z. Wang, Meng Wang, W. Wang, W. H. Wang, W. P. Wang, X. Wang, X. F. Wang, X. L. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. D. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. Q. Wang, Y. Y. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Y. Wang, Ziyi Wang, Zongyuan Wang, D. H. Wei, P. Weidenkaff, F. Weidner, S. P. Wen, D. J. White, U. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. Wolke, L. Wollenberg, J. F. Wu, L. H. Wu, L. J. Wu, X. Wu, Z. Wu, L. Xia, H. Xiao, S. Y. Xiao, Z. J. Xiao, X. H. Xie, Y. G. Xie, Y. H. Xie, T. Y. Xing, G. F. Xu, Q. J. Xu, W. Xu, X. P. Xu, Y. C. Xu, F. Yan, L. Yan, W. B. Yan, W. C. Yan, Xu Yan, H. J. Yang, H. X. Yang, L. Yang, S. L. Yang, Y. X. Yang, Yifan Yang, Zhi Yang, M. Ye, M. H. Ye, J. H. Yin, Z. Y. You, B. X. Yu, C. X. Yu, G. Yu, J. S. Yu, T. Yu, C. Z. Yuan, L. Yuan, X. Q. Yuan, Y. Yuan, Z. Y. Yuan, C. X. Yue, A. Yuncu, A. A. Zafar, Y. Zeng, B. X. Zhang, Guangyi Zhang, H. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. Y. Zhang, J. J. Zhang, J. L. Zhang, J. Q. Zhang, J. W. Zhang, J. Y. Zhang, J. Z. Zhang, Jianyu Zhang, Jiawei Zhang, L. M. Zhang, L. Q. Zhang, Lei Zhang, S. Zhang, S. F. Zhang, Shulei Zhang, X. D. Zhang, X. Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. H. Zhang, Y. T. Zhang, Yan Zhang, Yao Zhang, Yi Zhang, Z. H. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, G. Zhao, J. Zhao, J. Y. Zhao, J. Z. Zhao, Lei Zhao, Ling Zhao, M. G. Zhao, Q. Zhao, S. J. Zhao, Y. B. Zhao, Y. X. Zhao, Z. G. Zhao, A. Zhemchugov, B. Zheng, J. P. Zheng, W. J. Zheng, Y. Zheng, Y. H. Zheng, B. Zhong, C. Zhong, L. P. Zhou, Q. Zhou, X. Zhou, X. K. Zhou, X. R. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, A. N. Zhu, J. Zhu, K. Zhu, K. J. Zhu, S. H. Zhu, T. J. Zhu, W. J. Zhu, W. J. Zhu, Y. C. Zhu, Z. A. Zhu, B. S. Zou, J. H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of $\chi_{bJ}(2P)\to\omega\Upsilon(1S)$ at Belle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a study of the hadronic transitions $\chi_{bJ}(2P)\to\omega\Upsilon(1S)$, with $\omega\to\pi^{+}\pi^{-}\pi^{0}$, using $28.2\times10^6~\Upsilon(3S)$ mesons recorded by the Belle detector. We present the first evidence for the near--threshold transition $\chi_{b0}(2P)\to\omega\Upsilon(1S)$, the analog of the charm sector decay $\chi_{c1}(3872)\to\omega J/\psi$, with a branching fraction of $\mathcal{B}\big(\chi_{b0}(2P)\to\omega\Upsilon(1S)\big) = \big(0.55\pm0.19\pm0.07\big)\%$. We also obtain branching fractions of $\mathcal{B}\big(\chi_{b1}(2P)\to\omega\Upsilon(1S)\big) = \big(2.39{}^{+0.20}_{-0.19}\pm0.24\big)\%$ and $\mathcal{B}\big(\chi_{b2}(2P)\to\omega\Upsilon(1S)\big) = \big(0.47{}^{+0.13}_{-0.12}\pm0.06\big)\%$, confirming the measurement of the $\omega$ transitions of the $J=1,2~P$--wave states. The ratio for the $J=2$ to $J=1$ transitions is also measured and found to differ by 3.3 standard deviations from the expected value in the QCD multipole expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00879v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. S. Stottler, T. K. Pedlar, B. G. Fulsom, I. Adachi, K. Adamczyk, H. Aihara, S. Al Said, D. M. Asner, H. Atmacan, T. Aushev, R. Ayad, V. Babu, Sw. Banerjee, M. Bauer, P. Behera, K. Belous, J. Bennett, F. Bernlochner, M. Bessner, T. Bilka, D. Biswas, A. Bobrov, D. Bodrov, G. Bonvicini, J. Borah, A. Bozek, M. Bra\v{c}ko, P. Branchini, T. E. Browder, A. Budano, M. Campajola, L. Cao, D. \v{C}ervenkov, M. -C. Chang, B. G. Cheon, K. Chilikin, H. E. Cho, K. Cho, S. -K. Choi, Y. Choi, S. Choudhury, D. Cinabro, S. Das, G. De Nardo, G. De Pietro, R. Dhamija, F. Di Capua, Z. Dole\v{z}al, T. V. Dong, S. Dubey, P. Ecker, D. Epifanov, T. Ferber, D. Ferlewicz, V. Gaur, A. Garmash, A. Giri, P. Goldenzweig, E. Graziani, T. Gu, Y. Guan, K. Gudkova, C. Hadjivasiliou, T. Hara, K. Hayasaka, S. Hazra, M. T. Hedges, D. Herrmann, W. -S. Hou, C. -L. Hsu, K. Inami, N. Ipsita, A. Ishikawa, R. Itoh, M. Iwasaki, Y. Iwasaki, W. W. Jacobs, S. Jia, Y. Jin, A. B. Kaliyar, T. Kawasaki, C. Kiesling, C. H. Kim, D. Y. Kim, K. -H. Kim, Y. -K. Kim, P. Kody\v{s}, A. Korobov, S. Korpar, E. Kovalenko, P. Kri\v{z}an, P. Krokovny, T. Kuhr, M. Kumar, R. Kumar, K. Kumara, A. Kuzmin, Y. -J. Kwon, Y. -T. Lai, T. Lam, M. Laurenza, S. C. Lee, D. Levit, P. Lewis, L. K. Li, J. Libby, K. Lieret, D. Liventsev, T. Luo, Y. Ma, M. Masuda, S. K. Maurya, F. Meier, M. Merola, K. Miyabayashi, G. B. Mohanty, R. Mussa, I. Nakamura, M. Nakao, A. Natochii, L. Nayak, N. K. Nisar, S. Nishida, K. Ogawa, S. Ogawa, H. Ono, P. Oskin, P. Pakhlov, G. Pakhlova, T. Pang, S. Pardi, J. Park, S. -H. Park, S. Patra, S. Paul, R. Pestotnik, L. E. Piilonen, T. Podobnik, E. Prencipe, M. T. Prim, N. Rout, G. Russo, S. Sandilya, A. Sangal, L. Santelj, V. Savinov, G. Schnell, C. Schwanda, Y. Seino, K. Senyo, W. Shan, M. Shapkin, C. Sharma, J. -G. Shiu, A. Sokolov, E. Solovieva, M. Stari\v{c}, M. Sumihama, W. Sutcliffe, M. Takizawa, U. Tamponi, K. Tanida, F. Tenchini, R. Tiwary, M. Uchida, Y. Unno, S. Uno, S. E. Vahsen, G. Varner, D. Wang, E. Wang, M. -Z. Wang, S. Watanuki, O. Werbycka, E. Won, B. D. Yabsley, W. Yan, J. H. Yin, C. Z. Yuan, L. Yuan, Y. Yusa, Z. P. Zhang, V. Zhilich, V. Zhukova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the integrated luminosity of data samples collected during 2019-2022 by the Belle II experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A series of data samples was collected with the Belle II detector at the SuperKEKB collider from March 2019 to June 2022. We determine the integrated luminosities of these data samples using three distinct methodologies involving Bhabha ($e^+e^- \to e^+e^-(n\gamma)$), digamma ($e^+e^- \to \gamma\gamma(n\gamma)$), and dimuon ($e^+e^- \to \mu^+ \mu^- (n\gamma)$) events. The total integrated luminosity obtained with Bhabha, digamma, and dimuon events is (426.52 $\pm$ 0.03 $\pm$ 2.48)~fb$^{-1}$, (427.32 $\pm$ 0.03 $\pm$ 2.56)~fb$^{-1}$, and (424.84 $\pm$ 0.04 $\pm$ 3.88)~fb$^{-1}$, where the first uncertainties are statistical and the second are systematic. The resulting total integrated luminosity obtained from the combination of the three methods is (426.88 $\pm$ 1.93)~fb$^{-1}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00965v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> The Belle II Collaboration, I. Adachi, L. Aggarwal, H. Ahmed, J. K. Ahn, H. Aihara, N. Akopov, A. Aloisio, N. Althubiti, N. Anh Ky, D. M. Asner, H. Atmacan, T. Aushev, V. Aushev, M. Aversano, R. Ayad, V. Babu, H. Bae, S. Bahinipati, P. Bambade, Sw. Banerjee, M. Barrett, J. Baudot, A. Baur, A. Beaubien, F. Becherer, J. Becker, J. V. Bennett, F. U. Bernlochner, V. Bertacchi, M. Bertemes, E. Bertholet, M. Bessner, S. Bettarini, B. Bhuyan, F. Bianchi, L. Bierwirth, T. Bilka, D. Biswas, A. Bobrov, D. Bodrov, J. Borah, A. Boschetti, A. Bozek, P. Branchini, T. E. Browder, A. Budano, S. Bussino, Q. Campagna, M. Campajola, L. Cao, G. Casarosa, C. Cecchi, J. Cerasoli, M. -C. Chang, P. Chang, R. Cheaib, P. Cheema, B. G. Cheon, K. Chilikin, K. Chirapatpimol, H. -E. Cho, K. Cho, S. -J. Cho, S. -K. Choi, S. Choudhury, J. Cochran, L. Corona, J. X. Cui, S. Das, E. De La Cruz-Burelo, S. A. De La Motte, G. de Marino, G. De Nardo, G. De Pietro, R. de Sangro, M. Destefanis, S. Dey, R. Dhamija, A. Di Canto, F. Di Capua, J. Dingfelder, Z. Dole\v{z}al, I. Dom\'inguez Jim\'enez, T. V. Dong, K. Dort, D. Dossett, S. Dubey, K. Dugic, G. Dujany, P. Ecker, D. Epifanov, J. Eppelt, P. Feichtinger, T. Ferber, T. Fillinger, C. Finck, G. Finocchiaro, A. Fodor, F. Forti, A. Frey, B. G. Fulsom, A. Gabrielli, E. Ganiev, M. Garcia-Hernandez, R. Garg, G. Gaudino, V. Gaur, A. Gaz, A. Gellrich, G. Ghevondyan, D. Ghosh, H. Ghumaryan, G. Giakoustidis, R. Giordano, A. Giri, P. Gironella, B. Gobbo, R. Godang, O. Gogota, P. Goldenzweig, W. Gradl, E. Graziani, D. Greenwald, Z. Gruberov\'a, T. Gu, K. Gudkova, I. Haide, S. Halder, Y. Han, K. Hara, T. Hara, C. Harris, K. Hayasaka, H. Hayashii, S. Hazra, C. Hearty, M. T. Hedges, A. Heidelbach, I. Heredia de la Cruz, M. Hern\'andez Villanueva, T. Higuchi, M. Hoek, M. Hohmann, R. Hoppe, P. Horak, C. -L. Hsu, T. Humair, K. Inami, N. Ipsita, A. Ishikawa, R. Itoh, M. Iwasaki, W. W. Jacobs, D. E. Jaffe, E. -J. Jang, Q. P. Ji, S. Jia, Y. Jin, A. Johnson, K. K. Joo, H. Junkerkalefeld, M. Kaleta, D. Kalita, J. Kandra, K. H. Kang, G. Karyan, T. Kawasaki, F. Keil, C. Kiesling, C. -H. Kim, D. Y. Kim, J. -Y. Kim, K. -H. Kim, Y. -K. Kim, Y. J. Kim, H. Kindo, K. Kinoshita, P. Kody\v{s}, T. Koga, S. Kohani, K. Kojima, A. Korobov, S. Korpar, E. Kovalenko, R. Kowalewski, P. Kri\v{z}an, P. Krokovny, T. Kuhr, R. Kumar, K. Kumara, A. Kuzmin, Y. -J. Kwon, S. Lacaprara, Y. -T. Lai, K. Lalwani, T. Lam, L. Lanceri, J. S. Lange, M. Laurenza, K. Lautenbach, R. Leboucher, M. J. Lee, C. Lemettais, P. Leo, D. Levit, P. M. Lewis, C. Li, L. K. Li, S. X. Li, W. Z. Li, Y. Li, Y. B. Li, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, J. Lin, M. H. Liu, Q. Y. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, D. Liventsev, S. Longo, T. Lueck, C. Lyu, Y. Ma, M. Maggiora, S. P. Maharana, R. Maiti, S. Maity, G. Mancinelli, R. Manfredi, E. Manoni, M. Mantovano, D. Marcantonio, S. Marcello, C. Marinas, C. Martellini, A. Martens, A. Martini, T. Martinov, L. Massaccesi, M. Masuda, K. Matsuoka, D. Matvienko, S. K. Maurya, J. A. McKenna, R. Mehta, F. Meier, M. Merola, C. Miller, M. Mirra, S. Mitra, K. Miyabayashi, G. B. Mohanty, S. Mondal, S. Moneta, H. -G. Moser, R. Mussa, I. Nakamura, M. Nakao, Y. Nakazawa, M. Naruki, D. Narwal, Z. Natkaniec, A. Natochii, M. Nayak, G. Nazaryan, M. Neu, C. Niebuhr, S. Nishida, S. Ogawa, Y. Onishchuk, H. Ono, P. Pakhlov, G. Pakhlova, E. Paoloni, S. Pardi, K. Parham, H. Park, J. Park, K. Park, S. -H. Park, B. Paschen, A. Passeri, S. Patra, T. K. Pedlar, R. Peschke, R. Pestotnik, G. Pinna Angioni, P. L. M. Podesta-Lerma, T. Podobnik, S. Pokharel, C. Praz, S. Prell, E. Prencipe, M. T. Prim, H. Purwar, P. Rados, G. Raeuber, S. Raiz, N. Rauls, M. Reif, S. Reiter, M. Remnev, L. Reuter, I. Ripp-Baudot, G. Rizzo, S. H. Robertson, M. Roehrken, J. M. Roney, A. Rostomyan, N. Rout, S. Sandilya, L. Santelj, Y. Sato, V. Savinov, B. Scavino, M. Schnepf, C. Schwanda, A. J. Schwartz, Y. Seino, A. Selce, K. Senyo, J. Serrano, C. Sfienti, W. Shan, C. Sharma, C. P. Shen, X. D. Shi, T. Shillington, T. Shimasaki, J. -G. Shiu, D. Shtol, B. Shwartz, A. Sibidanov, F. Simon, J. B. Singh, J. Skorupa, R. J. Sobie, M. Sobotzik, A. Soffer, A. Sokolov, E. Solovieva, W. Song, S. Spataro, B. Spruck, M. Stari\v{c}, P. Stavroulakis, S. Stefkova, R. Stroili, Y. Sue, M. Sumihama, K. Sumisawa, W. Sutcliffe, N. Suwonjandee, H. Svidras, M. Takahashi, M. Takizawa, U. Tamponi, K. Tanida, F. Tenchini, A. Thaller, O. Tittel, R. Tiwary, E. Torassa, K. Trabelsi, I. Ueda, K. Unger, Y. Unno, K. Uno, S. Uno, P. Urquijo, Y. Ushiroda, S. E. Vahsen, R. van Tonder, K. E. Varvell, M. Veronesi, A. Vinokurova, V. S. Vismaya, L. Vitale, V. Vobbilisetti, R. Volpe, A. Vossen, M. Wakai, S. Wallner, E. Wang, M. -Z. Wang, Z. Wang, A. Warburton, S. Watanuki, C. Wessel, E. Won, X. P. Xu, B. D. Yabsley, S. Yamada, W. Yan, S. B. Yang, J. Yelton, J. H. Yin, K. Yoshihara, C. Z. Yuan, L. Zani, B. Zhang, V. Zhilich, J. S. Zhou, Q. D. Zhou, V. I. Zhukova, R. \v{Z}leb\v{c}\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the inclusive isolated-photon production cross section in pp collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The production cross section of inclusive isolated photons has been measured by the ALICE experiment at the CERN LHC in pp collisions at centre-of-momentum energy of $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV collected during the LHC Run 2 data-taking period. The measurement is performed by combining the measurements of the electromagnetic calorimeter EMCal and the central tracking detectors ITS and TPC, covering a pseudorapidity range of $|\eta^{\gamma}|&lt;0.67$ and a transverse momentum range of $7&lt;p_{\rm T}^{\gamma}&lt;200$ GeV/$c$. The result extends to lower $p_{\rm T}^{\gamma}$ and $x_{\rm T}^{\gamma} = 2p_{\rm T}^{\gamma}/\sqrt{s}$ ranges, the lowest $x_{\rm T}^{\gamma}$ of any isolated photon measurements to date, extending significantly those measured by the ATLAS and CMS experiments towards lower $p_{\rm T}^{\gamma}$ at the same collision energy with a small overlap between the measurements. The measurement is compared with next-to-leading order perturbative QCD calculations and the results from the ATLAS and CMS experiments as well as with measurements at other collision energies. The measurement and theory prediction are in agreement with each other within the experimental and theoretical uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01165v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ALICE Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance of small-diameter muon drift tube chambers with new fast readout ASIC at high background rates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Experiments like ATLAS at the HL-LHC or detectors at future hadron colliders need muon detectors with excellent momentum resolution up to the TeV scale both at the trigger and offline reconstruction levels. This requires muon tracking chambers with high spatial resolution even at the highest background fluxes. Drift-tube chambers are the most cost-effective technology for large-area muon systems, providing the required high rate capability and three-dimensional spatial resolution. Thanks to advances in electronics, the new generation small-diameter Muon Drift Tube (sMDT) detectors with 15 mm tube diameter can be used in stand-alone mode up to the background rates expected at future hadron collider experiments, providing event times and second coordinates without additional trigger chambers. New developments in integrated front-end electronics include fast baseline restoration of the shaped signal and picosecond time-to-digital converters for second coordinate measurement with double-sided read-out. Self-triggered operation is now possible using modern high-performance FPGAs for real-time pattern recognition and track reconstruction. A new amplifier shaper discriminator chip in 65 nm TSMC CMOS technology with increased sensitivity and faster baseline recovery has been developed to cope with high background fluxes. Extensive test beam campaigns using sMDT chambers with new readout electronics have been performed at the CERN Gamma Irradiation Facility (GIF++). Results show that the shorter peaking time of the new chip enhances the spatial resolution of the drift tubes by up to 100 $\mu$m at a background rate of 1 MHz, the maximum rate expected at the 100 TeV collider experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01201v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Abovyan, Nayana Bangaru, Francesco Fallavollita, Oliver Kortner, Sandra Kortner, Hubert Kroha, Elena Voevodina, Robert Richter, Yazhou Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomaly-aware summary statistic from data batches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Signal-agnostic data exploration based on machine learning could unveil very subtle statistical deviations of collider data from the expected Standard Model of particle physics. The beneficial impact of a large training sample on machine learning solutions motivates the exploration of increasingly large and inclusive samples of acquired data with resource efficient computational methods. In this work we consider the New Physics Learning Machine (NPLM), a multivariate goodness-of-fit test built on the Neyman-Pearson maximum-likelihood-ratio construction, and we address the problem of testing large size samples under computational and storage resource constraints. We propose to perform parallel NPLM routines over batches of the data, and to combine them by locally aggregating over the data-to-reference density ratios learnt by each batch. The resulting data hypothesis defining the likelihood-ratio test is thus shared over the batches, and complies with the assumption that the expected rate of new physical processes is time invariant. We show that this method outperforms the simple sum of the independent tests run over the batches, and can recover, or even surpass, the sensitivity of the single test run over the full data. Beside the significant advantage for the offline application of NPLM to large size samples, the proposed approach offers new prospects toward the use of NPLM to construct anomaly-aware summary statistics in quasi-online data streaming scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01249v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaia Grosso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for a light sterile neutrino with 7.5 years of IceCube DeepCore data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a search for an eV-scale sterile neutrino using 7.5 years of data from the IceCube DeepCore detector. The analysis uses a sample of 21,914 events with energies between 5 and 150 GeV to search for sterile neutrinos through atmospheric muon neutrino disappearance. Improvements in event selection and treatment of systematic uncertainties provide greater statistical power compared to previous DeepCore sterile neutrino searches. Our results are compatible with the absence of mixing between active and sterile neutrino states, and we place constraints on the mixing matrix elements $|U_{\mu 4}|^2 &lt; 0.0534$ and $|U_{\tau 4}|^2 &lt; 0.0574$ at 90% CL under the assumption that $\Delta m^2_{41}\geq 1\;\mathrm{eV^2}$. These null results add to the growing tension between anomalous appearance results and constraints from disappearance searches in the 3+1 sterile neutrino landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01314v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Abbasi, M. Ackermann, J. Adams, S. K. Agarwalla, J. A. Aguilar, M. Ahlers, J. M. Alameddine, N. M. Amin, K. Andeen, C. Arg\"uelles, Y. Ashida, S. Athanasiadou, L. Ausborm, S. N. Axani, X. Bai, A. Balagopal V., M. Baricevic, S. W. Barwick, S. Bash, V. Basu, R. Bay, J. J. Beatty, J. Becker Tjus, J. Beise, C. Bellenghi, C. Benning, S. BenZvi, D. Berley, E. Bernardini, D. Z. Besson, E. Blaufuss, L. Bloom, S. Blot, F. Bontempo, J. Y. Book Motzkin, C. Boscolo Meneguolo, S. B\"oser, O. Botner, J. B\"ottcher, J. Braun, B. Brinson, J. Brostean-Kaiser, L. Brusa, R. T. Burley, D. Butterfield, M. A. Campana, I. Caracas, K. Carloni, J. Carpio, S. Chattopadhyay, N. Chau, Z. Chen, D. Chirkin, S. Choi, B. A. Clark, A. Coleman, G. H. Collin, A. Connolly, J. M. Conrad, R. Corley, D. F. Cowen, P. Dave, C. De Clercq, J. J. DeLaunay, D. Delgado, S. Deng, A. Desai, P. Desiati, K. D. de Vries, G. de Wasseige, T. DeYoung, A. Diaz, J. C. D\'iaz-V\'elez, P. Dierichs, M. Dittmer, A. Domi, L. Draper, H. Dujmovic, D. Durnford, K. Dutta, M. A. DuVernois, T. Ehrhardt, L. Eidenschink, A. Eimer, P. Eller, E. Ellinger, S. El Mentawi, D. Els\"asser, R. Engel, H. Erpenbeck, J. Evans, P. A. Evenson, K. L. Fan, K. Fang, K. Farrag, A. R. Fazely, A. Fedynitch, N. Feigl, S. Fiedlschuster, C. Finley, L. Fischer, D. Fox, A. Franckowiak, S. Fukami, P. F\"urst, J. Gallagher, E. Ganster, A. Garcia, M. Garcia, G. Garg, E. Genton, L. Gerhardt, A. Ghadimi, C. Girard-Carillo, C. Glaser, T. Gl\"usenkamp, J. G. Gonzalez, S. Goswami, A. Granados, D. Grant, S. J. Gray, O. Gries, S. Griffin, S. Griswold, K. M. Groth, D. Guevel, C. G\"unther, P. Gutjahr, C. Ha, C. Haack, A. Hallgren, L. Halve, F. Halzen, H. Hamdaoui, M. Ha Minh, M. Handt, K. Hanson, J. Hardin, A. A. Harnisch, P. Hatch, A. Haungs, J. H\"au{\ss}ler, K. Helbing, J. Hellrung, J. Hermannsgabner, L. Heuermann, N. Heyer, S. Hickford, A. Hidvegi, C. Hill, G. C. Hill, K. D. Hoffman, S. Hori, K. Hoshina, M. Hostert, W. Hou, T. Huber, K. Hultqvist, M. H\"unnefeld, R. Hussain, K. Hymon, A. Ishihara, W. Iwakiri, M. Jacquart, S. Jain, O. Janik, M. Jansson, G. S. Japaridze, M. Jeong, M. Jin, B. J. P. Jones, N. Kamp, D. Kang, W. Kang, X. Kang, A. Kappes, D. Kappesser, L. Kardum, T. Karg, M. Karl, A. Karle, A. Katil, U. Katz, M. Kauer, J. L. Kelley, M. Khanal, A. Khatee Zathul, A. Kheirandish, J. Kiryluk, S. R. Klein, A. Kochocki, R. Koirala, H. Kolanoski, T. Kontrimas, L. K\"opke, C. Kopper, D. J. Koskinen, P. Koundal, M. Kovacevich, M. Kowalski, T. Kozynets, J. Krishnamoorthi, K. Kruiswijk, E. Krupczak, A. Kumar, E. Kun, N. Kurahashi, N. Lad, C. Lagunas Gualda, M. Lamoureux, M. J. Larson, S. Latseva, F. Lauber, J. P. Lazar, J. W. Lee, K. Leonard DeHolton, A. Leszczy\'nska, J. Liao, M. Lincetto, Y. T. Liu, M. Liubarska, C. Love, L. Lu, F. Lucarelli, W. Luszczak, Y. Lyu, J. Madsen, E. Magnus, K. B. M. Mahn, Y. Makino, E. Manao, S. Mancina, W. Marie Sainte, I. C. Mari\c{s}, S. Marka, Z. Marka, M. Marsee, I. Martinez-Soler, R. Maruyama, F. Mayhew, F. McNally, J. V. Mead, K. Meagher, S. Mechbal, A. Medina, M. Meier, Y. Merckx, L. Merten, J. Micallef, J. Mitchell, T. Montaruli, R. W. Moore, Y. Morii, R. Morse, M. Moulai, T. Mukherjee, R. Naab, R. Nagai, M. Nakos, U. Naumann, J. Necker, A. Negi, L. Neste, M. Neumann, H. Niederhausen, M. U. Nisa, K. Noda, A. Noell, A. Novikov, A. Obertacke Pollmann, V. O'Dell, B. Oeyen, A. Olivas, R. Orsoe, J. Osborn, E. O'Sullivan, V. Palusova, H. Pandya, N. Park, G. K. Parker, E. N. Paudel, L. Paul, C. P\'erez de los Heros, T. Pernice, J. Peterson, A. Pizzuto, M. Plum, A. Pont\'en, Y. Popovych, M. Prado Rodriguez, B. Pries, R. Procter-Murphy, G. T. Przybylski, C. Raab, J. Rack-Helleis, M. Ravn, K. Rawlins, Z. Rechav, A. Rehman, P. Reichherzer, E. Resconi, S. Reusch, W. Rhode, B. Riedel, A. Rifaie, E. J. Roberts, S. Robertson, S. Rodan, G. Roellinghoff, M. Rongen, A. Rosted, C. Rott, T. Ruhe, L. Ruohan, D. Ryckbosch, I. Safa, J. Saffer, D. Salazar-Gallegos, P. Sampathkumar, A. Sandrock, M. Santander, S. Sarkar, S. Sarkar, J. Savelberg, P. Savina, P. Schaile, M. Schaufel, H. Schieler, S. Schindler, L. Schlickmann, B. Schl\"uter, F. Schl\"uter, N. Schmeisser, T. Schmidt, J. Schneider, F. G. Schr\"oder, L. Schumacher, S. Sclafani, D. Seckel, M. Seikh, M. Seo, S. Seunarine, P. Sevle Myhr, R. Shah, S. Shefali, N. Shimizu, M. Silva, B. Skrzypek, B. Smithers, R. Snihur, J. Soedingrekso, A. S{\o}gaard, D. Soldin, P. Soldin, G. Sommani, C. Spannfellner, G. M. Spiczak, C. Spiering, M. Stamatikos, T. Stanev, T. Stezelberger, T. St\"urwald, T. Stuttard, G. W. Sullivan, I. Taboada, S. Ter-Antonyan, A. Terliuk, M. Thiesmeyer, W. G. Thompson, J. Thwaites, S. Tilav, K. Tollefson, C. T\"onnis, S. Toscano, D. Tosi, A. Trettin, R. Turcotte, J. P. Twagirayezu, M. A. Unland Elorrieta, A. K. Upadhyay, K. Upshaw, A. Vaidyanathan, N. Valtonen-Mattila, J. Vandenbroucke, N. van Eijndhoven, D. Vannerom, J. van Santen, J. Vara, F. Varsi, J. Veitch-Michaelis, M. Venugopal, M. Vereecken, S. Vergara Carrasco, S. Verpoest, D. Veske, A. Vijai, C. Walck, A. Wang, C. Weaver, P. Weigel, A. Weindl, J. Weldert, A. Y. Wen, C. Wendt, J. Werthebach, M. Weyrauch, N. Whitehorn, C. H. Wiebusch, D. R. Williams, L. Witthaus, A. Wolf, M. Wolf, G. Wrede, X. W. Xu, J. P. Yanez, E. Yildizci, S. Yoshida, R. Young, S. Yu, T. Yuan, Z. Zhang, P. Zhelnin, P. Zilberman, M. Zimmerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for decays of the Higgs boson into a pair of pseudoscalar particles decaying into $b\bar{b}\tau^+\tau^-$ using $pp$ collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV with the ATLAS detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a search for exotic decays of the Higgs boson into a pair of new pseudoscalar particles, $H\rightarrow aa$, where one pseudoscalar decays into a $b$-quark pair and the other decays into a $\tau$-lepton pair, in the mass range $12\leq m_{a}\leq 60$ GeV. The analysis uses $pp$ collision data at $\sqrt{s} = 13$ TeV collected with the ATLAS detector at the LHC, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 140 ${fb}^{-1}$. No significant excess above the Standard Model (SM) prediction is observed. Assuming the SM Higgs boson production cross-section, the search sets upper limits at 95% confidence level on the branching ratio of Higgs bosons decaying into $b\bar{b}\tau^+\tau^-$, $\mathcal{B}(H \rightarrow aa \rightarrow b\bar{b}\tau^+\tau^-)$, between 2.2% and 3.9% depending on the pseudoscalar mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01335v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection, sky localization and early warning for binary neutron star mergers by detectors located in China of different configurations in third generation detector network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18228v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work shows the results of an evaluation of the impact that a detector located in China, with a noise budget comparable to that of a proposed high-frequency detector with a 20 km arm length, an Einstein Telescope (ET) or a Cosmic Explorer (CE), could have on the network of ET-CE in terms of detection rate, localization, and providing early warning alert for simulated binary neutron star (BNS)s. The results indicate that a three-detector network including a Chinese detector could identify at least 4.4% more BNS mergers than an ET-CE network alone. The localization uncertainty could be reduced by a factor of more than 5 on average compared to the ET-CE network. With a three-detector network involving a Chinese detector, up to 89% of BNS mergers could be located within 10 square degrees of the sky 10 minutes prior to the merger. The assessment suggests that the potential for early warning signals is highest when the Chinese detector is similar to ET, whereas the sources are detected with the highest signal-to-noise ratio and localized to the smallest regions when the detector is more akin to CE. Interestingly, the C20N network (comprising ET+CE+C20) can achieve comparable localization performance as the ET network while outperforming the ETCN network (featuring the ET+CE+ an ET-like detector in China) in terms of detection capabilities, especially at large distances, indicating that adding a 20 km kilohertz detector in China to ET-CE network would make significant contributions at least as adding an ET-like detector in China to multi-messenger astronomy for almost all BNS observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18228v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yufeng Li, Ik Siong Heng, Man Leong Chan, Xilong Fan, Lijun Gou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical point of view on Cabibbo angle anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00122v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the current situation of the determinations of the first-row CKM components and show the Cabibbo angle anomaly corresponding to a deficit in the first-row CKM unitarity condition at the $3\sigma$ level. In this contribution, we show two new physics interpretations: heavy vector-like quark models and a MeV scale sterile neutrino models. The super tau-charm facility will directly probe the other CKM unitarity conditions related to $V_{cd}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00122v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teppei Kitahara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculation of crystal defects induced in CaWO$_{4}$ by 100 eV displacement cascades using a linear Machine Learning interatomic potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00133v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We determine the energy stored in the crystal defects induced by $\mathcal{O}(10-100)$\,eV nuclear recoils in low-threshold CaWO$_{4}$ cryogenic detectors. A Machine Learning interatomic potential is developed to perform molecular dynamics simulations. We show that the energy spectra expected from Dark Matter and neutrino coherent scattering are affected by the crystal defects and we provide reference predictions. We discuss the special case of the spectrum of nuclear recoils induced by neutron capture, which could offer a unique sensitivity to the calculated stored energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00133v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabrielle Soum-Sidikov, Jean-Paul Crocombette, Mihai-Cosmin Marinica, Corentin Doutre, David Lhuillier, Lo\"ic Thulliez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top-philic Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00183v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we review the application of modern machine-learning~(ML) techniques to boost the search for processes involving the top quarks at the LHC. We revisit the formalism of Convolutional Neural Networks~(CNNs), Graph Neural Networks~(GNNs), and Attention Mechanisms. Based on recent studies, we explore their applications in designing improved top taggers, top reconstruction, and event classification tasks. We also examine the ML-based likelihood-free inference approach and generative unfolding models, focusing on their applications to scenarios involving top quarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00183v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahool Kumar Barman, Sumit Biswas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice QCD Calculation of $x$-dependent Meson Distribution Amplitudes at Physical Pion Mass with Threshold Logarithm Resummation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00206v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a lattice QCD calculation of the $x$-dependent pion and kaon distribution amplitudes (DA) in the framework of large momentum effective theory. This calculation is performed on a fine lattice of $a=0.076$~fm at physical pion mass, with the pion boosted to $1.8$~GeV and kaon boosted to $2.3$~GeV. We renormalize the matrix elements in the hybrid scheme and match to $\overline{\rm MS}$ with a subtraction of the leading renormalon in the Wilson-line mass. The perturbative matching is improved by resumming the large logarithms related to the small quark and gluon momenta in the soft-gluon limit. After resummation, we demonstrate that we are able to calculate a range of $x\in[x_0,1-x_0]$ with $x_0=0.25$ for pion and $x_0=0.2$ for kaon with systematics under control. The kaon DA is shown to be slighted skewed, and narrower than pion DA. Although the $x$-dependence cannot be direct calculated beyond these ranges, we estimate higher moments of the pion and kaon DAs {by complementing} our calculation with short-distance factorization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00206v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Cloet, Xiang Gao, Swagato Mukherjee, Sergey Syritsyn, Nikhil Karthik, Peter Petreczky, Rui Zhang, Yong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging of single barium atoms in a second matrix site in solid xenon for barium tagging in a $^{136}$Xe double beta decay experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00285v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutrinoless double beta decay is one of the most sensitive probes for new physics beyond the Standard Model of particle physics. One of the isotopes under investigation is $^{136}$Xe, which would double beta decay into $^{136}$Ba. Detecting the single $^{136}$Ba daughter provides a sort of ultimate tool in the discrimination against backgrounds. Previous work demonstrated the ability to perform single atom imaging of Ba atoms in a single-vacancy site of a solid xenon matrix. In this paper, the effort to identify signal from individual barium atoms is extended to Ba atoms in a hexa-vacancy site in the matrix and is achieved despite increased photobleaching in this site. Abrupt fluorescence turn-off of a single Ba atom is also observed. Significant recovery of fluorescence signal lost through photobleaching is demonstrated upon annealing of Ba deposits in the Xe ice. Following annealing, it is observed that Ba atoms in the hexa-vacancy site exhibit antibleaching while Ba atoms in the tetra-vacancy site exhibit bleaching. This may be evidence for a matrix site transfer upon laser excitation. Our findings offer a path of continued research toward tagging of Ba daughters in all significant sites in solid xenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00285v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Yvaine, D. Fairbank, J. Soderstrom, C. Taylor, J. Stanley, T. Walton, C. Chambers, A. Iverson, W. Fairbank, S. Al Kharusi, A. Amy, E. Angelico, A. Anker, I. J. Arnquist, A. Atencio, J. Bane, V. Belov, E. P. Bernard, T. Bhatta, A. Bolotnikov, J. Breslin, P. A. Breur, J. P. Brodsky, E. Brown, T. Brunner, E. Caden, G. F. Cao, D. Cesmecioglu, E. Chambers, B. Chana, D. Chernyak, M. Chiu, R. Collister, M. Cvitan, T. Daniels, L. Darroch, R. DeVoe, M. L. di Vacri, M. J. Dolinski, B. Eckert, M. Elbeltagi, R. Elmansali, N. Fatemighomi, B. Foust, Y. S. Fu, D. Gallacher, N. Gallice, G. Giacomini, W. Gillis, C. Gingras, R. Gornea, G. Gratta, C. A. Hardy, S. Hedges, E. Hein, J. D. Holt, E. W. Hoppe, A. Karelin, D. Keblbeck, I. Kotov, A. Kuchenkov, K. S. Kumar, A. A. Kwiatkowski, A. Larson, M. B. Latif, K. G. Leach, A. Lennarz, D. S. Leonard, H. Lewis, G. Li, Z. Li, C. Licciardi, R. Lindsay, R. MacLellan, S. Majidi, C. Malbrunot, J. Masbou, K. McMichael, M. Medina Peregrina, M. Moe, B. Mong, D. C. Moore, C. R. Natzke, X. E. Ngwadla, K. Ni, A. Nolan, S. C. Nowicki, J. C. Nzobadila Ondze, A. Odian, J. L. Orrell, G. S. Ortega, C. T. Overman, L. Pagani, H. Peltz Smalley, A. Perna, A. Pocar, V. Radeka, E. Raguzin, H. Rasiwala, D. Ray, S. Rescia, G. Richardson, R. Ross, P. C. Rowson, R. Saldanha, S. Sangiorgio, S. Schwartz, S. Sekula, L. Si, A. K. Soma, F. Spadoni, V. Stekhanov, X. L. Sun, S. Thibado, A. Tidball, T. Totev, S. Triambak, T. Tsang, O. A. Tyuka, E. van Bruggen, M. Vidal, M. Walent, K. Wamba, H. W. Wang, Q. D. Wang, W. Wang, Y. G. Wang, M. Watts, M. Wehrfritz, L. J. Wen, U. Wichoski, S. Wilde, M. Worcester, H. Xu, L. Yang, M. Yu, O. Zeldovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for particle acceleration approaching PeV energies in the W51 complex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00624v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The $\gamma$-ray emission from the W51 complex is widely acknowledged to be attributed to the interaction between the cosmic rays (CRs) accelerated by the shock of supernova remnant (SNR) W51C and the dense molecular clouds in the adjacent star-forming region, W51B. However, the maximum acceleration capability of W51C for CRs remains elusive. Based on observations conducted with the Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory (LHAASO), we report a significant detection of $\gamma$ rays emanating from the W51 complex, with energies from 2 TeV to 200 TeV. The LHAASO measurements, for the first time, extend the $\gamma$-ray emission from the W51 complex beyond 100 TeV and reveal a significant spectrum bending at tens of TeV. By combining the ``$\pi^0$-decay bump" featured data from Fermi-LAT, the broadband $\gamma$-ray spectrum of the W51 region can be well-characterized by a simple pp-collision model. The observed spectral bending feature suggests an exponential cutoff at $\sim400$~TeV or a power-law break at $\sim200$~TeV in the CR proton spectrum, most likely providing the first evidence of SNRs serving as CR accelerators approaching the PeV regime. Additionally, two young star clusters within W51B could also be theoretically viable to produce the most energetic $\gamma$ rays observed by LHAASO. Our findings strongly support the presence of extreme CR accelerators within the W51 complex and provide new insights into the origin of Galactic CRs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00624v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> LHAASO Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The third family quark mass hierarchy and FCNC in the universal seesaw model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00732v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the study of the quark sector of the universal seesaw model with $\mathrm{SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R \times U(1)_{Y'}}$ gauge symmetry in the massless case of the two lightest quark families. This model aims to explain the mass hierarchy of the third family quark by introducing a vector-like quark (VLQ) partner for each quark. In this model, we introduce $\mathrm{SU(2)_L}$ and $\mathrm{SU(2)_R}$ Higgs doublets. We derive explicitly the Lagrangian for the quark sector, Higgs sector, and kinetic terms of the gauge fields, starting from the Lagrangian, which is invariant under $\mathrm{SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R \times U(1)_{Y'}}$ gauge symmetry. At each stage of the symmetry breaking, we present the Lagrangian with the remaining gauge symmetry. Additionally, we investigate the flavor-changing neutral currents (FCNC) of Higgs ($h$) and $Z$-boson in the interaction with the top, heavy top, bottom, and heavy bottom quark.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00732v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Morozumi, Albertus Hariwangsa Panuluh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs-Portal Spin-1 Dark Matter with Parity-Violating Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the spin-1 $U(1)_X$ gauged field $X$ with $Z_2$ odd dark parity for evading the current strong constraints for the kinetic mixing. Then, $X$ becomes stable and a candidate for the dark matter. The lowest mass dimension of interaction is six, and the type is like Higgs portal. Two types of dim-6 operators are introduced. We consider the freeze-out dark matter scenario. With the limit of null momentum transfer, a parity odd operator is free from the direct detection constraints. Accordingly, the strong constraints on a parity even operator indicate turning on this parity odd operator to realize the dark matter relic density of the universe. With the 1 TeV cut-off scale, our dark matter of around 400 GeV mass can explain the dark matter relic density and is allowed from the LUX-ZEPLIN experiment of the direct detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01002v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kimiko Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Photon Dark Matter in Quantum Electromagnetodynamics and Detection at Haloscope Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01070v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The ultralight dark photon is one of intriguing dark matter candidates. The interaction between the visible photon and dark photon is introduced by the gauge kinetic mixing between the field strength tensors of the Abelian gauge groups in the Standard Model and dark sector. The relativistic electrodynamics was generalized to quantum electromagnetodynamics (QEMD) in the presence of both electric and magnetic charges. The photon is described by two four-potentials corresponding to two $U(1)$ gauge groups and satisfying non-trivial commutation relations. In this work, we construct the low-energy dark photon-photon interactions in the framework of QEMD and obtain new dark photon-photon kinetic mixings. The consequent field equations and the new Maxwell's equations are derived in this framework. We also investigate the detection strategies of dark photon as light dark matter as well as the generic kinetic mixings at haloscope experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01070v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tong Li, Rui-Jia Zhang, Chang-Jie Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From the $P^{N}_{\psi}$/$P^{\Lambda}_{\psi s}$ to $\bar{T}^f_{cc}$: symmetry analysis to the interactions of the $(\bar{c}q)(\bar{c}q)$/$(ccq)(\bar{c}q)$/$(ccq)(ccq)$ di-hadron systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01185v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the interactions of the $(\bar{c}q)(\bar{c}q)$/$(ccq)(\bar{c}q)$/$(ccq)(ccq)$ di-hadron systems based on a contact lagrangian possessing the SU(3) flavor and SU(2) spin symmetries. Under the assumptions of two scenarios for the $J^P$ quantum numbers of the $P_{\psi}^N(4440)$ and $P_{\psi}^N(4457)$ states, we obtain the parameters ($\tilde{g}_s$, $\tilde{g}_a$) introduced from this contact lagrangian. Then we include the SU(3) breaking effect by introducing a factor $g_x$, this quantity can be further constrained by the experimental mass of the $P_{\psi s}^\Lambda(4338)$ state. We can reproduce the mass of the $T^f_{cc}(3875)$ state with the parameters extracted from the observed $P_{\psi}^N$ states, this consistency indicates a unified description of the di-hadron molecular states composed of two heavy-light hadrons. With the same parameters, we discuss the possible mass spectra of the $\bar{T}_{cc}^f$/$P_{\psi c}^\Lambda$/$H_{\Omega_{ccc}c}^\Lambda$ systems. Then we proceed to discuss the existences of the $\bar{T}_{cc\bar{s}}^\theta$/$P_{\psi cs}^N$/$H_{\Omega_{ccc}cs}^N$ states by investigating the SU(3) breaking effects. Our results show that the states in the $\bar{T}_{cc\bar{s}}^\theta$/$P_{\psi cs}^N$ systems can hardly form bound states, while the states in the $H_{\Omega_{ccc}cs}^N$ system can form bound states due to their larger reduced masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01185v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kan Chen, Bo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic scattering at $\sqrt{s} = 6$ GeV up to $ \sqrt{s} = 13$ TeV (proton-proton; proton-antiproton; proton-neutron)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01311v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the framework of the Regge-eikonal model of hadron interaction, based on the analyticity of the scattering amplitude with taking into account the hadron structure, the simultaneous analysis is carried out of the 90 sets of data. These sets include the data obtained at low energies ($\sqrt{s} &gt; 3.6 $ GeV and at high energies at FNAL, ISR, $S\bar{p}pS$, TEVATRON and LHC with 4326 experimental points, including the polarization data of analysing power. The energy and momentum transfer dependence of separate sets of data is analyzed on the basis of the eikonalized Born amplitude with taking into account two additional anomalous terms. Different origins of the nonlinear behavior of the slope of the scattering amplitude are compared. No contribution of hard-Pomeron in the elastic hadron scattering is shown. However, the importance of Odderon's contribution is presented. The form and energy dependence of different terms of the cross-even and cross-odd parts of the elastic nucleon-nucleon scattering amplitude is determined in the framework of the High Energy Generalize Structure (HEGS) model. In the framework of the HEGS model, using the electromagnetic and gravitomagnetic form factors, the differential cross sections in the Coulomb Nuclear Interference (CNI) region and at large momentum transfer are described well in a wide energy region simultaneously. It is shown that the cross-even part includes the soft pomeron growing like $\ln^{2}(s)$ and an additional term with a large slope and with and with energy dependence $\ln^2(s)$. The cross-odd part includes the maximal odderon term and an additional oscillation term with $\ln(s)$. It is shown that both additional terms are proportional to charge distributions but the maximal odderon term is proportional to matter distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01311v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. V. Selyugin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs-boson production in the full theory at NNLO+PS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01354v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the production of a Standard-Model (SM) Higgs boson in gluon fusion in hadronic collisions and compute the QCD corrections up to next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) and match them to parton showers (NNLO+PS). The complete dependence on the top-quark mass is taken into account without making any approximations to the top quark loops mediating the coupling between the gluons and the Higgs boson. To this end, we have included the $gg\to H$ amplitudes up to three loops and the $pp\to H$+jet amplitudes up to two loops in the full SM theory. This is the first fully differential calculation of the top-quark mass effects up to NNLO in QCD, and we study their impact on relevant observables for the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01354v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Niggetiedt, Marius Wiesemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds to strong gravity from electron-positron annihilations near threshold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01430v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss bounds to strong gravity arising from annihilation of electron and positrons and the corresponding enhancement of the cross section for the production of massive particles. Two complementary examples are discussed, the case of the $e^+e^- \to W^+ W^-$ processes, with maximum mass and short lifetime for the particle pairs in the final state, and the case of electron positron annihilation into heavier charged lepton pairs, $e^+ e^- \to \mu^+ \mu^-$ and $e^+ e^- \to \tau^+ \tau^-$. These bounds may be improved by the next generation of electron-positron colliders, and are complementary to bounds arising from direct graviton searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01430v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.115021</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 109, 115021 (2014)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nathaniel Alden, Roberto Onofrio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A measurement of the sodium and iodine scintillation quenching factors across multiple NaI(Tl) detectors to identify systematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.12480v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The amount of light produced by nuclear recoils in scintillating targets is strongly quenched compared to that produced by electrons. A precise understanding of the quenching factor is particularly interesting for WIMP searches and CE{\nu}NS measurements since both rely on nuclear recoils, whereas energy calibrations are more readily accessible from electron recoils. There is a wide variation among the current measurements of the quenching factor in sodium iodide (NaI) crystals, especially below 10 keV, the energy region of interest for dark matter and CE{\nu}NS studies. A better understanding of the quenching factor in NaI(Tl) is of particular interest for resolving the decades-old puzzle in the field of dark matter between the null results of most WIMP searches and the claim for dark matter detection by the DAMA/LIBRA collaboration. In this work, we measured sodium and iodine quenching factors for five small NaI(Tl) crystals grown with similar thallium concentrations and growth procedures. Unlike previous experiments, multiple crystals were tested, with measurements made in the same experimental setup to control systematic effects. The quenching factors agree in all crystals we investigated, and both sodium and iodine quenching factors are smaller than those reported by DAMA/LIBRA. The dominant systematic effect was due to the electron equivalent energy calibration originating from the non-proportional behavior of the NaI(Tl) light yield at lower energies, potentially the cause for the discrepancies among the previous measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.12480v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Cintas, S. Hedges, W. G. Thompson, P. An, C. Awe, P. S. Barbeau, E. Barbosa de Souza, J. H. Jo, L. Li, M. Mart\'inez, R. H. Maruyama, G. C. Rich, R. Runge, M. L. Sarsa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for heavy neutral leptons in final states with electrons, muons, and hadronically decaying tau leptons in proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A search for heavy neutral leptons (HNLs) of Majorana or Dirac type using proton-proton collision data at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV is presented. The data were collected by the CMS experiment at the CERN LHC and correspond to an integrated luminosity of 138 fb$^{-1}$. Events with three charged leptons (electrons, muons, and hadronically decaying tau leptons) are selected, corresponding to HNL production in association with a charged lepton and decay of the HNL to two charged leptons and a standard model (SM) neutrino. The search is performed for HNL masses between 10 GeV and 1.5 TeV. No evidence for an HNL signal is observed in data. Upper limits at 95% confidence level are found for the squared coupling strength of the HNL to SM neutrinos, considering exclusive coupling of the HNL to a single SM neutrino generation, for both Majorana and Dirac HNLs. The limits exceed previously achieved experimental constraints for a wide range of HNL masses, and the limits on tau neutrino coupling scenarios with HNL masses above the W boson mass are presented for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00100v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP06(2024)123</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 06 (2024) 123</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> CMS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combined Pre-Supernova Alert System with Kamland and Super-Kamiokande</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09920v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Preceding a core-collapse supernova, various processes produce an increasing amount of neutrinos of all flavors characterized by mounting energies from the interior of massive stars. Among them, the electron antineutrinos are potentially detectable by terrestrial neutrino experiments such as KamLAND and Super-Kamiokande via inverse beta decay interactions. Once these pre-supernova neutrinos are observed, an early warning of the upcoming core-collapse supernova can be provided. In light of this, KamLAND and Super-Kamiokande, both located in the Kamioka mine in Japan, have been monitoring pre-supernova neutrinos since 2015 and 2021, respectively. Recently, we performed a joint study between KamLAND and Super-Kamiokande on pre-supernova neutrino detection. A pre-supernova alert system combining the KamLAND detector and the Super-Kamiokande detector was developed and put into operation, which can provide a supernova alert to the astrophysics community. Fully leveraging the complementary properties of these two detectors, the combined alert is expected to resolve a pre-supernova neutrino signal from a 15 M$_{\odot}$ star within 510 pc of the Earth, at a significance level corresponding to a false alarm rate of no more than 1 per century. For a Betelgeuse-like model with optimistic parameters, it can provide early warnings up to 12 hours in advance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09920v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> KamLAND, Super-Kamiokande Collaborations,  :, Seisho Abe, Minori Eizuka, Sawako Futagi, Azusa Gando, Yoshihito Gando, Shun Goto, Takahiko Hachiya, Kazumi Hata, Koichi Ichimura, Sei Ieki, Haruo Ikeda, Kunio Inoue, Koji Ishidoshiro, Yuto Kamei, Nanami Kawada, Yasuhiro Kishimoto, Masayuki Koga, Maho Kurasawa, Tadao Mitsui, Haruhiko Miyake, Daisuke Morita, Takeshi Nakahata, Rika Nakajima, Kengo Nakamura, Rikuo Nakamura, Ryo Nakamura, Jun Nakane, Hideyoshi Ozaki, Keita Saito, Taichi Sakai, Itaru Shimizu, Junpei Shirai, Kensuke Shiraishi, Ryunosuke Shoji, Atsuto Suzuki, Atsuto Takeuchi, Kyoko Tamae, Hiroko Watanabe, Kazuho Watanabe, Sei Yoshida, Saori Umehara, Ken-Ichi Fushimi, Kenta Kotera, Yusuke Urano, Bruce E. Berger, Brian K. Fujikawa, John G. Larned, Jelena Maricic, Zhenghao Fu, Joseph Smolsky, Lindley A. Winslow, Yuri Efremenko, Hugon J. Karwowski, Diane M. Markoff, Werner Tornow, Stefano Dell'Oro, Thomas O'Donnell, Jason A. Detwiler, Sanshiro Enomoto, Michal P. Decowski, Kelly M. Weerman, Christopher Grant, Hasung Song, Aobo Li, Spencer N. Axani, Miles Garcia, Ko Abe, Seisho Abe, Christophe Bronner, Yoshinari Hayato, Katsuki Hiraide, Keishi Hosokawa, Kei Ieki, Motoyasu Ikeda, June Kameda, Yuki Kanemura, Ryota Kaneshima, Yuri Kashiwagi, Yousuke Kataoka, Shintaro Miki, Shunichi Mine, Makoto Miura, Shigetaka Moriyama, Masayuki Nakahata, Yuuki Nakano, Shoei Nakayama, Yohei Noguchi, Kazufumi Sato, Hiroyuki Sekiya, Hayato Shiba, Kotaro Shimizu, Masato Shiozawa, Yutaro Sonoda, Yoichiro Suzuki, Atsushi Takeda, Yasuhiro Takemoto, Hidekazu K. Tanaka, Takatomi Yano, Seungho Han, Takaaki Kajita, Kimihiro Okumura, Takuya Tashiro, Takuya Tomiya, Xubin Wang, Shunsuke Yoshida, Pablo Fernandez, Luis Labarga, Nataly Ospina, Bryan Zaldivar, Barry W. Pointon, Edward Kearns, Jennifer L. Raaf, Linyan Wan, Thomas Wester, Jianming Bian, Jeff Griskevich, Michael B. Smy, Henry W. Sobel, Volodymyr Takhistov, Alejandro Yankelevich, James Hill, MinCheol Jang, Seonghak Lee, DongHo Moon, RyeongGyoon Park, Baran Bodur, Kate Scholberg, Chris W. Walter, Antoine Beauch\^ene, Olivier Drapier, Alberto Giampaolo, Thomas A. Mueller, Andrew D. Santos, Pascal Paganini, Benjamin Quilain, Rudolph Rogly, Taku Nakamura, Jee-Seung Jang, Lucas N. Machado, John G. Learned, Koun Choi, Nadege Iovine, Son V. Cao, Lauren H. V. Anthony, Daniel G. R. Martin, Nick W. Prouse, Mark Scott, Yoshi Uchida, Vincenzo Berardi, Nicola F. Calabria, M. G. Catanesi, Emilio Radicioni, Aurora Langella, Gianfranca de Rosa, Gianmaria Collazuol, Matteo Feltre, Fabio Iacob, Marco Mattiazzi, Lucio Ludovici, Michel Gonin, Lorenzo P\'eriss\'e, Guillaume Pronost, Chiori Fujisawa, Shogo Horiuchi, Misaki Kobayashi, Yu-Ming Liu, Yuto Maekawa, Yasuhiro Nishimura, Reo Okazaki, Ryosuke Akutsu, Megan Friend, Takuya Hasegawa, Taku Ishida, Takashi Kobayashi, Mahesh Jakkapu, Tsunayuki Matsubara, Takeshi Nakadaira, Kenzo Nakamura, Yuichi Oyama, Ken Sakashita, Tetsuro Sekiguchi, Toshifumi Tsukamoto, Antoniosk Portocarrero Yrey, Nahid Bhuiyan, George T. Burton, Francesca Di Lodovico, Joanna Gao, Alexander Goldsack, Teppei Katori, Jost Migenda, Rory M. Ramsden, Zhenxiong Xie, Stephane Zsoldos, Atsumu T. Suzuki, Yusuke Takagi, Yasuo Takeuchi, Haiwen Zhong, Jiahui Feng, Li-Cheng Feng, Jianrun Hu, Zhuojun Hu, Masaki Kawaue, Tatsuya Kikawa, Masamitsu Mori, Tsuyoshi Nakaya, Roger A. Wendell, Kenji Yasutome, Sam J. Jenkins, Neil K. McCauley, Pruthvi Mehta, Adam Tarrant, Mike J. Wilking, Yoshiyuki Fukuda, Yoshitaka Itow, Hiroaki Menjo, Kotaro Ninomiya, Yushi Yoshioka, Justyna Lagoda, Maitrayee Mandal, Piotr Mijakowski, Yashwanth S. Prabhu, Joanna Zalipska, Mo Jia, Junjie Jiang, Wei Shi, Chiaki Yanagisawa, Masayuki Harada, Yota Hino, Hirokazu Ishino, Yusuke Koshio, Fumi Nakanishi, Seiya Sakai, Tomoaki Tada, Tomohiro Tano, Takeharu Ishizuka, Giles Barr, Daniel Barrow, Laurence Cook, Soniya Samani, David Wark, Anna Holin, Federico Nova, Seunghyun Jung, Byeongsu Yang, JeongYeol Yang, Jonghee Yoo, Jack E. P. Fannon, Liz Kneale, Matthew Malek, Jordan M. McElwee, Matthew D. Thiesse, Lee F. Thompson, Stephen T. Wilson, Hiroko Okazawa, Lakshmi S. Mohan, SooBong Kim, Eunhyang Kwon, Ji-Woong Seo, Intae Yu, Atsuko K. Ichikawa, Kiseki D. Nakamura, Seidai Tairafune, Kyoshi Nishijima, Aoi Eguchi, Kota Nakagiri, Yasuhiro Nakajima, Shizuka Shima, Natsumi Taniuchi, Eiichiro Watanabe, Masashi Yokoyama, Patrick de Perio, Saki Fujita, Cesar Jesus-Valls, Kai Martens, Ka M. Tsui, Mark R. Vagins, Junjie Xia, Shota Izumiyama, Masahiro Kuze, Ryo Matsumoto, Kotaro Terada, Ryusei Asaka, Masaki Ishitsuka, Hiroshi Ito, Yuga Ommura, Natsuki Shigeta, Masataka Shinoki, Koki Yamauchi, Tsukasa Yoshida, Rhea Gaur, Vincent Gousy-Leblan, Mark Hartz, Akira Konaka, Xiaoyue Li, Shaomin Chen, Benda Xu, Aiqiang Zhang, Bin Zhang, Magdalena Posiadala-Zezula, Steven B. Boyd, Rory Edwards, David Hadley, Matthew Nicholson, Marcus O'Flaherty, Benjamin Richards, Ajmi Ali, Blair Jamieson, Shogo Amanai, Lluis Marti-Magro, Akihiro Minamino, Ryo Shibayama, Serina Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal kinematic imbalances in neutrino and antineutrino interactions for improved measurements of neutrino energy and the axial vector form factor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.15633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.15633v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Current and future accelerator neutrino oscillation experiments require an improved understanding of nuclear effects in neutrino-nucleus interactions. One important systematic uncertainty is introduced by the collective impact of nuclear effects which bias the reconstruction of the neutrino energy, such as the nuclear removal energy. In this manuscript, we introduce a novel observable for accelerator neutrino oscillation experiments, the visible longitudinal momentum imbalance, reconstructed in charged current quasi-elastic interactions from the outgoing charged lepton and nucleon. We demonstrate it to be minimally dependent on the neutrino energy and sensitive to sources of bias in neutrino energy reconstruction. Furthermore, we show how the use of the longitudinal imbalance in antineutrino interactions in a target containing hydrogen allows for an improved, high-purity selection of the interactions on hydrogen. This approach offers the potential for precise measurements of the nuclear axial vector form factor as well as of the antineutrino flux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.15633v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Baudis, Stephen Dolan, Davide Sgalaberna, Sara Bolognesi, Laura Munteanu, Till Dieminger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Optimal Observables to Machine Learning: an Effective-Field-Theory Analysis of $e^+e^- \to W^+W^-$ at Future Lepton Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02474v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We apply machine-learning techniques to the effective-field-theory analysis of the $e^+e^- \to W^+W^-$ processes at future lepton colliders, and demonstrate their advantages in comparison with conventional methods, such as optimal observables. Compared to traditional algorithms, we show that simulation-based inference methods are more robust to detector effects and backgrounds, and could in principle produce unbiased results with sufficient Monte Carlo simulation samples that accurately describe experiments. This is crucial for the analyses at future lepton colliders given the outstanding precision of the $e^+e^- \to W^+W^-$ measurement ($\sim 10^{-4}$ in terms of anomalous triple gauge couplings or even better) that can be reached. Our framework can be generalized to other effective-field-theory analyses, such as the one of $e^+e^- \to t\bar{t}$ or similar processes at muon colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02474v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengdu Chai, Jiayin Gu, Lingfeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous Determination of Fragmentation Functions and Test on Momentum Sum Rule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02781v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform a simultaneous global analysis of hadron fragmentation functions (FFs) to various charged hadrons at next-to-leading order in QCD. The world data set includes results from electron-positron single-inclusive annihilation, semi-inclusive deep inelastic scattering, as well as proton-proton collisions including jet fragmentation measurements which lead to strong constraints on the gluon fragmentations. By carefully selecting hadron kinematics to ensure the validity of QCD factorization and the convergence of perturbative calculations, we achieve a satisfying best fit with $\chi^2/$d.o.f.$=0.90$, in the simultaneous extraction of FFs for light charged hadrons ($\pi^{\pm}$, $K^{\pm}$ and $p/\bar{p}$). The total momentum of $u$, $d$ quarks and gluon carried by light charged hadrons have been determined precisely. That urges future precision measurements on fragmentation to neutral hadrons, which are crucial for the test of fundamental sum rules in QCD fragmentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02781v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.261903</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Lett. 132 (2024) 26, 261903</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jun Gao, ChongYang Liu, XiaoMin Shen, Hongxi Xing, Yuxiang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of the ground and excited states of triply heavy spin-1/2 baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14348v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the triply heavy spin-1/2 baryons with quark contents $ ccb $ and $ bbc $, and calculate their mass and residue using QCD sum rules. In the calculations, we consider the ground (1S), first orbitally excited (1P) and first radially excited (2S) states. Aiming to achieve higher accuracies in the results, we perform the computations by taking into account the non-perturbative operators up to eight mass dimensions. We compare our results with the predictions of other theoretical studies existing in the literature. The obtained results may help experimental groups in their search for these yet unseen, but previously predicted by the quark model, interesting particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14348v5</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Rajabi Najjar, K. Azizi, H. R. Moshfegh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NLO+NLL' accurate predictions for three-jet event shapes in hadronic Higgs decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06929v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present resummed predictions at next-to-leading logarithmic accuracy matched to the exact next-to-leading order results for a set of classical event-shape observables in hadronic Higgs decays, i.e., for the channels $H\to gg$ and $H\to b\bar{b}$. We furthermore consider soft-drop grooming of the hadronic final states and derive corresponding $\text{NLO}+\text{NLL}^\prime$ predictions for the groomed thrust observable. Differences in the QCD radiation pattern of gluon- and quark-initiated final states are imprinted in the event-shape distributions, offering separation power for the two decay channels. In particular, we show that ungroomed event shapes in $H\to gg$ decays develop a considerably harder spectrum than in $H\to b\bar b$ decays. We highlight that soft-drop grooming can substantially alter this behaviour, unless rather inclusive grooming parameters are chosen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06929v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aude Gehrmann-De Ridder, Christian T Preuss, Daniel Reichelt, Steffen Schumann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass spectra of heavy hybrid quarkonia and $\overline{b}gc$ mesons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12692v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Masses and current couplings of the charmonium and bottomonium hybrids $ \overline{c}gc$ and $\overline{b}gb$ with spin-parities $J^{\mathrm{PC} }=0^{++},\ 0^{+-},\ 0^{-+},\ 0^{--}$ and $1^{++},\ 1^{+-},\ 1^{-+},\ 1^{--}$ are calculated using QCD two-point sum rule method. Computations are performed by taking into account gluon condensates up to dimension 12 including terms $\sim \langle g_{s}^{3}G^{3}\rangle ^{2}$. The parameters of the bottom-charm hybrids $\overline{b}gc$ with quantum numbers $J^{\mathrm{PC }}=0^{+},\ 0^{-},\ 1^{+}$, and $1^{-}$ are calculated as well. In computations the dominance of the pole contribution to sum rule results is ensured. It is demonstrated that all charmonia hybrids decay strongly to two-meson final states. The bottomonium hybrids $0^{-+}$ and $1^{-+}$ as well as the bottom-charm hybrid mesons $0^{-(+)}$ and $1^{-(+)}$ may be stable against strong two-meson decay modes. Results of the present work are compared with ones obtained using the sum rule and alternative approaches. Our predictions for parameters of the heavy hybrid mesons may be useful to study their various decay channels which are important for interpretation of ongoing and future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12692v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Alaakol, S. S. Agaev, K. Azizi, H. Sundu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of hidden-color components in the tetraquark mixing model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18411v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multiquarks can have two-hadron components and hidden-color components in their wave functions. The presence of two-hadron components in multiquarks introduces a potential source of confusion, particularly with respect to their resemblance to hadronic molecules. On the other hand, hidden-color components are essential for distinguishing between multiquarks and hadronic molecules. In this work, we study the hidden-color components in the wave functions of the tetraquark mixing model, a model that has been proposed as a suitable framework for describing the properties of two nonets in the $J^P=0^+$ channel: the light nonet [$a_0 (980)$, $K_0^* (700)$, $f_0 (500)$, $f_0 (980)$] and the heavy nonet [$a_0 (1450)$, $K_0^* (1430)$, $f_0 (1370)$, $f_0 (1500)$]. Our analysis reveals a substantial presence of hidden-color components within the tetraquark wave functions. To elucidate the impact of hidden-color components on physical quantities, we conduct computations of the hyperfine masses, $\langle V_{CS}\rangle$, for the two nonets, considering scenarios involving only the two-meson components and those incorporating the hidden-color components. We demonstrate that the hidden-color components constitute an important part of the hyperfine masses, such that the mass difference formula, $\Delta M\approx \Delta \langle V_{CS}\rangle$, which has been successful for the two nonets, cannot be achieved without the hidden-color contributions. This can provide another evidence supporting the tetraquark nature of the two nonets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18411v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hungchong Kim, K. S. Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opening a meV mass window for Axion-like particles with a microwave-laser-mixed stimulated resonant photon collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03577v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a microwave-laser-mixed three-beam stimulated resonant photon collider, which enables access to axion-like particles in the meV mass range. Collisions between a focused pulse laser beam and a focused microwave pulse beam directly produce axion-like particles (ALPs) and another focused pulse laser beam stimulates their decay. The expected sensitivity in the meV mass range has been evaluated. The result shows that the sensitivity can reach the ALP-photon coupling down to $O(10^{-13})$ GeV${}^{-1}$ with $10^6$ shots if 10 -100 TW class high-intensity lasers are properly combined with a conventional 100 MW class S-band klystron. This proposal paves the way for identifying the nature of ALPs as candidates for dark matter, independent of any cosmological and astrophysical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03577v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kensuke Homma, Yuri Kirita, Takafumi Miyamaru, Takumi Hasada, Airi Kodama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Parity Detectors: a qubit based particle detection scheme with meV thresholds for rare-event searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17192v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The next generation of rare-event searches, such as those aimed at determining the nature of particle dark matter or in measuring fundamental neutrino properties, will benefit from particle detectors with thresholds at the meV scale, 100-1000x lower than currently available. Quantum parity detectors (QPDs) are a novel class of proposed quantum devices that use the tremendous sensitivity of superconducting qubits to quasiparticle tunneling events as their detection concept. As envisioned, phonons generated by particle interactions within a crystalline substrate cause an eventual quasiparticle cascade within a surface patterned superconducting qubit element. This process alters the fundamental charge parity of the device in a binary manner, which can be used to deduce the initial properties of the energy deposition. We lay out the operating mechanism, noise sources, and expected sensitivity of QPDs based on a spectrum of charge-qubit types and readout mechanisms and detail an R&amp;D pathway to demonstrating sensitivity to sub-eV energy deposits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17192v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karthik Ramanathan, John E. Parker, Lalit M. Joshi, Andrew D. Beyer, Pierre M. Echternach, Serge Rosenblum, Brandon J. Sandoval, Sunil R. Golwala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using graph neural networks to reconstruct charged pion showers in the CMS High Granularity Calorimeter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11937v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel method to reconstruct the energy of hadronic showers in the CMS High Granularity Calorimeter (HGCAL) is presented. The HGCAL is a sampling calorimeter with very fine transverse and longitudinal granularity. The active media are silicon sensors and scintillator tiles readout by SiPMs and the absorbers are a combination of lead and Cu/CuW in the electromagnetic section, and steel in the hadronic section. The shower reconstruction method is based on graph neural networks and it makes use of a dynamic reduction network architecture. It is shown that the algorithm is able to capture and mitigate the main effects that normally hinder the reconstruction of hadronic showers using classical reconstruction methods, by compensating for fluctuations in the multiplicity, energy, and spatial distributions of the shower's constituents. The performance of the algorithm is evaluated using test beam data collected in 2018 prototype of the CMS HGCAL accompanied by a section of the CALICE AHCAL prototype. The capability of the method to mitigate the impact of energy leakage from the calorimeter is also demonstrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11937v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Aamir, B. Acar, G. Adamov, T. Adams, C. Adloff, S. Afanasiev, C. Agrawal, C. Agrawal, A. Ahmad, H. A. Ahmed, S. Akbar, N. Akchurin, B. Akgul, B. Akgun, R. O. Akpinar, E. Aktas, A. AlKadhim, V. Alexakhin, J. Alimena, J. Alison, A. Alpana, W. Alshehri, P. Alvarez Dominguez, M. Alyari, C. Amendola, R. B. Amir, S. B. Andersen, Y. Andreev, P. D. Antoszczuk, U. Aras, L. Ardila, P. Aspell, M. Avila, I. Awad, O. Aydilek, Z. Azimi, A. Aznar Pretel, O. A. Bach, R. Bainbridge, A. Bakshi, B. Bam, S. Banerjee, D. Barney, O. Bayraktar, F. Beaudette, F. Beaujean, E. Becheva, P. K. Behera, A. Belloni, T. Bergauer, M. Besancon, O. Bessidskaia Bylund, L. Bhatt, D. Bhowmil, F. Blekman, P. Blinov, P. Bloch, A. Bodek, a. Boger, A. Bonnemaison, F. Bouyjou, L. Brennan, E. Brondolin, A. Brusamolino, I. Bubanja, A. Buchot Perraguin, P. Bunin, A. Burazin Misura, A. Butler-nalin, A. Cakir, S. Callier, S. Campbell, K. Canderan, K. Cankocak, A. Cappati, S. Caregari, S. Carron, C. Carty, A. Cauchois, L. Ceard, S. Cerci, P. J. Chang, R. M. Chatterjee, S. Chatterjee, P. Chattopadhyay, T. Chatzistavrou, M. S. Chaudhary, A. Chauhan, J. A. Chen, J. Chen, Y. Chen, K. Cheng, H. Cheung, J. Chhikara, A. Chiron, M. Chiusi, D. Chokheli, R. Chudasama, E. Clement, S. Coco Mendez, D. Coko, K. Coskun, F. Couderc, B. Crossman, Z. Cui, T. Cuisset, G. Cummings, E. M. Curtis, M. D'Alfonso, J. D-hler-ball, O. Dadazhanova, J. Damgov, I. Das, S. DasGupta, P. Dauncey, A. David Tinoco Mendes, G. Davies, O. Davignon, P. deBarbaroC. DeLa, M. DeSilva, A. DeWit, P. Debbins, M. M. Defranchis, E. Delagnes, P. Devouge, C. Dewangan, G. DiGuglielmo, L. Diehl, K. Dilsiz, G. G. Dincer, J. Dittmann, M. Dragicevic, D. Du, B. Dubinchik, S. Dugad, F. Dulucq, I. Dumanoglu, B. Duran, S. Dutta, V. Dutta, A. Dychkant, M. D\"unser, T. Edberg, I. T. Ehle, A. El Berni, F. Elias, S. C. Eno, E. N. Erdogan, B. Erkmen, Y. Ershov, E. Y. Ertorer, S. Extier, L. Eychenne, Y. E. Fedar, G. Fedi, J. P. Figueiredo De De S\'a Sousa De Almeida, B. A. Fontana Santos Santos Alves, E. Frahm, K. Francis, J. Freeman, T. French, F. Gaede, P. K. Gandhi, S. Ganjour, A. Garcia-Bellido, F. Gastaldi, L. Gazi, Z. Gecse, H. Gerwig, O. Gevin, S. Ghosh, S. Ghosh, K. Gill, S. Gleyzer, N. Godinovic, M. Goek, P. Goettlicher, R. Goff, A. Golunov, B. Gonultas, J. D. Gonz\'alez Mart\'inez, N. Gorbounov, L. Gouskos, A. Gray, L. Gray, C. Grieco, S. Groenroos, D. Groner, A. Gruber, A. Grummer, S. Gr\"onroos, F. Guilloux, Y. Guler, A. D. Gungordu, J. Guo, K. Guo, E. Gurpinar Guler, H. K. Gutti, A. A. Guvenli, E. G\"ulmez, B. Hacisahinoglu, Y. Halkin, Y. Halkin, G. Hamilton Ilha Machado, H. S. Hare, K. Hatakeyama, A. H. Heering, V. Hegde, U. Heintz, N. Hinton, A. Hinzmann, J. Hirschauer, D. Hitlin, \.I. Hos, B. Hou, X. Hou, A. Howard, C. Howe, H. Hsieh, T. Hsu, H. Hua, F. Hummer, M. Imran, J. Incandela, E. Iren, B. Isildak, P. S. Jackson, W. J. Jackson, S. Jain, P. Jana, J. Jaroslavceva, S. Jena, A. Jige, P. P. Jordano, U. Joshi, K. Kaadze, A. Kafizov, L. Kalipoliti, A. Kallil Tharayil, O. Kaluzinska, S. Kamble, A. Kaminskiy, M. Kanemura, H. Kanso, Y. Kao, A. Kapic, C. Kapsiak, V. Karjavine, S. Karmakar, A. Karneyeu, M. Kaya, A. Kayis Topaksu, B. Kaynak, Y. Kazhykarim, F. A. Khan, A. Khudiakov, J. Kieseler, R. S. Kim, T. Klijnsma, E. G. Kloiber, M. Klute, Z. Kocak, K. R. Kodali, K. Koetz, T. Kolberg, O. B. Kolcu, J. R. Komaragiri, M. Komm, I. Kopsalis, H. A. Krause, M. A. Krawczyk, T. R. Krishnaswamy Vinayakam, K. Kristiansen, A. Kristic, M. Krohn, B. Kronheim, K. Kr\"uger, C. Kudtarkar, S. Kulis, M. Kumar, N. Kumar, S. Kumar, R. Kumar Verma, S. Kunori, A. Kunts, A. Kunts, C. Kuo, A. Kurenkov, V. Kuryatkov, S. Kyre, J. Ladenson, K. Lamichhane, G. Landsberg, J. Langford, A. Laudrain, R. Laughlin, J. Lawhorn, O. Le Dortz, S. W. Lee, A. Lektauers, D. Lelas, M. Leon, L. Levchuk, A. J. Li, J. Li, Y. Li, Z. Liang, H. Liao, K. Lin, W. Lin, Z. Lin, D. Lincoln, L. Linssen, A. Litomin, A. Litomin, G. Liu, Y. Liu, A. Lobanov, V. Lohezic, T. Loiseau, C. Lu, R. Lu, S. Y. Lu, P. Lukens, M. Mackenzie, A. Magnan, F. Magniette, A. Mahjoub, D. Mahon, G. Majumder, V. Makarenko, V. Makarenko, A. Malakhov, L. Malgeri, S. Mallios, C. Mandloi, A. Mankel, M. Mannelli, J. Mans, C. Mantilla, G. Martinez, C. Massa, P. Masterson, M. Matthewman, V. Matveev, S. Mayekar, I. Mazlov, A. Mehta, A. Mestvirishvili, Y. Miao, G. Milella, I. R. Mirza, P. Mitra, S. Moccia, G. B. Mohanty, F. Monti, F. Moortgat, S. Murthy, J. Music, Y. Musienko, S. Nabili, S. Nayak, J. W. Nelson, A. Nema, I. Neutelings, J. Niedziela, A. Nikitenko, D. Noonan, M. Noy, K. Nurdan, S. Obraztsov, C. Ochando, H. Ogul, J. Olsson, Y. Onel, S. Ozkorucuklu, E. Paganis, P. Palit, R. Pan, S. Pandey, F. Pantaleo, C. Papageorgakis, S. Paramesvaran, M. M. Paranjpe, S. Parolia, A. G. Parsons, P. Parygin, M. Paulini, C. Paus, K. Pe\~nal\'o, K. Pedro, V. Pekic, T. Peltola, B. Peng, A. Perego, D. Perini, A. Petrilli, H. Pham, T. Pierre-Emile, S. K. Podem, V. Popov, L. Portales, L. Portales, O. Potok, P. B. Pradeep, R. Pramanik, H. Prosper, M. Prvan, S. R. Qasim, H. Qu, T. Quast, A. Quiroga Trivino, L. Rabour, N. Raicevic, H. Rajpoot, M. A. Rao, K. Rapacz, W. Redjeb, M. Reinecke, M. Revering, A. Roberts, J. Rohlf, P. Rosado, A. Rose, S. Rothman, P. K. Rout, M. Rovere, P. Rumerio, R. Rusack, L. Rygaard, V. Ryjov, S. Sadivnycha, M. \"O. Sahin, U. Sakarya, R. Salerno, R. Saradhy, M. Saraf, K. Sarbandi, M. A. Sarkisla, I. Satyshev, N. Saud, J. Sauvan, G. Schindler, A. Schmidt, I. Schmidt, M. H. Schmitt, A. Sculac, T. Sculac, A. Sedelnikov, C. Seez, F. Sefkow, D. Selivanova, M. Selvaggi, V. Sergeychik, H. Sert, M. Shahid, P. Sharma, R. Sharma, S. Sharma, M. Shelake, A. Shenai, C. W. Shih, R. Shinde, D. Shmygol, R. Shukla, E. Sicking, P. Silva, C. Simsek, E. Simsek, B. K. Sirasva, Y. Sirois, S. Song, Y. Song, G. Soudais, S. Sriram, R. R. StJacques, A. G. StahlLeiton, A. Steen, J. Stein, J. Strait, N. Strobbe, X. Su, E. Sukhov, A. Suleiman, D. Sunar Cerci, P. Suryadevara, K. Swain, C. Syal, B. Tali, K. Tanay, W. Tang, A. Tanvir, J. Tao, A. Tarabini, T. Tatli, R. Taylor, Z. C. Taysi, G. Teafoe, C. Z. Tee, W. Terrill, D. Thienpont, R. Thomas, M. Titov, C. Todd, E. Todd, M. Toms, A. Tosun, J. Troska, L. Tsai, Z. Tsamalaidze, D. Tsionou, G. Tsipolitis, M. Tsirigoti, R. Tu, S. N. Tural Polat, S. Undleeb, E. Usai, E. Uslan, V. Ustinov, E. Vernazza, O. Viahin, O. Viazlo, P. Vichoudis, A. Vijay, T. Virdee, E. Voirin, M. Vojinovic, N. Voytishin, T. \'A. V\'ami, A. Wade, D. Walter, C. Wang, F. Wang, J. Wang, K. Wang, X. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, E. Wanlin, M. Wayne, J. Wetzel, A. Whitbeck, R. Wickwire, D. Wilmot, J. Wilson, H. Wu, M. Xiao, J. Yang, B. Yazici, Y. Ye, T. Yetkin, R. Yi, R. Yohay, T. Yu, C. Yuan, X. Yuan, O. Yuksel, I. YushmanoV, I. Yusuff, A. Zabi, D. Zareckis, A. Zarubin, P. Zehetner, A. Zghiche, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, H. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. Zhang, Z. Zhang, X. Zhao, J. Zhong, Y. Zhou, \c{C}. Zorbilmez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-independent interactions of Dirac Fermionic Dark Matter in the composite Higgs models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12483v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: According to recent measurements, dark matter magnetic dipole moment is strongly constrained. In the composite Higgs models the magnetic dipole moment of the Dirac dark matter fermion and its mass can be suppressed by the approximate U(1) symmetry. We consider E_6 inspired composite Higgs model (E_6CHM) with U(1) symmetry violating operators, which give rise to dark matter's mass and coupling constant to Higgs boson. The dependence of the spin-independent dark matter-nucleon scattering cross section on the E_6CHM parameters is explored. We argue that there are regions of the parameter space which are still safe from all current constraints and may lead to spectacular LHC signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12483v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. G. Belyakova, R. Nevzorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LHC EFT WG Note: SMEFT predictions, event reweighting, and simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14620v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This note gives an overview of the tools for predicting expectations in the Standard Model effective field theory (SMEFT) at the tree level and one loop available through event generators. Methods of event reweighting, the separate simulation of squared matrix elements, and the simulation of the full SMEFT process are compared in terms of statistical efficacy and potential biases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14620v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Belvedere (ed.), Saptaparna Bhattacharya (ed.), Giacomo Boldrini (ed.), Suman Chatterjee (ed.), Alessandro Calandri (ed.), Sergio S\'anchez Cruz (ed.), Jennet Dickinson (ed.), Franz J. Glessgen (ed.), Reza Goldouzian (ed.), Alexander Grohsjean (ed.), Laurids Jeppe (ed.), Charlotte Knight (ed.), Olivier Mattelaer (ed.), Kelci Mohrman (ed.), Hannah Nelson (ed.), Vasilije Perovic (ed.), Matteo Presilla (ed.), Robert Sch\"ofbeck (ed.), Nick Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
