<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Particle production and entropy measurement in ALICE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the main goals in the study of hadronic interactions at LHC energies is the attempt to characterize the mechanisms involved in particle production in different regimes. The charged-particle multiplicity is one of the most interesting observables in these kind of studies. Measurements of charged-particle pseudorapidity densities in pp collisions at $\sqrt{\textit{s}}$ = 13.6 TeV are presented, for the first time. Furthermore, we present a method for better understanding the collision dynamics. On the one hand, the pseudorapidity dependence of charged-particle production provides information on the partonic structure of the colliding hadrons and is sensitive to non-linear QCD evolution in the initial state. On the other hand to understand the thermal-like behavior and particle yields in pp collisions, a possible approach is to address the principles of quantum states and their entanglement in the produced system. The entanglement in the initial state has a measurable effect on the evolution of the system and is the driving mechanism behind the thermal-like behavior and particle yields observed. We describe a method to understand the level of entanglement in the initial and final states of the collision using a calculation of entropy, the final-state entropy being calculated from multiplicity distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03698v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alek Hutson (On behalf of the ALICE collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparks in the Dark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study presents a novel method for the definition of signal regions in searches for new physics at collider experiments, specifically those conducted at CERN's Large Hadron Collider. By leveraging multi-dimensional histograms with precise arithmetic and utilizing the SparkDensityTree library, it is possible to identify high-density regions within the available phase space, potentially improving sensitivity to very small signals. Inspired by an ongoing search for dark mesons at the ATLAS experiment, CMS open data is used for this proof-of-concept intentionally targeting an already excluded signal. Several signal regions are defined based on density estimates of signal and background. These preliminary regions align well with the physical properties of the signal while effectively rejecting background events. While not explored in this work, this method is also scalable, which makes it ideal for large datasets such as those expected at the high-luminosity upgrade of the LHC. Finally, this method is flexible and can be easily extended, promising a boost to the signal region definition process for new physics searches at colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04138v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olga Sunneborn Gudnadottir, Axel Gall\'en, Giulia Ripellino, Jochen Jens Heinrich, Raazesh Sainudiin, Rebeca Gonzalez Suarez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of the performance of the event reconstruction algorithms in the JSNS$^2$ experiment using a $^{252}$Cf calibration source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04153v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: JSNS$^2$ searches for short baseline neutrino oscillations with a baseline of 24~meters and a target of 17~tonnes of the Gd-loaded liquid scintillator. The correct algorithm on the event reconstruction of events, which determines the position and energy of neutrino interactions in the detector, are essential for the physics analysis of the data from the experiment. Therefore, the performance of the event reconstruction is carefully checked with calibrations using $^{252}$Cf source. This manuscript describes the methodology and the performance of the event reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04153v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. H. Lee, M. K. Cheoun, J. H. Choi, J. Y. Choi, T. Dodo, J. Goh, K. Haga, M. Harada, S. Hasegawa, W. Hwang, T. Iida, H. I. Jang, J. S. Jang, K. K. Joo, D. E. Jung, S. K. Kang, Y. Kasugai, T. Kawasaki, E. J. Kim, J. Y. Kim, S. B Kim, W. Kim, H. Kinoshita, T. Konno, I. T. Lim, C. Little, E. Marzec, T. Maruyama, S. Masuda, S. Meigo, D. H. Moon, T. Nakano, M. Niiyama, K. Nishikawa, M. Y. Pac, H. W. Park, J. S. Park, R. G. Park, S. J. M. Peeters, C. Rott, K. Sakai, S. Sakamoto, T. Shima, J. Spitz, F. Suekane, Y. Sugaya, K. Suzuya, Y. Takeuchi, Y. Yamaguchi, M. Yeh, I. S. Yeo, C. Yoo, I. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inclusive $\bar{B}\to X_s \ell^+\ell^-$ at the LHC: theory predictions and new-physics reach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03517v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present theoretical predictions for observables in inclusive $\bar{B}\to X_s \ell^+\ell^-$ suitable for measurements at hadron colliders through a sum-over-exclusive approach. At low $q^2$ we calculate the branching ratio and three angular observables. At high $q^2$ we provide the branching ratio and the ratio of the $\bar B \to X_s \ell^+\ell^-$ rate with respect to the inclusive $\bar B \to X_u \ell \bar\nu$ rate with the same phase-space cut. We compare our predictions to an extraction of the experimental rate through a sum-over-exclusive method using branching ratios of the exclusive $\bar B \to K^{(*)}\mu^+\mu^-$ modes measured at LHCb. Our analysis does not support a recent claim about a deficit in the inclusive branching ratio in the high-$q^2$ region. Finally, we present current model-independent bounds on new physics and emphasize the potential of complementary analyses of $\bar{B}\to X_s \ell^+\ell^-$ at Belle II and the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03517v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Huber, Tobias Hurth, Jack Jenkins, Enrico Lunghi, Qin Qin, K. Keri Vos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Status of the production of GEM chambers for the CMS experiment at Large Hadron Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The High Luminosity LHC phase includes an upgrade to the muon stations for the CMS Experiment. CMS trigger and muon identification performance will be crucial, and it is, therefore, necessary to install new GEM stations to extend acceptance in the high-{\eta} region. An explanation of the quality control test and an update on the status of production will be provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03677v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Benussi, S. Bianco, R. Campagnola, M. Caponero, S. Colafranceschi, S. Meola, E. Paoletti, L. Passamonti, D. Piccolo, D. Pierluigi, A. Russo, G. Saviano, R. Tesauro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pulse Shape Discrimination in JSNS$^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03679v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: JSNS$^2$ (J-PARC Sterile Neutrino Search at J-PARC Spallation Neutron Source) is an experiment that is searching for sterile neutrinos via the observation of $\bar{\nu}_{\mu} \rightarrow \bar{\nu}_e$ appearance oscillations using neutrinos with muon decay-at-rest. For this search, rejecting cosmic-ray-induced neutron events by Pulse Shape Discrimination (PSD) is essential because the JSNS$^2$ detector is located above ground, on the third floor of the building. We have achieved 95$\%$ rejection of neutron events while keeping 90$\%$ of signal, electron-like events using a data driven likelihood method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03679v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Dodo, M. K. Cheoun, J. H. Choi, J. Y. Choi, J. Goh, K. Haga, M. Harada, S. Hasegawa, W. Hwang, T. Iida, H. I. Jang, J. S. Jang, K. K. Joo, D. E. Jung, S. K. Kang, Y. Kasugai, T. Kawasaki, E. J. Kim, J. Y. Kim, S. B. Kim, W. Kim, H. Kinoshita, T. Konno, D. H. Lee, I. T. Lim, C. Little, E. Marzec, T. Maruyama, S. Masuda, S. Meigo, D. H. Moon, T. Nakano, M. Niiyama, K. Nishikawa, M. Y. Pac, H. W. Park, J. S. Park, R. G. Park, S. J. M. Peeters, C. Rott, K. Sakai, S. Sakamoto, T. Shima, C. D. Shin, J. Spitz, F. Suekane, Y. Sugaya, K. Suzuya, Y. Takeuchi, Y. Yamaguchi, M. Yeh, I. S. Yeo, C. Yoo, I. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon Track Reconstruction in the Scintillator Phase of SNO+</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03680v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The large depth of the SNO+ experiment (2070 m, 6010 m.w.e.) means that only a few muons per day pass through the detector. However, their high energy causes muon induced backgrounds which can affect multiple physics analyses. Reconstructing the muon track would allow for improved rejection for these induced backgrounds. Currently there is no muon tracker for the scintillator phase of SNO+. This poster presents a novel method of muon track reconstruction by using the high photon sampling from muons and the assumption that each PMT first registers a hit from a photon that takes the fastest possible path from the muon entry point to the PMT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03680v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jasmine Simms</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon beamtest results of high-density glass scintillator tiles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03681v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To achieve the physics goal of precisely measure the Higgs, Z, W bosons and the top quark, future electron-positron colliders require that their detector system has excellent jet energy resolution. One feasible technical option is the high granular calorimetery based on the particle flow algorithm (PFA). A new high-granularity hadronic calorimeter with glass scintillator tiles (GSHCAL) has been proposed, which focus on the significant improvement of hadronic energy resolution with a notable increase of the energy sampling fraction by using high-density glass scintillator tiles. The minimum ionizing particle (MIP) response of a glass scintillator tile is crucial to the hadronic calorimeter, so a dedicated beamtest setup was developed for testing the first batch of large-size glass scintillators. The maximum MIP response of the first batch of glass scintillator tiles can reach up to 107 p.e./MIP, which essentially meets the design requirements of the CEPC GSHCAL. An optical simulation model of a single glass scintillator tile has been established, and the simulation results are consistent with the beamtest results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03681v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dejing Du, Yong Liu, Hua Cai, Danping Chen, Zhehao Hua, Jifeng Han, Jifeng Han, Baohua Qi, Sen Qian, Jing Ren, Xinyuan Sun, Xinyuan Sun, Dong Yang, Shenghua Yin, Minghui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beam test of a baseline vertex detector prototype for CEPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03688v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Circular Electron Positron Collider (CEPC) has been proposed to enable more thorough and precise measurements of the properties of Higgs, W, and Z bosons, as well as to search for new physics. In response to the stringent performance requirements of the vertex detector for the CEPC, a baseline vertex detector prototype was tested and characterized for the first time using a 6 GeV electron beam at DESY II Test Beam Line 21. The baseline vertex detector prototype is designed with a cylindrical barrel structure that contains six double-sided detector modules (ladders). Each side of the ladder includes TaichuPix-3 sensors based on Monolithic Active Pixel Sensor (MAPS) technology, a flexible printed circuit, and a carbon fiber support structure. Additionally, the readout electronics and the Data Acquisition system were also examined during this beam test. The performance of the prototype was evaluated using an electron beam that passed through six ladders in a perpendicular direction. The offline data analysis indicates a spatial resolution of about 5 um, with detection efficiency exceeding 99 % and an impact parameter resolution of about 5.1 um. These promising results from this baseline vertex detector prototype mark a significant step toward realizing the optimal vertex detector for the CEPC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03688v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuqi Li (a, c), Tianya Wu (b), Xinhui Huang (a, c), Jia Zhou (a, c), Ziyue Yan (a, c), Wei Wang (a, c), Hao Zeng (a, c), Yiming Hu (f), Xiaoxu Zhang (f), Zhijun Liang (a, c), Wei Wei (a, c), Ying Zhang (a, c), Xiaomin Wei (e), Lei Zhang (f), Ming Qi (f), Jun Hu (a, c), Jinyu Fu (a, c), Hongyu Zhang (a, c, d), Gang Li (a), Linghui Wu (a), Mingyi Dong (a, c, d), Xiaoting Li (a, c), Raimon Casanova (h), Liang Zhang (g), Jianing Dong (g), Jia Wang (e), Ran Zheng (e), Weiguo Lu (a, c), Sebastian Grinstein (h, i), Jo\~ao Guimar\~aes da Costa (a)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upgrade of NaI(Tl) crystal encapsulation for the NEON experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03691v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Neutrino Elastic-scattering Observation with NaI(Tl) experiment (NEON) aims to detect coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering~(CE$\nu$NS) in a NaI(Tl) crystal using reactor anti-electron neutrinos at the Hanbit nuclear power plant complex. A total of 13.3 kg of NaI(Tl) crystals were initially installed in December 2020 at the tendon gallery, 23.7$\pm$0.3\,m away from the reactor core, which operates at a thermal power of 2.8\,GW. Initial engineering operation was performed from May 2021 to March 2022 and observed unexpected photomultiplier-induced noise and a decreased light yield that were induced by leakage of liquid scintillator into the detector due to weakness of detector encapsulation. We upgraded the detector encapsulation design to prevent leakage of the liquid scintillator. Meanwhile two small size detectors were replaced with large size detectors returning a total mass of 16.7\,kg. With this new design implementation, the detector system has been operating stably since April 2022 for over a year without detector gain drop. In this paper, we present an improved crystal encapsulation design and stability of the NEON experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03691v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. J. Choi, E. J. Jeon, J. Y. Kim, K. W. Kim, S. H. Kim, S. K. Kim, Y. D. Kim, Y. J. Ko, B. C. Koh, C. Ha, B. J. Park, S. H. Lee, I. S. Lee, H. Lee, H. S. Lee, J. Lee, Y. M. Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new 700 GeV scalar in the LHC data?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03711v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As an alternative to the metastability of the electroweak vacuum, resulting from perturbative calculations, one can consider a non-perturbative effective potential which, as at the beginning of the Standard Model, is restricted to the pure $\Phi^4$ sector yet consistent with the known analytical and numerical studies. In this approach, where the electroweak vacuum is now the lowest-energy state, besides the resonance of mass $m_h=$ 125 GeV defined by the quadratic shape of the potential at its minimum, the Higgs field should exhibit a second resonance with mass $(M_H)^{\rm Theor}=690\,(30)$ GeV associated with the zero-point energy determining the potential depth. In spite of its large mass, this resonance would couple to longitudinal $W$s with the same typical strength as the low-mass state at 125 GeV and represent a relatively narrow resonance, mainly produced at LHC by gluon-gluon fusion.
  In this Letter, we review LHC data suggesting a new resonance of mass $(M_H)^{\rm EXP} \sim 682\,(10)$ GeV, with a statistical significance that is far from negligible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03711v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurizio Consoli, George Rupp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summary of Working Group 4: Mixing and mixing-related $CP$ violation in the B system: $\Delta m$, $\Delta \Gamma$, $\phi_s$, $\phi_1/\alpha$, $\phi_2/\beta$, $\phi_3/\gamma$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This summary reviews contributions to the CKM 2023 workshop in Working Group 4: mixing and mixing-related $CP$ violation in B system. The theoretical and experimental progress is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03945v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agnieszka Dziurda, Felix Erben, Marc Quentin F\"uhring, Thibaud Humair, Thomas Latham, Eleftheria Malami, Pascal Reeck, Vladyslav Shtabovenko, Melissa Cruz Torres, Yuma Uematsu, K. Keri Vos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor-spin symmetry of the $P^N_{\psi}/H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N$ and $P^\Lambda_{\psi s}/H^{\Lambda}_{\Omega_{ccc}s}$ molecular states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04016v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Based on a contact lagrangian that incorporates the SU(3) flavor and SU(2) spin symmetries, we discuss the symmetry properties of the interactions among the heavy flavor meson-baryon $P_{\psi}^N$, $P_{\psi s}^\Lambda$ (with quark components [$n\bar{c}$][$nnc$], [$s\bar{c}$][$nnc$], or [$n\bar{c}$][$nsc$]) systems and di-baryon $H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N$, $H^{\Lambda}_{\Omega_{ccc}s}$ (with quark components [$nnc$][$ncc$], [$nnc$][$scc$] or [$nsc$][$ncc$]) systems ($n=u$, $d$). The light quark components of the $P_{\psi}^N$ ($P_{\psi s}^\Lambda$) and $H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N$ ($H_{\Omega_{ccc}s}^\Lambda$) systems have identical flavors, the interactions generated from the exchanges of light mesons in the $P_{\psi}^N$ ($P^\Lambda_{\psi s}$) systems should be very similar to that of the $H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N$ ($H^{\Lambda}_{\Omega_{ccc}s}$) systems. We perform the single-channel and multi-channel calculations on the $P_{\psi}^N/P^\Lambda_{\psi s}/H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N/H^{\Lambda}_{\Omega_{ccc}s}$ systems and introduce the SU(3) breaking effect to identify the different mass spectra among the $P_{\psi}^N$ ($H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N$) and $P^\Lambda_{\psi s}$ ($H^{\Lambda}_{\Omega_{ccc}s}$) systems. We suggest two kinds of evidences for the existence of the flavor-spin symmetry among the heavy flavor $P_{\psi}^N/H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N/P^\Lambda_{\psi s}/H^{\Lambda}_{\Omega_{ccc}s}$ molecule community, i.e., the mass arrangements of the $P_{\psi}^N/H_{\Omega_{ccc}}^N/P^\Lambda_{\psi s}/H^{\Lambda}_{\Omega_{ccc}s}$ mass spectra and the binding energies of the heavy flavor meson-baryon (di-baryon) systems attributed to the same contact potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04016v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kan Chen, Bo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Center-of-mass energy dependence of intrinsic-$k_T$ distributions obtained from Drell-Yan production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04088v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The internal motion of partons inside hadrons has been studied through its impact on very low transverse momentum spectra of Drell-Yan (DY) pairs created in hadron-hadron collisions. We study DY production at next-to-leading order using the Parton Branching (PB) method which describes the evolution of transverse momentum dependent parton distributions. The main focus is on studying the intrinsic transverse momentum distribution (intrinsic-$k_T$) as a function of the center-of-mass energy $\sqrt s$. While collinear parton shower Monte Carlo event generators require intrinsic transverse momentum distributions strongly dependent on $\sqrt s$, this is not the case for the PB method. We perform a detailed study of the impact of soft parton emissions. We show that by requiring a minimal transverse momentum, $q_0$, of a radiated parton, a dependence of the width of the intrinsic-$k_T$ distribution as a function of $\sqrt{s}$ is observed. This dependence becomes stronger with increasing $q_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04088v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Bubanja, H. Jung, A. Lelek, N. Raicevic, S. Taheri Monfared</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jet angularities in dijet production in proton-proton and heavy-ion collisions at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04168v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study jet angularities for dijet production at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider (RHIC) in proton-proton (pp) and nucleus-nucleus (AA) collisions at 200 GeV nucleon-nucleon center-of-mass collision energy. In particular, we provide $\mathrm{NLL}$ resummed predictions for angularity observables of groomed and ungroomed jets produced in $\rm pp$ collisions matched to next-to-leading order QCD calculations resulting in $\mathrm{NLO+NLL^\prime}$ accuracy. Our parton-level predictions are corrected for non-perturbative effects, such as hadronization and underlying event, using parton-to-hadron level transfer matrices obtained with the Sherpa event generator. Furthermore, we use the Q-Pythia and JEWEL generators to estimate the impact of the interaction between quarks and gluons produced by the parton shower with the dense medium formed in heavy-ion collisions on the considered jet angularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04168v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang-Ting Chien, Oleh Fedkevych, Daniel Reichelt, Steffen Schumann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring orbital angular momentum and spin-orbit correlation for gluons at the Electron-Ion Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04209v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In our previous work [Phys. Rev. Lett. 128, 182002 (2022)], we introduced a pioneering observable aimed at experimentally detecting the orbital angular momentum (OAM) of gluons. Our focus was on the longitudinal double spin asymmetry observed in exclusive dijet production during electron-proton scattering. We demonstrated the sensitivity of the $\cos \phi$ angular correlation between the scattered electron and proton as a probe for gluon OAM at small-$x$ and its intricate interplay with gluon helicity. This current work provides a comprehensive exposition, diving further into the aforementioned calculation with added elaboration and in-depth analysis. We reveal that, in addition to the gluon OAM, one also gains access to the spin-orbit correlation of gluons. We supplement our work with a detailed numerical analysis of our observables for the kinematics of the Electron-Ion Collider. In addition to dijet production, we also consider the recently proposed semi-inclusive diffractive deep inelastic scattering process which potentially offers experimental advantages over dijet measurements. Finally, we investigate quark-channel contributions to these processes and find an unexpected breakdown of collinear factorization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04209v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shohini Bhattacharya, Renaud Boussarie, Yoshitaka Hatta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the CKM angle $\gamma$ using the $B^{\pm}\rightarrow D^{*} h^{\pm}$ channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04277v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A measurement of the $CP$-violating observables from $B^{\pm}\rightarrow D^* K^{\pm}$ and $B^{\pm}\rightarrow D^* \pi^{\pm}$ decays is presented, where $D^* (D) $ is an admixture of $D^{*0}$ and $\bar{D}^{*0}$ ($D^0$ and $\bar{D}^0$) states and is reconstructed through the decay chains $ D^* \rightarrow D\pi^0/\gamma$ and $D \to K_S^0 \pi^+\pi^-/K_S^0 K^+K^-$. The measurement is performed by analysing the signal yield variation across the $D$ decay phase space and is independent of any amplitude model. The data sample used was collected by the LHCb experiment in proton-proton collisions and corresponds to a total integrated luminosity of 9 fb$^{-1}$ at centre-of-mass energies of 7, 8 and 13 TeV. The CKM angle $\gamma$ is determined to be $(69^{+13}_{-14})^{\circ}$ using the measured $CP$-violating observables. The hadronic parameters $r^{D^* K^{\pm}}_B, r^{D^* \pi^{\pm}}_B, \delta^{D^* K^{\pm}}_B, \delta^{D^* \pi^{\pm}}_B$, which are the ratios and strong phase differences between favoured and suppressed $B^{\pm}$ decays, are also reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04277v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2023)013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP12(2023)013</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, H. Afsharnia, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, M. Alexander, A. Alfonso Albero, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, A. Andreianov, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, D. Andreou, D. Ao, F. Archilli, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, A. Bailly-reyre, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, W. Baldini, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, M. Bartolini, F. Baryshnikov, J. M. Basels, G. Bassi, B. Batsukh, A. Battig, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, A. Beiter, S. Belin, V. Bellee, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, D. Berninghoff, H. C. Bernstein, C. Bertella, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, J. Bhom, L. Bian, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, M. P. Blago, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, D. Bobulska, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, N. Bondar, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, S. A. Bouchiba, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, M. J. Bradley, S. Braun, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, A. Buonaura, L. Buonincontri, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, A. Bursche, A. Butkevich, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, R. Calabrese, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, J. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, J. Cerasoli, D. Cervenkov, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, M. G. Chapman, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, C. A. Chavez Barajas, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, S. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, V. Chobanova, S. Cholak, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, M. F. Cicala, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, J. L. Cobbledick, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, P. Collins, T. Colombo, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, A. Danilina, P. d'Argent, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, A. Davis, O. De Aguiar Francisco, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, D. De Simone, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, C. T. Dean, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, V. Dedu, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, A. Dolmatov, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, L. Douglas, A. G. Downes, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, D. Dutta, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, C. Eirea Orro, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, S. Ek-In, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, E. Epple, S. Escher, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, L. N. Falcao, Y. Fan, B. Fang, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, S. Farry, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, L. Ferreira Lopes, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, S. Ferreres Sole, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, M. Firlej, K. M. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, T. Fiutowski, F. Fleuret, M. Fontana, F. Fontanelli, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, L. Frontini, J. Fu, Q. Fuehring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, E. Gabriel, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, H. Gao, R. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, M. Garau, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, B. Garcia Plana, F. A. Garcia Rosales, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, R. E. Geertsema, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, P. Gironella Gironell, C. Giugliano, M. A. Giza, K. Gizdov, E. L. Gkougkousis, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, A. Gomes, S. Gomez Fernandez, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, M. Guittiere, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, J. Haimberger, S. C. Haines, M. Hajheidari, T. Halewood-leagas, M. M. Halvorsen, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, T. Harrison, M. Hartmann, C. Hasse, M. Hatch, J. He, K. Heijhoff, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, D. Hill, M. Hilton, S. E. Hollitt, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Huang, X. Huang, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, P. Ibis, M. Idzik, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Inglessi, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, R. Jacobsson, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, Y. Kang, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, M. Karpov, A. M. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, F. Keizer, D. M. Keller, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Kondybayeva, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, R. Kopecna, P. Koppenburg, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, S. Kretzschmar, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, J. Kubat, S. Kubis, W. Kucewicz, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, B. K. Kutsenko, D. Lacarrere, G. Lafferty, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, R. Lane, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, S. H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, B. Leverington, A. Li, H. Li, K. Li, L. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Z. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, V. Lisovskyi, R. Litvinov, G. Liu, H. Liu, K. Liu, Q. Liu, S. Liu, Y. Liu, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, J. Lomba Castro, T. Long, I. Longstaff, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, G. H. Lovell, Y. Lu, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, S. Luchuk, M. Lucio Martinez, V. Lukashenko, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, R. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, I. Mackay, V. Macko, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. M. Madurai, A. Maevskiy, D. Maisuzenko, M. W. Majewski, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, B. Malecki, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, D. Manuzzi, C. A. Manzari, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, U. Marconi, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, P. J. Marshall, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Massafferri, M. Materok, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, L. Mcconnell, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, M. Milovanovic, M. -N. Minard, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, S. E. Mitchell, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, A. M\"odden, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, S. Mokhnenko, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, I. A. Monroy, S. Monteil, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, J. Moron, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, D. Murray, R. Murta, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, R. Newcombe, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, S. Nieswand, N. Nikitin, P. Nogga, N. S. Nolte, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, S. Okamura, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, T. Ovsiannikova, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, P. R. Pais, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, A. Pereiro Castro, P. Perret, A. Perro, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, S. Petrucci, H. Pham, A. Philippov, L. Pica, M. Piccini, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, L. Promberger, C. Prouve, V. Pugatch, V. Puill, G. Punzi, H. R. Qi, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, B. Rachwal, J. H. Rademacker, R. Rajagopalan, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, R. Ribatti, G. R. Ricart, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, D. L. Rolf, A. Rollings, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, M. Romero Lamas, A. Romero Vidal, F. Ronchetti, M. Rotondo, M. S. Rudolph, T. Ruf, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, A. Ryzhikov, J. Ryzka, J. J. Saborido Silva, N. Sagidova, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, C. Sanchez Gras, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, D. Saranin, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, A. Sarti, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, L. G. Scantlebury Smead, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, A. M. Schertz, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, M. Schubiger, N. Schulte, S. Schulte, M. H. Schune, R. Schwemmer, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, E. B. Shields, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, B. G. Siddi, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, M. Singla, N. Skidmore, R. Skuza, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, J. C. Smallwood, J. G. Smeaton, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, A. Snoch, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, I. Solovyev, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, O. Stenyakin, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, Y. Sun, P. N. Swallow, K. Swientek, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, M. Szymanski, Y. Tan, S. Taneja, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, E. Ursov, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, A. Valassi, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, M. Van Dijk, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Vesterinen, D. Vieira, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, V. Vorobyev, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, C. Vrahas, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, C. Wang, G. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, B. D. C. Westhenry, D. J. White, M. Whitehead, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, I. Williams, M. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, F. F. Wilson, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, C. P. Wong, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, Y. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, A. Xu, J. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, D. Yang, S. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zharkova, A. Zhelezov, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, Z. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, S. Zucchelli, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determination of short- and long-distance contributions in $B^{0}\to K^{*0}\mu^+\mu^-$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09102v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An amplitude analysis of the $B^0 \to K^{*0} \mu^+\mu^-$ decay is presented. The analysis is based on data collected by the LHCb experiment from proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s} = 7,\,8$ and $13$ TeV, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of $4.7$ fb$^{-1}$. For the first time, Wilson coefficients and non-local hadronic contributions are accessed directly from the unbinned data, where the latter are parameterised as a function of $q^2$ with a polynomial expansion. Wilson coefficients and non-local hadronic parameters are determined under two alternative hypotheses: the first relies on experimental information alone, while the second one includes information from theoretical predictions for the non-local contributions. Both models obtain similar results for the parameters of interest. The overall level of compatibility with the Standard Model is evaluated to be between 1.8 and 1.9 standard deviations when looking at the $\mathcal{C}_9$ Wilson coefficient alone, and between 1.3 and 1.4 standard deviations when considering the full set of $\mathcal{C}_9, \, \mathcal{C}_{10}, \, \mathcal{C}_9^\prime$ and $\mathcal{C}_{10}^\prime$ Wilson coefficients. The ranges reflect the theoretical assumptions made in the analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09102v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.052009</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109 (2024) 052009</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, M. Alexander, A. Alfonso Albero, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, A. Andreianov, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, D. Andreou, A. Anelli, D. Ao, F. Archilli, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, A. Bailly-reyre, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, W. Baldini, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, M. Bartolini, F. Baryshnikov, J. M. Basels, G. Bassi, B. Batsukh, A. Battig, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, A. Beiter, S. Belin, V. Bellee, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, H. C. Bernstein, C. Bertella, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, J. Bhom, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, M. P. Blago, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, D. Bobulska, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, N. Bondar, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, S. A. Bouchiba, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, M. J. Bradley, S. Braun, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, A. Buonaura, L. Buonincontri, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, A. Bursche, A. Butkevich, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, R. Calabrese, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, J. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, J. Castro Godinez, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, J. Cerasoli, D. Cervenkov, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, C. A. Chavez Barajas, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, S. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, V. Chobanova, S. Cholak, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, M. F. Cicala, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, J. L. Cobbledick, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, P. Collins, T. Colombo, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, A. Danilina, P. d'Argent, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, A. Davis, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, D. De Simone, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, V. Dedu, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, A. Dolmatov, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, L. Douglas, A. G. Downes, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, C. Eirea Orro, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, S. Ek-In, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, E. Epple, S. Escher, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, L. N. Falcao, Y. Fan, B. Fang, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, S. Ferreres Sole, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, M. Firlej, K. M. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, T. Fiutowski, F. Fleuret, M. Fontana, F. Fontanelli, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, L. Frontini, J. Fu, Q. Fuehring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, E. Gabriel, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, H. Gao, R. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, M. Garau, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, B. Garcia Plana, K. G. Garg, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, R. E. Geertsema, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, P. Gironella Gironell, C. Giugliano, M. A. Giza, E. L. Gkougkousis, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, A. Gomes, S. Gomez Fernandez, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, M. Guittiere, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, J. Haimberger, M. Hajheidari, T. Halewood-leagas, M. M. Halvorsen, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, T. Harrison, M. Hartmann, C. Hasse, J. He, K. Heijhoff, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, P. Herrero Gascon, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, D. Hill, S. E. Hollitt, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Huang, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, M. Idzik, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Inglessi, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, R. Jacobsson, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, Y. Kang, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, M. Karpov, A. M. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, F. Keizer, D. M. Keller, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, S. Kretzschmar, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, J. Kubat, S. Kubis, W. Kucewicz, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, B. K. Kutsenko, D. Lacarrere, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, R. Lane, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, S. H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, B. Leverington, A. Li, H. Li, K. Li, L. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, V. Lisovskyi, R. Litvinov, G. Liu, H. Liu, K. Liu, Q. Liu, S. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, J. Lomba Castro, T. Long, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, G. H. Lovell, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, S. Luchuk, M. Lucio Martinez, V. Lukashenko, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, R. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, I. Mackay, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. M. Madurai, A. Maevskiy, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, M. W. Majewski, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, B. Malecki, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, P. J. Marshall, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Massafferri, M. Materok, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, L. Mcconnell, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, S. E. Mitchell, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, A. M\"odden, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, S. Mokhnenko, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, I. A. Monroy, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, J. Moron, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. M\~unoz-Rojas, R. Murta, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, R. Newcombe, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, P. Nogga, N. S. Nolte, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, S. Okamura, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, T. Ovsiannikova, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, P. R. Pais, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, A. Pereiro Castro, P. Perret, A. Perro, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, S. Petrucci, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, V. Pugatch, V. Puill, G. Punzi, H. R. Qi, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, B. Rachwal, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, R. Ribatti, G. R. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, A. Rollings, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, M. Romero Lamas, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, T. Ruf, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, A. Ryzhikov, J. Ryzka, J. J. Saborido Silva, R. Sadek, N. Sagidova, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, C. Sanchez Gras, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, A. Sarti, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, L. G. Scantlebury Smead, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, A. M. Schertz, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, S. Schulte, M. H. Schune, R. Schwemmer, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, E. B. Shields, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, N. Skidmore, R. Skuza, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, J. C. Smallwood, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, A. Snoch, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, I. Solovyev, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, O. Stenyakin, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, Y. Sun, P. N. Swallow, K. Swientek, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, M. Szymanski, Y. Tan, S. Taneja, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, E. Ursov, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, A. Valassi, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Vesterinen, D. Vieira, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, V. Vorobyev, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, G. Vouters, C. Vrahas, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, C. Wang, G. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, B. D. C. Westhenry, D. J. White, M. Whitehead, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, F. F. Wilson, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, C. P. Wong, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, Y. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, A. Xu, J. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, D. Yang, S. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zharkova, A. Zhelezov, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, Z. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplitude analysis of the $B^{0}\to K^{*0}\mu^+\mu^-$ decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09115v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An amplitude analysis of the $B^{0}\to K^{*0}\mu^+\mu^-$ decay is presented using a dataset corresponding to an integrated luminosity of $4.7$ fb$^{-1}$ of $pp$ collision data collected with the LHCb experiment. For the first time, the coefficients associated to short-distance physics effects, sensitive to processes beyond the Standard Model, are extracted directly from the data through a $q^2$-unbinned amplitude analysis, where $q^2$ is the $\mu^+\mu^-$ invariant mass squared. Long-distance contributions, which originate from non-factorisable QCD processes, are systematically investigated and the most accurate assessment to date of their impact on the physical observables is obtained. The pattern of measured corrections to the short-distance couplings is found to be consistent with previous analyses of $b$- to $s$-quark transitions, with the largest discrepancy from the Standard Model predictions found to be at the level of 1.8 standard deviations. The global significance of the observed differences in the decay is 1.4 standard deviations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09115v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.131801</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132 (2024) 131801</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, M. Alexander, A. Alfonso Albero, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, A. Andreianov, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, D. Andreou, A. Anelli, D. Ao, F. Archilli, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, A. Bailly-reyre, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, W. Baldini, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, M. Bartolini, F. Baryshnikov, J. M. Basels, G. Bassi, B. Batsukh, A. Battig, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, A. Beiter, S. Belin, V. Bellee, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, H. C. Bernstein, C. Bertella, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, J. Bhom, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, M. P. Blago, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, D. Bobulska, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, N. Bondar, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, S. A. Bouchiba, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, M. J. Bradley, S. Braun, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, A. Buonaura, L. Buonincontri, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, A. Bursche, A. Butkevich, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, R. Calabrese, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, J. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, J. Castro Godinez, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, J. Cerasoli, D. Cervenkov, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, C. A. Chavez Barajas, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, S. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, V. Chobanova, S. Cholak, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, M. F. Cicala, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, J. L. Cobbledick, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, P. Collins, T. Colombo, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, A. Danilina, P. d'Argent, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, A. Davis, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, D. De Simone, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, V. Dedu, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, A. Dolmatov, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, L. Douglas, A. G. Downes, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, C. Eirea Orro, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, S. Ek-In, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, E. Epple, S. Escher, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, L. N. Falcao, Y. Fan, B. Fang, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, S. Ferreres Sole, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, M. Firlej, K. M. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, T. Fiutowski, F. Fleuret, M. Fontana, F. Fontanelli, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, L. Frontini, J. Fu, Q. Fuehring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, E. Gabriel, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, H. Gao, R. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, M. Garau, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, B. Garcia Plana, K. G. Garg, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, R. E. Geertsema, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, P. Gironella Gironell, C. Giugliano, M. A. Giza, E. L. Gkougkousis, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, A. Gomes, S. Gomez Fernandez, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, M. Guittiere, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, J. Haimberger, M. Hajheidari, T. Halewood-leagas, M. M. Halvorsen, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, T. Harrison, M. Hartmann, C. Hasse, J. He, K. Heijhoff, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, P. Herrero Gascon, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, D. Hill, S. E. Hollitt, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Huang, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, M. Idzik, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Inglessi, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, R. Jacobsson, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, Y. Kang, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, M. Karpov, A. M. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, F. Keizer, D. M. Keller, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, S. Kretzschmar, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, J. Kubat, S. Kubis, W. Kucewicz, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, B. K. Kutsenko, D. Lacarrere, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, R. Lane, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, S. H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, B. Leverington, A. Li, H. Li, K. Li, L. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, V. Lisovskyi, R. Litvinov, G. Liu, H. Liu, K. Liu, Q. Liu, S. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, J. Lomba Castro, T. Long, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, G. H. Lovell, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, S. Luchuk, M. Lucio Martinez, V. Lukashenko, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, R. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, I. Mackay, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. M. Madurai, A. Maevskiy, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, M. W. Majewski, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, B. Malecki, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, P. J. Marshall, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Massafferri, M. Materok, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, L. Mcconnell, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, S. E. Mitchell, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, A. M\"odden, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, S. Mokhnenko, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, I. A. Monroy, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, J. Moron, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. Mu\~noz-Rojas, R. Murta, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, R. Newcombe, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, P. Nogga, N. S. Nolte, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, S. Okamura, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, T. Ovsiannikova, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, P. R. Pais, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, A. Pereiro Castro, P. Perret, A. Perro, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, S. Petrucci, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, V. Pugatch, V. Puill, G. Punzi, H. R. Qi, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, B. Rachwal, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, R. Ribatti, G. R. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, A. Rollings, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, M. Romero Lamas, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, T. Ruf, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, A. Ryzhikov, J. Ryzka, J. J. Saborido Silva, R. Sadek, N. Sagidova, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, C. Sanchez Gras, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, A. Sarti, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, L. G. Scantlebury Smead, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, A. M. Schertz, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, S. Schulte, M. H. Schune, R. Schwemmer, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, E. B. Shields, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, N. Skidmore, R. Skuza, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, J. C. Smallwood, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, A. Snoch, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, I. Solovyev, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, O. Stenyakin, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, Y. Sun, P. N. Swallow, K. Swientek, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, M. Szymanski, Y. Tan, S. Taneja, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, E. Ursov, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, A. Valassi, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Vesterinen, D. Vieira, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, V. Vorobyev, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, G. Vouters, C. Vrahas, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, C. Wang, G. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, B. D. C. Westhenry, D. J. White, M. Whitehead, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, F. F. Wilson, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, C. P. Wong, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, Y. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, A. Xu, J. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, D. Yang, S. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zharkova, A. Zhelezov, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, Z. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Final CONUS results on coherent elastic neutrino nucleus scattering at the Brokdorf reactor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07684v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The CONUS experiment studies coherent elastic neutrino nucleus scattering in four 1 kg germanium spectrometers. Low ionization energy thresholds of 210 eV were achieved. The detectors were operated inside an optimized shield at the Brokdorf nuclear power plant which provided a reactor antineutrino flux of up to $2.3\cdot10^{13}$ cm$^{-2}$s$^{-1}$. In the final phase of data collection at this site, the constraints on the neutrino interaction rate were improved by an order of magnitude as compared to the previous CONUS analysis. The new limit of less than 0.34 signal events kg$^{-1}$d$^{-1}$ is within a factor 2 of the rate predicted by the Standard Model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07684v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Ackermann, H. Bonet, A. Bonhomme, C. Buck, K. F\"ulber, J. Hakenm\"uller, J. Hempfling, J. Henrichs, G. Heusser, M. Lindner, W. Maneschg, T. Rink, E. Sanchez Garcia, J. Stauber, H. Strecker, R. Wink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved measurements of the Dalitz decays $\eta/\eta'\rightarrow\gamma e^{+}e^{-}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09136v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Based on a data sample of 10 billion $J/\psi$ events collected with the BESIII detector, improved measurements of the Dalitz decays $\eta/\eta'\rightarrow\gamma e^+e^-$ are performed, where the $\eta$ and $\eta'$ are produced through the radiative decays $J/\psi\rightarrow\gamma \eta/\eta'$. The branching fractions of $\eta\rightarrow\gamma e^+e^-$ and $\eta'\rightarrow\gamma e^+e^-$ are measured to be $(7.07 \pm 0.05 \pm 0.23)\times10^{-3}$ and $(4.83\pm0.07\pm0.14)\times10^{-4}$, respectively. Within the single pole model, the parameter of electromagnetic transition form factor for $\eta\rightarrow\gamma e^+e^-$ is determined to be $\Lambda_{\eta}=(0.749 \pm 0.027 \pm 0.007)~ {\rm GeV}/c^{2}$. Within the multi-pole model, we extract the electromagnetic transition form factors for $\eta'\rightarrow\gamma e^+e^-$ to be $\Lambda_{\eta'} = (0.802 \pm 0.007\pm 0.008)~ {\rm GeV}/c^{2}$ and $\gamma_{\eta'} = (0.113\pm0.010\pm0.002)~ {\rm GeV}/c^{2}$. The results are consistent with both theoretical predictions and previous measurements. The characteristic sizes of the interaction regions for the $\eta$ and $\eta'$ are calculated to be $(0.645 \pm 0.023 \pm 0.007 )~ {\rm fm}$ and $(0.596 \pm 0.005 \pm 0.006)~ {\rm fm}$, respectively. In addition, we search for the dark photon in $\eta/\eta^\prime\rightarrow\gamma e^{+}e^{-}$, and the upper limits of the branching fractions as a function of the dark photon are given at 90\% confidence level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09136v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.072001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 7, 072001</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> BESIII Collaboration, M. Ablikim, M. N. Achasov, P. Adlarson, O. Afedulidis, X. C. Ai, R. Aliberti, A. Amoroso, Q. An, Y. Bai, O. Bakina, I. Balossino, Y. Ban, H. -R. Bao, V. Batozskaya, K. Begzsuren, N. Berger, M. Berlowski, M. Bertani, D. Bettoni, F. Bianchi, E. Bianco, A. Bortone, I. Boyko, R. A. Briere, A. Brueggemann, H. Cai, X. Cai, A. Calcaterra, G. F. Cao, N. Cao, S. A. Cetin, J. F. Chang, W. L. Chang, G. R. Che, G. Chelkov, C. Chen, C. H. Chen, Chao Chen, G. Chen, H. S. Chen, M. L. Chen, S. J. Chen, S. L. Chen, S. M. Chen, T. Chen, X. R. Chen, X. T. Chen, Y. B. Chen, Y. Q. Chen, Z. J. Chen, Z. Y. Chen, S. K. Choi, X. Chu, G. Cibinetto, F. Cossio, J. J. Cui, H. L. Dai, J. P. Dai, A. Dbeyssi, R. E. de Boer, D. Dedovich, C. Q. Deng, Z. Y. Deng, A. Denig, I. Denysenko, M. Destefanis, F. De Mori, B. Ding, X. X. Ding, Y. Ding, Y. Ding, J. Dong, L. Y. Dong, M. Y. Dong, X. Dong, M. C. Du, S. X. Du, Z. H. Duan, P. Egorov, Y. H. Fan, J. Fang, J. Fang, S. S. Fang, W. X. Fang, Y. Fang, Y. Q. Fang, R. Farinelli, L. Fava, F. Feldbauer, G. Felici, C. Q. Feng, J. H. Feng, Y. T. Feng, K. Fischer, M. Fritsch, C. D. Fu, J. L. Fu, Y. W. Fu, H. Gao, Y. N. Gao, Yang Gao, S. Garbolino, I. Garzia, P. T. Ge, Z. W. Ge, C. Geng, E. M. Gersabeck, A. Gilman, K. Goetzen, L. Gong, W. X. Gong, W. Gradl, S. Gramigna, M. Greco, M. H. Gu, Y. T. Gu, C. Y. Guan, Z. L. Guan, A. Q. Guo, L. B. Guo, M. J. Guo, R. P. Guo, Y. P. Guo, A. Guskov, J. Gutierrez, K. L. Han, T. T. Han, X. Q. Hao, F. A. Harris, K. K. He, K. L. He, F. H. Heinsius, C. H. Heinz, Y. K. Heng, C. Herold, T. Holtmann, P. C. Hong, G. Y. Hou, X. T. Hou, Y. R. Hou, Z. L. Hou, B. Y. Hu, H. M. Hu, J. F. Hu, T. Hu, Y. Hu, G. S. Huang, K. X. Huang, L. Q. Huang, X. T. Huang, Y. P. Huang, T. Hussain, F. H\"olzken, N H\"usken, N. in der Wiesche, M. Irshad, J. Jackson, S. Janchiv, J. H. Jeong, Q. Ji, Q. P. Ji, W. Ji, X. B. Ji, X. L. Ji, Y. Y. Ji, X. Q. Jia, Z. K. Jia, D. Jiang, H. B. Jiang, P. C. Jiang, S. S. Jiang, T. J. Jiang, X. S. Jiang, Y. Jiang, J. B. Jiao, J. K. Jiao, Z. Jiao, S. Jin, Y. Jin, M. Q. Jing, X. M. Jing, T. Johansson, S. Kabana, N. Kalantar-Nayestanaki, X. L. Kang, X. S. Kang, M. Kavatsyuk, B. C. Ke, V. Khachatryan, A. Khoukaz, R. Kiuchi, O. B. Kolcu, B. Kopf, M. Kuessner, X. Kui, A. Kupsc, W. K\"uhn, J. J. Lane, P. Larin, L. Lavezzi, T. T. Lei, Z. H. Lei, H. Leithoff, M. Lellmann, T. Lenz, C. Li, C. Li, C. H. Li, Cheng Li, D. M. Li, F. Li, G. Li, H. Li, H. B. Li, H. J. Li, H. N. Li, Hui Li, J. R. Li, J. S. Li, Ke Li, L. J Li, L. K. Li, Lei Li, M. H. Li, P. R. Li, Q. M. Li, Q. X. Li, R. Li, S. X. Li, T. Li, W. D. Li, W. G. Li, X. Li, X. H. Li, X. L. Li, Xiaoyu Li, Y. G. Li, Z. J. Li, Z. X. Li, C. Liang, H. Liang, H. Liang, Y. F. Liang, Y. T. Liang, G. R. Liao, L. Z. Liao, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, A. Limphirat, D. X. Lin, T. Lin, B. J. Liu, B. X. Liu, C. Liu, C. X. Liu, F. H. Liu, Fang Liu, Feng Liu, G. M. Liu, H. Liu, H. B. Liu, H. M. Liu, Huanhuan Liu, Huihui Liu, J. B. Liu, J. Y. Liu, K. Liu, K. Y. Liu, Ke Liu, L. Liu, L. C. Liu, Lu Liu, M. H. Liu, P. L. Liu, Q. Liu, S. B. Liu, T. Liu, W. K. Liu, W. M. Liu, X. Liu, X. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. B. Liu, Z. A. Liu, Z. D. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, X. C. Lou, F. X. Lu, H. J. Lu, J. G. Lu, X. L. Lu, Y. Lu, Y. P. Lu, Z. H. Lu, C. L. Luo, M. X. Luo, T. Luo, X. L. Luo, X. R. Lyu, Y. F. Lyu, F. C. Ma, H. Ma, H. L. Ma, J. L. Ma, L. L. Ma, M. M. Ma, Q. M. Ma, R. Q. Ma, X. T. Ma, X. Y. Ma, Y. Ma, Y. M. Ma, F. E. Maas, M. Maggiora, S. Malde, A. Mangoni, Y. J. Mao, Z. P. Mao, S. Marcello, Z. X. Meng, J. G. Messchendorp, G. Mezzadri, H. Miao, T. J. Min, R. E. Mitchell, X. H. Mo, B. Moses, N. Yu. Muchnoi, J. Muskalla, Y. Nefedov, F. Nerling, I. B. Nikolaev, Z. Ning, S. Nisar, Q. L. Niu, W. D. Niu, Y. Niu, S. L. Olsen, Q. Ouyang, S. Pacetti, X. Pan, Y. Pan, A. Pathak, P. Patteri, Y. P. Pei, M. Pelizaeus, H. P. Peng, Y. Y. Peng, K. Peters, J. L. Ping, R. G. Ping, S. Plura, V. Prasad, F. Z. Qi, H. Qi, H. R. Qi, M. Qi, T. Y. Qi, S. Qian, W. B. Qian, C. F. Qiao, J. J. Qin, L. Q. Qin, X. S. Qin, Z. H. Qin, J. F. Qiu, S. Q. Qu, Z. H. Qu, C. F. Redmer, K. J. Ren, A. Rivetti, M. Rolo, G. Rong, Ch. Rosner, S. N. Ruan, N. Salone, A. Sarantsev, Y. Schelhaas, K. Schoenning, M. Scodeggio, K. Y. Shan, W. Shan, X. Y. Shan, J. F. Shangguan, L. G. Shao, M. Shao, C. P. Shen, H. F. Shen, W. H. Shen, X. Y. Shen, B. A. Shi, H. C. Shi, J. L. Shi, J. Y. Shi, Q. Q. Shi, R. S. Shi, S. Y. Shi, X. Shi, J. J. Song, T. Z. Song, W. M. Song, Y. J. Song, S. Sosio, S. Spataro, F. Stieler, Y. J. Su, G. B. Sun, G. X. Sun, H. Sun, H. K. Sun, J. F. Sun, K. Sun, L. Sun, S. S. Sun, T. Sun, W. Y. Sun, Y. Sun, Y. J. Sun, Y. Z. Sun, Z. Q. Sun, Z. T. Sun, C. J. Tang, G. Y. Tang, J. Tang, Y. A. Tang, L. Y. Tao, Q. T. Tao, M. Tat, J. X. Teng, V. Thoren, W. H. Tian, Y. Tian, Z. F. Tian, I. Uman, Y. Wan, S. J. Wang, B. Wang, B. L. Wang, Bo Wang, D. Y. Wang, F. Wang, H. J. Wang, J. P. Wang, K. Wang, L. L. Wang, M. Wang, Meng Wang, N. Y. Wang, S. Wang, S. Wang, T. Wang, T. J. Wang, W. Wang, W. Wang, W. P. Wang, X. Wang, X. F. Wang, X. J. Wang, X. L. Wang, X. N. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. D. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. L. Wang, Y. N. Wang, Y. Q. Wang, Yaqian Wang, Yi Wang, Z. Wang, Z. L. Wang, Z. Y. Wang, Ziyi Wang, D. Wei, D. H. Wei, F. Weidner, S. P. Wen, Y. R. Wen, U. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. Wolke, L. Wollenberg, C. Wu, J. F. Wu, L. H. Wu, L. J. Wu, X. Wu, X. H. Wu, Y. Wu, Y. H. Wu, Y. J. Wu, Z. Wu, L. Xia, X. M. Xian, B. H. Xiang, T. Xiang, D. Xiao, G. Y. Xiao, S. Y. Xiao, Y. L. Xiao, Z. J. Xiao, C. Xie, X. H. Xie, Y. Xie, Y. G. Xie, Y. H. Xie, Z. P. Xie, T. Y. Xing, C. F. Xu, C. J. Xu, G. F. Xu, H. Y. Xu, Q. J. Xu, Q. N. Xu, W. Xu, W. L. Xu, X. P. Xu, Y. C. Xu, Z. P. Xu, Z. S. Xu, F. Yan, L. Yan, W. B. Yan, W. C. Yan, X. Q. Yan, H. J. Yang, H. L. Yang, H. X. Yang, Tao Yang, Y. Yang, Y. F. Yang, Y. X. Yang, Yifan Yang, Z. W. Yang, Z. P. Yao, M. Ye, M. H. Ye, J. H. Yin, Z. Y. You, B. X. Yu, C. X. Yu, G. Yu, J. S. Yu, T. Yu, X. D. Yu, C. Z. Yuan, J. Yuan, L. Yuan, S. C. Yuan, Y. Yuan, Z. Y. Yuan, C. X. Yue, A. A. Zafar, F. R. Zeng, S. H. Zeng, X. Zeng, Y. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, X. Y. Zhai, Y. C. Zhai, Y. H. Zhan, A. Q. Zhang, B. L. Zhang, B. X. Zhang, D. H. Zhang, G. Y. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. C. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. Q. Zhang, H. Y. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. J. Zhang, J. L. Zhang, J. Q. Zhang, J. W. Zhang, J. X. Zhang, J. Y. Zhang, J. Z. Zhang, Jianyu Zhang, L. M. Zhang, Lei Zhang, P. Zhang, Q. Y. Zhang, Shuihan Zhang, Shulei Zhang, X. D. Zhang, X. M. Zhang, X. Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. T. Zhang, Y. H. Zhang, Y. M. Zhang, Yan Zhang, Yao Zhang, Z. D. Zhang, Z. H. Zhang, Z. L. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, G. Zhao, J. Y. Zhao, J. Z. Zhao, Lei Zhao, Ling Zhao, M. G. Zhao, R. P. Zhao, S. J. Zhao, Y. B. Zhao, Y. X. Zhao, Z. G. Zhao, A. Zhemchugov, B. Zheng, J. P. Zheng, W. J. Zheng, Y. H. Zheng, B. Zhong, X. Zhong, H. Zhou, J. Y. Zhou, L. P. Zhou, X. Zhou, X. K. Zhou, X. R. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, Y. Z. Zhou, J. Zhu, K. Zhu, K. J. Zhu, L. Zhu, L. X. Zhu, S. H. Zhu, S. Q. Zhu, T. J. Zhu, W. J. Zhu, Y. C. Zhu, Z. A. Zhu, J. H. Zou, J. Zu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unfolding environmental $\gamma$ flux spectrum with portable CZT detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12034v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Environmental $\gamma$-rays constitute a crucial source of background in various nuclear, particle and quantum physics experiments. To evaluate the flux rate and the spectrum of $\gamma$ background, we have developed a novel and straightforward approach to reconstruct the environmental $\gamma$ flux spectrum by applying a portable CZT $\gamma$ detector and iterative Bayesian unfolding, which possesses excellent transferability for broader applications. In this paper, the calibration and GEANT4 Monte-Carlo modeling of the CZT detector, the unfolding procedure as well as the uncertainty estimation are demonstrated in detail. The reconstructed spectrum reveals an environmental $\gamma$ flux intensity of $3.3\pm 0.9\times 10^{7}$~ (m$^2\cdot$sr$\cdot$hour)$^{-1}$ ranging from 73 to 3033~keV, along with characteristic peaks primarily arising from $^{232}$Th series, $^{238}$U series and $^{40}$K. We also give an instance of background rate evaluation with the unfolded spectrum for validation of the approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12034v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2024.169315</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nuclear Inst. and Methods in Physics Research, A (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Taiyuan Liu, Mingxuan Xue, Haiping Peng, Kangkang Zhao, Deyong Duan, Yichao Wang, Changqing Feng, Yifeng Wei, Qing Lin, Zizong Xu, Xiaolian Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CCube reconstruction algorithm for the SoLid experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03580v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The SoLid experiment is a very-short-baseline experiment aimed at searching for nuclear reactor-produced active to sterile antineutrino oscillations. The detection principle is based on the pairing of two types of solid scintillators: polyvinyl toluene and $^6$LiF:ZnS(Ag), which is a new technology used in this field of Physics. In addition to good neutron-gamma discrimination, this setup allows the detector to be highly segmented (the basic detection unit is a 5 cm side cube). High segmentation provides numerous advantages, including the precise location of Inverse Beta Decay (IBD) products, the derivation of the considerate antineutrino energy estimator, and a powerful background reduction tool based on the topological signature of the signal. Finally, the system is read out by a network of wavelength-shifting fibres coupled to a photodetector (MPPC). This paper describes the design of the reconstruction algorithm that allows maximum use of the granularity of the detector. The goal of the algorithm is to convert the output of the optical-fibre readout to the list of the detection units from which it originated. This paper provides a performance comparison for three methods and concludes with a choice of the baseline approach for the experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03580v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> The SoLid collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
