<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 02:45:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of branching fractions, CP asymmetry, and isospin asymmetry for $\boldsymbol{B\rightarrow\rho\gamma}$ decays using Belle and Belle II data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present measurements of $B^{+}\rightarrow\rho^{+}\gamma$ and $B^{0}\rightarrow\rho^{0}\gamma$ decays using a combined data sample of $772 \times 10^6$ $B\overline{B}$ pairs collected by the Belle experiment and $387\times 10^6$ $B\overline{B}$ pairs collected by the Belle II experiment in $e^{+}e^{-}$ collisions at the $\Upsilon (4S)$ resonance. After an optimized selection, a simultaneous fit to the Belle and Belle II data sets yields $114\pm 12$ $B^{+}\rightarrow\rho^{+}\gamma$ and $99\pm 12$ $B^{0}\rightarrow\rho^{0}\gamma$ decays. The measured branching fractions are $(13.1^{+2.0 +1.3}_{-1.9 -1.2})\times 10^{-7}$ and $(7.5\pm 1.3^{+1.0}_{-0.8})\times 10^{-7}$ for $B^{+}\rightarrow\rho^{+}\gamma$ and $B^{0}\rightarrow\rho^{0}\gamma$ decays, respectively, where the first uncertainty is statistical and the second is systematic. We also measure the isospin asymmetry $A_{\rm I}(B\rightarrow\rho\gamma)=(10.9^{+11.2 +7.8}_{-11.7 -7.3})\%$ and the direct CP asymmetry $A_{CP}(B^{+}\rightarrow\rho^{+}\gamma)=(-8.2\pm 15.2^{+1.6}_{-1.2})\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08984v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Belle II Collaboration, I. Adachi, K. Adamczyk, L. Aggarwal, H. Aihara, N. Akopov, A. Aloisio, N. Anh Ky, D. M. Asner, H. Atmacan, T. Aushev, V. Aushev, M. Aversano, R. Ayad, V. Babu, H. Bae, S. Bahinipati, P. Bambade, Sw. Banerjee, S. Bansal, M. Barrett, J. Baudot, A. Baur, A. Beaubien, F. Becherer, J. Becker, J. V. Bennett, F. U. Bernlochner, V. Bertacchi, M. Bertemes, E. Bertholet, M. Bessner, S. Bettarini, B. Bhuyan, F. Bianchi, L. Bierwirth, T. Bilka, S. Bilokin, D. Biswas, A. Bobrov, D. Bodrov, A. Bolz, A. Bondar, A. Bozek, M. Bra\v{c}ko, P. Branchini, R. A. Briere, T. E. Browder, A. Budano, S. Bussino, M. Campajola, L. Cao, G. Casarosa, C. Cecchi, J. Cerasoli, M. -C. Chang, P. Chang, R. Cheaib, P. Cheema, B. G. Cheon, K. Chilikin, K. Chirapatpimol, H. -E. Cho, K. Cho, S. -K. Choi, S. Choudhury, L. Corona, S. Das, F. Dattola, E. De La Cruz-Burelo, S. A. De La Motte, G. De Nardo, M. De Nuccio, G. De Pietro, R. de Sangro, M. Destefanis, R. Dhamija, A. Di Canto, F. Di Capua, J. Dingfelder, Z. Dole\v{z}al, T. V. Dong, M. Dorigo, K. Dort, D. Dossett, S. Dreyer, S. Dubey, G. Dujany, P. Ecker, M. Eliachevitch, D. Epifanov, P. Feichtinger, T. Ferber, D. Ferlewicz, T. Fillinger, C. Finck, G. Finocchiaro, A. Fodor, F. Forti, A. Frey, B. G. Fulsom, A. Gabrielli, E. Ganiev, M. Garcia-Hernandez, R. Garg, G. Gaudino, V. Gaur, A. Gaz, A. Gellrich, G. Ghevondyan, D. Ghosh, H. Ghumaryan, G. Giakoustidis, R. Giordano, A. Giri, A. Glazov, B. Gobbo, R. Godang, O. Gogota, P. Goldenzweig, W. Gradl, T. Grammatico, E. Graziani, D. Greenwald, Z. Gruberov\'a, T. Gu, Y. Guan, K. Gudkova, S. Halder, Y. Han, T. Hara, H. Hayashii, S. Hazra, M. T. Hedges, A. Heidelbach, I. Heredia de la Cruz, M. Hern\'andez Villanueva, T. Higuchi, M. Hoek, M. Hohmann, P. Horak, C. -L. Hsu, T. Humair, T. Iijima, K. Inami, N. Ipsita, A. Ishikawa, R. Itoh, M. Iwasaki, P. Jackson, W. W. Jacobs, E. -J. Jang, Q. P. Ji, S. Jia, Y. Jin, K. K. Joo, H. Junkerkalefeld, D. Kalita, A. B. Kaliyar, J. Kandra, K. H. Kang, G. Karyan, T. Kawasaki, F. Keil, C. Kiesling, C. -H. Kim, D. Y. Kim, K. -H. Kim, Y. -K. Kim, H. Kindo, K. Kinoshita, P. Kody\v{s}, T. Koga, S. Kohani, K. Kojima, A. Korobov, S. Korpar, E. Kovalenko, R. Kowalewski, T. M. G. Kraetzschmar, P. Kri\v{z}an, P. Krokovny, T. Kuhr, J. Kumar, M. Kumar, R. Kumar, K. Kumara, T. Kunigo, A. Kuzmin, Y. -J. Kwon, S. Lacaprara, Y. -T. Lai, T. Lam, L. Lanceri, J. S. Lange, M. Laurenza, K. Lautenbach, R. Leboucher, F. R. Le Diberder, M. J. Lee, D. Levit, P. M. Lewis, C. Li, L. K. Li, Y. Li, Y. B. Li, J. Libby, M. H. Liu, Q. Y. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, D. Liventsev, S. Longo, T. Lueck, C. Lyu, Y. Ma, M. Maggiora, S. P. Maharana, R. Maiti, S. Maity, G. Mancinelli, R. Manfredi, E. Manoni, M. Mantovano, D. Marcantonio, S. Marcello, C. Marinas, L. Martel, C. Martellini, A. Martini, T. Martinov, L. Massaccesi, M. Masuda, D. Matvienko, S. K. Maurya, J. A. McKenna, R. Mehta, F. Meier, M. Merola, F. Metzner, C. Miller, M. Mirra, K. Miyabayashi, H. Miyake, R. Mizuk, G. B. Mohanty, N. Molina-Gonzalez, S. Mondal, S. Moneta, H. -G. Moser, M. Mrvar, R. Mussa, I. Nakamura, K. R. Nakamura, M. Nakao, Y. Nakazawa, A. Narimani Charan, M. Naruki, D. Narwal, Z. Natkaniec, A. Natochii, L. Nayak, M. Nayak, G. Nazaryan, M. Neu, C. Niebuhr, S. Nishida, S. Ogawa, Y. Onishchuk, H. Ono, P. Oskin, F. Otani, P. Pakhlov, G. Pakhlova, A. Panta, S. Pardi, K. Parham, H. Park, S. -H. Park, A. Passeri, S. Patra, S. Paul, T. K. Pedlar, R. Peschke, R. Pestotnik, M. Piccolo, L. E. Piilonen, G. Pinna Angioni, P. L. M. Podesta-Lerma, T. Podobnik, S. Pokharel, C. Praz, S. Prell, E. Prencipe, M. T. Prim, H. Purwar, P. Rados, G. Raeuber, S. Raiz, N. Rauls, M. Reif, S. Reiter, M. Remnev, I. Ripp-Baudot, G. Rizzo, S. H. Robertson, M. Roehrken, J. M. Roney, A. Rostomyan, N. Rout, G. Russo, D. A. Sanders, S. Sandilya, L. Santelj, Y. Sato, V. Savinov, B. Scavino, C. Schmitt, C. Schwanda, A. J. Schwartz, M. Schwickardi, Y. Seino, A. Selce, K. Senyo, J. Serrano, M. E. Sevior, C. Sfienti, W. Shan, C. P. Shen, X. D. Shi, T. Shillington, T. Shimasaki, J. -G. Shiu, D. Shtol, A. Sibidanov, F. Simon, J. B. Singh, J. Skorupa, R. J. Sobie, M. Sobotzik, A. Soffer, A. Sokolov, E. Solovieva, S. Spataro, B. Spruck, M. Stari\v{c}, P. Stavroulakis, S. Stefkova, R. Stroili, M. Sumihama, K. Sumisawa, W. Sutcliffe, H. Svidras, M. Takizawa, U. Tamponi, S. Tanaka, K. Tanida, F. Tenchini, O. Tittel, R. Tiwary, D. Tonelli, E. Torassa, K. Trabelsi, I. Tsaklidis, M. Uchida, I. Ueda, Y. Uematsu, T. Uglov, K. Unger, Y. Unno, K. Uno, S. Uno, P. Urquijo, Y. Ushiroda, S. E. Vahsen, R. van Tonder, K. E. Varvell, M. Veronesi, A. Vinokurova, V. S. Vismaya, L. Vitale, V. Vobbilisetti, R. Volpe, B. Wach, M. Wakai, S. Wallner, E. Wang, M. -Z. Wang, X. L. Wang, Z. Wang, A. Warburton, S. Watanuki, C. Wessel, J. Wiechczynski, E. Won, X. P. Xu, B. D. Yabsley, S. Yamada, W. Yan, S. B. Yang, J. Yelton, J. H. Yin, K. Yoshihara, C. Z. Yuan, L. Zani, B. Zhang, Y. Zhang, V. Zhilich, Q. D. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, V. I. Zhukova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of $CP$ asymmetries in $B^0 \to K^0_S \pi^0 \gamma$ decays at Belle II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09139v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report measurements of time-dependent $CP$ asymmetries in $B^0 \to K^0_S \pi^0 \gamma$ decays based on a data sample of $(388\pm6)\times10^6$ $B\bar{B}$ events collected at the $\Upsilon(4S)$ resonance with the Belle II detector. The Belle II experiment operates at the SuperKEKB asymmetric-energy $e^+e^-$ collider. We measure decay-time distributions to determine $CP$-violating parameters $S$ and $C$. We determine these parameters for two ranges of $K^0_S \pi^0$ invariant mass: $m(K^0_S \pi^0)\in (0.8, 1.0)$ $GeV/c^2$, which is dominated by $B^0 \to K^{*0} (\to K^0_S \pi^0) \gamma$ decays, and a complementary region $m(K^0_S \pi^0)\in (0.6, 0.8)\cup(1.0, 1.8)$ $GeV/c^2$. Our results have improved precision as compared to previous measurements and are consistent with theory predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09139v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Belle II Collaboration, I. Adachi, L. Aggarwal, H. Ahmed, H. Aihara, N. Akopov, A. Aloisio, N. Anh Ky, D. M. Asner, H. Atmacan, T. Aushev, V. Aushev, M. Aversano, R. Ayad, V. Babu, H. Bae, S. Bahinipati, P. Bambade, Sw. Banerjee, S. Bansal, M. Barrett, J. Baudot, A. Baur, A. Beaubien, F. Becherer, J. Becker, J. V. Bennett, F. U. Bernlochner, V. Bertacchi, M. Bertemes, E. Bertholet, M. Bessner, S. Bettarini, B. Bhuyan, F. Bianchi, L. Bierwirth, T. Bilka, S. Bilokin, D. Biswas, D. Bodrov, A. Bolz, A. Bondar, J. Borah, A. Boschetti, A. Bozek, M. Bra\v{c}ko, P. Branchini, R. A. Briere, T. E. Browder, A. Budano, S. Bussino, M. Campajola, L. Cao, G. Casarosa, C. Cecchi, J. Cerasoli, M. -C. Chang, P. Chang, R. Cheaib, P. Cheema, C. Chen, B. G. Cheon, K. Chilikin, K. Chirapatpimol, H. -E. Cho, K. Cho, S. -J. Cho, S. -K. Choi, S. Choudhury, J. Cochran, L. Corona, J. X. Cui, S. Das, F. Dattola, E. De La Cruz-Burelo, S. A. De La Motte, G. De Nardo, M. De Nuccio, G. De Pietro, R. de Sangro, M. Destefanis, S. Dey, R. Dhamija, A. Di Canto, F. Di Capua, J. Dingfelder, Z. Dole\v{z}al, I. Dom\'inguez Jim\'enez, T. V. Dong, M. Dorigo, D. Dorner, K. Dort, D. Dossett, S. Dreyer, S. Dubey, K. Dugic, G. Dujany, P. Ecker, M. Eliachevitch, P. Feichtinger, T. Ferber, D. Ferlewicz, T. Fillinger, C. Finck, G. Finocchiaro, A. Fodor, F. Forti, A. Frey, B. G. Fulsom, A. Gabrielli, E. Ganiev, M. Garcia-Hernandez, R. Garg, G. Gaudino, V. Gaur, A. Gaz, A. Gellrich, G. Ghevondyan, D. Ghosh, H. Ghumaryan, G. Giakoustidis, R. Giordano, A. Giri, A. Glazov, B. Gobbo, R. Godang, O. Gogota, P. Goldenzweig, W. Gradl, T. Grammatico, E. Graziani, D. Greenwald, Z. Gruberov\'a, T. Gu, Y. Guan, K. Gudkova, S. Halder, Y. Han, K. Hara, T. Hara, K. Hayasaka, H. Hayashii, S. Hazra, C. Hearty, M. T. Hedges, A. Heidelbach, I. Heredia de la Cruz, M. Hern\'andez Villanueva, T. Higuchi, M. Hoek, M. Hohmann, P. Horak, C. -L. Hsu, T. Humair, T. Iijima, K. Inami, N. Ipsita, A. Ishikawa, R. Itoh, M. Iwasaki, P. Jackson, W. W. Jacobs, D. E. Jaffe, E. -J. Jang, Q. P. Ji, S. Jia, Y. Jin, K. K. Joo, H. Junkerkalefeld, M. Kaleta, D. Kalita, A. B. Kaliyar, J. Kandra, K. H. Kang, S. Kang, G. Karyan, T. Kawasaki, F. Keil, C. Kiesling, C. -H. Kim, D. Y. Kim, K. -H. Kim, Y. -K. Kim, H. Kindo, K. Kinoshita, P. Kody\v{s}, T. Koga, S. Kohani, K. Kojima, A. Korobov, S. Korpar, E. Kovalenko, R. Kowalewski, T. M. G. Kraetzschmar, P. Kri\v{z}an, P. Krokovny, T. Kuhr, Y. Kulii, J. Kumar, M. Kumar, K. Kumara, T. Kunigo, A. Kuzmin, Y. -J. Kwon, S. Lacaprara, Y. -T. Lai, T. Lam, L. Lanceri, J. S. Lange, M. Laurenza, R. Leboucher, F. R. Le Diberder, M. J. Lee, P. Leo, D. Levit, C. Li, L. K. Li, S. X. Li, Y. Li, Y. B. Li, J. Libby, Y. -R. Lin, M. H. Liu, Q. Y. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, D. Liventsev, S. Longo, T. Lueck, T. Luo, C. Lyu, Y. Ma, M. Maggiora, S. P. Maharana, R. Maiti, S. Maity, G. Mancinelli, R. Manfredi, E. Manoni, M. Mantovano, D. Marcantonio, S. Marcello, C. Marinas, L. Martel, C. Martellini, A. Martini, T. Martinov, L. Massaccesi, M. Masuda, K. Matsuoka, D. Matvienko, S. K. Maurya, J. A. McKenna, R. Mehta, F. Meier, M. Merola, F. Metzner, C. Miller, M. Mirra, S. Mitra, K. Miyabayashi, H. Miyake, R. Mizuk, G. B. Mohanty, N. Molina-Gonzalez, S. Mondal, S. Moneta, H. -G. Moser, M. Mrvar, R. Mussa, I. Nakamura, K. R. Nakamura, M. Nakao, H. Nakazawa, Y. Nakazawa, A. Narimani Charan, M. Naruki, D. Narwal, Z. Natkaniec, A. Natochii, L. Nayak, M. Nayak, G. Nazaryan, M. Neu, C. Niebuhr, S. Nishida, S. Ogawa, Y. Onishchuk, H. Ono, Y. Onuki, P. Oskin, F. Otani, P. Pakhlov, G. Pakhlova, A. Panta, S. Pardi, K. Parham, H. Park, S. -H. Park, B. Paschen, A. Passeri, S. Patra, S. Paul, T. K. Pedlar, R. Peschke, R. Pestotnik, M. Piccolo, L. E. Piilonen, G. Pinna Angioni, P. L. M. Podesta-Lerma, T. Podobnik, S. Pokharel, C. Praz, S. Prell, E. Prencipe, M. T. Prim, I. Prudiiev, H. Purwar, P. Rados, G. Raeuber, S. Raiz, N. Rauls, K. Ravindran, M. Reif, S. Reiter, M. Remnev, I. Ripp-Baudot, G. Rizzo, S. H. Robertson, M. Roehrken, J. M. Roney, A. Rostomyan, N. Rout, G. Russo, D. A. Sanders, S. Sandilya, A. Sangal, L. Santelj, Y. Sato, V. Savinov, B. Scavino, C. Schmitt, C. Schwanda, A. J. Schwartz, M. Schwickardi, Y. Seino, A. Selce, K. Senyo, J. Serrano, M. E. Sevior, C. Sfienti, W. Shan, X. D. Shi, T. Shillington, T. Shimasaki, J. -G. Shiu, D. Shtol, B. Shwartz, A. Sibidanov, F. Simon, J. B. Singh, J. Skorupa, R. J. Sobie, M. Sobotzik, A. Soffer, A. Sokolov, E. Solovieva, S. Spataro, B. Spruck, M. Stari\v{c}, P. Stavroulakis, S. Stefkova, R. Stroili, M. Sumihama, K. Sumisawa, W. Sutcliffe, H. Svidras, M. Takahashi, M. Takizawa, U. Tamponi, S. Tanaka, K. Tanida, F. Tenchini, A. Thaller, O. Tittel, R. Tiwary, D. Tonelli, E. Torassa, K. Trabelsi, I. Tsaklidis, M. Uchida, I. Ueda, Y. Uematsu, T. Uglov, K. Unger, Y. Unno, K. Uno, S. Uno, P. Urquijo, Y. Ushiroda, S. E. Vahsen, R. van Tonder, K. E. Varvell, M. Veronesi, A. Vinokurova, V. S. Vismaya, L. Vitale, V. Vobbilisetti, R. Volpe, B. Wach, M. Wakai, S. Wallner, E. Wang, M. -Z. Wang, X. L. Wang, Z. Wang, A. Warburton, M. Watanabe, S. Watanuki, C. Wessel, E. Won, Y. Xie, X. P. Xu, B. D. Yabsley, S. Yamada, S. B. Yang, J. Yelton, J. H. Yin, K. Yoshihara, C. Z. Yuan, Y. Yusa, L. Zani, F. Zeng, B. Zhang, Y. Zhang, V. Zhilich, Q. D. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, V. I. Zhukova, R. \v{Z}leb\v{c}\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for light neutral particles decaying promptly into collimated pairs of electrons or muons in $pp$ collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV with the ATLAS detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A search for a dark photon, a new light neutral particle, which decays promptly into collimated pairs of electrons or muons is presented. The search targets dark photons resulting from the exotic decay of the Standard Model Higgs boson, assuming its production via the dominant gluon-gluon fusion mode. The analysis is based on 140 fb$^{-1}$ of data collected with the ATLAS detector at the Large Hadron Collider from proton-proton collisions at a center-of-mass energy of 13 TeV. Events with collimated pairs of electrons or muons are analysed and background contributions are estimated using data-driven techniques. No significant excess in the data above the Standard Model background is observed. Upper limits are set at 95% confidence level on the branching ratio of the Higgs boson decay into dark photons between 0.001% and 5%, depending on the assumed dark photon mass and signal model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09168v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for neutral long-lived particles that decay into displaced jets in the ATLAS calorimeter in association with leptons or jets using $pp$ collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09183v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A search for neutral long-lived particles (LLPs) decaying in the ATLAS hadronic calorimeter using 140 fb$^{-1}$ of proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV delivered by the LHC is presented. The analysis is composed of three channels. The first targets pair-produced LLPs, where at least one LLP is produced with sufficiently low boost that its decay products can be resolved as separate jets. The second and third channels target LLPs respectively produced in association with a $W$ or $Z$ boson that decays leptonically. In each channel, different search regions target different kinematic regimes, to cover a broad range of LLP mass hypotheses and models. No excesses of events relative to the background predictions are observed. Higgs boson branching fractions to pairs of hadronically decaying neutral LLPs larger than 1% are excluded at 95% confidence level for proper decay lengths in the range of 30 cm to 4.5 m depending on the LLP mass, a factor of three improvement on previous searches in the hadronic calorimeter. The production of long-lived dark photons in association with a $Z$ boson with cross-sections above 0.1 pb is excluded for dark photon mean proper decay lengths in the range of 20 cm to 50 m, improving previous ATLAS results by an order of magnitude. Finally, long-lived photo-phobic axion-like particle models are probed for the first time by ATLAS, with production cross-sections above 0.1 pb excluded in the 0.1 mm to 10 m range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09183v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting $C$ and $CP$ Violation in $\eta \to \pi^+\pi^-\pi^0$ Decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08766v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The decay $\eta\to \pi^+\pi^-\pi^0$ is an ideal process in which to study flavor-conserving $C$ and $CP$ violation beyond the Standard Model. We deduce the $C$- and $CP$-odd quark operators that contribute to $\eta\to \pi^+\pi^-\pi^0$ originating from the mass-dimension 6 Standard Model effective field theory. The corresponding hadron-level operators that generate a non-vanishing $I=0$ amplitude at order $p^6$ in the chiral effective theory are presented for the first time, in addition to the leading order operatorsascribed to the $I=2$ final state. By fitting the KLOE-2 and the most recent BESIII experimental data, we determine the coefficients of the lowest order $I=0$ and $I=2$ amplitudes and estimate the potential new physics energy scale. We also perform an impact study of the future $\eta\to \pi^+\pi^-\pi^0$ experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08766v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Shi, Jian Liang, Susan Gardner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TeV Analysis of a Source Rich Region with HAWC Observatory: Is HESS J1809-193 a Potential Hadronic PeVatron?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08849v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: HESS J1809-193 is an unidentified TeV source, first detected by the High Energy Stereoscopic System (H.E.S.S.) Collaboration. The emission originates in a source-rich region that includes several Supernova Remnants (SNR) and Pulsars (PSR) including SNR G11.1+0.1, SNR G11.0-0.0, and the young radio pulsar J1809-1917. Originally classified as a pulsar wind nebula (PWN) candidate, recent studies show the peak of the TeV region overlapping with a system of molecular clouds. This resulted in the revision of the original leptonic scenario to look for alternate hadronic scenarios. Marked as a potential PeVatron candidate, this region has been studied extensively by H.E.S.S. due to its emission extending up-to several tens of TeV. In this work, we use 2398 days of data from the High Altitude Water Cherenkov (HAWC) observatory to carry out a systematic source search for the HESS J1809-193 region. We were able to resolve emission detected as an extended component (modelled as a Symmetric Gaussian with a 1 $\sigma$ radius of 0.21 $^\circ$) with no clear cutoff at high energies and emitting photons up-to 210 TeV. We model the multi-wavelength observations for the region HESS J1809-193 using a time-dependent leptonic model and a lepto-hadronic model. Our model indicates that both scenarios could explain the observed data within the region of HESS J1809-193.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08849v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Albert, R. Alfaro, C. Alvarez, J. C. Arteaga-Vel\'azquez, D. Avila Rojas, R. Babu, E. Belmont-Moreno, A. Bernal, M. Breuhaus, K. S. Caballero-Mora, T. Capistr\'an, A. Carrami\~nana, S. Casanova, J. Cotzomi, E. De la Fuente, D. Depaoli, N. Di Lalla, R. Diaz Hernandez, B. L. Dingus, M. A. DuVernois, C. Espinoza, K. L. Fan, K. Fang, B. Fick, N. Fraija, J. A. Garc\'ia-Gonz\'alez, F. Garfias, A. Gonzalez Munoz, M. M. Gonz\'alez, J. A. Goodman, S. Groetsch, J. P. Harding, S. Hern\'andez-Cadena, I. Herzog, D. Huang, F. Hueyotl-Zahuantitla, P. H\"untemeyer, A. Iriarte, V. Joshi, S. Kaufmann, A. Lara, J. Lee, H. Le\'on Vargas, A. L. Longinotti, G. Luis-Raya, K. Malone, J. Mart\'inez-Castro, J. A. Matthews, P. Miranda-Romagnoli, J. A. Montes, J. A. Morales-Soto, E. Moreno, M. Mostaf\'a, L. Nellen, M. Newbold, M. U. Nisa, R. Noriega-Papaqui, M. Osorio, Y. P\'erez Araujo, E. G. P\'erez-P\'erez, C. D. Rho, D. Rosa-Gonz\'alez, E. Ruiz-Velasco, H. Salazar, A. Sandoval, M. Schneider, J. Serna-Franco, A. J. Smith, Y. Son, R. W. Springer, O. Tibolla, K. Tollefson, I. Torres, R. Torres-Escobedo, R. Turner, F. Ure\~na-Mena, E. Varela, X. Wang, I. J. Watson, E. Willox, S. Yun-C\'arcamo, H. Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commissioning of a compact multibend achromat lattice: A new 3 GeV synchrotron radiation facility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08925v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: NanoTerasu, a new 3 GeV synchrotron light source in Japan, began user operation in April 2024. It provides high-brilliance soft to tender X-rays and covers a wide spectral range from ultraviolet to tender X-rays. Its compact storage ring with a circumference of 349 m is based on a four-bend achromat lattice to provide two straight sections in each cell for insertion devices with a natural horizontal emittance of 1.14 nm rad, which is small enough for soft X-rays users. The NanoTerasu accelerator incorporates several innovative technologies, including a full-energy injector C-band linear accelerator with a length of 110 m, an in-vacuum off-axis injection system, a four-bend achromat with B-Q combined bending magnets, and a TM020 mode accelerating cavity with built-in higher-order-mode dampers in the storage ring. This paper presents the accelerator machine commissioning over a half-year period and our model-consistent ring optics correction. The first user operation with a stored beam current of 160 mA is also reported. We summarize the storage ring parameters obtained from the commissioning. This is helpful for estimating the effective optical properties of synchrotron radiation at NanoTerasu.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08925v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuhei Obara, Kota Ueshima, Takao Asaka, Yuji Hosaka, Koichi Kan, Nobuyuki Nishimori, Toshitaka Aoki, Hiroyuki Asano, Koichi Haga, Yuto Iba, Akira Ihara, Katsumasa Ito, Taiki Iwashita, Masaya Kadowaki, Rento Kanahama, Hajime Kobayashi, Hideki Kobayashi, Hideo Nishihara, Masaaki Nishikawa, Haruhiko Oikawa, Ryota Saida, Keisuke Sakuraba, Kento Sugimoto, Masahiro Suzuki, Kouki Takahashi, Shunya Takahashi, Tatsuki Tanaka, Tsubasa Tsuchiyama, Risa Yoshioka, Tsuyoshi Aoki, Hideki Dewa, Takahiro Fujita, Morihiro Kawase, Akio Kiyomich, Takashi Hamano, Mitsuhiro Masaki, Takemasa Masuda, Shinichi Matsubara, Kensuke Okada, Choji Saji, Tsutomu Taniuchi, Yukiko Taniuchi, Yosuke Ueda, Hiroshi Yamaguchi, Kenichi Yanagida, Kenji Fukami, Naoyasu Hosoda, Miho Ishii, Toshiro Itoga, Eito Iwai, Tamotsu Magome, Masaya Oishi, Takashi Ohshima, Chikara Kondo, Tatsuyuki Sakurai, Masazumi Shoji, Takashi Sugimoto, Shiro Takano, Kazuhiro Tamura, Takahiro Watanabe, Takato Tomai, Noriyoshi Azumi, Takahiro Inagaki, Hirokazu Maesaka, Sunao Takahashi, Takashi Tanaka, Shinobu Inoue, Hirosuke Kumazawa, Kazuki Moriya, Kohei Sakai, Toshio Seno, Hiroshi Sumitomo, Ryoichi Takesako, Shinichiro Tanaka, Ryo Yamamoto, Kazutoshi Yokomachi, Masamichi Yoshioka, Toru Hara, Sakuo Matsui, Toshihiko Hiraiwa, Hitoshi Tanaka, Hiroyasu Ego</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Quantum Realization of Jet Clustering in High-Energy Physics Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09056v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exploring the application of quantum technologies to fundamental sciences holds the key to fostering innovation for both sides. In high-energy particle collisions, quarks and gluons are produced and immediately form collimated particle sprays known as jets. Accurate jet clustering is crucial as it retains the information of the originating quark or gluon and forms the basis for studying properties of the Higgs boson, which underlies teh mechanism of mass generation for subatomic particles. For the first time, by mapping collision events into graphs--with particles as nodes and their angular separations as edges--we realize jet clustering using the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA), a hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for addressing classical combinatorial optimization problems with available quantum resources. Our results, derived from 30 qubits on quantum computer simulator and 6 qubits on quantum computer hardware, demonstrate that jet clustering performance with QAOA is comparable with or even better than classical algorithms for a small-sized problem. This study highlights the feasibility of quantum computing to revolutionize jet clustering, bringing the practical application of quantum computing in high-energy physics experiments one step closer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09056v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongfeng Zhu, Weifeng Zhuang, Chen Qian, Yunheng Ma, Dong E. Liu, Manqi Ruan, Chen Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical advances in electroweak, Higgs, and top physics at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In these proceedings, I review recent precision calculations relevant for the LHC, all related to the electroweak, Higgs or top sector of the Standard Model. These applications range from triboson production to the production of a top-antitop pair in association with a W boson and to Higgs production in association with another Higgs boson, a top-antitop pair or a W boson. These proceedings reflect a presentation given at DIS2024 and provide a snapshot of the current frontier for theoretical predictions at the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09246v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Pellen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding flavon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09255v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We conduct a comprehensive investigation into the flavour phenomenology and collider signatures of flavon of $\mathcal{Z}_{\rm N} \times \mathcal{Z}_{\rm M}$ flavour symmetries for the soft symmetry-breaking scenario and a new symmetry-conserving mechanism at the high-luminosity LHC, high energy LHC, and a 100 TeV hadron collider. The flavour physics of quark and leptonic observables places different bounds on the parameter space of flavons of $\mathcal{Z}_{\rm N} \times \mathcal{Z}_{\rm M}$ flavour symmetries. On the collider side, the decay $t \rightarrow c a$ can be probed by the high-luminosity LHC, high energy LHC, and a 100 TeV hadron collider for the $\mathcal{Z}_{\rm 8} \times \mathcal{Z}_{\rm 22}$ flavour symmetry. The inclusive production signatures can be used to probe the flavon of all the $\mathcal{Z}_{\rm N} \times \mathcal{Z}_{\rm M} $ flavour symmetries for the soft symmetry-breaking scenario for a heavy flavon at a 100 TeV collider. Flavons of all the $\mathcal{Z}_{\rm N} \times \mathcal{Z}_{\rm M} $ flavour symmetries can be probed at high energy LHC and a 100 TeV collider for a low mass in the case of soft symmetry-breaking. The di-flavon production is within reach of the high-luminosity LHC, high energy LHC, and a 100 TeV collider only for a light flavon. The 14 TeV high-luminosity LHC can probe only the $\mathcal{Z}_{\rm 2} \times \mathcal{Z}_{\rm 5}$ and $\mathcal{Z}_{\rm 8} \times \mathcal{Z}_{\rm 22}$ flavour symmetries for a few specific inclusive signatures. The symmetry-conserving scenario remains beyond the detection capabilities of any collider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09255v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gauhar Abbas, Ashutosh Kumar Alok, Neetu Raj Singh Chundawat, Najimuddin Khan, Neelam Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-Newtonian Tests of Gravitational Quantum Field Theory with Spin and Scaling Gauge Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A self-consistent gravitational quantum field theory, with gravitational force treated on the same footing as the other three fundamental interactions, was established recently. The gravidynamics predicted by such a theory could lead to important implications, and the comparisons with experimental results may provide us opportunities to test such new approach of gravity based on the framework of the quantum field theory of gauge interactions. In this work, we start with the effective field equation of the gravitational quantum field theory, and then solve the perturbative gravigauge field order by order up to the 1st post-Newtonian level under the assumption of a simplified energy-momentum tensor of perfect fluids. Having the constraints on the related post-Newtonian parameters from the most up-to-date observational data, the new bound on the combined coupling in the gravitational quantum field theory $|\gamma_G(\alpha_G-\alpha_W/2)| \leq (2.4\pm30)\times10^{-6}$ is obtained. Under such bound, we found that the new gravitational quantum field theory successfully passed and found no conflict with the contemporary keynote Solar system experiments of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09410v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying-jian Chen, Peng Xu, Yue-liang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Longer-Lived Mediators from Charged Mesons and Photons at Neutrino Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.01491v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Since many of the dark-sector particles interact with Standard Model (SM) particles in multiple ways, they can appear in experimental facilities where SM particles appear in abundance. In this study, we explore a particular class of longer-lived mediators that are produced from photons, charged mesons, neutral mesons, and $e^\pm$ that arise in proton-beam fixed-target-type neutrino experiments. This class of mediators encompasses light scalars that appear in theories like extended Higgs sectors, muon(electro)philic scalars, etc. We evaluate the sensitivities of these mediators at beam-based neutrino experiments such as the finished ArgoNeuT, ongoing MicroBooNE, SBND, ICARUS, and the upcoming DUNE experiment. We realize that scalars are more enhanced while produced from three-body decay of charged mesons, especially if they are muonphilic in nature. For scenarios that contain muonphilic scalars, these experiments can probe unexplored regions of parameter space that can explain the current discrepancy in the anomalous magnetic moment of muons. The sensitivity of electrophilic scalars at the DUNE Near Detector can explore new regions. We also show that Bethe-Heitler scattering processes can be used to probe flavor-specific lepton final states even for the mediator masses below twice the lepton mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.01491v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhaskar Dutta, Aparajitha Karthikeyan, Doojin Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refinable modeling for unbinned SMEFT analyses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19076v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present techniques for estimating the effects of systematic uncertainties in unbinned data analyses at the LHC. Our primary focus is constraining the Wilson coefficients in the standard model effective field theory (SMEFT), but the methodology applies to broader parametric models of phenomena beyond the standard model (BSM). We elevate the well-established procedures for binned Poisson counting experiments to the unbinned case by utilizing machine-learned surrogates of the likelihood ratio. This approach can be applied to various theoretical, modeling, and experimental uncertainties. By establishing a common statistical framework for BSM and systematic effects, we lay the groundwork for future unbinned analyses at the LHC. Additionally, we introduce a novel tree-boosting algorithm capable of learning highly accurate parameterizations of systematic effects. This algorithm extends the existing toolkit with a versatile and robust alternative. We demonstrate our approach using the example of an SMEFT interpretation of highly energetic top quark pair production in proton-proton collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19076v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Sch\"ofbeck</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
