<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Search for $e^+e^-\to K^+ K^- \psi(3770)$ at center-of-mass energies from 4.84 to 4.95 GeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using $e^+e^-$ collision data, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of $892\,\rm pb^{-1}$ collected at center-of-mass energies from 4.84 to 4.95\,GeV with the BESIII detector, we search for the process $e^+e^-\to K^+ K^- \psi(3770)$ by reconstructing two charged kaons and one $D$ meson from $\psi(3770)$. No significant signal of $e^+e^-\to K^+ K^- \psi(3770)$ is found and the upper limits of the Born cross sections are reported at 90\% confidence level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11927v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> BESIII Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acceleration of electromagnetic shower development and enhancement of light yield in oriented scintillating crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We observed a substantial increase of the scintillation light output of lead tungstate (PbWO$_4$) at a small incidence angle with respect to two main lattice axes. This reflects the acceleration of electromagnetic shower development that occurs in the crystalline Strong Field. We measured the scintillation light generated by $120$-$\mathrm{GeV}$ electrons and $10$-$100$-$\mathrm{GeV}$ $\gamma$ rays on thick samples. This result deepens the knowledge of the shower development mechanisms in crystal scintillators and could pave the way to the development of innovative accelerator- and space-borne calorimeters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12016v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Soldani, Pietro Monti-Guarnieri, Alessia Selmi, Nicola Argiolas, Luca Bomben, Claudia Brizzolari, Nicola Canale, Stefano Carsi, Nikolaos Charitonidis, Davide De Salvador, Vincenzo Guidi, Viktar Haurylavets, Mikhail Korzhik, Giulia Lezzani, Alexander Lobko, Lorenzo Malagutti, Sofia Mangiacavalli, Valerio Mascagna, Andrea Mazzolari, Vitaly Mechinsky, Matthew Moulson, Riccardo Negrello, Gianfranco Patern\`o, Leonardo Perna, Christian Petroselli, Michela Prest, Marco Romagnoni, Federico Ronchetti, Giosu\'e Saibene, Francesco Sgarbossa, Alexei Sytov, Viktor Tikhomirov, Erik Vallazza, Laura Bandiera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>tt+X measurements by CMS and ATLAS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: These proceedings present the observation of the 4-top production process and the latest results of the production of top-quark pairs associated with W and $\gamma$ bosons ($t\bar{t}W$ and $t\bar{t}\gamma$) and b jets ($t\bar{t}b\bar{b}$) at a collision energy of 13 TeV carried out by the CMS and ATLAS Collaborations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12046v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barbara Alvarez Gonzalez on behalf of the CMS, ATLAS Collaborations</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino Masses in the Mirror Twin Higgs with Spontaneous $\mathbb{Z}_2$ Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11651v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a mirror twin Higgs model with spontaneous $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry breaking that ameliorates the constraints in twin Higgs cosmology and, at the same time, generates the Standard Model neutrino masses. The model features an $SU(2)$ triplet with hypercharge $1$ alongside its twin counterpart. Spontaneous breaking of both $\mathbb{Z}_2$ and electroweak symmetry occurs in the scalar sector. The Standard Model neutrinos acquire small masses through the type-II seesaw mechanism. In contrast, their twin counterparts acquire large masses, effectively addressing the dark radiation problem in mirror twin Higgs scenarios. We study the impact of the model on the $N_{\rm eff.}$ constraints, as well as on collider phenomenology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11651v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Bittar, Davi B. Costa, Gustavo Burdman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Flow and Flavor Mixing in the Flavor Spin Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11914v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that in the flavor spin theories (theories with non-Euclidean signature of the kinematic quadratic term of the Lagrangian) for physical mass eigenstates the transition from the interaction to the mass eigenstate basis is constrained. In the corresponding modification of the SM the constraints result in the experimentally observed textures of both lepton and quark flavor mixing matrices. Furthermore, the number of real mixing parameters is reduced by one for each of the quark and lepton sectors. In addition some pairs of elements of V_CKM and separately U_PMNS must have the same absolute values. The equalities are observed experimentally within the error bounds. Apart from its imprint on the flavor mixing the modified SM is identical to the SM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11914v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Jourjine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for the lepton flavor violating $\tau$ $\to$ 3$\mu$ decay in proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02371v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A search for the lepton flavor violating $\tau$ $\to$ 3$\mu$ decay is performed using proton-proton collision events at a center-of-mass energy of 13 TeV collected by the CMS experiment at the LHC in 2017-2018, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 97.7 fb$^{-1}$. Tau leptons produced in both heavy-flavor hadron and W boson decays are exploited in the analysis. No evidence for the decay is observed. The results of this search are combined with an earlier null result based on data collected in 2016 to obtain a total integrated luminosity of 131 fb$^{-1}$. The observed (expected) upper limits on the branching fraction $\mathcal{B}$($\tau$ $\to$ 3$\mu$) at confidence levels of 90 and 95% are 2.9 $\times$ 10$^{-8}$ (2.4 $\times$ 10$^{-8}$) and 3.6 $\times$ 10$^{-8}$ (3.0 $\times$ 10$^{-8}$), respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02371v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 853 (2024) 138633</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> CMS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel method for identifying the heaviest QED atom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.00171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.00171v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The bound state of a $\tau^+\tau^-$ pair by the electromagnetic force is the heaviest and smallest QED atom. Since the discovery of the two lightest QED atoms more than 60 years ago, no evidence for the third one has been found. We demonstrate that the $J_\tau$ ($\tau^+\tau^-$ atom with $J^{PC}=1^{--}$) resonance signal can be observed with a significance larger than $5\sigma$ including both statistical and systematic uncertainties, via the process $e^+e^-\to X^+ Y^- \slashed{E}$ ($X,\,Y=e$, $\mu$, $\pi$, $K$, or $\rho$, and $\slashed{E}$ is the missing energy) with $1.5~{\rm ab^{-1}}$ data taken around the $\tau$ pair production threshold. The $\tau$ lepton mass can be measured in a precision of 2 keV with the same data sample. This is within one year's running time of the proposed super tau-charm factory or super charm-tau factory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.00171v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.scib.2024.04.003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science Bulletin 69 (2024) pp. 32-37</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Hang Fu, Sen Jia, Xing-Yu Zhou, Yu-Jie Zhang, Cheng-Ping Shen, Chang-Zheng Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the oscillating electric dipole moment induced by axion-fermion couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16135v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been recently claimed that the axion coupling to fermions is responsible for an oscillating electric dipole moment (EDM) in the background of axion dark matter. In this work, we re-examine the derivation of this effect. Contrary to previous studies, we point out the physical relevance of an axion boundary term, which is crucial in restoring the axion shift symmetry and drastically affects the EDM phenomenology. To describe the latter, we introduce the notion of a time-averaged effective axion EDM, which encodes the boundary term and whose magnitude depends on the oscillation regime. For slow oscillations, the boundary term washes out the standard oscillating EDM, resulting in an exact cancellation in the static limit. Conversely, during fast oscillations, the boundary term amplifies the effective EDM relatively to the standard EDM contribution. This observable is especially interesting in the case of the electron EDM. For an $\mathcal{O}(1)$ axion-electron coupling, the overall size of the effective EDM in the regime of intermediate or fast oscillations is comparable to the present static EDM limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16135v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP04(2024)076</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2024, 76 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luca Di Luzio, Hector Gisbert, Philip S{\o}rensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The neutrino fog for dark matter-electron scattering experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04303v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The search for sub-GeV dark matter via scattering on electrons has ramped up in the last few years. Like in the case of dark matter scattering on nuclei, electron-recoil-based searches also face an ultimate background in the form of neutrinos. The so-called ``neutrino fog'' refers to the range of open dark-matter parameter space where the background of neutrinos can potentially prevent a conclusive discovery claim of a dark matter signal from being made. In this study, we map the neutrino fog for a range of electron recoil experiments based on silicon, germanium, xenon and argon targets. In analogy to the nuclear recoil case, we also calculate the ''edge'' to the neutrino fog, which can be used as a visual guide to where neutrinos become an important background -- this boundary excludes some parts of the key theory milestones used to motivate these experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04303v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 083016 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ben Carew, Ashlee R. Caddell, Tarak Nath Maity, Ciaran A. J. O'Hare</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About the magnitude of the $\gamma^\ast N \to N(1520)$ transverse amplitudes near $Q^2=0$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10654v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $\gamma^\ast N \to N(1520)$ transition has a property that differs from the other low-lying nucleon resonance amplitudes: the magnitude of the transverse helicity amplitudes.The transition helicity amplitudes are defined in terms of square-transfer momentum $q^2$, or $Q^2=-q^2$. Near the photon point ($Q^2=0$) there is a significant difference in the magnitude of the transverse amplitudes: $A_{3/2}$ is very large and $A_{1/2}$ is very small. This atypical behavior contrasts with the relation between the amplitudes at the pseudothreshold [the limit where the nucleon and the $N(1520)$ are both at rest and $Q^2 &lt;0$], where $A_{3/2} = A_{1/2}/\sqrt{3}$, and also in the large-$Q^2$ region, where theory and data suggest that $A_{3/2}$ is suppressed relative to $A_{1/2}$. In the present work, we look for the source of the suppression of the $A_{1/2}$ amplitude at $Q^2=0$. The result is easy to understand in first approximation, when we look into the relation between the transverse amplitudes and the elementary form factors, defined by a gauge-invariant parametrization of the $\gamma^\ast N \to N(1520)$ transition current, near $Q^2=0$. There is a partial cancellation between contributions of two elementary form factors near $Q^2=0$. We conclude, however, that the correlation between the two elementary form factors at $Q^2=0$ is not sufficient to explain the transverse amplitude data below $Q^2 = 1$ GeV$^2$. The description of the dependence of the transverse amplitudes on $Q^2$ requires the determination of the scale of variation of the elementary form factors in the range $Q^2=0$...0.5 GeV$^2$,a region with almost non existent data. We conclude at the end that the low-$Q^2$ data for the transverse amplitudes can be well described when we relate the scale of variation of the elementary form factors with the nucleon dipole form factor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10654v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.074021</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 074021 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. Ramalho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD parameters and SM-high precision from $e^+e^-$ to Hadrons: Updated</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13983v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: 1. I update my previous comparison of the theoretical value of the muon anomaly with the new measurement and found $\Delta a_\mu\equiv a_\mu^{exp}-a_\mu^{th} = (143\pm 42_{th}\pm 22_{exp})\times 10^{-11}$ indicating about 3$\sigma$ discrepancy between the SM predictions and experiment. 2. I improve the estimate of QCD power corrections up to dimension D=12 and provide a new estimate of the ones up to D=20 within the SVZ expansion by combining the ratio of the Borel/Laplace sum rules (LSR) with the BNP $\tau$-like decay moments for the I=1 vector current. The results summarized in Table 1 confirm a violation of the factorization of the four-quark condensates and the value of the gluon one $ &lt;\alpha_s G^2&gt;$ from some other sources. Up to D=20, I do not observe any factorial nor exponential growth of the size of these power corrections. 3. I use these new values of power corrections to extract $\alpha_s$ from the BNP lowest moment. To order $\alpha_s^4$, I find within the SVZ expansion: $\alpha_s(M_\tau)= 0.3081(50)_{fit}(71)_{\alpha_s^5}$ [resp. $0.3260 (47)_{fit}(62)_{\alpha_s^5}]$ implying $\alpha_s(M_Z)= 0.1170(6)(3)_{evol}$ [resp. $0.1192(6)(3)_{evol}$] for Fixed Order (FO) [resp. Contour Improved (CI)] PT series. They lead to the mean: $ \alpha_s(M_\tau)\vert_{SVZ}=0.3179(58)_{fit}(81)_{syst}$ and $ \alpha_s(M_Z)\vert_{SVZ}= 0.1182(12)(3)_{evol}$ where the systematic error(syst) takes into account the discrepancy between FO and CI. Using the lowest BNP moment, we also obtain from the $V+A$ component of $\tau$-decay: $ \alpha_s(M_\tau)\vert_{\tau,V+A}=0.3040(76)_{fit}(68)_{syst}$ giving: $\alpha_s(M_Z)\vert_{\tau,V+A}=0.1166(8)(3)_{evol}$. The average of the two determinations leads to: $ \alpha_s(M_\tau)=0.3099(60)$ and $\alpha_s(M_Z)= 0.1174(10)(3)_{evol}$. 4. Some contributions beyond the SVZ expansion ($1/Q^2$, instantons and duality violation) are discussed in Sections 10,11.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13983v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2024.122873</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Narison (LUPM CNRS/IN2P3, Univ. Montpellier,,iHEPMAD, Univ. Antananarivo - MG)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An optimized basis for hadronic light-by-light scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14060v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a new basis for the hadronic light-by-light (HLbL) tensor that is optimized for the evaluation of narrow-resonance contributions to HLbL scattering in the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon. As main advantage, kinematic singularities are manifestly absent for pseudoscalar, scalar, and axial-vector states, while the remaining singularities for tensor resonances are minimized, even avoided for special cases, and simple crossing relations among the scalar functions maintained. We scrutinize the properties of this new basis for the scalar-QED pion box, demonstrating that the partial-wave convergence even slightly improves compared to our previous work, and discuss the physical sum rules that ensure basis independence of the HLbL contribution. Finally, we provide explicit expressions for narrow (pseudo-)scalar, axial-vector, and tensor intermediate states in terms of their respective transition form factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14060v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP04(2024)092</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 04 (2024) 092</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Martin Hoferichter, Peter Stoffer, Maximilian Zillinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
