<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>New Structures in the $J/\psi$ $J/\psi$ Mass Spectrum at CMS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A search is reported for structures near the $J/\psi$ $J/\psi$ mass threshold using a dataset of proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s} \: =13 \: \mathrm{TeV} $ recorded with the CMS detector at the LHC, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of about $135 \: \mathrm{fb^{-1}}$. Two structures are observed with a significance exceeding $5\sigma$ and evidence of an additional structure is reported with a local significance of $4.7\sigma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04722v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xining Wang, Kai Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting Signal Electron Trajectories in the COMET Phase-I Cylindrical Drift Chamber Using Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a pioneering approach to tracking analysis within the COMET Phase-I experiment, which aims to search for the charged lepton flavor violating $\mu\to e$ conversion process in a muonic atom, at J-PARC, Japan. This paper specifically introduces the extraction of signal electron trajectories in the COMET Phase-I cylindrical drift chamber (CDC) amidst a high background hit rate, with more than $40\,\%$ occupancy of the total CDC cells, utilizing deep learning techniques of semantic segmentation. Our model achieved remarkable results, with a purity rate of $98\,\%$ and a retention rate of $90\,\%$ for CDC cells with signal hits, surpassing the design-goal performance of $90\,\%$ for both metrics. This study marks the initial application of deep learning to COMET tracking, paving the way for more advanced techniques in future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04795v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fumihiro Kaneko, Yoshitaka Kuno, Joe Sato, Ikuya Sato, Dorian Pieters, Chen Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pay Attention To Mean Fields For Point Cloud Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04997v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collider data generation with machine learning has become increasingly popular in particle physics due to the high computational cost of conventional Monte Carlo simulations, particularly for future high-luminosity colliders. We propose a generative model for point clouds that employs an attention-based aggregation while preserving a linear computational complexity with respect to the number of points. The model is trained in an adversarial setup, ensuring input permutation equivariance and invariance for the generator and critic, respectively. To stabilize known unstable adversarial training, a feature matching loss is introduced. We evaluate the performance on two different datasets. The former is the top-quark \textsc{JetNet150} dataset, where the model outperforms the current state-of-the-art GAN-based model, despite having significantly fewer parameters. The latter is dataset 2 of the CaloChallenge, which comprises point clouds with up to $30\times$ more points compared to the first dataset. The model and its corresponding code are available at \url{https://github.com/kaechb/MDMA/tree/NeurIPS}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04997v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benno K\"ach, Isabell Melzer-Pellmann, Dirk Kr\"ucker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for heavy right-handed Majorana neutrinos in the decay of top quarks produced in proton$-$proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV with the ATLAS detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A search for heavy right-handed Majorana neutrinos is performed with the ATLAS detector at the CERN Large Hadron Collider, using the 140 $\mathrm{fb}^{-1}$ of proton$-$proton collision data at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV collected during Run 2. This search targets $t\bar{t}$ production, in which both top quarks decay into a bottom quark and a $W$ boson, where one of the $W$ bosons decays hadronically and the other decays into an electron or muon and a heavy neutral lepton. The heavy neutral lepton is identified through a decay into an electron or muon and another $W$ boson, resulting in a pair of same-charge same-flavor leptons in the final state. This paper presents the first search for heavy neutral leptons in the mass range of 15$-$75 GeV using $t\bar{t}$ events. No significant excess is observed over the background expectation, and upper limits are placed on the signal cross-sections. Assuming a benchmark scenario of the phenomenological type-I seesaw model, these cross-section limits are then translated into upper limits on the mixing parameters of the heavy Majorana neutrino with Standard Model neutrinos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05000v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurements of Pion and Muon Nuclear Capture at Rest on Argon in the LArIAT Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the measurement of the final-state products of negative pion and muon nuclear capture at rest on argon by the LArIAT experiment at the Fermilab Test Beam Facility. We measure a population of isolated MeV-scale energy depositions, or blips, in 296 LArIAT events containing tracks from stopping low-momentum pions and muons. The average numbers of visible blips are measured to be 0.74 $\pm$ 0.19 and 1.86 $\pm$ 0.17 near muon and pion track endpoints, respectively. The 3.6$\sigma$ statistically significant difference in blip content between muons and pions provides the first demonstration of a new method of pion-muon discrimination in neutrino liquid argon time projection chamber experiments. LArIAT Monte Carlo simulations predict substantially higher average blip counts for negative muon (1.22 $\pm$ 0.08) and pion (2.34 $\pm$ 0.09) nuclear captures. We attribute this difference to Geant4's inaccurate simulation of the nuclear capture process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05133v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Hernandez-Morquecho, R. Acciarri, J. Asaadi, M. Backfish, W. Badgett, V. Basque, F. d. M. Blaszczyk, W. Foreman, R. Gomes, E. Gramellini, J. Ho, E. Kearns, E. Kemp, T. Kobilarcik, M. King, B. R. Littlejohn, X. Luo, A. Marchionni, C. A. Moura, J. L. Raaf, D. W. Schmitz, M. Soderberg, J. M. St. John, A. M. Szelc, T. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of muonic Dalitz decays of $\chi_{b}$ mesons and precise spectroscopy of hidden-beauty states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The decays of the $\chi_{b1}(1P)$, $\chi_{b2}(1P)$, $\chi_{b1}(2P)$ and $\chi_{b2}(2P)$~mesons into the~$\Upsilon(1S)\mu^+\mu^-$ final state are observed with a high significance using proton-proton collision data collected with the LHCb detector and corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 9fb$^{-1}$. The newly observed decays together with the $\Upsilon(2S)\rightarrow \Upsilon(1S)\pi^+\pi^-$ and $\Upsilon(3S)\rightarrow \Upsilon(2S)\pi^+\pi^-$ decay modes are used for precision measurements of the mass and mass splittings for the hidden-beauty states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05134v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, A. A. Adefisoye, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, M. Alexander, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, A. Andreianov, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, D. Andreou, A. Anelli, D. Ao, F. Archilli, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, R. Ata\'ide Da Silva, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, W. Baldini, L. Balzani, H. Bao, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, C. Barbero Pretel, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, M. Barnyakov, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, M. Bartolini, J. Bartz, J. M. Basels, S. Bashir, G. Bassi, B. Batsukh, P. B. Battista, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, N. B. Behling, S. Belin, V. Bellee, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, J. Bhom, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, N. Bondar, A. Bordelius, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, S. A. Bouchiba, M. Bovill, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, E. Buchanan, A. Buonaura, L. Buonincontri, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, A. C. Caillet, R. Calabrese, S. Calderon Ramirez, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, P. Camargo Magalhaes, J. I. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, J. Castro Godinez, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, D. Cervenkov, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, E. Chatzianagnostou, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, S. Chen, Z. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, X. Chiotopoulos, V. Chobanova, S. Cholak, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, P. Collins, T. Colombo, M. C. Colonna, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, E. Curras Rivera, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, A. Danilina, P. d'Argent, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, A. Davis, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, F. De Benedetti, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, V. Dedu, S. Dekkers, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, L. Dittmann, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, A. D. Dowling, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, O. D. Durmus, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, E. Epple, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, L. N. Falcao, Y. Fan, B. Fang, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, A. Fernandez Casani, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, M. Firlej, K. L. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, T. Fiutowski, F. Fleuret, M. Fontana, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, V. Franco Lima, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, J. Fu, Q. Fuehring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, E. Gabriel, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, B. Ganie, H. Gao, R. Gao, T. Q. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, M. Garau, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, K. G. Garg, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, R. E. Geertsema, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, S. G. Ghizzo, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, L. Girardey, P. Gironella Gironell, C. Giugliano, M. A. Giza, E. L. Gkougkousis, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, A. Gomes, S. Gomez Fernandez, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, L. Guerry, M. Guittiere, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, K. Habermann, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, J. Haimberger, M. Hajheidari, G. H. Hallett, M. M. Halvorsen, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, M. Hartmann, S. Hashmi, J. He, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, P. Herrero Gascon, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, G. Hijano Mendizabal, D. Hill, S. E. Hollitt, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Huang, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, M. Idzik, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Inglessi, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, R. Jacobsson, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, A. John Rubesh Rajan, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, J. Juan Castella, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, M. Kane, Y. Kang, C. Kar, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, A. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, M. K. Kazanecki, F. Keizer, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, O. K. Kshyvanskyi, S. Kubis, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, B. K. Kutsenko, D. Lacarrere, P. Laguarta Gonzalez, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, R. Lane, G. Lanfranchi, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, E. Lemos Cid, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, E. Lesser, B. Leverington, A. Li, C. Li, H. Li, K. Li, L. Li, M. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, Q. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, S. Libralon, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, V. Lisovskyi, R. Litvinov, F. L. Liu, G. Liu, K. Liu, S. Liu, W. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, J. Lomba Castro, T. Long, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, Q. Lu, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, M. Lucio Martinez, V. Lukashenko, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, R. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, B. Mack, I. Mackay, L. M. Mackey, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. J. Madurai, A. Maevskiy, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, M. W. Majewski, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, E. Mariani, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, L. Martel, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Massafferri, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, J. Mazorra de Cos, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, L. Mcconnell, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, F. M. Meng, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, S. Mokhnenko, E. F. Molina Cardenas, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, J. Moron, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. Mu\~noz-Rojas, R. Murta, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, P. Nogarolli, P. Nogga, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, S. Okamura, A. Okhotnikov, O. Okhrimenko, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, D. Osthues, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, F. Paciolla, A. Padee, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, P. R. Pais, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, A. Paul, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, J. Peng, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, H. Pereira Da Costa, A. Pereiro Castro, P. Perret, A. Perro, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, J. P. Pfaller, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, L. Piccolo, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, T. Poeschl, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, D. Provenzano, V. Pugatch, G. Punzi, S. Qasim, Q. Q. Qian, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, V. Ramos De Oliveira, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, R. Ribatti, G. R. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, J. Roensch, A. Rogachev, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, M. Romero Lamas, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, T. Rong, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, A. Ryzhikov, J. Ryzka, J. J. Saavedra-Arias, J. J. Saborido Silva, R. Sadek, N. Sagidova, D. Sahoo, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, A. Sarnatskiy, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, L. G. Scantlebury Smead, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, S. Schulte, M. H. Schune, R. Schwemmer, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, T. Senger, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, R. S. Sharma, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, Q. Shi, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, N. Skidmore, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, J. C. Smallwood, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, A. Snoch, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, I. Solovyev, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, O. Stenyakin, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, Y. Sun, D. Sundfeld, W. Sutcliffe, P. N. Swallow, K. Swientek, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, Y. Tan, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, E. Ursov, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, V. Valcarce Cadenas, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, G. Vasquez, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Verdoglia, M. Vesterinen, D. Vico Benet, P. V. Vidrier Villalba, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, G. Vouters, C. Vrahas, J. Wagner, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, C. Wang, G. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, M. Waterlaat, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, J. Wendel, B. D. C. Westhenry, C. White, M. Whitehead, E. Whiter, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, Z. Williams, F. F. Wilson, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, Y. Wu, Z. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, A. Xu, J. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, D. Yang, K. Yang, S. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, Y Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, F. Zenesini, C. Zeng, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zharkova, A. Zhelezov, S. Z. Zheng, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Description of Wave Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04696v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We outline a fundamentally quantum description of bosonic dark matter (DM) from which the conventional classical-wave picture emerges in the limit $m \ll 10~\textrm{eV}$. As appropriate for a quantum system, we start from the density matrix which encodes the full information regarding the possible measurements we could make of DM and their fluctuations. Following fundamental results in quantum optics, we argue that for DM it is most likely that the density matrix takes the explicitly mixed form of a Gaussian over the basis of coherent states. Deviations from this would generate non-Gaussian fluctuations in DM observables, allowing a direct probe of the quantum state of DM. Our quantum optics inspired approach allows us to rigorously define and interpret various quantities that are often only described heuristically, such as the coherence time or length. The formalism further provides a continuous description of DM through the wave-particle transition, which we exploit to study how density fluctuations over various physical scales evolve between the two limits and to reveal the unique behavior of DM near the boundary of the wave and particle descriptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04696v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhong Yeon Cheong, Nicholas L. Rodd, Lian-Tao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Born$-$Oppenheimer Effective Theory to rule them all: hybrids, tetraquarks, pentaquarks, doubly heavy baryons and quarkonium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04719v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The discovery of XYZ exotic states in the hadronic sector with two heavy quarks, represents a significant challenge in particle theory. Understanding and predicting their nature remains an open problem. In this work, we demonstrate how the Born$-$Oppenheimer (BO) effective field theory (BOEFT), derived from Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) on the basis of scale separation and symmetries, can address XYZ exotics of any composition. We derive the Schr\"odinger coupled equations that describe hybrids, tetraquarks, pentaquarks, doubly heavy baryons, and quarkonia at leading order, incorporating nonadiabatic terms, and present the predicted multiples. We define the static potentials in terms of the QCD static energies for all relevant cases. We provide the precise form of the nonperturbative low-energy gauge-invariant correlators required for the BOEFT: static energies, generalized Wilson loops, gluelumps, and adjoint mesons. These are to be calculated on the lattice and we calculate here their short-distance behavior. Furthermore, we outline how spin-dependent corrections and mixing terms can be incorporated using matching computations. Lastly, we discuss how static energies with the same BO quantum numbers mix at large distances leading to the phenomenon of avoided level crossing. This effect is crucial to understand the emergence of exotics with molecular characteristics, such as the $\chi_{c1}(3872)$. With BOEFT both the tetraquark and the molecular picture appear as part of the same description.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04719v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Berwein, Nora Brambilla, Abhishek Mohapatra, Antonio Vairo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Athermal Phonons in Novel Materials using the G4CMP Simulation Toolkit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04732v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding phonon and charge propagation in superconducting devices plays an important role in both performing low-threshold dark matter searches and limiting correlated errors in superconducting qubits. The Geant4 Condensed Matter Physics (G4CMP) package, originally developed for the Cryogenic Dark Matter Search (CDMS) experiment, models charge and phonon transport within silicon and germanium detectors and has been validated by experimental measurements of phonon caustics, mean charge-carrier drift velocities, and heat pulse propagation times. In this work, we present a concise framework for expanding the capabilities for phonon transport to a number of other novel substrate materials of interest to the dark matter and quantum computing communities, including sapphire (Al$_{2}$O$_{3}$), gallium arsenide (GaAs), lithium fluoride (LiF), calcium tungstate (CaWO$_{4}$), and calcium fluoride (CaF$_{2}$). We demonstrate the use of this framework in generating phonon transport properties of these materials and compare these properties with experimentally-determined values where available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04732v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Israel Hernandez, Ryan Linehan, Rakshya Khatiwada, Kester Anyang, Daniel Baxter, Grace Bratrud, Enectali Figueroa-Feliciano, Lauren Hsu, Mike Kelsey, Dylan Temples</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multi-Scale Cognitive Interaction Model of Instrument Operations at the Linac Coherent Light Source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We describe a novel multi-agent, multi-scale computational cognitive interaction model of instrument operations at the Linac Coherent Light Source (LCLS). A leading scientific user facility, LCLS is the world's first hard x-ray free electron laser, operated by the SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory for the U.S. Department of Energy. As the world's first x-ray free electron laser, LCLS is in high demand and heavily oversubscribed. Our overall project employs cognitive engineering methodologies to improve experimental efficiency and scientific productivity by refining experimental interfaces and workflows, simplifying tasks, reducing errors, and improving operator safety and stress levels. Our model simulates aspects of human cognition at multiple cognitive and temporal scales, ranging from seconds to hours, and among agents playing multiple roles, including instrument operator, real time data analyst, and experiment manager. The model can predict impacts stemming from proposed changes to operational interfaces and workflows. Because the model code is open source, and supplemental videos go into detail on all aspects of the model and results, this approach could be applied to other experimental apparatus and processes. Example results demonstrate the model's potential in guiding modifications to improve operational efficiency and scientific output. We discuss the implications of our findings for cognitive engineering in complex experimental settings and outline future directions for research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04734v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Segal, Wan-Lin Hu, Paul Fuoss, Frank E. Ritter, Jeff Shrager</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charmonium-like states with the exotic quantum number $J^{PC} = 3^{-+}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04828v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We apply the method of QCD sum rules to study the $q c \bar q \bar c$ tetraquark states with the exotic quantum number $J^{PC} = 3^{-+}$, and extract the mass of the lowest-lying state to be ${4.49^{+0.45}_{-0.41}}$ GeV. To construct the relevant tetraquark currents we need to explicitly add the covariant derivative operator. Our systematic analysis of these interpolating currents indicates that: a) this state readily decays into the $P$-wave $[\rho J/\psi] / [\omega J/\psi ]$ channel but not into the $ [\rho \chi_{c2}]/[\omega \chi_{c2}]/[J/\psi f_2(1270)]$ channels, and b) it readily decays into the $[D^* \bar D_2^*]$ channel but not into the $P$-wave $[D^* \bar D^*]$ channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04828v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Zhou Xi, Hua-Xing Chen, Wei Chen, T. G. Steele, Yong Zhang, Dan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement and Bell inequality violation in $B\to \it{\Phi\Phi}$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05010v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The decays of the $B$ meson into vector mesons, observed at the LHCb experiment, provide an ideal laboratory to investigate particle physics phenomena with quantum information theory methods. In this article, we focus on the decays yielding a pair of $\it{\Phi}$ mesons to investigate the presence of entanglement in the spin correlations of the system and quantify the amount of Bell inequality violation it entails. Our results show that the present LHCb data allows access to entanglement and to the Bell inequality violation with a significance exceeding the 5$\sigma$ threshold in both the cases. This demonstrates that the strong and electroweak interactions responsible for the $B$ meson decay act as a source of entanglement and the quantum mechanics nature of high-energy phenomena. Particular attention is paid to the assessment of loopholes: deficiencies in the experimental setup which could invalidate the results of the Bell test.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05010v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emidio Gabrielli, Luca Marzola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of the $\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ $\to$ $\psi$(2S)$\Xi^-$ decay and studies of the $\Xi_\mathrm{b}$(5945)$^{0}$ baryon in proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17738v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The first observation of the decay $\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ $\to$ $\psi$(2S)$\Xi^-$ and measurement of the branching ratio of $\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ $\to$ $\psi$(2S)$\Xi^-$ to $\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ $\to$ J/$\psi$$\Xi^-$ are presented. The J/$\psi$ and $\psi$(2S) mesons are reconstructed using their dimuon decay modes. The results are based on proton-proton colliding beam data from the LHC collected by the CMS experiment at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV in 2016-2018, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 140 fb$^{-1}$. The branching fraction ratio is measured to be $\mathcal{B}$($\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ $\to$ $\psi$(2S)$\Xi^-$) / $\mathcal{B}$($\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ $\to$ J/$\psi$$\Xi^-$) = 0.84 $^{+0.21}_{-0.19}$ (stat) $\pm$ 0.10 (syst) $\pm$ 0.02 ($\mathcal{B}$), where the last uncertainty comes from the uncertainties in the branching fractions of the charmonium states. New measurements of the $\Xi_\mathrm{b}$(5945)$^{0}$ baryon mass and natural width are also presented, using the $\Xi_\mathrm{b}^-\pi^+$ final state, where the $\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ baryon is reconstructed through the decays J/$\psi \Xi^-$, $\psi$(2S)$\Xi^-$, J/$\psi \Lambda$K$^-$, and J/$\psi \Sigma^0$K$^-$. Finally, the fraction of the $\Xi^-_\mathrm{b}$ baryons produced from $\Xi_\mathrm{b}$(5945)$^{0}$ decays is determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17738v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.012002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110 (2024) 012002</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> CMS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CaloShowerGAN, a Generative Adversarial Networks model for fast calorimeter shower simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.06515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.06515v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In particle physics, the demand for rapid and precise simulations is rising. The shift from traditional methods to machine learning-based approaches has led to significant advancements in simulating complex detector responses. CaloShowerGAN is a new approach for fast calorimeter simulation based on Generative Adversarial Network (GAN). We use Dataset 1 of the Fast Calorimeter Simulation Challenge 2022 to demonstrate the efficacy of the model to simulate calorimeter showers produced by photons and pions. The dataset is originated from the ATLAS experiment, and we anticipate that this approach can be seamlessly integrated into the ATLAS system. This development brings a significant improvement compared to the deployed GANs by ATLAS and could offer great enhancement to the current ATLAS fast simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.06515v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjp/s13360-024-05397-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. Plus 139, 597 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michele Faucci Giannelli, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Portable Parton-Level Event Generator for the High-Luminosity LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06198v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rapid deployment of computing hardware different from the traditional CPU+RAM model in data centers around the world mandates a change in the design of event generators for the Large Hadron Collider, in order to provide economically and ecologically sustainable simulations for the high-luminosity era of the LHC. Parton-level event generation is one of the most computationally demanding parts of the simulation and is therefore a prime target for improvements. We present a production-ready leading-order parton-level event generation framework capable of utilizing most modern hardware and discuss its performance in the standard candle processes of vector boson and top-quark pair production with up to five additional jets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06198v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Bothmann, Taylor Childers, Walter Giele, Stefan H\"oche, Joshua Isaacson, Max Knobbe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum entanglement and Bell inequality violation at colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07972v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The study of entanglement in particle physics has been gathering pace in the past few years. It is a new field that is providing important results about the possibility of detecting entanglement and testing Bell inequality at colliders for final states as diverse as top-quark, $\tau$-lepton pairs and $\Lambda$-baryons, massive gauge bosons and vector mesons. In this review, after presenting definitions, tools and basic results that are necessary for understanding these developments, we summarize the main findings -- as published by the beginning of year 2024 -- including analyses of experimental data in $B$ meson decays and top-quark pair production. We include a detailed discussion of the results for both qubit and qutrits systems, that is, final states containing spin one-half and spin one particles. Entanglement has also been proposed as a new tool to constrain new particles and fields beyond the Standard Model and we introduce the reader to this promising feature as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07972v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan J. Barr, Marco Fabbrichesi, Roberto Floreanini, Emidio Gabrielli, Luca Marzola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The third family quark mass hierarchy and FCNC in the universal seesaw model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00732v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the study of the quark sector of the universal seesaw model with $\mathrm{SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R \times U(1)_{Y'}}$ gauge symmetry in the massless case of the two lightest quark families. This model aims to explain the mass hierarchy of the third family quark by introducing a vector-like quark (VLQ) partner for each quark. In this model, we introduce $\mathrm{SU(2)_L}$ and $\mathrm{SU(2)_R}$ Higgs doublets. We derive explicitly the Lagrangian for the quark sector, Higgs sector, and kinetic terms of the gauge fields, starting from the Lagrangian, which is invariant under $\mathrm{SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R \times U(1)_{Y'}}$ gauge symmetry. At each stage of the symmetry breaking, we present the Lagrangian with the remaining gauge symmetry. Additionally, we investigate the flavor-changing neutral currents (FCNC) of Higgs ($h$) and $Z$-boson in the interaction with the top, heavy top, bottom, and heavy bottom quark.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00732v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Morozumi, Albertus Hariwangsa Panuluh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Stress Test of Global PDF Fits: Closure Testing the MSHT PDFs and a First Direct Comparison to the Neural Net Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07944v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a first global closure test of the fixed parameterisation (MSHT) approach to PDF fitting. We find that the default MSHT20 parameterisation can reproduce the features of the input set in such a closure test to well within the textbook uncertainties. This provides strong evidence that parameterisation inflexibility in the MSHT20 fit is not a significant issue in the data region. We also present the first completely like-for-like comparison between two global PDF fits, namely MSHT and NNPDF, where the only difference is guaranteed to be due to the fitting methodology. To achieve this, we present a fit to the NNPDF4.0 data and theory inputs, but with the MSHT fixed parameterisation. We find that this gives a moderately, but noticeably, better fit quality than the central NNPDF4.0 fits, both with perturbative and fitted charm, and that this difference persists at the level of the PDFs and benchmark cross sections. The NNPDF4.0 uncertainties are found to be broadly in line with the MSHT results if a textbook $T^2=1$ tolerance is applied, but to be significantly smaller if a tolerance typical of the MSHT20 fit is applied. This points to an inherent inconsistency between these approaches. We discuss the need for an enlarged tolerance criterion in global PDF fits in detail, and demonstrate the impact of data/theory inconsistencies in the closure test setting; namely, these do not lead to any increase in the $T^2=1$ PDF uncertainty. We also investigate the impact of restricting the PDF parameterisation to have fewer free parameters than the default MSHT20 case, and find this can be significant at the level of both closure tests and the full fit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07944v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. A. Harland-Lang, T. Cridge, R. S. Thorne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angular dependent measurement of electron-ion recombination in liquid argon for ionization calorimetry in the ICARUS liquid argon time projection chamber</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12969v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper reports on a measurement of electron-ion recombination in liquid argon in the ICARUS liquid argon time projection chamber (LArTPC). A clear dependence of recombination on the angle of the ionizing particle track relative to the drift electric field is observed. An ellipsoid modified box (EMB) model of recombination describes the data across all measured angles. These measurements are used for the calorimetric energy scale calibration of the ICARUS TPC, which is also presented. The impact of the EMB model is studied on calorimetric particle identification, as well as muon and proton energy measurements. Accounting for the angular dependence in EMB recombination improves the accuracy and precision of these measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12969v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ICARUS collaboration, P. Abratenko, N. Abrego-Martinez, A. Aduszkiewic, F. Akbar, L. Aliaga Soplin, M. Artero Pons, J. Asaadi, W. F. Badgett, B. Baibussinov, B. Behera, V. Bellini, R. Benocci, J. Berger, S. Berkman, S. Bertolucci, M. Betancourt, M. Bonesini, T. Boone, B. Bottino, A. Braggiotti, D. Brailsford, S. J. Brice, V. Brio, C. Brizzolari, H. S. Budd, A. Campani, A. Campos, D. Carber, M. Carneiro, I. Caro Terrazas, H. Carranza, F. Castillo Fernandez, A. Castro, S. Centro, G. Cerati, A. Chatterjee, D. Cherdack, S. Cherubini, N. Chitirasreemadam, M. Cicerchia, T. E. Coan, A. Cocco, M. R. Convery, L. Cooper-Troendle, S. Copello, A. A. Dange, A. de Roeck, S. Di Domizio, L. Di Noto, C. Di Stefano, D. Di Ferdinando, M. Diwan, S. Dolan, L. Domine, S. Donati, F. Drielsma, J. Dyer, S. Dytman, A. Falcone, C. Farnese, A. Fava, A. Ferrari, N. Gallice, F. G. Garcia, C. Gatto, D. Gibin, A. Gioiosa, W. Gu, A. Guglielmi, G. Gurung, H. Hausner, A. Heggestuen, B. Howard, R. Howell, I. Ingratta, C. James, W. Jang, Y. -J. Jwa, L. Kashur, W. Ketchum, J. S. Kim, D. -H. Koh, J. Larkin, Y. Li, C. Mariani, C. M. Marshall, S. Martynenko, N. Mauri, K. S. McFarland, D. P. M\'endez, A. Menegolli, G. Meng, O. G. Miranda, A. Mogan, N. Moggi, E. Montagna, C. Montanari, A. Montanari, M. Mooney, G. Moreno-Granados, J. Mueller, M. Murphy, D. Naples, V. C. L. Nguyen, S. Palestini, M. Pallavicini, V. Paolone, R. Papaleo, L. Pasqualini, L. Patrizii, L. Paudel, G. Petrillo, C. Petta, V. Pia, F. Pietropaolo, F. Poppi, M. Pozzato, G. Putnam, X. Qian, A. Rappoldi, G. L. Raselli, S. Repetto, F. Resnati, A. M. Ricci, G. Riccobene, E. Richards, M. Rosenberg, M. Rossella, P. Roy, C. Rubbia, M. Saad, S. Saha, P. Sala, S. Samanta, P. Sapienza, A. Scaramelli, A. Scarpelli, D. Schmitz, A. Schukraft, D. Senadheera, S-H. Seo, F. Sergiampietri, G. Sirri, J. S. Smedley, J. Smith, L. Stanco, J. Stewart, H. A. Tanaka, F. Tapia, M. Tenti, K. Terao, F. Terranova, V. Togo, D. Torretta, M. Torti, F. Tortorici, R. Triozzi, Y. -T. Tsai, S. Tufanli, T. Usher, F. Varanini, S. Ventura, M. Vicenzi, C. Vignoli, B. Viren, Z. Williams, R. J. Wilson, P. Wilson, J. Wolfs, T. Wongjirad, A. Wood, E. Worcester, M. Wospakrik, H. Yu, J. Yu, A. Zani, J. Zennamo, J. Zettlemoyer, C. Zhang, S. Zucchelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
