<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of d2sigma/d|q|dEavail in charged current neutrino-nucleus interactions at &lt;Ev&gt; = 1.86 GeV using the NOvA Near Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Double- and single-differential cross sections for inclusive charged-current neutrino-nucleus scattering are reported for the kinematic domain 0 to 2 GeV/c in three-momentum transfer and 0 to 2 GeV in available energy, at a mean muon-neutrino energy of 1.86 GeV. The measurements are based on an estimated 995,760 muon-neutrino CC interactions in the scintillator medium of the NOvA Near Detector. The subdomain populated by 2-particle-2-hole reactions is identified by the cross-section excess relative to predictions for neutrino-nucleus scattering that are constrained by a data control sample. Models for 2-particle-2- hole processes are rated by chi-square comparisons of the predicted-versus-measured muon-neutrino CC inclusive cross section over the full phase space and in the restricted subdomain. Shortfalls are observed in neutrino generator predictions obtained using the theory-based Val`encia and SuSAv2 2p2h models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05526v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Acero, B. Acharya, P. Adamson, L. Aliaga, N. Anfimov, A. Antoshkin, E. Arrieta-Diaz, L. Asquith, A. Aurisano, A. Back, N. Balashov, P. Baldi, B. A. Bambah, E. Bannister, A. Barros, S. Bashar, A. Bat, K. Bays, R. Bernstein, T. J. C. Bezerra, V. Bhatnagar, D. Bhattarai, B. Bhuyan, J. Bian, A. C. Booth, R. Bowles, B. Brahma, C. Bromberg, N. Buchanan, A. Butkevich, S. Calvez, T. J. Carroll, E. Catano-Mur, J. P. Cesar, A. Chatla, R. Chirco, B. C. Choudhary, A. Christensen, M. F. Cicala, T. E. Coan, A. Cooleybeck, C. Cortes-Parra, D. Coveyou, L. Cremonesi, G. S. Davies, P. F. Derwent, P. Ding, Z. Djurcic, K. Dobbs, M. Dolce, D. Doyle, D. Duenas Tonguino, E. C. Dukes, A. Dye, R. Ehrlich, E. Ewart, P. Filip, M. J. Frank, H. R. Gallagher, F. Gao, A. Giri, R. A. Gomes, M. C. Goodman, M. Groh, R. Group, A. Habig, F. Hakl, J. Hartnell, R. Hatcher, M. He, K. Heller, V Hewes, A. Himmel, T. Horoho, Y. Ivaneev, A. Ivanova, B. Jargowsky, J. Jarosz, C. Johnson, M. Judah, I. Kakorin, D. M. Kaplan, A. Kalitkina, B. Kirezli-Ozdemir, J. Kleykamp, O. Klimov, L. W. Koerner, L. Kolupaeva, R. Kralik, A. Kumar, C. D. Kuruppu, V. Kus, T. Lackey, K. Lang, J. Lesmeister, A. Lister, J. Liu, J. A. Lock, M. Lokajicek, M. MacMahon, S. Magill, W. A. Mann, M. T. Manoharan, M. Manrique Plata, M. L. Marshak, M. Martinez-Casales, V. Matveev, B. Mehta, M. D. Messier, H. Meyer, T. Miao, W. H. Miller, S. Mishra, S. R. Mishra, R. Mohanta, A. Moren, A. Morozova, W. Mu, L. Mualem, M. Muether, K. Mulder, D. Myers, D. Naples, A. Nath, S. Nelleri, J. K. Nelson, R. Nichol, E. Niner, A. Norman, A. Norrick, T. Nosek, H. Oh, A. Olshevskiy, T. Olson, M. Ozkaynak, A. Pal, J. Paley, L. Panda, R. B. Patterson, G. Pawloski, R. Petti, R. K. Plunkett, L. R. Prais, M. Rabelhofer, A. Rafique, V. Raj, M. Rajaoalisoa, B. Ramson, B. Rebel, P. Roy, O. Samoylov, M. C. Sanchez, S. Sanchez Falero, P. Shanahan, P. Sharma, A. Sheshukov,  Shivam, A. Shmakov, W. Shorrock, S. Shukla, D. K. Singha, I. Singh, P. Singh, V. Singh, E. Smith, J. Smolik, P. Snopok, N. Solomey, A. Sousa, K. Soustruznik, M. Strait, L. Suter, A. Sutton, K. Sutton, S. Swain, C. Sweeney, A. Sztuc, B. Tapia Oregui, P. Tas, T. Thakore, J. Thomas, E. Tiras, Y. Torun, D. Tran, J. Trokan-Tenorio, J. Urheim, P. Vahle, Z. Vallari, J. D. Villamil, K. J. Vockerodt, M. Wallbank, M. Wetstein, D. Whittington, D. A. Wickremasinghe, T. Wieber, J. Wolcott, M. Wrobel, S. Wu, W. Wu, Y. Xiao, B. Yaeggy, A. Yahaya, A. Yankelevich, K. Yonehara, Y. Yu, S. Zadorozhnyy, J. Zalesak, R. Zwaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge ratio of cosmic ray muons in momentum range ~ 1 to 3 GeV/c</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents the measurements of the cosmic muon charge ratio as a function of full azimuthal angle and momentum within the range of 0.8 to 3.0 GeV/c, using the mini-ICAL detector. The detector, comprising 10 layers of RPCs, has collected cosmic muon data since August 2018 till recent time, at an altitude of 160 m above sea level at the Inter-Institutional Center for High Energy Physics in Madurai, India $(9^\circ56'\,N, 78^\circ00'\,E)$. The muon charge identification is achieved through the use of a magnetic field of strength 1.4 T. The analysis shows that the cosmic muon charge ratio, $R_\mu = N_{\mu^+}/N_{\mu^-}$, ranges from 1.1 to 1.2 and has small dependency on the zenith angle. The charge ratio's dependence on momentum and azimuthal angle is thoroughly examined for a wide range of zenith angle upto $50^\circ$. These measurements are compared with the predictions from various combinations of different hadronic models in CORSIKA extensive air shower simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05719v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raj Shah, J. M. John, Suryanarayan Mondal, S. Pethuraj, G. Majumder, P. Shukla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of an axial-vector state in the study of $\psi(3686) \to \phi \eta \eta'$ decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using (2712.4 $\pm$ 14.3)$\times 10^{6}$ $\psi(3686)$ events collected with the BESIII detector at BEPCII, a partial wave analysis of the decay $\psi(3686) \to \phi \eta \eta' $ is performed with the covariant tensor approach. An axial-vector state with a mass near 2.3 $\rm GeV/c^2$ is observed for the first time. Its mass and width are measured to be 2316 $\pm 9_{\mathrm{stat}} \pm 30_{\mathrm{syst}}\,\rm MeV/c^2$ and 89 $\pm 15_{\mathrm{stat}} \pm 26_{\mathrm{syst}}\,\rm MeV$, respectively. The product branching fractions of $\mathcal{B}(\psi(3686) \to X(2300) \eta') \mathcal{B}(X(2300)\to \phi \eta)$ and $\mathcal{B}(\psi(3686) \to X(2300) \eta)\mathcal{B}(X(2300)\to \phi \eta')$ are determined to be (4.8 $\pm 1.3_{\mathrm{stat}} \pm 0.7_{\mathrm{syst}})\times 10^{-6}$ and (2.2 $\pm 0.7_{\mathrm{stat}} \pm 0.7_{\mathrm{syst}})\times 10^{-6}$, respectively. The branching fraction $\mathcal{B}(\psi(3686) \to \phi \eta \eta')$ is measured for the first time to be (3.14$\pm0.17_{\mathrm{stat}}\pm0.24_{\mathrm{syst}})\times10^{-5}$.
  The first uncertainties are statistical and the second are systematic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05736v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> BESIII Collaboration, M. Ablikim, M. N. Achasov, P. Adlarson, O. Afedulidis, X. C. Ai, R. Aliberti, A. Amoroso, Q. An, Y. Bai, O. Bakina, I. Balossino, Y. Ban, H. -R. Bao, V. Batozskaya, K. Begzsuren, N. Berger, M. Berlowski, M. Bertani, D. Bettoni, F. Bianchi, E. Bianco, A. Bortone, I. Boyko, R. A. Briere, A. Brueggemann, H. Cai, X. Cai, A. Calcaterra, G. F. Cao, N. Cao, S. A. Cetin, J. F. Chang, W. L. Chang, G. R. Che, G. Chelkov, C. Chen, C. H. Chen, Chao Chen, G. Chen, H. S. Chen, M. L. Chen, S. J. Chen, S. L. Chen, S. M. Chen, T. Chen, X. R. Chen, X. T. Chen, Y. B. Chen, Y. Q. Chen, Z. J. Chen, Z. Y. Chen, S. K. Choi, X. Chu, G. Cibinetto, F. Cossio, J. J. Cui, H. L. Dai, J. P. Dai, A. Dbeyssi, R. E. de Boer, D. Dedovich, C. Q. Deng, Z. Y. Deng, A. Denig, I. Denysenko, M. Destefanis, F. De Mori, B. Ding, X. X. Ding, Y. Ding, Y. Ding, J. Dong, L. Y. Dong, M. Y. Dong, X. Dong, M. C. Du, S. X. Du, Z. H. Duan, P. Egorov, Y. H. Fan, J. Fang, J. Fang, S. S. Fang, W. X. Fang, Y. Fang, Y. Q. Fang, R. Farinelli, L. Fava, F. Feldbauer, G. Felici, C. Q. Feng, J. H. Feng, Y. T. Feng, K. Fischer, M. Fritsch, C. D. Fu, J. L. Fu, Y. W. Fu, H. Gao, Y. N. Gao, Yang Gao, S. Garbolino, I. Garzia, L. Ge, P. T. Ge, Z. W. Ge, C. Geng, E. M. Gersabeck, A. Gilman, K. Goetzen, L. Gong, W. X. Gong, W. Gradl, S. Gramigna, M. Greco, M. H. Gu, Y. T. Gu, C. Y. Guan, Z. L. Guan, A. Q. Guo, L. B. Guo, M. J. Guo, R. P. Guo, Y. P. Guo, A. Guskov, J. Gutierrez, K. L. Han, T. T. Han, X. Q. Hao, F. A. Harris, K. K. He, K. L. He, F. H. Heinsius, C. H. Heinz, Y. K. Heng, C. Herold, T. Holtmann, P. C. Hong, G. Y. Hou, X. T. Hou, Y. R. Hou, Z. L. Hou, B. Y. Hu, H. M. Hu, J. F. Hu, T. Hu, Y. Hu, G. S. Huang, K. X. Huang, L. Q. Huang, X. T. Huang, Y. P. Huang, T. Hussain, F. H\"olzken, N H\"usken, N. in der Wiesche, M. Irshad, J. Jackson, S. Janchiv, J. H. Jeong, Q. Ji, Q. P. Ji, W. Ji, X. B. Ji, X. L. Ji, Y. Y. Ji, X. Q. Jia, Z. K. Jia, D. Jiang, H. B. Jiang, P. C. Jiang, S. S. Jiang, T. J. Jiang, X. S. Jiang, Y. Jiang, J. B. Jiao, J. K. Jiao, Z. Jiao, S. Jin, Y. Jin, M. Q. Jing, X. M. Jing, T. Johansson, S. Kabana, N. Kalantar-Nayestanaki, X. L. Kang, X. S. Kang, M. Kavatsyuk, B. C. Ke, V. Khachatryan, A. Khoukaz, R. Kiuchi, O. B. Kolcu, B. Kopf, M. Kuessner, X. Kui, N. Kumar, A. Kupsc, W. K\"uhn, J. J. Lane, P. Larin, L. Lavezzi, T. T. Lei, Z. H. Lei, H. Leithoff, M. Lellmann, T. Lenz, C. Li, C. Li, C. H. Li, Cheng Li, D. M. Li, F. Li, G. Li, H. Li, H. B. Li, H. J. Li, H. N. Li, Hui Li, J. R. Li, J. S. Li, Ke Li, L. J Li, L. K. Li, Lei Li, M. H. Li, P. R. Li, Q. M. Li, Q. X. Li, R. Li, S. X. Li, T. Li, W. D. Li, W. G. Li, X. Li, X. H. Li, X. L. Li, Xiaoyu Li, Y. G. Li, Z. J. Li, Z. X. Li, C. Liang, H. Liang, H. Liang, Y. F. Liang, Y. T. Liang, G. R. Liao, L. Z. Liao, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, A. Limphirat, D. X. Lin, T. Lin, B. J. Liu, B. X. Liu, C. Liu, C. X. Liu, F. H. Liu, Fang Liu, Feng Liu, G. M. Liu, H. Liu, H. B. Liu, H. M. Liu, Huanhuan Liu, Huihui Liu, J. B. Liu, J. Y. Liu, K. Liu, K. Y. Liu, Ke Liu, L. Liu, L. C. Liu, Lu Liu, M. H. Liu, P. L. Liu, Q. Liu, S. B. Liu, T. Liu, W. K. Liu, W. M. Liu, X. Liu, X. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. B. Liu, Z. A. Liu, Z. D. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, X. C. Lou, F. X. Lu, H. J. Lu, J. G. Lu, X. L. Lu, Y. Lu, Y. P. Lu, Z. H. Lu, C. L. Luo, M. X. Luo, T. Luo, X. L. Luo, X. R. Lyu, Y. F. Lyu, F. C. Ma, H. Ma, H. L. Ma, J. L. Ma, L. L. Ma, M. M. Ma, Q. M. Ma, R. Q. Ma, X. T. Ma, X. Y. Ma, Y. Ma, Y. M. Ma, F. E. Maas, M. Maggiora, S. Malde, A. Mangoni, Y. J. Mao, Z. P. Mao, S. Marcello, Z. X. Meng, J. G. Messchendorp, G. Mezzadri, H. Miao, T. J. Min, R. E. Mitchell, X. H. Mo, B. Moses, N. Yu. Muchnoi, J. Muskalla, Y. Nefedov, F. Nerling, I. B. Nikolaev, Z. Ning, S. Nisar, Q. L. Niu, W. D. Niu, Y. Niu, S. L. Olsen, Q. Ouyang, S. Pacetti, X. Pan, Y. Pan, A. Pathak, P. Patteri, Y. P. Pei, M. Pelizaeus, H. P. Peng, Y. Y. Peng, K. Peters, J. L. Ping, R. G. Ping, S. Plura, V. Prasad, F. Z. Qi, H. Qi, H. R. Qi, M. Qi, T. Y. Qi, S. Qian, W. B. Qian, C. F. Qiao, X. K. Qiao, J. J. Qin, L. Q. Qin, X. S. Qin, Z. H. Qin, J. F. Qiu, S. Q. Qu, Z. H. Qu, C. F. Redmer, K. J. Ren, A. Rivetti, M. Rolo, G. Rong, Ch. Rosner, S. N. Ruan, N. Salone, A. Sarantsev, Y. Schelhaas, K. Schoenning, M. Scodeggio, K. Y. Shan, W. Shan, X. Y. Shan, Z. J Shang, J. F. Shangguan, L. G. Shao, M. Shao, C. P. Shen, H. F. Shen, W. H. Shen, X. Y. Shen, B. A. Shi, H. C. Shi, J. L. Shi, J. Y. Shi, Q. Q. Shi, R. S. Shi, S. Y. Shi, X. Shi, J. J. Song, T. Z. Song, W. M. Song, Y. J. Song, Y. X. Song, S. Sosio, S. Spataro, F. Stieler, Y. J. Su, G. B. Sun, G. X. Sun, H. Sun, H. K. Sun, J. F. Sun, K. Sun, L. Sun, S. S. Sun, T. Sun, W. Y. Sun, Y. Sun, Y. J. Sun, Y. Z. Sun, Z. Q. Sun, Z. T. Sun, C. J. Tang, G. Y. Tang, J. Tang, Y. A. Tang, L. Y. Tao, Q. T. Tao, M. Tat, J. X. Teng, V. Thoren, W. H. Tian, Y. Tian, Z. F. Tian, I. Uman, Y. Wan, S. J. Wang, B. Wang, B. L. Wang, Bo Wang, D. Y. Wang, F. Wang, H. J. Wang, J. P. Wang, K. Wang, L. L. Wang, M. Wang, Meng Wang, N. Y. Wang, S. Wang, S. Wang, T. Wang, T. J. Wang, W. Wang, W. Wang, W. P. Wang, X. Wang, X. F. Wang, X. J. Wang, X. L. Wang, X. N. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. D. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. L. Wang, Y. N. Wang, Y. Q. Wang, Yaqian Wang, Yi Wang, Z. Wang, Z. L. Wang, Z. Y. Wang, Ziyi Wang, D. Wei, D. H. Wei, F. Weidner, S. P. Wen, Y. R. Wen, U. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. Wolke, L. Wollenberg, C. Wu, J. F. Wu, L. H. Wu, L. J. Wu, X. Wu, X. H. Wu, Y. Wu, Y. H. Wu, Y. J. Wu, Z. Wu, L. Xia, X. M. Xian, B. H. Xiang, T. Xiang, D. Xiao, G. Y. Xiao, S. Y. Xiao, Y. L. Xiao, Z. J. Xiao, C. Xie, X. H. Xie, Y. Xie, Y. G. Xie, Y. H. Xie, Z. P. Xie, T. Y. Xing, C. F. Xu, C. J. Xu, G. F. Xu, H. Y. Xu, Q. J. Xu, Q. N. Xu, W. Xu, W. L. Xu, X. P. Xu, Y. C. Xu, Z. P. Xu, Z. S. Xu, F. Yan, L. Yan, W. B. Yan, W. C. Yan, X. Q. Yan, H. J. Yang, H. L. Yang, H. X. Yang, Tao Yang, Y. Yang, Y. F. Yang, Y. X. Yang, Yifan Yang, Z. W. Yang, Z. P. Yao, M. Ye, M. H. Ye, J. H. Yin, Z. Y. You, B. X. Yu, C. X. Yu, G. Yu, J. S. Yu, T. Yu, X. D. Yu, Y. C. Yu, C. Z. Yuan, J. Yuan, L. Yuan, S. C. Yuan, Y. Yuan, Z. Y. Yuan, C. X. Yue, A. A. Zafar, F. R. Zeng, S. H. Zeng, X. Zeng, Y. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, X. Y. Zhai, Y. C. Zhai, Y. H. Zhan, A. Q. Zhang, B. L. Zhang, B. X. Zhang, D. H. Zhang, G. Y. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. C. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. Q. Zhang, H. Y. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. J. Zhang, J. L. Zhang, J. Q. Zhang, J. W. Zhang, J. X. Zhang, J. Y. Zhang, J. Z. Zhang, Jianyu Zhang, L. M. Zhang, Lei Zhang, P. Zhang, Q. Y. Zhang, R. Y Zhang, Shuihan Zhang, Shulei Zhang, X. D. Zhang, X. M. Zhang, X. Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. T. Zhang, Y. H. Zhang, Y. M. Zhang, Yan Zhang, Yao Zhang, Z. D. Zhang, Z. H. Zhang, Z. L. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, G. Zhao, J. Y. Zhao, J. Z. Zhao, Lei Zhao, Ling Zhao, M. G. Zhao, R. P. Zhao, S. J. Zhao, Y. B. Zhao, Y. X. Zhao, Z. G. Zhao, A. Zhemchugov, B. Zheng, J. P. Zheng, W. J. Zheng, Y. H. Zheng, B. Zhong, X. Zhong, H. Zhou, J. Y. Zhou, L. P. Zhou, X. Zhou, X. K. Zhou, X. R. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, Y. Z. Zhou, J. Zhu, K. Zhu, K. J. Zhu, L. Zhu, L. X. Zhu, S. H. Zhu, S. Q. Zhu, T. J. Zhu, W. J. Zhu, Y. C. Zhu, Z. A. Zhu, J. H. Zou, J. Zu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angular distribution study for high mass dimuon pairs in CMS open 2012 data and for Mono-Z$^{\prime}$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This analysis uses the CMS open data to study the angular distribution of high-mass dimuon pairs produced during proton-proton interaction at a center of mass energy of 8 TeV. The study uses the cos$\theta_{\text{CS}}$ variable defined in the Collins Soper frame. In the Standard Model, the production of high-mass dimuon pairs is dominated by the Drell-Yan process, which exhibits a strong forward-backward asymmetry. However, many scenarios beyond the Standard Model predict different shapes for the cos$\theta_{CS}$ distribution. In excess events beyond the Standard Model, the angular distribution can be used to distinguish between those models. The Mono-Z$^{\prime}$ model has been used to interpret the data, and no deviation from the SM has been observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05755v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Elgammal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean transverse momentum fluctuations in pp collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV using ALICE detector at LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05914v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An analysis of the high-multiplicity triggered pp data at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV, obtained with the ALICE detector, is carried out to study the event-by-event fluctuations of mean transverse momentum ($\langle p_{\rm T}\rangle$) using a two-particle \pt correlator. The driving force behind these studies is the search for dynamical fluctuations that may be associated with the formation of Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP) droplets in small collision systems, such as pp, for which traces have been observed in previous studies. The values of the correlator are observed to decrease with increasing charged particle density and exhibit power-law behavior similar to the one observed for pp and Pb--Pb collisions at lower energies. The findings also reveal that Monte Carlo model PYTHIA reproduces the observed dependence of the correlator on charged particle density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05914v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bushra Ali (for the ALICE Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Hadron Production in $e^+e^-$ Annihilation at BESIII</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This talk presents recent experimental findings at BESIII experiment, including three distinct studies. Firstly, it reports the measurements of the Born cross-sections of $e^+e^-\to\Sigma^+\bar\Sigma^-$, $\Xi^-\bar\Xi^+$, $K^{0}_{S}K^{0}_{L}$ and $K^-\bar\Xi^+\Lambda/\Sigma^0+c.c.$ at center-of-mass energies between 3.5 and 4.9 GeV. Secondly, it delves into the observation of significant flavor-SU(3) breaking in the kaon wave function at 12 GeV$^2$$&lt;Q^2&lt;$25 GeV$^2$, the discovery of $\psi(3770)\to K^{0}_{S}K^{0}_{L}$ and the evidence of $\psi(4160)\to K^-\bar\Xi^+\Lambda+c.c.$. Thirdly, it discusses the search for the production of deuterons in $e^+e^-$ annihilation at center-of-mass energies between 4.1 and 4.7 GeV in the reactions of $e^+e^-\to pp\pi^-\bar{d}+c.c.$ and $pp\bar{p}\bar{n}\pi^-+c.c.$. These results offer new perspectives on hadron production in the baryonic final states and the flavor dynamics within the kaon wave function, and the rare decay processes involving the $\psi(3770)$ resonance, contributing to our understanding of hadron dynamics in this energy regime through baryon final states produced in $e^+e^-$ collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05990v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiongfei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for the radiative decays $D^+\to\gamma\rho^+$ and $D^+\to\gamma K^{*+}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We search for the radiative decays $D^{+} \to \gamma \rho^+$ and $D^{+} \to \gamma K^{*+}$ using 20.3~fb$^{-1}$ of $e^+e^-$ annihilation data collected at the center-of-mass energy $\sqrt{s}=3.773$ GeV by the BESIII detector operating at the BEPCII collider. No significant signals are observed, and the upper limits on the branching fractions of $D^{+} \to \gamma \rho^+$ and $D^{+} \to \gamma K^{*+}$ at 90\% confidence level are set to be $1.3\times10^{-5}$ and $1.8\times10^{-5}$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06500v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> BESIII Collaboration, M. Ablikim, M. N. Achasov, P. Adlarson, O. Afedulidis, X. C. Ai, R. Aliberti, A. Amoroso, Q. An, Y. Bai, O. Bakina, I. Balossino, Y. Ban, H. -R. Bao, V. Batozskaya, K. Begzsuren, N. Berger, M. Berlowski, M. Bertani, D. Bettoni, F. Bianchi, E. Bianco, A. Bortone, I. Boyko, R. A. Briere, A. Brueggemann, H. Cai, X. Cai, A. Calcaterra, G. F. Cao, N. Cao, S. A. Cetin, X. Y. Chai, J. F. Chang, G. R. Che, Y. Z. Che, G. Chelkov, C. Chen, C. H. Chen, Chao Chen, G. Chen, H. S. Chen, H. Y. Chen, M. L. Chen, S. J. Chen, S. L. Chen, S. M. Chen, T. Chen, X. R. Chen, X. T. Chen, Y. B. Chen, Y. Q. Chen, Z. J. Chen, Z. Y. Chen, S. K. Choi, G. Cibinetto, F. Cossio, J. J. Cui, H. L. Dai, J. P. Dai, A. Dbeyssi, R. E. de Boer, D. Dedovich, C. Q. Deng, Z. Y. Deng, A. Denig, I. Denysenko, M. Destefanis, F. De Mori, B. Ding, X. X. Ding, Y. Ding, Y. Ding, J. Dong, L. Y. Dong, M. Y. Dong, X. Dong, M. C. Du, S. X. Du, Y. Y. Duan, Z. H. Duan, P. Egorov, Y. H. Fan, J. Fang, J. Fang, S. S. Fang, W. X. Fang, Y. Fang, Y. Q. Fang, R. Farinelli, L. Fava, F. Feldbauer, G. Felici, C. Q. Feng, J. H. Feng, Y. T. Feng, M. Fritsch, C. D. Fu, J. L. Fu, Y. W. Fu, H. Gao, X. B. Gao, Y. N. Gao, Yang Gao, S. Garbolino, I. Garzia, L. Ge, P. T. Ge, Z. W. Ge, C. Geng, E. M. Gersabeck, A. Gilman, K. Goetzen, L. Gong, W. X. Gong, W. Gradl, S. Gramigna, M. Greco, M. H. Gu, Y. T. Gu, C. Y. Guan, A. Q. Guo, L. B. Guo, M. J. Guo, R. P. Guo, Y. P. Guo, A. Guskov, J. Gutierrez, K. L. Han, T. T. Han, F. Hanisch, X. Q. Hao, F. A. Harris, K. K. He, K. L. He, F. H. Heinsius, C. H. Heinz, Y. K. Heng, C. Herold, T. Holtmann, P. C. Hong, G. Y. Hou, X. T. Hou, Y. R. Hou, Z. L. Hou, B. Y. Hu, H. M. Hu, J. F. Hu, Q. P. Hu, S. L. Hu, T. Hu, Y. Hu, G. S. Huang, K. X. Huang, L. Q. Huang, X. T. Huang, Y. P. Huang, Y. S. Huang, T. Hussain, F. H\"olzken, N. H\"usken, N. in der Wiesche, J. Jackson, S. Janchiv, Q. Ji, Q. P. Ji, W. Ji, X. B. Ji, X. L. Ji, Y. Y. Ji, X. Q. Jia, Z. K. Jia, D. Jiang, H. B. Jiang, P. C. Jiang, S. S. Jiang, T. J. Jiang, X. S. Jiang, Y. Jiang, J. B. Jiao, J. K. Jiao, Z. Jiao, S. Jin, Y. Jin, M. Q. Jing, X. M. Jing, T. Johansson, S. Kabana, N. Kalantar-Nayestanaki, X. L. Kang, X. S. Kang, M. Kavatsyuk, B. C. Ke, V. Khachatryan, A. Khoukaz, R. Kiuchi, O. B. Kolcu, B. Kopf, M. Kuessner, X. Kui, N. Kumar, A. Kupsc, W. K\"uhn, J. J. Lane, L. Lavezzi, T. T. Lei, Z. H. Lei, M. Lellmann, T. Lenz, C. Li, C. Li, C. H. Li, Cheng Li, D. M. Li, F. Li, G. Li, H. B. Li, H. J. Li, H. N. Li, Hui Li, J. R. Li, J. S. Li, K. Li, K. L. Li, L. J. Li, L. K. Li, Lei Li, M. H. Li, P. R. Li, Q. M. Li, Q. X. Li, R. Li, S. X. Li, T. Li, W. D. Li, W. G. Li, X. Li, X. H. Li, X. L. Li, X. Y. Li, X. Z. Li, Y. G. Li, Z. J. Li, Z. Y. Li, C. Liang, H. Liang, H. Liang, Y. F. Liang, Y. T. Liang, G. R. Liao, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, A. Limphirat, C. C. Lin, D. X. Lin, T. Lin, B. J. Liu, B. X. Liu, C. Liu, C. X. Liu, F. Liu, F. H. Liu, Feng Liu, G. M. Liu, H. Liu, H. B. Liu, H. H. Liu, H. M. Liu, Huihui Liu, J. B. Liu, J. Y. Liu, K. Liu, K. Y. Liu, Ke Liu, L. Liu, L. C. Liu, Lu Liu, M. H. Liu, P. L. Liu, Q. Liu, S. B. Liu, T. Liu, W. K. Liu, W. M. Liu, X. Liu, X. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. B. Liu, Z. A. Liu, Z. D. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, X. C. Lou, F. X. Lu, H. J. Lu, J. G. Lu, X. L. Lu, Y. Lu, Y. P. Lu, Z. H. Lu, C. L. Luo, J. R. Luo, M. X. Luo, T. Luo, X. L. Luo, X. R. Lyu, Y. F. Lyu, F. C. Ma, H. Ma, H. L. Ma, J. L. Ma, L. L. Ma, L. R. Ma, M. M. Ma, Q. M. Ma, R. Q. Ma, T. Ma, X. T. Ma, X. Y. Ma, Y. M. Ma, F. E. Maas, I. MacKay, M. Maggiora, S. Malde, Y. J. Mao, Z. P. Mao, S. Marcello, Z. X. Meng, J. G. Messchendorp, G. Mezzadri, H. Miao, T. J. Min, R. E. Mitchell, X. H. Mo, B. Moses, N. Yu. Muchnoi, J. Muskalla, Y. Nefedov, F. Nerling, L. S. Nie, I. B. Nikolaev, Z. Ning, S. Nisar, Q. L. Niu, W. D. Niu, Y. Niu, S. L. Olsen, S. L. Olsen, Q. Ouyang, S. Pacetti, X. Pan, Y. Pan, Y. P. Pei, M. Pelizaeus, H. P. Peng, Y. Y. Peng, K. Peters, J. L. Ping, R. G. Ping, S. Plura, V. Prasad, F. Z. Qi, H. Qi, H. R. Qi, M. Qi, T. Y. Qi, S. Qian, W. B. Qian, C. F. Qiao, J. H. Qiao, X. K. Qiao, J. J. Qin, L. Q. Qin, L. Y. Qin, X. P. Qin, X. S. Qin, Z. H. Qin, J. F. Qiu, Z. H. Qu, C. F. Redmer, K. J. Ren, A. Rivetti, M. Rolo, G. Rong, Ch. Rosner, M. Q. Ruan, S. N. Ruan, N. Salone, A. Sarantsev, Y. Schelhaas, K. Schoenning, M. Scodeggio, K. Y. Shan, W. Shan, X. Y. Shan, Z. J. Shang, J. F. Shangguan, L. G. Shao, M. Shao, C. P. Shen, H. F. Shen, W. H. Shen, X. Y. Shen, B. A. Shi, H. Shi, J. L. Shi, J. Y. Shi, Q. Q. Shi, S. Y. Shi, X. Shi, J. J. Song, T. Z. Song, W. M. Song, Y. J. Song, Y. X. Song, S. Sosio, S. Spataro, F. Stieler, S. S Su, Y. J. Su, G. B. Sun, G. X. Sun, H. Sun, H. K. Sun, J. F. Sun, K. Sun, L. Sun, S. S. Sun, T. Sun, W. Y. Sun, Y. Sun, Y. J. Sun, Y. Z. Sun, Z. Q. Sun, Z. T. Sun, C. J. Tang, G. Y. Tang, J. Tang, M. Tang, Y. A. Tang, L. Y. Tao, Q. T. Tao, M. Tat, J. X. Teng, V. Thoren, W. H. Tian, Y. Tian, Z. F. Tian, I. Uman, Y. Wan, S. J. Wang, B. Wang, B. L. Wang, Bo Wang, D. Y. Wang, F. Wang, H. J. Wang, J. J. Wang, J. P. Wang, K. Wang, L. L. Wang, L. W. Wang, M. Wang, N. Y. Wang, S. Wang, S. Wang, T. Wang, T. J. Wang, W. Wang, W. Wang, W. P. Wang, X. Wang, X. F. Wang, X. J. Wang, X. L. Wang, X. N. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. D. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. H. Wang, Y. L. Wang, Y. N. Wang, Y. Q. Wang, Yaqian Wang, Yi Wang, Z. Wang, Z. L. Wang, Z. Y. Wang, Ziyi Wang, D. H. Wei, F. Weidner, S. P. Wen, Y. R. Wen, U. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. Wolke, L. Wollenberg, C. Wu, J. F. Wu, L. H. Wu, L. J. Wu, X. Wu, X. H. Wu, Y. Wu, Y. H. Wu, Y. J. Wu, Z. Wu, L. Xia, X. M. Xian, B. H. Xiang, T. Xiang, D. Xiao, G. Y. Xiao, S. Y. Xiao, Y. L. Xiao, Z. J. Xiao, C. Xie, X. H. Xie, Y. Xie, Y. G. Xie, Y. H. Xie, Z. P. Xie, T. Y. Xing, C. F. Xu, C. J. Xu, G. F. Xu, H. Y. Xu, M. Xu, Q. J. Xu, Q. N. Xu, W. Xu, W. L. Xu, X. P. Xu, Y. Xu, Y. C. Xu, Z. S. Xu, F. Yan, L. Yan, W. B. Yan, W. C. Yan, X. Q. Yan, H. J. Yang, H. L. Yang, H. X. Yang, J. H. Yang, T. Yang, Y. Yang, Y. F. Yang, Y. F. Yang, Y. X. Yang, Z. W. Yang, Z. P. Yao, M. Ye, M. H. Ye, J. H. Yin, Junhao Yin, Z. Y. You, B. X. Yu, C. X. Yu, G. Yu, G. Yu, J. S. Yu, M. C. Yu, T. Yu, X. D. Yu, Y. C. Yu, C. Z. Yuan, J. Yuan, J. Yuan, L. Yuan, S. C. Yuan, Y. Yuan, Z. Y. Yuan, C. X. Yue, A. A. Zafar, F. R. Zeng, S. H. Zeng, X. Zeng, Y. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, X. Y. Zhai, Y. C. Zhai, Y. H. Zhan, A. Q. Zhang, B. L. Zhang, B. X. Zhang, D. H. Zhang, G. Y. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. C. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. Q. Zhang, H. R. Zhang, H. Y. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. J. Zhang, J. L. Zhang, J. Q. Zhang, J. S. Zhang, J. W. Zhang, J. X. Zhang, J. Y. Zhang, J. Z. Zhang, Jianyu Zhang, L. M. Zhang, Lei Zhang, P. Zhang, Q. Y. Zhang, R. Y. Zhang, S. H. Zhang, Shulei Zhang, X. M. Zhang, X. Y Zhang, X. Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. T. Zhang, Y. H. Zhang, Y. M. Zhang, Yan Zhang, Z. D. Zhang, Z. H. Zhang, Z. L. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Z. Zhang, G. Zhao, J. Y. Zhao, J. Z. Zhao, L. Zhao, Lei Zhao, M. G. Zhao, N. Zhao, R. P. Zhao, S. J. Zhao, Y. B. Zhao, Y. X. Zhao, Z. G. Zhao, A. Zhemchugov, B. Zheng, B. M. Zheng, J. P. Zheng, W. J. Zheng, Y. H. Zheng, B. Zhong, X. Zhong, J. Y. Zhou, L. P. Zhou, S. Zhou, X. Zhou, X. K. Zhou, X. R. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, Y. Z. Zhou, Z. C. Zhou, A. N. Zhu, J. Zhu, K. Zhu, K. J. Zhu, K. S. Zhu, L. Zhu, L. X. Zhu, S. H. Zhu, T. J. Zhu, W. D. Zhu, Y. C. Zhu, Z. A. Zhu, J. H. Zou, J. Zu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepMuon: Accelerating Cosmic-Ray Muon Simulation Based on Optimal Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cosmic muon imaging technology is increasingly being applied in various fields. However, simulating cosmic muons typically requires the rapid generation of a large number of muons and tracking their complex trajectories through intricate structures. This process is highly computationally demanding and consumes significant CPU time.To address these challenges, we introduce DeepMuon, an innovative deep learning model designed to efficiently and accurately generate cosmic muon distributions. In our approach, we employ the inverse Box-Cox transformation to reduce the kurtosis of the muon energy distribution, making it more statistically manageable for the model to learn. Additionally, we utilize the Sliced Wasserstein Distance (SWD) as a loss function to ensure precise simulation of the high-dimensional distributions of cosmic muons.We also demonstrate that DeepMuon can accurately learn muon distribution patterns from a limited set of data, enabling it to simulate real-world cosmic muon distributions as captured by detectors. Compared to traditional tools like CRY, DeepMuon significantly increases the speed of muon generation at sea level. Furthermore, we have developed a pipeline using DeepMuon that directly simulates muon distributions in underwater environments, dramatically accelerating simulations for underwater muon radiography and tomography.For more details on our open-source project, please visit https://github.com/wangab0/deepmuon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06539v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ao-Bo Wang, Chu-Cheng Pan, Xiang Dong, Yu-Chang Sun, Yu-Xuan Hu, Ao-Yan Cheng, Hao Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning opportunities for online and offline tagging of photo-induced and diffractive events in continuous readout experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06983v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing data rates in modern high-energy physics experiments such as ALICE at the LHC and the upcoming ePIC experiment at the Electron-Ion Collider (EIC) present significant challenges in real-time event selection and data storage. This paper explores the novel application of machine learning techniques, to enhance the identification of rare low-multiplicity events, such as ultraperipheral collisions (UPCs) and central exclusive diffractive processes. We focus on utilising machine learning models to perform early event classification, even before full event reconstruction, in continuous readout systems. We estimate data rates and disk space requirements for photoproduction and central exclusive diffractive processes in both ALICE and ePIC. We show that machine learning techniques can not only optimize data selection but also significantly reduce storage requirements in continuous readout environments, providing a scalable solution for the upcoming era of high-luminosity particle physics experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06983v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Ragoni, Janet Seger, Christopher Anson, David Tlusty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPECTER: Efficient Evaluation of the Spectral EMD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05379v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Energy Mover's Distance (EMD) has seen use in collider physics as a metric between events and as a geometric method of defining infrared and collinear safe observables. Recently, the Spectral Energy Mover's Distance (SEMD) has been proposed as a more analytically tractable alternative to the EMD. In this work, we obtain a closed-form expression for the Riemannian-like p = 2 SEMD metric between events, eliminating the need to numerically solve an optimal transport problem. Additionally, we show how the SEMD can be used to define event and jet shape observables by minimizing the distance between events and parameterized energy flows (similar to the EMD), and we obtain closed-form expressions for several of these observables. We also present the SPECTER framework, an efficient and highly parallelized implementation of the SEMD metric and SEMD-derived shape observables as an analogue of the previously-introduced SHAPER for EMD-based computations. We demonstrate that computing the SEMD with SPECTER can be up to a thousand times faster than computing the EMD with standard optimal transport libraries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05379v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rikab Gambhir, Andrew J. Larkoski, Jesse Thaler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NuFit-6.0: Updated global analysis of three-flavor neutrino oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an updated global analysis of neutrino
  oscillation data as of September 2024. The parameters
  $\theta_{12}$, $\theta_{13}$, $\Delta m^2_{21}$, and $|\Delta m^2_{3\ell}|$
  ($\ell = 1,2$) are well-determined with relative precision at
  $3\sigma$ of about 13\%, 8\%, 15\%, and 6\%, respectively. The
  third mixing angle $\theta_{23}$ still suffers from the octant
  ambiguity, with no clear indication of whether it is larger or
  smaller than $45^\circ$. The determination of the leptonic CP phase
  $\delta_{CP}$ depends on the neutrino mass ordering: for normal ordering
  the global fit is consistent with CP conservation within $1\sigma$,
  whereas for inverted ordering CP-violating values of $\delta_{CP}$ around
  $270^\circ$ are favored against CP conservation at more than
  $3.6\sigma$. While the present data has in principle
  $2.5$--$3\sigma$ sensitivity to the neutrino mass ordering, there
  are different tendencies in the global data that reduce the
  discrimination power: T2K and NOvA appearance data individually
  favor normal ordering, but they are more consistent with each other
  for inverted ordering. Conversely, the joint determination of
  $|\Delta m^2_{3\ell}|$ from global disappearance data prefers normal
  ordering. Altogether, the global fit including long-baseline,
  reactor and IceCube atmospheric data results into an almost equally
  good fit for both orderings. Only when the $\chi^2$ table for
  atmospheric neutrino data from Super-Kamiokande is added to our
  $\chi^2$, the global fit prefers normal ordering with $\Delta\chi^2
  = 6.1$. We provide also updated ranges and correlations for the
  effective parameters sensitive to the absolute neutrino mass from
  $\beta$-decay, neutrinoless double-beta decay, and cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05380v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Esteban, M. C. Gonzalez-Garcia, Michele Maltoni, Ivan Martinez-Soler, Jo\~ao Paulo Pinheiro, Thomas Schwetz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Gluino LSP at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyse relevant signals expected at the LHC, assuming that the gluino is the lightest supersymmetric particle (LSP) in the framework of the $\mu\nu$SSM. In this $R$-parity violating model, the presence of couplings involving right-handed neutrinos solves simultaneously the $\mu$ problem and the accommodations of neutrino masses and mixing angles. We study gluino pair production in quark-antiquark and gluon-gluon collisions. The main decay channels for the gluino LSP are the three-body decays to two quarks and a lepton or a neutrino. In both cases, the leading channels occur for the third family of quarks. We compare the predictions of this scenario with LHC searches for prompt and long-lived particles.To analyse the parameter space we sample the $\mu\nu$SSM for a gluino LSP, paying special attention to reproduce the current experimental data on neutrino and Higgs physics, as well as flavour observables. Our results imply a lower limit on the mass of the gluino LSP of about 2600 GeV, and an upper limit for the decay length of about 6 cm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05421v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Essodjolo Kpatcha, Paulina Knees, I\~naki Lara, Daniel E. L\'opez-Fogliani, Carlos Mu\~noz, Natsumi Nagata, Hidetoshi Otono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly Excited Electron Cyclotron for QCD Axion and Dark-Photon Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05549v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose using highly excited cyclotron states of a trapped electron to detect meV axion and dark photon dark matter, marking a significant improvement over our previous proposal and demonstration [Phys. Rev. Lett. 129, 261801]. When the axion mass matches the cyclotron frequency $\omega_c$, the cyclotron state is resonantly excited, with a transition probability proportional to its initial quantum number, $n_c$. The sensitivity is enhanced by taking $n_c \sim 10^6 \left( \frac{0.1~\text{meV}}{\omega_c} \right)^2$. By optimizing key experimental parameters, we minimize the required averaging time for cyclotron detection to $t_{\text{ave}} \sim 10^{-6} $ seconds, permitting detection of such a highly excited state before its decay. An open-endcap trap design enables the external photon signal to be directed into the trap, rendering our background-free detector compatible with large focusing cavities, such as the BREAD proposal, while capitalizing on their strong magnetic fields. Furthermore, the axion conversion rate can be coherently enhanced by incorporating layers of dielectrics with alternating refractive indices within the cavity. Collectively, these optimizations enable us to probe the QCD axion parameter space from 0.1 meV to 2.3 meV (25-560 GHz), covering a substantial portion of the predicted post-inflationary QCD axion mass range. This sensitivity corresponds to probing the kinetic mixing parameter of the dark photon down to $\epsilon \approx 2 \times 10^{-16}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05549v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing Fan, Gerald Gabrielse, Peter W. Graham, Harikrishnan Ramani, Samuel S. Y. Wong, Yawen Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $X(4500)$ state considered as the mixture of hadronic molecule and diquark-antidiquark within effective field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05749v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the present work, we construct the Lagrangians including three-meson, meson-diquark-antidiquark vertices, such that the diquark-antidiquark component as well as the molecular component are introduced within the effective field theory. With the obtained effective potentials projecting to spin 0, 1 and 2, we solve the Bethe-Salpeter equation with the on-shell approximation, and find that $X(4500)$ can be explained as the mixture of components $D_{s}^{*+}D_{s}^{*-}$, ${A}_{cq}\bar{A}_{cq}$ and ${A}_{cs}\bar{A}_{cs}$ with $I^G(J^{PC})=0^+(0^{++})$. In addition, another two resonances with quantum numbers $I^G(J^{PC})=0^+(1^{++})$ and $I^G(J^{PC})=0^+(2^{++})$ are predicted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05749v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>De-Shun Zhang, Wei He, Chu-Wen Xiao, Zhi-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four top final states with NLO accuracy in perturbative QCD: 3 lepton channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05960v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We examine the effect of higher-order QCD corrections on the four top-quark production cross section in the $3$ lepton decay channel. Top-quark and $W$ gauge-boson decays are included at next-to-leading order in perturbative QCD. The narrow-width approximation, that preserves spin correlations, is used to perform the calculation for this complex $2 \to 12 \,(13)$ process. We present differential cross-section distributions of top-quark decay products for the LHC Run III energy of $\sqrt{s}=13.6$ TeV, using realistic selection cuts. Our results show that QCD corrections and jet radiation in top-quark and $W$ decays can lead to significant changes in shapes of basic kinematic distributions and, therefore, need to be included for the accurate description of $pp \to t\bar{t}t\bar{t}+X$ process in the $3\ell$ decay channel. The NLO QCD results obtained in this work are important in the context of the recent observation of the $pp\to t\bar{t}t\bar{t}+X$ process by the ATLAS and CMS collaborations and are of great significance for the High-Luminosity phase of the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05960v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Dimitrakopoulos, Malgorzata Worek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Experimental Application of a Radon Diffusion Chamber for Determining Diffusion Coefficients in Membrane Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06054v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, the issue of radon emanation and diffusion has become a critical concern for rare decay experiments, such as JUNO and PandaX-4T. This paper introduces a detector design featuring a symmetric radon detector cavity for the quantitative assessment of membrane materials' radon blocking capabilities. The performance of this design is evaluated through the application of Fick's Law and the diffusion equation considering material solubility. Our detector has completed measurements of radon diffusion coefficients for four types of membrane materials currently used in experiments, which also confirms the rationality of this detector design. The findings are instrumental in guiding the selection and evaluation of optimal materials for radon shielding to reduce radon background, contributing to boost sensitivities of rare event research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06054v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang-Yu Wu, Lin Si, Yuan Wu, Zhi-Xing Gao, Yue-Kun Heng, Yuan Li, Jiang-Lai Liu, Xiao-Lan Luo, Fei Ma, Yue Meng, Xiao-Hui Qian, Zhi-Cheng Qian, Hao Wang, You-Hui Yun, Gao-Feng Zhang, Jie Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The QED nonfactorizable correction to the semileptonic charmed three-body $B$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06087v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, the nonfactorizable photonic corrections to the effective four-fermion vertex for the $\overline{B}$ ${\to}$ $D^{({\ast})}$ $+$ ${\ell}^{-}$ $+$ $\bar{\nu}_{\ell}$ decays are considered at the quark level within SM, where ${\ell}$ $=$ $e$, ${\mu}$ and ${\tau}$. It is found that the QED corrections are closely related with the mass of the charged lepton. The QED contributions will enhance branching ratios, which results in the slight reduction of ratios $R(D^{(\ast)})$ and the relationship $R(D^{(\ast)})_{e}$ $&lt;$ $R(D^{(\ast)})_{\mu}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06087v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueling Yang, Liting Wang, Jiazhi Li, Qin Chang, Junfeng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits on planetary-mass primordial black holes from the OGLE high-cadence survey of the Magellanic Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06251v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Observations of the Galactic bulge revealed an excess of short-timescale gravitational microlensing events that are generally attributed to a large population of free-floating or wide-orbit exoplanets. However, in recent years, some authors suggested that planetary-mass primordial black holes (PBHs) comprising a substantial fraction (1-10%) of the dark matter in the Milky Way may be responsible for these events. If that was the case, a large number of short-timescale microlensing events should also be seen toward the Magellanic Clouds. Here we report the results of a high-cadence survey of the Magellanic Clouds carried out from October 2022 through May 2024 as part of the Optical Gravitational Lensing Experiment (OGLE). We observed almost 35 million source stars located in the central regions of the Large and Small Magellanic Clouds and found only one long-timescale microlensing event candidate. No short-timescale events were detected despite high sensitivity to such events. That allows us to infer the strongest available limits on the frequency of planetary-mass PBHs in dark matter. We find that PBHs and other compact objects with masses from $1.4 \times 10^{-8}\,M_{\odot}$ (half of the Moon mass) to $0.013\,M_{\odot}$ (planet/brown dwarf boundary) may comprise at most 1% of dark matter. That rules out the PBH origin hypothesis for the short-timescale events detected toward the Galactic bulge and indicates they are caused by the population of free-floating or wide-orbit planets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06251v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Przemek Mroz, Andrzej Udalski, Michal K. Szymanski, Igor Soszynski, Pawel Pietrukowicz, Szymon Kozlowski, Radoslaw Poleski, Jan Skowron, Krzysztof Ulaczyk, Mariusz Gromadzki, Krzysztof Rybicki, Patryk Iwanek, Marcin Wrona, Mateusz J. Mroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cherenkov Photon Background for Low-Noise Silicon Detectors in Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06261v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Future space observatories dedicated to direct imaging and spectroscopy of extra-solar planets will require ultra-low-noise detectors that are sensitive over a broad range of wavelengths. Silicon charge-coupled devices (CCDs), such as EMCCDs, Skipper CCDs, and Multi-Amplifier Sensing CCDs, have demonstrated the ability to detect and measure single photons from ultra-violet to near-infrared wavelengths, making them candidate technologies for this application. In this context, we study a relatively unexplored source of low-energy background coming from Cherenkov radiation produced by energetic charged particles traversing a silicon detector. In the intense radiation environment of space, energetic cosmic rays produce high-energy tracks and more extended halos of low-energy Cherenkov photons, which are detectable with ultra-low-noise detectors. We present a model of this effect that is calibrated to laboratory data, and we use this model to characterize the residual background rate for ultra-low noise silicon detectors in space. We find that the rate of cosmic-ray-induced Cherenkov photon production is comparable to other detector and astrophysical backgrounds that have previously been considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06261v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1117/12.3019241</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. SPIE 13103, X-Ray, Optical, and Infrared Detectors for Astronomy XI, 131031P (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Manuel E. Gaido, Javier Tiffenberg, Alex Drlica-Wagner, Guillermo Fernandez-Moroni, Bernard J. Rauscher, Fernando Chierche, Dar\'io Rodrigues, Lucas Giardino, Juan Estrada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Describing Hadronization via Histories and Observables for Monte-Carlo Event Reweighting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a novel method for extracting a fragmentation model directly from experimental data without requiring an explicit parametric form, called Histories and Observables for Monte-Carlo Event Reweighting (\homer), consisting of three steps: the training of a classifier between simulation and data, the inference of single fragmentation weights, and the calculation of the weight for the full hadronization chain. We illustrate the use of \homer on a simplified hadronization problem, a $q\bar{q}$ string fragmenting into pions, and extract a modified Lund string fragmentation function $f(z)$. We then demonstrate the use of \homer on three types of experimental data: (i) binned distributions of high level observables, (ii) unbinned event-by-event distributions of these observables, and (iii) full particle cloud information. After demonstrating that $f(z)$ can be extracted from data (the inverse of hadronization), we also show that, at least in this limited setup, the fidelity of the extracted $f(z)$ suffers only limited loss when moving from (i) to (ii) to (iii). Public code is available at https://gitlab.com/uchep/mlhad.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06342v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Bierlich, Phil Ilten, Tony Menzo, Stephen Mrenna, Manuel Szewc, Michael K. Wilkinson, Ahmed Youssef, Jure Zupan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New-Old Approach to Composite Scalars with Chiral Fermion Constituents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06887v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a dynamical, Lorentz invariant theory of composite scalars in configuration space consisting of chiral fermions, interacting by the perturbative exchange of a massive ``gluon'' of coupling $g_0$ and mass $M_0^2$ (the coloron model). The formalism is inspired by, but goes beyond, old ideas of Yukawa and the Nambu-Jona-Lasinio (NJL) model. It yields a non-pointlike internal wave-function of the bound state, $\phi(r)$, which satisfies a Schr\"odinger-Klein-Gordon (SKG) equation with eigenvalue $\mu^2$. For super-critical coupling, $g_0 &gt;g_{0c}$, we have $\mu^2&lt; 0$ leading to spontaneous symmetry breaking. The binding of chiral fermions is semiclassical, and not loop-level as in NJL. The mass scale is determined by the interaction as in NJL. We mainly focus on the short-distance, large $M_0^2$ limit, yielding an NJL pointlike interaction, but the bound state internal wave-function, $\phi(r)$, remains spatially extended and dilutes $\phi(0)$. This leads to power-law suppression of the induced Yukawa and quartic couplings and requires radically less fine-tuning of a hierarchy than does the NJL model. We include a discussion of loop corrections of the theory. A realistic top--condensation model appears possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06887v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher T. Hill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Guide to Exotic Hadrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06923v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exotic hadrons are a new class of hadronic states whose properties do not allow them to be classified as conventional quark-antiquark mesons or three quark baryons. Finding new and understanding established exotic states is the most important topic in today's hadron spectroscopy and a promising avenue to advance our knowledge on Quantum Chromodynamics in the non-perturbative regime. While several high-quality reviews on the topic exist, they are all at an advanced level. The present article aims to address new-comers to the field with a simple introduction to exotic hadrons with an emphasis on the experimental studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06923v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nils H\"usken, Elisabetta Spadaro Norella, Ivan Polyakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning tagged boosted dark photon: A signature of fermionic portal matter at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06925v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use machine learning techniques to identify a boosted dark photon jet as a signature of a heavy vector-like fermionic portal matter (PM) connecting the visible and the dark sectors. In this work, the fermionic PM which mixes only with the standard model (SM) third generation up-type quark, dominantly decays to a top quark and dark photon pair. The dark photon then decays $promptly$ to a pair of standard model fermions via the gauge kinetic mixing. We have analyzed two different final states, namely, $(i)~ exactly ~one ~tagged~ dark ~photon ~and ~exactly ~one ~tagged~ top ~quark ~jet$, and $(ii)~ at~ least~ two~tagged ~dark$ $photons~and~at ~least ~one ~tagged ~top ~quark ~jet$ at the 13 and 14 TeV LHC center of mass energies. Both these final states receive significant contributions from the pair and single production processes of the top partner. The rich event topology of the signal processes, $i.e.$, the presence of a boosted dark photon and top quark jet pair, along with the fact that the invariant mass of the system corresponds to the mass of the top partner, help us to significantly suppress the potential SM backgrounds. We have shown that one can set a $2\sigma$ exclusion limit of $3.0$ TeV on the top partner mass with $\sin\theta_L=0.1$ and assuming $100\%$ branching ratio of the top partner in the exactly one tagged dark photon and exactly one tagged top quark jet final state at the 14 TeV LHC center of mass energy assuming 300 fb$^{-1}$ of integrated luminosity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06925v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Verma, Sanjoy Biswas, Tanumoy Mandal, Subhadip Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs-muon interactions at a multi-TeV muon collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish a simple yet general parameterization of Higgs-muon interactions within the effective field theory frameworks, including both the Higgs Effective Field Theory (HEFT) and the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT). We investigate the potential of a muon collider, operating at center-of-mass energies of 3 and 10 TeV, to probe Higgs-muon interactions. All possible processes involving the direct production of multiple electroweak bosons ($W$, $Z$, and $H$) with up to five final-state particles are considered. Our findings indicate that a muon collider can achieve greater sensitivity than the high-luminosity LHC, especially considering the independence of the Higgs decay branching fraction to muons. Notably, a 10 TeV muon collider offers exceptional sensitivity to muon-Higgs interactions, surpassing the 3 TeV option. In particular, searches based on multi-Higgs production prove highly effective for probing these couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06991v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Ma, Eugenia Celada, Tao Han, Wolfgang Kilian, Nils Kreher, Fabio Maltoni, Davide Pagani, J\"urgen Reuter, Tobias Striegl, Keping Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-scale self-assembled nanophotonic scintillators for X-ray imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07141v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scintillators are essential for converting X-ray energy into visible light in imaging technologies. Their widespread application in imaging technologies has been enabled by scalable, high-quality, and affordable manufacturing methods. Nanophotonic scintillators, which feature nanostructures at the scale of their emission wavelength, provide a promising approach to enhance emission properties like light yield, decay time, and directionality. However, scalable fabrication of such nanostructured scintillators has been a significant challenge, impeding their widespread adoption. Here, we present a scalable fabrication method for large-area nanophotonic scintillators based on the self-assembly of chalcogenide glass photonic crystals. This technique enables the production of nanophotonic scintillators over wafer-scale areas, achieving a six-fold enhancement in light yield compared to unpatterned scintillators. We demonstrate this approach using a conventional X-ray scintillator material, cerium-doped yttrium aluminum garnet (YAG:Ce). By analyzing the influence of surface nanofabrication disorder, we establish its effect on imaging performance and provide a route towards large-scale scintillation enhancements without decrease in spatial resolution. Finally, we demonstrate the practical applicability of our nanophotonic scintillators through X-ray imaging of biological and inorganic specimens. Our results indicate that this scalable fabrication technique could enable the industrial implementation of a new generation of nanophotonic-enhanced scintillators, with significant implications for advancements in medical imaging, security screening, and nondestructive testing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07141v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Martin-Monier, Simo Pajovic, Muluneh G. Abebe, Joshua Chen, Sachin Vaidya, Seokhwan Min, Seou Choi, Steven E. Kooi, Bjorn Maes, Juejun Hu, Marin Soljacic, Charles Roques-Carmes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring atmospheric neutrino oscillations at ESSnuSB</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21663v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study provides an analysis of atmospheric neutrino oscillations at the ESSnuSB far detector facility. The prospects of the two cylindrical Water Cherenkov detectors with a total fiducial mass of 540 kt are investigated over 10 years of data taking in the standard three-flavor oscillation scenario. We present the confidence intervals for the determination of mass ordering, $\theta_{23}$ octant as well as for the precisions on $\sin^2\theta_{23}$ and $|\Delta m_{31}^2|$. It is shown that mass ordering can be resolved by $3\sigma$ CL ($5\sigma$ CL) after 4 years (10 years) regardless of the true neutrino mass ordering. Correspondingly, the wrong $\theta_{23}$ octant could be excluded by $3\sigma$ CL after 4 years (8 years) in the case where the true neutrino mass ordering is normal ordering (inverted ordering). The results presented in this work are complementary to the accelerator neutrino program in the ESSnuSB project.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21663v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ESSnuSB,  :, J. Aguilar, M. Anastasopoulos, E. Baussan, A. K. Bhattacharyya, A. Bignami, M. Blennow, M. Bogomilov, B. Bolling, E. Bouquerel, F. Bramati, A. Branca, G. Brunetti, I. Bustinduy, C. J. Carlile, J. Cederkall, T. W. Choi, S. Choubey, P. Christiansen, M. Collins, E. Cristaldo Morales, P. Cupia{\l}, H. Danared, J. P. A. M. de Andr\'e, M. Dracos, I. Efthymiopoulos, T. Ekel\"of, M. Eshraqi, G. Fanourakis, A. Farricker, E. Fasoula, T. Fukuda, N. Gazis, Th. Geralis, M. Ghosh, A. Giarnetti, G. Gokbulut, C. Hagner, L. Hali\'c, M. Hooft, K. E. Iversen, N. Jachowicz, M. Jenssen, R. Johansson, E. Kasimi, A. Kayis Topaksu, B. Kildetof, K. Kordas, A. Leisos, M. Lindroos, A. Longhin, C. Maiano, S. Marangoni, C. Marrelli, D. Meloni, M. Mezzetto, N. Milas, J. Mu\~noz, K. Niewczas, M. Oglakci, T. Ohlsson, M. Olveg{\aa}rd, M. Pari, D. Patrzalek, G. Petkov, Ch. Petridou, P. Poussot, A. Psallidas, F. Pupilli, D. Saiang, D. Sampsonidis, C. Schwab, F. Sordo, A. Sosa, G. Stavropoulos, R. Tarkeshian, F. Terranova, T. Tolba, E. Trachanas, R. Tsenov, A. Tsirigotis, S. E. Tzamarias, G. Vankova-Kirilova, N. Vassilopoulos, S. Vihonen, J. Wurtz, V. Zeter, O. Zormpa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Axion Search with HAYSTAC Phase II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08998v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This Letter reports new results from the HAYSTAC experiment's search for dark matter axions in our galactic halo. It represents the widest search to date that utilizes squeezing to realize sub-quantum limited noise. The new results cover 1.71 $\mu$eV of newly scanned parameter space in the mass ranges 17.28--18.44 $\mu$eV and 18.71--19.46 $\mu$eV. No statistically significant evidence of an axion signal was observed, excluding couplings $|g_\gamma|\geq$ 2.75$\times$$|g_{\gamma}^{\text{KSVZ}}|$ and $|g_\gamma|\geq$ 2.96$\times$$|g_{\gamma}^{\text{KSVZ}}|$ at the 90$\%$ confidence level over the respective region. By combining this data with previously published results using HAYSTAC's squeezed state receiver, a total of 2.27 $\mu$eV of parameter space has now been scanned between 16.96--19.46 $\mu$eV, excluding $|g_\gamma|\geq$ 2.86$\times$$|g_{\gamma}^{\text{KSVZ}}|$ at the 90$\%$ confidence level. These results demonstrate the squeezed state receiver's ability to probe axion models over a significant mass range while achieving a scan rate enhancement relative to a quantum-limited experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08998v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> HAYSTAC Collaboration, Xiran Bai, M. J. Jewell, J. Echevers, K. van Bibber, A. Droster, Maryam H. Esmat, Sumita Ghosh, Eleanor Graham, H. Jackson, Claire Laffan, S. K. Lamoreaux, A. F. Leder, K. W. Lehnert, S. M. Lewis, R. H. Maruyama, R. D. Nath, N. M. Rapidis, E. P. Ruddy, M. Silva-Feaver, M. Simanovskaia, Sukhman Singh, D. H. Speller, Sabrina Zacarias, Yuqi Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurements of decay branching fractions of the Higgs boson to hadronic final states at the CEPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04465v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Circular Electron Positron Collider (CEPC) is a large-scale particle accelerator designed to collide electrons and positrons at high energies. One of the primary goals of the CEPC is to achieve high-precision measurements of the properties of the Higgs boson, facilitated by the large number of Higgs bosons that can be produced with significantly low contamination. The measurements of Higgs boson branching fractions into $b\overline{b} /c\overline{c} /gg$ and $WW^{*} /ZZ^{*} $, where the $W$ or $Z$ bosons decay hadronically, are presented in the context of the CEPC experiment, assuming a scenario with 5600 fb$^{-1}$ of collision data at a center-of-mass energy of 240 GeV. In this study the Higgs bosons are produced in association with a $Z$ boson, with the $Z$ boson decaying into a pair of muons $(\mu^{+}\mu^{-})$, which have high efficiency and high resolution. In order to separate all decay channels simultaneously with high accuracy, the Particle Flow Network (PFN), a graph-based machine learning model, is considered. The precise classification provided by the PFN is employed in measuring the branching fractions using the migration matrix method, which accurately corrects for detector effects in each decay channel. The statistical uncertainty of the measured branching ratio is estimated to be 0.58% in $H\to b\overline{b}$ final state, and approximately 2%-10% in $H\to c\overline{c} /gg/WW^{*} /ZZ^{*} $ final states. In addition, the main sources of systematic uncertainties to the measurement of the branching fractions are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04465v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaotian Ma, Zuofei Wu, Jinfei Wu, Yanping Huang, Gang Li, Manqi Ruan, F\'abio L. Alves, Shan Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of quantum entanglement in top quark pairs at the ATLAS experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ATLAS Collaboration has recently reported the first observation of quantum entanglement in top quark pair production at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC). A brief review of the experimental status of top quark pair spin correlations is given, before highlighting the expected differences between classical and quantum correlations. A criterion for the detection of spin entanglement in top quark pairs has been proposed; the experimental strategy to implement it and observe the effect is discussed, and the positive results of the ATLAS measurement are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04590v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Ravina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical determination of the energy loss of heavy quarks in nuclear collisions at RHIC and LHC energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.02644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.02644v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Heavy quarks produced in the heavy ion collisions loose energy while propagting in the hot partonic matter which finally fragment to heavy ($D$ or $B$) mesons. The energy loss suffered by the heavy quarks is imprinted in the nuclear modification factor as a function of transverse momenta ($p_T$) of these heavy mesons. An alternate measure of in-medium energy loss comes through the effective shift in transverse momentum spectra of hadrons recorded in nucleus-nucleus collisions when it is compared to the same in proton-proton collisions. We start by parametrizing invariant momentum yields of heavy mesons in p+p collisions. The fit function from p+p collisions and measured nuclear modification factor in heavy ion collisions are then utilised to obtain the shift in the transeverse mass $\Delta m_T$ of heavy mesons produced at the RHIC and LHC experiments.The energy loss $\Delta m_T$ so obtained is found to scale with the transverse mass ($m_T$) of heavy mesons through a power law at different energies and centralities of collisions. We have also calculated using theoretical formalism, the total energy loss suffered by a charm quark in quark-gluon plasma produced in Pb~+~Pb collisions at the LHC energies. The evolution of the plasma is described by (2+1) dimensional longitudinal boost-invariant ideal hydrodynamics. It is found that the total energy loss of charm quarks scales with the transverse mass of charm quarks through a similar power law which supports our empirical analysis of energy loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.02644v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjp/s13360-024-05281-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. Plus (2024) 139:524</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Somnath De, Sudipan De, Prashant Shukla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic and hadronic decay of fully heavy tetraquark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16150v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we compute the electromagnetic and hadronic decay widths of the S-wave fully heavy tetraquark $T_{4Q}$ ($Q=c$ or $b$) at lowest order in $\alpha_s$ and $v$, in the framework of nonrelativistic QCD. The short-distance coefficients are determined through the standard procedure of matching. The nonperturbative long-distance matrix elements are related to the phenomenological four-body Schr\"odinger wave functions at the origin, whose values are taken from literature. The branching fractions are predicted to be around $10^{-4}$ and $10^{-7}-10^{-6}$ for the $T_{4c}$ hadronic decay and electromagnetic decay, respectively. Combing our results with the $T_{4c}$ production cross sections at the LHC, we also predict the event numbers for various decay channels. With integrated luminosity $\mathcal{L}=100 \,{\rm fb}^{-1}$, it is expected that the event numbers can reach $10^3$ for $T_{4c}\to \gamma\gamma$, and $10^6$ for $T_{4c}\to {\rm LH}$, at the LHC. The detecting prospect is promising. In addition, the decay widths of $T_{4b}$ are estimated based on simple dimensional analysis as well as velocity scaling rule.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16150v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Long Sang (SWU), Tao Wang (SWU), Yu-Dong Zhang (CCNU), Feng Feng (CUMT)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarity effects in elastic scattering at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11385v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the high-energy behavior of the elastic scattering amplitude using two distinct unitarization schemes: the eikonal and the $U$-matrix. Our analysis begins with a formalism involving solely Pomerons, incorporating pion-loop insertions in the Pomeron trajectory representing the nearest singularity generated by $t$-channel unitarity. Subsequently, we explore a scenario that includes the presence of an Odderon. In our analyses, we explore the tension between the TOTEM and the ATLAS measurements for $\sigma_{tot}$ and $d\sigma/dt$ at 7, 8, and 13 TeV, and the subsequent implications for the properties of both the Pomeron and Odderon. Our results show that the Odderon phase factor $\xi_{\Bbb O}= -1$ is favored in both unitarization schemes, supporting an Odderon with a phase opposite to that of other crossing-odd components of the scattering amplitude. More interestingly, this specific phase factor stands as the sole one that aligns with results consistent with a non-zero Odderon coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11385v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Maneyro, E. G. S. Luna, M. Pel\'aez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear suppression of coherent $J/\psi$ photoproduction in heavy-ion UPCs and leading twist nuclear shadowing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17476v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We determine the nuclear suppression factor $S_{Pb}(x)$, where $x=M_{J/\psi}^2/W_{\gamma p}^2$ with $M_{J/\psi}$ the $J/\psi$ mass and $W_{\gamma p}$ the photon-nucleon energy, for the cross section of coherent $J/\psi$ photoproduction in heavy-ion ultraperipheral collisions (UPCs) at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider (RHIC) by performing the $\chi^2$ fit to all available data on the cross section $d\sigma^{AA \to J/\psi AA}/dy$ as a function of the $J/\psi$ rapidity $y$ and the photoproduction cross section $\sigma^{\gamma A \to J/\psi A}(W_{\gamma p})$ as a function of $W_{\gamma p}$. We find that while the $d\sigma^{AA \to J/\psi AA}/dy$ data alone constrain $S_{Pb}(x)$ for $x \geq 10^{-3}$, the combined $d\sigma^{AA \to J/\psi AA}/dy$ and $\sigma^{\gamma A \to J/\psi A}(W_{\gamma p})$ data allow us to determine $S_{Pb}(x)$ in the wide interval $10^{-5} &lt; x &lt; 0.05$. In particular, the data favor $S_{Pb}(x)$, which decreases with a decrease of $x$ in the $10^{-4} &lt; x &lt; 0.01$ interval, and can be both decreasing or constant for $x&lt; 10^{-4}$. Identifying $S_{Pb}(x)$ with the ratio of the gluon distributions in Pb and the proton $R_g(x,Q_0^2)=g_A(x,Q_0^2)/[A g_p(x,Q_0^2)]$, we demonstrate that the leading twist approximation (LTA) for nuclear shadowing provides a good description of all the data on $d\sigma^{AA \to J/\psi AA}/dy$ and $\sigma^{\gamma A \to J/\psi A}(W_{\gamma p})$ as well as on the experimental values for $S_{Pb}(x)$ derived from $\sigma^{\gamma A \to J/\psi A}(W_{\gamma p})$. We also show that modern nuclear PDFs reasonably reproduce $S_{Pb}(x)$ as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17476v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Guzey (Jyvaskyla U.,Helsinki Inst. of Phys.), M. Strikman (Penn State U.)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudoscalar heavy quarkonium production in heavy ion ultraperipheral collision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19735v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The inclusive production of pseudoscalar heavy quarkoniua ($\eta_c,~\eta_b$ and $B_c$) via photon-photon fusion in heavy ion ultraperipheral collision (UPC) are calculated to QCD next-to-leading order in the framework of non-relativistic QCD (NRQCD). The total cross section of $\eta_c$ produced in Pb-Pb UPC is 194 $\mathrm{nb}$ and 1275 $\mathrm{nb}$ at nucleon-nucleon c.m. energies $\sqrt{S_{\mathrm{NN}}}=$ 5.52 TeV and 39.4 TeV, respectively. The cross sections for $\eta_b$ and $B_c$ mesons are more than two to three orders of magnitude smaller. We make a detailed phenomenological analysis on the $\eta_c$ production; the uncertainties caused by the renormalization scale and the charm quark mass, the cross sections in other ultraperipheral nucleon-nucleon colliding systems, and the transverse momentum distribution are discussed. At the coming HL-LHC and future FCC, the heavy ion UPC opens another door of the study on the production of heavy quarkonium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19735v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.056039</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 110 (2024) 5, 056039</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jun Jiang, Shi-Yuan Li, Xiao Liang, Yan-Rui Liu, Cong-Feng Qiao, Zong-Guo Si, Hao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Froggatt-Nielsen ALP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02998v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Froggatt-Nielsen (FN) mechanism, a prominent framework for explaining the observed flavor hierarchies, generically predicts the existence of an axion-like particle (ALP). This work examines a class of FN models based on $\mathbb{Z}_N$ discrete symmetries. We chart the allowed parameter space from a set of theoretical considerations and construct explicit renormalizable completions with minimal field content necessary to generate consistent textures. We then conduct comprehensive phenomenological analyses of two particularly elegant $\mathbb{Z}_4$ and $\mathbb{Z}_8$ models, highlighting the interplay between the effects of the ALP and the associated UV fields. We find that the FN scale can be as low as a few TeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02998v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Admir Greljo, Aleks Smolkovi\v{c}, Alessandro Valenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicity distributions in the eikonal and the $U$-matrix unitarization schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00194v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The multiplicity distribution of charged particles produced in the central rapidity ($|\eta|&lt;2.5$) region is calculated for the eikonal and the $U$-matrix unitarization schemes using the AGK cutting rules and compared with the ATLAS 13 TeV data. The data favours the eikonal approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00194v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. G. S. Luna, M. G. Ryskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon Gravitational Form Factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15547v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A symmetry-preserving analysis of strong interaction quantum field equations is used to complete a unified treatment of pion, kaon, nucleon electromagnetic and gravitational form factors. Findings include a demonstration that the pion near-core pressure is roughly twice that in the proton, so both are significantly greater than that of a neutron star; parton species separations of the nucleon's three gravitational form factors, in which, inter alia, the glue-to-quark ratio for each form factor is seen to take the same constant value, independent of momentum transfer; and a determination of proton radii orderings, with the mechanical (normal force) radius being less than the mass-energy radius, which is less than the proton charge radius. This body of predictions should prove useful in an era of anticipated experiments that will enable them to be tested.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15547v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. -Q. Yao, Y. -Z. Xu, D. Binosi, Z. -F. Cui, M. Ding, K. Raya, C. D. Roberts, J. Rodr\'iguez-Quintero, S. M. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
