<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 03:43:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Search for $H\rightarrow c\bar{c}$ and measurement of $H\rightarrow b\bar{b}$ in vector-boson fusion production with the ATLAS Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A search for Standard Model (SM) Higgs bosons produced via vector-boson fusion at the Large Hadron Collider and decaying into a charm quark-antiquark pair ($H\rightarrow c\bar{c}$) is presented. The datasets used correspond to integrated luminosities of 37.5 fb$^{-1}$ and 51.5 fb$^{-1}$ and were collected by the ATLAS detector from proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$=13 and 13.6 TeV, respectively. The observed (expected) upper limit on the $H\rightarrow c\bar{c}$ production cross-section times branching ratio is 41 (28) times the SM prediction at 95% confidence level. Combining this search with the previous $H\rightarrow c\bar{c}$ search in associated production with a $W$ or $Z$ boson yields an observed (expected) limit on the Higgs-charm Yukawa coupling modifier of $|\kappa_{c}| $ &lt; 4.7 (3.9). Higgs bosons decaying into a bottom quark-antiquark pair ($H\rightarrow b\bar{b}$) are measured simultaneously using the 51.5 fb$^{-1}$ dataset at $\sqrt{s}$=13.6 TeV, with an observed signal strength of 0.97$^{+0.57}_{-0.50}$ relative to the SM expectation. When combined with previous $H\rightarrow b\bar{b}$ results at 13 TeV, the observed (expected) significance reaches 3.2 (3.6) standard deviations, providing evidence for $H\rightarrow b\bar{b}$ events from vector-boson fusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21911v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An interpretable unsupervised representation learning for high precision measurement in particle physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unsupervised learning has been widely applied to various tasks in particle physics. However, existing models lack precise control over their learned representations, limiting physical interpretability and hindering their use for accurate measurements. We propose the Histogram AutoEncoder (HistoAE), an unsupervised representation learning network featuring a custom histogram-based loss that enforces a physically structured latent space. Applied to silicon microstrip detectors, HistoAE learns an interpretable two-dimensional latent space corresponding to the particle's charge and impact position. After simple post-processing, it achieves a charge resolution of $0.25\,e$ and a position resolution of $3\,\mu\mathrm{m}$ on beam-test data, comparable to the conventional approach. These results demonstrate that unsupervised deep learning models can enable physically meaningful and quantitatively precise measurements. Moreover, the generative capacity of HistoAE enables straightforward extensions to fast detector simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22246v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing-Jian Lv, De-Xing Miao, Zi-Jun Xu, Jian-Chun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Huizhou Hadron Spectrometer -- a Proposed High-rate Experimental Setup at the High Intensity Heavy-ion Accelerator Facility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The High-Intensity Heavy-Ion Accelerator Facility (HIAF), currently under construction in Huizhou, Guangdong Province, China, is projected to be completed by 2025. This facility will be capable of producing proton and heavy-ion beams with energies reaching several GeV, thereby offering a versatile platform for advanced fundamental physics research. Key scientific objectives include exploring physics beyond the Standard Model through the search for novel particles and interactions, testing fundamental symmetries, investigating exotic hadronic states such as di-baryons, pentaquark states and multi-strange hypernuclei, conducting precise measurements of hadron and hypernucleus properties, and probing the phase boundary and critical point of nuclear matter. To facilitate these investigations, we propose the development of a dedicated experimental apparatus at HIAF - the Huizhou Hadron Spectrometer (HHaS). This paper presents the conceptual design of HHaS, comprising a solenoid magnet, a five-dimensional silicon pixel tracker, a Low-Gain Avalanche Detector (LGAD) for time-of-flight measurements, and a Cherenkov-scintillation dual-readout electromagnetic calorimeter. The design anticipates an unprecedented event rate of 1-100 MHz, extensive particle acceptance, a track momentum resolution at 1% level, an electromagnetic energy resolution of ~3% @ 1 GeV and multi-particle identification capabilities. Such capabilities position HHaS as a powerful instrument for advancing experimental studies in particle and nuclear physics. The successful realization of HHaS is expected to significantly bolster the development of medium- and high-energy physics research within China.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22864v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xurong Chen, Yunyun Fan, Shuangshi Fang, Zhao-Qing Feng, Feng-Kun Guo, Weijia Han, Jun He, Qinghua He, Xionghong He, Hongxia Huang, Xiaolin Kang, Hongli Ma, Weihu Ma, Yong-Liang Ma, Norihito Muramatsu, Zaiba Mushtaq, Xiaoyang Niu, Jialun Ping, Hao Qiu, Jun Shi, Ye Tian, Qian Wang, Rong Wang, Shuai-Chun Wang, Xiao-Yun Wang, Jia-Jun Wu, Chuwen Xiao, Ju-Jun Xie, Haibo Yang, Xieyang Yu, Honglin Zhang, Shenghui Zhang, Chengxin Zhao, Kuang-Ta Chao, Qiang Zhao, Bing-Song Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the top-quark mass using decays with a $J/\psi$ meson at $\sqrt{s}=$13 TeV with the ATLAS detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The top-quark mass is measured using top-quark decays producing an isolated lepton and $J/\psi$ meson reconstructed in its $\mu^+\mu^-$ decay mode. The data sample was recorded with the ATLAS detector in proton-proton collisions at a centre-of-mass energy of $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV during Run 2 of the Large Hadron Collider, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 140 fb$^{-1}$. The measurement is based on the invariant mass $m(\ell \mu^+\mu^-)$ of the system made of the isolated lepton $\ell$ from the $W$ boson decay and the non-isolated $\mu^+\mu^-$ pair from a $J/\psi$ decay of a $b$-hadron, exploiting its sensitivity to the top-quark mass. An unbinned maximum-likelihood fit to the $m(\ell \mu^+\mu^-)$ distribution is performed to extract the top-quark mass. The top-quark mass is measured to be $m_{top} = 172.17 \pm 0.80 (stat) \pm 0.81 (syst) \pm 1.07 (recoil)$ GeV, with a total uncertainty of 1.56 GeV. The third uncertainty arises from changing the dipole parton shower gluon-recoil scheme used in top-quark decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23091v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision Measurements of Higgs Hadronic Decay Modes at the FCC-ee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23149v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The expected precision at the FCC-ee on the product $\sigma\times\mathcal{B}(H\rightarrow b\bar{b}, c\bar{c},s\bar{s},gg)$ of Higgs boson production cross sections times branching ratios of hadronic decays is presented. This study provides the first comprehensive determination of all major hadronic Higgs decay modes in a combined fit at future $e^+ e^-$ colliders, using both Higgs-strahlung ($ZH$) and Vector boson fusion ($\nu\bar{\nu} H$) production processes, with a full treatment of interference effects in the $\nu\bar{\nu} jj$ final state. It assumes four identical IDEA detectors collecting $e^+e^-$ collisions at $\sqrt{s}=240$ and $365\,$GeV. The combination of all channels across both energies, with full covariance between production and decay modes, yields a production cross-section times branching-ratio precision at the percent to per-mil level for the dominant hadronic final states ($b\bar{b}, c\bar{c},gg$). These results provide a comprehensive input to the determination of Higgs coupling projections at the FCC-ee, and they establish for the first time sensitivity to the rare decay $H\rightarrow s\bar{s}$, demonstrating that FCC-ee has the potential to provide evidence of the strange-quark Yukawa coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23149v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Del Vecchio, Jan Eysermans, Loukas Gouskos, George Iakovidis, Alexis Maloizel, Giovanni Marchiori, Michele Selvaggi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MUSIC: A Multi-Purpose Detector Concept for Physics at the 10 TeV Muon Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23273v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a proof of concept for MUSIC, a multi-purpose detector conceived for high-precision and ultra-high-energy physics studies in the challenging environment of $\sqrt{s}=10$ TeV muon-antimuon collisions. The detector features a central tracking system, electromagnetic and hadronic calorimeters, and dedicated muon detectors. This paper outlines the main design elements of each subdetector, with an emphasis on the effects of machine-induced backgrounds and the reconstruction strategies employed for key physics objects. Performance results for electrons, photons, muons, and jets are reported, and studies of jet flavour identification are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23273v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Andreetto (INFN Sezione di Padova, Padua, Italy), Nazar Bartosik (INFN Sezione di Torino, Turin, Italy, Universit\`a del Piemonte Orientale, Vercelli, Italy), Andrea Bersani (INFN Sezione di Genova, Genoa, Italy), Daniele Calzolari (Universit\`a di Padova, Padua, Italy, European Organization for Nuclear Research, Geneva, Switzerland), Massimo Casarsa (INFN Sezione di Trieste, Trieste, Italy), Vittoria Ludovica Ciccarella (INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, Frascati, Italy, Sapienza Universit\`a di Roma, Rome, Italy), Elisa Di Meco (INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, Frascati, Italy), Ruben Gargiulo (INFN Sezione di Roma 1, Rome, Italy), Alessio Gianelle (INFN Sezione di Padova, Padua, Italy), Carlo Giraldin (INFN Sezione di Trieste, Trieste, Italy, Universit\`a di Trieste, Trieste, Italy), Karol Krizka (University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom), Anton Lechner (European Organization for Nuclear Research, Geneva, Switzerland), Luigi Longo (INFN Sezione di Bari, Bari, Italy), Donatella Lucchesi (INFN Sezione di Padova, Padua, Italy, Universit\`a di Padova, Padua, Italy), Leonardo Palombini (INFN Sezione di Padova, Padua, Italy, Universit\`a di Padova, Padua, Italy), Nadia Pastrone (INFN Sezione di Torino, Turin, Italy), Ivano Sarra (INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, Frascati, Italy), Lorenzo Sestini (INFN Sezione di Firenze, Florence, Italy), Rosamaria Venditti (INFN Sezione di Bari, Bari, Italy, Universit\`a di Bari, Bari, Italy), Davide Zuliani (INFN Sezione di Padova, Padua, Italy, Universit\`a di Padova, Padua, Italy)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chasing the muon EDM to constrain the SMEFT and UV models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21828v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Following a proposal for an experiment with sensitivity to an electric dipole moment (EDM) of the muon $d_\mu$ of order $6\times10^{-23}\ e$ cm, three to four orders of magnitude below the current bound, but still seven orders of magnitude above the current bound on the EDM of the electron $d_e$, we explore the discovery potential of such an experiment. Within the dimension-six CP violating operators of the Standard Model effective field theory (SMEFT), we identify two dipole operators where $d_\mu$ has the strongest sensitivity, and four classes of four-fermion operators where it has the best sensitivity for regions of parameter space that are far from minimal flavor violation. We further consider three UV completions: vector-like leptons (VLLs), heavy vector boson with off-diagonal leptonic couplings, and two Higgs doublet model. For each, we identify the region in parameter space that will be uniquely explored by the proposed $d_\mu$ experiment. In case of VLLs, we also find measurements of $\Gamma (h \rightarrow \mu \mu)$ offer competitive sensitivity, highlighting the complementary role of collider observables. Generically, the potential reach is to ${\cal O}(10\ {\rm TeV})$ scale of new physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21828v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuldeep Deka, Marta Losada, Yosef Nir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Di-Higgs to 4b with Bayesian inference: improving simulation estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21832v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Measuring di-Higgs production in the four-bottom channel is challenged by overwhelming QCD backgrounds and imperfect simulations. We develop a Bayesian mixture model that simultaneously infers signal and background fractions and their individual shapes directly in the signal region. The likelihood is a nuanced combination of a one-dimensional kinematic discriminator and per-jet flavour scores; with their correlations incorporated via kinematic bins. Monte Carlo informs weak Dirichlet priors, while the posterior adjusts to the interplay of the model, priors and observed data. Using pseudo-data simulated with standard tools and with controlled mismatches, we show that the method corrects biased priors, delivers calibrated 68-95% credible intervals for the signal count, and improves dataset-level ROC/AUC relative to simple cut-and-count baselines. This study highlights how Bayesian inference can harvest information present in the signal region and self-calibrate model parameters, providing a robust route to increased sensitivity in di-Higgs searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21832v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ezequiel Alvarez, Leandro Da Rold, Manuel Szewc, Alejandro Szynkman, Santiago Tanco, Tatiana Tarutina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Physics Searches at the LHC through Event-based Anomaly Detection and Development of ADFilter Web-tool</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents advancements in model-agnostic searches for new physics at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) through the application of event-based anomaly detection techniques utilizing unsupervised machine learning. We discuss the advantages of the anomaly detection approach, as demonstrated in a recent ATLAS analysis, and introduce ADFilter, a web-based tool designed to process collision events using autoencoders based on deep unsupervised neural networks. ADFilter calculates loss distributions for input events, aiding in determining the degree to which events can be considered anomalous. Real-life examples are provided to demonstrate how the tool can be used to reinterpret existing LHC results, with the goal of significantly improving exclusion limits. Furthermore, we present a comparative study between anomaly detection and supervised machine learning techniques, using the search for heavy resonances decaying into two or more Higgs bosons as a representative case to demonstrate the application and effectiveness of these methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21869v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wasikul Islam, Sergei Chekanov, Nicholas Luongo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological production of charmonia with event-shape engineering in $pp$ collisions at $\sqrt{s} = 13$ TeV using PYTHIA8</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22190v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The production of heavy quarks (charm and beauty) in high-energy hadronic and nuclear collisions provides an excellent testing ground for the theory of strong interaction and validates models based on quantum chromodynamics. In this work, prompt and nonprompt production of $\rm{J/}\psi$ in $pp$ collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV are studied as a function of transverse spherocity using PYTHIA8. $\rm{J/}\psi$ is reconstructed via its electromagnetic decay to dielectrons and dimuons, in mid- and forward-rapidity, respectively. Transverse spherocity, an event shape observable, is used to distinguish hard QCD events from the softer, isotropic ones. In PYTHIA8, the production of $\rm{J/}\psi$ can be influenced by the average number of multiple parton interactions ($\langle N_{\rm mpi} \rangle$), owing to the underlying events (UE), which have a dominant contribution to particle production at lower transverse momentum. Since transverse spherocity is correlated to $\langle N_{\rm mpi} \rangle$, this can serve as an experimentally available tool for event selection to study the underlying QCD processes influencing the prompt and nonprompt $\rm{J/}\psi$ production. This study reveals the correlation between heavy-flavor production dynamics and topological event selection in $pp$ collisions using PYTHIA8, whose relevance awaits experimental validation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22190v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aswathy Menon Kavumpadikkal Radhakrishnan, Suraj Prasad, Neelkamal Mallick, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete one-loop QED corrections to $D_s^+$ leptonic decays and impact on the CKM unitarity test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, a violation of the CKM unitarity condition has been reported in the latest charm-meson data, and the latest lattice results once the universal electroweak correction is taken into account. In this article, we analytically derive for the first time the complete one-loop electroweak (EW) and QED corrections to the $D_{s}^+ \to \ell^+ \nu_\ell$ decays for $\ell = \mu, \tau$. Our analysis incorporates both short-distance EW-QED corrections, which are beyond the leading-logarithmic approximation (the so-called Sirlin factor), and long-distance soft-photon corrections depending on the maximum total energy of undetected photons with their resummation. Although the inclusive photon QED corrections to the meson leptonic decays are well known, they do not match the actual measurement circumstances in $D_s^+ \to \mu^+ \nu_\mu$. We show that properly including these radiative corrections is essential to bring the second-column CKM unitarity tests into agreement with the Standard Model expectation. The study emphasizes that the current limiting factor in confirming CKM unitarity is the precision of QED corrections, and it points out that improving lattice simulations, taking the QED corrections into account, would be desired for a more robust confirmation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22383v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teppei Kitahara, Jun Miyamoto, Kota Sasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extractions of the strong coupling from collider data without PDF refitting are biased</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22561v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an explicit demonstration that a determination of the strong coupling constant $\alpha_s(m_Z)$ from deep-inelastic scattering and hadron collider data without a simultaneous determination of the parton distribution functions (PDFs) leads to a biased result for both the central value and the uncertainty, even in the ideal scenario (closure test) where there are no internal tensions between datasets and where theoretical calculations describe perfectly the experimental measurements. Specifically, we show that a determination of $\alpha_s(m_Z)$ from a single process leads in general to a result that differs from the global best fit more than the value of $\alpha_s(m_Z)$ that is actually favoured by this process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22561v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Forte, Juan Rojo, Roy Stegeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Physics Searches via Beam Normal Spin Asymmetry in Bhabha Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22568v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We examine the sensitivity of the beam normal spin asymmetry in Bhabha scattering to beyond the Standard Model (BSM) mediators, in the context of the JLab polarized positron program. A key property of this observable is that the Standard Model contribution exhibits a zero crossing at a fixed scattering angle, providing a clean, effectively background-free point for these searches. We consider scalar, vector and axial-vector mediators and present projected bounds, finding scalar and vector scenarios allowing to extend their search ranges significantly beyond existing constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22568v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandr Pustyntsev, Muthubharathi S. Ramasamy, Marc Vanderhaeghen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-range production of three bottom mesons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22590v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Previous investigations of the three-body dynamics of $B$ mesons have shown that no Efimov effect arises in systems composed of three $B$ and $B^*$ mesons. This implies that the properties of such three-body systems can be described reliably in nonrelativistic effective field theory (NREFT) with two-body input alone, as three-body forces are strongly suppressed. In this work, we present leading-order predictions for the three-body point production rates of systems consisting of three $B$ and $B^*$ mesons. These predictions provide a novel way to experimentally probe the $B^{(*)}$-$\bar{B}^{(*)}$ interactions, which play a crucial role in the hadronic-molecule interpretation of the $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10610)$ and $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10650)$ states. Moreover, they provide a way to test the approximate conformal symmetry predicted for such systems at low energies experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22590v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong-Hui Lin, Hans-Werner Hammer, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initial Assessment of Second Generation of Large-Area Picosecond Photodetectors with Multi-Channel Systems-on-a-Chip Readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22765v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We first briefly describe the history and motivation behind Cherenkov and scintillation light detection. We then discuss the instrumentation needed to detect these photons as it applies to both photodetectors and readout electronics. One of the motivations is future large neutrino detectors that could in principle differentiate between Cherenkov and scintillation light if using novel water-based scintillators. In this paper, we present the first measurements utilizing the second generation of Large Area Picosecond Photodetectors (LAPPDs) in conjunction with commercial system-on-a-chip readouts from Nalu Scientific -- specifically, the High Density System on Chip (HDSoC) and Advanced ASoC Rapid Digitizer, Variable Adaptive Readout Chip (AARDVARC) platforms. These state-of-the-art full-waveform digitizers feature sampling rates on the order of 1 and 10 samples per nanosecond, respectively. Using a picosecond laser, we measured the timing jitter between a pair of LAPPD channels, demonstrating the potential of this setup for precise timing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22765v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0269181</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Sci. Instrum. 96, 113102 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Li, O. A. Akindele, M. Bondin, S. R. Durham, J. A. Foot, M. J. Ford, S. -W. Stradleigh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Approach to the Calculation of Particle Creation from Analog Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22895v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of particle creation from accelerating mirrors is crucial for interpreting forthcoming analog Hawking radiation experiments such as AnaBHEL. However, realistic experimental setups render the associated Bogoliubov integrals analytically intractable. To address this challenge, we introduce the Inertial Replacement Method (IRM), a hybrid analytic-numerical framework for computing Bogoliubov coefficients for general moving-mirror trajectories. The IRM replaces the asymptotically inertial portions of a trajectory with analytic inertial extensions, so that numerical evaluation is required only for the finite accelerating segment. We derive perturbative error bounds for both perfectly and imperfectly reflecting mirrors, providing controlled accuracy estimates and guiding the choice of segmentation thresholds. The method is validated against analytically solvable trajectories and then applied to a fully numerical, PIC-based Chen-Mourou plasma-mirror trajectory relevant to the planned AnaBHEL experiment. A key physical insight emerging from this analysis is that the radiation spectrum is determined almost entirely by the finite accelerating region, with negligible sensitivity to the far-past and far-future inertial motion. These results establish the IRM as a reliable and broadly applicable computational tool for modeling particle creation in realistic analog-gravity systems such as AnaBHEL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22895v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang-Shuo Hsiung, Pisin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quark mixing from muon collider neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23288v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A high energy muon collider naturally produces a collimated beam of neutrinos for a fixed-target experiment at a dedicated far-forward facility. The high intensity and energy of the beam makes it ideally suited for astonishingly precise measurements of neutrino scattering on nucleons in the deeply inelastic regime, enabling the determination of the Cabibbo--Kobayashi--Maskawa~(CKM) quark mixing matrix. We assess the floor to the attainable sensitivity set by irreducible sources of uncertainties from the imperfect knowledge of the parton distribution (PDF) and fragmentation functions, showing that a strong improvement is possible well above current standards. As a by-product, our analysis also outlines extraordinary perspectives for a combined determination of the PDF. The results demonstrate the potential of a parasitic neutrino experiment at the muon collider, motivating detailed future studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23288v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Marzocca, Francesco Montagno, Manuel Morales-Alvarado, Andrea Wulzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity of the FCC-ee to the decay of a dark photon into a $\mu^+\mu^-$ pair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23337v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The production of a dark photon $A^{\prime}$ at the proposed CERN FCC-ee collider is investigated. The study addresses the associated production $e^+e^-\rightarrow\gamma A^{\prime}$ followed by the decay $A^{\prime}\rightarrow\mu^+\mu^-$. The 95% CL sensitivity on the mixing between the photon and the dark photon is evaluated in the $m_{A^{\prime}}$ mass range 0.4-360 GeV, based on a parametrised simulation of the IDEA detector. The study is performed both for prompt and long-lived decays of the $A^{\prime}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23337v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Polesello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Particles at the Z-Pole: Tera-Z factories as discovery and precision machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23461v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Several proposed future lepton colliders are capable of producing trillions of Z-bosons, including FCC-ee, CEPC, LEP3 and LEP-Z. Such Tera-Z factories can discover new elementary particles with couplings to the Z-boson that are orders of magnitude smaller than current bounds. For couplings near the currently excluded parameter regions they could produce sufficiently large samples to study the new particles' properties in detail, hence acting as a discovery and precision machine in one. Using simple analytic estimates, we quantify the dependence of the expected event yield in long-lived particle searches on the number of produced Z-bosons and on the detector dimensions. From this, we derive estimates for both the discovery reach and the measurement precision attainable at such facilities. While the precision of such estimates of course falls short of proper simulations, the analytic approach is suitable for a quick assessment of the sensitivity for a given design. We illustrate this with two examples, heavy neutral leptons and axion-like particles. Under optimistic assumptions, these could be produced in the millions and billions, respectively, effectively turning future lepton colliders into exotics factories.
  We provide a code that quickly generates the sensitivity curves displayed in this work and can be extended to other models at https://github.com/liyuanzhen98/LLPatTeraZ.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23461v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Drewes, Juraj Klari\'c, Yuan-Zhen Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for neutral long-lived particles that decay into displaced jets in the ATLAS calorimeter in association with leptons or jets using $pp$ collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09183v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A search for neutral long-lived particles (LLPs) decaying in the ATLAS hadronic calorimeter using 140 fb$^{-1}$ of proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV delivered by the LHC is presented. The analysis is composed of three channels. The first targets pair-produced LLPs, where at least one LLP is produced with sufficiently low boost that its decay products can be resolved as separate jets. The second and third channels target LLPs respectively produced in association with a $W$ or $Z$ boson that decays leptonically. In each channel, different search regions target different kinematic regimes, to cover a broad range of LLP mass hypotheses and models. No excesses of events relative to the background predictions are observed. Higgs boson branching fractions to pairs of hadronically decaying neutral LLPs larger than 1% are excluded at 95% confidence level for proper decay lengths in the range of 30 cm to 4.5 m depending on the LLP mass, a factor of three improvement on previous searches in the hadronic calorimeter. The production of long-lived dark photons in association with a $Z$ boson with cross-sections above 0.1 pb is excluded for dark photon mean proper decay lengths in the range of 20 cm to 50 m, improving previous ATLAS results by an order of magnitude. Finally, long-lived photo-phobic axion-like particle models are probed for the first time by ATLAS, with production cross-sections above 0.1 pb excluded in the 0.1 mm to 10 m range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09183v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP11(2024)036</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 11 (2024) 036</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of systematic uncertainty-aware neural network trainings for binned-likelihood analyses at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13047v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a neural network training method capable of accounting for the effects of systematic variations of the data model in the training process and describe its extension towards neural network multiclass classification. The procedure is evaluated on the realistic case of the measurement of Higgs boson production via gluon fusion and vector boson fusion in the $\tau\tau$ decay channel at the CMS experiment. The neural network output functions are used to infer the signal strengths for inclusive production of Higgs bosons as well as for their production via gluon fusion and vector boson fusion. We observe improvements of 12 and 16% in the uncertainty in the signal strengths for gluon and vector-boson fusion, respectively, compared with a conventional neural network training based on cross-entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13047v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14713-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 85 (2025)1360</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> CMS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining off-shell Higgs boson production and the Higgs boson total width using $WW\to \ell\nu\ell\nu$ final states with the ATLAS detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07710v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A measurement of off-shell Higgs boson production is performed in the $H^{*} \rightarrow WW$ channel. The measurement uses a proton-proton collision dataset with an integrated luminosity of 140 fb$^{-1}$ collected at a centre-of-mass energy of 13 TeV by the ATLAS detector at the Large Hadron Collider. Final states in which both $W$ bosons decay leptonically are targeted, and events are categorised based on the flavour of the final-state leptons, the jet multiplicity, and the output of neural-network-based classifiers. The data are found to be compatible with the Standard Model expectation. An observed (expected) upper bound on the 95% symmetric confidence level interval is set on the rate of off-shell Higgs boson production at a value of 3.4 (4.4) times the Standard Model prediction. These results are combined with the results from the measurement of on-shell Higgs boson production in the same final states to obtain an observed (expected) upper bound at 95% confidence level on the Higgs boson total width of 13.1 (17.3) MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07710v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139898</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 870 (2025) 139898</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental overview on the charmed baryon decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19141v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The charmed baryon was first observed experimentally in 1975, one year after the charm quark's confirmation via the discovery of the $J/\psi$ particle. Studying charmed baryon decays provides a pathway to investigate both strong and weak interactions, leveraging the weak decays of the embedded charm quark. However, for approximately three decades following its discovery, experimental knowledge of charmed baryons remained significantly limited compared to those of the hidden-charm $\psi$ mesons and open-charm $D_{(s)}$ mesons. This situation changed markedly starting in 2014, when dedicated data collection for charmed baryons commenced at BESIII. In this article, we review the experimental progress achieved since 2014 in understanding the weak decays of the charmed baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19141v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-1137/ae1187</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chinese Physics C 50, 022002 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Rong Li, Xiao-Rui Lyu, Yangheng Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time Anomaly Detection for Liquid Argon Time Projection Chambers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21817v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a real-time anomaly detection framework for liquid argon time projection chambers (LArTPCs), targeting applications in particle physics experiments such as the Short Baseline Near Detector (SBND) or the future Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE). These experiments employ detectors that generate and stream high-resolution but sparse images of neutrino and other particle interactions. Our approach utilizes anomaly detection with autoencoders, compressed through knowledge distillation (KD), to enable the detection of anomalous signals in the data through efficient inference on resource-constrained hardware. The framework is targeted for deployment on computing platforms equipped with field-programmable gate arrays (FPGAs), GPUs, or CPUs, allowing low-latency selection of relevant activity directly from the raw detector data stream. We demonstrate that our approach is suitable for the detection and localization of anomalously "high-multiplicity" activity, and outline promising applications for LArTPC online data filtering and triggering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21817v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokju Chung, Jack Cleeve, Akshay Malige, Georgia Karagiorgi, Lino Gerlach, Adrian A. Pol, Isobel Ojalvo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for new physics with charm rare decays at BESIII</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08026v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Search for new physics with charm rare decays at BESIII. The BESIII experiment has collected 2.6 billion $\psi(3686)$ events, 10 billion $J/\psi$ events, $20 fb^{-1}$ D meson pairs at 3.773 GeV, and $7.33 fb^{-1}~D_{s}D_{s}^{*}$ events from 4.128 to 4.226 GeV. The huge data samples allow us to search for rare processes in charm hadron decays. In this paper, we report the FCNC decay in $J/\psi\to D^0\mu^+\mu^-$, $J/\psi\to D^0\gamma$ and $D_{s}^{+}\to h(h')e^+e^-$. The search for $J/\psi$ weak decays containing a D meson, $J/\psi\to D_{s}^{-}\pi^{+}$, and $J/\psi\to D_{s}^{-}\rho^{+}$ will also be presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08026v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonghua Zhan (On behalf of the BESIII Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First observation of the $\overline{B}_{s}^{0}\to\Lambda_{c}^{+}\overline{\Lambda}_{c}{}^{-}$ decay and evidence for the $\overline{B}^{0}\to\Lambda_{c}^{+}\overline{\Lambda}_{c}{}^{-}$ decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20476v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A search is presented for the two-body charmed baryonic decays $\overline{B}_{(s)}^{0}\to\Lambda_{c}^{+}\overline{\Lambda}_{c}{}^{-}$, using a data sample collected by the LHCb experiment during 2011--2012 and 2015--2018 corresponding to an integrated luminosity of $9\,\mathrm{fb}^{-1}$. The first observation of the $\overline{B}_{s}^{0}\to\Lambda_{c}^{+}\overline{\Lambda}_{c}{}^{-}$ decay is reported with $6.2\sigma$ significance, along with $4.3\sigma$ evidence for the $\overline{B}^{0}\to\Lambda_{c}^{+}\overline{\Lambda}_{c}{}^{-}$ decay. The branching fractions are measured to be $\mathcal{B}{}(\overline{B}^{0}\to\Lambda_{c}^{+}\overline{\Lambda}_{c}{}^{-}) = (1.01^{+0.27}_{-0.28} \pm 0.08 \pm 0.15) \times 10^{-5}$ and $\mathcal{B}{}(\overline{B}_{s}^{0}\to\Lambda_{c}^{+}\overline{\Lambda}_{c}{}^{-}) = (5.0 \pm 1.3 \pm 0.5 \pm 0.8) \times 10^{-5}$, where the first uncertainty is statistical, the second systematic, and the third due to external inputs. These results provide novel experimental inputs for the theoretical framework describing two-body baryonic decays of $B$ mesons via $W$-emission and $W$-exchange mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20476v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, A. A. Adefisoye, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, M. Akthar, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, R. Aleksiejunas, F. Alessio, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, S. Andres Estrada, A. Anelli, D. Ao, C. Arata, F. Archilli, Z. Areg, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, L. Arnone, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, R. Ata\'ide Da Silva, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, J. A. Authier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, A. Balboni, W. Baldini, Z. Baldwin, L. Balzani, H. Bao, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, C. Barbero Pretel, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, M. Barnyakov, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, J. Bartz, S. Bashir, B. Batsukh, P. B. Battista, A. Bavarchee, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, N. A. Behling, S. Belin, A. Bellavista, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, A. Bertolin, F. Betti, J. Bex, O. Bezshyyko, S. Bhattacharya, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, R. B. Bonacci, N. Bondar, A. Bordelius, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, E. Bottalico, S. A. Bouchiba, M. Bovill, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, J. D. Brandenburg, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, J. Brown, D. Brundu, E. Buchanan, M. Burgos Marcos, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, C. Buti, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, Y. Cai, A. Caillet, R. Calabrese, S. Calderon Ramirez, L. Calefice, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, P. Camargo Magalhaes, J. I. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, A. C. Campos, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, M. Caporale, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, I. Celestino, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, H. Chang, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, E. Chatzianagnostou, R. Cheaib, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, J. Chen, S. Chen, Z. Chen, A. Chen Hu, M. Cherif, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, X. Chiotopoulos, V. Chobanova, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, S. Collaviti, P. Collins, T. Colombo, M. Colonna, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, J. Connaughton, A. Contu, N. Cooke, G. Cordova, C. Coronel, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, M. Cubero Campos, E. Curras Rivera, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, G. Darze, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, F. De Benedetti, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, S. Dekkers, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, Y. Ding, L. Dittmann, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, A. Doheny, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, A. D. Dowling, L. Dreyfus, W. Duan, P. Duda, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, O. D. Durmus, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, D. Elizondo Blanco, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, J. Eschle, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, S. Faghih, L. N. Falcao, B. Fang, R. Fantechi, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, F. Fassin, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, A. Fernandez Casani, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, M. Firlej, K. L. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, T. Fiutowski, F. Fleuret, A. Fomin, M. Fontana, L. A. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, V. Franco Lima, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, J. Fu, Q. F\"uhring, T. Fulghesu, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, B. Ganie, H. Gao, R. Gao, T. Q. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, P. Gardner, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, A. Gavrikov, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, S. Ghizzo, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, L. Girardey, M. A. Giza, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, L. Golinka-Bezshyyko, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, S. Gomez Fernandez, W. Gomulka, I. Gon\c{c}ales Vaz, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, E. Govorkova, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, L. Guerry, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, K. Habermann, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, S. Haken, G. Hallett, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, T. H. Harris, M. Hartmann, S. Hashmi, J. He, N. Heatley, A. Hedes, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, P. Herrero Gascon, J. Heuel, A. Heyn, A. Hicheur, G. Hijano Mendizabal, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, D. C. Houston, N. Howarth, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, M. Idzik, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Iniukhin, A. Iohner, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, T. Jakoubek, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, C. Jayaweera, A. Jelavic, V. Jevtic, Z. Jia, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, E. Jimenez Moya, N. Jindal, M. John, A. John Rubesh Rajan, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, J. Juan Castella, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, K. Kalecinska, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, M. Kane, Y. Kang, C. Kar, M. Karacson, A. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, M. K. Kazanecki, F. Keizer, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, F. Kiraz, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, A. Kleimenova, D. K. Klekots, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, T. Knospe, R. Kolb, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, A. Korchin, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, E. Kowalczyk, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, O. Kravcov, M. Kreps, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, O. Kshyvanskyi, S. Kubis, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, V. Kushnir, B. Kutsenko, J. Kvapil, I. Kyryllin, D. Lacarrere, P. Laguarta Gonzalez, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, G. Lanfranchi, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, E. Lemos Cid, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, E. D. Lesser, B. Leverington, A. Li, C. Li, C. Li, H. Li, J. Li, K. Li, L. Li, M. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, Q. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Lian, Q. Liang, X. Liang, Z. Liang, S. Libralon, A. Lightbody, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, H. Linton, R. Litvinov, D. Liu, F. L. Liu, G. Liu, K. Liu, S. Liu, W. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, G. Loachamin Ordonez, I. Lobo, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, T. Long, F. C. L. Lopes, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, C. Lopez Iribarnegaray, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, Q. Lu, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, M. Lucio Martinez, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, H. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, B. Mack, I. Mackay, L. M. Mackey, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. J. Madurai, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, F. M. Manganella, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, E. Mariani, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, L. Martel, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Gomez, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Martorell i Granollers, A. Massafferri, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, J. Mazorra de Cos, M. Mazurek, D. Mazzanti Tarancon, M. McCann, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, D. Melnychuk, D. Mendoza Granada, P. Menendez Valdes Perez, F. M. Meng, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, R. Mocanu, A. Modak, L. Moeser, R. D. Moise, E. F. Molina Cardenas, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, T. Monnard, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, A. Moro, J. Moron, W. Morren, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. Mu\~noz-Rojas, R. Murta, V. Mytrochenko, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, G. Napoletano, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, E. Nekrasova, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, L. Nisi, Q. Niu, B. K. Njoki, P. Nogarolli, P. Nogga, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, A. Okhotnikov, O. Okhrimenko, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, E. Olivart Pino, M. Olocco, R. H. O'Neil, J. S. Ordonez Soto, D. Osthues, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, F. Paciolla, A. Padee, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, T. Pajero, A. Palano, L. Palini, M. Palutan, C. Pan, X. Pan, S. Panebianco, S. Paniskaki, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, D. Parmar, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, A. Paul, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, J. Peng, X. Peng, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, H. Pereira Da Costa, M. Pereira Martinez, A. Pereiro Castro, C. Perez, P. Perret, A. Perrevoort, A. Perro, M. J. Peters, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, S. Pezzulo, J. P. Pfaller, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, L. Piccolo, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, R. N. Pilato, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. M. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, T. Poeschl, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, K. Popp, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, D. Provenzano, V. Pugatch, A. Puicercus Gomez, G. Punzi, J. R. Pybus, Q. Q. Qian, W. Qian, N. Qin, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, R. Racz, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, V. Ramos De Oliveira, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, M. Ribalda Galvez, R. Ribatti, G. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, F. Riehn, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, A. Rodriguez Alvarez, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, J. Roensch, A. Rogachev, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, T. Rong, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, J. J. Saavedra-Arias, J. J. Saborido Silva, S. E. R. Sacha Emile R., N. Sagidova, D. Sahoo, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, A. Sarnatskiy, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, F. Sborzacchi, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, N. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, M. H. Schune, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, G. Scriven, I. Segal, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, T. Senger, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, B. Sevilla Sanjuan, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, R. S. Sharma, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, J. Shi, Q. Shi, W. S. Shi, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, M. Singha, I. Siral, N. Skidmore, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, E. Smith, M. Smith, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, K. Solovieva, N. S. Sommerfeld, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, K. M. Sowa, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, P. Spradlin, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, M. Stefaniak, O. Steinkamp, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, J. Sun, L. Sun, D. Sundfeld, W. Sutcliffe, P. Svihra, V. Svintozelskyi, K. Swientek, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, Y. Tan, Y. Tang, Y. T. Tang, M. D. Tat, J. A. Teijeiro Jimenez, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, A. R. Thomson-Strong, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, T. T. Todorov, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, T. Tork, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, A. Upadhyay, B. Urbach, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, A. Vaitkevicius, V. Valcarce Cadenas, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, J. van Eldik, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, G. Vasquez, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. Velilla Serna, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Verdoglia, M. Vesterinen, W. Vetens, D. Vico Benet, P. Vidrier Villalba, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, B. Vivacqua, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, C. Vrahas, J. Wagner, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, A. Wang, B. Wang, C. Wang, G. Wang, H. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. H. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, M. Waterlaat, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, Z. Weida, J. Wendel, B. D. C. Westhenry, C. White, M. Whitehead, E. Whiter, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, M. A. Wiegertjes, C. Wild, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. J. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, S. Williams, Z. Williams, F. F. Wilson, M. Winn, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, T. Wolf, E. Wood, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, X. Wu, Y. Wu, Z. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, T. X. Xing, A. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, S. Yadav, K. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, X. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, Y Yuan, J. A. Zamora Saa, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, F. Zenesini, C. Zeng, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, R. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. L. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zhelezov, S. Z. Zheng, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, Y. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding spin-parity quantum numbers and decay widths of double $J/\psi$ exotic states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13455v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive helicity amplitudes for the fully charmed tetraquark states decays into vector meson pair under two types of models, where the one is from quark model and the other one is from diquark model. The decay angular distributions have been given by the cascade decays $T_{4c}\to J/\psi(D_{(s)}^*)+J/\psi(\bar{D}_{(s)}^*)$ along with $J/\psi\to \mu^++\mu^-$ or $D_{(s)}^*\to D_{(s)}+\pi$, showing that spin-0 and spin-2 states can be distinguished. We also find that the spin-0 state decay to $J/\psi$-pair exhibits a higher degree of quantum entanglement than that in spin-2 state decays. These findings will assist in experimentally differentiating various spin-parity states, determining decay widths and unveiling undiscovered hadronic states within existing structures, thereby shedding light on the internal properties of double $J/\psi$ exotic states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13455v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaiwen Chen, Feng-Xiao Liu, Qiang Zhao, Xian-Hui Zhong, Ruilin Zhu, Bing-Song Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on Kinetic Mixing of Dark Photons from Dilepton Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11163v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dark photons, the hypothetical gauge bosons associated with an additional $U(1)^{\prime}$ symmetry, can couple to Standard Model particles through a small kinetic mixing parameter $\varepsilon$ with the ordinary photon. This mechanism provides a portal between the dark sector and visible matter. In this study, we present a procedure to derive theoretical upper bounds on the kinetic mixing parameter $\varepsilon^2(M_U)$ by analyzing dilepton spectra from heavy-ion collisions across a broad energy range, from SIS to LHC energies. Our analysis is based on the microscopic Parton-Hadron-String Dynamics (PHSD) transport approach, which successfully reproduces the measured dilepton spectra in $p+p$, $p+A$, and $A+A$ collisions across the same energy range. Besides the dilepton channels resulting from interactions and decays of Standard Model particles (such as mesons and baryons), the PHSD has been extended to include the decay of hypothetical dark photons into dileptons, $U \to e^+ e^-$. The production of these dark photons occurs via Dalitz decays of $\pi^0$, $\eta$, $\omega$, $\eta^{\prime}$, and $\Delta$ resonances; direct decays of $\rho$, $\omega$, and $\phi$; the kaon mode $K^+ \to \pi^+ U$; and thermal $q\bar q$ annihilation in the quark-gluon plasma. Our results show that high-precision measurements of dilepton spectra in heavy-ion collisions provide a sensitive and competitive probe of dark photons in the MeV to multi-GeV mass range. Furthermore, we quantify the experimental accuracy required to constrain the remaining viable parameter space of kinetic mixing in dark photon scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11163v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qzzg-h1xw</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A.W.R.Jorge, E.Bratkovskaya, T.Song and L.Sagunski,Constraints on kinetic mixing of dark photons from dilepton spectra, Phys. Rev. C, 112 (2025) no.5, 054905</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. W. Romero Jorge, E. Bratkovskaya, T. Song, L. Sagunski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rare few-body decays of the Standard Model Higgs boson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00466v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a survey of rare and exclusive few-body decays of the standard model (SM) Higgs boson, defined as those into two to four final particles with branching fractions $\mathcal{B}\lesssim 10^{-5}$. Studies of such decays can be exploited to constrain Yukawa couplings of quarks and leptons, probe flavour-changing Higgs decays, estimate backgrounds for exotic Higgs decays into beyond-SM particles, and/or confirm quantum chromodynamics factorization with small nonperturbative corrections. We collect the theoretical $\mathcal{B}$ values for about 70 unobserved Higgs rare decay channels, indicating their current experimental limits, and estimating their expected bounds in p-p collisions at the HL-LHC. Among those, we include 20 new decay channels computed for the first time for ultrarare Higgs boson decays into photons and/or neutrinos, radiative quark-flavour-changing exclusive decays, and radiative decays into leptonium states. This survey can help guide and prioritize upcoming experimental and theoretical studies of unobserved Higgs boson decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00466v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David d'Enterria, Van Dung Le</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the nature and charge state of the X-Defect, a radiation-induced Silicon defect with field-enhanced charge carrier emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16197v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The elusive X-Defect, a defect found in low-resistivity $p$-type Silicon after irradiation, observed as a low-temperature shoulder of the $\mathrm{B}_\mathrm{i}\mathrm{O}_\mathrm{i}$ defect (Boron-interstitial-Oxygen-interstitial complex) in Thermally Stimulated Current (TSC) measurements, was investigated to determine its properties, matching them with those of a previously identified defect. Through a combination of TSC, Deep-Level Transient Spectroscopy (DLTS), Difference-DLTS (DDLTS), numerical simulations of field-enhanced charge carrier emissions in TSC measurements and a comparison to literature, the X-Defect was identified as the singly positively charged Silicon di-vacancy $\mathrm{V}_2(+/0)$. This assignment is supported by an agreement in activation energy, capture cross-section, trap type and charge emission process, as well as simulations comparing the effects of phonon-assisted tunnelling (PAT) and Poole-Frenkel (PF) mechanisms on TSC spectra. DDTLS measurements revealed a quadratic dependence of the activation energy on the electric field strength, confirming PAT as the prevailing mechanism over PF in the case of the radiation-induced X-Defect. Assigning the X-Defect to an electrically neutral defect in the space charge region resolves previous contradictions regarding its deficiency in impacting on the effective doping concentration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16197v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2025.171133</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Niels Sorgenfrei, Yana Gurimskaya, Anja Himmerlich, Michael Moll, Ulrich Parzefall, Ioana Pintilie, Joern Schwandt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Way of Axion Detection with Mass $10^{-4} \text{-}10^{-3}$eV Using Cylindrical Sample with Low Electric Conductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16746v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A dark matter axion with mass $m_a$ induces an oscillating electric field in a cylindrical sample placed under a magnetic field $B$ parallel to the cylinder axis. When the cylinder is made of a highly electrically conductive material, the induced oscillating current flows only at the surface. In contrast, if the cylinder is composed of a material with small conductivity, e.g. $\sigma = 10^{-3}\text{eV}$, the electric current flows inside the bulk of the cylinder. Within the QCD axion model, the current $I$ is estimated as $I(m_a=10^{-4}\text{eV}) \simeq 1.9\times 10^{-14}\text{A}g_{\gamma}(R/6\text{cm})^2 (\sigma/10^{-3}\text{eV})(B/10\text{T})(10/\epsilon)(\rho_a/0.3\text{GeVcm}^{-3}) $ with radius $R$, length $L$, permittivity $\epsilon = 10$ of the cylinder and axion energy density $\rho_a$, where $g_{\gamma}$ is model dependent parameter; $g_{\gamma}(\text{KSVZ}) = -0.96$ and $g_{\gamma}(\text{DFSZ}) = 0.37$. Using an LC circuit with a quality factor $Q = 10$, the signal-to-noise ratio at temperature $T=100$mK and observation time $t_{ob}=60$second is $\sim 0.5(Q/10)\sqrt{(m_a/10^{-4}\text{eV})(100\text{mK}/T)(t_{ob}/60\text{s})}$. The detection of dark matter axions is feasible in the mass range $m_a =10^{-4}\text{-}10^{-3}\text{eV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16746v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aiichi Iwazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studies of jet quenching in O+O collisions at $\sqrt{s_{\rm NN}}$ = 200 GeV by STAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18616v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Jet quenching is a well-established probe of the QGP in large collision systems such as Au+Au and Pb+Pb, but is absent in smaller p+A collisions despite the presence of collectivity. This makes it important to study its dependence on system size. O+O collisions offer an ideal opportunity, bridging the gap between small and large systems. In these proceedings, we present the measurements of the following observables related to jet quenching: inclusive charged hadron $R_{\rm AA}$ and $R_{\rm CP}$ at high transverse momentum ($p_{\rm T}$), inclusive jet $R_{\rm CP}$, and semi-inclusive hadron+jet $I_{\rm CP}$, using O+O collisions data collected with the STAR detector in 2021 at $\sqrt{s_{\rm NN}} = 200$ GeV. For jet measurements, combinatorial background is subtracted based on the event mixing technique, while background fluctuations and detector effects are corrected via unfolding. Inclusive charged hadron and jet $R_{\rm CP}$ and h+jet $I_{\rm CP}$ are found to be below unity, indicating suppression relative to peripheral events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18616v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sijie Zhang (for the STAR Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing quantum entanglement with Generalized Parton Distributions at the Electron-Ion Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04537v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Within the collinear factorization framework based on Generalized Parton Distributions (GPDs), we calculate the spin density matrix of exclusively produced quark and antiquark pairs $u\bar{u}$, $d\bar{d}$, $s\bar{s}$, $c\bar{c}$, $b\bar{b}$ in Deep Inelastic Scattering. The presence of both real and imaginary parts in the GPD amplitudes leads to a rich pattern of entanglement between the quark and the antiquark. We map out kinematical regions where the pairs exhibit entanglement, Bell nonlocality and non-stabilizerness (`magic'). We also predict that massive quarks and antiquarks are transversely polarized, similar to the well-known transverse hyperon polarization in unpolarized collisions. In strangeness, charm and bottom productions, the polarization can reach 50-80% in certain kinematic regions in the low-energy runs of the Electron-Ion Collider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04537v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshitaka Hatta, Jakob Schoenleber</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
