<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Sterile Neutrino Searches: Impact of Position Resolution in Short-Baseline Reactor Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The impact of position resolution on the sensitivity of short-baseline reactor neutrino experiments searching for light sterile neutrinos is investigated. Detailed simulations are conducted to evaluate two detector configurations: a segmented detector and an opaque liquid scintillator (OLS) detector, each positioned at two candidate research reactor sites, HANARO and Kijang. For both detector types, pseudo-data are generated under realistic assumptions regarding neutrino flux, detector response, and background levels. Oscillation analyses are performed to estimate detector sensitivity, incorporating both statistical and systematic uncertainties. The results indicate that the OLS detector, owing to its superior position resolution, achieves leading sensitivity across a wide range of oscillation parameters, even under conservative experimental conditions. These findings underscore the potential of OLS technology as a highly effective approach for future sterile neutrino searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20952v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s40042-025-01448-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Young Ju Ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-independent ZH production cross section at FCC-ee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents prospects for a model-independent measurement of the $ZH$ production cross section at the FCC-ee using the recoil-mass technique at center-of-mass energies of $\sqrt{s}=240$ and $365$ GeV. The analysis considers the muon, electron, and hadronic decay modes of the associated $Z$ boson. Event selections rely primarily on the kinematic properties of the reconstructed $Z$ decay products, ensuring maximal independence from specific Higgs boson decay modes, while multivariate techniques are employed to further enhance sensitivity. Statistical interpretations of the individual final states yield relative precisions of $0.52\%$ for the combined leptonic channels and $0.38\%$ for the hadronic channel at $\sqrt{s}=240$ GeV with an integrated luminosity of $10.8$ ab$^{-1}$. Their full statistical combination leads to total uncertainties of $0.31\%$ at $\sqrt{s}=240$ GeV and $0.52\%$ at $\sqrt{s}=365$ GeV with $3.12$ ab$^{-1}$. Dedicated statistical tests demonstrate model independence at the level of the obtained precision. This study presents, for the first time, a consistent and combined analysis of the leptonic and hadronic final states, achieving the most precise projected determination of the $ZH$ production cross section at future lepton colliders, with model independence demonstrated within the statistical precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21290v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ang Li, Jan Eysermans, Gregorio Bernardi, Kevin Dewyspelaere, Michele Selvaggi, Christoph Paus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs-Pair Production via Gluon Fusion: Top-Yukawa- and light-quark-induced electroweak Corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.14823v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gluon fusion, $gg\to HH$, is the dominant Higgs-pair production process at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and provides the first direct access to the trilinear Higgs self-interaction. The process is loop-induced, with the main contribution emerging from top-quark loops within the Standard Model. In the past, the QCD corrections have been calculated and found to increase the cross section significantly. With the anticipated accuracies achievable at the high-luminosity LHC (HL--LHC), the theoretical uncertainties will be of increased relevance to compete with the experimental precision at the level of less than 30\%. In this work, we take the next steps towards the determination of the complete electroweak corrections at next-to-leading order by calculating the full top-Yukawa and light-quark induced corrections. These corrections modify the cross section moderately in the kinematical regimes of interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.14823v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arunima Bhattacharya, Francisco Campanario, Sauro Carlotti, Jamie Chang, Javier Mazzitelli, Margarete M\"uhlleitner, Jonathan Ronca, Michael Spira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopy of VUV luminescence in dual-phase xenon detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20935v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present spectroscopic measurements of xenon luminescence in a time projection chamber operated in a dual-phase (liquid-gas) configuration. Thorium-228 $\alpha$ decays excited the liquid, resulting in the formation of singlet and triplet excimers that emit vacuum ultraviolet (VUV) scintillation. Ionisation electrons were drifted to the liquid surface and extracted into the vapour, where they produced VUV electroluminescence. A time-resolved photon-counting technique was used to obtain the scintillation spectrum in the liquid, which exhibited a peak wavelength of $177.1\pm0.1_\mathrm{stat} \pm0.1_\mathrm{sys}\,\textrm{nm}$ and a full-width at half maximum (FWHM) of $11.3\pm0.2_\mathrm{stat} \pm0.0_\mathrm{sys}\,\textrm{nm}$. The data were also used to obtain distinct singlet and triplet emission models, with the singlet emission peaking $1.8\pm0.3_{\mathrm{stat}}\pm 0.3_{\mathrm{sys}}\,\textrm{nm}$ shorter than the triplet. The gas electroluminescence spectrum was obtained simultaneously, while under conditions of thermal equilibrium. It remained consistent across vapour pressures of $1.3$-$2.2\,\textrm{bar}$, with a peak of $173.28\pm0.02_\mathrm{stat} {_{-0.1}^{+0.2}}{}_\mathrm{sys}\,\textrm{nm}$, a FWHM of $10.59\pm0.03_\mathrm{stat} {_{-0.2}^{+0.0}}{}_\mathrm{sys}\,\textrm{nm}$, and a small short-wavelength tail that constitutes $(0.6\pm0.1)$% of the total spectrum. These are the only spectroscopic measurements of liquid scintillation and gas electroluminescence acquired simultaneously to date, and the first such measurements of singlet and triplet emission in the liquid phase. They are important for precisely characterising dual-phase xenon detectors used to search for dark matter particle interactions and other rare events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20935v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. C. Oliver-Mallory, A. M. Baker, E. Jacquet, T. J. Sumner, H. M. Araujo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The throttling refrigeration system for the large cooling power recovery of the PandaX-xT cryogenic distillation system for radon removal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20947v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In order to solve the continuous large cooling power supply problem (20 kW) for the radon-removal cryogenic distillation system, which operates at high liquid ffow rate of 856 kg/h (5 LPM) for the dark matter detector PandaX-xT of the next-generation, a throttling refrigeration system based on carbon tetraffuoride (R14) refrigerant for cooling power recovery is designed and developed. According to this system, the cooling power of the liquid xenon in the reboiler of 178K could be transferred to the product xenon cryostat to liquefy the gaseous product xenon by the R14 circulation, thus the liqueffed xenon could return to the detector with the same condition of which extracted from the detector to form a stable cooling cycle and prevent the instability of the detector. A research and development experiment is implemented to validate the feasibility of this large cooling recovery system, using the ethanol to simulate the liquid xenon. Experimental results show that the cooling power recovery of this system could achieve 17 kW with the efffciency of 76.5%, and the R14 ffow rate is 0.16 kg/s. This study realizes the online radon removal distillation with large ffow rate while eliminating the dependence of liquid nitrogen or cryocoolers, which means saving 2414 m3 liquid nitrogen per year or the power consumption of 230 kW. Furthermore, process simulation and optimization of the throttling refrigeration cycle is studied using Aspen Hysys to reveal the inffuences of the key parameters to the system, and the deviation between the simulation and experimental results is &lt; 2.52%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20947v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunyu Yao, Zhou Wang, Kangkang Zhao, Zhi Zheng, Haoyu Wang, Xiangyi Cui, Tao Zhang, Li Zhao, Huaikuang Ding, Wenbing Tao, Xiang Xiao, Shaobo Wang, Yonglin Ju, Jianglai Liu, Xiangdong Ji, Shuaijie Li, Manbin Shen, Chengbo Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron spectral shape of the third-forbidden $\beta$-decay of $^{87}$Rb measured using a Rb$_2$ZrCl$_6$ crystal scintillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, interest in experimental studies of $\beta$-decay electron spectra -- often referred to as $\beta$ spectra -- has been growing. This is particularly true for $\beta$ transitions where the electron spectra are sensitive to the effective value of the weak axial coupling, $g_{\rm A}$. Such measurements serve as important benchmarks for nuclear physics calculations and can also be used to characterize background in astroparticle physics experiments. In this work, a dedicated experiment has been carried out to investigate the spectral shape of the third-forbidden $^{87}$Rb $\beta$-decays, with the goal of estimating the effective $g_{\rm A}$ value for this transition and of deriving the T$_{1/2}$ value. This was done by comparing the experimental spectral shape with the estimates from various phenomenological models. The $^{87}$Rb source was embedded directly within the detector material of a new Rb$_2$ZrCl$_6$ crystal scintillator; the data taking was performed deep underground at Gran Sasso National Laboratory. The obtained experimental half-life value for the studied process is T$_{1/2} = 5.08(13) \times$ 10$^{10}$ yr; while a $g_{\rm A}$ value in the range 0.4 to 0.6 is obtained when accounting for uncertainties and depending on the model adopted as discussed in detail in the text.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21082v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Belli, R. Bernabei, F. Cappella, V. Caracciolo, R. Cerulli, A. Incicchitti, A. Leoncini, V. Merlo, S. S. Nagorny, V. V. Nahorna, S. Nisi, P. Wang, J. Suhonen, M. Ramalho, J. Kostensalo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operation of a tunable Power over Fiber system for light detectors down to 4.6 K</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21207v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Power over Fiber (PoF) technology delivers electrical power by transmitting laser light through a lightweight, non-conductive fiber optic cable to a remote photovoltaic optical converter, which in turn powers sensors or electrical devices. Among the several advantages offered by this solution are spark-free operation in the presence of electric fields, elimination of noise induced by power lines, immunity to electromagnetic interference, and high robustness in hostile environments. The R\&amp;D for the application of PoF in cryogenic environments started at FNAL and BNL (USA) in 2020 to power the Photon Detection System of the DUNE Vertical Drift module. This paper presents the results obtained in the framework of Cryo-PoF project where we developed a single-laser input line system to power an electronic amplifier and the photosensors at cryogenic temperatures. Unlike the DUNE solution, our system allows tuning of the photosensor bias by adjusting the input laser power. We also demonstrate the operation of the optical converter at temperatures down to 4.6 K, opening the possibility of using this technology in a much broader range of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21207v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Andreani, C. Brizzolari, E. J. Cristaldo Morales, M. J. Delgado Gonzales, A. Falcone, N. Gallice, C. Gotti, M. Lazzaroni, L. Meazza, G. Pessina, D. Santoro, F. Terranova, M. Torti, V. Trabattoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of Coherent Elastic Neutrino-Nucleus Scattering with COHERENT's Germanium Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the first detection of coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering (CEvNS) on natural germanium, measured at the Spallation Neutron Source at Oak Ridge National Laboratory. The Ge-Mini detector of the COHERENT collaboration employs large-mass, low-noise, high-purity germanium spectrometers, enabling excellent energy resolution, and an analysis threshold of 1.5 keV electron-equivalent ionization energy. We observe a on-beam excess of 20.6 +7.1 -6.3 counts with a total exposure of 10.22 GWhkg and we reject the no-CEvNS hypothesis with 3.9 sigma significance. The result agrees with the predicted standard model of particle physics signal rate within 2 sigma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13806v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 231801 (Published 9 June, 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Adamski, M. Ahn, P. S. Barbeau, V. Belov, I. Bernardi, C. Bock, A. Bolozdynya, R. Bouabid, J. Browning, B. Cabrera-Palmer, N. Cedarblade-Jones, A. I. Col\'on Rivera, E. Conley, V. da Silva, J. Daughhetee, J. Detwiler, K. Ding, M. R. Durand, Y. Efremenko, S. R. Elliott, A. Erlandson, L. Fabris, A. Galindo-Uribarri, M. P. Green, J. Hakenm\"uller, M. R. Heath, S. Hedges, H. Jeong, B. A. Johnson, T. Johnson, H. Jones, A. Khromov, D. Kim, A. Konovalov, E. Kozlova, A. Kumpan, O. Kyzylova, Y. Lee, G. Li, L. Li, J. M. Link, J. Liu, M. Luxnat, A. Major, K. Mann, D. M. Markoff, J. Mattingly, J. Moye, P. E. Mueller, J. Newby, N. Ogoi, J. O'Reilly, D. S. Parno, D. P\'erez-Loureiro, D. Pershey, C. G. Prior, J. Queen, R. Rapp, H. Ray, O. Razuvaeva, D. Reyna, G. C. Rich, D. Rudik, J. Runge, D. J. Salvat, J. Sander, K. Scholberg, A. Shakirov, G. Simakov, W. M. Snow, V. Sosnovtsev, M. Stringer, T. Subedi, B. Suh, B. Sur, R. Tayloe, K. Tellez-Giron-Flores, Y. -T. Tsai, E. E. van Nieuwenhuizen, C. J. Virtue, G. Visser, K. Walkup, E. M. Ward, T. Wongjirad, Y. Yang, J. Yoo, C. -H. Yu, A. Zaalishvili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supernova Pointing Capabilities of DUNE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10339v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The determination of the direction of a stellar core collapse via its neutrino emission is crucial for the identification of the progenitor for a multimessenger follow-up. A highly effective method of reconstructing supernova directions within the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE) is introduced. The supernova neutrino pointing resolution is studied by simulating and reconstructing electron-neutrino charged-current absorption on 40Ar and elastic scattering of neutrinos on electrons. Procedures to reconstruct individual interactions, including a newly developed technique called ``brems flipping'', as well as the burst direction from an ensemble of interactions are described. Performance of the burst direction reconstruction is evaluated for supernovae happening at a distance of 10 kpc for a specific supernova burst flux model. The pointing resolution is found to be 3.4 degrees at 68% coverage for a perfect interaction-channel classification and a fiducial mass of 40 kton, and 6.6 degrees for a 10 kton fiducial mass respectively. Assuming a 4% rate of charged-current interactions being misidentified as elastic scattering, DUNE's burst pointing resolution is found to be 4.3 degrees (8.7 degrees) at 68% coverage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10339v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 092006 (Published 12 May, 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> DUNE Collaboration, A. Abed Abud, B. Abi, R. Acciarri, M. A. Acero, M. R. Adames, G. Adamov, M. Adamowski, D. Adams, M. Adinolfi, C. Adriano, A. Aduszkiewicz, J. Aguilar, B. Aimard, F. Akbar, K. Allison, S. Alonso Monsalve, M. Alrashed, A. Alton, R. Alvarez, T. Alves, H. Amar, P. Amedo, J. Anderson, D. A. Andrade, C. Andreopoulos, M. Andreotti, M. P. Andrews, F. Andrianala, S. Andringa, N. Anfimov, A. Ankowski, M. Antoniassi, M. Antonova, A. Antoshkin, A. Aranda-Fernandez, L. Arellano, E. Arrieta Diaz, M. A. Arroyave, J. Asaadi, A. Ashkenazi, D. Asner, L. Asquith, E. Atkin, D. Auguste, A. Aurisano, V. Aushev, D. Autiero, F. Azfar, A. Back, H. Back, J. J. Back, I. Bagaturia, L. Bagby, N. Balashov, S. Balasubramanian, P. Baldi, W. Baldini, J. Baldonedo, B. Baller, B. Bambah, R. Banerjee, F. Barao, G. Barenboim, P. Barham Alz\'as, G. J. Barker, W. Barkhouse, G. Barr, J. Barranco Monarca, A. Barros, N. Barros, D. Barrow, J. L. Barrow, A. Basharina-Freshville, A. Bashyal, V. Basque, C. Batchelor, L. Bathe-Peters, J. B. R. Battat, F. Battisti, F. Bay, M. C. Q. Bazetto, J. L. L. Bazo Alba, J. F. Beacom, E. Bechetoille, B. Behera, E. Belchior, G. Bell, L. Bellantoni, G. Bellettini, V. Bellini, O. Beltramello, N. Benekos, C. Benitez Montiel, D. Benjamin, F. Bento Neves, J. Berger, S. Berkman, J. Bernal, P. Bernardini, A. Bersani, S. Bertolucci, M. Betancourt, A. Betancur Rodr\'iguez, A. Bevan, Y. Bezawada, A. T. Bezerra, T. J. Bezerra, A. Bhat, V. Bhatnagar, J. Bhatt, M. Bhattacharjee, M. Bhattacharya, S. Bhuller, B. Bhuyan, S. Biagi, J. Bian, K. Biery, B. Bilki, M. Bishai, A. Bitadze, A. Blake, F. D. Blaszczyk, G. C. Blazey, E. Blucher, J. Bogenschuetz, J. Boissevain, S. Bolognesi, T. Bolton, L. Bomben, M. Bonesini, C. Bonilla-Diaz, F. Bonini, A. Booth, F. Boran, S. Bordoni, R. Borges Merlo, A. Borkum, N. Bostan, J. Bracinik, D. Braga, B. Brahma, D. Brailsford, F. Bramati, A. Branca, A. Brandt, J. Bremer, C. Brew, S. J. Brice, V. Brio, C. Brizzolari, C. Bromberg, J. Brooke, A. Bross, G. Brunetti, M. Brunetti, N. Buchanan, H. Budd, J. Buergi, D. Burgardt, S. Butchart, G. Caceres V., I. Cagnoli, T. Cai, R. Calabrese, J. Calcutt, M. Calin, L. Calivers, E. Calvo, A. Caminata, A. F. Camino, W. Campanelli, A. Campani, A. Campos Benitez, N. Canci, J. Cap\'o, I. Caracas, D. Caratelli, D. Carber, J. M. Carceller, G. Carini, B. Carlus, M. F. Carneiro, P. Carniti, I. Caro Terrazas, H. Carranza, N. Carrara, L. Carroll, T. Carroll, A. Carter, E. Casarejos, D. Casazza, J. F. Casta\~no Forero, F. A. Casta\~no, A. Castillo, C. Castromonte, E. Catano-Mur, C. Cattadori, F. Cavalier, F. Cavanna, S. Centro, G. Cerati, C. Cerna, A. Cervelli, A. Cervera Villanueva, K. Chakraborty, S. Chakraborty, M. Chalifour, A. Chappell, N. Charitonidis, A. Chatterjee, H. Chen, M. Chen, W. C. Chen, Y. Chen, Z. Chen-Wishart, D. Cherdack, C. Chi, F. Chiapponi, R. Chirco, N. Chitirasreemadam, K. Cho, S. Choate, D. Chokheli, P. S. Chong, B. Chowdhury, D. Christian, A. Chukanov, M. Chung, E. Church, M. F. Cicala, M. Cicerchia, V. Cicero, R. Ciolini, P. Clarke, G. Cline, T. E. Coan, A. G. Cocco, J. A. B. Coelho, A. Cohen, J. Collazo, J. Collot, E. Conley, J. M. Conrad, M. Convery, S. Copello, P. Cova, C. Cox, L. Cremaldi, L. Cremonesi, J. I. Crespo-Anad\'on, M. Crisler, E. Cristaldo, J. Crnkovic, G. Crone, R. Cross, A. Cudd, C. Cuesta, Y. Cui, F. Curciarello, D. Cussans, J. Dai, O. Dalager, R. Dallavalle, W. Dallaway, H. da Motta, Z. A. Dar, R. Darby, L. Da Silva Peres, Q. David, G. S. Davies, S. Davini, J. Dawson, R. De Aguiar, P. De Almeida, P. Debbins, I. De Bonis, M. P. Decowski, A. de Gouv\^ea, P. C. De Holanda, I. L. De Icaza Astiz, P. De Jong, P. Del Amo Sanchez, A. De la Torre, G. De Lauretis, A. Delbart, D. Delepine, M. Delgado, A. Dell'Acqua, G. Delle Monache, N. Delmonte, P. De Lurgio, R. Demario, G. De Matteis, J. R. T. de Mello Neto, D. M. DeMuth, S. Dennis, C. Densham, P. Denton, G. W. Deptuch, A. De Roeck, V. De Romeri, J. P. Detje, J. Devine, R. Dharmapalan, M. Dias, A. Diaz, J. S. D\'iaz, F. D\'iaz, F. Di Capua, A. Di Domenico, S. Di Domizio, S. Di Falco, L. Di Giulio, P. Ding, L. Di Noto, E. Diociaiuti, C. Distefano, R. Diurba, M. Diwan, Z. Djurcic, D. Doering, S. Dolan, F. Dolek, M. J. Dolinski, D. Domenici, L. Domine, S. Donati, Y. Donon, S. Doran, D. Douglas, T. A. Doyle, A. Dragone, F. Drielsma, L. Duarte, D. Duchesneau, K. Duffy, K. Dugas, P. Dunne, B. Dutta, H. Duyang, D. A. Dwyer, A. S. Dyshkant, S. Dytman, M. Eads, A. Earle, S. Edayath, D. Edmunds, J. Eisch, P. Englezos, A. Ereditato, T. Erjavec, C. O. Escobar, J. J. Evans, E. Ewart, A. C. Ezeribe, K. Fahey, L. Fajt, A. Falcone, M. Fani', C. Farnese, S. Farrell, Y. Farzan, D. Fedoseev, J. Felix, Y. Feng, E. Fernandez-Martinez, G. Ferry, L. Fields, P. Filip, A. Filkins, F. Filthaut, R. Fine, G. Fiorillo, M. Fiorini, S. Fogarty, W. Foreman, J. Fowler, J. Franc, K. Francis, D. Franco, J. Franklin, J. Freeman, J. Fried, A. Friedland, S. Fuess, I. K. Furic, K. Furman, A. P. Furmanski, R. Gaba, A. Gabrielli, A. M Gago, F. Galizzi, H. Gallagher, A. Gallas, N. Gallice, V. Galymov, E. Gamberini, T. Gamble, F. Ganacim, R. Gandhi, S. Ganguly, F. Gao, S. Gao, D. Garcia-Gamez, M. \'A. Garc\'ia-Peris, F. Gardim, S. Gardiner, D. Gastler, A. Gauch, J. Gauvreau, P. Gauzzi, S. Gazzana, G. Ge, N. Geffroy, B. Gelli, S. Gent, L. Gerlach, Z. Ghorbani-Moghaddam, T. Giammaria, D. Gibin, I. Gil-Botella, S. Gilligan, A. Gioiosa, S. Giovannella, C. Girerd, A. K. Giri, C. Giugliano, V. Giusti, D. Gnani, O. Gogota, S. Gollapinni, K. Gollwitzer, R. A. Gomes, L. V. Gomez Bermeo, L. S. Gomez Fajardo, F. Gonnella, D. Gonzalez-Diaz, M. Gonzalez-Lopez, M. C. Goodman, S. Goswami, C. Gotti, J. Goudeau, E. Goudzovski, C. Grace, E. Gramellini, R. Gran, E. Granados, P. Granger, C. Grant, D. R. Gratieri, G. Grauso, P. Green, S. Greenberg, J. Greer, W. C. Griffith, F. T. Groetschla, K. Grzelak, L. Gu, W. Gu, V. Guarino, M. Guarise, R. Guenette, E. Guerard, M. Guerzoni, D. Guffanti, A. Guglielmi, B. Guo, Y. Guo, A. Gupta, V. Gupta, G. Gurung, D. Gutierrez, P. Guzowski, M. M. Guzzo, S. Gwon, A. Habig, H. Hadavand, L. Haegel, R. Haenni, L. Hagaman, A. Hahn, J. Haiston, J. Hakenm\"uller, T. Hamernik, P. Hamilton, J. Hancock, F. Happacher, D. A. Harris, J. Hartnell, T. Hartnett, J. Harton, T. Hasegawa, C. Hasnip, R. Hatcher, K. Hayrapetyan, J. Hays, E. Hazen, M. He, A. Heavey, K. M. Heeger, J. Heise, S. Henry, M. A. Hernandez Morquecho, K. Herner, V. Hewes, A. Higuera, C. Hilgenberg, S. J. Hillier, A. Himmel, E. Hinkle, L. R. Hirsch, J. Ho, J. Hoff, A. Holin, T. Holvey, E. Hoppe, S. Horiuchi, G. A. Horton-Smith, M. Hostert, T. Houdy, B. Howard, R. Howell, I. Hristova, M. S. Hronek, J. Huang, R. G. Huang, Z. Hulcher, M. Ibrahim, G. Iles, N. Ilic, A. M. Iliescu, R. Illingworth, G. Ingratta, A. Ioannisian, B. Irwin, L. Isenhower, M. Ismerio Oliveira, R. Itay, C. M. Jackson, V. Jain, E. James, W. Jang, B. Jargowsky, D. Jena, I. Jentz, X. Ji, C. Jiang, J. Jiang, L. Jiang, A. Jipa, F. R. Joaquim, W. Johnson, C. Jollet, B. Jones, R. Jones, D. Jos\'e Fern\'andez, N. Jovancevic, M. Judah, C. K. Jung, T. Junk, Y. Jwa, M. Kabirnezhad, A. C. Kaboth, I. Kadenko, I. Kakorin, A. Kalitkina, D. Kalra, M. Kandemir, D. M. Kaplan, G. Karagiorgi, G. Karaman, A. Karcher, Y. Karyotakis, S. Kasai, S. P. Kasetti, L. Kashur, I. Katsioulas, A. Kauther, N. Kazaryan, L. Ke, E. Kearns, P. T. Keener, K. J. Kelly, E. Kemp, O. Kemularia, Y. Kermaidic, W. Ketchum, S. H. Kettell, M. Khabibullin, N. Khan, A. Khvedelidze, D. Kim, J. Kim, B. King, B. Kirby, M. Kirby, A. Kish, J. Klein, J. Kleykamp, A. Klustova, T. Kobilarcik, L. Koch, K. Koehler, L. W. Koerner, D. H. Koh, L. Kolupaeva, D. Korablev, M. Kordosky, T. Kosc, U. Kose, V. A. Kosteleck\'y, K. Kothekar, I. Kotler, M. Kovalcuk, V. Kozhukalov, W. Krah, R. Kralik, M. Kramer, L. Kreczko, F. Krennrich, I. Kreslo, T. Kroupova, S. Kubota, M. Kubu, Y. Kudenko, V. A. Kudryavtsev, G. Kufatty, S. Kuhlmann, J. Kumar, P. Kumar, S. Kumaran, P. Kunze, J. Kunzmann, R. Kuravi, N. Kurita, C. Kuruppu, V. Kus, T. Kutter, J. Kvasnicka, T. Labree, T. Lackey, A. Lambert, B. J. Land, C. E. Lane, N. Lane, K. Lang, T. Langford, M. Langstaff, F. Lanni, O. Lantwin, J. Larkin, P. Lasorak, D. Last, A. Laudrain, A. Laundrie, G. Laurenti, E. Lavaut, A. Lawrence, P. Laycock, I. Lazanu, M. Lazzaroni, T. Le, S. Leardini, J. Learned, T. LeCompte, C. Lee, V. Legin, G. Lehmann Miotto, R. Lehnert, M. A. Leigui de Oliveira, M. Leitner, D. Leon Silverio, L. M. Lepin, J. -Y Li, S. W. Li, Y. Li, H. Liao, C. S. Lin, D. Lindebaum, S. Linden, R. A. Lineros, J. Ling, A. Lister, B. R. Littlejohn, H. Liu, J. Liu, Y. Liu, S. Lockwitz, M. Lokajicek, I. Lomidze, K. Long, T. V. Lopes, J. Lopez, I. L\'opez de Rego, N. L\'opez-March, T. Lord, J. M. LoSecco, W. C. Louis, A. Lozano Sanchez, X. -G. Lu, K. B. Luk, B. Lunday, X. Luo, E. Luppi, J. Maalmi, D. MacFarlane, A. A. Machado, P. Machado, C. T. Macias, J. R. Macier, M. MacMahon, A. Maddalena, A. Madera, P. Madigan, S. Magill, C. Magueur, K. Mahn, A. Maio, A. Major, K. Majumdar, M. Man, R. C. Mandujano, J. Maneira, S. Manly, A. Mann, K. Manolopoulos, M. Manrique Plata, S. Manthey Corchado, V. N. Manyam, M. Marchan, A. Marchionni, W. Marciano, D. Marfatia, C. Mariani, J. Maricic, F. Marinho, A. D. Marino, T. Markiewicz, F. Das Chagas Marques, C. Marquet, D. Marsden, M. Marshak, C. M. Marshall, J. Marshall, L. Martina, J. Mart\'in-Albo, N. Martinez, D. A. Martinez Caicedo, F. Mart\'inez L\'opez, P. Mart\'inez Mirav\'e, S. Martynenko, V. Mascagna, C. Massari, A. Mastbaum, F. Matichard, S. Matsuno, G. Matteucci, J. Matthews, C. Mauger, N. Mauri, K. Mavrokoridis, I. Mawby, R. Mazza, A. Mazzacane, T. McAskill, N. McConkey, K. S. McFarland, C. McGrew, A. McNab, L. Meazza, V. C. N. Meddage, B. Mehta, P. Mehta, P. Melas, O. Mena, H. Mendez, P. Mendez, D. P. M\'endez, A. Menegolli, G. Meng, A. C. E. A. Mercuri, A. Meregaglia, M. D. Messier, S. Metallo, J. Metcalf, W. Metcalf, M. Mewes, H. Meyer, T. Miao, A. Miccoli, G. Michna, V. Mikola, R. Milincic, F. Miller, G. Miller, W. Miller, O. Mineev, A. Minotti, L. Miralles, O. G. Miranda, C. Mironov, S. Miryala, S. Miscetti, C. S. Mishra, S. R. Mishra, A. Mislivec, M. Mitchell, D. Mladenov, I. Mocioiu, A. Mogan, N. Moggi, R. Mohanta, T. A. Mohayai, N. Mokhov, J. Molina, L. Molina Bueno, E. Montagna, A. Montanari, C. Montanari, D. Montanari, D. Montanino, L. M. Monta\~no Zetina, M. Mooney, A. F. Moor, Z. Moore, D. Moreno, O. Moreno-Palacios, L. Morescalchi, D. Moretti, R. Moretti, C. Morris, C. Mossey, M. Mote, C. A. Moura, G. Mouster, W. Mu, L. Mualem, J. Mueller, M. Muether, F. Muheim, A. Muir, M. Mulhearn, D. Munford, L. J. Munteanu, H. Muramatsu, J. Muraz, M. Murphy, T. Murphy, J. Muse, A. Mytilinaki, J. Nachtman, Y. Nagai, S. Nagu, R. Nandakumar, D. Naples, S. Narita, A. Nath, A. Navrer-Agasson, N. Nayak, M. Nebot-Guinot, A. Nehm, J. K. Nelson, O. Neogi, J. Nesbit, M. Nessi, D. Newbold, M. Newcomer, R. Nichol, F. Nicolas-Arnaldos, A. Nikolica, J. Nikolov, E. Niner, K. Nishimura, A. Norman, A. Norrick, P. Novella, J. A. Nowak, M. Oberling, J. P. Ochoa-Ricoux, S. Oh, S. B. Oh, A. Olivier, A. Olshevskiy, T. Olson, Y. Onel, Y. Onishchuk, A. Oranday, M. Osbiston, J. A. Osorio V\'elez, L. Otiniano Ormachea, J. Ott, L. Pagani, G. Palacio, O. Palamara, S. Palestini, J. M. Paley, M. Pallavicini, C. Palomares, S. Pan, P. Panda, W. Panduro Vazquez, E. Pantic, V. Paolone, V. Papadimitriou, R. Papaleo, A. Papanestis, D. Papoulias, S. Paramesvaran, A. Paris, S. Parke, E. Parozzi, S. Parsa, Z. Parsa, S. Parveen, M. Parvu, D. Pasciuto, S. Pascoli, L. Pasqualini, J. Pasternak, C. Patrick, L. Patrizii, R. B. Patterson, T. Patzak, A. Paudel, L. Paulucci, Z. Pavlovic, G. Pawloski, D. Payne, V. Pec, E. Pedreschi, S. J. M. Peeters, W. Pellico, A. Pena Perez, E. Pennacchio, A. Penzo, O. L. G. Peres, Y. F. Perez Gonzalez, L. P\'erez-Molina, C. Pernas, J. Perry, D. Pershey, G. Pessina, G. Petrillo, C. Petta, R. Petti, M. Pfaff, V. Pia, L. Pickering, F. Pietropaolo, V. L. Pimentel, G. Pinaroli, J. Pinchault, K. Pitts, K. Plows, R. Plunkett, C. Pollack, T. Pollman, D. Polo-Toledo, F. Pompa, X. Pons, N. Poonthottathil, V. Popov, F. Poppi, J. Porter, M. Potekhin, R. Potenza, J. Pozimski, M. Pozzato, T. Prakash, C. Pratt, M. Prest, F. Psihas, D. Pugnere, X. Qian, J. Queen, J. L. Raaf, V. Radeka, J. Rademacker, B. Radics, A. Rafique, E. Raguzin, M. Rai, S. Rajagopalan, M. Rajaoalisoa, I. Rakhno, L. Rakotondravohitra, L. Ralte, M. A. Ramirez Delgado, B. Ramson, A. Rappoldi, G. Raselli, P. Ratoff, R. Ray, H. Razafinime, E. M. Rea, J. S. Real, B. Rebel, R. Rechenmacher, M. Reggiani-Guzzo, J. Reichenbacher, S. D. Reitzner, H. Rejeb Sfar, E. Renner, A. Renshaw, S. Rescia, F. Resnati, Diego Restrepo, C. Reynolds, M. Ribas, S. Riboldi, C. Riccio, G. Riccobene, J. S. Ricol, M. Rigan, E. V. Rinc\'on, A. Ritchie-Yates, S. Ritter, D. Rivera, R. Rivera, A. Robert, J. L. Rocabado Rocha, L. Rochester, M. Roda, P. Rodrigues, M. J. Rodriguez Alonso, A. J. Roeth, J. Rodriguez Rondon, S. Rosauro-Alcaraz, P. Rosier, D. Ross, M. Rossella, M. Rossi, M. Ross-Lonergan, N. Roy, P. Roy, C. Rubbia, A. Ruggeri, G. Ruiz Ferreira, B. Russell, D. Ruterbories, A. Rybnikov, A. Saa-Hernandez, R. Saakyan, S. Sacerdoti, S. K. Sahoo, N. Sahu, P. Sala, N. Samios, O. Samoylov, M. C. Sanchez, A. S\'anchez Bravo, P. Sanchez-Lucas, V. Sandberg, D. A. Sanders, S. Sanfilippo, D. Sankey, D. Santoro, N. Saoulidou, P. Sapienza, C. Sarasty, I. Sarcevic, I. Sarra, G. Savage, V. Savinov, G. Scanavini, A. Scaramelli, A. Scarff, T. Schefke, H. Schellman, S. Schifano, P. Schlabach, D. Schmitz, A. W. Schneider, K. Scholberg, A. Schukraft, B. Schuld, A. Segade, E. Segreto, A. Selyunin, C. R. Senise, J. Sensenig, M. H. Shaevitz, P. Shanahan, P. Sharma, R. Kumar, K. Shaw, T. Shaw, K. Shchablo, J. Shen, C. Shepherd-Themistocleous, A. Sheshukov, W. Shi, S. Shin, S. Shivakoti, I. Shoemaker, D. Shooltz, R. Shrock, B. Siddi, M. Siden, J. Silber, L. Simard, J. Sinclair, G. Sinev, Jaydip Singh, J. Singh, L. Singh, P. Singh, V. Singh, S. Singh Chauhan, R. Sipos, C. Sironneau, G. Sirri, K. Siyeon, K. Skarpaas, J. Smedley, E. Smith, J. Smith, P. Smith, J. Smolik, M. Smy, M. Snape, E. L. Snider, P. Snopok, D. Snowden-Ifft, M. Soares Nunes, H. Sobel, M. Soderberg, S. Sokolov, C. J. Solano Salinas, S. S\"oldner-Rembold, S. R. Soleti, N. Solomey, V. Solovov, W. E. Sondheim, M. Sorel, A. Sotnikov, J. Soto-Oton, A. Sousa, K. Soustruznik, F. Spinella, J. Spitz, N. J. C. Spooner, K. Spurgeon, D. Stalder, M. Stancari, L. Stanco, J. Steenis, R. Stein, H. M. Steiner, A. F. Steklain Lisb\^oa, A. Stepanova, J. Stewart, B. Stillwell, J. Stock, F. Stocker, T. Stokes, M. Strait, T. Strauss, L. Strigari, A. Stuart, J. G. Suarez, J. Subash, A. Surdo, L. Suter, C. M. Sutera, K. Sutton, Y. Suvorov, R. Svoboda, S. K. Swain, B. Szczerbinska, A. M. Szelc, A. Sztuc, A. Taffara, N. Talukdar, J. Tamara, H. A. Tanaka, S. Tang, N. Taniuchi, A. M. Tapia Casanova, B. Tapia Oregui, A. Tapper, S. Tariq, E. Tarpara, E. Tatar, R. Tayloe, D. Tedeschi, A. M. Teklu, J. Tena Vidal, P. Tennessen, M. Tenti, K. Terao, F. Terranova, G. Testera, T. Thakore, A. Thea, A. Thiebault, S. Thomas, A. Thompson, C. Thorn, S. C. Timm, E. Tiras, V. Tishchenko, N. Todorovi\'c, L. Tomassetti, A. Tonazzo, D. Torbunov, M. Torti, M. Tortola, F. Tortorici, N. Tosi, D. Totani, M. Toups, C. Touramanis, D. Tran, R. Travaglini, J. Trevor, E. Triller, S. Trilov, J. Truchon, D. Truncali, W. H. Trzaska, Y. Tsai, Y. -T. Tsai, Z. Tsamalaidze, K. V. Tsang, N. Tsverava, S. Z. Tu, S. Tufanli, C. Tunnell, J. Turner, M. Tuzi, J. Tyler, E. Tyley, M. Tzanov, M. A. Uchida, J. Ure\~na Gonz\'alez, J. Urheim, T. Usher, H. Utaegbulam, S. Uzunyan, M. R. Vagins, P. Vahle, S. Valder, G. A. Valdiviesso, E. Valencia, R. Valentim, Z. Vallari, E. Vallazza, J. W. F. Valle, R. Van Berg, R. G. Van de Water, D. V. Forero, A. Vannozzi, M. Van Nuland-Troost, F. Varanini, D. Vargas Oliva, S. Vasina, N. Vaughan, K. Vaziri, A. V\'azquez-Ramos, J. Vega, S. Ventura, A. Verdugo, S. Vergani, M. Verzocchi, K. Vetter, M. Vicenzi, H. Vieira de Souza, C. Vignoli, C. Vilela, E. Villa, S. Viola, B. Viren, A. Vizcaya-Hernandez, T. Vrba, Q. Vuong, A. V. Waldron, M. Wallbank, J. Walsh, T. Walton, H. Wang, J. Wang, L. Wang, M. H. L. S. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Wang, K. Warburton, D. Warner, L. Warsame, M. O. Wascko, D. Waters, A. Watson, K. Wawrowska, A. Weber, C. M. Weber, M. Weber, H. Wei, A. Weinstein, H. Wenzel, S. Westerdale, M. Wetstein, K. Whalen, J. Whilhelmi, A. White, A. White, L. H. Whitehead, D. Whittington, M. J. Wilking, A. Wilkinson, C. Wilkinson, F. Wilson, R. J. Wilson, P. Winter, W. Wisniewski, J. Wolcott, J. Wolfs, T. Wongjirad, A. Wood, K. Wood, E. Worcester, M. Worcester, M. Wospakrik, K. Wresilo, C. Wret, S. Wu, W. Wu, W. Wu, M. Wurm, J. Wyenberg, Y. Xiao, I. Xiotidis, B. Yaeggy, N. Yahlali, E. Yandel, K. Yang, T. Yang, A. Yankelevich, N. Yershov, K. Yonehara, T. Young, B. Yu, H. Yu, J. Yu, Y. Yu, W. Yuan, R. Zaki, J. Zalesak, L. Zambelli, B. Zamorano, A. Zani, O. Zapata, L. Zazueta, G. P. Zeller, J. Zennamo, K. Zeug, C. Zhang, S. Zhang, M. Zhao, E. Zhivun, E. D. Zimmerman, S. Zucchelli, J. Zuklin, V. Zutshi, R. Zwaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for Light Dark Matter with 259-day data in PandaX-4T</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11930v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a search for light dark matter particles through their interactions with atomic electrons and nucleons, utilizing PandaX-4T data with an effective exposure of 1.04 tonne$\cdot$year for ionization-only data and 1.20 tonne$\cdot$year for paired data. Our analysis focuses on the energy range (efficiency$&gt;$0.01) of approximately 0.33 to 3 keV for nuclear recoils, and from 0.04 to 0.39 keV for electronic recoils. We establish the most stringent constraints on spin-independent dark matter-nucleon interactions within a mass range of 2.5 to 5.0 GeV/$c^2$, spin-dependent neutron-only interactions within 2.0 to 5.3 GeV/$c^2$, and spin-dependent proton-only interactions within 2.0 to 3.8 GeV/$c^2$. Their corresponding limits at 3\,GeV/$c^2$ are $1.1 \times 10^{-43}$, $1.6 \times 10^{-38}$, and $5.6 \times 10^{-37}$\,cm$^2$, respectively. Additionally, our results improve the upper limits on the dark matter-electron scattering cross-section by a factor of 1.5 and 9.3 for heavy and light mediator scenarios respectively within 50 MeV/$c^2$ to 10 GeV/$c^2$, compared with previous best results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11930v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/rtnh-jn8s</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Minzhen Zhang, Zihao Bo, Wei Chen, Xun Chen, Yunhua Chen, Chen Cheng, Xiangyi Cui, Manna Deng, Yingjie Fan, Deqing Fang, Xuanye Fu, Zhixing Gao, Yujie Ge, Lisheng Geng, Karl Giboni, Xunan Guo, Xuyuan Guo, Zichao Guo, Chencheng Han, Ke Han, Changda He, Jinrong He, Houqi Huang, Junting Huang, Yule Huang, Ruquan Hou, Xiangdong Ji, Yonglin Ju, Xiaorun Lan, Chenxiang Li, Jiafu Li, Mingchuan Li, Peiyuan Li, Shuaijie Li, Tao Li, Yangdong Li, Zhiyuan Li, Qing Lin, Jianglai Liu, Yuanchun Liu, Congcong Lu, Xiaoying Lu, Lingyin Luo, Yunyang Luo, Yugang Ma, Yajun Mao, Yue Meng, Binyu Pang, Ningchun Qi, Zhicheng Qian, Xiangxiang Ren, Dong Shan, Xiaofeng Shang, Xiyuan Shao, Guofang Shen, Manbin Shen, Wenliang Sun, Xuyan Sun, Yi Tao, Yueqiang Tian, Yuxin Tian, Anqing Wang, Guanbo Wang, Hao Wang, Haoyu Wang, Jiamin Wang, Lei Wang, Meng Wang, Qiuhong Wang, Shaobo Wang, Shibo Wang, Siguang Wang, Wei Wang, Xu Wang, Zhou Wang, Yuehuan Wei, Weihao Wu, Yuan Wu, Mengjiao Xiao, Xiang Xiao, Kaizhi Xiong, Jianqin Xu, Yifan Xu, Shunyu Yao, Binbin Yan, Xiyu Yan, Yong Yang, Peihua Ye, Chunxu Yu, Ying Yuan, Zhe Yuan, Youhui Yun, Xinning Zeng, Peng Zhang, Shibo Zhang, Siyuan Zhang, Shu Zhang, Tao Zhang, Wei Zhang, Yang Zhang, Yingxin Zhang, Yuanyuan Zhang, Li Zhao, Kangkang Zhao, Jifang Zhou, Jiaxu Zhou, Jiayi Zhou, Ning Zhou, Xiaopeng Zhou, Zhizhen Zhou, Chenhui Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of a Reflecting Material on a Search for Neutron--Antineutron Oscillations using Ultracold Neutrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17725v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate neutron--antineutron oscillations of ultracold neutrons in a storage bottle represented by a one-dimensional potential. The experimental sensitivity is determined by the annihilation rate of antineutrons. Its dependence on the antineutron reflectivity and the relative phase shift between the neutron and the antineutron wavefunctions by a reflection from the wall is derived. Optimization of the antineutron pseudopotential was found crucial to maximize the sensitivity of the experiment. Furthermore, methods are discussed for determining the antineutron pseudopotential, which has only been studied indirectly thus far.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17725v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyuki Fujioka, Takashi Higuchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification of tau leptons using a convolutional neural network with domain adaptation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05468v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A tau lepton identification algorithm, DeepTau, based on convolutional neural network techniques, has been developed in the CMS experiment to discriminate reconstructed hadronic decays of tau leptons ($\tau_\mathrm{h}$) from quark or gluon jets and electrons and muons that are misreconstructed as $\tau_\mathrm{h}$ candidates. The latest version of this algorithm, v2.5, includes domain adaptation by backpropagation, a technique that reduces discrepancies between collision data and simulation in the region with the highest purity of genuine $\tau_\mathrm{h}$ candidates. Additionally, a refined training workflow improves classification performance with respect to the previous version of the algorithm, with a reduction of 30$-$50% in the probability for quark and gluon jets to be misidentified as $\tau_\mathrm{h}$ candidates for given reconstruction and identification efficiencies. This paper presents the novel improvements introduced in the DeepTau algorithm and evaluates its performance in LHC proton-proton collision data at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 and 13.6 TeV collected in 2018 and 2022 with integrated luminosities of 60 and 35 fb$^{-1}$, respectively. Techniques to calibrate the performance of the $\tau_\mathrm{h}$ identification algorithm in simulation with respect to its measured performance in real data are presented, together with a subset of results among those measured for use in CMS physics analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05468v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1748-0221/20/12/P12032</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JINST 20 (2025) P12032</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> CMS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven core collapse supernova multilateration with first neutrino events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11984v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A Galactic core-collapse supernova (CCSN) is likely to be observed in neutrino detectors around the world minutes to hours before the electromagnetic radiation arrives. The SNEWS2.0 network of neutrino and dark matter detectors aims to use the relative arrival times of the neutrinos at the different experiments to point back to the supernova so as to facilitate follow-up observation. One of the simplest methods to estimate the CCSN direction is to use the first neutrino events detected through the inverse beta decay (IBD) process, $\overline{\nu}_e p\rightarrow e^+n$. We will consider neutrino detectors sensitive to IBD interactions with low backgrounds. The difference in signal arrival times between a large and a small detector will be biased, however, with the first event at the smaller detector, on average, arriving later than that at the larger detector. This bias can be mitigated by using these first events in a data-driven approach without recourse to simulations or models. The resulting method requires, at minimum, only the times of the first events at most detectors, along with a longer time series of events from one larger detector to act as a reference lightcurve. In this article, we demonstrate this method and its uncertainty estimate using pairs of detectors of different sizes and with different supernova distances. Finally, we use this method to calculate probability skymaps using four detectors currently in operation (Super-Kamiokande, JUNO, LVD, and SNO+) and show that the calculated probabilities yield appropriate confidence intervals for all supernova directions. The area of the 68\% confidence interval varies by distance and direction, but is expected to be a few thousand square degrees. The resulting skymaps should be useful for the multi-messenger community as a rapid, initial pointing to follow up on the SNEWS2.0 Galactic CCSN neutrino alert.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11984v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farrukh Azfar, Jeff Tseng, Marta Colomer Molla, Kate Scholberg, Alec Habig, Segev BenZvi, Melih Kara, James Kneller, Jost Migenda, Dan Milisavljevic, Evan O'Connor</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
