<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 03:49:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The ANUBIS detector and its sensitivity to neutral long-lived particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Long-lived particles (LLPs), i.e., particles with macroscopic lifetimes $\tau&gt;10$~ns, appear in various extensions of the Standard Model (SM) that address fundamental questions like the particulate nature of dark matter or baryogenesis. The ANUBIS detector will achieve unprecedented sensitivity to such models compared to existing and approved experiments by instrumenting a large decay volume adjacent to the ATLAS experiment at the High-Luminosity LHC with tracking detectors. This paper outlines the proposed detector layouts for ANUBIS, explores their physics potential with a scalar LLP model, and identifies the preferred layout, comparing it to other experiments. The potential background contributions to ANUBIS are estimated using a data-driven method, and the topology of potential background events is studied using Monte Carlo simulations. Overall, ANUBIS is expected to probe branching ratios down to $\mathcal{O}$(10$^{-6})$ for exotic decays of the Higgs boson to scalar long-lived particles with masses of 10, 15, 40, and 60 GeV and proper lifetimes of $c\tau=2.4,\, 3.0,\, 12$, and 18 m, respectively. Moreover, for branching ratios of 0.1\% of the Higgs boson into long-lived scalars with a mass of 15 GeV, ANUBIS can probe a $c\tau$ range between $1.1\times10^{-1}$~m and $4.0\times10^3$~m.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26932v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ANUBIS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of the radiative decay $D_s (2317)^+ \to D_s^* \gamma$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We observe the radiative decay $D^{*}_{s0}(2317)^{+} \to D_{s}^{*+} \gamma$ for the first time, with a significance exceeding $10$ standard deviations. The signal is found in the continuum $e^+ e^- \to c\bar{c}$ process with the combined data samples of 980.4~$\rm fb^{-1}$ and 427.9~$\rm fb^{-1}$ collected by the Belle and Belle~II detectors operating at the KEKB and SuperKEKB asymmetric-energy $e^+e^-$ colliders, respectively. The branching fraction ratio ${\cal B}(D^{*}_{s0}(2317)^{+} \to D_{s}^{*+} \gamma)/{\cal B}(D^{*}_{s0}(2317)^{+} \to D_{s}^{+} \pi^{0})$ is measured to be $[7.14 \pm 0.70({\rm stat.}) \pm 0.23({\rm syst.})]\%$. This result provides significant new experimental input for the determination of the quark structure of the $D^{*}_{s0}(2317)^{+}$, which remains unknown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27174v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Belle II Collaboration, M. Abumusabh, I. Adachi, L. Aggarwal, H. Ahmed, Y. Ahn, H. Aihara, N. Akopov, S. Alghamdi, M. Alhakami, A. Aloisio, N. Althubiti, K. Amos, N. Anh Ky, C. Antonioli, D. M. Asner, H. Atmacan, T. Aushev, R. Ayad, V. Babu, N. K. Baghel, S. Bahinipati, P. Bambade, Sw. Banerjee, M. Barrett, M. Bartl, J. Baudot, A. Beaubien, J. Becker, J. V. Bennett, F. U. Bernlochner, V. Bertacchi, M. Bertemes, E. Bertholet, M. Bessner, S. Bettarini, F. Bianchi, T. Bilka, D. Biswas, A. Bobrov, D. Bodrov, A. Bondar, G. Bonvicini, J. Borah, A. Boschetti, A. Bozek, M. Bra\v{c}ko, P. Branchini, R. A. Briere, T. E. Browder, A. Budano, S. Bussino, Q. Campagna, M. Campajola, G. Casarosa, C. Cecchi, P. Chang, P. Cheema, L. Chen, B. G. Cheon, C. Cheshta, H. Chetri, K. Chilikin, K. Chirapatpimol, H. -E. Cho, K. Cho, S. -J. Cho, S. -K. Choi, S. Choudhury, S. Chutia, J. A. Colorado-Caicedo, I. Consigny, L. Corona, J. X. Cui, E. De La Cruz-Burelo, S. A. De La Motte, G. De Nardo, G. De Pietro, R. de Sangro, M. Destefanis, S. Dey, A. Di Canto, Z. Dole\v{z}al, I. Dom\'inguez Jim\'enez, T. V. Dong, X. Dong, M. Dorigo, G. Dujany, P. Ecker, J. Eppelt, R. Farkas, P. Feichtinger, T. Ferber, T. Fillinger, C. Finck, G. Finocchiaro, F. Forti, B. G. Fulsom, A. Gabrielli, E. Ganiev, M. Garcia-Hernandez, R. Garg, G. Gaudino, V. Gaur, V. Gautam, A. Gaz, A. Gellrich, G. Ghevondyan, D. Ghosh, H. Ghumaryan, R. Giordano, A. Giri, P. Gironella Gironell, A. Glazov, B. Gobbo, R. Godang, O. Gogota, P. Goldenzweig, W. Gradl, E. Graziani, D. Greenwald, K. Gudkova, I. Haide, Y. Han, H. Hayashii, S. Hazra, C. Hearty, M. T. Hedges, G. Heine, I. Heredia de la Cruz, T. Higuchi, M. Hoek, M. Hohmann, R. Hoppe, P. Horak, X. T. Hou, C. -L. Hsu, A. Huang, T. Humair, T. Iijima, N. Ipsita, A. Ishikawa, R. Itoh, M. Iwasaki, D. Jacobi, W. W. Jacobs, E. -J. Jang, Q. P. Ji, S. Jia, Y. Jin, A. Johnson, J. Kandra, K. H. Kang, S. Kang, G. Karyan, F. Keil, C. Kiesling, D. Y. Kim, J. -Y. Kim, K. -H. Kim, H. Kindo, K. Kinoshita, P. Kody\v{s}, T. Koga, S. Kohani, A. Korobov, S. Korpar, E. Kovalenko, R. Kowalewski, P. Kri\v{z}an, P. Krokovny, T. Kuhr, D. Kumar, K. Kumara, T. Kunigo, A. Kuzmin, Y. -J. Kwon, S. Lacaprara, T. Lam, J. S. Lange, T. S. Lau, M. Laurenza, R. Leboucher, F. R. Le Diberder, H. Lee, M. J. Lee, C. Lemettais, P. Leo, P. M. Lewis, C. Li, H. -J. Li, L. K. Li, Q. M. Li, S. X. Li, W. Z. Li, Y. Li, Y. B. Li, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, J. Lin, V. Lisovskyi, M. H. Liu, Q. Y. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, D. Liventsev, S. Longo, A. Lozar, T. Lueck, C. Lyu, J. L. Ma, Y. Ma, M. Maggiora, S. P. Maharana, R. Maiti, G. Mancinelli, R. Manfredi, M. Mantovano, D. Marcantonio, M. Marfoli, C. Marinas, C. Martellini, A. Martens, T. Martinov, L. Massaccesi, M. Masuda, D. Matvienko, M. Maushart, J. A. McKenna, Z. Mediankin Gruberov\'a, R. Mehta, F. Meier, D. Meleshko, M. Merola, C. Miller, M. Mirra, H. Miyake, R. Mizuk, G. B. Mohanty, S. Moneta, H. -G. Moser, I. Nakamura, M. Nakao, M. Naruki, Z. Natkaniec, A. Natochii, M. Nayak, S. Nishida, R. Nomaru, S. Ogawa, H. Ono, F. Otani, G. Pakhlova, A. Panta, S. Pardi, K. Parham, J. Park, S. -H. Park, A. Passeri, S. Patra, S. Paul, T. K. Pedlar, R. Pestotnik, M. Piccolo, L. E. Piilonen, P. L. M. Podesta-Lerma, T. Podobnik, C. Praz, S. Prell, M. T. Prim, S. Privalov, H. Purwar, P. Rados, S. Raiz, K. Ravindran, J. U. Rehman, M. Reif, S. Reiter, L. Reuter, D. Ricalde Herrmann, I. Ripp-Baudot, G. Rizzo, S. H. Robertson, J. M. Roney, A. Rostomyan, S. Saha, L. Salutari, D. A. Sanders, L. Santelj, C. Santos, V. Savinov, B. Scavino, S. Schneider, K. Schoenning, C. Schwanda, Y. Seino, K. Senyo, J. Serrano, C. Sfienti, W. Shan, G. Sharma, C. P. Shen, X. D. Shi, T. Shillington, J. -G. Shiu, D. Shtol, B. Shwartz, A. Sibidanov, F. Simon, J. Skorupa, R. J. Sobie, M. Sobotzik, A. Soffer, A. Sokolov, E. Solovieva, S. Spataro, K. \v{S}penko, B. Spruck, M. Stari\v{c}, P. Stavroulakis, R. Stroili, M. Sumihama, S. S. Tang, K. Tanida, F. Tenchini, F. Testa, A. Thaller, T. Tien Manh, O. Tittel, R. Tiwary, E. Torassa, K. Trabelsi, F. F. Trantou, I. Ueda, K. Unger, Y. Unno, K. Uno, S. Uno, P. Urquijo, Y. Ushiroda, S. E. Vahsen, R. van Tonder, K. E. Varvell, M. Veronesi, V. S. Vismaya, L. Vitale, V. Vobbilisetti, R. Volpe, M. Wakai, S. Wallner, M. -Z. Wang, A. Warburton, M. Watanabe, S. Watanuki, C. Wessel, E. Won, X. P. Xu, B. D. Yabsley, W. Yan, J. Yelton, K. Yi, J. H. Yin, K. Yoshihara, J. Yuan, Y. Yusa, L. Zani, M. Zeyrek, J. S. Zhou, Q. D. Zhou, L. Zhu, R. \v{Z}leb\v{c}\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of Central Exclusive Production of $\pi^+\pi^-$, $K^+K^-$ and $p \bar{p}$ Pairs in Proton-Proton Collisions at $\sqrt{s} = 510$ GeV with the STAR Detector at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on the first measurement of the Central Exclusive Production (CEP) process in proton-proton (pp) collisions:, $pp \ \rightarrow \ p h^+ h^- p$ (where $h = \pi, K, p$) at the center-of-mass energy $\sqrt{s} = 510$ GeV with the STAR experiment at RHIC. At this energy, the process is dominated by a double I$\!$Pomeron exchange mechanism. Hence, it provides a clean environment for investigating I$\!$Pomeron interactions by measuring fully reconstructed final states involving only two hadrons and two forward scattered protons. The oppositely charged hadron pairs are measured within the central detector of STAR. The forward scattered protons are measured in the Roman Pot system allowing the verification of the event's exclusivity. Differential fiducial cross sections within the STAR acceptance are presented as a function of the difference in the azimuthal angle between the outgoing protons. The invariant masses of the charged hadron pairs are measured up to approximately 3 GeV and the square of the four-momentum transfer ($t_1$ and $t_2$) of the two forward-scattered protons in the range $0.3 \text{ GeV}^2 &lt; -t_1 , -t_2 &lt; 1.6 \text{ GeV}^2$. The differential fiducial cross sections of the forward protons as a function of the $|t_1 + t_2|$ are also presented. All results for the $\pi^+\pi^-$ pair are presented in three mass ranges. A comparison with GRANIITTI Monte Carlo predictions are also presented, where the spectra include continuum and resonant contributions. The observed spectra are consistent with double I$\!$Pomeron exchange, including resonances seen in previous studies, while the $f_0(980)$ resonance is reported here for the first time in the $K^+K^-$ decay channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27482v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomas Truhlar (for the STAR Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated event generation for S-wave quarkonium and leptonium production in NRQCD and NRQED</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26773v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an extension of the MadGraph5_aMC@NLO framework that enables the automated calculation of leading-order cross sections for S-wave quarkonium and leptonium production within the non-relativistic QCD (NRQCD) and non-relativistic QED (NRQED) factorisation formalisms. The framework has been validated against a variety of benchmark processes, demonstrating robustness and flexibility for phenomenological studies. A key advantage of this implementation is its seamless integration with existing MadGraph5_aMC@NLO features, allowing computations not only within the Standard Model but also in a wide range of Beyond the Standard Model or Effective Field Theory scenarios via a modified Universal Feynman Output (UFO) interface. Furthermore, the framework maintains compatibility with standard Monte Carlo event generators for parton showering and hadronisation. Through numerous examples, we highlight that theoretical studies of quarkonium processes require careful consideration: the impact of subleading contributions is often difficult to predict using simple counting arguments based solely on the hierarchy of couplings and velocity-scaling rules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26773v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice Colpani Serri, Chris A. Flett, Jean-Philippe Lansberg, Olivier Mattelaer, Hua-Sheng Shao, Lukas Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved calculation of radiative corrections to $\boldsymbol{\tau\to\pi\pi\nu_\tau}$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A reliable calculation of radiative corrections to $\tau\to\pi\pi\nu_\tau$ decays is an important prerequisite for using hadronic $\tau$ decays for a data-driven evaluation of the hadronic-vacuum-polarization contribution to the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon, $a_\mu^\text{HVP, LO}[\pi\pi,\tau]$. In this Letter, we present an improved model-independent analysis of these radiative corrections, including, for the first time, effects beyond point-like pions in the evaluation of the loop diagrams. These structure-dependent corrections, implemented via a dispersive representation of the pion form factor, lead to significant changes compared to previous calculations due to enhancements near the $\rho(770)$ resonance. We also devise strategies for the matching to chiral perturbation theory and a stable implementation of the real corrections down to the two-pion threshold, which shows that some higher-order isospin-breaking corrections need to be kept due to a strong threshold enhancement. Finally, we perform dispersive fits to the currently available $\tau\to\pi\pi\nu_\tau$ spectra and discuss the consequences for isospin-breaking corrections in the evaluation of $a_\mu^\text{HVP, LO}[\pi\pi,\tau]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26871v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gilberto Colangelo, Martina Cottini, Martin Hoferichter, Simon Holz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryon anti-Baryon Photoproduction Cross Sections off the Proton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26890v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The GlueX experiment at Jefferson Lab has observed $p\bar{p}$ and, for the first time, $\Lambda\bar{\Lambda}$ and $p\bar{\Lambda}$ photoproduction from a proton target at photon energies up to 11.6 GeV. The angular distributions are forward peaked for all produced pairs, consistent with Regge-like $t$-channel exchange. Asymmetric wide-angle anti-baryon distributions show the presence of additional processes. In a phenomenological model, we find consistency with a double $t$-channel exchange process where anti-baryons are created only at the middle vertex. The model matches all observed distributions with a small number of free parameters. In the hyperon channels, we observe a clear distinction between photoproduction of the $\Lambda\bar{\Lambda}$ and $p\bar{\Lambda}$ systems but general similarity to the $p\bar{p}$ system. We report both total cross sections and cross sections differential with respect to momentum transfer and the invariant masses of the created particle pairs. No narrow resonant structures were found in these reaction channels. The suppression of $s\bar{s}$ quark pairs relative to $d\bar{d}$ quark pairs is similar to what has been seen in other reactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26890v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Afzal, M. Albrecht, M. Amaryan, S. Arrigo, V. Arroyave, A. Asaturyan, A. Austregesilo, Z. Baldwin, F. Barbosa, J. Barlow, E. Barriga, R. Barsotti, D. Barton, V. Baturin, V. V. Berdnikov, A. Berger, W. Boeglin, M. Boer, W. J. Briscoe, T. Britton, R. Brunner, S. Cao, C. Chen, E. Chudakov, G. Chung, P. L. Cole, O. Cortes, V. Crede, M. M. Dalton, D. Darulis, A. Deur, L. Dietrich, S. Dobbs, A. Dolgolenko, M. Dugger, R. Dzhygadlo, D. Ebersole, M. Edo, H. Egiyan, P. Eugenio, A. Fabrizi, C. Fanelli, S. Fang, M. Fritsch, S. Furletov, L. Gan, H. Gao, A. Gardner, A. Gasparian, D. I. Glazier, C. Gleason, B. Grube, J. Guo, J. Hernandez, K. Hernandez, N. Herrmann, N. D. Hoffman, D. Hornidge, G. M. Huber, P. Hurck, W. Imoehl, D. G. Ireland, M. M. Ito, I. Jaegle, N. S. Jarvis, T. Jeske, M. Jing, R. T. Jones, V. Kakoyan, G. Kalicy, X. Kang, V. Khachatryan, C. Kourkoumelis, A. LaDuke, I. Larin, D. Lawrence, D. I. Lersch, H. Li, B. Liu, K. Livingston, L. Lorenti, V. Lyubovitskij, H. Marukyan, V. Matveev, M. McCaughan, M. McCracken, C. A. Meyer, R. Miskimen, R. E. Mitchell, P. Moran, L. Ng, E. Nissen, S. Ore\v{s}i\'c, A. I. Ostrovidov, Z. Papandreou, L. Pentchev, K. J. Peters, L. Puthiya Veetil, S. Rakshit, J. Reinhold, A. Remington, J. Ritman, G. Rodriguez, K. Saldana, S. Schadmand, A. M. Schertz, K. Scheuer, A. Schmidt, R. A. Schumacher, J. Schwiening, M. Scott, N. Septian, P. Sharp, V. J. Shen, X. Shen, M. R. Shepherd, J. Sikes, H. Singh, A. Smith, E. S. Smith, A. Somov, S. Somov, J. R. Stevens, I. I. Strakovsky, B. Sumner, K. Suresh, V. V. Tarasov, S. Taylor, A. Teymurazyan, A. Thiel, M. Thomson, T. Viducic, T. Whitlatch, Y. Wunderlich, B. Yu, J. Zarling, Z. Zhang, X. Zhou, B. Zihlmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic tomography of spin-$\frac{3}{2}$ hidden-charm strange pentaquarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26893v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding how quarks are spatially arranged inside exotic pentaquarks remains one of the key open problems in contemporary hadron spectroscopy. The electromagnetic multipole moments of hadrons provide a direct probe of their internal quark--gluon geometry and spatial charge distributions. Motivated by this, we employ QCD light-cone sum rules to compute the magnetic dipole, electric quadrupole, and magnetic octupole moments of the $J^P = 3/2^-$ pentaquark with strangeness $S = -1$. Five distinct diquark--diquark--antiquark interpolating currents are constructed to explore possible internal configurations. The resulting electromagnetic moments exhibit pronounced sensitivity to the underlying quark arrangement: magnetic dipole moments range from $-2.28\mu_N$ to $+3.36\mu_N$, establishing this observable as a key discriminator among configurations with identical quantum numbers. Nonzero electric quadrupole and magnetic octupole moments indicate clear deviations from spherical symmetry, while a detailed decomposition shows that light quarks dominate the magnetic response and the charm quark drives quadrupole deformation. These findings position electromagnetic multipole moments as quantitative and discriminating probes of exotic hadron structure, providing concrete benchmarks for forthcoming LHCb, Belle~II, and lattice QCD studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26893v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ula\c{s} \"Ozdem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Calculation of Light Meson Radiative Leptonic Decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26993v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we perform a lattice QCD calculation of the branching ratios and the form factors of radiative leptonic decays $P \to \ell \nu_\ell \gamma$ ($P = \pi, K$) using $N_f=2+1$ domain wall fermion ensembles generated by the RBC and UKQCD collaborations at the physical pion mass. We adopt the infinite volume reconstruction (IVR) method, which extends lattice data to infinite volume and effectively controls the finite volume effects. This study represents a first step toward a complete calculation of radiative corrections to leptonic decays using the IVR method, including both real photon emissions and virtual photon loops. For decays involving a final state electron, collinear radiative corrections, enhanced by the large logarithmic factors such as $\ln(m_\pi^2/m_e^2)$ and $\ln(m_K^2/m_e^2)$, can reach the level of $O(10\%)$ and are essential at the current level of theoretical and experimental precision. After including these corrections, our result for $\pi \to e\nu_e\gamma$ agrees with the PIBETA measurement; for \(K \to e\nu_e\gamma\), our results are consistent with the KLOE data and exhibit a $1.7\sigma$ tension with E36; and for $K \to \mu\nu_\mu\gamma$, where radiative corrections are negligible, our results confirm the previously observed discrepancies between lattice results and the ISTRA/OKA measurements at large photon energies, and with the E787 results at large muon photon angles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26993v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norman H. Christ, Xu Feng, Taku Izubuchi, Luchang Jin, Christopher T. Sachrajda, Xin-Yu Tuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon veto system for the CROSS double-beta decay search experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In preparation to the CROSS experiment at the Canfranc underground laboratory (Spain) $-$ aiming to search for neutrinoless double-beta ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decay of $^{100}$Mo using low-temperature detectors with heat-scintillation readout $-$ we report on development of a dedicated muon veto system. The need for the muon veto in CROSS is caused by a comparatively high residual cosmic muon flux at the experimental site ($\sim$20 $\mu$/m$^2$/h), being a dominant background in the region of interest (ROI) at $\sim$3 MeV. Thus, we installed the muon veto system around the CROSS low-background setup, forming four lateral, one top, and four bottom sectors. In this paper we describe the design, construction and operation of the CROSS muon veto system, as well as its optimization and validation by comparing dedicated Monte Carlo (MC) simulations of muons with low-temperature measurements in the setup. We demonstrate a stable operation of the veto system with the average trigger rates compatible with MC simulations. Also, we investigated two muon trigger logics based on coincidences with either 2 sectors or a single sector of the veto. The MC study shows that, in combination with the multiplicity cut of thermal detectors, these trigger logics allow to reject 99.2\% and 99.7\% of muon-induced events in the ROI, respectively. Despite a comparatively high dead time ($\sim$18\%) introduced by coincidences with any of nine sectors of the veto $-$ the adopted strategy $-$ the muon-induced background in the ROI of the CROSS experiment can be reduced down to $\sim$2 $\times 10^{-3}$ cnts/keV/kg/yr, i.e., an acceptable level compatible with a high-sensitivity $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay search foreseen in CROSS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27406v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. S. Barabash, L. Berg\'e, M. Buchynska, J. M. Calvo-Mozota, A. Candela, P. Carniti, M. Chapellier, D. Cintas, A. Corsi, I. Dafinei, F. A. Danevich, M. De Deo, L. Dumoulin, F. Ferri, A. Giuliani, C. Gotti, P. Gras, A. Ianni, V. V. Kobychev, S. I. Konovalov, P. Loaiza, P. de Marcillac, S. Marnieros, C. A. Marrache-Kikuchi, M. Martinez, C. Nones, E. Olivieri, A. Ortiz de Sol\'orzano, V. Perez, G. Pessina, D. V. Poda, B. Romualdi, Ph. Rosier, R. Serino, V. I. Tretyak, V. I. Umatov, G. Ursini, M. M. Zarytskyy, A. Zolotarova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved phenomenology of $\pi N$ transition distribution amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27425v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To study cross sections and polarization asymmetries for the processes $e p \to e n \pi^+$ and $e p \to e p \pi^0$ in the backward region, we develop a flexible phenomenological model for nucleon-to-pion transition distribution amplitudes ($\pi N$ TDAs), which are used in the QCD collinear factorization description of the scattering amplitudes. Our model is based on the two-component factorized Ansatz for the corresponding spectral densities, quadruple distribution. It takes into account the constraints for $\pi N$ TDAs arising from the threshold pion production theorem and also includes a forward limit contribution that can be fitted to experimental data. We examine the sensitivity of observable predictions to various modelling assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27425v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernard Pire, Kirill Semenov-Tian-Shansky, Pawe{\l} Sznajder, Lech Szymanowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-independent determination of nuclear charge radii from Li-like ions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that recent advances in QED theory of Li-like ions [V. A. Yerokhin et al., Phys. Rev. A 112, 042801 (2025)] enable determinations of absolute nuclear charge radii for heavy elements. By incorporating constraints derived from electron-scattering data, we obtain radii that are independent of the assumed model of the nuclear charge distribution. Our approach is validated for $^{208}$Pb, a well-studied spherical nucleus, and is then applied to $^{209}$Bi, where low-lying nuclear excitations complicate the interpretation of muonic-atom data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27427v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Yerokhin, B. Ohayon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the Lund plane for light- and beauty-quark jets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23530v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The substructure of jets in quantum chromodynamics (QCD) has garnered significant attention with the advent of infrared- and collinear-safe clustering algorithms and observables. A key question emerging from these studies is how in-jet emissions at soft and hard energy scales, across collinear and wide angles relative to the emitter, differ with the mass of the emitting parton. The Lund jet plane (LJP) is a perturbatively well-defined substructure observable that maps the radiation pattern of jets onto a plane, visually distinguishing emissions with different kinematic properties. Comparing LJP for jets containing hadrons of low versus high mass enables the testing of QCD splitting functions from first-principles calculations across both soft and hard regimes and at different radiation angles. This article presents the first measurement of the LJP for light-quark-enriched and beauty-initiated jets at center-of-mass energy of 13\tev at LHCb. This marks the first direct observation of the dead-cone effect in beauty-quark jets, measured in the collinear region of the LJP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23530v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/r16d-b4my</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D112 (2025) 072015</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, A. A. Adefisoye, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, A. Anelli, D. Ao, F. Archilli, Z Areg, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, R. Ata\'ide Da Silva, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, J. A. Authier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, A. Balboni, W. Baldini, L. Balzani, H. Bao, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, C. Barbero Pretel, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, M. Barnyakov, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, J. Bartz, S. Bashir, B. Batsukh, P. B. Battista, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, N. A. Behling, S. Belin, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, O. Bezshyyko, J. Bhom, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, R. B. Bonacci, N. Bondar, A. Bordelius, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, E. Bottalico, S. A. Bouchiba, M. Bovill, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, J. D. Brandenburg, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, E. Buchanan, L. Buonincontri, M. Burgos Marcos, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, Y. Cai, A. Caillet, R. Calabrese, S. Calderon Ramirez, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, P. Camargo Magalhaes, J. I. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, H. Chang, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, E. Chatzianagnostou, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, J. Chen, S. Chen, Z. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, X. Chiotopoulos, V. Chobanova, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, S. Collaviti, P. Collins, T. Colombo, M. Colonna, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, C. Coronel, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, E. Curras Rivera, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, P. d'Argent, G. Darze, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, F. De Benedetti, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, S. Dekkers, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, Y. Ding, L. Dittmann, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, A. D. Dowling, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, O. D. Durmus, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, S. Faghih, L. N. Falcao, B. Fang, R. Fantechi, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, A. Fernandez Casani, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, M. Firlej, K. L. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, T. Fiutowski, F. Fleuret, A. Fomin, M. Fontana, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, V. Franco Lima, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, J. Fu, Q. F\"uhring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, B. Ganie, H. Gao, R. Gao, T. Q. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, P. Gardner, K. G. Garg, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, A. Gavrikov, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, S. Ghizzo, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, L. Girardey, M. A. Giza, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, L. Golinka-Bezshyyko, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, S. Gomez Fernandez, W. Gomulka, I. Gon\c{c}ales Vaz, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, E. Govorkova, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, L. Guerry, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, K. Habermann, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, G. Hallett, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, T. H. Harris, M. Hartmann, S. Hashmi, J. He, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, P. Herrero Gascon, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, G. Hijano Mendizabal, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, M. Idzik, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, A. John Rubesh Rajan, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, J. Juan Castella, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, M. Kane, Y. Kang, C. Kar, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, A. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, M. K. Kazanecki, F. Keizer, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, A. Korchin, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, E. Kowalczyk, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, O. Kshyvanskyi, S. Kubis, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, V. Kushnir, B. Kutsenko, I. Kyryllin, D. Lacarrere, P. Laguarta Gonzalez, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, G. Lanfranchi, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, E. Lemos Cid, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, E. D. Lesser, B. Leverington, A. Li, C. Li, C. Li, H. Li, J. Li, K. Li, L. Li, M. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, Q. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, S. Libralon, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, H. Linton, R. Litvinov, D. Liu, F. L. Liu, G. Liu, K. Liu, S. Liu, W. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, G. Loachamin Ordonez, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, T. Long, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, Q. Lu, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, M. Lucio Martinez, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, B. Mack, I. Mackay, L. M. Mackey, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. J. Madurai, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, F. M. Manganella, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, E. Mariani, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, L. Martel, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Gomez, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Martorell i Granollers, A. Massafferri, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, J. Mazorra de Cos, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, F. M. Meng, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, L. Moeser, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, E. F. Molina Cardenas, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, J. Moron, W. Morren, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. Mu\~noz-Rojas, R. Murta, V. Mytrochenko, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, E. Nekrasova, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, Q. Niu, P. Nogarolli, P. Nogga, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, A. Okhotnikov, O. Okhrimenko, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, D. Osthues, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, F. Paciolla, A. Padee, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, C. Pan, X. Pan, S. Panebianco, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, D. Parmar, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, A. Paul, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, J. Peng, X. Peng, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, H. Pereira Da Costa, A. Pereiro Castro, C. Perez, P. Perret, A. Perrevoort, A. Perro, M. J. Peters, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, J. P. Pfaller, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, L. Piccolo, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, R. N. Pilato, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. M. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, T. Poeschl, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, D. Provenzano, V. Pugatch, G. Punzi, S. Qasim, Q. Q. Qian, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, V. Ramos De Oliveira, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, M. Ribalda Galvez, R. Ribatti, G. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, A. Rodriguez Alvarez, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, J. Roensch, A. Rogachev, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, T. Rong, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, J. J. Saavedra-Arias, J. J. Saborido Silva, R. Sadek, N. Sagidova, D. Sahoo, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, A. Sarnatskiy, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, C. Satriano, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, F. Sborzacchi, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, M. H. Schune, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, I. Segal, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, T. Senger, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, B. Sevilla Sanjuan, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, R. S. Sharma, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, Q. Shi, W. S. Shi, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, M. Singha, N. Skidmore, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, N. S. Sommerfeld, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, M. Stefaniak, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, D. Sundfeld, W. Sutcliffe, K. Swientek, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, Y. Tan, Y. Tang, Y. T. Tang, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, A. R. Thomson-Strong, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, T. Tork, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, A. Upadhyay, B. Urbach, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, V. Valcarce Cadenas, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, J. van Eldik, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, G. Vasquez, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Verdoglia, M. Vesterinen, W. Vetens, D. Vico Benet, P. Vidrier Villalba, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, B. Vivacqua, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, C. Vrahas, J. Wagner, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, A. Wang, B. Wang, C. Wang, G. Wang, H. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. W. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, M. Waterlaat, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, J. Wendel, B. D. C. Westhenry, C. White, M. Whitehead, E. Whiter, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. J. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, Z. Williams, F. F. Wilson, M. Winn, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, T. W. Wolf, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, X. Wu, Y. Wu, Z. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, T. X. Xing, A. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, K. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, X. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, Y Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, F. Zenesini, C. Zeng, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, R. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zhelezov, S. Z. Zheng, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, Y. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An independent search for Jovian neutrinos using BOREXINO data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14506v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a recent study, arXiv:2401.13043 found evidence for a 6% flux contribution from Jupiter to the total flux rate time series data from the BOREXINO solar neutrino experiment, specifically during the time intervals 2019-2021 and 2011-2013. The significance of this detection was estimated to be around $2\sigma$. We reanalyze the BOREXINO data and independently confirm the Jovian signal with the same amplitude and significance as that obtained in arXiv:2401.13043. However, using the same technique, we also find a spurious flux contribution from Venus and Saturn (at $\sim 2\sigma$ significance), whereas prima facie one should not expect any signal from any other planet. We then implement Bayesian model comparison to ascertain whether the BOREXINO data contain an additional contribution from Jupiter, Venus or Saturn. We find Bayes factors of less than five for an additional contribution from Jupiter, and less than or close to one for Venus and Saturn. This implies that the evidence for an additional contribution from Jupiter is very marginal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14506v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuva Himanshu Pallam, Shantanu Desai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for an Axion-Like Particle in $B\rightarrow K^{(*)} a (\rightarrow\gamma\gamma)$ Decays at Belle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01249v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report a search for an axion-like particle $a$ in $B\rightarrow K^{(*)} a (\rightarrow\gamma\gamma)$ decays using data collected with the Belle detector at the KEKB asymmetric energy electron-positron collider. The search is based on a $711 \mathrm{fb^{-1}}$ data sample collected at the $\Upsilon 4S$ resonance energy, corresponding to a sample of $772\times10^6$ $\Upsilon 4S$ events. In this study, we search for the decay of the axion-like particle into a pair of photons, $a \rightarrow \gamma\gamma$. We scan the two-photon invariant mass in the range $0.16\ \mathrm{GeV/}c^2-4.50\ \mathrm{GeV}/c^2$ for the $K$ modes and $0.16\ \mathrm{GeV/}c^2-4.20\ \mathrm{GeV}/c^2$ for the $K^{*}$ modes. No significant signal is observed in any of the modes, and 90\% confidence level upper limits are established on the coupling to the $W$ boson, $g_aW$, as a function of $a$ mass. The limits range from $3 \times 10^{-6} \mathrm{GeV}^{-1}$ to $3 \times 10^{-5} \mathrm{GeV}^{-1}$, improving the current constraints on $g_aW$ by a factor of two over the most stringent previous experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01249v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Belle, Belle II Collaborations,  :, I. Adachi, L. Aggarwal, H. Ahmed, Y. Ahn, H. Aihara, N. Akopov, S. Alghamdi, M. Alhakami, A. Aloisio, N. Althubiti, K. Amos, M. Angelsmark, N. Anh Ky, C. Antonioli, D. M. Asner, H. Atmacan, T. Aushev, V. Aushev, M. Aversano, R. Ayad, V. Babu, H. Bae, N. K. Baghel, S. Bahinipati, P. Bambade, Sw. Banerjee, S. Bansal, M. Barrett, M. Bartl, J. Baudot, A. Baur, A. Beaubien, F. Becherer, J. Becker, J. V. Bennett, F. U. Bernlochner, V. Bertacchi, M. Bertemes, E. Bertholet, M. Bessner, S. Bettarini, B. Bhuyan, F. Bianchi, T. Bilka, D. Biswas, A. Bobrov, D. Bodrov, A. Bondar, G. Bonvicini, J. Borah, A. Boschetti, A. Bozek, M. Bra\v{c}ko, P. Branchini, T. E. Browder, A. Budano, S. Bussino, Q. Campagna, M. Campajola, L. Cao, G. Casarosa, C. Cecchi, M. -C. Chang, P. Cheema, L. Chen, B. G. Cheon, K. Chilikin, J. Chin, K. Chirapatpimol, H. -E. Cho, K. Cho, S. -J. Cho, S. -K. Choi, S. Choudhury, J. Cochran, I. Consigny, L. Corona, J. X. Cui, E. De La Cruz-Burelo, S. A. De La Motte, G. De Nardo, G. De Pietro, R. de Sangro, M. Destefanis, S. Dey, A. Di Canto, J. Dingfelder, Z. Dole\v{z}al, I. Dom\'inguez Jim\'enez, T. V. Dong, K. Dugic, G. Dujany, P. Ecker, J. Eppelt, R. Farkas, P. Feichtinger, T. Ferber, T. Fillinger, C. Finck, G. Finocchiaro, A. Fodor, F. Forti, A. Frey, B. G. Fulsom, A. Gabrielli, A. Gale, M. Garcia-Hernandez, R. Garg, G. Gaudino, V. Gaur, V. Gautam, A. Gaz, A. Gellrich, G. Ghevondyan, D. Ghosh, H. Ghumaryan, G. Giakoustidis, R. Giordano, A. Giri, P. Gironella Gironell, B. Gobbo, R. Godang, O. Gogota, P. Goldenzweig, E. Graziani, D. Greenwald, Z. Gruberov\'a, Y. Guan, K. Gudkova, I. Haide, Y. Han, T. Hara, K. Hayasaka, H. Hayashii, S. Hazra, C. Hearty, M. T. Hedges, G. Heine, I. Heredia de la Cruz, M. Hern\'andez Villanueva, T. Higuchi, M. Hoek, M. Hohmann, R. Hoppe, P. Horak, C. -L. Hsu, T. Humair, T. Iijima, K. Inami, N. Ipsita, A. Ishikawa, R. Itoh, M. Iwasaki, P. Jackson, W. W. Jacobs, E. -J. Jang, Q. P. Ji, S. Jia, Y. Jin, A. Johnson, K. K. Joo, H. Junkerkalefeld, J. Kandra, K. H. Kang, G. Karyan, T. Kawasaki, F. Keil, C. Ketter, M. Khan, C. Kiesling, C. Kim, C. -H. Kim, D. Y. Kim, J. -Y. Kim, K. -H. Kim, Y. J. Kim, Y. -K. Kim, H. Kindo, K. Kinoshita, P. Kody\v{s}, T. Koga, S. Kohani, K. Kojima, A. Korobov, S. Korpar, E. Kovalenko, P. Kri\v{z}an, P. Krokovny, T. Kuhr, Y. Kulii, D. Kumar, R. Kumar, K. Kumara, T. Kunigo, A. Kuzmin, Y. -J. Kwon, S. Lacaprara, K. Lalwani, T. Lam, J. S. Lange, T. S. Lau, M. Laurenza, R. Leboucher, F. R. Le Diberder, M. J. Lee, C. Lemettais, P. Leo, P. M. Lewis, C. Li, H. -J. Li, L. K. Li, Q. M. Li, W. Z. Li, Y. Li, Y. B. Li, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, J. Lin, S. Lin, M. H. Liu, Q. Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, D. Liventsev, S. Longo, T. Lueck, C. Lyu, Y. Ma, C. Madaan, M. Maggiora, S. P. Maharana, R. Maiti, G. Mancinelli, R. Manfredi, E. Manoni, M. Mantovano, D. Marcantonio, S. Marcello, C. Marinas, C. Martellini, A. Martens, T. Martinov, L. Massaccesi, M. Masuda, D. Matvienko, S. K. Maurya, M. Maushart, J. A. McKenna, R. Mehta, F. Meier, D. Meleshko, M. Merola, C. Miller, M. Mirra, S. Mitra, K. Miyabayashi, H. Miyake, R. Mizuk, G. B. Mohanty, S. Mondal, S. Moneta, A. L. Moreira de Carvalho, H. -G. Moser, R. Mussa, I. Nakamura, M. Nakao, Y. Nakazawa, M. Naruki, Z. Natkaniec, A. Natochii, M. Nayak, M. Neu, M. Niiyama, S. Nishida, S. Ogawa, H. Ono, G. Pakhlova, S. Pardi, K. Parham, H. Park, J. Park, K. Park, S. -H. Park, B. Paschen, A. Passeri, S. Patra, S. Paul, T. K. Pedlar, I. Peruzzi, R. Peschke, R. Pestotnik, M. Piccolo, L. E. Piilonen, P. L. M. Podesta-Lerma, T. Podobnik, S. Pokharel, A. Prakash, C. Praz, S. Prell, E. Prencipe, M. T. Prim, S. Privalov, H. Purwar, P. Rados, G. Raeuber, S. Raiz, K. Ravindran, J. U. Rehman, M. Reif, S. Reiter, M. Remnev, L. Reuter, D. Ricalde Herrmann, I. Ripp-Baudot, G. Rizzo, S. H. Robertson, J. M. Roney, A. Rostomyan, N. Rout, L. Salutari, D. A. Sanders, S. Sandilya, L. Santelj, V. Savinov, B. Scavino, J. Schmitz, S. Schneider, G. Schnell, M. Schnepf, C. Schwanda, Y. Seino, A. Selce, K. Senyo, J. Serrano, M. E. Sevior, C. Sfienti, W. Shan, G. Sharma, C. P. Shen, X. D. Shi, T. Shillington, T. Shimasaki, J. -G. Shiu, D. Shtol, A. Sibidanov, F. Simon, J. B. Singh, J. Skorupa, M. Sobotzik, A. Soffer, A. Sokolov, E. Solovieva, S. Spataro, B. Spruck, M. Stari\v{c}, P. Stavroulakis, S. Stefkova, R. Stroili, Y. Sue, M. Sumihama, K. Sumisawa, N. Suwonjandee, H. Svidras, M. Takizawa, U. Tamponi, K. Tanida, F. Tenchini, F. Testa, A. Thaller, O. Tittel, R. Tiwary, E. Torassa, K. Trabelsi, F. F. Trantou, I. Tsaklidis, I. Ueda, T. Uglov, K. Unger, Y. Unno, K. Uno, S. Uno, P. Urquijo, Y. Ushiroda, S. E. Vahsen, R. van Tonder, K. E. Varvell, M. Veronesi, A. Vinokurova, V. S. Vismaya, L. Vitale, V. Vobbilisetti, R. Volpe, A. Vossen, E. Waheed, M. Wakai, S. Wallner, M. -Z. Wang, A. Warburton, S. Watanuki, C. Wessel, E. Won, X. P. Xu, B. D. Yabsley, S. Yamada, W. Yan, W. C. Yan, S. B. Yang, J. Yelton, K. Yi, J. H. Yin, K. Yoshihara, C. Z. Yuan, J. Yuan, L. Zani, F. Zeng, M. Zeyrek, B. Zhang, V. Zhilich, J. S. Zhou, Q. D. Zhou, L. Zhu, R. \v{Z}leb\v{c}\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next-to-Next-to-Leading Order QCD Corrections to Polarized Semi-Inclusive Deep-Inelastic Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09959v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Polarized semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering (SIDIS) is a key process in the quest for a resolution of the proton spin puzzle. We present the complete results for the polarized SIDIS process at next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) in perturbative quantum chromodynamics. Our analytical results include all partonic channels for the scattering of polarized leptons off hadrons and a spin-averaged hadron identified in the final state. A numerical analysis of the NNLO corrections illustrates their significance and the reduced residual scale dependence in the kinematic range probed by the future Electron-Ion-Collider EIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09959v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.211905</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 211905 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saurav Goyal, Roman N. Lee, Sven-Olaf Moch, Vaibhav Pathak, Narayan Rana, V. Ravindran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NNLO QCD corrections to unpolarized and polarized SIDIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19309v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering (SIDIS) process requires the presence of an identified hadron H$'$ in the final state, which arises from the scattering of a lepton with an initial hadron P. By employing factorization in quantum chromodynamics (QCD), SIDIS provides essential knowledge on the hadron structure, enabling the exploration of parton distribution functions (PDFs) and fragmentation functions (FFs). The coefficient functions for SIDIS can be calculated in perturbative QCD and are currently known to the next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) for the cases, where the incoming lepton and the hadron P are either both polarized or unpolarized. We present a detailed description of these NNLO computations, including a thorough discussion of all the partonic channels, the calculation of the amplitudes and master integrals for the phase-space integration as well as the renormalization of ultraviolet divergences and mass factorization of infrared divergences in dimensional regularization through NNLO. We provide an extensive phenomenological analysis of the effects of NNLO corrections on SIDIS cross sections for different PDFs and FFs and various kinematics, including those of the future Electron-Ion Collider (EIC). We find that these corrections are not only significant but also crucial for reducing the dependence on the renormalization and factorization scales $\mu_R$ and $\mu_F$ to obtain stable predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19309v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.094007</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 111 (2025) 9, 094007</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saurav Goyal, Roman N. Lee, Sven-Olaf Moch, Vaibhav Pathak, Narayan Rana, V. Ravindran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Precision Physics Experiments at Huizhou Large-Scale Scientific Facilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21050v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In response to the capabilities presented by the High-Intensity Heavy Ion Accelerator Facility (HIAF) and the Accelerator-Driven Subcritical System (CiADS), as well as the proposed Chinese Advanced Nuclear Physics Research Facility (CNUF), we are assembling a consortium of experts in relevant discipline--both domestically and internationally--to delineate high-precision physics experiments that leverage the state-of-the-art research environment afforded by CNUF. Our focus encompasses six primary domains of inquiry: hadron physics--including endeavors such as the super eta factory and investigations into light hadron structures; muon physics; neutrino physics; neutron physics; the testing of fundamental symmetries; and the exploration of quantum effects within nuclear physics, along with the utilization of vortex accelerators. We aim to foster a well-rounded portfolio of large, medium, and small-scale projects, thus unlocking new scientific avenues and optimizing the potential of the Huizhou large scientific facility. The aspiration for international leadership in scientific research will be a guiding principle in our strategic planning. This initiative will serve as a foundational reference for the Institute of Modern Physics in its strategic planning and goal-setting, ensuring alignment with its developmental objectives while striving to secure a competitive edge in technological advancement. Our ambition is to engage in substantive research within these realms of high-precision physics, to pursue groundbreaking discoveries, and to stimulate progress in China's nuclear physics landscape, positioning Huizhou as a preeminent global hub for advanced nuclear physics research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21050v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>FengPeng An, Dong Bai, Siyuan Chen, Xurong Chen, Hongyue Duyang, Leyun Gao, Shao-Feng Ge, Jun He, Junting Huang, Zhongkui Huang, Igor Ivanov, Chen Ji, Huan Jia, Junjie Jiang, Xiaolin Kang, Soo-Bong Kim, Chui-Fan Kong, Wei Kou, Qiang Li, Qite Li, Jiajun Liao, Jiajie Ling, Cheng-en Liu, Xinwen Ma, Hao Qiu, Jian Tang, Rong Wang, Weiqiang Wen, Jia-Jun Wu, Jun Xiao, Xiang Xiao, Yu Xu, Weihua Yang, Xiaofei Yang, Jiangming Yao, Ye Yuan, Mushtaq Zaiba, Pengming Zhang, Shaofeng Zhang, Shuo Zhang, Shihan Zhao, Liping Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of Lateral Amorphous Selenium Photodetectors for Low-Photon and VUV Detection at Cryogenic Temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18497v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The performance of amorphous selenium (a-Se) as a cryogenic photodetector material is evaluated through a series of experiments using laterally structured devices operated in a custom optical test stand. These studies investigate the response of a-Se detectors to low-photon fluxes at high electric fields near avalanche conditions, the linearity of the photoconductive response over a wide dynamic range and the direct detection of narrowband 130 nm vacuum ultraviolet (VUV) illumination. At 87 K, matched-filter analysis shows reliable single-shot detection with efficiencies greater than or equal to 80 percent and area under the curve (AUC) greater than or equal to 0.85 using as few as approximately 6800 incident 401 nm photons, corresponding to approximately 3400 photons within field-active regions after accounting for geometric constraints. Measurements are performed at cryogenic temperatures using calibrated photon fluxes derived from a silicon photomultiplier reference and a characterized optical filter stack. Additional experiments using a tellurium-doped a-Se (a-SeTe) device explore the material's behavior under identical test conditions and demonstrate that avalanche is achievable in a-SeTe at cryogenic temperatures. The results demonstrate reproducible low-noise operation, VUV sensitivity and field-dependent gain behavior in a lateral a-Se architecture, representing the first reported observation of avalanche multiplication in laterally structured a-Se and a-SeTe devices at cryogenic temperatures. These findings support the potential integration of laterally structured a-Se devices into next-generation pixelated liquid-argon time projection chambers (TPCs) requiring scalable, high-field-compatible photon detection systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18497v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Rooks, S. Abbaszadeh, J. Asaadi, V. A. Chirayath, M. Febbraro, M. \'A. Garc\'ia-Peris, E. Gramellini, K. Hellier, B. Sudarsan, I. Tzoka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold improved $Z H$ production at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20676v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present precise theoretical results for the $ZH$ production cross section and invariant mass distribution at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) taking into account the effects of soft gluons. We improve both quark-initiated and gluon-initiated subprocesses through threshold resummation within the QCD framework and present combined results relevant for $13.6$ TeV LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20676v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Goutam Das, Chinmoy Dey, M. C. Kumar, Kajal Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The strong coupling from the IR to the UV extremes: Determination of $\alpha_s$ and prospects from EIC and JLab at 22 GeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19556v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss how the Bjorken sum rule allows access to the QCD running coupling $\alpha_s$ at any scale, including in the deep infrared IR domain. The Bjorken sum data from Jefferson Lab, together with the world data on $\alpha_s$ reported by the Particle Data Group, allow us to determine the running of $\alpha_s(Q)$ over five orders of magnitude in four-momentum $Q$. We present two possible future measurements of the running of $\alpha_s(Q)$ using the Bjorken sum rule: the first at the EIC, covering the range $1.5 &lt; Q &lt; 8.7$ GeV, and the second at Jefferson Lab at 22 GeV, covering the range $1.0 &lt; Q &lt; 4.7$ GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19556v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Deur</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
