<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Neural Network Flavor Tagger and measurement of $\mathrm{sin}2\beta$ at Belle II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present GFlaT, a new algorithm that uses a graph-neural-network to determine the flavor of neutral B mesons produced in $\mathrm{\Upsilon(4S)}$ decays. We evaluate its performance using $B$ decays to flavor-specific hadronic final states reconstructed in a $362$ $\mathrm{fb}^{-1}$ sample of electron-positron collisions recorded at the $\mathrm{\Upsilon(4S)}$ resonance with the Belle II detector at the SuperKEKB collider. We achieve an effective tagging efficiency of $(37.40 \pm 0.43 \pm 0.36) \%$, where the first uncertainty is statistical and the second systematic, which is $18\%$ better than the previous Belle II algorithm. Demonstrating the algorithm, we use $B^0 \to J/\psi K_\mathrm{S}^0$ decays to measure the direct and mixing-induced CP violation parameters, $C = (-0.035 \pm 0.026 \pm 0.013)$ and $S = (0.724 \pm 0.035 \pm 0.014)$, from which we obtain $\beta = (23.2 \pm 1.5 \pm 0.6)^{\circ}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17631v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petros Stavroulakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MuonSLab: A plastic scintillator based detector for muon measurement in the deep ocean</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atmospheric muons are important probes for studying primary cosmic rays and extensive air showers. Additionally, they constitute a significant background for many underground and deep-sea neutrino experiments, such as TRopIcal DEep-sea Neutrino Telescope (TRIDENT). Understanding the muon flux at various depths in the deep sea is essential for validating TRIDENT simulations and guiding the development of optimized trigger strategies. This paper introduces a novel device based on plastic scintillalors and silicon photomultipliers (SiPMs) named MuonSLab, which is designed to measure muon flux in the deep sea and has the potential to be extended to other atmospheric muon property measurements. We discuss the design and instrumentation of MuonSLab and present results from several muon flux measurements, demonstrating its sensitivity to muon detection and its stability during operations across multiple locations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17639v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiacheng Wu, Weilun Huang, Ruike Cao, Qichao Chang, Wang Ding, Jingtao Huang, Liang Li, Xinchen Li, Hualin Mei, Cen Mo, Hengbin Shao, Wei Tian, Xinliang Tian, Yichen Tian, Xin Xiang, Donglian Xu, Fuyudi Zhang, Wei Zhi, Yiwei Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Dark Matter with MeVCube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13162v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: CubeSat technology is an emerging alternative to large-scale space telescopes due to its short development time and cost-effectiveness. MeVCube is a proposed CubeSat mission to study the least explored MeV gamma-ray sky, also known as the `MeV gap'. Besides being sensitive to a plethora of astrophysical phenomena, MeVCube can also be important in the hunt for dark matter. If dark matter is made up of evaporating primordial black holes, then it can produce photons in the sensitivity range of MeVCube. Besides, particle dark matter can also decay or annihilate to produce final state gamma-ray photons. We perform the first comprehensive study of dark matter discovery potential of a near-future MeVCube CubeSat mission. In all cases, we find that MeVCube will have much better discovery reach compared to existing limits in the parameter space. This may be an important step towards discovering dark matter through its non-gravitational interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13162v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Kumar Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Correlators Beyond Angles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17218v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Energy correlators are theoretically simple and physically intuitive observables that bridge experimental and theoretical particle physics. They have for example enabled the most precise jet substructure determination of the strong coupling constant to date, and recent proposals suggest that they may be used to precisely determine of the top quark mass with calculable, small theoretical uncertainties. However, existing energy correlators all measure correlations in angles between particles, from which other observables such as mass must be inferred through potentially complicated procedures. In this work, we generalize energy correlators to enable straightforward measurements of non-angular correlations, which we call Energy Weighted Observable Correlations (EWOCs). To enforce collinear safety, EWOCs quantify correlations between subjets rather than particles. The subjet radius can be tuned to control both the physical scales probed by EWOCs and their sensitivity to non-perturbative physics. We focus on the phenomenologically relevant example of the mass EWOC, which measures mass correlations between pairs of subjets, in the task of extracting mass scales from jets. In jet substructure determinations of the mass of a hadronically-decaying W boson, we show that the mass EWOC outperforms the angle-based energy correlator, and performs comparably to the soft-drop groomed jet mass. As a first exploration of the theoretical properties of EWOCs, we also calculate the mass EWOC on light-quark jets and compare to results obtained with Pythia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17218v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Alipour-fard, Wouter J. Waalewijn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD Theory meets Information Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17219v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel technique to incorporate precision calculations from quantum chromodynamics into fully differential particle-level Monte-Carlo simulations. By minimizing an information-theoretic quantity subject to constraints, we achieve consistency with the theory input and its estimated systematic uncertainties. Our method can be applied to arbitrary observables known from precision calculations, including multiple observables simultaneously. It generates strictly positive weights, thus offering a clear path to statistically powerful and theoretically precise computations for current and future collider experiments. As a proof of concept, we apply our technique to event-shape observables at electron-positron colliders, leveraging existing precision calculations of thrust. Our analysis highlights the importance of logarithmic moments of event shapes, which have not been previously studied in the collider physics literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17219v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beno\^it Assi, Stefan H\"oche, Kyle Lee, Jesse Thaler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-body charmed baryon nonleptonic weak decays with decuplet baryon involving SU(3) breaking effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17237v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the singly charmed baryon two-body decays of $\mathbf{B}_c \rightarrow \mathbf{B}_D P$ under $SU(3)_{F}$ flavor symmetry, where ${\bf B}_{c}$ refers to anti-triplet singly charmed baryons, and ${\bf B}_{D}$ and $P$ denote decuplet baryons and pseudoscalar mesons, respectively. Compared to the literature, we adopt a concise and reasonable treatment of the $SU(3)$ flavor symmetry breaking, by considering the final-state mass dependence of partial waves. With 4 real parameters in total and 9 experimental data points, we achieve a minimal $\chi^2/\text{d.o.f.} $ value of $ 1.46$, providing a satisfactory explanation to the experiment results. We evaluate the branching ratios and Lee-Yang parameters suggesting the absence of the strong phase in $\mathbf{B}_c \rightarrow \mathbf{B}_D P$, along with an unusual positive decay asymmetry $\alpha\,(\Xi_{c}^{0}\rightarrow \Omega^{-}K^{+})$. The predicted results of large $SU(3)_{F}$ breaking effects in $\mathbf{B}_c \rightarrow \mathbf{B}_D P$ can be verified in the further research by the experiments at BESIII, Belle-II and LHCb.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17237v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao-Qiang Geng, Chia-Wei Liu, Sheng-Lin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Miniaturized chip calorimeter for high-pressure cells at low temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17659v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Heat capacity measurements under high pressure places high demands on the calorimeter. Here we describe the development of a miniaturized nanocalorimeter for high-pressure heat capacity measurements at low temperature. The device, fabricated on a silicon substrate, employs a high-frequency AC calorimetry technique and features a design with an outer diameter of 300 ${\mu}$m and thickness of 25-40 ${\mu}$m, small enough to fit into high pressure diamond anvil cells. Miniaturization is achieved by stacking all components, including thermometer and heaters, within a central area. The thin-film calorimeter thermometer measures 40 ${\mu}$m square and maintains the sensitivity and properties of larger thermometers. The fabrication process uses controlled anisotropic etch to produce calorimeter chips with a balance between robustness and thickness, suitable for experiments at high pressures and low temperatures. The calorimeter operates at a relatively high characteristic frequency between 10 Hz and 1 kHz, constraining the thermal oscillation to an effective volume dominated by the sample, thereby avoiding the use of a suspended membrane that is the basis for conventional nanocalorimeters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17659v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neha Kondedan, Andreas Rydh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bottom quark forward-backward asymmetry at the future electron-positron collider FCC-ee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Standard Model (SM) prediction for the \PZ-boson pole $b$-quark forward-backward (FB) asymmetry is: $(A_{FB}^{0,b})_{th} = 0.1030 \pm 0.0002$. The LEP electron-positron collider measured instead $A_{FB}^{0,b} = 0.0992 \pm 0.0016$, value which presents the largest discrepancy with any of the SM predictions as of today. All the $A_{FB}^b$ measurements performed at LEP suffered however of an important statistical uncertainty and of different sources of systematic uncertainties. This study shows that the proposed high-luminosity electron-positron collider FCC-ee, collecting orders of magnitude more data at the \PZ-pole than LEP, will significantly reduce the statistical uncertainties on the measurement of $A_{FB}^{0,b}$, thus allowing us to shed further light on this tension</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17677v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marina Cobal, Giovanni Guerrieri, Hamzeh Khanpour, Giancarlo Panizzo, Michele Pinamonti, Laura Pintucci, Leonardo Toffolin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel and self-consistent analysis for the $\eta_c\rightarrow \gamma\gamma$ process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17681v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The next-to-next-to-leading-order (NNLO) pQCD predictions for both the decay width and the transition form factor in the $\eta_c\rightarrow \gamma\gamma$ process, based on nonrelativistic QCD (NRQCD), deviate from precise experimental measurements. These significant discrepancies have cast doubt on the applicability of NRQCD to charmonium processes. In this paper, we analyze the $\eta_c\rightarrow \gamma\gamma$ process by applying the Principle of Maximum Conformality (PMC), a systematic method for eliminating renormalization scheme and scale ambiguities. The PMC renormalization scales are determined by absorbing the non-conformal $\beta$ terms which govern the behavior of the QCD running coupling via the Renormalization Group Equation. We obtain the PMC scale $Q_\star=4.49\,m_c$ for the $\eta_c\rightarrow \gamma\gamma$ decay width. The resulting value for $\Gamma_{\eta_c\rightarrow \gamma\gamma}$ is in good agreement with the Particle Data Group's reported value of $\Gamma_{\eta_c\rightarrow \gamma\gamma}=5.1\pm0.4$ keV. Moreover, the transition form factor obtained using the PMC is also in good agreement with precise experimental measurements. The application of the PMC provides a rigorous solution for the $\eta_c\rightarrow \gamma\gamma$ puzzle and supports the applicability of NRQCD to charmonium processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17681v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng-Quan Wang, Zhu-Yu Ren, Jian-Ming Shen, Xing-Gang Wu, Leonardo Di Giustino, Stanley J. Brodsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feasibility of true muonium observation in Belle-II existing dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17753v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: True muonium ($\mu^+\mu^-$) is one of the cleanest bound states, being composed only of leptons, along with true tauonium and positronium. Unlike the latter, true muonium and true tauonium have not been observed so far. This article shows that the spin-0 state of true muonium (para-TM), decaying into two photons, can be observed at a discovery level of significance in the dataset already collected by the Belle-II experiment at the $\Upsilon (4S)$ peak, with certain assumptions on systematic uncertainties. Para-TM is produced via photon-photon fusion, and its observation is based on the detection of the photon pair resulting from its decay, on top of the continuum background due predominantly to light-by-light scattering. Trigger, acceptance and isolation cuts, along with calorimeter resolution and reconstruction efficiency, are taken into account during the Monte Carlo simulation of both signal and background. In order to separate signal and background, a machine learning method, based on extremely randomized trees, is trained on simulated events. Finally, the expected statistical significance of TM observation is evaluated, taking into account systematic uncertainties in a parametric fashion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17753v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruben Gargiulo, Elisa Di Meco, Stefano Palmisano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective field theory and inelastic dark matter results from XENON1T</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.07591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.07591v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we expand on the XENON1T nuclear recoil searches to study the individual signals of dark matter interactions from operators up to dimension-eight in a Chiral Effective Field Theory (ChEFT) and a model of inelastic dark matter (iDM). We analyze data from two science runs of the XENON1T detector totaling 1\,tonne$\times$year exposure. For these analyses, we extended the region of interest from [4.9, 40.9]$\,$keV$_{\text{NR}}$ to [4.9, 54.4]$\,$keV$_{\text{NR}}$ to enhance our sensitivity for signals that peak at nonzero energies. We show that the data is consistent with the background-only hypothesis, with a small background over-fluctuation observed peaking between 20 and 50$\,$keV$_{\text{NR}}$, resulting in a maximum local discovery significance of 1.7\,$\sigma$ for the Vector$\otimes$Vector$_{\text{strange}}$ ($VV_s$) ChEFT channel for a dark matter particle of 70$\,$GeV/c$^2$, and $1.8\,\sigma$ for an iDM particle of 50$\,$GeV/c$^2$ with a mass splitting of 100$\,$keV/c$^2$. For each model, we report 90\,\% confidence level (CL) upper limits. We also report upper limits on three benchmark models of dark matter interaction using ChEFT where we investigate the effect of isospin-breaking interactions. We observe rate-driven cancellations in regions of the isospin-breaking couplings, leading to up to 6 orders of magnitude weaker upper limits with respect to the isospin-conserving case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.07591v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.112017</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 112017 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>E. Aprile, K. Abe, F. Agostini, S. Ahmed Maouloud, L. Althueser, B. Andrieu, E. Angelino, J. R. Angevaare, V. C. Antochi, D. Ant\'on Martin, F. Arneodo, L. Baudis, A. L. Baxter, L. Bellagamba, R. Biondi, A. Bismark, A. Brown, S. Bruenner, G. Bruno, R. Budnik, C. Cai, C. Capelli, J. M. R. Cardoso, D. Cichon, M. Clark, A. P. Colijn, J. Conrad, J. J. Cuenca-Garc\'ia, J. P. Cussonneau, V. D'Andrea, M. P. Decowski, P. Di Gangi, S. Di Pede, A. Di Giovanni, R. Di Stefano, S. Diglio, K. Eitel, A. Elykov, S. Farrell, A. D. Ferella, H. Fischer, W. Fulgione, P. Gaemers, R. Gaior, A. Gallo Rosso, M. Galloway, F. Gao, R. Glade-Beucke, L. Grandi, J. Grigat, M. Guida, R. Hammann, A. Higuera, C. Hils, L. Hoetzsch, J. Howlett, M. Iacovacci, Y. Itow, J. Jakob, F. Joerg, A. Joy, N. Kato, M. Kara, P. Kavrigin, S. Kazama, M. Kobayashi, G. Koltman, A. Kopec, H. Landsman, R. F. Lang, L. Levinson, I. Li, S. Li, S. Liang, S. Lindemann, M. Lindner, K. Liu, J. Loizeau, F. Lombardi, J. Long, J. A. M. Lopes, Y. Ma, C. Macolino, J. Mahlstedt, A. Mancuso, L. Manenti, A. Manfredini, F. Marignetti, T. Marrod\'an Undagoitia, K. Martens, J. Masbou, D. Masson, E. Masson, S. Mastroianni, M. Messina, K. Miuchi, K. Mizukoshi, A. Molinario, S. Moriyama, K. Mor{\aa}, Y. Mosbacher, M. Murra, J. M\"uller, K. Ni, U. Oberlack, B. Paetsch, J. Palacio, R. Peres, J. Pienaar, M. Pierre, V. Pizzella, G. Plante, J. Qi, J. Qin, D. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, S. Reichard, A. Rocchetti, N. Rupp, L. Sanchez, J. M. F. dos Santos, I. Sarnoff, G. Sartorelli, J. Schreiner, D. Schulte, P. Schulte, H. Schulze Ei{\ss}ing, M. Schumann, L. Scotto Lavina, M. Selvi, F. Semeria, P. Shagin, S. Shi, E. Shockley, M. Silva, H. Simgen, A. Takeda, P. L. Tan, A. Terliuk, D. Thers, F. Toschi, G. Trinchero, C. Tunnell, F. T\"onnies, K. Valerius, G. Volta, Y. Wei, C. Weinheimer, M. Weiss, D. Wenz, C. Wittweg, T. Wolf, D. Xu, Z. Xu, M. Yamashita, L. Yang, J. Ye, L. Yuan, G. Zavattini, M. Zhong, T. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity to longitudinal vector boson scattering and doubly-charged Higgs production in $\mathbf{W^\pm W^\pm jj}$ at future hadron colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.07994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.07994v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the sensitivity to longitudinal vector boson scattering at a 27, 50 and 100 TeV $pp$ collider using events containing two leptonically-decaying same-electric-charge $W$ bosons produced in association with two jets. Additionally, expected limits are set on doubly charged Higgs bosons produced via vector boson fusion processes and decaying to same-sign $W$ boson pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.07994v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aram Apyan, Samuel Kelson, Chilufya Mwewa, Luka Nedic, Marc-Andr\'e Pleier, Karolos Potamianos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Light Source of the TRIDENT Pathfinder Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.14608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.14608v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In September 2021, a site scouting mission known as the TRIDENT pathfinder experiment (TRIDENT EXplorer, T-REX for short) was conducted in the South China Sea with the goal of envisaging a next-generation multi-cubic-kilometer neutrino telescope. One of the main tasks is to measure the in-situ optical properties of seawater at depths between $2800~\mathrm{m}$ and $3500~\mathrm{m}$, where the neutrino telescope will be instrumented. To achieve this, we have developed a light emitter module equipped with a clock synchronization system to serve as the light source, which could be operated in pulsing and steady modes. Two light receiver modules housing both photomultiplier tubes (PMTs) and cameras are employed to detect the photons emitted by the light source. This paper presents the instrumentation of the light source in T-REX, including its design, calibration, and performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.14608v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenlian Li, Xiaohui Liu, Wei Tian, Fuyudi Zhang, Shishen Xian, Mingxin Wang, Jiannan Tang, Fan Hu, Ziping Ye, Peng Miao, Zhengyang Sun, Donglian Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the resolution of dual readout calorimeters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15329v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dual readout calorimeters allow state-of-the-art resolutions for hadronic energy measurements. Their various incarnations are leading candidates for the calorimeter systems for future colliders. In this paper, we present a simple formula for the resolution of a dual readout calorimeter, which we verify with a toy simulation and with full simulation results. This formula can help those new to dual readout calorimetry understand its strengths and limitations. The paper also highlights that the dual readout correction works not just to compensate for binding energy loss, but also for energies escaping the calorimeter or clustering algorithm. Formulae are also presented for approximate resolutions and energy scales in terms of different sources of response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15329v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Eno, L. Wu, M. Y. Aamir, S. V. Chekanov, S. Nabili, C. Palmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
