<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 02:31:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>CMS Upgrades for the High-Luminosity LHC Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The High-Luminosity LHC (HL-LHC) era, set to begin in 2029, will provide the general-purpose experiments with an instantaneous luminosity of up to $\mathcal{L} = 7.5 \times 10^{34}$ cm$^{-2}$ s$^{-1}$ from pp collisions at a centre-of-mass energy of 14 TeV. To fully exploit this unprecedented data set, the experimental setups must be upgraded to withstand the challenging conditions of the HL-LHC, including up to 200 simultaneous collisions per bunch crossing and a substantial radiation dose delivered to the detectors. The CMS collaboration is currently undertaking the Phase-2 upgrade, which aims to enhance the detector's capabilities to maintain high performance under these conditions. This upgrade includes significant improvements to the muon spectrometer and barrel calorimeter, a complete replacement of the silicon tracker, endcap calorimeter and beam radiation and luminosity subsystems, the introduction of a new MIP timing detector layer, and a redesigned trigger and data acquisition system. These enhancements will ensure that the CMS experiment can fully profit from on the HL-LHC data, maximising its physics potential and expanding its ability to make the most precise measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03412v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thiago R. F. P. Tomei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential search for direct slepton pair production in $\sqrt{s}$ = 360 GeV at CEPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The center-of-mass energy of Circular Electron Positron Collider (CEPC) could be upgrade to 360 GeV level (CEPC@360GeV) after its ten-year running at 240 GeV. Besides SM precision measurements, CEPC@360GeV also has good potential for BSM physics searches, which is a good complementary for hadron colliders. This paper presents the sensitivity study of direct stau and smuon pair production at CEPC with $\sqrt{s}$ = 360 GeV by full Monte Carlo (MC) simulation. With 1.0 ab$^{-1}$ integrated luminosity and the assumption of flat 5% systematic uncertainty, the CEPC@360 GeV has the potential to discover the production of combined left-handed and right-handed stau up to 168.5 GeV if exists, or up to 159 GeV for the production of pure left-handed or right-handed stau; the discovery potential of direct smuon reaches up to 175 GeV with the same assumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03600v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng Lyu, Jiarong Yuan, Huajie Cheng, Xuai Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design, Construction, and Testing of the APOLLO ATCA Blades for Use at the HL-LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03702v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Apollo Advanced Telecommunications Computing Architecture (ATCA) platform is an open-source design consisting of a generic "Service Module" (SM) and a customizable "Command Module" (CM), allowing for cost-effective use in applications such as the readout of the inner tracker and the Level-1 track trigger for the CMS Phase-II upgrade at the HL-LHC. The SM integrates an intelligent IPMC, robust power entry and conditioning systems, a powerful system-on-module computer, and flexible clock and communication infrastructure. The CM is designed around two Xilinx Ultrascale+ FPGAs and high-density, high-bandwidth optical transceivers capable of 25 Gb/s. Crates of Apollo blades are currently being tested at Boston University, Cornell University, and CERN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03702v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Akpinar, A. Blaizot, S. Cholak, G. de Castro, Z. Demiragli, A. Duquette, J. Fulcher, D. Gastler, K. Hahn, E. Hazen, P. Kotamnives, A. Madorsky, D. Monk, S. Noorudhin, M. Oshiro, J. Rohlf, C. Strohman, E. Tsai, P. Wittich, S. Yuan, R. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top quark spin and quantum entanglement in the ATLAS experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03755v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Top quark pair spin correlation measurements performed by the ATLAS experiment using $pp$ collisions at the CERN Large Hadron Collider are summarized. Moreover, the measurement of a specific observable $D$ related to top quark pair spin correlations is presented using the full LHC Run 2 data taking at the center-of-mass energy of $\sqrt{s} = 13$ TeV. This allowed the ATLAS experiment to observe the quantum entanglement, one of the fundamental property of the quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03755v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Lysak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GraphNeT 2.0 -- A Deep Learning Library for Neutrino Telescopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03817v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutrino telescopes, an extension of traditional multiwavelength astronomy, provide a complementary view of the universe using neutrinos. Differences in detector geometry and detection medium mean that improvements to reconstruction techniques made at one experiment are not readily applicable to another. Recently, deep learning has been shown to improve prediction speed and accuracy and offer indifference to detector geometry and detection medium, providing a unique opportunity for collaboration. This work introduces GraphNeT 2.0, an open-source, detector-agnostic deep learning library for neutrino telescopes and related experiments. GraphNeT enables inter-experimental collaboration on the use and development of advanced methods based on major deep learning paradigms like transformers, normalizing flows, graph neural networks, and more.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03817v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasmus F. {\O}rs{\o}e, Aske Rosted, GraphNeT Team</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The trace distance between density matrices, a nifty tool in new-physics searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03311v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum information methods have been brought to bear on high-energy physics, including the study of entanglement and Bell nonlocality in collider experiments. Quantum information observables have also been employed to constrain possible new physics effects. We improve on this point by introducing quantum information tools routinely used to compare quantum states: the trace distance and the fidelity. We find that the former outperforms other quantum information observables considered in the literature and, together with the cross section, yields the strongest bounds on possible departures from the Standard Model. The power of the proposed methodology is demonstrated with three examples of new physics searches. The first concerns the chromomagnetic dipole moment of the top quark and yields the first bound computed by means of quantum tomography and actual experimental data. The other two examples use Monte Carlo simulations and set the projected limits on the anomalous couplings of the $\tau$ leptons at Belle and at a future collider, which is taken to be LEP3. For these new physics searches we also compare the sensitivity of the trace distance to those of other quantum information quantities like concurrence, magic, and the fidelity distance. In passing, we provide the first determinations of magic in colliders data by analyzing the top-quark pair production at the LHC and the charmonium decays. The significance is well above the $5\sigma$ level in both the cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03311v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Fabbrichesi, Matthew Low, Luca Marzola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bell Inequality Violation of Light Quarks in Back-to-Back Dihadron Pair Production at Lepton Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spin correlations between particles produced at colliders provide valuable insights for quantum information studies. While traditional studies of quantum information at colliders are typically limited to massive particles with perturbative decay, we propose an innovative method to explore the Bell inequality in massless quark pair systems by analyzing the azimuthal correlations in back-to-back $\pi^+\pi^-$ dihadron pair production at lepton colliders. Revisiting the Belle data, we have shown the potential to detect Bell inequality violation of light quarks by introducing an additional angular cut, achieving a significance of 2.5 $\sigma$ even in the worst-case scenario of 100% correlated systematic uncertainties in each bins. The significance substantially exceeds $5\sigma$ when considering uncorrelated systematic uncertainties. Our approach opens avenues for exploring spin quantum information in the non-perturbative aspect and leverages existing data for quantum information research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03321v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Cheng, Bin Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Thorne-\.Zytkow Objects through Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thorne-\.Zytkow Objects (T\.ZOs) have been predicted to form when a neutron star is engulfed by a diffuse, convective giant envelope. Accretion onto a neutron star at a rate that is larger than $10^{-4}\, M_\odot$ yr$^{-1}$ is expected to lead to significant emission of neutrinos of all flavors with energy of 1-100 MeV. Since the neutrino signal is expected to largely vary in time (from milliseconds to thousands of years), we outline detection strategies tailored to the signal duration. We find that neutrino detection from T\.ZOs up to the Small Magellanic Cloud is within the reach of current- and next-generation neutrino observatories, such as Super- and Hyper-Kamiokande, the IceCube Neutrino Observatory, and JUNO. Interestingly, if targeted searches for neutrinos from T\.ZO candidates (e.g. VX Sgr in our Galaxy as well as HV 2112 and HV 11417 in the Small Magellanic Cloud) should lead to positive results, neutrinos could positively identify the nature of such sources and their accretion rate. Our findings should serve as motivation for establishing dedicated searches for neutrino emission from T\.ZOs. This is especially timely since it is challenging to detect T\.ZOs via electromagnetic radiation unambiguously, and the T\.ZO gravitational wave signal could be probed with next-generation detectors for sources within our Galaxy only.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03330v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Mart\'inez-Mirav\'e, Irene Tamborra, Alejandro Vigna-G\'omez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FEL Gain Enhancement in an Optical Klystron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03334v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A formula for the spectral distribution of intensity of radiation from a system of gap-separated undulators is derived. Due to the constructive addition of radiation fields formed in undulators, the line shape of the spontaneous radiation at zero angle is narrowed. According to Madey's theory, the gain is proportional to the derivative of the line shape of the spontaneous radiation, hence, it is enhanced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03334v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anahit H. Shamamian, Hayk L. Gevorgyan, Lekdar A. Gevorgian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gallium Solar Neutrino Capture Cross Section Revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03528v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solar neutrino flux constraints from the legacy GALLEX/GNO and SAGE experiments continue to influence contemporary global analyses of neutrino properties. The constraints depend on the neutrino absorption cross sections for various solar sources. Following recent work updating the $^{51}$Cr and $^{37}$Ar neutrino source cross sections, we reevaluate the $^{71}$Ga solar neutrino cross sections, focusing on contributions from transitions to $^{71}$Ge excited states, but also revising the ground-state transition to take into account new $^{71}$Ge electron-capture lifetime measurements and various theory corrections. The excited-state contributions have been traditionally taken from forward-angle $(p,n)$ cross sections. Here we correct this procedure for the $\approx 10\%-20\%$ tensor operator contribution that alters the relationship between Gamow-Teller and $(p,n)$ transition strengths. Using state-of-the-art nuclear shell-model calculations to evaluate this correction, we find that it lowers the $^8$B and hep neutrino cross sections. However, the addition of other corrections, including contributions from near-threshold continuum states that radiatively decay, leads to an overall increase in the $^8$B and hep cross sections of $\approx 10\%$ relative to the values recommended by Bahcall. Uncertainties are propagated using Monte Carlo simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03528v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. C. Haxton, Evan Rule</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinvestigating the semileptonic $B\to D^{(\ast)}\tau\bar{\nu}_{\tau}$ decays in the model independent scenarios and leptoquark models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we revisit the possible new physics (NP) solutions by analyzing the observables associated with $B\to D^{(\ast)}\tau\bar{\nu}_{\tau}$ decays. To explore the structure of new physics, the form factors of $B\to D^{(\ast)}$ decays play a crucial role. In this study, we utilize the form factor results obtained from a simultaneous fit to Belle data and lattice QCD calculations. Using these form factors, we conduct a global fit of the new physics Wilson coefficients, incorporating the most recent experimental data. Additionally, we use the form factors and Wilson coefficients to make predictions for physical observables, including the lepton flavor universality ratio $R_{D^{(\ast)}}$, polarized observables, and the normalized angular coefficients $\langle I\rangle$'s related to the four-fold decays $B\to D^{\ast}(\to D\pi, D\gamma)\tau\bar{\nu}_{\tau}$. These predictions are calculated in both model-independent scenarios and for three different leptoquark models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03734v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faisal Munir Bhutta, Nimra Farooq, Zhuo-Ran Huang, Ying Li, M. Ali Paracha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel experimental approach to uncover the nature of cosmic-ray Deuterium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03966v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Studying the isotopic composition of cosmic-rays (CRs) provides crucial insights into the galactic environment and helps improve existing propagation models. Special attention is given to the secondary-to-primary ratios of light isotopic components in CRs, as these measurements can offer complementary data compared to traditional secondary-to-primary ratios like B/C. Recently, a precision measurement of the Deuterium (D) abundance in CR in the 2-21 GV rigidity range provided by the AMS02 experiment unexpectedly detected an excess of D with respect to its expected secondary nature, opening the field for new measurements at high rigidity to determine how the spectrum evolves and whether there is confirmation of a primary or primary plus secondary origin. While there are theoretical models that attempt to explain this excess, the experimental uncertainties on D production cross-sections and on CR propagation models remain significant, and only new and precise measurements can dissipate existing doubts. In this work we review the current experimental scenario and we propose a dedicated experiment able to extend the D abundance measurement up to 100 GeV/nucl without the need of a magnetic spectrometer, using a multiple scattering based technique for the measurement of particle momentum. The expected performances of the proposed detector were assessed through a dedicated simulation using the GEANT4 package, and its role in the current particle physics scenario is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03966v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Dimiccoli, Francesco Maria Follega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-independent search for pair production of new bosons decaying into muons in proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The results of a model-independent search for the pair production of new bosons within a mass range of 0.21 $\lt$ $m$ $\lt$ 60 GeV, are presented. This study utilizes events with a four-muon final state. We use two data sets, comprising 41.5 fb$^{-1}$ and 59.7 fb$^{-1}$ of proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV, recorded in 2017 and 2018 by the CMS experiment at the CERN LHC. The study of the 2018 data set includes a search for displaced signatures of a new boson within the proper decay length range of 0 $\lt$ $c\tau$ $\lt$ 100 $\mu$m. Our results are combined with a previous CMS result, based on 35.9 fb$^{-1}$ of proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV collected in 2016. No significant deviation from the expected background is observed. Results are presented in terms of a model-independent upper limit on the product of cross section, branching fraction, and acceptance. The findings are interpreted across various benchmark models, such as an axion-like particle model, a vector portal model, the next-to-minimal supersymmetric standard model, and a dark supersymmetric scenario, including those predicting a non-negligible proper decay length of the new boson. In all considered scenarios, substantial portions of the parameter space are excluded, expanding upon prior results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20425v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)172</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 12 (2024) 172</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> CMS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hadronic cross section measurements with the DAMPE space mission using 20GeV-10TeV cosmic-ray protons and $^4$He</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.17224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.17224v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Precise direct cosmic-ray (CR) measurements provide an important probe to study the energetic particle sources in our Galaxy, and the interstellar environment through which these particles propagate. Uncertainties on hadronic models, ion-nucleon cross sections in particular, are currently the limiting factor towards obtaining more accurate CR ion flux measurements with calorimetric space-based experiments. We present an energy-dependent measurement of the inelastic cross section of protons and helium-4 nuclei (alpha particles) on a Bi$_4$Ge$_3$O$_{12}$ target, using 88 months of data collected by the DAMPE space mission. The kinetic energy range per nucleon of the measurement points ranges from 18 GeV to 9 TeV for protons, and from 5 GeV/n to 3 TeV/n for helium-4 nuclei. Our results lead to a significant improvement of the CR flux normalisation. In the case of helium-4, these results correspond to the first cross section measurements on a heavy target material at energies above 10 GeV/n.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.17224v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.012002</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>F. Alemanno, Q. An, P. Azzarello, F. C. T. Barbato, P. Bernardini, X. J. Bi, I. Cagnoli, M. S. Cai, E. Casilli, E. Catanzani, J. Chang, D. Y. Chen, J. L. Chen, Z. F. Chen, P. Coppin, M. Y. Cui, T. S. Cui, Y. X. Cui, H. T. Dai, A. De Benedittis, I. De Mitri, F. de Palma, A. Di Giovanni, Q. Ding, T. K. Dong, Z. X. Dong, G. Donvito, D. Droz, J. L. Duan, K. K. Duan, R. R. Fan, Y. Z. Fan, F. Fang, K. Fang, C. Q. Feng, L. Feng, J. M. Frieden, P. Fusco, M. Gao, F. Gargano, K. Gong, Y. Z. Gong, D. Y. Guo, J. H. Guo, S. X. Han, Y. M. Hu, G. S. Huang, X. Y. Huang, Y. Y. Huang, M. Ionica, L. Y. Jiang, Y. Z. Jiang, W. Jiang, J. Kong, A. Kotenko, D. Kyratzis, S. J. Lei, W. H. Li, W. L. Li, X. Li, X. Q. Li, Y. M. Liang, C. M. Liu, H. Liu, J. Liu, S. B. Liu, Y. Liu, F. Loparco, C. N. Luo, M. Ma, P. X. Ma, T. Ma, X. Y. Ma, G. Marsella, M. N. Mazziotta, D. Mo, X. Y. Niu, X. Pan, A. Parenti, W. X. Peng, X. Y. Peng, C. Perrina, E. Putti-Garcia, R. Qiao, J. N. Rao, A. Ruina, R. Sarkar, P. Savina, A. Serpolla, Z. Shangguan, W. H. Shen, Z. Q. Shen, Z. T. Shen, L. Silveri, J. X. Song, M. Stolpovskiy, H. Su, M. Su, H. R. Sun, Z. Y. Sun, A. Surdo, X. J. Teng, A. Tykhonov, J. Z. Wang, L. G. Wang, S. Wang, S. X. Wang, X. L. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. Z. Wang, Z. M. Wang, D. M. Wei, J. J. Wei, Y. F. Wei, D. Wu, J. Wu, S. S. Wu, X. Wu, Z. Q. Xia, H. T. Xu, J. Xu, Z. H. Xu, Z. L. Xu, E. H. Xu, Z. Z. Xu, G. F. Xue, H. B. Yang, P. Yang, Y. Q. Yang, H. J. Yao, Y. H. Yu, G. W. Yuan, Q. Yuan, C. Yue, J. J. Zang, S. X. Zhang, W. Z. Zhang, Yan Zhang, Yi Zhang, Y. J. Zhang, Y. L. Zhang, Y. P. Zhang, Y. Q. Zhang, Z. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, C. Zhao, H. Y. Zhao, X. F. Zhao, C. Y. Zhou, Y. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of $\it{\Lambda}_\it{b}^0$, $\it{\Lambda}_\it{c}^+$ and $\it{\Lambda}$ decay parameters using $\it{\Lambda}_\it{b}^0 \to \it{\Lambda}_\it{c}^+ h^-$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02759v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A comprehensive study of the angular distributions in the bottom-baryon decays $\it{\Lambda}^\mathrm{0}_b\to\it{\Lambda}_c^+ h^-(h=\pi, K)$, followed by $\it{\Lambda}_c^+\to\it{\Lambda} h^+$ with $\it{\Lambda}\to \it{p} \pi^-$ or $\it{\Lambda}_c^+\to\it{p}\it{K}^0_\mathrm{S}$ decays, is performed using a data sample of proton-proton collisions corresponding to an integrated luminosity of $9~\mathrm{fb}^{-1}$ collected by the LHCb experiment at center-of-mass energies of 7, 8 and 13 $\mathrm{Te\kern -0.1em V}$. The decay parameters and the associated charge-parity ($C\!P$) asymmetries are measured, with no significant $C\!P$ violation observed. For the first time, the $\it{\Lambda}^\mathrm{0}_b \to \it{\Lambda}_c^+ h^-$ decay parameters are measured. The most precise measurements of the decay parameters $\alpha, \beta$ and $\gamma$ are obtained for $\it{\Lambda}_c^+$ decays and an independent measurement of the decay parameters for the strange-baryon $\it{\Lambda}$ decay is provided. The results deepen our understanding of weak decay dynamics in baryon decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02759v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.261804</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133 (2024) 261804</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, A. A. Adefisoye, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, M. Alexander, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, A. Andreianov, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, D. Andreou, A. Anelli, D. Ao, F. Archilli, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, R. Ataide Da Silva, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, W. Baldini, L. Balzani, H. Bao, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, C. Barbero Pretel, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, M. Barnyakov, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, M. Bartolini, J. Bartz, J. M. Basels, S. Bashir, G. Bassi, B. Batsukh, P. B. Battista, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, N. B. Behling, S. Belin, V. Bellee, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, J. Bhom, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, N. Bondar, A. Bordelius, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, S. A. Bouchiba, M. Bovill, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, E. Buchanan, A. Buonaura, L. Buonincontri, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, A. Butkevich, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, A. C. Caillet, R. Calabrese, S. Calderon Ramirez, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, P. Camargo Magalhaes, J. I. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, J. Castro Godinez, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, D. Cervenkov, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, E. Chatzianagnostou, C. A. Chavez Barajas, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, S. Chen, Z. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, X. Chiotopoulos, V. Chobanova, S. Cholak, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, P. Collins, T. Colombo, M. C. Colonna, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, E. Curras Rivera, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, A. Danilina, P. d'Argent, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, A. Davis, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, F. De Benedetti, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, V. Dedu, S. Dekkers, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, L. Dittmann, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, A. D. Dowling, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, O. D. Durmus, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, E. Epple, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, L. N. Falcao, Y. Fan, B. Fang, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, A. Fernandez Casani, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, K. M. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, F. Fleuret, M. Fontana, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, J. Fu, Q. Fuehring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, E. Gabriel, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, B. Ganie, H. Gao, R. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, M. Garau, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, K. G. Garg, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, R. E. Geertsema, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, S. G. Ghizzo, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, L. Girardey, P. Gironella Gironell, C. Giugliano, M. A. Giza, E. L. Gkougkousis, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, A. Gomes, S. Gomez Fernandez, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, L. Guerry, M. Guittiere, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, K. Habermann, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, J. Haimberger, M. Hajheidari, G. H. Hallett, M. M. Halvorsen, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, M. Hartmann, S. Hashmi, J. He, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, P. Herrero Gascon, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, G. Hijano Mendizabal, D. Hill, S. E. Hollitt, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Huang, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Inglessi, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, R. Jacobsson, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, A. John Rubesh Rajan, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, J. Juan Castella, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, M. Kane, Y. Kang, C. Kar, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, A. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, F. Keizer, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, O. K. Kshyvanskyi, J. Kubat, S. Kubis, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, B. K. Kutsenko, D. Lacarrere, P. Laguarta Gonzalez, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, R. Lane, G. Lanfranchi, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, E. Lemos Cid, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, B. Leverington, A. Li, C. Li, H. Li, K. Li, L. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, Q. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, S. Libralon, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, V. Lisovskyi, R. Litvinov, F. L. Liu, G. Liu, K. Liu, S. Liu, W. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, J. Lomba Castro, T. Long, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, Q. Lu, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, M. Lucio Martinez, V. Lukashenko, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, R. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, B. Mack, I. Mackay, L. M. Mackey, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. M. Madurai, A. Maevskiy, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, M. W. Majewski, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, E. Mariani, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, L. Martel, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Massafferri, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, J. Mazorra de Cos, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, L. Mcconnell, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, F. M. Meng, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, S. Mokhnenko, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. Mu\~noz-Rojas, R. Murta, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, P. Nogarolli, P. Nogga, N. S. Nolte, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, S. Okamura, A. Okhotnikov, O. Okhrimenko, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, D. Osthues, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, F. Paciolla, A. Padee, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, P. R. Pais, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, A. Paul, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, J. Peng, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, H. Pereira Da Costa, A. Pereiro Castro, P. Perret, A. Perro, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, J. P. Pfaller, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, T. Poeschl, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, V. Pugatch, G. Punzi, S. Qasim, Q. Q. Qian, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, V. Ramos De Oliveira, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, R. Ribatti, G. R. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, J. Roensch, A. Rogachev, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, M. Romero Lamas, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, T. Rong, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, T. Ruf, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, A. Ryzhikov, J. Ryzka, J. J. Saavedra-Arias, J. J. Saborido Silva, R. Sadek, N. Sagidova, D. Sahoo, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, C. Sanchez Gras, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, A. S. Sarnatskiy, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, L. G. Scantlebury Smead, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, S. Schulte, M. H. Schune, R. Schwemmer, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, T. Senger, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, R. S. Sharma, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, Q. Shi, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, N. Skidmore, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, J. C. Smallwood, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, A. Snoch, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, I. Solovyev, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, O. Stenyakin, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, Y. Sun, D. S. Sundfeld Lima, W. Sutcliffe, P. N. Swallow, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, Y. Tan, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, E. Ursov, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, G. Vasquez, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Vesterinen, D. Vico Benet, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, G. Vouters, C. Vrahas, J. Wagner, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, C. Wang, G. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, M. Waterlaat, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, J. Wendel, B. D. C. Westhenry, C. White, M. Whitehead, E. Whiter, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, Z. Williams, F. F. Wilson, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, C. P. Wong, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, Y. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, A. Xu, J. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, D. Yang, K. Yang, S. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, Y Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, C. Zeng, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zharkova, A. Zhelezov, S. Z. Zheng, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reusable Verification Components for High-Energy Physics readout ASICs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03478v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Verification is a critical aspect of designing front-end (FE) readout ASICs for High-Energy Physics (HEP) experiments. These ASICs share several similar functional features, resulting in similar verification objectives, which can be addressed using comparable verification strategies. This contribution presents a set of re-usable verification components for addressing common verification tasks, such as clock generation, reset handling, configuration, as well as hit and fault injections. The components were developed as part of the CHIPS initiative and they have been successfully used in the verification of multiple HEP ASICs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03478v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Lupi S. Esposito, X. Llopart-Cudie, A. Pulli, S. Scarf\'i, N. Kharwadkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersive Analysis of $B\to K^{(*)}$ and $B_s\to \phi$ Form Factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.06301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.06301v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform the first simultaneous dispersive analysis of the $B\to K$, $B\to K^*$, and $B_s\to \phi$ form factors. By means of an improved parametrization, we take into account the form factors' below-threshold branch cuts arising from on-shell $\bar{B}_s \pi^0$ and $\bar{B}_s \pi^0 \pi^0$ states, which so far have been ignored in the literature. In this way, we eliminate a source of hard-to-quantify systematic uncertainties. We provide machine-readable files to obtain the full set of the $\bar{B}\to \bar{K}^{(*)}$ and $\bar{B}_s\to \phi$ form factors in and beyond the entire semileptonic phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.06301v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2023)153</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 12 (2023) 153</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nico Gubernari, M\'eril Reboud, Danny van Dyk, Javier Virto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization and Optimization of a Cryogenic Pure CsI Detector with Remarkable Light Yield and Unprecedented Energy Resolution for CLOVERS Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05026v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we comprehensively characterized and optimized a cryogenic pure CsI (pCsI) detector. We utilized a {$\SI{2}{cm}\times\SI{2}{cm}\times\SI{2}{cm}$} cube crystal coupled with a HAMAMATSU R11065 photomultiplier tube, achieving a remarkable light yield of \SI{35.2}{PE/\keV_{ee}} and an unprecedented energy resolution of \SI{6.9}{\%} at {\SI{59.54}{\keV}}. Additionally, we measured the scintillation decay time of pCsI, which was significantly shorter than that of CsI(Na) at room temperature. Furthermore, we investigated the impact of temperature, surface treatment, and crystal shape on light yield. Notably, the light yield peaked at approximately \SI{20}{\K} and remained stable within the range of \SI{70}--\SI{100}{\K}. The light yield of the polished crystals was approximately 1.5 times greater than that of the ground crystals, whereas the crystal shape exhibited minimal influence on the light yield. These results are crucial for the design of the \SI{10}{\kg} pCsI detector for the future CLOVERS (Coherent eLastic neutrinO(V)-nucleus scattERing at China Spallation Neutron Source (CSNS)) experiment.`</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05026v4</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenguang Su, Qian Lin, Linqquan Kong, Shi Chen, Kimiya Moharrami, Yangheng Zheng, Jin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Azimuthal angular correlation of $J/\psi$ plus jet production at the electron-ion collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02097v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By investigating the soft gluon radiation in the $J/\psi$ plus jet photoproduction at the electron-ion collider (EIC), we demonstrate that the azimuthal angular correlations between the leading jet and heavy quarkonium provide a unique probe to the production mechanism of the latter. In particular, a significant $\cos(\phi)$ asymmetry is found for the color-singlet channel, whereas it vanishes or has an opposite sign for color-octet production, depending on the jet transverse momentum. Numerical results of $\cos(\phi)$ and $\cos(2\phi)$ asymmetries employing both the color-singlet model and the nonrelativistic QCD approach are presented for typical kinematics at the future EIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02097v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.114042</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 114042 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luca Maxia, Feng Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hadronic Weak Decays of Charmed Baryons in the Topological Diagrammatic Approach: An Update</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04675v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There exist two distinct ways in realizing the approximate SU(3) flavor symmetry of QCD to describe the two-body nonleptonic decays of charmed baryons: the irreducible SU(3) approach (IRA) and the topological diagram approach (TDA). The TDA has the advantage that it is more intuitive, graphic and easier to implement model calculations. We perform a global fit to the currently available data of two-body charmed baryon decays within the framework of the TDA and IRA. The number of the minimum set of tensor invariants in the IRA and the topological amplitudes in the TDA is the same, namely, five in the tree-induced amplitudes and four in the penguin amplitudes. Since we employ the new LHCb measurements to fix the sign ambiguity of the decay parameters $\beta$ and $\gamma$, the fit results for the magnitudes of $S$- and $P$-wave amplitudes and their phase shift $\delta_P-\delta_S$ in both the TDA and IRA are more trustworthy than our previous analyses with uncertainties substantially improved. These results can be tested in the near future. The perspective of having direct {\it CP} violation in the charmed baryon sector at the per mille level is briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04675v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Yang Cheng, Fanrong Xu, Huiling Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunting New Animalcula with Rare K and B Decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03440v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We summarize the recent strategy for an efficient hunting of new animalcula with the help of rare K and B decays that avoids the use of the $V_{cb}$ and $V_{ub}$ parameters that are subject to tensions between their determinations from inclusive and exclusive decays. In particular we update the values of the $V_{cb}$-independent ratios of various K and B decay branching ratios predicted by the Standard Model. We also stress the usefulness of the $V_{cb}-\gamma$ plots in the search for new physics. We select the magnificant seven among rare K and B decays that should play a leading role in the search for new physics due to their theoretical cleanness: $B^+\to K^+(K^*)\nu\bar\nu$ and $K^+\to\pi^+\nu\bar\nu$ measured recently by Belle II and NA62, respectively, $K_L\to\pi^0\nu\bar\nu$ investigated by KOTO and also $B_{s,d}\to\mu^+\mu^-$ and $K_S\to\mu^+\mu^-$ measured by the LHCb, CMS and ATLAS experiments at CERN. %</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03440v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej J. Buras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional Verification for Endcap Concentrator ASICs in the High-Granularity Calorimeter Upgrade of CMS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03476v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The High-Granularity Calorimeter (HGCAL) will replace the current CMS Endcap Calorimeter during Long-Shutdown 3. The Endcap Concentrator (ECON) ASICs represent key elements in the readout chain, processing trigger (ECON-T) and data (ECON-D) streams from the HGCROC to the lpGBT. The ECONs will operate in a radiation environment with a High-Energy Hadron (${E\geq20MeV}$) flux up to $2\cdot10^{7} cm^{-2}s^{-1}$. This contribution describes the Universal Verification Methodology (UVM)-based functional verification of the ECON ASICs focusing on the re-use of existing components to manage the complexity of the verification environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03476v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Lupi, G. Bergamin, D. Ceresa, D. Coko, G. Cummings, V. Gingu, M. Hammer, J. Hirschauer, J. Hoff, N. Kharwadkar, S. Kulis, C. Mantilla-Suarez, D. Noonan, P. Rubinov, S. Scarf\`i, A. Shenai, C. Syal, X. Wang, R. Wickwire, J. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Left-right asymmetry calculation comparisons and projected sensitivity to the weak mixing angle in polarized Bhabha scattering at 10.58 GeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16592v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Consideration is being given to upgrading the SuperKEKB electron-positron collider with the introduction of electron-beam polarization. This would enable a unique precision electroweak physics program that opens new ways to search for physics beyond the Standard Model. The upgrade would enable Belle II to make a number of high precision measurements, one of which is the left-right cross-section asymmetry in the $e^+e^-\rightarrow e^+e^-$ Bhabha scattering process. The expected level of precision in such a measurement will require the theoretical values of the asymmetry to be calculated at least to the next-to-leading order (NLO) level, and the implementation of simulation event generators with a similar level of precision. In this study, we compare the calculations of the ReneSANCe Monte Carlo generator with those of an independent NLO calculation to determine the level of agreement in this process. A 2.3% difference between the calculations is found and attributed to some higher-order effects being accounted for in the ReneSANCe generator. Using the published Belle II efficiency for selecting Bhabha events and assuming a 40 ab$^{-1}$ dataset having 70% polarization, the projected uncertainty on the weak mixing angle, sin$^2\theta_W$ , is calculated using ReneSANCe to be $\pm$0.00032 or better. Combining this with left-right asymmetry measurements from muons and taus under the assumption of lepton universality yields a projected overall uncertainty of $\pm$0.00019 on sin$^2\theta_W$ with SuperKEKB upgraded to have polarized electron beams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16592v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caleb Miller, J. Michael Roney</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
