<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Weakly supervised anomaly detection for resonant new physics in the dijet final state using proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV with the ATLAS detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An anomaly detection search for narrow-width resonances beyond the Standard Model that decay into a pair of jets is presented. The search is based on 139 fb$^{-1}$ of proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s}=13$ TeV recorded during 2015-2018 with the ATLAS detector at the Large Hadron Collider. The analysis is optimized without a particular signal model and aims to be sensitive to a broad range of new physics. It uses two different machine learning strategies to estimate the background in different signal regions. In each region, a weakly supervised classifier is trained to distinguish this background estimate from data. The analysis focuses on events with high transverse momentum jets reconstructed as large-radius jets. The mass and substructure of these jets are used as inputs to the classifiers. After a classifier-based selection, the distribution of the invariant mass of the two jets is used to search for potential local excesses. The model-independent results of both the anomaly detection methods show no signs of significant local excesses. In addition to model-independent results, a representative set of signal models is injected into the data, and the sensitivity of the methods to these scenarios is reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09770v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of the P_ccbars(4459)0 in Upsilon(1S, 2S) inclusive decays at Belle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using data samples of 102 million Upsilon(1S) events and 158 million Upsilon(2S) events collected by the Belle detector at the KEKB asymmetric-energy e+e- collider, we search for [udsccbar] pentaquark states decaying to Jpsi Lambda. Using the first observations of Upsilon(1S, 2S) inclusive decays to Jpsi Lambda, we find evidence of the P_ccbars(4459)0 state with a significance of 3.3 standard deviations, including statistical and systematic uncertainties. We measure the mass and width of the Pccbars(4459)0 to be (4471.7 +- 4.8 +- 0.6) MeV/c2 and (21.9 +- 13.1 +- 2.7) MeV, respectively. The branching fractions for P_ccbars(4459)0 production are measured to be B[Upsilon(1S) -&gt; P_ccbars(4459)0/ Pbar_ccbars(4459)0 + anything] = (3.5 +- 2.0 +- 0.2)*10-6 and B[Upsilin(2S) -&gt; P_ccbars(4459)0/ Pbar_ccbars(4459)0 +anything] = (2.9 +- 1.7 +- 0.4)*10-6. The inclusive branching fractions of Upsilon(1S, 2S) -&gt; Jpsi Lambda/Lambdabar are measured to be B[Upsilin(1S) -&gt; Jpsi Lambda/Lambdabar + anything] = (36.9 +- 5.3 +- 2.4)*10-6 and B[Upsilon(2S) -&gt; Jpsi Lambda/Lambdabar + anything] = (22.3 +- 5.7 +- 3.1)*10-6. We measure the visible cross section sigma(e+e- -&gt; Jpsi Lambda/Lambdabar + anything) = (90 +- 14 +- 6) fb for the continuum production at sqrt(s) = 10.52 GeV. In all cases, the first uncertainties are statistical and the second are systematic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09951v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Adachi, L. Aggarwal, H. Ahmed, J. K. Ahn, H. Aihara, N. Akopov, M. Alhakami, A. Aloisio, N. Althubiti, D. M. Asner, H. Atmacan, V. Aushev, M. Aversano, R. Ayad, V. Babu, H. Bae, N. K. Baghel, S. Bahinipati, P. Bambade, Sw. Banerjee, S. Bansal, M. Barrett, M. Bartl, J. Baudot, A. Baur, A. Beaubien, F. Becherer, J. Becker, J. V. Bennett, F. U. Bernlochner, V. Bertacchi, M. Bertemes, E. Bertholet, M. Bessner, S. Bettarini, V. Bhardwaj, B. Bhuyan, F. Bianchi, D. Biswas, D. Bodrov, A. Bolz, A. Boschetti, A. Bozek, M. Bracko, P. Branchini, R. A. Briere, T. E. Browder, A. Budano, S. Bussino, Q. Campagna, M. Campajola, L. Cao, G. Casarosa, C. Cecchi, J. Cerasoli, M. -C. Chang, P. Chang, R. Cheaib, P. Cheema, B. G. Cheon, K. Chilikin, K. Chirapatpimol, H. -E. Cho, K. Cho, S. -J. Cho, S. -K. Choi, S. Choudhury, J. Cochran, L. Corona, J. X. Cui, E. De La Cruz-Burelo, S. A. De La Motte, G. De Nardo, G. De Pietro, R. de Sangro, M. Destefanis, S. Dey, R. Dhamija, F. Di Capua, J. Dingfelder, Z. Dolezal, I. Domnguez Jimenez, T. V. Dong, X. Dong, D. Dossett, K. Dugic, G. Dujany, P. Ecker, J. Eppelt, P. Feichtinger, T. Ferber, T. Fillinger, C. Finck, G. Finocchiaro, F. Forti, B. G. Fulsom, A. Gabrielli, E. Ganiev, M. Garcia-Hernandez, G. Gaudino, V. Gaur, A. Gellrich, G. Ghevondyan, D. Ghosh, H. Ghumaryan, G. Giakoustidis, R. Giordano, A. Giri, P. Gironella Gironell, A. Glazov, B. Gobbo, R. Godang, P. Goldenzweig, E. Graziani, D. Greenwald, Z. Gruberova, Y. Guan, K. Gudkova, I. Haide, Y. Han, C. Harris, K. Hayasaka, H. Hayashii, S. Hazra, C. Hearty, M. T. Hedges, A. Heidelbach, I. Heredia de la Cruz, M. Hernandez Villanueva, T. Higuchi, M. Hoek, M. Hohmann, R. Hoppe, P. Horak, C. -L. Hsu, T. Humair, T. Iijima, K. Inami, N. Ipsita, A. Ishikawa, R. Itoh, M. Iwasaki, P. Jackson, D. Jacobi, W. W. Jacobs, E. -J. Jang, Q. P. Ji, S. Jia, Y. Jin, A. Johnson, K. K. Joo, H. Junkerkalefeld, M. Kaleta, J. Kandra, K. H. Kang, S. Kang, G. Karyan, T. Kawasaki, F. Keil, C. Ketter, C. Kiesling, C. -H. Kim, D. Y. Kim, J. -Y. Kim, K. -H. Kim, Y. -K. Kim, H. Kindo, K. Kinoshita, P. Kodys, T. Koga, S. Kohani, K. Kojima, A. Korobov, S. Korpar, E. Kovalenko, P. Krizan, P. Krokovny, T. Kuhr, Y. Kulii, D. Kumar, R. Kumar, K. Kumara, T. Kunigo, A. Kuzmin, Y. -J. Kwon, S. Lacaprara, K. Lalwani, T. Lam, J. S. Lange, T. S. Lau, M. Laurenza, R. Leboucher, F. R. Le Diberder, M. J. Lee, C. Lemettais, P. Leo, P. M. Lewis, C. Li, L. K. Li, Q. M. Li, W. Z. Li, Y. Li, Y. B. Li, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, J. Lin, M. H. Liu, Q. Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, D. Liventsev, S. Longo, C. Lyu, Y. Ma, C. Madaan, M. Maggiora, S. P. Maharana, R. Maiti, G. Mancinelli, R. Manfredi, E. Manoni, M. Mantovano, D. Marcantonio, S. Marcello, C. Marinas, C. Martellini, A. Martens, A. Martini, T. Martinov, L. Massaccesi, M. Masuda, D. Matvienko, S. K. Maurya, M. Maushart, J. A. McKenna, R. Mehta, F. Meier, D. Meleshko, M. Merola, C. Miller, M. Mirra, S. Mitra, K. Miyabayashi, H. Miyake, R. Mizuk, G. B. Mohanty, S. Mondal, S. Moneta, H. -G. Moser, R. Mussa, I. Nakamura, M. Nakao, H. Nakazawa, Y. Nakazawa, M. Naruki, Z. Natkaniec, A. Natochii, M. Nayak, G. Nazaryan, M. Neu, S. Nishida, S. Ogawa, H. Ono, Y. Onuki, F. Otani, G. Pakhlova, S. Pardi, K. Parham, H. Park, J. Park, K. Park, S. -H. Park, B. Paschen, S. Patra, T. K. Pedlar, I. Peruzzi, R. Peschke, R. Pestotnik, M. Piccolo, L. E. Piilonen, P. L. M. Podesta-Lerma, T. Podobnik, S. Pokharel, C. Praz, S. Prell, E. Prencipe, M. T. Prim, H. Purwar, P. Rados, G. Raeuber, S. Raiz, N. Rauls, K. Ravindran, J. U. Rehman, M. Reif, S. Reiter, M. Remnev, L. Reuter, D. Ricalde Herrmann, I. Ripp-Baudot, G. Rizzo, M. Roehrken, J. M. Roney, A. Rostomyan, N. Rout, D. A. Sanders, S. Sandilya, L. Santelj, V. Savinov, B. Scavino, J. Schmitz, S. Schneider, G. Schnell, C. Schwanda, Y. Seino, A. Selce, K. Senyo, J. Serrano, M. E. Sevior, C. Sfienti, W. Shan, C. Sharma, X. D. Shi, T. Shillington, T. Shimasaki, J. -G. Shiu, D. Shtol, A. Sibidanov, F. Simon, J. B. Singh, J. Skorupa, M. Sobotzik, A. Soffer, A. Sokolov, E. Solovieva, S. Spataro, B. Spruck, W. Song, M. Staric, P. Stavroulakis, S. Stefkova, R. Stroili, J. Strube, Y. Sue, M. Sumihama, K. Sumisawa, W. Sutcliffe, N. Suwonjandee, H. Svidras, M. Takahashi, M. Takizawa, U. Tamponi, K. Tanida, F. Tenchini, A. Thaller, O. Tittel, R. Tiwary, E. Torassa, K. Trabelsi, I. Tsaklidis, M. Uchida, I. Ueda, K. Unger, Y. Unno, K. Uno, S. Uno, P. Urquijo, Y. Ushiroda, S. E. Vahsen, R. van Tonder, M. Veronesi, A. Vinokurova, V. S. Vismaya, L. Vitale, V. Vobbilisetti, R. Volpe, A. Vossen, M. Wakai, S. Wallner, M. -Z. Wang, X. L. Wang, Z. Wang, A. Warburton, M. Watanabe, S. Watanuki, C. Wessel, E. Won, X. P. Xu, B. D. Yabsley, S. Yamada, S. B. Yang, J. Yelton, J. H. Yin, K. Yoshihara, C. Z. Yuan, J. Yuan, L. Zani, F. Zeng, B. Zhang, J. S. Zhou, Q. D. Zhou, L. Zhu, V. I. Zhukova, R. Zlebck, S. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing neutrinoless double beta decay event kinematics in a xenon gas detector with vertex tagging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If neutrinoless double beta decay is discovered, the next natural step would be understanding the lepton number violating physics responsible for it. Several alternatives exist beyond the exchange of light neutrinos. Some of these mechanisms can be distinguished by measuring phase-space observables, namely the opening angle $\cos\theta$ among the two decay electrons, and the electron energy spectra, $T_1$ and $T_2$. In this work, we study the statistical accuracy and precision in measuring these kinematic observables in a future xenon gas detector with the added capability to precisely locate the decay vertex. For realistic detector conditions (a gas pressure of 10 bar and spatial resolution of 4 mm), we find that the average $\overline{\cos\theta}$ and $\overline{T_1}$ values can be reconstructed with a precision of 0.19 and 110 keV, respectively, assuming that only 10 neutrinoless double beta decay events are detected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10198v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> NEXT Collaboration, M. Mart\'inez-Vara, K. Mistry, F. Pompa, B. J. P. Jones, J. Mart\'in-Albo, M. Sorel, C. Adams, H. Almaz\'an, V. \'Alvarez, B. Aparicio, A. I. Aranburu, L. Arazi, I. J. Arnquist, F. Auria-Luna, S. Ayet, C. D. R. Azevedo, K. Bailey, F. Ballester, M. del Barrio-Torregrosa, A. Bayo, J. M. Benlloch-Rodr\'iguez, F. I. G. M. Borges, A. Brodolin, N. Byrnes, S. C\'arcel, A. Castillo, E. Church, L. Cid, C. A. N. Conde, T. Contreras, F. P. Coss\'io, R. Coupe, E. Dey, G. D\'iaz, C. Echevarria, M. Elorza, J. Escada, R. Esteve, R. Felkai, L. M. P. Fernandes, P. Ferrario, A. L. Ferreira, F. W. Foss, Z. Freixa, J. Garc\'ia-Barrena, J. J. G\'omez-Cadenas, J. W. R. Grocott, R. Guenette, J. Hauptman, C. A. O. Henriques, J. A. Hernando Morata, P. Herrero-G\'omez, V. Herrero, C. Herv\'es Carrete, Y. Ifergan, F. Kellerer, L. Larizgoitia, A. Larumbe, P. Lebrun, F. Lopez, N. L\'opez-March, R. Madigan, R. D. P. Mano, A. P. Marques, G. Mart\'inez-Lema, R. L. Miller, J. Molina-Canteras, F. Monrabal, C. M. B. Monteiro, F. J. Mora, K. E. Navarro, P. Novella, A. Nu\~nez, D. R. Nygren, E. Oblak, J. Palacio, B. Palmeiro, A. Para, I. Parmaksiz, A. Pazos, J. Pelegrin, M. P\'erez Maneiro, M. Querol, J. Renner, I. Rivilla, C. Rogero, L. Rogers, B. Romeo, C. Romo-Luque, V. San Nacienciano, F. P. Santos, J. M. F. dos Santos, M. Seemann, I. Shomroni, P. A. O. C. Silva, A. Sim\'on, S. R. Soleti, J. Soto-Oton, J. M. R. Teixeira, S. Teruel-Pardo, J. F. Toledo, C. Tonnel\'e, S. Torelli, J. Torrent, A. Trettin, A. Us\'on, P. R. G. Valle, J. F. C. A. Veloso, J. Waiton, A. Yubero-Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angular analysis of $B^0\rightarrow K^{*0}e^{+}e^{-}$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An angular analysis of $B^0\rightarrow K^{*0}e^{+}e^{-}$ decays is presented using proton-proton collision data collected by the LHCb experiment at centre-of-mass energies of 7, 8 and 13 TeV, corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 9 fb$^{-1}$. The analysis is performed in the region of the dilepton invariant mass squared of 1.1-6.0 GeV$^{2}/c^{4}$. In addition, a test of lepton flavour universality is performed by comparing the obtained angular observables with those measured in $B^0\rightarrow K^{*0}\mu^{+}\mu^{-}$ decays. In general, the angular observables are found to be consistent with the Standard Model expectations as well as with global analyses of other $b \rightarrow s \ell^{+} \ell^{-}$ processes, where $\ell$ is either a muon or an electron. No sign of lepton-flavour-violating effects is observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10291v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, A. A. Adefisoye, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, M. Alexander, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, A. Andreianov, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, D. Andreou, A. Anelli, D. Ao, F. Archilli, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, R. Ata\'ide Da Silva, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, W. Baldini, L. Balzani, H. Bao, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, C. Barbero Pretel, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, M. Barnyakov, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, M. Bartolini, J. Bartz, J. M. Basels, S. Bashir, G. Bassi, B. Batsukh, P. B. Battista, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, N. A. Behling, S. Belin, V. Bellee, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, J. Bhom, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, N. Bondar, A. Bordelius, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, S. A. Bouchiba, M. Bovill, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, E. Buchanan, A. Buonaura, L. Buonincontri, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, A. Caillet, R. Calabrese, S. Calderon Ramirez, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, P. Camargo Magalhaes, J. I. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, J. Castro Godinez, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, D. Cervenkov, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, E. Chatzianagnostou, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, S. Chen, Z. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, X. Chiotopoulos, V. Chobanova, S. Cholak, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, P. Collins, T. Colombo, M. Colonna, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, E. Curras Rivera, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, A. Danilina, P. d'Argent, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, A. Davis, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, F. De Benedetti, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, V. Dedu, S. Dekkers, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, L. Dittmann, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, A. D. Dowling, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, O. D. Durmus, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, E. Epple, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, L. N. Falcao, Y. Fan, B. Fang, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, A. Fernandez Casani, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, K. L. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, F. Fleuret, M. Fontana, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, V. Franco Lima, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, J. Fu, Q. F\"uhring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, E. Gabriel, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, B. Ganie, H. Gao, R. Gao, T. Q. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, M. Garau, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, K. G. Garg, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, R. E. Geertsema, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, S. Ghizzo, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, L. Girardey, P. Gironella Gironell, C. Giugliano, M. A. Giza, E. L. Gkougkousis, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, A. Gomes, S. Gomez Fernandez, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, L. Guerry, M. Guittiere, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, K. Habermann, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, J. Haimberger, M. Hajheidari, G. Hallett, M. M. Halvorsen, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, M. Hartmann, S. Hashmi, J. He, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, P. Herrero Gascon, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, G. Hijano Mendizabal, D. Hill, S. E. Hollitt, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Huang, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Inglessi, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, R. Jacobsson, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, A. John Rubesh Rajan, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, J. Juan Castella, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, M. Kane, Y. Kang, C. Kar, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, A. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, M. K. Kazanecki, F. Keizer, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, O. Kshyvanskyi, S. Kubis, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, B. K. Kutsenko, D. Lacarrere, P. Laguarta Gonzalez, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, R. Lane, G. Lanfranchi, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, E. Lemos Cid, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, E. D. Lesser, B. Leverington, A. Li, C. Li, H. Li, K. Li, L. Li, M. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, Q. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, S. Libralon, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, V. Lisovskyi, R. Litvinov, F. L. Liu, G. Liu, K. Liu, S. Liu, W. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, J. Lomba Castro, T. Long, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, Q. Lu, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, M. Lucio Martinez, V. Lukashenko, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, R. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, B. Mack, I. Mackay, L. M. Mackey, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. J. Madurai, A. Maevskiy, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, M. W. Majewski, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, E. Mariani, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, L. Martel, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Massafferri, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, J. Mazorra de Cos, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, L. Mcconnell, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, F. M. Meng, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, S. Mokhnenko, E. F. Molina Cardenas, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. Mu\~noz-Rojas, R. Murta, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, Q. Niu, P. Nogarolli, P. Nogga, N. S. Nolte, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, S. Okamura, A. Okhotnikov, O. Okhrimenko, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, D. Osthues, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, F. Paciolla, A. Padee, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, P. R. Pais, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, A. Paul, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, J. Peng, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, H. Pereira Da Costa, A. Pereiro Castro, P. Perret, A. Perro, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, J. P. Pfaller, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, L. Piccolo, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, T. Poeschl, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, D. Provenzano, V. Pugatch, G. Punzi, S. Qasim, Q. Q. Qian, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, V. Ramos De Oliveira, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, R. Ribatti, G. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, J. Roensch, A. Rogachev, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, M. Romero Lamas, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, T. Rong, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, A. Ryzhikov, J. Ryzka, J. J. Saavedra-Arias, J. J. Saborido Silva, R. Sadek, N. Sagidova, D. Sahoo, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, A. Sarnatskiy, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, F. Sborzacchi, L. G. Scantlebury Smead, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, S. Schulte, M. H. Schune, R. Schwemmer, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, T. Senger, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, R. S. Sharma, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, Q. Shi, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, N. Skidmore, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, J. C. Smallwood, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, A. Snoch, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, I. Solovyev, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, O. Stenyakin, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, Y. Sun, D. Sundfeld, W. Sutcliffe, P. N. Swallow, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, Y. Tan, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, E. Ursov, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, V. Valcarce Cadenas, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, G. Vasquez, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Verdoglia, M. Vesterinen, D. Vico Benet, P. Vidrier Villalba, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, G. Vouters, C. Vrahas, J. Wagner, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, C. Wang, G. Wang, H. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. W. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, M. Waterlaat, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, J. Wendel, B. D. C. Westhenry, C. White, M. Whitehead, E. Whiter, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, Z. Williams, F. F. Wilson, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, Y. Wu, Z. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, A. Xu, J. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, D. Yang, K. Yang, S. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, X. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, Y Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, F. Zenesini, C. Zeng, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zharkova, A. Zhelezov, S. Z. Zheng, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antimatter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12128v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article we concisely explain: what antimatter is, its differentiation between primordial and secondary, how it is produced, where it can be found, the experiments carried out at CERN to create and analyze antiatoms, the problem of the matter-antimatter asymmetry, and the medical and technological applications of antimatter in our society.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12128v1</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatriz Gato-Rivera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B\to K\sf{+}invisible$, dark matter, and $CP$ violation in hyperon decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09603v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently the Belle II Collaboration has reported a measurement of the $B^+\to K^+\nu\bar\nu$ rate that is higher than the standard-model expectation. Since the emitted neutrinos are unobserved, the excess could be due to the $B^+$ decaying into a $K^+$ and a dark-matter pair. We entertain this possibility in a two-Higgs-doublet model supplemented with a real singlet scalar boson acting as the dark matter. This model also accommodates strangeness-changing interactions providing new sources of $CP$ violation which can affect hyperon and kaon nonleptonic transitions. We find that the resulting $CP$ violation in the hyperon sector can be significant, reaching the current empirical bounds, after taking into account constraints from kaon mixing and decay and from dark-matter relic-density data and direct searches including the Migdal effect. We demonstrate that the hyperon and kaon processes are complementary probes of this new-physics scenario. Its prediction for sizable hyperon $CP$ violation is potentially testable in ongoing experiments, such as BESIII, Belle II, and LHCb, and in next-generation ones like PANDA and at the Super Tau Charm Facility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09603v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Gang He, Xiao-Dong Ma, Jusak Tandean, German Valencia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Custodial Naturalness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09699v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Custodial Naturalness is a new symmetry-based idea to explain the large separation between the electroweak~(EW) scale and ultraviolet completions of the Standard Model~(SM). Classical scale invariance is combined with an enhanced scalar-sector custodial symmetry and both are spontaneously broken by dimensional transmutation at a new intermediate scale. The SM-like Higgs boson is an elementary pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone-Boson~(pNGB) of the extended custodial symmetry, which naturally explains the suppression of the EW scale without a little hierarchy problem. We explain details of the general mechanism, its minimal realization and simplest extensions which populate Higgs-, gauge-, and neutrino portals and introduce candidates for particle Dark Matter~(DM). We show the stability of the mechanism under inclusion of new sources of explicit custodial symmetry violation, as well as under variations of boundary conditions at the high scale. Custodial Naturalness is experimentally testable -- including a specific correlation between the Higgs and top quark masses, as well as by the prediction of a new heavy $Z'$ gauge boson and a new dilaton-like scalar which are well-motivated targets for future colliders and Higgs factories. The cosmological evolution features a strongly supercooled phase transition implying that consequences of Custodial Naturalness may also be tested by gravitational wave observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09699v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thede de Boer, Manfred Lindner, Andreas Trautner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fiber-coupled Digital Photo Sensors for Large Time Projection Chambers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach to addressing challenges in neutrino event reconstruction within large Time Projection Chambers (TPCs). By integrating fiber-coupled digital silicon photomultipliers, we propose a design that enhances light detection, improves energy resolution, and enhance event reconstruction. Advancements in power and signal over fiber technologies are leveraged to deploy digital sensors within the TPC bulk volume, enabling precise timing and robust particle identification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09729v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pieter Alexander Breur, Xavier Defay, David Jackson, James Robert Sinclair, Elizabeth Triller, Andrew Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nonfactorizable QED correction to the $\overline{B}_{s}$ ${\to}$ $D_{s}^{(\ast)} {\ell} \bar{\nu}_{\ell}$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09883v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Considering the nonfactorizable QED corrections, the branching ratios and ratios of branching ratios $R(D_{s}^{({\ast})})$ for the semileptonic $\overline{B}_{s}$ ${\to}$ $D_{s}^{(\ast)} {\ell} \bar{\nu}_{\ell}$ decays are reevaluated. It is found that (a) the QED contributions can enhance the branching ratios and reduce the ratios $R(D_{s}^{({\ast})})$. (b) The $SU(3)$ flavor symmetry holds basically well in the ratios $R(D)$-$R(D^{\ast})$ for the semileptonic charmed $\overline{B}_{u,d,s}$ decays. (c) The current theoretical uncertainties of branching ratios ${\cal B}(\overline{B}_{s} {\to} D_{s}^{\ast} {\ell} \bar{\nu}_{\ell})$ from the form factors are very large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09883v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueling Yang, Jiazhi Li, Liting Wang, Junfeng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity study of a sapphire detector using Coherent Elastic Neutrino-Nucleus Scattering process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09972v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Indian Coherent Neutrino-nucleus Scattering Experiment(ICNSE) has been proposed at Bhabha Atomic Research Centre in India to measure the coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering process using electron antineutrinos produced from reactors. Phenomenological studies are performed to find out the sensitivity of sapphire detector for various fundamental physics parameters at an exposure of one year. Reactors of different core compositions, sizes, and thermal powers have been considered as sources of electron antineutrinos. The potential of the ICNSE to measure the weak mixing angle at a low energy regime has been extracted. Furthermore, the detector's capability has been investigated for examining the electromagnetic properties of neutrinos, including their magnetic moment. Additionally, an exploration has been conducted on the detector's sensitivity in restricting new interactions between neutrinos and electrons or nuclei, thereby constraining the parameter space related to light mediators. It is found that the ICNSE detector can put a stronger constraints on the scalar and vector mediators masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09972v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. P. Behera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights on the Scale of Leptogenesis from Neutrino Masses and Neutrinoless Double-Beta Decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the thermal leptogenesis scenario in the type-I seesaw framework featuring three heavy Majorana neutrinos with a hierarchical mass spectrum. We focus on low energy observables, specifically the lightest neutrino mass $m_{\nu}^{\rm lightest}$ and the neutrinoless double-beta decay effective mass parameter $m^{\rm eff}_{\beta\beta}$. In particular, we numerically calculate the minimum mass of the lightest heavy Majorana neutrino, $M_1^{\rm min}$, required for successful leptogenesis as a function of $m_{\nu}^{\rm lightest}$ and $m_{\beta\beta}^{\rm eff}$, considering both normal and inverted light neutrino mass orderings. Flavour effects are taken into account within the flavoured density matrix formalism. We also examine the interplay between fine-tuned cancellations in the seesaw relation and $M_1^{\rm min}$. Recent and forthcoming searches for neutrinoless double-beta decay, along with cosmological probes of the sum of neutrino masses, motivate this analysis, as they can provide key insights into the minimal scale of thermal leptogenesis and its broader implications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10093v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Granelli, Koichi Hamaguchi, Maura E. Ramirez-Quezada, Kengo Shimada, Juntaro Wada, Tatsuya Yokoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing anomaly detection with topology-aware autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10163v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Anomaly detection in high-energy physics is essential for identifying new physics beyond the Standard Model. Autoencoders provide a signal-agnostic approach but are limited by the topology of their latent space. This work explores topology-aware autoencoders, embedding phase-space distributions onto compact manifolds that reflect energy-momentum conservation. We construct autoencoders with spherical ($S^n$), product ($S^2 \otimes S^2$), and projective ($\mathbb{RP}^2$) latent spaces and compare their anomaly detection performance against conventional Euclidean embeddings. Our results show that autoencoders with topological priors significantly improve anomaly separation by preserving the global structure of the data manifold and reducing spurious reconstruction errors. Applying our approach to simulated hadronic top-quark decays, we show that latent spaces with appropriate topological constraints enhance sensitivity and robustness in detecting anomalous events. This study establishes topology-aware autoencoders as a powerful tool for unsupervised searches for new physics in particle-collision data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10163v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishal S. Ngairangbam, B{\l}a\.zej Rozwoda, Kazuki Sakurai, Michael Spannowsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recasting the ATLAS search for displaced hadronic jets in the ATLAS calorimeter with additional jets or leptons using surrogate models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10231v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This note describes the validation of a new form of re-interpretation material provided by an ATLAS search for hadronically-decaying neutral long-lived particles in association with jets or leptons, using the full Run-2 dataset. This reference ATLAS analysis provided a set of machine-learning-based "surrogate models" which return the probability of an event being selected in a given channel of the analysis, using as input truth-level kinematic information (decay position, transverse momentum and decay products of the long-lived particles). In this document, we describe the surrogate model framework in detail, and how it responds to issues identified in other re-interpretation procedures. We describe independent validations of the surrogate models' performance in reproducing the original analysis results -- first using a standalone framework and then employing the HackAnalysis framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10231v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louie Corpe, Abdelhamid Haddad, Mark Goodsell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Attenuation Effects: Sensitivity Ceilings for Spin-Dependent and Spin-Independent Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10251v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Direct detection experiments aimed at uncovering the elusive nature of dark matter (DM) have made significant progress in probing ever lower cross-sections for DM-nucleon interactions. At the same time, an upper limit in the cross-section sensitivity region is present due to DM scattering in the Earth and atmosphere and as a result never reaching the detector. We investigate the impact of this effect for both spin-dependent and spin-independent interactions. In contrast to previous studies that assume a straight line path for DM scattering we employ a semi-analytic diffusion model that takes into account the impact of potentially large angle deviations prevalent for light DM masses. We find that for sufficiently low energy thresholds, this difference in modelling impacts the DM interaction cross-section sensitivity. This study evaluates the impact in the context of the QUEST-DMC experiment, which utilises surface-based detectors with superfluid Helium-3 bolometers to search for sub-GeV DM exploiting low energy threshold. At masses below 1 GeV$/c^2$ the deviation between the two frameworks becomes pronounced. The ceiling sensitivity limit for QUEST-DMC on spin-dependent DM-neutron cross-sections is $\sim 3 \times 10^{-24}$ cm$^2$ using the diffusive framework and approximately doubles with the straight-line path DM scattering. Similarly, for spin-independent DM-nucleon cross-sections, the ceiling limit is $\sim 7.5 \times 10^{-27}$ cm$^2$ under the diffusive framework and also increases about a factor of two with the straight-line path approximation, within the mass range of 0.025-5 GeV$/c^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10251v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> DMC Collaboration, N. Darvishi, J. Smirnov, S. Autti, L. Bloomfield, A. Casey, N. Eng, P. Franchini, R. P. Haley, P. J. Heikkinen, A. Jennings, A. Kemp, E. Leason, J. March-Russell, A. Mayer, J. Monroe, D. Munstermann, M. T. Noble, J. R. Prance, X. Rojas, T. Salmon, J. Saunders, R. Smith, M. D. Thompson, A. Thomson, A. Ting, V. Tsepelin, S. M. West, L. Whitehead, D. E. Zmeev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NA62e+: dark sector searches with high intensity positron beams in ECN3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10346v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark sector models present a rich phenomenology that requires high-intensity beams and precision detectors for thorough exploration. The NA62 experiment has already published several constraints on dark sector candidates, leveraging proton beam dump and meson decay techniques. This proposal seeks to significantly enhance NA62's discovery potential for dark sector candidates by using the positron-on-target technique. High intensity and high-energy positron beams, reaching up to $\sim$150 GeV energy, have already been produced at the SPS extracted beam lines. If a positron beam with an intensity in the range of 2$\times10^{14}$ positrons on target per year is delivered to the present K12 beam line, the NA62 detector would be ideal for searches of dark sector particles in both visible and invisible decay channels. Additionally, this approach would enable precision measurement of key standard model observable, including a detailed scan of $\sigma(e^+e^-\to\pi^+\pi^-$) and $\sigma(e^+e^-\to\mu^+\mu^-)$ at the di-pion and di-muon production threshold, with discovery potential for the True Muonium ($\mu^+\mu^-$) bound state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10346v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Arias-Arag\'on, L. Darm\'e, R. Gargiulo, G. Grilli di Cortona, V. Kozhuharov, E. Nardi, M. Raggi, T. Spadaro, P. Valente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for the FCNC charmonium decay $J/\psi \to D^0 \mu^+ \mu^- + \text{c.c.}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08080v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Based on a data sample of $(10087 \pm 44) \times 10^6$ $J/\psi$ events taken with the BESIII detector, we search for the flavor-changing neutral current charmonium decay $J/\psi \to D^{0} \mu^{+} \mu^{-} + \text{c.c.}$. No significant signal above the background is observed, and the upper limit on its branching fraction is set to be $\mathcal{B}(J/\psi \to D^{0}\mu^{+}\mu^{-} + \text{c.c.} ) &lt; 1.1 \times 10^{-7}$ at the 90% confidence level. This marks the first search for a flavor-changing neutral current charmonium decay involving muons in the final state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08080v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> BESIII Collaboration, M. Ablikim, M. N. Achasov, P. Adlarson, X. C. Ai, R. Aliberti, A. Amoroso, Q. An, Y. Bai, O. Bakina, Y. Ban, H. -R. Bao, V. Batozskaya, K. Begzsuren, N. Berger, M. Berlowski, M. Bertani, D. Bettoni, F. Bianchi, E. Bianco, A. Bortone, I. Boyko, R. A. Briere, A. Brueggemann, H. Cai, M. H. Cai, X. Cai, A. Calcaterra, G. F. Cao, N. Cao, S. A. Cetin, X. Y. Chai, J. F. Chang, G. R. Che, Y. Z. Che, G. Chelkov, C. Chen, C. H. Chen, Chao Chen, G. Chen, H. S. Chen, H. Y. Chen, M. L. Chen, S. J. Chen, S. L. Chen, S. M. Chen, T. Chen, X. R. Chen, X. T. Chen, Y. B. Chen, Y. Q. Chen, Z. J. Chen, Z. K. Chen, S. K. Choi, X. Chu, G. Cibinetto, F. Cossio, J. J. Cui, H. L. Dai, J. P. Dai, A. Dbeyssi, R. E. de Boer, D. Dedovich, C. Q. Deng, Z. Y. Deng, A. Denig, I. Denysenko, M. Destefanis, F. De Mori, B. Ding, X. X. Ding, Y. Ding, Y. Ding, Y. X. Ding, J. Dong, L. Y. Dong, M. Y. Dong, X. Dong, M. C. Du, S. X. Du, Y. Y. Duan, Z. H. Duan, P. Egorov, G. F. Fan, J. J. Fan, Y. H. Fan, J. Fang, J. Fang, S. S. Fang, W. X. Fang, Y. Q. Fang, R. Farinelli, L. Fava, F. Feldbauer, G. Felici, C. Q. Feng, J. H. Feng, Y. T. Feng, M. Fritsch, C. D. Fu, J. L. Fu, Y. W. Fu, H. Gao, X. B. Gao, Y. N. Gao, Y. N. Gao, Y. Y. Gao, Yang Gao, S. Garbolino, I. Garzia, P. T. Ge, Z. W. Ge, C. Geng, E. M. Gersabeck, A. Gilman, K. Goetzen, J. D. Gong, L. Gong, W. X. Gong, W. Gradl, S. Gramigna, M. Greco, M. H. Gu, Y. T. Gu, C. Y. Guan, A. Q. Guo, L. B. Guo, M. J. Guo, R. P. Guo, Y. P. Guo, A. Guskov, J. Gutierrez, K. L. Han, T. T. Han, F. Hanisch, K. D. Hao, X. Q. Hao, F. A. Harris, K. K. He, K. L. He, F. H. Heinsius, C. H. Heinz, Y. K. Heng, C. Herold, T. Holtmann, P. C. Hong, G. Y. Hou, X. T. Hou, Y. R. Hou, Z. L. Hou, B. Y. Hu, H. M. Hu, J. F. Hu, Q. P. Hu, S. L. Hu, T. Hu, Y. Hu, Z. M. Hu, G. S. Huang, K. X. Huang, L. Q. Huang, P. Huang, X. T. Huang, Y. P. Huang, Y. S. Huang, T. Hussain, N. H\"usken, N. in der Wiesche, J. Jackson, S. Janchiv, Q. Ji, Q. P. Ji, W. Ji, X. B. Ji, X. L. Ji, Y. Y. Ji, Z. K. Jia, D. Jiang, H. B. Jiang, P. C. Jiang, S. J. Jiang, T. J. Jiang, X. S. Jiang, Y. Jiang, J. B. Jiao, J. K. Jiao, Z. Jiao, S. Jin, Y. Jin, M. Q. Jing, X. M. Jing, T. Johansson, S. Kabana, N. Kalantar-Nayestanaki, X. L. Kang, X. S. Kang, M. Kavatsyuk, B. C. Ke, V. Khachatryan, A. Khoukaz, R. Kiuchi, O. B. Kolcu, B. Kopf, M. Kuessner, X. Kui, N. Kumar, A. Kupsc, W. K\"uhn, Q. Lan, W. N. Lan, T. T. Lei, M. Lellmann, T. Lenz, C. Li, C. Li, C. H. Li, C. K. Li, Cheng Li, D. M. Li, F. Li, G. Li, H. B. Li, H. J. Li, H. N. Li, Hui Li, J. R. Li, J. S. Li, K. Li, K. L. Li, K. L. Li, L. J. Li, Lei Li, M. H. Li, M. R. Li, P. L. Li, P. R. Li, Q. M. Li, Q. X. Li, R. Li, T. Li, T. Y. Li, W. D. Li, W. G. Li, X. Li, X. H. Li, X. L. Li, X. Y. Li, X. Z. Li, Y. Li, Y. G. Li, Y. P. Li, Z. J. Li, Z. Y. Li, C. Liang, H. Liang, Y. F. Liang, Y. T. Liang, G. R. Liao, L. B. Liao, M. H. Liao, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, A. Limphirat, C. C. Lin, C. X. Lin, D. X. Lin, L. Q. Lin, T. Lin, B. J. Liu, B. X. Liu, C. Liu, C. X. Liu, F. Liu, F. H. Liu, Feng Liu, G. M. Liu, H. Liu, H. B. Liu, H. H. Liu, H. M. Liu, Huihui Liu, J. B. Liu, J. J. Liu, K. Liu, K. Liu, K. Y. Liu, Ke Liu, L. Liu, L. C. Liu, Lu Liu, P. L. Liu, Q. Liu, S. B. Liu, T. Liu, W. K. Liu, W. M. Liu, W. T. Liu, X. Liu, X. Liu, X. Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. B. Liu, Z. A. Liu, Z. D. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, X. C. Lou, F. X. Lu, H. J. Lu, J. G. Lu, Y. Lu, Y. H. Lu, Y. P. Lu, Z. H. Lu, C. L. Luo, J. R. Luo, J. S. Luo, M. X. Luo, T. Luo, X. L. Luo, Z. Y. Lv, X. R. Lyu, Y. F. Lyu, Y. H. Lyu, F. C. Ma, H. Ma, H. L. Ma, J. L. Ma, L. L. Ma, L. R. Ma, Q. M. Ma, R. Q. Ma, R. Y. Ma, T. Ma, X. T. Ma, X. Y. Ma, Y. M. Ma, F. E. Maas, I. MacKay, M. Maggiora, S. Malde, Y. J. Mao, Z. P. Mao, S. Marcello, F. M. Melendi, Y. H. Meng, Z. X. Meng, J. G. Messchendorp, G. Mezzadri, H. Miao, T. J. Min, R. E. Mitchell, X. H. Mo, B. Moses, N. Yu. Muchnoi, J. Muskalla, Y. Nefedov, F. Nerling, L. S. Nie, I. B. Nikolaev, Z. Ning, S. Nisar, Q. L. Niu, W. D. Niu, S. L. Olsen, Q. Ouyang, S. Pacetti, X. Pan, Y. Pan, A. Pathak, Y. P. Pei, M. Pelizaeus, H. P. Peng, Y. Y. Peng, K. Peters, J. L. Ping, R. G. Ping, S. Plura, V. Prasad, F. Z. Qi, H. R. Qi, M. Qi, S. Qian, W. B. Qian, C. F. Qiao, J. H. Qiao, J. J. Qin, J. L. Qin, L. Q. Qin, L. Y. Qin, P. B. Qin, X. P. Qin, X. S. Qin, Z. H. Qin, J. F. Qiu, Z. H. Qu, C. F. Redmer, A. Rivetti, M. Rolo, G. Rong, S. S. Rong, F. Rosini, Ch. Rosner, M. Q. Ruan, S. N. Ruan, N. Salone, A. Sarantsev, Y. Schelhaas, K. Schoenning, M. Scodeggio, K. Y. Shan, W. Shan, X. Y. Shan, Z. J. Shang, J. F. Shangguan, L. G. Shao, M. Shao, C. P. Shen, H. F. Shen, W. H. Shen, X. Y. Shen, B. A. Shi, H. Shi, J. L. Shi, J. Y. Shi, S. Y. Shi, X. Shi, H. L. Song, J. J. Song, T. Z. Song, W. M. Song, Y. X. Song, S. Sosio, S. Spataro, F. Stieler, S. S Su, Y. J. Su, G. B. Sun, G. X. Sun, H. Sun, H. K. Sun, J. F. Sun, K. Sun, L. Sun, S. S. Sun, T. Sun, Y. C. Sun, Y. H. Sun, Y. J. Sun, Y. Z. Sun, Z. Q. Sun, Z. T. Sun, C. J. Tang, G. Y. Tang, J. Tang, L. F. Tang, M. Tang, Y. A. Tang, L. Y. Tao, M. Tat, J. X. Teng, J. Y. Tian, W. H. Tian, Y. Tian, Z. F. Tian, I. Uman, B. Wang, B. Wang, Bo Wang, C. Wang, Cong Wang, D. Y. Wang, H. J. Wang, J. J. Wang, K. Wang, L. L. Wang, L. W. Wang, M. Wang, M. Wang, N. Y. Wang, S. Wang, T. Wang, T. J. Wang, W. Wang, W. Wang, W. P. Wang, X. Wang, X. F. Wang, X. J. Wang, X. L. Wang, X. N. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. D. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. H. Wang, Y. L. Wang, Y. N. Wang, Y. Q. Wang, Yaqian Wang, Yi Wang, Yuan Wang, Z. Wang, Z. L. Wang, Z. L. Wang, Z. Q. Wang, Z. Y. Wang, D. H. Wei, H. R. Wei, F. Weidner, S. P. Wen, Y. R. Wen, U. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. Wolke, C. Wu, J. F. Wu, L. H. Wu, L. J. Wu, Lianjie Wu, S. G. Wu, S. M. Wu, X. Wu, X. H. Wu, Y. J. Wu, Z. Wu, L. Xia, X. M. Xian, B. H. Xiang, T. Xiang, D. Xiao, G. Y. Xiao, H. Xiao, Y. L. Xiao, Z. J. Xiao, C. Xie, K. J. Xie, X. H. Xie, Y. Xie, Y. G. Xie, Y. H. Xie, Z. P. Xie, T. Y. Xing, C. F. Xu, C. J. Xu, G. F. Xu, H. Y. Xu, H. Y. Xu, M. Xu, Q. J. Xu, Q. N. Xu, W. L. Xu, X. P. Xu, Y. Xu, Y. Xu, Y. C. Xu, Z. S. Xu, H. Y. Yan, L. Yan, W. B. Yan, W. C. Yan, W. P. Yan, X. Q. Yan, H. J. Yang, H. L. Yang, H. X. Yang, J. H. Yang, R. J. Yang, T. Yang, Y. Yang, Y. F. Yang, Y. H. Yang, Y. Q. Yang, Y. X. Yang, Y. Z. Yang, M. Ye, M. H. Ye, Junhao Yin, Z. Y. You, B. X. Yu, C. X. Yu, G. Yu, J. S. Yu, M. C. Yu, T. Yu, X. D. Yu, Y. C. Yu, C. Z. Yuan, H. Yuan, J. Yuan, J. Yuan, L. Yuan, S. C. Yuan, Y. Yuan, Z. Y. Yuan, C. X. Yue, Ying Yue, A. A. Zafar, S. H. Zeng, X. Zeng, Y. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, X. Y. Zhai, Y. H. Zhan, A. Q. Zhang, B. L. Zhang, B. X. Zhang, D. H. Zhang, G. Y. Zhang, G. Y. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. C. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. Q. Zhang, H. R. Zhang, H. Y. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. J. Zhang, J. L. Zhang, J. Q. Zhang, J. S. Zhang, J. W. Zhang, J. X. Zhang, J. Y. Zhang, J. Z. Zhang, Jianyu Zhang, L. M. Zhang, Lei Zhang, N. Zhang, P. Zhang, Q. Zhang, Q. Y. Zhang, R. Y. Zhang, S. H. Zhang, Shulei Zhang, X. M. Zhang, X. Y Zhang, X. Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. T. Zhang, Y. H. Zhang, Y. M. Zhang, Z. D. Zhang, Z. H. Zhang, Z. L. Zhang, Z. L. Zhang, Z. X. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Z. Zhang, Zh. Zh. Zhang, G. Zhao, J. Y. Zhao, J. Z. Zhao, L. Zhao, Lei Zhao, M. G. Zhao, N. Zhao, R. P. Zhao, S. J. Zhao, Y. B. Zhao, Y. L. Zhao, Y. X. Zhao, Z. G. Zhao, A. Zhemchugov, B. Zheng, B. M. Zheng, J. P. Zheng, W. J. Zheng, X. R. Zheng, Y. H. Zheng, B. Zhong, X. Zhong, H. Zhou, J. Q. Zhou, J. Y. Zhou, S. Zhou, X. Zhou, X. K. Zhou, X. R. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, Y. Z. Zhou, Z. C. Zhou, A. N. Zhu, J. Zhu, K. Zhu, K. J. Zhu, K. S. Zhu, L. Zhu, L. X. Zhu, S. H. Zhu, T. J. Zhu, W. D. Zhu, W. D. Zhu, W. J. Zhu, W. Z. Zhu, Y. C. Zhu, Z. A. Zhu, X. Y. Zhuang, J. H. Zou, J. Zu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Holes as Fermion Factories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00741v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultralight bosons near rotating black holes can undergo significant growth through superradiant energy extraction, potentially reaching field values close to the Planck scale and transforming black holes into effective transducers for these fields. The interaction between boson fields and fermions may lead to parametric production or Schwinger pair production of fermions, with efficiencies significantly exceeding those of perturbative decay processes. Additionally, the spatial gradients of scalar clouds and the electric components of vector clouds can accelerate fermions, resulting in observable fluxes. This study considers both Standard Model neutrinos and dark sector fermions, which could contribute to boosted dark matter. Energy loss due to fermion emissions can potentially quench the exponential growth of the cloud, leading to a saturated state. This dynamic provides a framework for establishing limits on boson-neutrino interactions, previously constrained by neutrino self-interaction considerations. In the saturation phase, boson clouds have the capacity to accelerate fermions to TeV energies, producing fluxes that surpass those from atmospheric neutrinos near black holes. These fluxes open new avenues for observations through high-energy neutrino detectors like IceCube, as well as through dark matter direct detection efforts focused on targeted black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00741v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/02/035</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP02(2025)035</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Chen, Xiao Xue, Vitor Cardoso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Production of $\eta$ and $\eta'$ mesons in $pp$ and $p$Pb collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17326v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The production of $\eta$ and $\eta'$ mesons is studied in proton-proton and proton-lead collisions collected with the LHCb detector. Proton-proton collisions are studied at center-of-mass energies of $5.02$ and $13~{\rm TeV}$, and proton-lead collisions are studied at a center-of-mass energy per nucleon of $8.16~{\rm TeV}$. The studies are performed in center-of-mass rapidity regions $2.5&lt;y_{\rm c.m.}&lt;3.5$ (forward rapidity) and $-4.0&lt;y_{\rm c.m.}&lt;-3.0$ (backward rapidity) defined relative to the proton beam direction. The $\eta$ and $\eta'$ production cross sections are measured differentially as a function of transverse momentum for $1.5&lt;p_{\rm T}&lt;10~{\rm GeV}$ and $3&lt;p_{\rm T}&lt;10~{\rm GeV}$, respectively. The differential cross sections are used to calculate nuclear modification factors. The nuclear modification factors for $\eta$ and $\eta'$ mesons agree at both forward and backward rapidity, showing no significant evidence of mass dependence. The differential cross sections of $\eta$ mesons are also used to calculate $\eta/\pi^0$ cross section ratios, which show evidence of a deviation from the world average. These studies offer new constraints on mass-dependent nuclear effects in heavy-ion collisions, as well as $\eta$ and $\eta'$ meson fragmentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17326v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.109.024907</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. C109 (2024), 024907</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij, A. S. W. Abdelmotteleb, C. Abellan Beteta, F. Abudin\'en, T. Ackernley, B. Adeva, M. Adinolfi, P. Adlarson, C. Agapopoulou, C. A. Aidala, Z. Ajaltouni, S. Akar, K. Akiba, P. Albicocco, J. Albrecht, F. Alessio, M. Alexander, A. Alfonso Albero, Z. Aliouche, P. Alvarez Cartelle, R. Amalric, S. Amato, J. L. Amey, Y. Amhis, L. An, L. Anderlini, M. Andersson, A. Andreianov, P. Andreola, M. Andreotti, D. Andreou, A. A. Anelli, D. Ao, F. Archilli, M. Argenton, S. Arguedas Cuendis, A. Artamonov, M. Artuso, E. Aslanides, M. Atzeni, B. Audurier, D. Bacher, I. Bachiller Perea, S. Bachmann, M. Bachmayer, J. J. Back, A. Bailly-reyre, P. Baladron Rodriguez, V. Balagura, W. Baldini, J. Baptista de Souza Leite, M. Barbetti, I. R. Barbosa, R. J. Barlow, S. Barsuk, W. Barter, M. Bartolini, F. Baryshnikov, J. M. Basels, G. Bassi, B. Batsukh, A. Battig, A. Bay, A. Beck, M. Becker, F. Bedeschi, I. B. Bediaga, A. Beiter, S. Belin, V. Bellee, K. Belous, I. Belov, I. Belyaev, G. Benane, G. Bencivenni, E. Ben-Haim, A. Berezhnoy, R. Bernet, S. Bernet Andres, H. C. Bernstein, C. Bertella, A. Bertolin, C. Betancourt, F. Betti, J. Bex, Ia. Bezshyiko, J. Bhom, M. S. Bieker, N. V. Biesuz, P. Billoir, A. Biolchini, M. Birch, F. C. R. Bishop, A. Bitadze, A. Bizzeti, M. P. Blago, T. Blake, F. Blanc, J. E. Blank, S. Blusk, D. Bobulska, V. Bocharnikov, J. A. Boelhauve, O. Boente Garcia, T. Boettcher, A. Bohare, A. Boldyrev, C. S. Bolognani, R. Bolzonella, N. Bondar, F. Borgato, S. Borghi, M. Borsato, J. T. Borsuk, S. A. Bouchiba, T. J. V. Bowcock, A. Boyer, C. Bozzi, M. J. Bradley, S. Braun, A. Brea Rodriguez, N. Breer, J. Brodzicka, A. Brossa Gonzalo, J. Brown, D. Brundu, A. Buonaura, L. Buonincontri, A. T. Burke, C. Burr, A. Bursche, A. Butkevich, J. S. Butter, J. Buytaert, W. Byczynski, S. Cadeddu, H. Cai, R. Calabrese, L. Calefice, S. Cali, M. Calvi, M. Calvo Gomez, J. Cambon Bouzas, P. Campana, D. H. Campora Perez, A. F. Campoverde Quezada, S. Capelli, L. Capriotti, R. Caravaca-Mora, A. Carbone, L. Carcedo Salgado, R. Cardinale, A. Cardini, P. Carniti, L. Carus, A. Casais Vidal, R. Caspary, G. Casse, J. Castro Godinez, M. Cattaneo, G. Cavallero, V. Cavallini, S. Celani, J. Cerasoli, D. Cervenkov, S. Cesare, A. J. Chadwick, I. Chahrour, M. Charles, Ph. Charpentier, C. A. Chavez Barajas, M. Chefdeville, C. Chen, S. Chen, A. Chernov, S. Chernyshenko, V. Chobanova, S. Cholak, M. Chrzaszcz, A. Chubykin, V. Chulikov, P. Ciambrone, M. F. Cicala, X. Cid Vidal, G. Ciezarek, P. Cifra, P. E. L. Clarke, M. Clemencic, H. V. Cliff, J. Closier, J. L. Cobbledick, C. Cocha Toapaxi, V. Coco, J. Cogan, E. Cogneras, L. Cojocariu, P. Collins, T. Colombo, A. Comerma-Montells, L. Congedo, A. Contu, N. Cooke, I. Corredoira, A. Correia, G. Corti, J. J. Cottee Meldrum, B. Couturier, D. C. Craik, M. Cruz Torres, R. Currie, C. L. Da Silva, S. Dadabaev, L. Dai, X. Dai, E. Dall'Occo, J. Dalseno, C. D'Ambrosio, J. Daniel, A. Danilina, P. d'Argent, A. Davidson, J. E. Davies, A. Davis, O. De Aguiar Francisco, C. De Angelis, J. de Boer, K. De Bruyn, S. De Capua, M. De Cian, U. De Freitas Carneiro Da Graca, E. De Lucia, J. M. De Miranda, L. De Paula, M. De Serio, D. De Simone, P. De Simone, F. De Vellis, J. A. de Vries, F. Debernardis, D. Decamp, V. Dedu, L. Del Buono, B. Delaney, H. -P. Dembinski, J. Deng, V. Denysenko, O. Deschamps, F. Dettori, B. Dey, P. Di Nezza, I. Diachkov, S. Didenko, S. Ding, V. Dobishuk, A. D. Docheva, A. Dolmatov, C. Dong, A. M. Donohoe, F. Dordei, A. C. dos Reis, L. Douglas, A. G. Downes, W. Duan, P. Duda, M. W. Dudek, L. Dufour, V. Duk, P. Durante, M. M. Duras, J. M. Durham, A. Dziurda, A. Dzyuba, S. Easo, E. Eckstein, U. Egede, A. Egorychev, V. Egorychev, C. Eirea Orro, S. Eisenhardt, E. Ejopu, S. Ek-In, L. Eklund, M. Elashri, J. Ellbracht, S. Ely, A. Ene, E. Epple, S. Escher, J. Eschle, S. Esen, T. Evans, F. Fabiano, L. N. Falcao, Y. Fan, B. Fang, L. Fantini, M. Faria, K. Farmer, D. Fazzini, L. Felkowski, M. Feng, M. Feo, M. Fernandez Gomez, A. D. Fernez, F. Ferrari, F. Ferreira Rodrigues, S. Ferreres Sole, M. Ferrillo, M. Ferro-Luzzi, S. Filippov, R. A. Fini, M. Fiorini, M. Firlej, K. M. Fischer, D. S. Fitzgerald, C. Fitzpatrick, T. Fiutowski, F. Fleuret, M. Fontana, F. Fontanelli, L. F. Foreman, R. Forty, D. Foulds-Holt, M. Franco Sevilla, M. Frank, E. Franzoso, G. Frau, C. Frei, D. A. Friday, L. Frontini, J. Fu, Q. Fuehring, Y. Fujii, T. Fulghesu, E. Gabriel, G. Galati, M. D. Galati, A. Gallas Torreira, D. Galli, S. Gambetta, M. Gandelman, P. Gandini, H. Gao, R. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, Y. Gao, M. Garau, L. M. Garcia Martin, P. Garcia Moreno, J. Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, B. Garcia Plana, K. G. Garg, L. Garrido, C. Gaspar, R. E. Geertsema, L. L. Gerken, E. Gersabeck, M. Gersabeck, T. Gershon, Z. Ghorbanimoghaddam, L. Giambastiani, F. I. Giasemis, V. Gibson, H. K. Giemza, A. L. Gilman, M. Giovannetti, A. Giovent\`u, P. Gironella Gironell, C. Giugliano, M. A. Giza, E. L. Gkougkousis, F. C. Glaser, V. V. Gligorov, C. G\"obel, E. Golobardes, D. Golubkov, A. Golutvin, A. Gomes, S. Gomez Fernandez, F. Goncalves Abrantes, M. Goncerz, G. Gong, J. A. Gooding, I. V. Gorelov, C. Gotti, J. P. Grabowski, L. A. Granado Cardoso, E. Graug\'es, E. Graverini, L. Grazette, G. Graziani, A. T. Grecu, L. M. Greeven, N. A. Grieser, L. Grillo, S. Gromov, C. Gu, M. Guarise, M. Guittiere, V. Guliaeva, P. A. G\"unther, A. -K. Guseinov, E. Gushchin, Y. Guz, T. Gys, T. Hadavizadeh, C. Hadjivasiliou, G. Haefeli, C. Haen, J. Haimberger, M. Hajheidari, T. Halewood-leagas, M. M. Halvorsen, P. M. Hamilton, J. Hammerich, Q. Han, X. Han, S. Hansmann-Menzemer, L. Hao, N. Harnew, T. Harrison, M. Hartmann, C. Hasse, J. He, K. Heijhoff, F. Hemmer, C. Henderson, R. D. L. Henderson, A. M. Hennequin, K. Hennessy, L. Henry, J. Herd, J. Heuel, A. Hicheur, D. Hill, S. E. Hollitt, J. Horswill, R. Hou, Y. Hou, N. Howarth, J. Hu, J. Hu, W. Hu, X. Hu, W. Huang, W. Hulsbergen, R. J. Hunter, M. Hushchyn, D. Hutchcroft, M. Idzik, D. Ilin, P. Ilten, A. Inglessi, A. Iniukhin, A. Ishteev, K. Ivshin, R. Jacobsson, H. Jage, S. J. Jaimes Elles, S. Jakobsen, E. Jans, B. K. Jashal, A. Jawahery, V. Jevtic, E. Jiang, X. Jiang, Y. Jiang, Y. J. Jiang, M. John, D. Johnson, C. R. Jones, T. P. Jones, S. Joshi, B. Jost, N. Jurik, I. Juszczak, D. Kaminaris, S. Kandybei, Y. Kang, M. Karacson, D. Karpenkov, M. Karpov, A. M. Kauniskangas, J. W. Kautz, F. Keizer, D. M. Keller, M. Kenzie, T. Ketel, A. Khanal, B. Khanji, A. Kharisova, S. Kholodenko, G. Khreich, T. Kirn, V. S. Kirsebom, O. Kitouni, S. Klaver, N. Kleijne, K. Klimaszewski, M. R. Kmiec, S. Koliiev, L. Kolk, A. Konoplyannikov, P. Kopciewicz, P. Koppenburg, M. Korolev, I. Kostiuk, O. Kot, S. Kotriakhova, A. Kozachuk, P. Kravchenko, L. Kravchuk, M. Kreps, S. Kretzschmar, P. Krokovny, W. Krupa, W. Krzemien, J. Kubat, S. Kubis, W. Kucewicz, M. Kucharczyk, V. Kudryavtsev, E. Kulikova, A. Kupsc, B. K. Kutsenko, D. Lacarrere, A. Lai, A. Lampis, D. Lancierini, C. Landesa Gomez, J. J. Lane, R. Lane, C. Langenbruch, J. Langer, O. Lantwin, T. Latham, F. Lazzari, C. Lazzeroni, R. Le Gac, S. H. Lee, R. Lef\`evre, A. Leflat, S. Legotin, M. Lehuraux, O. Leroy, T. Lesiak, B. Leverington, A. Li, H. Li, K. Li, L. Li, P. Li, P. -R. Li, S. Li, T. Li, T. Li, Y. Li, Y. Li, Z. Li, Z. Lian, X. Liang, C. Lin, T. Lin, R. Lindner, V. Lisovskyi, R. Litvinov, G. Liu, H. Liu, K. Liu, Q. Liu, S. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. L. Liu, A. Lobo Salvia, A. Loi, J. Lomba Castro, T. Long, J. H. Lopes, A. Lopez Huertas, S. L\'opez Soli\~no, G. H. Lovell, C. Lucarelli, D. Lucchesi, S. Luchuk, M. Lucio Martinez, V. Lukashenko, Y. Luo, A. Lupato, E. Luppi, K. Lynch, X. -R. Lyu, G. M. Ma, R. Ma, S. Maccolini, F. Machefert, F. Maciuc, I. Mackay, L. R. Madhan Mohan, M. M. Madurai, A. Maevskiy, D. Magdalinski, D. Maisuzenko, M. W. Majewski, J. J. Malczewski, S. Malde, B. Malecki, L. Malentacca, A. Malinin, T. Maltsev, G. Manca, G. Mancinelli, C. Mancuso, R. Manera Escalero, D. Manuzzi, D. Marangotto, J. F. Marchand, R. Marchevski, U. Marconi, S. Mariani, C. Marin Benito, J. Marks, A. M. Marshall, P. J. Marshall, G. Martelli, G. Martellotti, L. Martinazzoli, M. Martinelli, D. Martinez Santos, F. Martinez Vidal, A. Massafferri, M. Materok, R. Matev, A. Mathad, V. Matiunin, C. Matteuzzi, K. R. Mattioli, A. Mauri, E. Maurice, J. Mauricio, P. Mayencourt, M. Mazurek, M. McCann, L. Mcconnell, T. H. McGrath, N. T. McHugh, A. McNab, R. McNulty, B. Meadows, P. Medley, G. Meier, D. Melnychuk, M. Merk, A. Merli, L. Meyer Garcia, D. Miao, H. Miao, M. Mikhasenko, D. A. Milanes, A. Minotti, E. Minucci, T. Miralles, S. E. Mitchell, B. Mitreska, D. S. Mitzel, A. Modak, A. M\"odden, R. A. Mohammed, R. D. Moise, S. Mokhnenko, T. Momb\"acher, M. Monk, I. A. Monroy, S. Monteil, A. Morcillo Gomez, G. Morello, M. J. Morello, M. P. Morgenthaler, J. Moron, A. B. Morris, A. G. Morris, R. Mountain, H. Mu, Z. M. Mu, E. Muhammad, F. Muheim, M. Mulder, K. M\"uller, F. M\~unoz-Rojas, R. Murta, P. Naik, T. Nakada, R. Nandakumar, T. Nanut, I. Nasteva, M. Needham, N. Neri, S. Neubert, N. Neufeld, P. Neustroev, R. Newcombe, J. Nicolini, D. Nicotra, E. M. Niel, N. Nikitin, P. Nogga, N. S. Nolte, C. Normand, J. Novoa Fernandez, G. Nowak, C. Nunez, H. N. Nur, A. Oblakowska-Mucha, V. Obraztsov, T. Oeser, S. Okamura, R. Oldeman, F. Oliva, M. Olocco, C. J. G. Onderwater, R. H. O'Neil, J. M. Otalora Goicochea, T. Ovsiannikova, P. Owen, A. Oyanguren, O. Ozcelik, K. O. Padeken, B. Pagare, P. R. Pais, T. Pajero, A. Palano, M. Palutan, G. Panshin, L. Paolucci, A. Papanestis, M. Pappagallo, L. L. Pappalardo, C. Pappenheimer, C. Parkes, B. Passalacqua, G. Passaleva, D. Passaro, A. Pastore, M. Patel, J. Patoc, C. Patrignani, C. J. Pawley, A. Pellegrino, M. Pepe Altarelli, S. Perazzini, D. Pereima, A. Pereiro Castro, P. Perret, A. Perro, K. Petridis, A. Petrolini, S. Petrucci, H. Pham, L. Pica, M. Piccini, B. Pietrzyk, G. Pietrzyk, D. Pinci, F. Pisani, M. Pizzichemi, V. Placinta, M. Plo Casasus, F. Polci, M. Poli Lener, A. Poluektov, N. Polukhina, I. Polyakov, E. Polycarpo, S. Ponce, D. Popov, S. Poslavskii, K. Prasanth, C. Prouve, V. Pugatch, V. Puill, G. Punzi, H. R. Qi, W. Qian, N. Qin, S. Qu, R. Quagliani, R. I. Rabadan Trejo, B. Rachwal, J. H. Rademacker, M. Rama, M. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, M. Ramos Pernas, M. S. Rangel, F. Ratnikov, G. Raven, M. Rebollo De Miguel, F. Redi, J. Reich, F. Reiss, Z. Ren, P. K. Resmi, R. Ribatti, G. R. Ricart, D. Riccardi, S. Ricciardi, K. Richardson, M. Richardson-Slipper, K. Rinnert, P. Robbe, G. Robertson, E. Rodrigues, E. Rodriguez Fernandez, J. A. Rodriguez Lopez, E. Rodriguez Rodriguez, A. Rogovskiy, D. L. Rolf, A. Rollings, P. Roloff, V. Romanovskiy, M. Romero Lamas, A. Romero Vidal, G. Romolini, F. Ronchetti, M. Rotondo, S. R. Roy, M. S. Rudolph, T. Ruf, M. Ruiz Diaz, R. A. Ruiz Fernandez, J. Ruiz Vidal, A. Ryzhikov, J. Ryzka, J. J. Saborido Silva, R. Sadek, N. Sagidova, N. Sahoo, B. Saitta, M. Salomoni, C. Sanchez Gras, I. Sanderswood, R. Santacesaria, C. Santamarina Rios, M. Santimaria, L. Santoro, E. Santovetti, A. Saputi, D. Saranin, G. Sarpis, M. Sarpis, A. Sarti, C. Satriano, A. Satta, M. Saur, D. Savrina, H. Sazak, L. G. Scantlebury Smead, A. Scarabotto, S. Schael, S. Scherl, A. M. Schertz, M. Schiller, H. Schindler, M. Schmelling, B. Schmidt, S. Schmitt, H. Schmitz, O. Schneider, A. Schopper, N. Schulte, S. Schulte, M. H. Schune, R. Schwemmer, G. Schwering, B. Sciascia, A. Sciuccati, S. Sellam, A. Semennikov, M. Senghi Soares, A. Sergi, N. Serra, L. Sestini, A. Seuthe, Y. Shang, D. M. Shangase, M. Shapkin, I. Shchemerov, L. Shchutska, T. Shears, L. Shekhtman, Z. Shen, S. Sheng, V. Shevchenko, B. Shi, E. B. Shields, Y. Shimizu, E. Shmanin, R. Shorkin, J. D. Shupperd, R. Silva Coutinho, G. Simi, S. Simone, N. Skidmore, R. Skuza, T. Skwarnicki, M. W. Slater, J. C. Smallwood, E. Smith, K. Smith, M. Smith, A. Snoch, L. Soares Lavra, M. D. Sokoloff, F. J. P. Soler, A. Solomin, A. Solovev, I. Solovyev, R. Song, Y. Song, Y. Song, Y. S. Song, F. L. Souza De Almeida, B. Souza De Paula, E. Spadaro Norella, E. Spedicato, J. G. Speer, E. Spiridenkov, P. Spradlin, V. Sriskaran, F. Stagni, M. Stahl, S. Stahl, S. Stanislaus, E. N. Stein, O. Steinkamp, O. Stenyakin, H. Stevens, D. Strekalina, Y. Su, F. Suljik, J. Sun, L. Sun, Y. Sun, P. N. Swallow, K. Swientek, F. Swystun, A. Szabelski, T. Szumlak, M. Szymanski, Y. Tan, S. Taneja, M. D. Tat, A. Terentev, F. Terzuoli, F. Teubert, E. Thomas, D. J. D. Thompson, H. Tilquin, V. Tisserand, S. T'Jampens, M. Tobin, L. Tomassetti, G. Tonani, X. Tong, D. Torres Machado, L. Toscano, D. Y. Tou, C. Trippl, G. Tuci, N. Tuning, L. H. Uecker, A. Ukleja, D. J. Unverzagt, E. Ursov, A. Usachov, A. Ustyuzhanin, U. Uwer, V. Vagnoni, A. Valassi, G. Valenti, N. Valls Canudas, H. Van Hecke, E. van Herwijnen, C. B. Van Hulse, R. Van Laak, M. van Veghel, R. Vazquez Gomez, P. Vazquez Regueiro, C. V\'azquez Sierra, S. Vecchi, J. J. Velthuis, M. Veltri, A. Venkateswaran, M. Vesterinen, D. Vieira, M. Vieites Diaz, X. Vilasis-Cardona, E. Vilella Figueras, A. Villa, P. Vincent, F. C. Volle, D. vom Bruch, V. Vorobyev, N. Voropaev, K. Vos, G. Vouters, C. Vrahas, J. Walsh, E. J. Walton, G. Wan, C. Wang, G. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, J. Wang, M. Wang, N. W. Wang, R. Wang, X. Wang, X. W. Wang, Y. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Wang, J. A. Ward, N. K. Watson, D. Websdale, Y. Wei, B. D. C. Westhenry, D. J. White, M. Whitehead, A. R. Wiederhold, D. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. K. Wilkinson, M. Williams, M. R. J. Williams, R. Williams, F. F. Wilson, W. Wislicki, M. Witek, L. Witola, C. P. Wong, G. Wormser, S. A. Wotton, H. Wu, J. Wu, Y. Wu, K. Wyllie, S. Xian, Z. Xiang, Y. Xie, A. Xu, J. Xu, L. Xu, L. Xu, M. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, Z. Xu, D. Yang, S. Yang, X. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yang, Z. Yang, V. Yeroshenko, H. Yeung, H. Yin, C. Y. Yu, J. Yu, X. Yuan, E. Zaffaroni, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zdybal, M. Zeng, C. Zhang, D. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, S. Zhang, S. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Z. Zhang, Y. Zhao, A. Zharkova, A. Zhelezov, X. Z. Zheng, Y. Zheng, T. Zhou, X. Zhou, Y. Zhou, V. Zhovkovska, L. Z. Zhu, X. Zhu, X. Zhu, Z. Zhu, V. Zhukov, J. Zhuo, Q. Zou, D. Zuliani, G. Zunica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$Ab$-$initio$ nucleon-nucleon correlations and their impact on high energy $^{16}$O+$^{16}$O collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08385v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Investigating nucleon-nucleon correlations inherent to the strong nuclear force is one of the core goals in nuclear physics research. We showcase the unique opportunities offered by collisions of $^{16}$O nuclei at high-energy facilities to reveal detailed many-body properties of the nuclear ground state. We interface existing knowledge about the geometry of $^{16}$O coming from \textit{ab-initio} calculations of nuclear structure with transport simulations of high-energy $^{16}$O+$^{16}$O collisions. Bulk observables in these processes, such as the elliptic flow or the fluctuations of the mean transverse momentum, are found to depend significantly on the input nuclear model and to be sensitive to realistic clustering and short-range repulsive correlations, effectively opening a new avenue to probe these features experimentally. This finding demonstrates collisions of oxygen nuclei as a tool to elucidate initial conditions of small collision systems while fostering connections with effective field theories of nuclei rooted in quantum chromodynamics (QCD).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08385v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunjian Zhang, Jinhui Chen, Giuliano Giacalone, Shengli Huang, Jiangyong Jia, Yu-Gang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lighting up the Photon Wigner Distribution via Dilepton Productions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07634v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic investigation of lepton pair production through photon-photon fusion processes in heavy-ion collisions. It is demonstrated that the dilepton production at a given impact parameter ($b_\perp$) with a fixed transverse momentum imbalance ($q_\perp$) can be factorized into a unified formula in terms of the Wigner photon distribution of heavy nuclei. We show that this framework provides a comprehensive description of all the relevant data from RHIC to the LHC, with a strong evidence that the quasi-real photon can be radiated not only from the nucleus as a whole, standing for the coherent contribution, but also from the sub-structures inside the nucleus, representing the incoherent contribution. Further predictions are made for the anisotropies in the correlations between $q_\perp$, $b_\perp$, and the dilepton transverse momentum ($P_\perp$). This will help us to constrain the photon Wigner distribution which plays a crucial role to study the gluonic matter of nucleus at small-$x$ through the diffractive photoproduction processes in heavy ion collision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07634v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Shi, Lin Chen, Shu-Yi Wei, Bo-Wen Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Line shape of the $J\psi \to \gamma \eta_{c}$ decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01984v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An accurate description of the photon spectrum line shape is essential for extracting resonance parameters of the $\eta_c$ meson through the radiative transition $J/\psi \to \gamma \eta_{c}$. However, a persistent challenge remains in the form of a divergent tail at high photon energies, arising from the $E_{\gamma}^3$ factor in theoretical calculations. Various damping functions have been proposed to mitigate this effect in practical experiments, but their empirical nature lacks a rigorous theoretical basis. In this study, we introduce two key considerations: incorporating full-order contributions of the Bessel function in the overlap integral of charmonium wave functions and the phase space factor neglected in previous experimental studies. By accounting for these factors, we demonstrate a more rational and effective damping function of the divergent tail associated with the $E_{\gamma}^3$ term. We present the implications of these findings on experimental measurements and provide further insights through toy Monte Carlo simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01984v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.016030</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D,111,016030 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ting Wang, Xiaolong Wang, Guangrui Liao, Kai Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Falsify String Theory at a Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13192v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The string landscape accommodates a broad range of possible effective field theories. This poses a challenge for extracting verifiable predictions as well as falsifiable signatures of string theory. Motivated by these considerations, in this work we observe that all known stringy Standard Models support only low-dimensional representations of the gauge group. While it is in principle possible to produce contrived models with higher-dimensional representations, these generically appear in a tower of states with lighter ones in lower-dimensional representations, i.e., not in isolation. With this in mind, we consider the phenomenologically well-motivated scenario given by adding a single Majorana field in a real, $n$-dimensional representation of $SU(2)_L$ with $n \geq 5$ \textit{and nothing else}. This scenario is not realized in any known string construction, and we conjecture that this is true of string theory in general. Detection of this scenario would thus amount to falsifying the (known) string landscape. We recast existing LHC searches for new electroweak states to extract updated bounds on this class of scenarios. Improved limits from future colliders and dark matter detection experiments provide additional routes to potentially falsifying string theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13192v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Baumgart, Panagiotis Christeas, Jonathan J. Heckman, Rebecca J. Hicks</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
