<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex</link>
    <description>hep-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 02:56:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning in online and offline reconstruction and identification with CMS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) plays an increasingly important role in both online and offline event reconstruction and identification at CMS experiment. A variety of ML techniques are used to improve the identification of physics objects. Dedicated algorithms enhance jet flavor tagging, including new approaches that strengthen sensitivity to Higgs boson decays to charm quarks. Tau identification has been significantly improved with ML-based methods, while in the electromagnetic calorimeter, ML-driven clustering techniques provide better energy reconstruction. Muon identification also benefits from multivariate approaches, leading to a higher signal efficiency and more background rejection. Looking at the future, ML will be central to the reconstruction strategy for the High-Granularity Calorimeter at high-luminosity LHC. New algorithms for the upgraded detectors are being developed to cope with extreme pileup conditions. All these advances ensure that CMS can fully exploit the physics potential of Run-3 and the HL-LHC, while also exploring novel ML strategies to maintain robust performance under evolving experimental conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08010v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uttiya Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing b-Jet Performance in the CMS High-Level Trigger with Run-3 Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The real-time identification and selection of b-jets play a crucial role in the CMS experiment, particularly in searches involving heavy-flavor jets. The High-Level Trigger (HLT) is designed to efficiently select events of interest while maintaining a manageable output rate of a few kilohertz. This report presents the commissioning and performance evaluation of b-jet triggers in the CMS HLT system using proton-proton collision data collected during Run-3 (2022-2024). Key aspects include algorithm optimization, efficiency studies, and comparisons with offline reconstruction. The results provide valuable insights into the current b-jet selection strategy and highlight potential refinements for future data-taking campaigns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08017v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uttiya Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on Higgs Light Yukawa Couplings with the CMS Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of the Higgs boson ten years ago and successful measurement of the Higgs boson couplings to third generation fermions by LHC mark great milestones for HEP. The much weaker coupling to the second generation quarks predicted by the SM makes the measurement of the light Yukawa Higgs couplings, as the Higgs-charm ones, much more challenging. With the latest tagging algorithms capabilities, a lot of progress has been made to constrain these couplings. In this talk, the latest results of direct and indirect measurements by the CMS experiment are presented. Prospects for future improvements are also given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08512v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Zucchetta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on non-standard neutrino interactions from Borexino extended data-set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutrino non-standard interactions (NSI) constitute an active research field, as they are closely related to potential new physics associated with dark matter searches and exotic interactions arising from fundamental symmetry violations. The Borexino's unprecedented sensitivity to solar neutrinos, derived from its low background and precision spectral measurements, enables stringent constraints on potential deviations from the standard three-flavor neutrino oscillation paradigm. This work presents an update on the analysis of flavor-diagonal NSI using the full Borexino Phase-III data set, extending the study previously reported in Constraints on flavor-diagonal non-standard neutrino interactions from Borexino Phase-II (JHEP 2020, 38). The updated analysis incorporates the extended temporal and statistical coverage of Phase-III. The results indicate improved sensitivity to the diagonal NSI parameters, with constraints exceeding those obtained in Phase-II. Furthermore, a more general analysis that includes all possible off-diagonal NSI terms is presented for the first time, providing a comprehensive exploration of the NSI parameter space associated with the flavors of the incoming and outgoing neutrinos. This work once again underlines Borexino's critical role in probing new physics scenarios and reinforces its legacy in neutrino research. Detailed comparisons with Phase-II results are discussed, along with implications for theoretical models of NSI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08685v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Antonelli, D. Basilico, G. Bellini, J. Benziger, R. Biondi, B. Caccianiga, F. Calaprice, A. Caminata, A. Chepurnov, D. D'Angelo, A. Derbin, A. Di Giacinto, V. Di Marcello, X. F. Ding, A. Di Ludovico, L. Di Noto, I. Drachnev, D. Franco, C. Galbiati, C. Ghiano, M. Giammarchi, A. Goretti, M. Gromov, D. Guffanti, Aldo Ianni, Andrea Ianni, A. Jany, V. Kobychev, G. Korga, S. Kumaran, M. Laubenstein, E. Litvinovich, P. Lombardi, I. Lomskaya, L. Ludhova, I. Machulin, J. Martyn, E. Meroni, L. Miramonti, M. Misiaszek, V. Muratova, L. Oberauer, V. Orekhov, F. Ortica, M. Pallavicini, L. Pelicci, O. Penek, L. Pietrofaccia, N. Pilipenko, A. Pocar, G. Raikov, M. T. Ranalli, G. Ranucci, A. Razeto, A. Re, N. Rossi, S. Schoenert, D. Semenov, G. Settanta, M. Skorokhvatov, A. Singhal, O. Smirnov, A. Sotnikov, G. Sun, R. Tartaglia, G. Testera, M. D. C. Torri, E. Unzhakov, A. Vishneva, R. B. Vogelaar, F. von Feilitzsch, M. Wojcik, M. Wurm, S. Zavatarelli, X. Zhou, K. Zuber, G. Zuzel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poisson Log-Normal Process for Count Data Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05926v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modeling count data is important in physics and other scientific disciplines, where measurements often involve discrete, non-negative quantities such as photon or neutrino detection events. Traditional parametric approaches can be trained to generate integer-count predictions but may struggle with capturing complex, non-linear dependencies often observed in the data. Gaussian process (GP) regression provides a robust non-parametric alternative to modeling continuous data; however, it cannot generate integer outputs. We propose the Poisson Log-Normal (PoLoN) process, a framework that employs GP to model Poisson log-rates. As in GP regression, our approach relies on the correlations between data points captured via GP kernel structure rather than explicit functional parameterizations. We demonstrate that the PoLoN predictive distribution is Poisson-LogNormal and provide an algorithm for optimizing kernel hyperparameters. Furthermore, we adapt the PoLoN approach to the problem of detecting weak localized signals superimposed on a smoothly varying background - a task of considerable interest in many areas of science and engineering. Our framework allows us to predict the strength, location and width of the detected signals. We evaluate PoLoN's performance using both synthetic and real-world datasets, including the open dataset from CERN which was used to detect the Higgs boson at the Large Hadron Collider. Our results indicate that the PoLoN process can be used as a non-parametric alternative for analyzing, predicting, and extracting signals from integer-valued data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05926v1</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anushka Saha, Abhijith Gandrakota, Alexandre V. Morozov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the Impact of Fitting Methodology at aN$^3$LO with FPPDF: an Open Source Tool for Extracting Parton Distribution Functions in the Hessian Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07118v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new public code, FPPDF, to perform global fits of parton distribution functions (PDFs). The fitting methodology follows that implemented by the MSHT collaboration, namely applying a fixed polynomial parameterisation of the PDFs and Hessian approach to error propagation, while for data and theory settings the libraries used by the NNPDF collaboration are taken. This therefore complements the already publicly available NNPDF fitting code to enable fits with both neural network and fixed polynomial PDF parameterisations to be performed by the community, with otherwise identical theoretical and experimental inputs. As a first application, we use the new code to compare the PDFs found from fits at both NNLO and aN$^3$LO perturbative orders, but applying these two fitting approaches. We assess the impact of the two different methodologies on the PDFs and their uncertainties, providing results that complement previous comparisons between published PDF sets at NNLO and aN$^3$LO. We in particular find that the relative impact of going to the higher perturbative order and/or including missing higher order uncertainties is rather insensitive to which of these PDF parameterisation methodologies are used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07118v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. M. Cruz-Martinez, T. Giani, L. A. Harland-Lang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Dirac neutrinos destabilize $\mathcal{Z}_2$ domain wall network?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In particle physics model building, a discrete $\mathcal{Z}_2$ symmetry is often spontaneously broken for phenomenological reasons. When this breaking occurs dynamically in the early Universe, stable domain wall networks are formed, which can eventually dominate the cosmic energy density. To avoid this problem, explicit $\mathcal{Z}_2$-breaking terms in the scalar potential are usually introduced in an ad hoc manner. In this Letter, we show that if the same $\mathcal{Z}_2$ symmetry is also responsible for generating light Dirac neutrino masses, such explicit breaking terms can instead arise radiatively from the particles involved in the Dirac mass generation. We find that the resulting bias term scales inversely with the cube of the Dirac neutrino mass, leading to a gravitational wave spectrum proportional to the sixth power of the Dirac neutrino mass. This establishes a nontrivial connection between the Dirac seesaw scale, the domain wall annihilation epoch, and the resulting stochastic gravitational wave signal. We further demonstrate that a wide range of Dirac seesaw scales can be probed by upcoming gravitational wave and cosmic microwave background experiments, while part of the parameter space simultaneously explains the observed baryon asymmetry via Dirac leptogenesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07380v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debasish Borah, Partha Kumar Paul, Narendra Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-Theoretic Gaps in Solar and Reactor Neutrino Oscillation Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum estimation theory provides a fundamental framework for analyzing how precisely physical parameters can be estimated from measurements. Neutrino oscillations are characterized by a set of parameters inferred from experiments conducted in different production and detection environments. The two solar oscillation parameters, $\Delta m^2_{21}$ and $\theta_{12}$, can be estimated using both solar neutrino experiments and reactor neutrino experiments. In reactor experiments, neutrinos are detected after coherent vacuum evolution, while solar neutrinos arrive at the detector as incoherent mixtures. In this work, we use Quantum Fisher Information (QFI) to quantify and compare the information content accessible in these two experimental setups. We find that for reactor neutrinos, flavor measurements saturate the QFI bound for both parameters over specific energy ranges, demonstrating their optimality and explaining the high precision achieved by these experiments. In contrast, for solar neutrinos the phase-based contribution to the QFI, originating from the quantum coherence, is absent, rendering the estimation of $\Delta m_{21}^2$ purely population-based and effectively classical, while the QFI for $\theta_{12}$ is dominated by basis rotation at high energies and is nearly saturated by flavor measurements. Consequently, solar neutrino experiments are intrinsically more sensitive to $\theta_{12}$ than to $\Delta m_{21}^2$. This analysis highlights a fundamental distinction between the two estimation problems and accounts for their differing achievable precisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07991v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neetu Raj Singh Chundawat, Yu-Feng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing $\alpha$ clustering in $^{12}\mathrm{C}$ at CSR energies using the Jet AA Microscopic Transport Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08288v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the sensitivity of low-energy nuclear collisions to intrinsic nuclear structure by studying the interplay between initial-state geometry and final-state observables in C+C and C+Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=2.36$~GeV, relevant for experiments at the Cooling Storage Ring (CSR) facility in Lanzhou and forthcoming experiments at the High Intensity heavy-ion Accelerator Facility (HIAF) in Huizhou. Calculations are performed within the Jet AA Microscopic Transport Model (JAM) using Woods--Saxon and triangular $\alpha$-clustered configurations for the $^{12}C$ nucleus. The initial geometry is characterized in terms of transverse size, compactness, eccentricities, and their event-by-event fluctuations. We find that $\alpha$ clustering leads to a more compact participant configuration than the Woods--Saxon case, while transverse-size and eccentricity fluctuations show only weak sensitivity to clustering. At this beam energy, radial observables remain sensitive to geometric compactness, with the proton mean transverse momentum $\langle p_T \rangle$ enhanced for $\alpha$-clustered configurations, whereas pions show little sensitivity. The anisotropic response is examined using flow harmonic coefficients. We find an enhancement of the mean flow magnitudes, $\langle v_n \rangle = \sqrt{\langle v_n^2\rangle}$, for $\alpha$-clustered configurations at large $N_{part}$, while the event-by-event fluctuation strength of individual harmonics remains small. Symmetric cumulants of the initial-state eccentricities show sensitivity to clustering, whereas the corresponding correlations among final-state flow harmonics do not exhibit a comparably strong separation. These results indicate that radial observables and correlation-based flow measurements provide complementary probes of $\alpha$ clustering in low-energy nuclear collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08288v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhash Singha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Light Dark Particles in Neutrino Scattering Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08314v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we investigate the production of a dark fermionic particle $\chi$ in the neutrino scattering experiments. In the framework of effective field theory, such process can be induced by the effective four-fermion interactions involving neutrinos, the dark particle $\chi$ and standard model particles. In particular, we examine the constraints on the effective couplings from the neutrinos scattering off nuclei in the COHERENT and CONUS+ experiments as well as the prospects at the DUNE near detector from neutrino-electron scattering. It turns out the current COHERENT and CONUS+ constraints on the cutoff scales are less stringent than those from the existing Large Hadron Collider data. However, the DUNE near detector could probe the cutoff scales beyond the existing CHARM II and LEP limits up to roughly 1 TeV, for the dark particle mass up to roughly 50 MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08314v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruofei Feng, Shao-Feng Ge, Yongchao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for the QCD Critical Point in High Energy Nuclear Collisions: A Status Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08356v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review recent results of net-proton multiplicity fluctuations from STAR experiment, aiming to locate the QCD critical point in high-energy nuclear collisions at RHIC. We show net-proton number cumulant and proton number factorial cumulant ratios up to fourth order using experimental data from RHIC BES-II Au+Au collisions in collider mode and fixed-target mode. The comparison is made between experimental data and non-critical model calculations from Lattice QCD, HRG, hydrodynamic simulations and transport model UrQMD. In addition, we discuss initial volume fluctuation effect, which plays significant role in fixed-target energies. Finally, an outlook on experimental research on the QCD critical point in future experiments will be presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08356v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhang, Zhaohui Wang, Xiaofeng Luo, Nu Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry-driven impact of photosensor placement on S2-based XY reconstruction in a dual-phase argon TPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08402v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate reconstruction of the horizontal vertex $(x,y)$ from the S2 electroluminescence pattern is essential for fiducialization and background rejection in dual-phase argon time projection chambers. In this work, we perform a Geant4-based simulation study using the G4DS framework to investigate how detector geometry, in particular the distance between the top photodetector plane and the gas pocket, impacts S2-based XY reconstruction. A compact dual-phase argon TPC instrumented with seven Hamamatsu R8520-506 PMTs is simulated with electron recoils at 41.5 keV (corresponding to the ${}^{83m}\mathrm{Kr}$ calibration energy), as well as 1.0 keV to probe the low-S2 regime. The PMT array height is scanned from 0 mm to 50 mm, and XY positions are reconstructed using a geometrical solid-angle (GSA) method with the S2 emission modeled by 1 mm-thick slices across the 7 mm gas pocket. The results show a clear non-monotonic dependence of reconstruction bias and resolution on PMT height, driven by the trade-off between S2 light sharing and photon statistics. These findings provide guidance for geometry optimization in future low-threshold dual-phase argon detectors and will be validated with upcoming prototype measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08402v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jilong Yin, Yi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrinoless double beta decays of hyperons in covariant chiral perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutrinoless double beta ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decays of spin-1/2 hyperons are investigated in a covariant baryon chiral perturbation theory framework, extended by a $\Delta L=2$ operator proportional to the Majorana neutrino mass, where $L$ denotes the lepton number. Within the light Majorana neutrino exchange mechanism, the decay amplitudes are found to emerge at the one-loop level, representing the long-range contribution. The extended-on-mass-shell scheme is employed to renormalize the one-loop amplitudes and restore consistent chiral power counting. Consequently, the differential decay rates for all accessible hyperon $0\nu\beta\beta$ channels are predicted and the corresponding branching ratios are more than 20 orders of magnitude smaller than the current experimental upper bounds. Interestingly, it is found that the leading contribution to hyperon $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay is actually from short-range counterterm operators, as required by the renormalization argument. Neutrinoless transition form factors are proposed to determine this leading contribution through future lattice QCD simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08453v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Ying Zhao, Ze-Rui Liang, Feng-Kun Guo, Li-Ping He, De-Liang Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge asymmetry in $e^{+}e^{-}\to B^{(*)}\bar{B}^{(*)}$ processes in the vicinity of $\Upsilon(4S)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08458v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The effects of isotopic invariance violation in the processes $e^{+}e^{-}\to B\bar{B}$, $e^{+}e^{-}\to B^{*}\bar{B}$, and $e^{+}e^{-}\to B^{*}\bar{B}^{*}$ are considered in the energy range between the thresholds of $B^{+}B^{-}$ and $B_{s}^{0}\bar{B}_{s}^{0}$ production. The analysis is based on taking into account the final-state interaction in a six-channel problem. Our approach allowed us to obtain good agreement with recent Belle-II results for the ratio of the $B^{0}\bar{B}^{0}$ and $B^{+}B^{-}$ production cross sections in $e^{+}e^{-}$ annihilation in the vicinity of $\Upsilon(4S)$. It is shown that at higher energies the ratios of the cross sections for pairs of neutral and charged $B^{(*)}$ mesons can differ significantly from unity. A detailed measurement of this effect will provide evidence that the nontrivial energy dependence of the $B^{(*)}\bar{B}^{(*)}$ production cross sections is a consequence of interference of the particle production amplitudes in the multichannel problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08458v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. G. Salnikov, A. I. Milstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global observables and identified-hadron production in pp, O-O and Pb-Pb collisions at LHC Run 3 energies with EPOS4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08534v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The observation of collectivity in small and large collision systems challenges our understanding of thermalization and particle production. EPOS4 models this via a dynamical core--corona separation, where high-density regions form a collectively expanding core while low-density regions hadronize via string fragmentation. Its microcanonical core hadronization improves the description of transverse momentum and multiplicity-dependent observables. We present EPOS4 predictions for pp, O-O and Pb-Pb collisions, with and without UrQMD, showing non-universal $\langle p_T\rangle$ scaling, significant hadronic-phase effects, and system-size-dependent $R_{AA}$ suppression. Charged-particle and transverse-energy densities show participant scaling; the transverse energy per charged particle is systematically larger in O--O than in Pb--Pb at comparable participant fraction, indicating a harder effective production in the lighter system. Identified-hadron spectra harden with event multiplicity with mass ordering and increasing core fractions. The mean transverse momentum exhibits a strong system dependence, with the steepest multiplicity evolution in pp, demonstrating that $\langle p_T\rangle$ does not follow universal multiplicity scaling. The $p/\pi$ ratio shows an enhanced intermediate-$p_T$ region; the suppression of the integrated $p/\pi$ at the highest Pb--Pb multiplicities is reproduced only with UrQMD, highlighting hadronic-phase effects. The nuclear modification factor shows sizeable suppression in Pb--Pb and substantial suppression in central O--O collisions. Blast-wave fits exhibit the anti-correlation between $T_{\rm kin}$ and $\langle\beta_T\rangle$, with UrQMD shifting the parameters towards lower $T_{\rm kin}$ and higher $\langle\beta_T\rangle$. These results provide a timely baseline for Run~3 measurements and for constraining the onset of medium-like effects across system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08534v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hirak Kumar Koley, Mitali Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal Variation of Polar Ice: Implications for Ultrahigh Energy Neutrino Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08921v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The upper $100 \, \mathrm{m}$ to $150 \, \mathrm{m}$ of the polar ice sheet, called the firn, has a time-dependent density due to seasonal variations in the surface temperature and snow accumulation. We present RF simulations of an in-ice neutrino-induced radio source that show that these density anomalies create variations in the amplitude and propagation times of radio signals propagating through polar firn at an altitude of ${\sim}3000 \, \mathrm{m}$ above sea level. The received power from signals generated in the ice that refract within the upper ${\sim} 15 \, \mathrm{m}$ firn are subject to a seasonal variation on the order of 10\%. These variations result in an irreducible background uncertainty on the reconstructed neutrino energy and arrival direction for detectors using ice as a detection medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08921v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kyriacou, Steven Prohira, Dave Besson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Anomalies in Muon-Induced Neutron Emissions from Pb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16666v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper examines neutron multiplicity spectra emitted from massive targets at depths of 3, 40, 210, 583, 1166, and 4000 m.w.e. The measurements, carried out between 2001 and 2024, used three experimental setups with either 14 or 60 He-3 neutron detectors and lead (Pb) targets weighing 306, 565, or 1134 kg. The total acquisition time exceeded six years. When available, the spectra obtained were compared with Monte Carlo simulations. Our data indicate potential anomalies that might limit the accuracy of modelling the muon-induced neutron multiplicity spectra with a single power-law function. Even at shallow depths, the single-power-law approach fails to account for a small but statistically significant excess of events at the highest multiplicities. This excess resembles a second power-law component. Since the anomaly varies only slightly with depth, it is unlikely to be directly linked to the muon flux. Our highest-quality data, acquired at 583 m.w.e., suggest a possible structure similar to the emission of approximately 74, 106, 143, and 214 neutrons from the target. We propose new underground measurements using low-cost, large-area, position-sensitive neutron arrays surrounding multi-ton Pb targets to verify and investigate these suspected anomalies and to determine their origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16666v5</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. H. Trzaska, A. Barzilov, T. Enqvist, K. Jedrzejczak, M. Kasztelan, P. Kuusiniemi, K. K. Loo, J. Orzechowski, M. S{\l}upecki, J. Szabelski, T. E. Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring spin correlation between quarks during QCD confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05499v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The vacuum is now understood to possess a rich and complex structure, characterized by fluctuating energy fields and a condensate of virtual quark-antiquark pairs. The spontaneous breaking of the approximate chiral symmetry, signaled by the nonvanishing quark condensate $\langle q\bar{q}\rangle$, is dynamically generated through topologically nontrivial gauge configurations such as instantons. The precise mechanism linking the chiral symmetry breaking to the mass generation associated with quark confinement remains a profound open question in Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) - the fundamental theory of strong interaction. High energy proton-proton collisions could liberate virtual quark-antiquark pairs from the vacuum that subsequently undergo confinement to form hadrons, whose properties could serve as probes into QCD confinement and the quark condensate. Here, we report evidence of spin correlations in $\Lambda\bar{\Lambda}$ hyperon pairs inherited from spin-correlated strange quark-antiquark virtual pairs. Measurements by the STAR experiment at the Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collider (RHIC) at Brookhaven National Laboratory reveal a relative polarization signal of $(18 \pm 4)\%$ that links the virtual spin-correlated quark pairs from the QCD vacuum to their final-state hadron counterparts. Crucially, this correlation vanishes when the hyperon pairs are widely separated in angle, consistent with the decoherence of the quantum system. Our findings provide a new experimental paradigm for exploring the dynamics and interplay of quark confinement and entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05499v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-025-09920-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>STAR Collaboration. Measuring spin correlation between quarks during QCD confinement. Nature 650, 65-71 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> The STAR Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Any Light Particle Searches with ALPS II: first science results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.14110v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The light-shining-through-a-wall experiment ALPS II at DESY in Hamburg searched for axions and similar lightweight particles in its first science campaign from February to May 2024. No evidence for the existence of such particles was found. For pseudoscalar bosons like the axion, with masses below about 0.1 meV, we achieved a limit for the di-photon coupling strength of 1.5e-9 1/GeV at a 95% confidence level. This is more than a factor of 20 improvement compared to all previous similar experiments. We also provide limits on photon interactions for scalar, vector and tensor bosons. An achievement of this first science campaign is the demonstration of stable operation and robust calibration of the complex experiment. Currently, the optical system of ALPS II is being upgraded aiming for another two orders of magnitude sensitivity increase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.14110v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel C. Brotherton, Sandy Croatto, Jacob Egge, Aldo Ejlli, Henry Fr\"adrich, Joe Gleason, Hartmut Grote, Ayman Hallal, Michael T. Hartman, Harold Hollis, Katharina-Sophie Isleif, Friederike Januschek, Kanioar Karan, Sven Karstensen, Todd Kozlowski, Axel Lindner, Manuel Meyer, Guido M\"uller, Gulden Othman, Jan H. P\~old, David Reuther, Andreas Ringwald, Elmeri Rivasto, Jos\'e Alejandro Rubiera Gimeno, J\"orn Schaffran, Uwe Schneekloth, Christina Schwemmbauer, Aaron D. Spector, David B. Tanner, Dieter Trines, Li-Wei Wei, Benno Willke, Rachel Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top-Quark Decay at Next-to-Next-to-Next-to-Leading Order in QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.01937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.01937v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the first complete high-precision QCD corrections to the inclusive decay width $\mathrm{\Gamma}_t$, the $W$-helicity fractions $f_{\mathrm{L,R,0}}$ and semi-inclusive distributions for the top-quark decay process $t \rightarrow b + W^+ + X_{\mathrm{\tiny QCD}}$ at NNNLO in the strong coupling constant $\alpha_s$. In particular, the pure NNNLO QCD correction decreases the $\mathrm{\Gamma}_t$ by about $0.8\%$ of the previous NNLO result at the top-quark pole mass scale, exceeding the error estimated by the usual scale-variation prescription. After taking into account all sources of errors, we get $\mathrm{\Gamma}_t = 1.3148^{+0.003}_{-0.005} + 0.027\,(m_t - 172.69)\,\text{GeV} $, the error of which meets the request by future colliders. On the other hand, the NNNLO QCD effects on $f_{\mathrm{L,R,0}}$ are found to be much smaller, at the level of one per-mille for the dominating $f_{0}$, predestining them to act as precision observables for the top-quark decay process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.01937v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Long Chen, Xiang Chen, Xin Guan, Yan-Qing Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry phase in axion physics, SM global structure, and generalized symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04749v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the Berry phase arising from axion-photon and axion-fermion interactions. The effective Hamiltonians in both systems share the same form, enabling a unified description of the Berry phase and providing a novel perspective on axion experiments. We conceptually propose a new photon-ring experiment for axion detection. Furthermore, we demonstrate that measuring the axion-induced Berry phase offers a unique method for probing the global structure of the Standard Model gauge group and axion-related generalized symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04749v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2026.140218</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 874 (2026) 140218</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qing-Hong Cao, Shuailiang Ge, Yandong Liu, Jun-Chen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No Flavor Anisotropy in the High-Energy Neutrino Sky Upholds Lorentz Invariance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15468v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Discovering Lorentz-invariance violation (LIV) would upend the foundations of modern physics. Because LIV effects grow with energy, high-energy astrophysical neutrinos provide the most sensitive tests of Lorentz invariance in the neutrino sector. We examine an understudied yet phenomenologically rich LIV signature: compass asymmetries, where neutrinos of different flavors propagate preferentially along different directions. Using the directional flavor composition of high-energy astrophysical neutrinos, i.e., the abundances of $\nu_{e}$, $\nu_{\mu}$, and $\nu_{\tau}$ across the sky, we find no evidence of LIV-induced flavor anisotropy in 7.5 years of IceCube High-Energy Starting Events. Thus, we place upper limits on the values of hundreds of LIV parameters with operator dimensions 2-8, tightening existing limits by orders of magnitude and bounding hundreds of parameters for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15468v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP02(2026)024</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP02(2026)024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bernanda Telalovic, Mauricio Bustamante</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Cosmic Neutrino Background through Parametric Fluorescence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10868v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We point out that relic neutrinos from the Big Bang may induce the parametric fluorescence in atomic or molecular systems, which offers a novel way to discover cosmic neutrino background. By coherently scattering with molecular energy levels, a massive neutrino can spontaneously ``decay" into a lighter neutrino and an infrared signal photon, i.e., $\nu^{}_{i} + M \to \nu^{}_{j} + \gamma^{}_{\rm S} + M$, where the molecular state $M$ remains unchanged after the scattering. Because the amplitudes of different radiants are matched in phase, the rate is coherently enhanced and proportional to the squared density of ambient dipoles. When the energy transfer from neutrinos coincides with the energy-level difference, the fluorescence will be on resonance. Near the resonance, the rate is proportional to the square of the coherence time $T^{}_{\rm c}$ of the ensemble. For a nominal target volume of $5~{\rm m^3}$ (or $5~{\rm cm^3}$), the signal rate can reach $1~{\rm yr}^{-1}$ for $T^{}_{\rm c} = 10~{\rm ns}$ (or $T^{}_{\rm c} = 10~{\rm \mu s}$). This event rate appears to be very promising in consideration of an even longer coherence time that is achievable in solid systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10868v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-yuan Huang, Shun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chasing the two-Higgs-doublet model via electroweak corrections at $e^+e^-$ colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05421v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive study of Higgs boson production associated with a neutrino pair at $e^+e^-$ colliders ($e^+ e^- \to h \, \nu \bar{\nu}$) at next-to-leading-order accuracy in both the Standard Model and the two-Higgs-doublet model. We show that these new physics effects will be observable in total and differential cross sections when compared with theoretical predictions that include electroweak corrections, even in the Higgs alignment limit. This highlights the potential of precision studies at future $e^+e^-$ colliders for searching new physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05421v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pia Bredt, Tatsuya Banno, Marius H\"ofer, Syuhei Iguro, Wolfgang Kilian, Yang Ma, J\"urgen Reuter, Hantian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for Axion-Like Particles in High-Magnetic-Field Pulsars with NICER</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03316v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axion-like particles (ALPs) can couple to photons in strong magnetic fields, producing characteristic fluctuations in X-ray spectra. Using data from NASA's Neutron Star Interior Composition Explorer (NICER), we analyzed three pulsars: PSR J2229+6114, PSR J1849-0001, and PSR B0531+21, to search for such features. Each spectrum was modeled with a sliding-window power-law fitting method to identify local deviations from the smooth continuum. From these analyses, we derived constraints on the axion-photon coupling constant $g_{a\gamma\gamma}$ assuming dipole and quadrupole magnetic field distributions. We obtain upper limits in the range $10^{-10}$--$10^{-13}\,\mathrm{GeV}^{-1}$ for ALP masses in the $0.8$--$10~\mathrm{keV}$ region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03316v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Jhen Liu, Yi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High precision heavy-boson-jet substructure with energy correlators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20923v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Energy-correlator-based jet substructure has gained significant attention in recent years. One of the notable applications has been the study of multi-scale jets, where distinct physical scales manifest as features localised in different angular regions of the correlator. In this article, we present the first high-precision study of energy correlators on the simplest multi-scale jets: heavy boson jets. In such systems, the boson mass $M$ introduces an additional scale, generating a sharp peak at angles $\sim M/p_T^{\rm jet}$. We show that this feature can be computed directly by boosting the EEC spectrum measured in $e^+e^- \rightarrow {\rm hadrons}$ at the $Z$ pole. We identify that the peak arises from boosting the well-studied Sudakov factorisation governing the back-to-back limit of the two-point correlator. As a result, the feature is controlled by Sudakov resummation, not a Breit-Wigner-like structure in the $Z$ decay, and is therefore calculable with exceptional precision. We provide predictions at N$^3$LL$'$ accuracy for both $pp$ $Z$-tagged jets and $e^+e^-$ di-$Z$ production, and compare them to Herwig and Pythia simulations, finding close agreement. We also demonstrate that the boosted-$Z$ spectrum can be constructed directly by boosting OPAL measurements at the $Z$ pole. In this light, energy-correlator jet substructure on the hadronic decays of heavy bosons at the LHC provide access to clean, lepton-collider-like measurements across a wide range of effective centre-of-mass energies set by the boson jet transverse momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20923v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Holguin, Ian Moult, Aditya Pathak, Massimiliano Procura, Siddharth Sule</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Gravitational Anomaly at Low Acceleration from a Highest-quality Sample of 36 Wide Binaries with Accurate 3D Velocities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21728v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We set out to accurately measure gravity in the low-acceleration range $(10^{-11},10^{-9})$ m s$^{-2}$ from 3D motions of isolated wide binary stars. Gaia DR3 provides precise measurements of the four sky-plane components of the 3D relative displacement and velocity ($\mathbf{r}, \mathbf{v}$) for a wide binary, but not comparably precise line-of-sight (radial) separation and relative velocity $v_{r}$. Based on our new observations and the public databases/publications, we assemble a sample of 36 nearby (distance $&lt;150$pc) wide binaries in the low-acceleration regime with accurate values of $v_{r}$ (uncertainty $&lt; 100$ m s$^{-1}$). Kinematic contaminants such as undetected stellar companions are well under control using various observational diagnostics such as Gaia's ruwe parameter, the color-magnitude diagram, multi-epoch observations of radial velocities, Speckle interferometric follow-up observations, and requiring Hipparcos-Gaia proper motion consistency. For the parameter $\Gamma \equiv \log_{10}\sqrt{\gamma}$ with $\gamma \equiv G/G_{\rm N}$ (where $G$ is a parameter generalizing Newton's constant $G_{\rm N}$ in elliptical orbits), we find $\Gamma=0.102_{-0.021}^{+0.023}$, inconsistent with standard gravity at $4.9\sigma$, giving a gravity boost factor of $\gamma=1.600_{-0.141}^{+0.171}$. Four wide binaries have 3D relative velocities exceeding their estimated Newtonian escape velocities with $1&lt;v_{\rm obs}/v_{\rm escN}\le1.2$. These systems are unlikely to be chance associations and are expected in a nonstandard paradigm such as Milgromian dynamics (MOND). The hypothesis that Newtonian gravity can be extrapolated to the low-acceleration limit is falsified by this independent study with accurate 3D velocities. Future radial velocity monitoring and Speckle interferometric imaging for larger samples will be useful to refine the present result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21728v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. -H. Chae, B. -C. Lee, X. Hernandez, V. G. Orlov, D. Lim, D. A. Turnshek, Y. -W. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Non-extensivity on the drag and diffusion coefficients of hadronic matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05478v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the drag and diffusion coefficients of various hadrons propagating through a hadronic thermal bath by employing the Fokker Planck equation within the framework of Tsallis nonextensive statistics. The nonextensive parameter $q$ accounts for the deviation from equilibrium and provides a more realistic description of the medium that is not perfectly thermalized. The hadronic bath, consisting of various mesonic and baryonic species, is characterized by different mass cutoffs that control the spectral composition of the medium. Our analysis shows that both the drag $F$ and momentum diffusion coefficients $\Gamma$ increases exponentially with temperature and increases systematically with increasing $q$ and mass cutoff. The spatial diffusion coefficient $D_x$ exhibits a decreasing trend with temperature $T$, $q$ and mass cutoff which highlights the significant influence of nonequilibrium effects and hadronic composition on the transport behaviour of hadrons, offering valuable insights into the thermal and dynamical properties of the hadronic phase preceding freezeout in heavy ion collisions. Additionally, we have studied the relaxation time of heavy mesons such as $D_0$, $J/\psi$ and $\Upsilon$. We found that the heavier mesons relaxed later in comparison to the lighter mesons in the hadronic medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05478v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Kumar Singh, Swatantra Kumar Tiwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
