<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.AS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.AS</link>
    <description>eess.AS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.AS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 04:00:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Infrastructure-less Localization from Indoor Environmental Sounds Based on Spectral Decomposition and Spatial Likelihood Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Human and/or asset tracking using an attached sensor units helps understand their activities. Most common indoor localization methods for human tracking technologies require expensive infrastructures, deployment and maintenance. To overcome this problem, environmental sounds have been used for infrastructure-free localization. While they achieve room-level classification, they suffer from two problems: low signal-to-noise-ratio (SNR) condition and non-uniqueness of sound over the coverage area. A microphone localization method was proposed using supervised spectral decomposition and spatial likelihood to solve these problems. The proposed method was evaluated with actual recordings in an experimental room with a size of 12 x 30 m. The results showed that the proposed method with supervised NMF was robust under low-SNR condition compared to a simple feature (mel frequency cepstrum coefficient: MFCC). Additionally, the proposed method could be easily integrated with prior distribution, which is available from other Bayesian localizations. The proposed method can be used to evaluate the spatial likelihood from environmental sounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17402v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/SII55687.2023.10039378</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Satoki Ogiso, Yoshiaki Bando, Takeshi Kurata, Takashi Okuma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speaker Distance Estimation in Enclosures from Single-Channel Audio</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Distance estimation from audio plays a crucial role in various applications, such as acoustic scene analysis, sound source localization, and room modeling. Most studies predominantly center on employing a classification approach, where distances are discretized into distinct categories, enabling smoother model training and achieving higher accuracy but imposing restrictions on the precision of the obtained sound source position. Towards this direction, in this paper we propose a novel approach for continuous distance estimation from audio signals using a convolutional recurrent neural network with an attention module. The attention mechanism enables the model to focus on relevant temporal and spectral features, enhancing its ability to capture fine-grained distance-related information. To evaluate the effectiveness of our proposed method, we conduct extensive experiments using audio recordings in controlled environments with three levels of realism (synthetic room impulse response, measured response with convolved speech, and real recordings) on four datasets (our synthetic dataset, QMULTIMIT, VoiceHome-2, and STARSS23). Experimental results show that the model achieves an absolute error of 0.11 meters in a noiseless synthetic scenario. Moreover, the results showed an absolute error of about 1.30 meters in the hybrid scenario. The algorithm's performance in the real scenario, where unpredictable environmental factors and noise are prevalent, yields an absolute error of approximately 0.50 meters. For reproducible research purposes we make model, code, and synthetic datasets available at https://github.com/michaelneri/audio-distance-estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17514v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TASLP.2024.3382504</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michael Neri, Archontis Politis, Daniel Krause, Marco Carli, Tuomas Virtanen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesizing Soundscapes: Leveraging Text-to-Audio Models for Environmental Sound Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the past few years, text-to-audio models have emerged as a significant advancement in automatic audio gener- ation. Although they represent impressive technological progress, the effectiveness of their use in the development of audio applications remains uncertain. This paper aims to investigate these aspects, specifically focusing on the task of classification of environmental sounds. This study analyzes the performance of two different environmental classification systems when data generated from text-to-audio models is used for training. Two cases are considered: a) when the training dataset is augmented by data coming from two different text-to-audio models; and b) when the training dataset consists solely of synthetic audio generated. In both cases, the performance of the classification task is tested on real data. Results indicate that text-to-audio models are effective for dataset augmentation, whereas the performance of the models drops when relying on only generated audio.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17864v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Ronchini, Luca Comanducci, Fabio Antonacci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy enhancement method for speech emotion recognition from spectrogram using temporal frequency correlation and positional information learning through knowledge transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17327v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a method to improve the accuracy of speech emotion recognition (SER) by using vision transformer (ViT) to attend to the correlation of frequency (y-axis) with time (x-axis) in spectrogram and transferring positional information between ViT through knowledge transfer. The proposed method has the following originality i) We use vertically segmented patches of log-Mel spectrogram to analyze the correlation of frequencies over time. This type of patch allows us to correlate the most relevant frequencies for a particular emotion with the time they were uttered. ii) We propose the use of image coordinate encoding, an absolute positional encoding suitable for ViT. By normalizing the x, y coordinates of the image to -1 to 1 and concatenating them to the image, we can effectively provide valid absolute positional information for ViT. iii) Through feature map matching, the locality and location information of the teacher network is effectively transmitted to the student network. Teacher network is a ViT that contains locality of convolutional stem and absolute position information through image coordinate encoding, and student network is a structure that lacks positional encoding in the basic ViT structure. In feature map matching stage, we train through the mean absolute error (L1 loss) to minimize the difference between the feature maps of the two networks. To validate the proposed method, three emotion datasets (SAVEE, EmoDB, and CREMA-D) consisting of speech were converted into log-Mel spectrograms for comparison experiments. The experimental results show that the proposed method significantly outperforms the state-of-the-art methods in terms of weighted accuracy while requiring significantly fewer floating point operations (FLOPs). Overall, the proposed method offers an promising solution for SER by providing improved efficiency and performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17327v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeong-Yoon Kim, Seung-Ho Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Analysis of Quality of Conventional Beamforming for Phased Microphone Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A theoretical study is performed to analyze the directional response of different types of microphone array designs. 1-D (linear) and 2-D (planar) microphone array types are considered, and the delay and sum beamforming and conventional beamforming techniques are employed to localize the sound source. A non-dimensional parameter, G, is characterized to simplify and standardize the rejection performance of both 1-D and 2-D microphone arrays as a function of array geometry and sound source parameters. This parameter G is then used to determine an improved design of a 2-D microphone array for far-field sound localization. One such design, termed the Equi-area array is introduced and analyzed in detail. The design is shown to have an advantageous rejection performance compared to other conventionally used 2-D planar microphone arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17376v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dheepak Khatri, Kenneth Granlund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Latency Neural Speech Phase Prediction based on Parallel Estimation Architecture and Anti-Wrapping Losses for Speech Generation Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17378v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel neural speech phase prediction model which predicts wrapped phase spectra directly from amplitude spectra. The proposed model is a cascade of a residual convolutional network and a parallel estimation architecture. The parallel estimation architecture is a core module for direct wrapped phase prediction. This architecture consists of two parallel linear convolutional layers and a phase calculation formula, imitating the process of calculating the phase spectra from the real and imaginary parts of complex spectra and strictly restricting the predicted phase values to the principal value interval. To avoid the error expansion issue caused by phase wrapping, we design anti-wrapping training losses defined between the predicted wrapped phase spectra and natural ones by activating the instantaneous phase error, group delay error and instantaneous angular frequency error using an anti-wrapping function. We mathematically demonstrate that the anti-wrapping function should possess three properties, namely parity, periodicity and monotonicity. We also achieve low-latency streamable phase prediction by combining causal convolutions and knowledge distillation training strategies. For both analysis-synthesis and specific speech generation tasks, experimental results show that our proposed neural speech phase prediction model outperforms the iterative phase estimation algorithms and neural network-based phase prediction methods in terms of phase prediction precision, efficiency and robustness. Compared with HiFi-GAN-based waveform reconstruction method, our proposed model also shows outstanding efficiency advantages while ensuring the quality of synthesized speech. To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to directly predict speech phase spectra from amplitude spectra only via neural networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17378v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Ai, Zhen-Hua Ling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring and Applying Audio-Based Sentiment Analysis in Music</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17379v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sentiment analysis is a continuously explored area of text processing that deals with the computational analysis of opinions, sentiments, and subjectivity of text. However, this idea is not limited to text and speech, in fact, it could be applied to other modalities. In reality, humans do not express themselves in text as deeply as they do in music. The ability of a computational model to interpret musical emotions is largely unexplored and could have implications and uses in therapy and musical queuing. In this paper, two individual tasks are addressed. This study seeks to (1) predict the emotion of a musical clip over time and (2) determine the next emotion value after the music in a time series to ensure seamless transitions. Utilizing data from the Emotions in Music Database, which contains clips of songs selected from the Free Music Archive annotated with levels of valence and arousal as reported on Russel's circumplex model of affect by multiple volunteers, models are trained for both tasks. Overall, the performance of these models reflected that they were able to perform the tasks they were designed for effectively and accurately.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17379v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Etash Jhanji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Visually Localize Sound Sources from Mixtures without Prior Source Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The goal of the multi-sound source localization task is to localize sound sources from the mixture individually. While recent multi-sound source localization methods have shown improved performance, they face challenges due to their reliance on prior information about the number of objects to be separated. In this paper, to overcome this limitation, we present a novel multi-sound source localization method that can perform localization without prior knowledge of the number of sound sources. To achieve this goal, we propose an iterative object identification (IOI) module, which can recognize sound-making objects in an iterative manner. After finding the regions of sound-making objects, we devise object similarity-aware clustering (OSC) loss to guide the IOI module to effectively combine regions of the same object but also distinguish between different objects and backgrounds. It enables our method to perform accurate localization of sound-making objects without any prior knowledge. Extensive experimental results on the MUSIC and VGGSound benchmarks show the significant performance improvements of the proposed method over the existing methods for both single and multi-source. Our code is available at: https://github.com/VisualAIKHU/NoPrior_MultiSSL</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17420v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongjin Kim, Sung Jin Um, Sangmin Lee, Jung Uk Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation of Fr\'echet Audio Distance With Human Perception of Environmental Audio Is Embedding Dependant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17508v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper explores whether considering alternative domain-specific embeddings to calculate the Fr\'echet Audio Distance (FAD) metric can help the FAD to correlate better with perceptual ratings of environmental sounds. We used embeddings from VGGish, PANNs, MS-CLAP, L-CLAP, and MERT, which are tailored for either music or environmental sound evaluation. The FAD scores were calculated for sounds from the DCASE 2023 Task 7 dataset. Using perceptual data from the same task, we find that PANNs-WGM-LogMel produces the best correlation between FAD scores and perceptual ratings of both audio quality and perceived fit with a Spearman correlation higher than 0.5. We also find that music-specific embeddings resulted in significantly lower results. Interestingly, VGGish, the embedding used for the original Fr\'echet calculation, yielded a correlation below 0.1. These results underscore the critical importance of the choice of embedding for the FAD metric design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17508v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Modan Tailleur, Junwon Lee, Mathieu Lagrange, Keunwoo Choi, Laurie M. Heller, Keisuke Imoto, Yuki Okamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Deepfake Environmental Audio</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17529v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the ever-rising quality of deep generative models, it is increasingly important to be able to discern whether the audio data at hand have been recorded or synthesized. Although the detection of fake speech signals has been studied extensively, this is not the case for the detection of fake environmental audio.
  We propose a simple and efficient pipeline for detecting fake environmental sounds based on the CLAP audio embedding. We evaluate this detector using audio data from the 2023 DCASE challenge task on Foley sound synthesis.
  Our experiments show that fake sounds generated by 44 state-of-the-art synthesizers can be detected on average with 98% accuracy. We show that using an audio embedding learned on environmental audio is beneficial over a standard VGGish one as it provides a 10% increase in detection performance. Informal listening to Incorrect Negative examples demonstrates audible features of fake sounds missed by the detector such as distortion and implausible background noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17529v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hafsa Ouajdi, Oussama Hadder, Modan Tailleur, Mathieu Lagrange, Laurie M. Heller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep functional multiple index models with an application to SER</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17562v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Speech Emotion Recognition (SER) plays a crucial role in advancing human-computer interaction and speech processing capabilities. We introduce a novel deep-learning architecture designed specifically for the functional data model known as the multiple-index functional model. Our key innovation lies in integrating adaptive basis layers and an automated data transformation search within the deep learning framework. Simulations for this new model show good performances. This allows us to extract features tailored for chunk-level SER, based on Mel Frequency Cepstral Coefficients (MFCCs). We demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach on the benchmark IEMOCAP database, achieving good performance compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17562v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Saumard, Abir El Haj, Thibault Napoleon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Pre-training for Speech with Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16338v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Generative models have gained more and more attention in recent years for their remarkable success in tasks that required estimating and sampling data distribution to generate high-fidelity synthetic data. In speech, text-to-speech synthesis and neural vocoder are good examples where generative models have shined. While generative models have been applied to different applications in speech, there exists no general-purpose generative model that models speech directly. In this work, we take a step toward this direction by showing a single pre-trained generative model can be adapted to different downstream tasks with strong performance. Specifically, we pre-trained a generative model, named SpeechFlow, on 60k hours of untranscribed speech with Flow Matching and masked conditions. Experiment results show the pre-trained generative model can be fine-tuned with task-specific data to match or surpass existing expert models on speech enhancement, separation, and synthesis. Our work suggested a foundational model for generation tasks in speech can be built with generative pre-training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16338v2</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander H. Liu, Matt Le, Apoorv Vyas, Bowen Shi, Andros Tjandra, Wei-Ning Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Room Transfer Function Reconstruction Using Complex-valued Neural Networks and Irregularly Distributed Microphones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04866v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reconstructing the room transfer functions needed to calculate the complex sound field in a room has several impor- tant real-world applications. However, an unpractical number of microphones is often required. Recently, in addition to classical signal processing methods, deep learning techniques have been applied to reconstruct the room transfer function starting from a very limited set of measurements at scattered points in the room. In this paper, we employ complex-valued neural networks to estimate room transfer functions in the frequency range of the first room resonances, using a few irregularly distributed microphones. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time that complex-valued neural networks are used to estimate room transfer functions. To analyze the benefits of applying complex- valued optimization to the considered task, we compare the proposed technique with a state-of-the-art kernel-based signal processing approach for sound field reconstruction, showing that the proposed technique exhibits relevant advantages in terms of phase accuracy and overall quality of the reconstructed sound field. For informative purposes, we also compare the model with a similarly-structured data-driven approach that, however, applies a real-valued neural network to reconstruct only the magnitude of the sound field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04866v2</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Ronchini, Luca Comanducci, Mirco Pezzoli, Fabio Antonacci, Augusto Sarti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Entrainment in Spontaneous Code-switched Speech</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07703v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is well-known that speakers who entrain to one another have more successful conversations than those who do not. Previous research has shown that interlocutors entrain on linguistic features in both written and spoken monolingual domains. More recent work on code-switched communication has also shown preliminary evidence of entrainment on certain aspects of code-switching (CSW). However, such studies of entrainment in code-switched domains have been extremely few and restricted to human-machine textual interactions. Our work studies code-switched spontaneous speech between humans, finding that (1) patterns of written and spoken entrainment in monolingual settings largely generalize to code-switched settings, and (2) some patterns of entrainment on code-switching in dialogue agent-generated text generalize to spontaneous code-switched speech. Our findings give rise to important implications for the potentially "universal" nature of entrainment as a communication phenomenon, and potential applications in inclusive and interactive speech technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07703v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debasmita Bhattacharya, Siying Ding, Alayna Nguyen, Julia Hirschberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AV2AV: Direct Audio-Visual Speech to Audio-Visual Speech Translation with Unified Audio-Visual Speech Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02512v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel direct Audio-Visual Speech to Audio-Visual Speech Translation (AV2AV) framework, where the input and output of the system are multimodal (i.e., audio and visual speech). With the proposed AV2AV, two key advantages can be brought: 1) We can perform real-like conversations with individuals worldwide in a virtual meeting by utilizing our own primary languages. In contrast to Speech-to-Speech Translation (A2A), which solely translates between audio modalities, the proposed AV2AV directly translates between audio-visual speech. This capability enhances the dialogue experience by presenting synchronized lip movements along with the translated speech. 2) We can improve the robustness of the spoken language translation system. By employing the complementary information of audio-visual speech, the system can effectively translate spoken language even in the presence of acoustic noise, showcasing robust performance. To mitigate the problem of the absence of a parallel AV2AV translation dataset, we propose to train our spoken language translation system with the audio-only dataset of A2A. This is done by learning unified audio-visual speech representations through self-supervised learning in advance to train the translation system. Moreover, we propose an AV-Renderer that can generate raw audio and video in parallel. It is designed with zero-shot speaker modeling, thus the speaker in source audio-visual speech can be maintained at the target translated audio-visual speech. The effectiveness of AV2AV is evaluated with extensive experiments in a many-to-many language translation setting. Demo page is available on https://choijeongsoo.github.io/av2av.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02512v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeongsoo Choi, Se Jin Park, Minsu Kim, Yong Man Ro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lodge: A Coarse to Fine Diffusion Network for Long Dance Generation Guided by the Characteristic Dance Primitives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10518v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose Lodge, a network capable of generating extremely long dance sequences conditioned on given music. We design Lodge as a two-stage coarse to fine diffusion architecture, and propose the characteristic dance primitives that possess significant expressiveness as intermediate representations between two diffusion models. The first stage is global diffusion, which focuses on comprehending the coarse-level music-dance correlation and production characteristic dance primitives. In contrast, the second-stage is the local diffusion, which parallelly generates detailed motion sequences under the guidance of the dance primitives and choreographic rules. In addition, we propose a Foot Refine Block to optimize the contact between the feet and the ground, enhancing the physical realism of the motion. Our approach can parallelly generate dance sequences of extremely long length, striking a balance between global choreographic patterns and local motion quality and expressiveness. Extensive experiments validate the efficacy of our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10518v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronghui Li, YuXiang Zhang, Yachao Zhang, Hongwen Zhang, Jie Guo, Yan Zhang, Yebin Liu, Xiu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multimodal Approach to Device-Directed Speech Detection with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14438v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Interactions with virtual assistants typically start with a predefined trigger phrase followed by the user command. To make interactions with the assistant more intuitive, we explore whether it is feasible to drop the requirement that users must begin each command with a trigger phrase. We explore this task in three ways: First, we train classifiers using only acoustic information obtained from the audio waveform. Second, we take the decoder outputs of an automatic speech recognition (ASR) system, such as 1-best hypotheses, as input features to a large language model (LLM). Finally, we explore a multimodal system that combines acoustic and lexical features, as well as ASR decoder signals in an LLM. Using multimodal information yields relative equal-error-rate improvements over text-only and audio-only models of up to 39% and 61%. Increasing the size of the LLM and training with low-rank adaption leads to further relative EER reductions of up to 18% on our dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14438v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICASSP48485.2024.10446224</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Wagner, Alexander Churchill, Siddharth Sigtia, Panayiotis Georgiou, Matt Mirsamadi, Aarshee Mishra, Erik Marchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>As Good As A Coin Toss: Human detection of AI-generated images, videos, audio, and audiovisual stimuli</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16760v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As synthetic media becomes progressively more realistic and barriers to using it continue to lower, the technology has been increasingly utilized for malicious purposes, from financial fraud to nonconsensual pornography. Today, the principal defense against being misled by synthetic media relies on the ability of the human observer to visually and auditorily discern between real and fake. However, it remains unclear just how vulnerable people actually are to deceptive synthetic media in the course of their day to day lives. We conducted a perceptual study with 1276 participants to assess how accurate people were at distinguishing synthetic images, audio only, video only, and audiovisual stimuli from authentic. To reflect the circumstances under which people would likely encounter synthetic media in the wild, testing conditions and stimuli emulated a typical online platform, while all synthetic media used in the survey was sourced from publicly accessible generative AI technology.
  We find that overall, participants struggled to meaningfully discern between synthetic and authentic content. We also find that detection performance worsens when the stimuli contains synthetic content as compared to authentic content, images featuring human faces as compared to non face objects, a single modality as compared to multimodal stimuli, mixed authenticity as compared to being fully synthetic for audiovisual stimuli, and features foreign languages as compared to languages the observer is fluent in. Finally, we also find that prior knowledge of synthetic media does not meaningfully impact their detection performance. Collectively, these results indicate that people are highly susceptible to being tricked by synthetic media in their daily lives and that human perceptual detection capabilities can no longer be relied upon as an effective counterdefense.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16760v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Cooke, Abigail Edwards, Sophia Barkoff, Kathryn Kelly</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
