<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.AS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.AS</link>
    <description>eess.AS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.AS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Through the Spike: Spike Window Decoding for Accelerated and Precise Automatic Speech Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, end-to-end automatic speech recognition has become the mainstream approach in both industry and academia. To optimize system performance in specific scenarios, the Weighted Finite-State Transducer (WFST) is extensively used to integrate acoustic and language models, leveraging its capacity to implicitly fuse language models within static graphs, thereby ensuring robust recognition while also facilitating rapid error correction. However, WFST necessitates a frame-by-frame search of CTC posterior probabilities through autoregression, which significantly hampers inference speed. In this work, we thoroughly investigate the spike property of CTC outputs and further propose the conjecture that adjacent frames to non-blank spikes carry semantic information beneficial to the model. Building on this, we propose the Spike Window Decoding algorithm, which greatly improves the inference speed by making the number of frames decoded in WFST linearly related to the number of spiking frames in the CTC output, while guaranteeing the recognition performance. Our method achieves SOTA recognition accuracy with significantly accelerates decoding speed, proven across both AISHELL-1 and large-scale In-House datasets, establishing a pioneering approach for integrating CTC output with WFST.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03257v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Zhang, Tian-Hao Zhang, Chao Luo, Hui Zhou, Chao Yang, Xinyuan Qian, Xu-Cheng Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning for Pathological Speech: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advancements in spoken language technologies for neurodegenerative speech disorders are crucial for meeting both clinical and technological needs. This overview paper is vital for advancing the field, as it presents a comprehensive review of state-of-the-art methods in pathological speech detection, automatic speech recognition, pathological speech intelligibility enhancement, intelligibility and severity assessment, and data augmentation approaches for pathological speech. It also high-lights key challenges, such as ensuring robustness, privacy, and interpretability. The paper concludes by exploring promising future directions, including the adoption of multimodal approaches and the integration of graph neural networks and large language models to further advance speech technology for neurodegenerative speech disorders</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03536v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shakeel A. Sheikh, Md. Sahidullah, Ina Kodrasi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Generalizable Speech Marker for Parkinson's Disease Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parkinson's Disease (PD) is a neurodegenerative disorder characterized by motor symptoms, including altered voice production in the early stages. Early diagnosis is crucial not only to improve PD patients' quality of life but also to enhance the efficacy of potential disease-modifying therapies during early neurodegeneration, a window often missed by current diagnostic tools. In this paper, we propose a more generalizable approach to PD recognition through domain adaptation and self-supervised learning. We demonstrate the generalization capabilities of the proposed approach across diverse datasets in different languages. Our approach leverages HuBERT, a large deep neural network originally trained for speech recognition and further trains it on unlabeled speech data from a population that is similar to the target group, i.e., the elderly, in a self-supervised manner. The model is then fine-tuned and adapted for use across different datasets in multiple languages, including English, Italian, and Spanish. Evaluations on four publicly available PD datasets demonstrate the model's efficacy, achieving an average specificity of 92.1% and an average sensitivity of 91.2%. This method offers objective and consistent evaluations across large populations, addressing the variability inherent in human assessments and providing a non-invasive, cost-effective and accessible diagnostic option.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03581v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maksim Siniukov, Ellie Xing,  Sanaz, Attaripour Isfahani, Mohammad Soleymani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Speaker Embedding Free Target Speaker Extraction and Personal Voice Activity Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Determining 'who spoke what and when' remains challenging in real-world applications. In typical scenarios, Speaker Diarization (SD) is employed to address the problem of 'who spoke when,' while Target Speaker Extraction (TSE) or Target Speaker Automatic Speech Recognition (TSASR) techniques are utilized to resolve the issue of 'who spoke what.' Although some works have achieved promising results by combining SD and TSE systems, inconsistencies remain between SD and TSE regarding both output inconsistency and scenario mismatch. To address these limitations, we propose a Universal Speaker Embedding Free Target Speaker Extraction and Personal Voice Activity Detection (USEF-TP) model that jointly performs TSE and Personal Voice Activity Detection (PVAD). USEF-TP leverages frame-level features obtained through a cross-attention mechanism as speaker-related features instead of using speaker embeddings as in traditional approaches. Additionally, a multi-task learning algorithm with a scenario-aware differentiated loss function is applied to ensure robust performance across various levels of speaker overlap. The experimental results show that our proposed USEF-TP model achieves superior performance in TSE and PVAD tasks on the LibriMix and SparseLibriMix datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03612v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bang Zeng, Ming Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Neurocognitive Disorders through Analyses of Topic Evolution and Cross-modal Consistency in Visual-Stimulated Narratives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03727v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Early detection of neurocognitive disorders (NCDs) is crucial for timely intervention and disease management. Speech analysis offers a non-intrusive and scalable screening method, particularly through narrative tasks in neuropsychological assessment tools. Traditional narrative analysis often focuses on local indicators in microstructure, such as word usage and syntax. While these features provide insights into language production abilities, they often fail to capture global narrative patterns, or microstructures. Macrostructures include coherence, thematic organization, and logical progressions, reflecting essential cognitive skills potentially critical for recognizing NCDs. Addressing this gap, we propose to investigate specific cognitive and linguistic challenges by analyzing topical shifts, temporal dynamics, and the coherence of narratives over time, aiming to reveal cognitive deficits by identifying narrative impairments, and exploring their impact on communication and cognition. The investigation is based on the CU-MARVEL Rabbit Story corpus, which comprises recordings of a story-telling task from 758 older adults. We developed two approaches: the Dynamic Topic Models (DTM)-based temporal analysis to examine the evolution of topics over time, and the Text-Image Temporal Alignment Network (TITAN) to evaluate the coherence between spoken narratives and visual stimuli. DTM-based approach validated the effectiveness of dynamic topic consistency as a macrostructural metric (F1=0.61, AUC=0.78). The TITAN approach achieved the highest performance (F1=0.72, AUC=0.81), surpassing established microstructural and macrostructural feature sets. Cross-comparison and regression tasks further demonstrated the effectiveness of proposed dynamic macrostructural modeling approaches for NCD detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03727v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinchao Li, Yuejiao Wang, Junan Li, Jiawen Kang, Bo Zheng, Simon Wong, Brian Mak, Helene Fung, Jean Woo, Man-Wai Mak, Timothy Kwok, Vincent Mok, Xianmin Gong, Xixin Wu, Xunying Liu, Patrick Wong, Helen Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo Strong Labels from Frame-Level Predictions for Weakly Supervised Sound Event Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03740v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weakly Supervised Sound Event Detection (WSSED), which relies on audio tags without precise onset and offset times, has become prevalent due to the scarcity of strongly labeled data that includes exact temporal boundaries for events. This study introduces Frame-level Pseudo Strong Labeling (FPSL) to overcome the lack of temporal information in WSSED by generating pseudo strong labels from frame-level predictions. This enhances temporal localization during training and addresses the limitations of clip-wise weak supervision. We validate our approach across three benchmark datasets (DCASE2017 Task 4, DCASE2018 Task 4, and UrbanSED) and demonstrate significant improvements in key metrics such as the Polyphonic Sound Detection Scores (PSDS), event-based F1 scores, and intersection-based F1 scores. For example, Convolutional Recurrent Neural Networks (CRNNs) trained with FPSL outperform baseline models by 4.9% in PSDS1 on DCASE2017, 7.6% on DCASE2018, and 1.8% on UrbanSED, confirming the effectiveness of our method in enhancing model performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03740v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuliang Zhang (David),  Defeng (David),  Huang, Roberto Togneri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral-Aware Low-Rank Adaptation for Speaker Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Previous research has shown that the principal singular vectors of a pre-trained model's weight matrices capture critical knowledge. In contrast, those associated with small singular values may contain noise or less reliable information. As a result, the LoRA-based parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) approach, which does not constrain the use of the spectral space, may not be effective for tasks that demand high representation capacity. In this study, we enhance existing PEFT techniques by incorporating the spectral information of pre-trained weight matrices into the fine-tuning process. We investigate spectral adaptation strategies with a particular focus on the additive adjustment of top singular vectors. This is accomplished by applying singular value decomposition (SVD) to the pre-trained weight matrices and restricting the fine-tuning within the top spectral space. Extensive speaker verification experiments on VoxCeleb1 and CN-Celeb1 demonstrate enhanced tuning performance with the proposed approach. Code is released at https://github.com/lizhepolyu/SpectralFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03829v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Li, Man-wai Mak, Mert Pilanci, Hung-yi Lee, Helen Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging Auditory Perception and Language Comprehension through MEG-Driven Encoding Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the neural mechanisms behind auditory and linguistic processing is key to advancing cognitive neuroscience. In this study, we use Magnetoencephalography (MEG) data to analyze brain responses to spoken language stimuli. We develop two distinct encoding models: an audio-to-MEG encoder, which uses time-frequency decompositions (TFD) and wav2vec2 latent space representations, and a text-to-MEG encoder, which leverages CLIP and GPT-2 embeddings. Both models successfully predict neural activity, demonstrating significant correlations between estimated and observed MEG signals. However, the text-to-MEG model outperforms the audio-based model, achieving higher Pearson Correlation (PC) score. Spatially, we identify that auditory-based embeddings (TFD and wav2vec2) predominantly activate lateral temporal regions, which are responsible for primary auditory processing and the integration of auditory signals. In contrast, textual embeddings (CLIP and GPT-2) primarily engage the frontal cortex, particularly Broca's area, which is associated with higher-order language processing, including semantic integration and language production, especially in the 8-30 Hz frequency range. The strong involvement of these regions suggests that auditory stimuli are processed through more direct sensory pathways, while linguistic information is encoded via networks that integrate meaning and cognitive control. Our results reveal distinct neural pathways for auditory and linguistic information processing, with higher encoding accuracy for text representations in the frontal regions. These insights refine our understanding of the brain's functional architecture in processing auditory and textual information, offering quantitative advancements in the modelling of neural responses to complex language stimuli.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03246v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Ciferri, Matteo Ferrante, Nicola Toschi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LHGNN: Local-Higher Order Graph Neural Networks For Audio Classification and Tagging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03464v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Transformers have set new benchmarks in audio processing tasks, leveraging self-attention mechanisms to capture complex patterns and dependencies within audio data. However, their focus on pairwise interactions limits their ability to process the higher-order relations essential for identifying distinct audio objects. To address this limitation, this work introduces the Local- Higher Order Graph Neural Network (LHGNN), a graph based model that enhances feature understanding by integrating local neighbourhood information with higher-order data from Fuzzy C-Means clusters, thereby capturing a broader spectrum of audio relationships. Evaluation of the model on three publicly available audio datasets shows that it outperforms Transformer-based models across all benchmarks while operating with substantially fewer parameters. Moreover, LHGNN demonstrates a distinct advantage in scenarios lacking ImageNet pretraining, establishing its effectiveness and efficiency in environments where extensive pretraining data is unavailable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03464v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubhr Singh, Emmanouil Benetos, Huy Phan, Dan Stowell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vocal Tract Length Warped Features for Spoken Keyword Spotting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03523v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose several methods that incorporate vocal tract length (VTL) warped features for spoken keyword spotting (KWS). The first method, VTL-independent KWS, involves training a single deep neural network (DNN) that utilizes VTL features with various warping factors. During training, a specific VTL feature is randomly selected per epoch, allowing the exploration of VTL variations. During testing, the VTL features with different warping factors of a test utterance are scored against the DNN and combined with equal weight. In the second method scores the conventional features of a test utterance (without VTL warping) against the DNN. The third method, VTL-concatenation KWS, concatenates VTL warped features to form high-dimensional features for KWS. Evaluations carried out on the English Google Command dataset demonstrate that the proposed methods improve the accuracy of KWS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03523v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achintya kr. Sarkar, Priyanka Dwivedi, Zheng-Hua Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AADNet: Exploring EEG Spatiotemporal Information for Fast and Accurate Orientation and Timbre Detection of Auditory Attention Based on A Cue-Masked Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03571v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Auditory attention decoding from electroencephalogram (EEG) could infer to which source the user is attending in noisy environments. Decoding algorithms and experimental paradigm designs are crucial for the development of technology in practical applications. To simulate real-world scenarios, this study proposed a cue-masked auditory attention paradigm to avoid information leakage before the experiment. To obtain high decoding accuracy with low latency, an end-to-end deep learning model, AADNet, was proposed to exploit the spatiotemporal information from the short time window of EEG signals. The results showed that with a 0.5-second EEG window, AADNet achieved an average accuracy of 93.46% and 91.09% in decoding auditory orientation attention (OA) and timbre attention (TA), respectively. It significantly outperformed five previous methods and did not need the knowledge of the original audio source. This work demonstrated that it was possible to detect the orientation and timbre of auditory attention from EEG signals fast and accurately. The results are promising for the real-time multi-property auditory attention decoding, facilitating the application of the neuro-steered hearing aids and other assistive listening devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03571v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keren Shi, Xu Liu, Xue Yuan, Haijie Shang, Ruiting Dai, Hanbin Wang, Yunfa Fu, Ning Jiang, Jiayuan He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective and Efficient Mixed Precision Quantization of Speech Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03643v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel mixed-precision quantization approach for speech foundation models that tightly integrates mixed-precision learning and quantized model parameter estimation into one single model compression stage. Experiments conducted on LibriSpeech dataset with fine-tuned wav2vec2.0-base and HuBERT-large models suggest the resulting mixed-precision quantized models increased the lossless compression ratio by factors up to 1.7x and 1.9x over the respective uniform-precision and two-stage mixed-precision quantized baselines that perform precision learning and model parameters quantization in separate and disjointed stages, while incurring no statistically word error rate (WER) increase over the 32-bit full-precision models. The system compression time of wav2vec2.0-base and HuBERT-large models is reduced by up to 1.9 and 1.5 times over the two-stage mixed-precision baselines, while both produce lower WERs. The best-performing 3.5-bit mixed-precision quantized HuBERT-large model produces a lossless compression ratio of 8.6x over the 32-bit full-precision system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03643v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoning Xu, Zhaoqing Li, Zengrui Jin, Huimeng Wang, Youjun Chen, Guinan Li, Mengzhe Geng, Shujie Hu, Jiajun Deng, Xunying Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAJL: A Model-Agnostic Joint Learning Framework for Music Source Separation and Pitch Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03689v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Music source separation and pitch estimation are two vital tasks in music information retrieval. Typically, the input of pitch estimation is obtained from the output of music source separation. Therefore, existing methods have tried to perform these two tasks simultaneously, so as to leverage the mutually beneficial relationship between both tasks. However, these methods still face two critical challenges that limit the improvement of both tasks: the lack of labeled data and joint learning optimization. To address these challenges, we propose a Model-Agnostic Joint Learning (MAJL) framework for both tasks. MAJL is a generic framework and can use variant models for each task. It includes a two-stage training method and a dynamic weighting method named Dynamic Weights on Hard Samples (DWHS), which addresses the lack of labeled data and joint learning optimization, respectively. Experimental results on public music datasets show that MAJL outperforms state-of-the-art methods on both tasks, with significant improvements of 0.92 in Signal-to-Distortion Ratio (SDR) for music source separation and 2.71% in Raw Pitch Accuracy (RPA) for pitch estimation. Furthermore, comprehensive studies not only validate the effectiveness of each component of MAJL, but also indicate the great generality of MAJL in adapting to different model architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03689v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haojie Wei, Jun Yuan, Rui Zhang, Quanyu Dai, Yueguo Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised Speech Segmentation: A General Approach Using Speech Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03711v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce an unsupervised approach for Speech Segmentation, which builds on previously researched approaches, e.g., Speaker Diarization, while being applicable to an inclusive set of acoustic-semantic distinctions, paving a path towards a general Unsupervised Speech Segmentation approach. Unlike traditional speech and audio segmentation, which mainly focuses on spectral changes in the input signal, e.g., phone segmentation, our approach tries to segment the spoken utterance into chunks with differing acoustic-semantic styles, focusing on acoustic-semantic information that does not translate well into text, e.g., emotion or speaker. While most Speech Segmentation tasks only handle one style change, e.g., emotion diarization, our approach tries to handle multiple acoustic-semantic style changes. Leveraging recent advances in Speech Language Models (SLMs), we propose a simple unsupervised method to segment a given speech utterance. We empirically demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach by considering several setups. Results suggest that the proposed method is superior to the evaluated baselines on boundary detection, segment purity, and over-segmentation. Code is available at https://github.com/avishaiElmakies/unsupervised_speech_segmentation_using_slm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03711v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avishai Elmakies, Omri Abend, Yossi Adi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guitar-TECHS: An Electric Guitar Dataset Covering Techniques, Musical Excerpts, Chords and Scales Using a Diverse Array of Hardware</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Guitar-related machine listening research involves tasks like timbre transfer, performance generation, and automatic transcription. However, small datasets often limit model robustness due to insufficient acoustic diversity and musical content. To address these issues, we introduce Guitar-TECHS, a comprehensive dataset featuring a variety of guitar techniques, musical excerpts, chords, and scales. These elements are performed by diverse musicians across various recording settings. Guitar-TECHS incorporates recordings from two stereo microphones: an egocentric microphone positioned on the performer's head and an exocentric microphone placed in front of the performer. It also includes direct input recordings and microphoned amplifier outputs, offering a wide spectrum of audio inputs and recording qualities. All signals and MIDI labels are properly synchronized. Its multi-perspective and multi-modal content makes Guitar-TECHS a valuable resource for advancing data-driven guitar research, and to develop robust guitar listening algorithms. We provide empirical data to demonstrate the dataset's effectiveness in training robust models for Guitar Tablature Transcription.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03720v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP) 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hegel Pedroza, Wallace Abreu, Ryan M. Corey, Iran R. Roman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeuroIncept Decoder for High-Fidelity Speech Reconstruction from Neural Activity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03757v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel algorithm designed for speech synthesis from neural activity recordings obtained using invasive electroencephalography (EEG) techniques. The proposed system offers a promising communication solution for individuals with severe speech impairments. Central to our approach is the integration of time-frequency features in the high-gamma band computed from EEG recordings with an advanced NeuroIncept Decoder architecture. This neural network architecture combines Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) and Gated Recurrent Units (GRUs) to reconstruct audio spectrograms from neural patterns. Our model demonstrates robust mean correlation coefficients between predicted and actual spectrograms, though inter-subject variability indicates distinct neural processing mechanisms among participants. Overall, our study highlights the potential of neural decoding techniques to restore communicative abilities in individuals with speech disorders and paves the way for future advancements in brain-computer interface technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03757v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Owais Mujtaba Khanday, Jos\'e L. P\'erez-C\'ordoba, Mohd Yaqub Mir, Ashfaq Ahmad Najar, Jose A. Gonzalez-Lopez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-label Cross-lingual automatic music genre classification from lyrics with Sentence BERT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03769v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Music genres are shaped by both the stylistic features of songs and the cultural preferences of artists' audiences. Automatic classification of music genres using lyrics can be useful in several applications such as recommendation systems, playlist creation, and library organization. We present a multi-label, cross-lingual genre classification system based on multilingual sentence embeddings generated by sBERT. Using a bilingual Portuguese-English dataset with eight overlapping genres, we demonstrate the system's ability to train on lyrics in one language and predict genres in another. Our approach outperforms the baseline approach of translating lyrics and using a bag-of-words representation, improving the genrewise average F1-Score from 0.35 to 0.69. The classifier uses a one-vs-all architecture, enabling it to assign multiple genre labels to a single lyric. Experimental results reveal that dataset centralization notably improves cross-lingual performance. This approach offers a scalable solution for genre classification across underrepresented languages and cultural domains, advancing the capabilities of music information retrieval systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03769v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiago Fernandes Tavares, Fabio Jos\'e Ayres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting the Undetectable: Assessing the Efficacy of Current Spoof Detection Methods Against Seamless Speech Edits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neural speech editing advancements have raised concerns about their misuse in spoofing attacks. Traditional partially edited speech corpora primarily focus on cut-and-paste edits, which, while maintaining speaker consistency, often introduce detectable discontinuities. Recent methods, like A\textsuperscript{3}T and Voicebox, improve transitions by leveraging contextual information. To foster spoofing detection research, we introduce the Speech INfilling Edit (SINE) dataset, created with Voicebox. We detailed the process of re-implementing Voicebox training and dataset creation. Subjective evaluations confirm that speech edited using this novel technique is more challenging to detect than conventional cut-and-paste methods. Despite human difficulty, experimental results demonstrate that self-supervised-based detectors can achieve remarkable performance in detection, localization, and generalization across different edit methods. The dataset and related models will be made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03805v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sung-Feng Huang, Heng-Cheng Kuo, Zhehuai Chen, Xuesong Yang, Chao-Han Huck Yang, Yu Tsao, Yu-Chiang Frank Wang, Hung-yi Lee, Szu-Wei Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harnessing the Zero-Shot Power of Instruction-Tuned Large Language Model in End-to-End Speech Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10524v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose to utilize an instruction-tuned large language model (LLM) for guiding the text generation process in automatic speech recognition (ASR). Modern large language models (LLMs) are adept at performing various text generation tasks through zero-shot learning, prompted with instructions designed for specific objectives. This paper explores the potential of LLMs to derive linguistic information that can facilitate text generation in end-to-end ASR models. Specifically, we instruct an LLM to correct grammatical errors in an ASR hypothesis and use the LLM-derived representations to refine the output further. The proposed model is built on the joint CTC and attention architecture, with the LLM serving as a front-end feature extractor for the decoder. The ASR hypothesis, subject to correction, is obtained from the encoder via CTC decoding and fed into the LLM along with a specific instruction. The decoder subsequently takes as input the LLM output to perform token predictions, combining acoustic information from the encoder and the powerful linguistic information provided by the LLM. Experimental results show that the proposed LLM-guided model achieves a relative gain of approximately 13\% in word error rates across major benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10524v3</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yosuke Higuchi, Tetsuji Ogawa, Tetsunori Kobayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Speech Emotion Recognition in Under-Resourced Languages via Speech-to-Speech Translation with Bootstrapping Data Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10985v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Speech Emotion Recognition (SER) is a crucial component in developing general-purpose AI agents capable of natural human-computer interaction. However, building robust multilingual SER systems remains challenging due to the scarcity of labeled data in languages other than English and Chinese. In this paper, we propose an approach to enhance SER performance in low SER resource languages by leveraging data from high-resource languages. Specifically, we employ expressive Speech-to-Speech translation (S2ST) combined with a novel bootstrapping data selection pipeline to generate labeled data in the target language. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method is both effective and generalizable across different upstream models and languages. Our results suggest that this approach can facilitate the development of more scalable and robust multilingual SER systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10985v2</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsi-Che Lin, Yi-Cheng Lin, Huang-Cheng Chou, Hung-yi Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Speech and Audio Coding: Modern AI Technology Meets Traditional Codecs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06954v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper explores the integration of model-based and data-driven approaches within the realm of neural speech and audio coding systems. It highlights the challenges posed by the subjective evaluation processes of speech and audio codecs and discusses the limitations of purely data-driven approaches, which often require inefficiently large architectures to match the performance of model-based methods. The study presents hybrid systems as a viable solution, offering significant improvements to the performance of conventional codecs through meticulously chosen design enhancements. Specifically, it introduces a neural network-based signal enhancer designed to post-process existing codecs' output, along with the autoencoder-based end-to-end models and LPCNet--hybrid systems that combine linear predictive coding (LPC) with neural networks. Furthermore, the paper delves into predictive models operating within custom feature spaces (TF-Codec) or predefined transform domains (MDCTNet) and examines the use of psychoacoustically calibrated loss functions to train end-to-end neural audio codecs. Through these investigations, the paper demonstrates the potential of hybrid systems to advance the field of speech and audio coding by bridging the gap between traditional model-based approaches and modern data-driven techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06954v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/MSP.2024.3444318</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>in IEEE Signal Processing Magazine, vol. 41, no. 6, pp. 85-93, Nov. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Minje Kim, Jan Skoglund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Diffusion Bridges for Unsupervised Musical Audio Timbre Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06096v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Music timbre transfer is a challenging task that involves modifying the timbral characteristics of an audio signal while preserving its melodic structure. In this paper, we propose a novel method based on dual diffusion bridges, trained using the CocoChorales Dataset, which consists of unpaired monophonic single-instrument audio data. Each diffusion model is trained on a specific instrument with a Gaussian prior. During inference, a model is designated as the source model to map the input audio to its corresponding Gaussian prior, and another model is designated as the target model to reconstruct the target audio from this Gaussian prior, thereby facilitating timbre transfer. We compare our approach against existing unsupervised timbre transfer models such as VAEGAN and Gaussian Flow Bridges (GFB). Experimental results demonstrate that our method achieves both better Fr\'echet Audio Distance (FAD) and melody preservation, as reflected by lower pitch distances (DPD) compared to VAEGAN and GFB. Additionally, we discover that the noise level from the Gaussian prior, $\sigma$, can be adjusted to control the degree of melody preservation and amount of timbre transferred.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06096v4</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Mancusi, Yurii Halychanskyi, Kin Wai Cheuk, Eloi Moliner, Chieh-Hsin Lai, Stefan Uhlich, Junghyun Koo, Marco A. Mart\'inez-Ram\'irez, Wei-Hsiang Liao, Giorgio Fabbro, Yuki Mitsufuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Faetar Benchmark: Speech Recognition in a Very Under-Resourced Language</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08103v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the Faetar Automatic Speech Recognition Benchmark, a benchmark corpus designed to push the limits of current approaches to low-resource speech recognition. Faetar, a Franco-Proven\c{c}al variety spoken primarily in Italy, has no standard orthography, has virtually no existing textual or speech resources other than what is included in the benchmark, and is quite different from other forms of Franco-Proven\c{c}al. The corpus comes from field recordings, most of which are noisy, for which only 5 hrs have matching transcriptions, and for which forced alignment is of variable quality. The corpus contains an additional 20 hrs of unlabelled speech. We report baseline results from state-of-the-art multilingual speech foundation models with a best phone error rate of 30.4%, using a pipeline that continues pre-training on the foundation model using the unlabelled set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08103v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Ong, Sean Robertson, Leo Peckham, Alba Jorquera Jimenez de Aberasturi, Paula Arkhangorodsky, Robin Huo, Aman Sakhardande, Mark Hallap, Naomi Nagy, Ewan Dunbar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apollo: Band-sequence Modeling for High-Quality Audio Restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08514v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Audio restoration has become increasingly significant in modern society, not only due to the demand for high-quality auditory experiences enabled by advanced playback devices, but also because the growing capabilities of generative audio models necessitate high-fidelity audio. Typically, audio restoration is defined as a task of predicting undistorted audio from damaged input, often trained using a GAN framework to balance perception and distortion. Since audio degradation is primarily concentrated in mid- and high-frequency ranges, especially due to codecs, a key challenge lies in designing a generator capable of preserving low-frequency information while accurately reconstructing high-quality mid- and high-frequency content. Inspired by recent advancements in high-sample-rate music separation, speech enhancement, and audio codec models, we propose Apollo, a generative model designed for high-sample-rate audio restoration. Apollo employs an explicit frequency band split module to model the relationships between different frequency bands, allowing for more coherent and higher-quality restored audio. Evaluated on the MUSDB18-HQ and MoisesDB datasets, Apollo consistently outperforms existing SR-GAN models across various bit rates and music genres, particularly excelling in complex scenarios involving mixtures of multiple instruments and vocals. Apollo significantly improves music restoration quality while maintaining computational efficiency. The source code for Apollo is publicly available at https://github.com/JusperLee/Apollo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08514v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Li, Yi Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaptVC: High Quality Voice Conversion with Adaptive Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01347v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The goal of voice conversion is to transform the speech of a source speaker to sound like that of a reference speaker while preserving the original content. A key challenge is to extract disentangled linguistic content from the source and voice style from the reference. While existing approaches leverage various methods to isolate the two, a generalization still requires further attention, especially for robustness in zero-shot scenarios. In this paper, we achieve successful disentanglement of content and speaker features by tuning self-supervised speech features with adapters. The adapters are trained to dynamically encode nuanced features from rich self-supervised features, and the decoder fuses them to produce speech that accurately resembles the reference with minimal loss of content. Moreover, we leverage a conditional flow matching decoder with cross-attention speaker conditioning to further boost the synthesis quality and efficiency. Subjective and objective evaluations in a zero-shot scenario demonstrate that the proposed method outperforms existing models in speech quality and similarity to the reference speech.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01347v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaehun Kim, Ji-Hoon Kim, Yeunju Choi, Tan Dat Nguyen, Seongkyu Mun, Joon Son Chung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MusicGen-Stem: Multi-stem music generation and edition through autoregressive modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01757v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While most music generation models generate a mixture of stems (in mono or stereo), we propose to train a multi-stem generative model with 3 stems (bass, drums and other) that learn the musical dependencies between them. To do so, we train one specialized compression algorithm per stem to tokenize the music into parallel streams of tokens. Then, we leverage recent improvements in the task of music source separation to train a multi-stream text-to-music language model on a large dataset. Finally, thanks to a particular conditioning method, our model is able to edit bass, drums or other stems on existing or generated songs as well as doing iterative composition (e.g. generating bass on top of existing drums). This gives more flexibility in music generation algorithms and it is to the best of our knowledge the first open-source multi-stem autoregressive music generation model that can perform good quality generation and coherent source editing. Code and model weights will be released and samples are available on https://simonrouard.github.io/musicgenstem/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01757v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Rouard, Robin San Roman, Yossi Adi, Axel Roebel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Samba-ASR: State-Of-The-Art Speech Recognition Leveraging Structured State-Space Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02832v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose Samba ASR,the first state of the art Automatic Speech Recognition(ASR)model leveraging the novel Mamba architecture as both encoder and decoder,built on the foundation of state space models(SSMs).Unlike transformerbased ASR models,which rely on self-attention mechanisms to capture dependencies,Samba ASR effectively models both local and global temporal dependencies using efficient statespace dynamics,achieving remarkable performance gains.By addressing the limitations of transformers,such as quadratic scaling with input length and difficulty in handling longrange dependencies,Samba ASR achieves superior accuracy and efficiency.Experimental results demonstrate that Samba ASR surpasses existing opensource transformerbased ASR models across various standard benchmarks,establishing it as the new state of theart in ASR.Extensive evaluations on the benchmark dataset show significant improvements in Word Error Rate(WER),with competitive performance even in lowresource scenarios.Furthermore,the inherent computational efficiency and parameter optimization of the Mamba architecture make Samba ASR a scalable and robust solution for diverse ASR tasks.Our contributions include the development of a new Samba ASR architecture for automatic speech recognition(ASR),demonstrating the superiority of structured statespace models(SSMs)over transformer based models for speech sequence processing.We provide a comprehensive evaluation on public benchmarks,showcasing stateoftheart(SOTA)performance,and present an indepth analysis of computational efficiency,robustness to noise,and sequence generalization.This work highlights the viability of Mamba SSMs as a transformerfree alternative for efficient and accurate ASR.By leveraging the advancements of statespace modeling,Samba ASR redefines ASR performance standards and sets a new benchmark for future research in this field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02832v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Syed Abdul Gaffar Shakhadri, Kruthika KR, Kartik Basavaraj Angadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piano Transcription by Hierarchical Language Modeling with Pretrained Roll-based Encoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03038v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Automatic Music Transcription (AMT), aiming to get musical notes from raw audio, typically uses frame-level systems with piano-roll outputs or language model (LM)-based systems with note-level predictions. However, frame-level systems require manual thresholding, while the LM-based systems struggle with long sequences. In this paper, we propose a hybrid method combining pre-trained roll-based encoders with an LM decoder to leverage the strengths of both methods. Besides, our approach employs a hierarchical prediction strategy, first predicting onset and pitch, then velocity, and finally offset. The hierarchical prediction strategy reduces computational costs by breaking down long sequences into different hierarchies. Evaluated on two benchmark roll-based encoders, our method outperforms traditional piano-roll outputs 0.01 and 0.022 in onset-offset-velocity F1 score, demonstrating its potential as a performance-enhancing plug-in for arbitrary roll-based music transcription encoder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03038v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dichucheng Li, Yongyi Zang, Qiuqiang Kong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Machine Learning Can Predict Videoconference Fluidity and Enjoyment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03190v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Videoconferencing is now a frequent mode of communication in both professional and informal settings, yet it often lacks the fluidity and enjoyment of in-person conversation. This study leverages multimodal machine learning to predict moments of negative experience in videoconferencing. We sampled thousands of short clips from the RoomReader corpus, extracting audio embeddings, facial actions, and body motion features to train models for identifying low conversational fluidity, low enjoyment, and classifying conversational events (backchanneling, interruption, or gap). Our best models achieved an ROC-AUC of up to 0.87 on hold-out videoconference sessions, with domain-general audio features proving most critical. This work demonstrates that multimodal audio-video signals can effectively predict high-level subjective conversational outcomes. In addition, this is a contribution to research on videoconferencing user experience by showing that multimodal machine learning can be used to identify rare moments of negative user experience for further study or mitigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03190v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Chang, Viswadruth Akkaraju, Ray McFadden Cogliano, David Poeppel, Dustin Freeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
