<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.AS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.AS</link>
    <description>eess.AS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.AS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Phi-Omni-ST: A multimodal language model for direct speech-to-speech translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04392v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Speech-aware language models (LMs) have demonstrated capabilities in understanding spoken language while generating text-based responses. However, enabling them to produce speech output efficiently and effectively remains a challenge. In this paper, we present Phi-Omni-ST, a multimodal LM for direct speech-to-speech translation (ST), built on the open-source Phi-4 MM model. Phi-Omni-ST extends its predecessor by generating translated speech using an audio transformer head that predicts audio tokens with a delay relative to text tokens, followed by a streaming vocoder for waveform synthesis. Our experimental results on the CVSS-C dataset demonstrate Phi-Omni-ST's superior performance, significantly surpassing existing baseline models trained on the same dataset. Furthermore, when we scale up the training data and the model size, Phi-Omni-ST reaches on-par performance with the current SOTA model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04392v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Hu, Haibin Wu, Ruchao Fan, Xiaofei Wang, Heng Lu, Yao Qian, Jinyu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can we reconstruct a dysarthric voice with the large speech model Parler TTS?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04397v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Speech disorders can make communication hard or even impossible for those who develop them. Personalised Text-to-Speech is an attractive option as a communication aid. We attempt voice reconstruction using a large speech model, with which we generate an approximation of a dysarthric speaker's voice prior to the onset of their condition. In particular, we investigate whether a state-of-the-art large speech model, Parler TTS, can generate intelligible speech while maintaining speaker identity. We curate a dataset and annotate it with relevant speaker and intelligibility information, and use this to fine-tune the model. Our results show that the model can indeed learn to generate from the distribution of this challenging data, but struggles to control intelligibility and to maintain consistent speaker identity. We propose future directions to improve controllability of this class of model, for the voice reconstruction task.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04397v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariadna Sanchez, Simon King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bringing Interpretability to Neural Audio Codecs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The advent of neural audio codecs has increased in popularity due to their potential for efficiently modeling audio with transformers. Such advanced codecs represent audio from a highly continuous waveform to low-sampled discrete units. In contrast to semantic units, acoustic units may lack interpretability because their training objectives primarily focus on reconstruction performance. This paper proposes a two-step approach to explore the encoding of speech information within the codec tokens. The primary goal of the analysis stage is to gain deeper insight into how speech attributes such as content, identity, and pitch are encoded. The synthesis stage then trains an AnCoGen network for post-hoc explanation of codecs to extract speech attributes from the respective tokens directly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04492v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samir Sadok, Julien Hauret, \'Eric Bavu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>French Listening Tests for the Assessment of Intelligibility, Quality, and Identity of Body-Conducted Speech Enhancement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study evaluates the Extreme Bandwidth Extension Network (EBEN) model on body-conduction sensors through listening tests. Using the Vibravox dataset, we assess intelligibility with a French Modified Rhyme Test, speech quality with a MUSHRA (MUltiple Stimuli with Hidden Reference and Anchor) protocol and speaker identity preservation with an A/B identification task. The experiments involved male and female speakers recorded with a forehead accelerometer, rigid in-ear and throat microphones. The results confirm that EBEN enhances both speech quality and intelligibility. It slightly degrades speaker identification performance when applied to female speakers' throat microphone recordings. The findings also demonstrate a correlation between Short-Time Objective Intelligibility (STOI) and perceived quality in body-conducted speech, while speaker verification using ECAPA2-TDNN aligns well with identification performance. No tested metric reliably predicts EBEN's effect on intelligibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04495v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Joubaud, Julien Hauret, V\'eronique Zimpfer, \'Eric Bavu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Efficient Speech-Text Jointly Decoding within One Speech Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Speech language models (Speech LMs) enable end-to-end speech-text modelling within a single model, offering a promising direction for spoken dialogue systems. The choice of speech-text jointly decoding paradigm plays a critical role in performance, efficiency, and alignment quality. In this work, we systematically compare representative joint speech-text decoding strategies-including the interleaved, and parallel generation paradigms-under a controlled experimental setup using the same base language model, speech tokenizer and training data. Our results show that the interleaved approach achieves the best alignment. However it suffers from slow inference due to long token sequence length. To address this, we propose a novel early-stop interleaved (ESI) pattern that not only significantly accelerates decoding but also yields slightly better performance. Additionally, we curate high-quality question answering (QA) datasets to further improve speech QA performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04518v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haibin Wu, Yuxuan Hu, Ruchao Fan, Xiaofei Wang, Kenichi Kumatani, Bo Ren, Jianwei Yu, Heng Lu, Lijuan Wang, Yao Qian, Jinyu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EMO-Debias: Benchmarking Gender Debiasing Techniques in Multi-Label Speech Emotion Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04652v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Speech emotion recognition (SER) systems often exhibit gender bias. However, the effectiveness and robustness of existing debiasing methods in such multi-label scenarios remain underexplored. To address this gap, we present EMO-Debias, a large-scale comparison of 13 debiasing methods applied to multi-label SER. Our study encompasses techniques from pre-processing, regularization, adversarial learning, biased learners, and distributionally robust optimization. Experiments conducted on acted and naturalistic emotion datasets, using WavLM and XLSR representations, evaluate each method under conditions of gender imbalance. Our analysis quantifies the trade-offs between fairness and accuracy, identifying which approaches consistently reduce gender performance gaps without compromising overall model performance. The findings provide actionable insights for selecting effective debiasing strategies and highlight the impact of dataset distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04652v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Cheng Lin, Huang-Cheng Chou, Yu-Hsuan Li Liang, Hung-yi Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multivariate Probabilistic Assessment of Speech Quality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04890v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mean opinion score (MOS) is a standard metric for assessing speech quality, but its singular focus fails to identify specific distortions when low scores are observed. The NISQA dataset addresses this limitation by providing ratings across four additional dimensions: noisiness, coloration, discontinuity, and loudness, alongside MOS. In this paper, we extend the explored univariate MOS estimation to a multivariate framework by modeling these dimensions jointly using a multivariate Gaussian distribution. Our approach utilizes Cholesky decomposition to predict covariances without imposing restrictive assumptions and extends probabilistic affine transformations to a multivariate context. Experimental results show that our model performs on par with state-of-the-art methods in point estimation, while uniquely providing uncertainty and correlation estimates across speech quality dimensions. This enables better diagnosis of poor speech quality and informs targeted improvements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04890v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fredrik Cumlin, Xinyu Liang, Victor Ungureanu, Chandan K. A. Reddy, Christian Sch\"uldt, Saikat Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Speaker Count, Duration, and Accent Diversity on Zero-Shot Accent Robustness in Low-Resource ASR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04364v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To build an automatic speech recognition (ASR) system that can serve everyone in the world, the ASR needs to be robust to a wide range of accents including unseen accents. We systematically study how three different variables in training data -- the number of speakers, the audio duration per each individual speaker, and the diversity of accents -- affect ASR robustness towards unseen accents in a low-resource training regime. We observe that for a fixed number of ASR training hours, it is more beneficial to increase the number of speakers (which means each speaker contributes less) than the number of hours contributed per speaker. We also observe that more speakers enables ASR performance gains from scaling number of hours. Surprisingly, we observe minimal benefits to prioritizing speakers with different accents when the number of speakers is controlled. Our work suggests that practitioners should prioritize increasing the speaker count in ASR training data composition for new languages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04364v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Xin Yong, Vineel Pratap, Michael Auli, Jean Maillard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grapheme-Coherent Phonemic and Prosodic Annotation of Speech by Implicit and Explicit Grapheme Conditioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04527v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a model to obtain phonemic and prosodic labels of speech that are coherent with graphemes. Unlike previous methods that simply fine-tune a pre-trained ASR model with the labels, the proposed model conditions the label generation on corresponding graphemes by two methods: 1) Add implicit grapheme conditioning through prompt encoder using pre-trained BERT features. 2) Explicitly prune the label hypotheses inconsistent with the grapheme during inference. These methods enable obtaining parallel data of speech, the labels, and graphemes, which is applicable to various downstream tasks such as text-to-speech and accent estimation from text. Experiments showed that the proposed method significantly improved the consistency between graphemes and the predicted labels. Further, experiments on accent estimation task confirmed that the created parallel data by the proposed method effectively improve the estimation accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04527v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hien Ohnaka, Yuma Shirahata, Byeongseon Park, Ryuichi Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LESS: Large Language Model Enhanced Semi-Supervised Learning for Speech Foundational Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04586v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce LESS (Large Language Model Enhanced Semi-supervised Learning), a versatile framework that leverages Large Language Models (LLMs) to correct pseudo labels generated from in-the-wild data. Within the LESS framework, pseudo-labeled text from Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) or Automatic Speech Translation (AST) of the unsupervised data is refined by an LLM, and augmented by a data filtering strategy to optimize LLM knowledge transfer efficiency. Experiments on both Mandarin ASR and Spanish-to-English AST tasks show that LESS achieves a notable absolute WER reduction of 3.77% on the Wenet Speech test set, as well as BLEU scores of 34.0 and 64.7 on Callhome and Fisher test sets respectively. These results validate the adaptability of LESS across different languages, tasks, and domains. Ablation studies conducted with various LLMs and prompt configurations provide novel insights into leveraging LLM-derived knowledge for speech processing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04586v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Ding, Fan Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-based phoneme-to-grapheme for phoneme-based speech recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04711v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In automatic speech recognition (ASR), phoneme-based multilingual pre-training and crosslingual fine-tuning is attractive for its high data efficiency and competitive results compared to subword-based models. However, Weighted Finite State Transducer (WFST) based decoding is limited by its complex pipeline and inability to leverage large language models (LLMs). Therefore, we propose LLM-based phoneme-to-grapheme (LLM-P2G) decoding for phoneme-based ASR, consisting of speech-to-phoneme (S2P) and phoneme-to-grapheme (P2G). A challenge is that there seems to have information loss in cascading S2P and P2G. To address this challenge, we propose two training strategies: data augmentation with noisy phonemes (DANP), and randomized top-$K$ marginalized (TKM) training and decoding. Our experimental results show that LLM-P2G outperforms WFST-based systems in crosslingual ASR for Polish and German, by relative WER reductions of 3.6% and 6.9% respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04711v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Te Ma, Min Bi, Saierdaer Yusuyin, Hao Huang, Zhijian Ou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IIITH-BUT system for IWSLT 2025 low-resource Bhojpuri to Hindi speech translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04714v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents the submission of IIITH-BUT to the IWSLT 2025 shared task on speech translation for the low-resource Bhojpuri-Hindi language pair. We explored the impact of hyperparameter optimisation and data augmentation techniques on the performance of the SeamlessM4T model fine-tuned for this specific task. We systematically investigated a range of hyperparameters including learning rate schedules, number of update steps, warm-up steps, label smoothing, and batch sizes; and report their effect on translation quality. To address data scarcity, we applied speed perturbation and SpecAugment and studied their effect on translation quality. We also examined the use of cross-lingual signal through joint training with Marathi and Bhojpuri speech data. Our experiments reveal that careful selection of hyperparameters and the application of simple yet effective augmentation techniques significantly improve performance in low-resource settings. We also analysed the translation hypotheses to understand various kinds of errors that impacted the translation quality in terms of BLEU.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04714v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhavana Akkiraju, Aishwarya Pothula, Santosh Kesiraju, Anil Kumar Vuppala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving AI-generated music with user-guided training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: AI music generation has advanced rapidly, with models like diffusion and autoregressive algorithms enabling high-fidelity outputs. These tools can alter styles, mix instruments, or isolate them. Since sound can be visualized as spectrograms, image-generation algorithms can be applied to generate novel music. However, these algorithms are typically trained on fixed datasets, which makes it challenging for them to interpret and respond to user input accurately. This is especially problematic because music is highly subjective and requires a level of personalization that image generation does not provide. In this work, we propose a human-computation approach to gradually improve the performance of these algorithms based on user interactions. The human-computation element involves aggregating and selecting user ratings to use as the loss function for fine-tuning the model. We employ a genetic algorithm that incorporates user feedback to enhance the baseline performance of a model initially trained on a fixed dataset. The effectiveness of this approach is measured by the average increase in user ratings with each iteration. In the pilot test, the first iteration showed an average rating increase of 0.2 compared to the baseline. The second iteration further improved upon this, achieving an additional increase of 0.39 over the first iteration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04852v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishwa Mohan Singh, Sai Anirudh Aryasomayajula, Ahan Chatterjee, Beste Aydemir, Rifat Mehreen Amin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Practitioner's Guide to Building ASR Models for Low-Resource Languages: A Case Study on Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04915v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An effective approach to the development of ASR systems for low-resource languages is to fine-tune an existing multilingual end-to-end model. When the original model has been trained on large quantities of data from many languages, fine-tuning can be effective with limited training data, even when the language in question was not present in the original training data. The fine-tuning approach has been encouraged by the availability of public-domain E2E models and is widely believed to lead to state-of-the-art results. This paper, however, challenges that belief. We show that an approach combining hybrid HMMs with self-supervised models can yield substantially better performance with limited training data. This combination allows better utilisation of all available speech and text data through continued self-supervised pre-training and semi-supervised training. We benchmark our approach on Scottish Gaelic, achieving WER reductions of 32% relative over our best fine-tuned Whisper model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04915v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ond\v{r}ej Klejch, William Lamb, Peter Bell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better Semi-supervised Learning for Multi-domain ASR Through Incremental Retraining and Data Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04981v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fine-tuning pretrained ASR models for specific domains is challenging when labeled data is scarce. But unlabeled audio and labeled data from related domains are often available. We propose an incremental semi-supervised learning pipeline that first integrates a small in-domain labeled set and an auxiliary dataset from a closely related domain, achieving a relative improvement of 4% over no auxiliary data. Filtering based on multi-model consensus or named entity recognition (NER) is then applied to select and iteratively refine pseudo-labels, showing slower performance saturation compared to random selection. Evaluated on the multi-domain Wow call center and Fisher English corpora, it outperforms single-step fine-tuning. Consensus-based filtering outperforms other methods, providing up to 22.3% relative improvement on Wow and 24.8% on Fisher over single-step fine-tuning with random selection. NER is the second-best filter, providing competitive performance at a lower computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04981v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andres Carofilis, Pradeep Rangappa, Srikanth Madikeri, Shashi Kumar, Sergio Burdisso, Jeena Prakash, Esau Villatoro-Tello, Petr Motlicek, Bidisha Sharma, Kadri Hacioglu, Shankar Venkatesan, Saurabh Vyas, Andreas Stolcke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The NTNU System at the S&amp;I Challenge 2025 SLA Open Track</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05121v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A recent line of research on spoken language assessment (SLA) employs neural models such as BERT and wav2vec 2.0 (W2V) to evaluate speaking proficiency across linguistic and acoustic modalities. Although both models effectively capture features relevant to oral competence, each exhibits modality-specific limitations. BERT-based methods rely on ASR transcripts, which often fail to capture prosodic and phonetic cues for SLA. In contrast, W2V-based methods excel at modeling acoustic features but lack semantic interpretability. To overcome these limitations, we propose a system that integrates W2V with Phi-4 multimodal large language model (MLLM) through a score fusion strategy. The proposed system achieves a root mean square error (RMSE) of 0.375 on the official test set of the Speak &amp; Improve Challenge 2025, securing second place in the competition. For comparison, the RMSEs of the top-ranked, third-ranked, and official baseline systems are 0.364, 0.384, and 0.444, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05121v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Yun Lin, Tien-Hong Lo, Yu-Hsuan Fang, Jhen-Ke Lin, Chung-Chun Wang, Hao-Chien Lu, Berlin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AudioLens: A Closer Look at Auditory Attribute Perception of Large Audio-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05140v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the internal mechanisms of large audio-language models (LALMs) is crucial for interpreting their behavior and improving performance. This work presents the first in-depth analysis of how LALMs internally perceive and recognize auditory attributes. By applying vocabulary projection on three state-of-the-art LALMs, we track how attribute information evolves across layers and token positions. We find that attribute information generally decreases with layer depth when recognition fails, and that resolving attributes at earlier layers correlates with better accuracy. Moreover, LALMs heavily rely on querying auditory inputs for predicting attributes instead of aggregating necessary information in hidden states at attribute-mentioning positions. Based on our findings, we demonstrate a method to enhance LALMs. Our results offer insights into auditory attribute processing, paving the way for future improvements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05140v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Kai Yang, Neo Ho, Yi-Jyun Lee, Hung-yi Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of LLMs in Speech is Often Flawed: Test Set Contamination in Large Language Models for Speech Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22251v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent work suggests that large language models (LLMs) can improve performance of speech tasks compared to existing systems. To support their claims, results on LibriSpeech and Common Voice are often quoted. However, this work finds that a substantial amount of the LibriSpeech and Common Voice evaluation sets appear in public LLM pretraining corpora. This calls into question the reliability of findings drawn from these two datasets. To measure contamination impact, LLMs trained with/without contamination are compared. A contaminated LLM is more likely to generate test sentences it has seen during training. Then, speech recognisers based on LLMs are compared. They show only subtle error rate differences if the LLM is contaminated, but assign significantly higher probabilities to transcriptions seen during LLM training. Results show that LLM outputs can be biased by tiny amounts of data contamination, highlighting the importance of evaluating LLM-based speech systems with held-out data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22251v2</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Tseng, Titouan Parcollet, Rogier van Dalen, Shucong Zhang, Sourav Bhattacharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inter-Speaker Relative Cues for Text-Guided Target Speech Extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01483v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel approach that utilizes inter-speaker relative cues for distinguishing target speakers and extracting their voices from mixtures. Continuous cues (e.g., temporal order, age, pitch level) are grouped by relative differences, while discrete cues (e.g., language, gender, emotion) retain their categories. Relative cues offers greater flexibility than fixed speech attribute classification, facilitating much easier expansion of text-guided target speech extraction datasets. Our experiments show that combining all relative cues yields better performance than random subsets, with gender and temporal order being the most robust across languages and reverberant conditions. Additional cues like pitch level, loudness, distance, speaking duration, language, and pitch range also demonstrate notable benefit in complex scenarios. Fine-tuning pre-trained WavLM Base+ CNN encoders improves overall performance over the baseline of using only a Conv1d encoder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01483v2</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang Dai, Archontis Politis, Tuomas Virtanen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Tuning Spectral Clustering for Speaker Diarization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00023v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Spectral clustering has proven effective in grouping speech representations for speaker diarization tasks, although post-processing the affinity matrix remains difficult due to the need for careful tuning before constructing the Laplacian. In this study, we present a novel pruning algorithm to create a sparse affinity matrix called spectral clustering on p-neighborhood retained affinity matrix (SC-pNA). Our method improves on node-specific fixed neighbor selection by allowing a variable number of neighbors, eliminating the need for external tuning data as the pruning parameters are derived directly from the affinity matrix. SC-pNA does so by identifying two clusters in every row of the initial affinity matrix, and retains only the top p % similarity scores from the cluster containing larger similarities. Spectral clustering is performed subsequently, with the number of clusters determined as the maximum eigengap. Experimental results on the challenging DIHARD-III dataset highlight the superiority of SC-pNA, which is also computationally more efficient than existing auto-tuning approaches. Our implementations are available at https://github.com/nikhilraghav29/SC-pNA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00023v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICASSP49660.2025.10890194</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ICASSP 2025 - 2025 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nikhil Raghav, Avisek Gupta, Md Sahidullah, Swagatam Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sonic: Shifting Focus to Global Audio Perception in Portrait Animation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16331v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The study of talking face generation mainly explores the intricacies of synchronizing facial movements and crafting visually appealing, temporally-coherent animations. However, due to the limited exploration of global audio perception, current approaches predominantly employ auxiliary visual and spatial knowledge to stabilize the movements, which often results in the deterioration of the naturalness and temporal inconsistencies.Considering the essence of audio-driven animation, the audio signal serves as the ideal and unique priors to adjust facial expressions and lip movements, without resorting to interference of any visual signals. Based on this motivation, we propose a novel paradigm, dubbed as Sonic, to {s}hift f{o}cus on the exploration of global audio per{c}ept{i}o{n}.To effectively leverage global audio knowledge, we disentangle it into intra- and inter-clip audio perception and collaborate with both aspects to enhance overall perception.For the intra-clip audio perception, 1). \textbf{Context-enhanced audio learning}, in which long-range intra-clip temporal audio knowledge is extracted to provide facial expression and lip motion priors implicitly expressed as the tone and speed of speech. 2). \textbf{Motion-decoupled controller}, in which the motion of the head and expression movement are disentangled and independently controlled by intra-audio clips. Most importantly, for inter-clip audio perception, as a bridge to connect the intra-clips to achieve the global perception, \textbf{Time-aware position shift fusion}, in which the global inter-clip audio information is considered and fused for long-audio inference via through consecutively time-aware shifted windows. Extensive experiments demonstrate that the novel audio-driven paradigm outperform existing SOTA methodologies in terms of video quality, temporally consistency, lip synchronization precision, and motion diversity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16331v3</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaozhong Ji, Xiaobin Hu, Zhihong Xu, Junwei Zhu, Chuming Lin, Qingdong He, Jiangning Zhang, Donghao Luo, Yi Chen, Qin Lin, Qinglin Lu, Chengjie Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMS-LLaMA: Efficient LLM-based Audio-Visual Speech Recognition with Minimal Multimodal Speech Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11315v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Audio-Visual Speech Recognition (AVSR) achieves robust speech recognition in noisy environments by combining auditory and visual information. However, recent Large Language Model (LLM) based AVSR systems incur high computational costs due to the high temporal resolution of audio-visual speech processed by LLMs. In this work, we introduce an efficient multimodal speech LLM framework that minimizes token length while preserving essential linguistic content. Our approach employs an early AV-fusion module for streamlined feature integration, an audio-visual speech Q-Former that dynamically allocates tokens based on input duration, and a refined query allocation strategy with a speech rate predictor to adjust token allocation according to speaking speed of each audio sample. Extensive experiments on the LRS3 dataset show that our method achieves state-of-the-art performance with a WER of 0.72% while using only 3.5 tokens per second. Moreover, our approach not only reduces token usage by 86% compared to the previous multimodal speech LLM framework, but also improves computational efficiency by reducing FLOPs by 35.7%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11315v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeong Hun Yeo, Hyeongseop Rha, Se Jin Park, Yong Man Ro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hearing Anywhere in Any Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10746v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In mixed reality applications, a realistic acoustic experience in spatial environments is as crucial as the visual experience for achieving true immersion. Despite recent advances in neural approaches for Room Impulse Response (RIR) estimation, most existing methods are limited to the single environment on which they are trained, lacking the ability to generalize to new rooms with different geometries and surface materials. We aim to develop a unified model capable of reconstructing the spatial acoustic experience of any environment with minimum additional measurements. To this end, we present xRIR, a framework for cross-room RIR prediction. The core of our generalizable approach lies in combining a geometric feature extractor, which captures spatial context from panorama depth images, with a RIR encoder that extracts detailed acoustic features from only a few reference RIR samples. To evaluate our method, we introduce ACOUSTICROOMS, a new dataset featuring high-fidelity simulation of over 300,000 RIRs from 260 rooms. Experiments show that our method strongly outperforms a series of baselines. Furthermore, we successfully perform sim-to-real transfer by evaluating our model on four real-world environments, demonstrating the generalizability of our approach and the realism of our dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10746v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiulong Liu, Anurag Kumar, Paul Calamia, Sebastia V. Amengual, Calvin Murdock, Ishwarya Ananthabhotla, Philip Robinson, Eli Shlizerman, Vamsi Krishna Ithapu, Ruohan Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Masked Autoencoders Also Listen to Birds?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12880v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Masked Autoencoders (MAEs) have shown competitive results in audio classification by learning rich semantic representations through an efficient self-supervised reconstruction task. However, general-purpose models fail to generalize well when applied directly to fine-grained audio domains. Specifically, bird-sound classification requires distinguishing subtle inter-species differences and managing high intra-species acoustic variability, thereby revealing the performance limitations of general-domain Audio-MAE models. This work demonstrates that bridging this domain gap requires more than domain-specific pretraining data; adapting the entire training pipeline is crucial. We systematically revisit and adapt the pretraining recipe, fine-tuning methods, and frozen feature utilization to bird sounds using BirdSet, a large-scale bioacoustic dataset comparable to AudioSet. Our resulting Bird-MAE achieves new state-of-the-art results in BirdSet's multi-label classification benchmark. Additionally, we introduce the parameter-efficient prototypical probing, enhancing the utility of frozen MAE representations and closely approaching fine-tuning performance in low-resource settings. Bird-MAE's prototypical probes outperform linear probing by up to 37%$_\text{p}$ in MAP and narrow the gap to fine-tuning to approximately 3.3%$_\text{p}$ on average across BirdSet downstream tasks. Bird-MAE also demonstrates robust few-shot capabilities with prototypical probing in our newly established few-shot benchmark on BirdSet, highlighting the potential of tailored self-supervised learning pipelines for fine-grained audio domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12880v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Rauch, Ren\'e Heinrich, Ilyass Moummad, Alexis Joly, Bernhard Sick, Christoph Scholz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAVL: A Multilingual Audio-Video Lyrics Dataset for Animated Song Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18614v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Lyrics translation requires both accurate semantic transfer and preservation of musical rhythm, syllabic structure, and poetic style. In animated musicals, the challenge intensifies due to alignment with visual and auditory cues. We introduce Multilingual Audio-Video Lyrics Benchmark for Animated Song Translation (MAVL), the first multilingual, multimodal benchmark for singable lyrics translation. By integrating text, audio, and video, MAVL enables richer and more expressive translations than text-only approaches. Building on this, we propose Syllable-Constrained Audio-Video LLM with Chain-of-Thought SylAVL-CoT, which leverages audio-video cues and enforces syllabic constraints to produce natural-sounding lyrics. Experimental results demonstrate that SylAVL-CoT significantly outperforms text-based models in singability and contextual accuracy, emphasizing the value of multimodal, multilingual approaches for lyrics translation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18614v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Woohyun Cho, Youngmin Kim, Sunghyun Lee, Youngjae Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STOPA: A Database of Systematic VariaTion Of DeePfake Audio for Open-Set Source Tracing and Attribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19644v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A key research area in deepfake speech detection is source tracing - determining the origin of synthesised utterances. The approaches may involve identifying the acoustic model (AM), vocoder model (VM), or other generation-specific parameters. However, progress is limited by the lack of a dedicated, systematically curated dataset. To address this, we introduce STOPA, a systematically varied and metadata-rich dataset for deepfake speech source tracing, covering 8 AMs, 6 VMs, and diverse parameter settings across 700k samples from 13 distinct synthesisers. Unlike existing datasets, which often feature limited variation or sparse metadata, STOPA provides a systematically controlled framework covering a broader range of generative factors, such as the choice of the vocoder model, acoustic model, or pretrained weights, ensuring higher attribution reliability. This control improves attribution accuracy, aiding forensic analysis, deepfake detection, and generative model transparency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19644v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Firc, Manasi Chibber, Jagabandhu Mishra, Vishwanath Pratap Singh, Tomi Kinnunen, Kamil Malinka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FGAS: Fixed Decoder Network-Based Audio Steganography with Adversarial Perturbation Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22266v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rapid development of Artificial Intelligence Generated Content (AIGC) has made high-fidelity generated audio widely available across the Internet, providing diverse cover signals for covert communication. Driven by advances in deep learning, current audio steganography schemes are mainly based on encoding-decoding network architectures. While these methods greatly improve the security of audio steganography, they typically require complex training and large pre-trained models. To address the aforementioned issues, this paper pioneers a Fixed Decoder Network-Based Audio Steganography with Adversarial Perturbation Generation (FGAS). Adversarial perturbations carrying secret message are embedded into the cover audio to generate stego audio. The receiver only needs to share the structure and weights of the fixed decoder network to accurately extract the secret message from the stego audio, this eliminates the reliance on large pre-trained models. In FGAS, we propose an audio Adversarial Perturbation Generation (APG) strategy and design a lightweight fixed decoder. The fixed decoder guarantees reliable extraction of the hidden message, while the adversarial perturbations are optimized to keep the stego audio perceptually and statistically close to the cover audio, thereby improving resistance to steganalysis. The experimental results show that FGAS significantly improves the quality of stego audio, achieving an average PSNR gain of over 10 dB compared to SOTA methods. Moreover, FGAS exhibits superior anti-steganalysis performance under different relative payloads; under high-capacity embedding, it achieves a classification error rate about 2% higher, indicating stronger anti-steganalysis performance compared to current SOTA methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22266v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialin Yan, Yu Cheng, Zhaoxia Yin, Xinpeng Zhang, Shilin Wang, Tanfeng Sun, Xinghao Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fewer Hallucinations, More Verification: A Three-Stage LLM-Based Framework for ASR Error Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24347v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) error correction aims to correct recognition errors while preserving accurate text. Although traditional approaches demonstrate moderate effectiveness, LLMs offer a paradigm that eliminates the need for training and labeled data. However, directly using LLMs will encounter hallucinations problem, which may lead to the modification of the correct text. To address this problem, we propose the Reliable LLM Correction Framework (RLLM-CF), which consists of three stages: (1) error pre-detection, (2) chain-of-thought sub-tasks iterative correction, and (3) reasoning process verification. The advantage of our method is that it does not require additional information or fine-tuning of the model, and ensures the correctness of the LLM correction under multi-pass programming. Experiments on AISHELL-1, AISHELL-2, and Librispeech show that the GPT-4o model enhanced by our framework achieves 21%, 11%, 9%, and 11.4% relative reductions in CER/WER.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24347v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangui Fang, Baixu Cheng, Jing Peng, Xu Li, Yu Xi, Chengwei Zhang, Guohui Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NTPP: Generative Speech Language Modeling for Dual-Channel Spoken Dialogue via Next-Token-Pair Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00975v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the impressive capabilities of GPT-4o, there is growing interest in enabling speech language models (SLMs) to engage in natural, fluid spoken interactions with humans. Recent advancements have led to the development of several SLMs that demonstrate promising results in this area. However, current approaches have yet to fully exploit dual-channel speech data, which inherently captures the structure and dynamics of human conversation. In this work, we systematically explore the use of dual-channel speech data in the context of modern large language models, and introduce a novel generative modeling paradigm, Next-Token-Pair Prediction (NTPP), to enable speaker-independent dual-channel spoken dialogue learning using decoder-only architectures for the first time. We evaluate our approach on standard benchmarks, and empirical results show that our proposed method, NTPP, significantly improves the conversational abilities of SLMs in terms of turn-taking prediction, response coherence, and naturalness. Moreover, compared to existing methods, NTPP achieves substantially lower inference latency, highlighting its practical efficiency for real-time applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00975v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qichao Wang, Ziqiao Meng, Wenqian Cui, Yifei Zhang, Pengcheng Wu, Bingzhe Wu, Irwin King, Liang Chen, Peilin Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
