<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Variational wavefunction for Mott insulator at finite $U$ using ancilla qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Mott regime with finite $U$ offers a promising platform for exploring novel phases of matter, such as quantum spin liquids (QSL) that exhibit fractionalization and emergent gauge field. Here, we provide a new class wavefunction, dubbed ancilla wavefunction, to capture both charge and spin (gauge) fluctuations in QSLs at finite $U$. The ancilla wavefunction can unify the Fermi liquid and Mott insulator phases with a single variation parameter $\Phi$ tuning the charge gap. As $\Phi \rightarrow\infty$, the wavefunction reduces to the Gutzwiller projected state, while at $\Phi=U/2$, it is effectively equivalent to applying an inverse Schrieffer-Wolff transformation to the Gutzwiller projected state. This wavefunction can be numerically simulated in the matrix product state representation, and its performance is supported by numerical results for both one- and two-dimensional Hubbard models. Besides, we propose the possibility of a narrow regime of fractional Fermi liquid phase between the usual Fermi liquid and the Mott insulator phases close to the metal insulator transition -- a scenario typically overlooked by the conventional slave rotor theory. Our ancilla wavefunction offers a novel conceptual framework and a powerful numerical tool for understanding Mott physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07512v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boran Zhou, Hui-Ke Jin, Ya-Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge Susceptibility and Kubo Response in Hatsugai-Kohmoto-related Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study in depth the charge susceptibility for the band Hatsugai-Kohmoto (HK) and orbital (OHK) models. As either of these models describes a Mott insulator, the charge susceptibility takes on the form of a modified Lindhard function with lower and upper Hubbard bands, thereby giving rise to a multi-pole structure. The particle-hole continuum consists of hot spots along the $\omega$ vs $q$ axis arising from inter-band transitions. Such transitions, which are strongly suppressed in non-interacting systems, are obtained here because of the non-rigidity of the Hubbard bands. This modified Lindhard function gives rise to a plasmon dispersion that is inversely dependent on the momentum, resulting in an additional contribution to the conventional f-sum rule. This extra contribution originates from a long-range diamagnetic contribution to the current. This results in a non-commutativity of the long-wavelength ($q\rightarrow 0$) and thermodynamic ($L\rightarrow\infty$) limits. When the correct limits are taken, we find that the Kubo response computed with either open or periodic boundary conditions yields identical results that are consistent with the continuity equation contrary to recent claims. We also show that the long wavelength pathology of the current noted previously also plagues the Anderson impurity model interpretation of dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT). Coupled with our previous work\cite{mai20231} which showed that HK is the correct $d=\infty$ limit of the Hubbard model, we arrive at the conclusion that single-orbital HK=DMFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07522v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhao Ma, Jinchao Zhao, Edwin W. Huang, Dhruv Kush, Barry Bradlyn, Philip W. Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fusion of Low-Entanglement Excitations in 2D Toric Code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07544v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: On top of a $D$-dimensional gapped bulk state, Low Entanglement Excitations (LEE) on $d$($&lt;D$)-dimensional sub-manifolds can have extensive energy but preserves the entanglement area law of the ground state. Due to their multi-dimensional nature, the LEEs embody a higher-category structure in quantum systems. They are the ground state of a modified Hamiltonian and hence capture the notions of `defects' of generalized symmetries. In previous works, we studied the low-entanglement excitations in a trivial phase as well as those in invertible phases. We find that LEEs in these phases have the same structure as lower-dimensional gapped phases and their defects within. In this paper, we study the LEEs inside non-invertible topological phases. We focus on the simple example of $\mathbb{Z}_2$ toric code and discuss how the fusion result of 1d LEEs with 0d morphisms can depend on both the choice of fusion circuit and the ordering of the fused defects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07544v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Yu Zhao, Xie Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incipient quantum spin Hall insulator under strong correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07557v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To assess prior mean-field studies that the interacting Kane-Mele model supports a novel antiferromagnetic Chern insulating phase (AFCI) for a wide range of sublattice potentials, we analyze the Kane-Mele-Hubbard model in the presence of a sublattice potential using determinant quantum Monte Carlo (DQMC). Instead of an AFCI, we find that the ground state is a quantum spin Hall (QSH) insulator for intermediate values of the sublattice potential $\lambda_v$, albeit with a small gap. The QSH state gives way to a trivial band insulator as the sublattice potential increases beyond a critical value. Only at small sublattice potentials does the QSH state transition into a trivial Mott insulator with xy antiferromagnetic correlations. The QAH feature is only observed at high temperature. The QAH feature crosses over to an incipient QSH state when the topological gap stabilizes. Our work is consistent with the experimental observation that in twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$ and WSe$_2$ as well as AB stacked MoTe$_2$/WSe$_2$, where QSH is consistently observed at even-integer filling over a wide range of parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07557v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peizhi Mai, Jinchao Zhao, Philip W. Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital inversion and emergent lattice dynamics in infinite layer CaCoO$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The layered cobaltate CaCoO$_2$ exhibits a unique herringbone-like structure. Serving as a potential prototype for a new class of complex lattice patterns, we study the properties of CaCoO$_2$ using X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) and resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS). Our results reveal a significant inter-plane hybridization between the Ca $4s-$ and Co $3d-$orbitals, leading to an inversion of the textbook orbital occupation of a square planar geometry. Further, our RIXS data reveal a strong low energy mode, with anomalous intensity modulations as a function of momentum transfer close to a quasi-static response suggestive of electronic and/or orbital ordering. These findings indicate that the newly discovered herringbone structure exhibited in CaCoO$_2$ may serve as a promising laboratory for the design of materials having strong electronic, orbital and lattice correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07705v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Jost, Eder G. Lomeli, Woo Jin Kim, Emily M. Been, Matteo Rossi, Stefano Agrestini, Kejin Zhou, Chunjing Jia, Brian Moritz, Zhi-Xun Shen, Harold Y. Hwang, Thomas P. Devereaux, Wei-Sheng Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Braided Ising spin-tube physics in a purported kagome magnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The magnetic insulator Nd$_3$BWO$_9$ has been proposed as a proximate spin-liquid candidate, realizing the highly frustrated breathing kagome lattice. We report a combination of single-crystal neutron scattering studies and numerical simulations, showing that it is the inter-plane couplings that determine the physics. To explain the exotic magnetism, we derive a simple one-dimensional Ising model composed of twisted triangular spin-tubes, i.e., triple braids of Ising spin chains with almost-orthogonal anisotropy frames and competing ferro-antiferromagnetic interactions. This model can account for the ground state, excitations, the numerous field-induced fractional magnetization plateau phases and incommensurate magnetic correlations at elevated temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07807v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Nagl, D. Flavi\'an, B. Duncan, S. Hayashida, O. Zaharko, E. Ressouche, J. Ollivier, Z. Yan, S. Gvasaliya, A. Zheludev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the 5$f$ electron hybridization process in UPd$_2$Al$_3$ via ARPES and Time-resolved PES</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the 5$f$-electron-conduction electron hybridization process in the heavy fermion superconductor UPd$_2$Al$_3$ using a combination of angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and time-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (tr-PES). ARPES measurements reveal the formation of a hybridization gap at a temperature of approximately 75 K, which becomes more pronounced as the temperature decreases. Notably, the persistence of a flat U 5$f$ band at temperatures well above the hybridization onset challenges conventional understanding. Our findings demonstrate a non-monotonic temperature dependence of the quasiparticle relaxation time, with an anomalous decrease at 20 K, suggesting complex electronic and magnetic interactions. These findings provide detailed insights into the 5$f$-electron hybridization process in UPd$_2$Al$_3$, with significant implications for the understanding of heavy fermion superconductivity and the role of 5$f$-electron hybridization in uranium-based materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07816v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiao-Jiao Song, Qi-Yi Wu, Chen Zhang, Steve M. Gilbertson, Peter S. Riseborough, Jan Rusz, John J. Joyce, Kevin S. Graham, Clifford G. Olson, Paul H. Tobash, Eric D. Bauer, Bo Chen, Hao Liu, Yu-Xia Duan, Peter M. Oppeneer, George Rodriguez, Tomasz Durakiewicz, Jian-Qiao Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional two-dimensional quantum oscillations in three-dimensional thick SrRuO$_3$ films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07835v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: SrRuO$_3$ is a prototypical transition metal oxide which hosts rich physical properties including itinerant ferromagnetism, high conductivity, and intrinsic Hall effect originating in the Weyl points. Recently, high-quality SrRuO$_3$ films with residual resistivity ratios of more than 50 have been reported to exhibit quantum oscillations at low temperatures in spite of its strong electron correlation. While the origin of the oscillations has been discussed in relation to Weyl orbits based on the Weyl semimetal band structure, so far experimentally reported results are neither consistent with each other nor with theoretically expected behavior, leaving the origin of the oscillations in SrRuO$_3$ films still elusive. In this report, we have carefully evaluated the quantum oscillations observed in three-dimensional thick SrRuO$_3$ films with a high residual resistivity ratio of RRR = 82. We reveal the coexistence of two oscillation components both derived from two-dimensional electronic states and with slightly different masses, suggesting the involvement of the surface Fermi arc states formed between different Weyl point pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07835v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0230365</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Physics Letters 125, 113105 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuta Matsuki, Shinichi Nishihaya, Markus Kriener, Ren Oshima, Fumiya Miwa, Masaki Uchida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for field induced quantum spin liquid behavior in a spin-1/2 honeycomb magnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the most important issues in modern condensed matter physics is the realization of fractionalized excitations, such as the Majorana excitations in the Kitaev quantum spin liquid. To this aim, the 3d-based Kitaev material Na2Co2TeO6 is a promising candidate whose magnetic phase diagram of B // a* contains a field-induced intermediate magnetically disordered phase within 7.5 T &lt; |B| &lt; 10 T. The experimental observations, including the restoration of the crystalline point group symmetry in the angle-dependent torque and the coexisting magnon excitations and spinon-continuum in the inelastic neutron scattering spectrum, provide strong evidence that this disordered phase is a field induced quantum spin liquid with partially polarized spins. Our variational Monte Carlo simulation with the effective K-J1-{\Gamma}-{\Gamma}'-J3 model reproduces the experimental data and further supports this conclusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07959v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaoting Lin, Mingfang Shu, Qirong Zhao, Gang Li, Yinina Ma, Jinlong Jiao, Yuting Li, Guijing Duan, Qing Huang, Jieming Sheng, Alexander I. Kolesnikov, Lu Li, Liusuo Wu, Hongwei Chen, Rong Yu, Xiaoqun Wang, Zhengxin Liu, Haidong Zhou, Jie Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear charge and thermal transport properties induced by orbital magnetic moment in chiral crystal cobalt monosilicide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08040v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The existence of exotic singularities in momentum space, such as spin-1 excitations and Rarita-Schwinger-Weyl (RSW) fermions, has been discussed so far to explore unique phenomena in the nonmagnetic B20-type compounds. Meanwhile, the Nonlinear Thermo-Electric (NCTE) charge and thermal Hall effect, a response proportional to the cross product of the electric field and temperature gradient, is expected in this chiral material, yet remains unexplored in B20-type compounds. Here, based on $ab \ initio$ calculations and symmetry analysis, we quantitatively analyze the NCTE charge and thermal Hall effects in cobalt monosilicide, obtaining experimentally measurable values of NCTE charge and thermal Hall current along [111] direction, which is not expected for second-order current responses to the DC electric field. Furthermore, we demonstrate that these significant responses are enhanced around RSW fermions and spin-1 excitations. Additionally, we clarify that the NCTE Hall effect is solely governed by orbital magnetic moments due to the cancellation of Berry curvature contributions in cubic chiral crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08040v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Nakazawa, Terufumi Yamaguchi, Ai Yamakage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistent quantum vibronic dynamics in a $5d^1$ double perovskite oxide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08095v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement between the spin, orbital and lattice degrees of freedom in condensed matter systems can emerge due to an interplay between spin-orbit and vibronic interactions. Heavy transition metal ions decorated on a face-centered cubic lattice, for example in $5d^1$ double perovskites, are particularly suited to support these quantum entangled states, but direct evidence has not yet been presented. In this work, we report additional peaks in the low-energy spectra of a $5d^1$ double perovskite, Ba$_2$CaReO$_6$, which cannot be explained by adopting a purely classical description of lattice vibrations. Instead, our theoretical analysis demonstrates that these spectroscopic signatures are characteristic of orbital-lattice entangled states in Ba$_2$CaReO$_6$. Crucially, both theory and experiment demonstrate that these quantum-entangled states persist to low temperatures, despite the onset of multipolar order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08095v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoya Iwahara, Jian-Rui Soh, Daigorou Hirai, Ivica \v{Z}ivkovi\'c, Yuan Wei, Wenliang Zhang, Carlos Galdino, Tianlun Yu, Kenji Ishii, Federico Pisani, Oleg Malanyuk, Thorsten Schmitt, Henrik M R{\o}nnow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unexpected changes in the band structure within AFM1 state of CeBi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements in conjunction with density functional theory (DFT) calculations to investigate the evolution of the electronic structure of CeBi upon a series of antiferromagnetic (AFM) transitions. We find evidence for a new AFM transition in addition to two previously known from transport studies. We demonstrate the development of an additional Dirac state in the (+-+-) ordered phase and a transformation of unconventional surface-state pairs in the (++--) ordered phase. This revises the phase diagram of this intriguing material, where there are now three distinct AFM states below TN in zero magnetic field instead of two as it was previously thought.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08125v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yevhen Kushnirenko, Brinda Kuthanazhi, Benjamin Schrunk, Evan O'Leary, Andrew Eaton, Robert-Jan Slager, Junyeong Ahn, Lin-Lin Wang, Paul C. Canfield, Adam Kaminski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inter-Layer Correlation of Loop Current Charge Density Wave on the Bilayer Kagom\'e Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08139v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Loop current order has been suggested as a promising candidate for the spontaneous time-reversal symmetry breaking $2a_0 \times 2a_0$ charge density wave (CDW) revealed in vanadium-based kagom\'e metals \avs\ ($A$ = K, Rb, Cs) near van Hove filling $n_\text{vH} = 5/12$. Weak-coupling analyses and mean field calculations have demonstrated that nearest-neighbor Coulomb repulsion $V_1$ and next-nearest-neighbor Coulomb repulsion $V_2$ drives, respectively, real and imaginary bond-ordered CDW, with the latter corresponding to time-reversal symmetry breaking loop current CDW. It is important to understand the inter-layer correlation of these bond-ordered CDWs and its consequences in the bulk kagom\'e materials. To provide physical insights, we investigate in this paper the $c$-axis stacking of them, loop current CDW in particular, on the minimal bilayer kagom\'e lattice. The bare susceptibilities for stacking of real and imaginary bond orders are calculated for the free electrons on the bilayer kagom\'e lattice with inter-layer coupling $t_\perp=0.2t$, which splits the van Hove filling to $n_{+\text{vH}}=4.64/12$ and $n_{-\text{vH}}=5.44/12$. While real and imaginary bond-ordered CDWs are still favored, respectively, by $V_1$ and $V_2$, their inter-layer coupling is sensitive to band filling $n$. They tend to stack symmetrically near $n_{\pm\text{vH}}$ with identical bond orders in the two layers and give rise to a $2a_0 \times 2a_0 \times 1c_0$ CDW. On the other hand, they prefer to stack antisymmetrically around $n_\text{vH}$ with opposite bond orders in the two layers and lead to a $2a_0 \times 2a_0 \times 2c_0$ CDW. The concrete bilayer $t$-$t_\perp$-$V_1$-V$_2$ model is then studied. We obtain the mean-field ground states and determine the inter-layer coupling as a function of band filling at various interactions. The nontrivial topological properties of loop current CDWs are studied ...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08139v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Wei Dong, Yu-Han Lin, Ruiqing Fu, Gang Su, Ziqiang Wang, Sen Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency-selective amplification of nonlinear response in strongly correlated bosons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a protocol to generate enhanced non-linear responses of incident pulses in the density wave phase within the extended Bose-Hubbard model using the concept of resonance-induced amplification (RIA). This method enables the selection of an incident pulse frequency to amplify the desired harmonic order. We characterize the enhancement of the non-linear harmonic spectra under various frequencies and field strengths of the incident pulses, and demonstrate that an optimal field strength is necessary to realize our protocol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08168v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Prakash, Debamalya Dutta, Arko Roy, Kush Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Bose-Einstein Singularities in Correlated Electron Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hidden singularities in correlated electron systems, which are caused by pair fluctuations of electron-electron or electron-hole bubbles obeying Bose-Einstein statistics, are unveiled theoretically. The correlation function of each pair fluctuation is shown to have a bound in the zero Matsubara frequency branch, similarly as the chemical potential of ideal Bose gases. Once the bound is reached, the self-energy starts to acquire a component proportional to Green's function itself, i.e., the structure called one-particle reducible, to keep the correlation function within the bound. The singularities are closely related with, but distinct from, phase transitions with broken symmetries. Passing down through them necessarily accompanies a change in the single-particle density of states around the excitation threshold, such as the pseudo-gap behavior found here for the negative-$U$ Hubbard model above the superconducting transition temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07660v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takafumi Kita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Riemannian Approach to the Lindbladian Dynamics of a Locally Purified Tensor Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tensor networks offer a valuable framework for implementing Lindbladian dynamics in many-body open quantum systems with nearest-neighbor couplings. In particular, a tensor network ansatz known as the Locally Purified Density Operator employs the local purification of the density matrix to guarantee the positivity of the state at all times. Within this framework, the dissipative evolution utilizes the Trotter-Suzuki splitting, yielding a second-order approximation error. However, due to the Lindbladian dynamics' nature, employing higher-order schemes results in non-physical quantum channels. In this work, we leverage the gauge freedom inherent in the Kraus representation of quantum channels to improve the splitting error. To this end, we formulate an optimization problem on the Riemannian manifold of isometries and find a solution via the second-order trust-region algorithm. We validate our approach using two nearest-neighbor noise models and achieve an improvement of orders of magnitude compared to other positivity-preserving schemes. In addition, we demonstrate the usefulness of our method as a compression scheme, helping to control the exponential growth of computational resources, which thus far has limited the use of the locally purified ansatz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08127v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emiliano Godinez-Ramirez, Richard Milbradt, Christian B. Mendl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on explicit construction of conformal generators on the fuzzy sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08257v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The lowest Landau level on the sphere was recently proposed as a continuum regularization of the three-dimensional conformal field theories, the so-called fuzzy sphere regularization. In this note, we propose an explicit construction of the conformal generators on the fuzzy sphere in terms of the microscopic Hamiltonian. Specifically, we construct the generators for the translation and special conformal transformation, which are used in defining the conformal primary states and thus are of special interest. We apply our method to a concrete example, the fuzzy sphere regularized three-dimensional Ising conformal field theory. We show that it can help capture all primaries with spin $\ell &lt; 4$ and scaling dimension $\Delta &lt; 7$. In particular, our method can clearly separate the primary from other states that differ in scaling dimension by $1\%$, making it hard otherwise based solely on using the conformal tower associated with the primaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08257v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruihua Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent dynamics of scale-free interactions in fractional quantum Hall fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06361v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that even in the limit of large cyclotron gap, Landau level (LL) mixing can be dominant with scale-free interaction between charged ``elementary particles" in a fractional quantum Hall system, as long as the filling factor exceeds certain critical values. The corresponding Hamiltonians with scale-free interaction can serve as exact model Hamiltonians for certain composite Fermion or parton states (unlike the well-known TK Hamiltonians where the number of LLs needs to be fixed by hand), and they are natural physical Hamiltonians for 2D systems embedded in higher-dimensional space-time. Even with LL mixing the null spaces of such Hamiltonians (spanned by the ground state and the quasiholes) can be analytically obtained, and we show these are the generalisation of the conformal Hilbert spaces (CHS) to more than one LLs. The effective interaction between the anyons for these topological phases emerges from the kinetic energy of the ``elementary particles", leading to an interesting duality between strongly and weakly interacting systems that can be easily understood via the tuning of parameters in the scale-free interaction. We also propose a novel experimental platform for approximately realising such model Hamiltonians with trion like particles, that can potentially lead to very robust (non-Abelian) FQH phases from two-body Coulomb-based interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06361v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B (Letter) 110, L121108 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Fractional Quantum Anomalous Hall Smectics to Polar Smectic Metals: Nontrivial Interplay Between Electronic Liquid Crystal Order and Topological Order in Correlated Topological Flat Bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00363v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symmetry-breaking orders can not only compete with each other, but also be interwined, and the interwined topological and symmetry-breaking orders make the situation more intriguing. This work examines the archetypal correlated flat band model on a checkerboard lattice at filling $\nu=2/3$ and we find the unique interplay between smectic charge order and topological order gives rise to two novel quantum states. As the interaction strength increases, the system first transitions from a Fermi liquid into FQAH smectic (FQAHS) state, where FQAH topological order coexists cooperatively with smectic charge order with enlarged ground-state degeneracy and interestingly, the Hall conductivity is $\sigma_{xy}=\nu=2/3$, different from the band-folding or doping scenarios. Further increasing the interaction strength, the system undergoes another quantum phase transition and evolves into a polar smectic metal (PSM) state. This emergent PSM is an anisotropic non-Fermi liquid, whose interstripe tunneling is irrelevant while it is metallic inside each stripe. Different from the FQAHS and conventional smectic orders, this PSM spontaneously breaks the two-fold rotational symmetry, resulting in a nonzero electric dipole moment and ferroelectric order. In addition to the exotic ground states, large-scale numerical simulations are also used to study low-energy excitations and thermodynamic characteristics. We find the onset temperature of the incompressible FQAHS state, which also coincides with the onset of non-polar smectic order, is dictated by the magneto-roton modes. Above this onset temperature, the PSM state exists at intermediate-temperature regime. Although the T = 0 quantum phase transition between PSM and FQAHS is first order, the thermal FQAHS-PSM transition could be continuous. We expect the features of the exotic states and thermal phase transitions could be accessed in future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00363v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6633/ad7640</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rep. Prog. Phys. 87 (2024) 108003</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hongyu Lu, Han-Qing Wu, Bin-Bin Chen, Kai Sun, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local magnetic moment formation and Kondo screening in the presence of Hund exchange: the two-band Hubbard model analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20036v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study formation and screening of local magnetic moments in the two-band Hubbard model in the presence of Hund exchange interaction using dynamic mean field theory approach. The characteristic temperatures of the formation, beginning and full screening of local magnetic moments are obtained from the analysis of temperature dependencies of the orbital, charge, and spin susceptibilities, as well as the respective instantaneous correlation functions. At half filling we find the phase diagram, which is similar to the single-orbital case with wide region of formation of local magnetic moments below the orbital Kondo temperature. Similarly to the single-orbital case, with decreasing temperature the screening of local magnetic moments is preceded by appearance of fermionic quasiparticles. In the two-band case the quasiparticles are however present also in some temperature region above the Mott insulating phase. At finite doping we find broad regime of presence of local magnetic moments, which coexist with incoherently or coherently moving holes. We also find, similarly to the half filled case, finite temperature interval in the doped regime, when the fermionic quasiparticles are formed, but do not yet screen local magnetic moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20036v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.075160</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 075160 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>T. B. Mazitov, A. A. Katanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation induced piezomagnetism in local moment altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01893v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It was recently discovered that, depending on their symmetries, collinear antiferromagnets may break spin degeneracy in momentum space, even in absence of spin-orbit coupling. Such systems, dubbed altermagnets, have electronic bands with a spin-momentum texture set mainly by the combined crystal-magnetic symmetry. This discovery motivates the question which novel physical properties derive from altermagnetic order. Here we show that one consequence of altermagnetic order is a fluctuation-driven piezomagnetic response. Using two Heisenberg models of d-wave altermagnets, a checkerboard one and one for rutiles, we determine the fluctuation induced piezomagnetic coefficients considering temperature induced transversal spin fluctuations. We establish in addition that magnetic fluctuations induce an anisotropic thermal spin conductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01893v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kostiantyn V. Yershov, Volodymyr P. Kravchuk, Maria Daghofer, Jeroen van den Brink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferromagnetic and spin spiral correlations in the doped two-dimensional Hubbard model: gauge symmetry, Ward identities, and dynamical mean-field theory analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04277v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We reconsider the derivation of Ward identities for spin stiffnesses, which determine the non-linear sigma model of magnetic degrees of freedom of interacting electrons in the presence of antiferromagnetic or incommensurate correlations. We emphasize that in the approaches, which do not break explicitly spin symmetry of the action, the spatial components of gauge kernel, which is used to obtain spin stiffnesses, remain gauge invariant even in case of spontaneous spin symmetry breaking. We derive the corrected Ward identities, which account for this gauge invariance. We emphasize that the frequency dependence of temporal spin stiffnesses is not fixed by the obtained identities, and show that the infinitesimally small external staggered field is crucially important to obtain finite static uniform transverse susceptibility. On the other hand, we find that the spatial spin stiffnesses are determined by the gauge kernel of the Legendre transformed theory, which is in general {\it different} from the gauge kernel of the original theory and obtain an explicit expressions for spatial spin stiffnesses through susceptibilities and current correlation functions. We verify numerically the obtained results within dynamic mean field theory, and obtain doping dependencies of the resulting spin stiffnesses for antiferromagnetic and incommensurate phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04277v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.085153</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 085153 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>I. A. Goremykin, A. A. Katanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractionalization of Coset Non-Invertible Symmetry and Exotic Hall Conductance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20401v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate fractionalization of non-invertible symmetry in (2+1)D topological orders. We focus on coset non-invertible symmetries obtained by gauging non-normal subgroups of invertible $0$-form symmetries. These symmetries can arise as global symmetries in quantum spin liquids, given by the quotient of the projective symmetry group by a non-normal subgroup as invariant gauge group. We point out that such coset non-invertible symmetries in topological orders can exhibit symmetry fractionalization: each anyon can carry a "fractional charge" under the coset non-invertible symmetry given by a gauge invariant superposition of fractional quantum numbers. We present various examples using field theories and quantum double lattice models, such as fractional quantum Hall systems with charge conjugation symmetry gauged and finite group gauge theory from gauging a non-normal subgroup. They include symmetry enriched $S_3$ and $O(2)$ gauge theories. We show that such systems have a fractionalized continuous non-invertible coset symmetry and a well-defined electric Hall conductance. The coset symmetry enforces a gapless edge state if the boundary preserves the continuous non-invertible symmetry. We propose a general approach for constructing coset symmetry defects using a "sandwich" construction: non-invertible symmetry defects can generally be constructed from an invertible defect sandwiched by condensation defects. The anomaly free condition for finite coset symmetry is also identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20401v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Po-Shen Hsin, Ryohei Kobayashi, Carolyn Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical properties of metallic and deconfined quantum critical points in Dirac systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17042v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use large-scale fermion quantum Monte Carlo simulations to study metallic and deconfined quantum phase transitions in a bilayer honeycomb model, focusing on their quantum critical and finite-temperature properties. At weak interaction, a fully symmetric Dirac semimetal state is realized. At intermediate and strong interaction, respectively, two long-range-ordered phases that break different symmetries are stabilized. The ordered phases feature partial and full, respectively, gap openings in the fermion spectrum. We clarify the symmetries of the different zero-temperature phases and the symmetry breaking patterns across the two quantum phase transitions between them. The first transition between the disordered and long-range-ordered semimetallic phases has previously been argued to be described by the $(2+1)$-dimensional Gross-Neveu-SO(3) field theory. By performing simulations with an improved symmetric Trotter decomposition, we further substantiate this claim by computing the critical exponents $1/\nu$, $\eta_\phi$, and $\eta_\psi$, which turn out to be consistent with the field-theoretical expectation within numerical and analytical uncertainties. The second transition between the two long-range-ordered phases has previously been proposed as a possible instance of a metallic deconfined quantum critical point. We further develop this scenario by analyzing the spectral functions in the single-particle, particle-hole, and particle-particle channels. Our results indicate gapless excitations with a unique velocity, supporting the emergence of Lorentz symmetry at criticality. We also determine the finite-temperature phase boundaries above the fully gapped state at large interaction, which smoothly vanish near the putative metallic deconfined quantum critical point, consistent with a continuous or weakly first-order transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17042v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.125123</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PhysRevB.110.125123(2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zi Hong Liu, Matthias Vojta, Fakher F. Assaad, Lukas Janssen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-metric-induced quantum Hall conductance inversion and reentrant transition in fractional Chern insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07894v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quantum metric of single-particle wave functions in topological flatbands plays a crucial role in determining the stability of fractional Chern insulating (FCI) states. Here, we unravel that the quantum metric causes the many-body Chern number of the FCI states to deviate sharply from the expected value associated with partial filling of the single-particle topological flatband. Furthermore, the variation of the quantum metric in momentum space induces band dispersion through interactions, affecting the stability of the FCI states. This causes a reentrant transition into the Fermi liquid from the FCI phase as the interaction strength increases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07894v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.L032063</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, L032063 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ang-Kun Wu, Siddhartha Sarkar, Xiaohan Wan, Kai Sun, Shi-Zeng Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of hidden octupolar order from nonlinear Hall effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03435v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Detecting symmetry-breaking hidden orders with conventional probes has been a long-standing challenge in the field of magnetism. Higher-rank multipolar ordering $-$ anisotropic charge and magnetization distributions arising from a combination of spin-orbit coupling and crystalline environments $-$ is a quintessential example of such hidden orders, where new protocols of direct detection remain highly desirable. In this work, we propose non-linear Hall effects as a novel probe for multipolar ordering in metallic systems. Taking inspiration from the family of Pr-based heavy-fermion compounds, Pr(Ti,V)$_2$Al$_{20}$, we formulate a minimal cubic-lattice model of conduction electrons coupled to a ferro-octupolar order parameter. The time-reversal-breaking order leads to a band structure that supports strong quadrupolar moments of the Berry curvature (BC). Using a semi-classical Boltzmann formalism in conjunction with a symmetry analysis, we demonstrate that the BC quadrupoles produce a third harmonic generation of the Hall voltage $[V_H(3 \omega)]$ measurable in an AC Hall experiment. Properties of the Hall response such as its anisotropy, its dissipationlessness, and its dependence on the order parameter are also examined. Our work encourages a new realm of investigation of multipolar ordering from non-linear transport experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03435v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.125127</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 125127 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sopheak Sorn, Adarsh S. Patri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signature of anyonic statistics in the integer quantum Hall regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06069v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Anyons are exotic low-dimensional quasiparticles whose unconventional quantum statistics extends the binary particle division into fermions and bosons. The fractional quantum Hall regime provides a natural host, with first convincing anyon signatures recently observed through interferometry and cross-correlations of colliding beams. However, the fractional regime is rife with experimental complications, such as an anomalous tunneling density of states, which impede the manipulation of anyons. Here we show experimentally that the canonical integer quantum Hall regime can provide a robust anyon platform. Exploiting the Coulomb interaction between two co-propagating quantum Hall channels, an electron injected into one channel splits into two fractional charges behaving as abelian anyons. Their unconventional statistics is revealed by negative cross-correlations between dilute quasiparticle beams. Similarly to fractional quantum Hall observations, we show that the negative signal stems from a time-domain braiding process, here involving the incident fractional quasiparticles and spontaneously generated electron-hole pairs. Beyond the dilute limit, a theoretical understanding is achieved via the edge magnetoplasmon description of interacting integer quantum Hall channels. Our findings establish that, counter-intuitively, the integer quantum Hall regime provides a platform of choice for exploring and manipulating quasiparticles with fractional quantum statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06069v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-50820-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Commun. 15, 6578 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>P. Glidic, I. Petkovic, C. Piquard, A. Aassime, A. Cavanna, Y. Jin, U. Gennser, C. Mora, D. Kovrizhin, A. Anthore, F. Pierre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifractality and Hyperuniformity in Quasicrystalline Bose-Hubbard Models with and without Disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05155v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Clarifying similarities and differences in physical properties between crystalline and quasicrystalline systems is one of central issues in studying quasicrystals. To contribute to this, we apply multifractal and hyperuniform analyses to nonuniform spatial patterns in the Bose-Hubbard model on the Penrose and Ammann-Beenker tilings. Based on the mean-field approximation, we obtain real-space distributions of local superfluid amplitude and bosonic condensate. In both Mott insulating and superfluid phases, the distributions are hyperuniform. Analyzing the order metric that quantifies the complexity of nonuniform spatial patterns, we find that both quasicrystals show a significant increase of the order metric at a phase boundary between the Mott insulating and superfluid phases, in stark contrast to the case of a periodic square lattice. Our results suggest that hyperuniformity is a useful concept to differentiate between crystalline and quasicrystalline bosonic systems. The order metric clarifies if the distribution of a physical quantity reflects the point distribution or not, and quantifies how complex the distribution is in comparison with the point distribution. Moreover, we introduce on-site random potentials into these quasicrystalline Bose-Hubbard models, leading to a Bose glass phase. Contrary to the Mott insulating and superfluid phases, we find that the Bose glass phase is multifractal. The same multifractality appears on a Bose glass phase in the periodic square lattice. Therefore, multifractality is common in a Bose glass phase irrespective of the periodicity of systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05155v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Hori, Takanori Sugimoto, Yoichiro Hashizume, Takami Tohyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Unitary Quantum Many-Body Dynamics using the Faber Polynomial Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10135v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Efficient numerical methods are still lacking to probe the unconventional dynamics of quantum many-body systems under non-unitary evolution. In this work, we use Faber polynomials to numerically simulate both the dynamics of non-Hermitian systems and the quantum jumps unravelling of the Lindblad dynamics. We apply the method to the non-interacting and interacting Hatano-Nelson models evolving from two different setups: i) a N\'eel state, and ii) a domain wall. In the first case, we study how interactions preserve the initial magnetic order against the skin effect. In the second example, we present numerical evidence of the existence of an effective hydrodynamic description for the domain-wall melting problem in the non-interacting limit. Additionally, we investigate both the conditional and unconditional dynamics of the quantum jump unravelling in two quantum spin chains, which exhibit either the non-Hermitian or the Liouvillian skin effect. This numerical method inherently generalises the well-established method based on Chebyshev polynomials to accommodate non-Hermitian scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10135v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael D. Soares, Marco Schir\`o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiperiodicity protects quantized transport in disordered systems without gaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07049v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The robustness of topological properties, such as quantized currents, generally depends on the existence of gaps surrounding the relevant energy levels or on symmetry-forbidden transitions. Here, we observe quantized currents that survive the addition of bounded local disorder beyond the closing of the relevant instantaneous energy gaps in a driven Aubry-Andr\'e-Harper chain, a prototypical model of quasiperiodic systems. We explain the robustness using a local picture in \textit{configuration-space} based on Landau-Zener transitions, which rests on the Anderson localisation of the eigenstates. Moreover, we propose a protocol, directly realizable in for instance cold atoms or photonic experiments, which leverages this stability to prepare topological many-body states with high Chern numbers and opens new experimental avenues for the study of both the integer and fractional quantum Hall effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07049v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emmanuel Gottlob, Dan S. Borgnia, Robert-Jan Slager, Ulrich Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Krylov complexity and chaos in deformed SYK models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09604v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Krylov complexity has recently been proposed as a quantum probe of chaos. The Krylov exponent characterising the exponential growth of Krylov complexity is conjectured to upper-bound the Lyapunov exponent. We compute the Krylov and the Lyapunov exponents in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model and in some of its deformations. We do this analysis both at infinite and finite temperatures, in models where the number of fermionic interactions is both finite and infinite. We consider deformations that interpolate between two regions of near-maximal chaos and deformations that become nearly-integrable at low temperatures. In all cases, we find that the Krylov exponent upper-bounds the Lyapunov one. However, we find that while the Lyapunov exponent can have non-monotonic behaviour as a function of temperature, in all studied examples the Krylov exponent behaves monotonically. For instance, we find models where the Lyapunov exponent goes to zero at low temperatures, while the Krylov exponent saturates to its maximal bound. We speculate on the possibility that this monotonicity might be a generic feature of the Krylov exponent in quantum systems evolving under unitary evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09604v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shira Chapman, Saskia Demulder, Dami\'an A. Galante, Sameer U. Sheorey, Osher Shoval</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Structure of the Majorana Clifford Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11319v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In quantum information science, Clifford operators and stabilizer codes play a central role for systems of qubits (or qudits). In this paper, we study the analogous objects for systems of Majorana fermions. A crucial role is played by fermion parity symmetry, which is an unbreakable symmetry present in any system in which the fundamental degrees of freedom are fermionic. We prove that the subgroup of parity-preserving fermionic Cliffords can be represented by the orthogonal group over the binary field $\mathbb{F}_2$, and we show how it can be generated by braiding operators and used to construct any (even-parity) Majorana stabilizer code. We also analyze the frame potential for this so-called p-Clifford group, proving that it is equivalent to the frame potential of the ordinary Clifford group acting on a fixed-parity sector of the Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11319v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Val\'erie Bettaque, Brian Swingle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nernst Plateau in the Quantum Limit of Topological Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07199v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nernst effect, a transverse electric current induced by a temperature gradient, is a promising tool for revealing emergent phases of condensed matter. We find a Nernst coefficient plateau in low carrier density topological insulators, as a signature of 1D Weyl points in the quantum limit of the weak topological insulator. The plateau height is inversely proportional to the impurity density, suggesting a way to engineer infinitely large Nernst effects. The Nernst plateau also exists in strong topological insulators, at the bottom of the lowest Landau band. We show that these plateaus have been overlooked in the previous experiments and we highlight the experimental conditions to observe them. Our results may inspire more investigations of employing anomalous Nernst effect to identify emergent phases of condensed matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07199v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng-Lu Zhao, J. L. Zhang, Hai-Zhou Lu, Qian Niu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
