<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of fragmentation for periodically driven fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the possible signatures of prethermal strong Hilbert space fragmentation (HSF) for one-dimensional (1D) fermions subjected to a periodic drive. We extend the results of Phys. Rev. Lett. 130, 120401 (2023) to show the possibility of such fragmentation for a large class of experimentally relevant drive protocols. Moreover, we demonstrate the persistence of HSF when the fermion chain is taken away from half-filling. Both these analysis indicate the robustness of the fragmentation phenomenon reported earlier. We also provide an alternate derivation of the Floquet Hamiltonian of the driven chain which yields insight into the generic nested commutator structure of its higher order terms. Finally, we study the density-density out-of-time-correlators (OTOC) of the driven chain both away and near the special drive frequencies at which its first order Floquet Hamiltonian exhibits fragmentation. We show that these OTOCs, for a chain with open boundary condition, exhibit a distinct periodic unscrambling of information at special drive frequencies; such unscrambling can therefore serve as a marker of prethermal HSF. We provide an approximate analytic explanation of the role of HSF behind such periodic unscrambling and discuss experiments which can detect signatures of strong HSF in such driven chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04328v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Somsubhra Ghosh, Indranil Paul, K. Sengupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartite Fluctuations of Critical Fermi Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the scaling behaviors of bipartite fluctuations $\mathcal{F}$ of conserved quantities across a class of interaction-driven quantum phase transitions out of Landau fermi liquids, where other phases involve fermi-surface states of fractionalized degrees of freedom. Examples of such phases include (compressible) composite fermi liquids for spinless electrons and (incompressible) spin-liquid Mott insulators for spin-$1/2$ electrons. The two sides of the critical points are typically distinguished by distinct leading-order scalings of bipartite charge fluctuations, $\mathcal{F}\sim L\log (L)$ in Landau fermi liquids, and $\mathcal{F}\sim L$ in the other phases, where $L$ is the linear size of the subsystem under bipartition. In the case of composite fermi liquids (with continuous translational and rotational invariance), we also identify a universal constant term $-\mathtt{F}(\theta)\sigma_{xy}/\pi$ arising when the subsystem geometry incorporates a sharp corner. Here, $\mathtt{F}(\theta)$ represents a function of the corner angle, and $\sigma_{xy}$ denotes the Hall conductivity. At the critical point of each example, we find that the leading-order scaling $\mathcal{F}\sim L$ is accompanied by a subleading universal corner contribution $-\mathtt{F}(\theta)C_{\rho}\log(L)$ with the same angle dependence $\mathtt{F}(\theta)$. The universal coefficient $C_{\rho}$ is linked to the predicted universal longitudinal (and Hall) resistivity jump $\Delta\rho_{xx}$ (and $\Delta\rho_{xy}$) at the critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04331v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Chuan Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder operators in 2D Fermi and non-Fermi liquids through multidimensional bosonization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04334v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Disorder operators are a type of non-local observables for quantum many-body systems, measuring the fluctuations of symmetry charges inside a region. It has been shown that disorder operators can reveal global aspects of many-body states that are otherwise difficult to access through local measurements. We study disorder operator for U(1) (charge or spin) symmetry in 2D Fermi and non-Fermi liquid states, using the multidimensional bosonization formalism. For a region $A$, the logarithm of the charge disorder parameter in a Fermi liquid with isotropic interactions scales asympototically as $l_A\ln l_A$, with $l_A$ being the linear size of the region $A$. We calculate the proportionality coefficient in terms of Landau parameters of the Fermi liquid theory. We then study models of Fermi surface coupled to gapless bosonic fields realizing non-Fermi liquid states. In a simple spinless model, where the fermion density is coupled to a critical scalar, we find that at the quantum critical point, the scaling behavior of the charge disorder operators is drastically modified to $l_A \ln^2 l_A$. We also consider the composite Fermi liquid state and argue that the charge disorder operator scales as $l_A$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04334v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang-Le Cai, Meng Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-dependent Magnons in a Honeycomb Antiferromagnet CoTiO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report field-dependent high-resolution inelastic neutron scattering (INS) measurements on the honeycomb lattice magnet, CoTiO$_3$, to study the evolution of its magnon excitations across a spin reorientation transition driven by an in-plane magnetic field. By carrying out elastic neutron scattering in a magnetic field, we show that the sample transitions from a collinear antiferromagnetic state with multiple magnetic domains at a low field to a mono-domain state with a canted magnetic structure at a high field. Concurrent with this transition, we observed significant changes in both the energy and the width of the zone center magnon peak. The observed width change is argued to be consistent with an unusual zero-field state with extended domain walls. On the other hand, the magnon spectra near the $\mathbf{K}$ point of the Brillouin zone boundary are found to be largely insensitive to the changes in the ordered moment directions and the domain configuration. We argue that this observation is difficult to explain within the framework of the bond-dependent model proposed in a recent INS study [Elliot \textit{et\,al}, Nat. Commun., \textbf{12}, 3936 (2021)]. Our study therefore calls for alternative explanations for the observed $\mathbf{K}$-point gap in CoTiO$_3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04390v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Yuan, Ezekiel Horsley, M. B. Stone, Nicholas P. Butch, Guangyong Xu, Guo-Jiun Shu, J. P. Clancy, Young-June Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-charge-lattice coupling across the charge density wave transition in a Kagome lattice antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding spin and lattice excitations in a metallic magnetic ordered system form the basis to unveil the magnetic and lattice exchange couplings and their interactions with itinerant electrons. Kagome lattice antiferromagnet FeGe is interesting because it displays rare charge density wave (CDW) deep inside the antiferromagnetic ordered phase that interacts with the magnetic order. We use neutron scattering to study the evolution of spin and lattice excitations across the CDW transition $T_{\rm CDW}$ in FeGe. While spin excitations below $\sim$100 meV can be well described by spin waves of a spin-1 Heisenberg Hamiltonian, spin excitations at higher energies are centered around the Brillouin zone boundary and extend up to $\sim180$ meV consistent with quasiparticle excitations across spin-polarized electron-hole Fermi surfaces. Furthermore, $c$-axis spin wave dispersion and Fe-Ge optical phonon modes show a clear hardening below $T_{\rm CDW}$ due to spin-charge-lattice coupling but with no evidence for a phonon Kohn anomaly. By comparing our experimental results with density functional theory calculations in absolute units, we conclude that FeGe is a Hund's metal in the intermediate correlated regime where magnetism has contributions from both itinerant and localized electrons arising from spin polarized electronic bands near the Fermi level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04459v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaokun Teng, David W. Tam, Lebing Chen, Hengxin Tan, Yaofeng Xie, Bin Gao, Garrett E. Granroth, Alexandre Ivanov, Philippe Bourges, Binghai Yan, Ming Yi, Pengcheng Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Site-selective insulating phase in twisted bilayer Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paramagnetic phase diagrams of the half-filled Hubbard model on a twisted bilayer square lattice are investigated using coherent potential approximation. Besides the conventional metallic, band insulating, and Mott insulating phases, we find two site-selective insulating phases where certain sites exhibit band insulating behaviors while the others display Mott insulating behaviors. These phases are identified by the band gap, the double occupancy, the density of states, as well as the imaginary part of self-energy. Furthermore, we examine the effect of on-site potential on the stability of the site-selective insulating phases. Our results indicate that fruitful site-selective phases can be engineered by twisting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04602v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.085104</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 085104 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiu-Cai Jiang, Ze Ruan, Yu-Zhong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective charge excitations studied by electron energy-loss spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamic charge susceptibility, $\chi(q,\omega)$, is a fundamental observable of all materials, in one, two, and three dimensions, quantifying the collective charge modes, the ability of a material to screen charge, as well as its electronic compressibility. Here, we review the current state of efforts to measure this quantity using inelastic electron scattering, which historically has been called electron energy-loss spectroscopy (EELS). We focus on comparison between transmission (T-EELS) and reflection (R-EELS) geometries as applied to a selection of 3D conductors. While a great deal is understood about simple metals, measurements of more strongly interacting and strange metals are currently contradictory, with different groups obtaining fundamentally conflicting results, emphasizing the importance of improved EELS measurements. Further, current opportunities for improvement in EELS techniques are vast, with the most promising future developments being in hemispherical and time-of-flight analyzers, as well as STEM instruments configured for high momentum resolution. We conclude that, despite more than half a century of work, EELS techniques are currently still in their infancy</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04670v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Abbamonte, J\"org Fink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information propagation in one-dimensional XY-$\Gamma$ chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The bond-dependent Kitaev model offers a playground in which one can search for quantum spin liquids. In these Kitaev materials, a symmetric off-diagonal $\Gamma$ term emerges, hosting a number of remarkable features, which has been particularly challenging to fully understand. One primary question that arises after recognizing a new phase is how information will spread in it. Out-of-time-ordered commutators and entanglement entropy describe processes whereby information about the initial condition of a unitarily evolving system propagates over the system. A possible way to investigate dynamics in such systems is by considering one-dimensional models. We investigate here the one-dimensional spin-1/2 XY model in a transverse field with a $\Gamma$ interaction with periodic boundary conditions imposed. We will show that the $\Gamma$ interaction constructs an asymmetric "light-cone" with different butterfly velocities. In addition, it leads to faster information propagation in the spiral phase and slower propagation in the ferromagnetic and paramagnetic phases. Interestingly, we observe a pronounced effect in the entanglement entropy, explicitly showing up as a two-stage linear growth in time as fast/slow then slow/fast for quenches originating from the spiral phase. We hope our work paves the way for studying more about the spreading of information in one-dimensional Kitaev materials, which can in turn help to discover unknown aspects of higher-dimensional models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04715v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.134303</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sasan Kheiri, Hadi Cheraghi, Saeed Mahdavifar, Nicholas Sedlmayr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite Grassmann time-evolving matrix product operator method for zero-temperature equilibrium quantum impurity problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04757v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Grassmann time-evolving matrix product operator (GTEMPO) method has proven to be an accurate and efficient numerical method for the real-time dynamics of quantum impurity problems. Whereas its application for imaginary-time calculations is much less competitive compared to well-established methods such as the continuous-time quantum Monte Carlo (CTQMC). In this work, we unleash the full power of GTEMPO for zero-temperature imaginary-time calculations: the multi-time impurity state is time-translationally invariant with infinite boundary condition, therefore it can be represented as an infinite Grassmann matrix product state (GMPS) with nontrivial unit cell in a single time step, instead of an open boundary GMPS spanning the whole imaginary-time axis. We devise a very efficient infinite GTEMPO algorithm targeted at zero-temperature equilibrium quantum impurity problems, which is known to be a hard regime for quantum Monte Carlo methods. To demonstrate the performance of our method, we benchmark it against exact solutions in the noninteracting limit, and against CTQMC calculations in the Anderson impurity models with up to two orbitals, where we show that the required bond dimension of the infinite GMPS is much smaller than its finite-temperature counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04757v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chu Guo, Ruofan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Improvement of the Hartree-Fock Approach to the 2D Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a refinement of the usual Hartree-Fock method applied the 2D Hubbard model, in Nambu spinor formulation. The new element is the addition of a ''condensate inducing'' term proportional to a variational parameter h to the Hartree-Fock Hamiltonian, which generates an s- or d-wave condensate. This modified Hartree-Fock Hamiltonian is used only to generate variational trial states; energy expectation values are computed in the full two-dimensional Hubbard Hamiltonian with no modification. It is found that there exist trial states with non-vanishing condensates that are significantly lower in energy than the standard Hartree-Fock ground states, in some range of the U/t-density plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04777v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazue Matsuyama, Jeff Greensite</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of collective spin excitation on electronic transport in topological spin texture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop an efficient real-time simulation method for the spin-charge coupled system in the velocity gauge. This method enables us to compute the real-time simulation for the two-dimensional system with the complex spin texture. We focus on the effect of the collective excitation of the localized spins on the electronic transport properties of the non-trivial topological state in real space. To investigate this effect, we calculate the linear optical conductivity by calculating the real-time evolution of the Kondo lattice model on the triangular lattice, which hosts an all-in/all-out magnetic structure. In the linear conductivity spectra, we observe multiple peaks below the bandgap regime, attributed to the resonant contributions of collective modes similar to the skyrmionic system, alongside broadband modifications resulting from off-resonant spin dynamics. The result shows that the collective excitation, similar to the skyrmionic system, influences the optical response of the electron systems based on symmetry analysis. We elucidate the interference between the contributions from the different spin excitations to the optical conductivity in the multiple spin texture, pointing out the mode-dependent electrical activity. We show the complex interplay between the complex spin texture and the itinerant electrons in the two-dimensional spin-charge coupled system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05204v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Hattori, Hikaru Watanabe, Junta Iguchi, Takuya Nomoto, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Floquet Chern insulator phases in the spin-charge coupled triangular-lattice ferrimagnet: Crucial roles of higher-order terms in the high-frequency expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the effects of photoirradiation with circularly polarized light on the Dirac half-metal state induced by the ferrimagnetic order in a triangular Kondo-lattice model. Our analysis based on the Floquet theory reveals that two types of Floquet Chern insulator phases appear as photoinduced nonequilibrium steady states and that these two phases can be experimentally detected and distinguished by measurements of the Hall conductivity. It is elucidated that these rich nonequilibrium topological phases come from higher-order terms in the high-frequency expansion called Brillouin-Wigner expansion, which is in striking contrast to usually discussed Floquet Chern insulator phases originating from the lowest-order terms of the expansion. So far, the lattice electron models on simple non-multipartite lattices such as triangular lattices and square lattices have not been regarded as targets of the Floquet engineering because the lowest-order terms of the high-frequency expansion for Floquet effective Hamiltonians cancel each other to vanish in these systems. Our findings of the Floquet Chern insulator phases in a triangular Kondo-lattice model are expected to expand the range of potential models and even materials targeted by the Floquet engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05385v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rintaro Eto, Masahito Mochizuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving quantum impurity problems on the L-shaped Kadanoff-Baym contour</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The path integral formalism is the building block of many powerful numerical methods for quantum impurity problems. However, existing path integral based numerical calculations have only been performed in either the imaginary-time or the real-time axis, while the most generic scenario formulated on the L-shaped Kadanoff-Baym contour is left unexplored. In this work, we extended the recently developed Grassmann time-evolving matrix product operator (GTEMPO) method to solve quantum impurity problems directly on the Kadanoff-Baym contour. The resulting method is numerically exact, with only two sources of numerical errors, e.g., the time discretization error and the matrix product state bond truncation error, which can both be well controlled. The accuracy of this method is numerically demonstrated against exact solutions in the noninteracting case, and against existing calculations on the real- and imaginary-time axes for the single-orbital Anderson impurity model. Our method is a perfect benchmarking baseline for its alternatives which often employ less-controlled approximations, and can also be used as a real-time impurity solver in dynamical mean field theory and its non-equilibrium extension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05410v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruofan Chen, Chu Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementation of the bilayer Hubbard model in a moir\'e heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e materials provide a unique platform for studies of correlated many-body physics of the Fermi-Hubbard model on triangular spin-charge lattices. Bilayer Hubbard models are of particular significance with regard to the physics of Mott insulating states and their relation to unconventional superconductivity, yet their experimental implementation in moir\'e systems has so far remained elusive. Here, we demonstrate the realization of a staggered bilayer triangular lattice of electrons in an antiparallel MoSe$_{2}$/WS$_{2}$ heterostructure. The bilayer lattice emerges due to strong electron confinement in the moir\'e potential minima and the near-resonant alignment of conduction band edges in MoSe$_{2}$ and WS$_{2}$. As a result, charge filling proceeds layer-by-layer, with the first and second electron per moir\'e cell consecutively occupying first the MoSe$_{2}$ and then the WS$_{2}$ layer. We describe the observed charging sequence by an electrostatic model and provide experimental evidence of spin correlations on the vertically offset and laterally staggered bilayer lattice, yielding absolute exciton Land\'e factors as high as $600$ at lowest temperatures. The bilayer character of the implemented spin-charge lattice allows for electrostatic tunability of Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida magnetism, and establishes antiparallel MoSe$_{2}$/WS$_{2}$ heterostructures as a viable platform for studies of bilayer Hubbard model physics with exotic magnetic phases on frustrated lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05494v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Borislav Polovnikov, Johannes Scherzer, Subhradeep Misra, Henning Schl\"omer, Julian Trapp, Xin Huang, Christian Mohl, Zhijie Li, Jonas G\"oser, Jonathan F\"orste, Ismail Bilgin, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Annabelle Bohrdt, Fabian Grusdt, Anvar S. Baimuratov, Alexander H\"ogele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice-Assisted Molecular Excitations in Frustrated Pyrochlores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Resonance-like molecular excitations have been discovered in a series of pyrochlore antiferromagnets, yet their origins and relationships with the coexisting magnon excitations remain a puzzle. Here, by incorporating the spin-lattice coupling and the consequent four-spin interactions through the site-phonon model, we accomplish a unified description of the molecular and magnon excitations, revealing the molecular modes as statistical approximations of the dispersive magnon excitations. Our work demonstrates a general approach to understand exotic spin dynamics in magnetoelastic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05523v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shang Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overcomplete intermediate representation of two-particle Green's functions and its relation to partial spectral functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-particle response functions are a centerpiece of both experimental and theoretical quantum many-body physics. Yet, due to their size and discontinuity structure, they are challenging to handle numerically. Recently, two advances were made to tackle this problem: first, the overcomplete intermediate representation (OIR), which provides a highly efficient compression of Green's functions in imaginary frequency, and second, partial spectral functions (PSFs), which allow for an efficient evaluation in real frequency. We show that there is a two-to-one correspondence between PSFs and OIR coefficients and exploit this fact to construct the OIR for three-or-more-particle propagators. We then use OIR to fit and compress imaginary-frequency data obtained from the numerical renormalization group (NRG), reaching a compression ratio of more than 400. Finally, we attempt to match the OIR data to partial Green's functions from NRG.Due to the overcompleteness, we achieve only qualitative agreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05541v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Selina Dirnb\"ock, Seung-Sup B. Lee, Fabian B. Kugler, Sebastian Huber, Jan von Delft, Karsten Held, Markus Wallerberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Candidate quantum spin liquids on the maple-leaf lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent numerical studies reporting putative quantum paramagnetic behavior in spin-$1/2$ Heisenberg models on the maple-leaf lattice, we classify Abrikosov fermion mean-field Ans\"atze of fully symmetric $U(1)$ and $\mathbb{Z}_{2}$ quantum spin liquids within the framework of projective symmetry groups. We obtain a total of $17$ $U(1)$ and $12$ $\mathbb{Z}_{2}$ algebraic PSGs, and, upon restricting their realization via mean-field Ans\"atze with nearest-neighbor amplitudes (relevant to the studied models), only 12 $U(1)$ and 8 $\mathbb{Z}_{2}$ distinct phases are obtained. We present both singlet and triplet fields for all Ans\"atze up to third nearest-neighbor bonds and discuss their spinon dispersions as well as their dynamical spin structure factors. We further assess the effects of Gutzwiller projection on the equal-time spin structure factors, and identify a $U(1)$ Fermi surface spin liquid whose structure factor most closely reproduces the one obtained from pseudo-fermion functional renormalization group calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05617v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Sonnenschein, Atanu Maity, Chunxiao Liu, Ronny Thomale, Francesco Ferrari, Yasir Iqbal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global phase diagram of doped quantum spin liquid on the Kagome lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has long been believed that doped quantum spin liquids (QSLs) can give rise to fascinating quantum phases, including the possibility of high-temperature superconductivity (SC) as proposed by P. W. Anderson's resonating valence bond (RVB) scenario. The Kagome lattice $t$-$J$ model is known to exhibit spin liquid behavior at half-filling, making it an ideal system for studying the properties of doped QSL. In this study, we employ the fermionic projected entangled simplex state (PESS) method to investigate the ground state properties of the Kagome lattice $t$-$J$ model with $t/J = 3.0$. Our results reveal a phase transition from charge density wave (CDW) states to uniform states around a critical doping level $\delta_c \approx 0.27$. Within the CDW phase, we observe different types of Wigner crystal (WC) formulated by doped holes that are energetically favored. As we enter the uniform phase, a non-Fermi liquid (NFL) state emerges within the doping range $0.27 &lt; \delta &lt; 0.32$, characterized by an exponential decay of all correlation functions. With further hole doping, we discover the appearance of a pair density wave (PDW) state within a narrow doping region $0.32 &lt; \delta &lt; 1/3$. We also discuss the potential experimental implications of our findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05685v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Tao Xu, Zheng-Cheng Gu, Shuo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chebyshev pseudosite matrix product state approach for cluster perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05686v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the Chebyshev pseudosite matrix product state approach (ChePSMPS) as a solver for cluster perturbation theory (CPT), crucial for simulating spectral functions in two-dimensional electron-phonon ($e$-ph) coupling systems. ChePSMPS distinguishes itself from conventional exact diagonalization solvers by supporting larger clusters, thereby significantly mitigating finite-size effects. Free from the fermion sign problem, ChePSMPS enhances its ability to explore $e$-ph effects and generate high-resolution spectral functions in doped Mott insulators. We use this method to simulate the spectra for both one- and two-dimensional Hubbard-Holstein models, highlighting its superiority over other methods. Our findings validate ChePSMPS as a powerful and reliable Green's function solver. In conjunction with embedding methods, ChePSMPS emerges as an essential tool for simulating strongly correlated $e$-ph coupling systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05686v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Yuan Zhao, Ke Ding, Shuo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher Landau-Level Analogues and Signatures of Non-Abelian States in Twisted Bilayer MoTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experimental discovery of fractional Chern insulators at zero magnetic field in moir\'e superlattices has sparked intense interests in bringing Landau level physics to flat Chern bands. In twisted MoTe$_2$ bilayers (tMoTe$_2$), recent theoretical and experimental studies have found three consecutive flat Chern bands at twist angle $\sim 2^\circ$. In this work, we investigate whether higher Landau level physics can be found in these consecutive Chern bands. At twist angles $2.00^\circ$ and $1.89^\circ$, we identify four consecutive $C = 1$ bands for the $K$ valley in tMoTe$_2$. By constructing Wannier functions directly from density functional theory (DFT) calculations, a six-orbital model is developed to describe the consecutive Chern bands, with the orbitals forming a honeycomb lattice. Exact diagonalization on top of Hartree-Fock calculations are carried out with the Wannier functions. Especially, when the second moir\'e miniband is half-filled, signatures of non-Abelian states are found. Our Wannier-based approach in modelling moir\'e superlattices is faithful to DFT wave functions and can serve as benchmarks for continuum models. The possibility of realizing non-Abelian anyons at zero magnetic field also opens up a new pathway for fault-tolerant quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05697v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong Wang, Xiao-Wei Zhang, Xiaoyu Liu, Jie Wang, Ting Cao, Di Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Luttinger parameter and Kane-Fisher effect in quasiperiodic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ground states of interacting one-dimensional metals are generically Luttinger liquids. Luttinger liquid theory is usually considered for translation invariant systems. The Luttinger liquid description remains valid for weak quasiperiodic modulations; however, as the quasiperiodic modulation gets increasingly strong, it is increasingly renormalized and eventually fails, as the system becomes localized. We explore how quasiperiodic modulation renormalizes the Luttinger parameter characterizing this emergent Luttinger liquid, using the renormalization of transmission coefficients across a barrier as a proxy that remains valid for general quasiperiodic modulation. We find, unexpectedly, that quasiperiodic modulation weakens the effects of short-range interactions, but enhances those of long-range interactions. We support the former finding with matrix-product numerics. We also discuss how interactions affect the localization phase boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05711v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. J. Vongkovit, Hansveer Singh, Romain Vasseur, Sarang Gopalakrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical behavior of dirty parafermionic chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04324v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A family of $\mathbb Z_n$-symmetric non-Hermitian models of Baxter was shown by Fendley to be exactly solvable via a parafermionic generalization of the Clifford algebra. We study these models with spatially random couplings, and obtain several exact results on thermodynamic singularities as the distributions of couplings are varied. We find that these singularities, independent of $n$, are identical to those in the random transverse-field Ising chain; correspondingly the models host infinite-randomness critical points. Similarities in structure to exact methods for random Ising models, a strong-disorder renormalization group, and generalizations to other models with free spectra, are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04324v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akshat Pandey, Aditya Cowsik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical absorption signatures of superconductors driven by Van Hove singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04329v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Due to the diverging density of states (DOS), Van Hove singularities (VHS) near the Fermi level are known to boost the susceptibility to a wide variety of electronic instabilities, including superconductivity. We theoretically show that the number of VHS in the normal state can be qualitatively inferred from the optical absorption spectra Re $\sigma_{ii}(\omega)$ in the superconducting state. The key feature is the absorption peak at frequency $\omega=2\Delta$ from the optical transition across the superconducting gap $\Delta$, which is forbidden in a single-band clean superconductor when the inversion symmetry is preserved and the band is quadratic. Although VHS dispersions are mostly quadratic, we find that a divergent peak occurs when there are multiple VHS on the Fermi surface under an applied current. In contrast, we find non-diverging weak peaks when there is only a single VHS. Depending on whether this single VHS has logarithmically or power-law divergent DOS, the peaks in Re $\sigma_{xx}(\omega)$ and Re $\sigma_{yy}(\omega)$ are nearly isotropic and anisotropic, respectively. Therefore, we propose that experimentally measured peak magnitude and anisotropy in the optical absorption spectra of VH-driven superconductors can be used to determine the number and type of VHS on the Fermi surface. Disorders could even facilitate in distinguishing the multiple and single VHS scenarios since only the diverging peak in the latter case is expected to survive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04329v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyeok-Jun Yang, Yi-Ting Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetoroton in a two-dimensional Bose-Bose mixture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04440v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend our theory of slow magnons in a two-component Bose-Einstein condensate to the case of two spatial dimensions (2D). We provide a detailed discussion of polaronic corrections to the magnon branch of the elementary excitation spectrum in a weakly- and strongly-interacting regimes. In a dilute system, the latter may be achieved by adjusting inter-species attraction such as to obtain a resonance in the $p$-wave scattering channel. Resonantly enhanced $p$-wave attraction results in the self-localization of magnons and formation of a magnetoroton. The nature of a ground state beyond the magnetoroton instability remains to be explored. We suggest a dilute p-wave crystal of alternating polarization as a possible candidate. In contrast to three dimensions (3D), the required strength of the attractive potential in the $s$-wave channel here corresponds to tight binding, and we suggest a potential realization of our model with excitons in 2D semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04440v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. I. Utesov, S. V. Andreev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden order in dielectrics: string condensation, solitons, and the charge-vortex duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04672v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Description of electrons as solitons of the polarization field implies that an ordinary dielectric has a hidden order, associated with the invariance with respect to adding loops of quantized electric flux. We describe the mechanism by which the finite polarizability of the medium renders the interaction between the solitons short-ranged (prior to their coupling to electromagnetism) and argue that the structure of the solitons allows them to be quantized as either fermions or bosons. At the quantum level, the theory has, in addition to the solitonic electric, elementary magnetic excitations, suggesting that small dielectrics may host quantized magnetic vortices carrying circular polarization currents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04672v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Khlebnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocal Nonlinear Responses in the Nonequilibrium States: Moving Charge Density Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04789v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The incommensurate charge density wave states (CDWs) can exhibit steady motion in the flow limit after depinning, behaving as a nonequilibrium system with time-dependent states. Since the moving CDW, like an electric current, breaks both time-reversal and inversion symmetries, one may speculate the emergence of nonreciprocal nonlinear responses from such motion. However, the moving CDW order parameter is intrinsically time-dependent in the lab frame, and it is known to be challenging to evaluate the responses of such a time-varying system. In this work, following the principle of Galilean relativity, we resolve this time-dependent hard problem in the lab frame by mapping the system to the comoving frame with static CDW states through the Galilean transformation. We explicitly show that the nonreciprocal nonlinear responses would be generated by the movement of CDW states through violating Galilean relativity. Our work demonstrates not only nonreciprocal nonlinear responses in nonequilibrium states but also the application of Galilean transformation in simplifying time-dependent problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04789v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying-Ming Xie, Hiroki Isobe, Naoto Nagaosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic Boundaries of 3D Color Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05033v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate boundaries of 3D color codes and provide a systematic classification into 101 distinct boundary types. The elementary types of boundaries are codimension-1 (2D) boundaries that condense electric particle ($Z$-type) or magnetic flux ($X$-type) excitations in the 3D color code, including the $Z$-boundary condensing only electric particles, the $X$-boundary condensing only the magnetic flux, and other boundaries condensing both electric and magnetic excitations. Two novel types of boundaries can be generated based on certain elementary types. The first type is generated by applying transversal-$T$ gate on the entire code in the presence of the $X$-boundary, which effectively sweeps the codimension-1 (2D) $T$-domain wall across the system and attaches it to the $X$-boundary. Since the $T$-domain wall cannot condense on the $X$-boundary, a new \textit{magic boundary} is produced, where the boundary stabilizers contain $XS$-stabilizers going beyond the conventional Pauli stabilizer formalism and hence contains `magic'. Neither electric nor magnetic excitations can condense on such a magic boundary, and only the composite of the magnetic flux and codimension-2 (1D) $S$-domain wall can condense on it, which makes the magic boundary going beyond the classification of the Lagrangian subgroup. The second type is generated by applying transversal-$S$ gate on a codimension-1 (2D) submanifold in the presence of certain codimension-1 (2D) boundaries, which effectively sweeps the $S$-domain wall across this submanifold and attaches it onto the boundary. This generates a codimension-2 (1D) \textit{nested boundary} at the intersection. We also connect these novel boundaries to their previously discovered counterpart in the $\mathbb{Z}_2^3$ gauge theory equivalent to three copies of 3D toric codes...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05033v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Song, Guanyu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxed hydrodynamic theory of electrically driven non-equilibrium steady states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05568v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hydrodynamics, as an effective theory capturing long-wavelength and late-time dynamics around thermal equilibrium states, finds applications in diverse physical systems, ranging from electron flow in metals, to ocean wave propagation, traffic flow, bacterial motion and the quark-gluon plasma. On the other hand, non-equilibrium steady states (NESS), characterized by a stationary flow of energy or matter in the presence of a driving force, are pervasive in nature but they present significant challenges to the foundational principles of statistical physics, as it is generally unclear if and how they satisfy the axiomatic assumptions of thermodynamics. The capability of hydrodynamics to accurately describe slow and long-wavelength fluctuations around a NESS remains an open question. In this study, we provide positive evidence by specifically addressing electrically driven non-equilibrium charged steady states. Our approach involves introducing gapped modes and extending the effective description into a relaxed hydrodynamic theory (RHT). Leveraging the gauge-gravity duality as a tool for controlled computations within non-equilibrium systems, we establish an ultraviolet complete model for these NESS that confirms the validity of our RHT. In summary, our findings present a concrete realization of a RHT applicable to a NESS. This expands the regime of validity of hydrodynamics beyond thermal equilibrium, offering valuable insights into the dynamics of non-equilibrium systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05568v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel K. Brattan, Masataka Matsumoto, Matteo Baggioli, Andrea Amoretti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emus live on the Gross-Neveu-Yukawa archipelago</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.00034v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is expected that the Gross-Neveu-Yukawa (GNY) chiral Ising transition of $N$ Majorana (or $N_f=N/4$ four-component Dirac) fermions coupled with scalar field in (2+1)D will be the first fermionic quantum critical point that various methods such as conformal bootstrap [1], perturbative renormalization group [2] and quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) simulations [3], would yield the converged critical exponents -- serving the same textbook role as the Ising and $O(N)$ models in the statistical and quantum phase transition. However, such expectation has not been fully realized from the lattice QMC simulations due to the obstacles introduced by the UV finite size effect. In this work, by means of the elective-momentum ultra-size (EMUS) QMC method [4], we compute the critical exponents of the GNY $N=8$ chiral Ising transition on a 2D $\pi$-flux fermion lattice model between Dirac semimetal and quantum spin Hall insulator phases [3, 5]. With the matching of fermionic and bosonic momentum transfer and collective update in momentum space, our QMC results provide the fully consistent exponents with those obtained from the bootstrap and perturbative approaches. In this way, the Emus now live happily on the $N=8$ island and could explore the Gross-Neveu-Yukawa archipelago [1] with ease.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.00034v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.108.L121112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 108, L121112, Vol. 108, Iss. 12, 22 September 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ting-Tung Wang, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermionic skyrmions and bosonization for a Gross-Neveu transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13716v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a 2+1-D interacting Dirac semimetal with onsite flavor SU(2) symmetry. Topological considerations imply that the skyrmions in the flavor-symmetry-breaking phase carry electron quantum numbers, motivating a dual bosonized low energy description in terms of two complex scalars coupled to an abelian Chern-Simons field. We propose that the transition between a nearby Chern insulator and the flavor symmetry-broken phase is a bicritical point in the bosonized description, and also suggest that the Gross-Neveu-Heisenberg (GNH) transition between the Dirac semimetal and the flavor symmetry-broken phase is a tricritical point. Heuristically, the dual description corresponds to the gap closing of fermionic skyrmions. We discuss implications and potential issues with our proposal, and motivated from it, perform extensive unbiased Determinantal Quantum Monte Carlo (DQMC) simulations on a lattice regularized Hamiltonian for the GNH transition, extending previously available results. We compare DQMC results with the estimates in the proposed dual from available perturbative renormalization group results. We also numerically demonstrate the presence of fermionic skyrmions in the symmetry-broken phase of our lattice model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13716v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.155112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 155112 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Yan Xu, Tarun Grover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partial molecular orbitals in face-sharing 3$d$ manganese trimer: Comparative studies on Ba$_{4}$TaMn$_{3}$O$_{12}$ and Ba$_{4}$NbMn$_{3}$O$_{12}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.14640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.14640v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a molecular orbital candidate Ba$_{4}$TaMn$_{3}$O$_{12}$ with a face-sharing octahedra trimer, by comparing it with a related compound Ba$_{4}$NbMn$_{3}$O$_{12}$. The synthesis of the polycrystalline powder is optimized by suppressing the secondary impurity phase via x-ray diffraction. Magnetic susceptibility measurements on the optimized samples reveal a weak magnetic hysteresis with magnetic transitions consistent with heat capacity results. The effective magnetic moments from susceptibility indicate a strongly coupled $S=2$ antiferromagnetic trimer at around room temperature, whereas the estimated magnetic entropy from heat capacity suggests the localized $S=3/2$ timer. These results can be explainable by a partial molecular orbital state, in which three $t_{2g}$ electrons are localized in each Mn ion and one $e_{g}$ electron is delocalized over two-end Mn ions of the trimer based on density functional theory calculations. This unconventional 3$d$ orbital state is comprehended as a consequence of competition between the hybrid interatomic orbitals within the Mn trimer and the local moment formation by on-site Coulomb correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.14640v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.013231</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, 013231 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anzar Ali, Heung-Sik Kim, Poonam Yadav, Suheon Lee, Duhee Yoon, Sungkyun Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic field induced partially polarized chiral spin liquid in a transition metal dichalcogenide moir\'e system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03056v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As one of the most intriguing states of matter, the chiral spin liquid (CSL) has attracted much scientific interest while its existence and mechanism in crystalline strongly correlated systems remain hotly debated. On the other hand, strong correlation driven emergent phenomena can be realized in twisted transition metal dichalcogenide bilayers with a tremendously tunable large length scale providing a new platform for the emergence of CSLs. We focus on a strongly correlated model relevant to heterobilayer $\textrm{WSe}_{2}/\textrm{MoSe}_{2}$ and investigate the Mott insulating phase at half filling under an out-of-plane magnetic field. Considering both its orbital and spin Zeeman effects we identify three conventionally ordered phases including a $120^{\circ}$ N\'{e}el phase, a stripe phase, and an up-up-down phase. For intermediate fields an emergent quantum spin liquid phase is identified with partial spin polarization. We further characterize its topological nature as the $\nu$ = 1/2 Laughlin CSL through the topological entanglement spectrum and quantized spin pumping under spin flux insertion. In addition, we map out the quantum phase diagram for different twisted angles in an experimentally accessible parameter regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03056v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.165109</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 165109 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yixuan Huang, D. N. Sheng, Jian-Xin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-frequency quantum field theory applied to the single-impurity Anderson model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.10791v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A major challenge in the field of correlated electrons is the computation of dynamical correlation functions. For comparisons with experiment, one is interested in their real-frequency dependence. This is difficult to compute, as imaginary-frequency data from the Matsubara formalism require analytic continuation, a numerically ill-posed problem. Here, we apply quantum field theory to the single-impurity Anderson model (AM), using the Keldysh instead of the Matsubara formalism with direct access to the self-energy and dynamical susceptibilities on the real-frequency axis. We present results from the functional renormalization group (fRG) at one-loop level and from solving the self-consistent parquet equations in the parquet approximation. In contrast to previous Keldysh fRG works, we employ a parametrization of the four-point vertex which captures its full dependence on three real-frequency arguments. We compare our results to benchmark data obtained with the numerical renormalization group and to second-order perturbation theory. We find that capturing the full frequency dependence of the four-point vertex significantly improves the fRG results compared to previous implementations, and that solving the parquet equations yields the best agreement with the NRG benchmark data, but is only feasible up to moderate interaction strengths. Our methodical advances pave the way for treating more complicated models in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.10791v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.115128</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Anxiang Ge, Nepomuk Ritz, Elias Walter, Santiago Aguirre, Jan von Delft, Fabian B. Kugler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of spin liquid phase in the $J_1-J_2$ Heisenberg model on the square lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.13630v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform an in-depth investigation of the phase diagram of the $J_1-J_2$ Heisenberg model on the square lattice. We take advantage of Density Matrix Renormalization Group and Fully-Augmented Matrix Product States methods and reach unprecedented accuracy with large bond dimensions. We utilize excited-level crossing analysis to pinpoint the phase transition points. It was believed before that there exists a narrow spin liquid phase sandwiched by the N\'eel antiferromagnetic (AFM) and valence bond solid (VBS) phases. Through careful finite size scaling of the level crossing points, we find a direct phase transition between the N\'eel AFM and VBS phases at $J_2/J_1 = 0.535(3)$, suggesting the absence of an intermediate spin liquid phase. We also provide accurate results for ground state energies for a variety of sizes, from which we find that the transition between the N\'eel AFM and VBS phases is continuous. These results indicate the existence of a deconfined quantum critical point at $J_2/J_1 = 0.535(3)$ in the model. From the crossing of the first derivative of the energies with $J_2$ for different sizes, we also determine the precise location of the first order phase transition between the VBS and stripe AFM phases at $J_2/J_1=0.610(5)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.13630v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.L161103</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, L161103 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiangjian Qian, Mingpu Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-group symmetry of (3+1)D fermionic $\mathbb{Z}_2$ gauge theory: logical CCZ, CS, and T gates from higher symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.05674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.05674v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has recently been understood that the complete global symmetry of finite group topological gauge theories contains the structure of a higher-group. Here we study the higher-group structure in (3+1)D $\mathbb{Z}_2$ gauge theory with an emergent fermion, and point out that pumping chiral $p+ip$ topological states gives rise to a $\mathbb{Z}_{8}$ 0-form symmetry with mixed gravitational anomaly. This ordinary symmetry mixes with the other higher symmetries to form a 3-group structure, which we examine in detail. We then show that in the context of stabilizer quantum codes, one can obtain logical CCZ and CS gates by placing the code on a discretization of $T^3$ (3-torus) and $T^2 \rtimes_{C_2} S^1$ (2-torus bundle over the circle) respectively, and pumping $p+ip$ states. Our considerations also imply the possibility of a logical $T$ gate by placing the code on $\mathbb{RP}^3$ and pumping a $p+ip$ topological state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.05674v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maissam Barkeshli, Po-Shen Hsin, Ryohei Kobayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry, topology, duality, chirality, and criticality in a spin-1/2 XXZ ladder with a four-spin interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07053v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the ground-state phase diagram of a spin-1/2 XXZ model with a chirality-chirality interaction (CCI) on a two-leg ladder. This model offers a minimal setup to study an interplay between spin and chirality degrees of freedom. The spin-chirality duality transformation allows us to relate the regimes of weak and strong CCIs. By applying the Abelian bosonization and the duality, we obtain a rich phase diagram that contains distinct gapped featureless and ordered phases. In particular, Neel and vector chiral orders appear for easy-axis anisotropy, while two distinct symmetry protected topological (SPT) phases appear for easy-plane anisotropy. The two SPT phases can be viewed as twisted variants of the Haldane phase. We also present an effective description in terms of (spinor) hard-core bosons, which reveals critical behavior on the self-dual line in the easy-axis and easy-plane regimes. We perform numerical simulations to confirm the predicted phase structure and critical properties. We further demonstrate that the two SPT phases and a trivial phase are distinguished by topological indices in the presence of certain symmetries. A similar phase structure is expected in a spin-1/2 XXZ ladder with four-spin ring exchange.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07053v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateo Fontaine, Koudai Sugimoto, Shunsuke Furukawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge symmetry of excited states in projected entangled-pair state simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04555v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While gauge symmetry is a well-established requirement for representing topological orders in projected entangled-pair state (PEPS), its impact on the properties of low-lying excited states remains relatively unexplored. Here we perform PEPS simulations of low-energy dynamics in the Kitaev honeycomb model, which supports fractionalized gauge flux (vison) excitations. We identify gauge symmetry emerging upon optimizing an unbiased PEPS ground state. Using the PEPS adapted local mode approximation, we further classify the low-lying excited states by discerning different vison sectors. Our simulations of spin and spin-dimer dynamical correlations establish close connections with experimental observations. Notably, the selection rule imposed by the locally conserved visons results in nearly flat dispersions in momentum space for excited states belonging to the 2-vison or 4-vison sectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04555v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Tan, Ji-Yao Chen, Didier Poilblanc, Jia-Wei Mei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retaining Landau quasiparticles in the presence of realistic charge fluctuations in cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02200v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Charge excitation spectra are getting clear in cuprate superconductors in momentum-energy space especially around a small momentum region, where plasmon excitations become dominant. Here, we study whether Landau quasiparticles survive in the presence of charge fluctuations observed in experiments. We employ the layered t-J model with the long-range Coulomb interaction, which can reproduce the realistic charge fluctuations. We find that Landau quasiparticles are retained in a realistic temperature and doping region, although the quasiparticle spectral weight is strongly reduced to 0.08-0.24. Counterintuitively, the presence of this small quasiparticle weight does not work favorably to generate a pseudogap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02200v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.104515</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 104515 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyuki Yamase, Matias Bejas, Andres Greco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Similarity between a many-body quantum avalanche model and the ultrametric random matrix model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07431v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the field of ergodicity-breaking phases, it has been recognized that quantum avalanches can destabilize many-body localization at a wide range of disorder strengths. This has in particular been demonstrated by the numerical study of a toy model, sometimes simply called the "avalanche model" or the "quantum sun model" [Phys. Rev. Lett. 129, 060602 (2022)], which consists of an ergodic seed coupled to a perfectly localized material. In this paper, we connect this toy model to a well-studied model in random matrix theory, the ultrametric ensemble. We conjecture that the models share the following features. 1) The location of the critical point may be predicted sharply by analytics. 2) On the localized site, both models exhibit Fock space localization. 3) There is a manifold of critical points. On the critical manifold, the eigenvectors exhibit nontrivial multifractal behaviour that can be tuned by moving on the manifold. 4) The spectral statistics at criticality is intermediate between Poisson statistics and random matrix statistics, also tunable on the critical manifold. We confirm numerically these properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07431v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, 023030 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jan \v{S}untajs, Miroslav Hopjan, Wojciech De Roeck, Lev Vidmar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remarks on effects of projective phase on eigenstate thermalization hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11425v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The existence of $p$-form symmetry in $(d+1)$-dimensional quantum field is known to always lead to the breakdown of the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis (ETH) for certain $(d-p)$-dimensional operators other than symmetry operators under some assumptions. The assumptions include the mixing of symmetry sectors within a given energy shell, which is rather challenging to verify because it requires information on the eigenstates in the middle of the spectrum. We reconsider this assumption from the viewpoint of projective representations to avoid this difficulty. In the case of $\mathbb{Z}_N$ symmetries, we can circumvent the difficulty by considering $\mathbb{Z}_N\times\mathbb{Z}_N$-symmetric theories with nontrivial projective phases, and perturbing the Hamiltonian while preserving one of the $\mathbb{Z}_N$ symmetries of our interest. We also perform numerical analyses for $(1+1)$-dimensional spin chains and the $(2+1)$-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11425v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/ptep/ptae039</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Osamu Fukushima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current-controlled chirality dynamics in a mesoscopic magnetic domain wall</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07487v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Chirality as internal degree of freedom of a mesoscopic domain wall inside a quasi-one-dimensional fixture can be controlled by spin-polarized current for ferro- as well as anti-ferro-magnetic domain walls. We show that the current density required for the chirality manipulation can be significantly reduced in the low-temperature regime where the chirality dynamics exhibits quantum effects. In this quantum regime, weak currents can excite Bloch oscillations of the domain wall angular rotation velocity, with the oscillation frequency proportional to the current, modulated by a much higher magnon-range frequency. In addition to that, the Wannier-Stark localization effects enable controlled switching between different chiral states, suppressing inertial effects characteristic for the classical regime. We also show that for recently discovered novel class of magnetic materials -- altermagnets -- chirality switching can be driven by the usual charge current (not spin-polarized).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07487v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksiy Kolezhuk, Roman Teslia, Ihor Buryak, Olena Gomonay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon hydrodynamics in bulk insulators and semi-metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14870v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Decades ago, Gurzhi proposed that if momentum-conserving collisions prevail among heat-carrying phonons in insulators and charge-carrying electrons in metals, hydrodynamic features will become detectable. In this paper, we will review the experimental evidence emerging in the last few years supporting this viewpoint and raising new questions. The focus of the paper will be bulk crystals without (or with a very dilute concentration) of mobile electrons and steady-state thermal transport. We will also discuss the possible link between this field of investigation and other phenomena, such as the hybridization of phonon modes and the phonon thermal Hall effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14870v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yo Machida, Valentina Martelli, Alexandre Jaoui, Beno\^it Fauqu\'e, Kamran Behnia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonic near-CFT$_1$ models from Fock-space fluxes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13131v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a family of near-CFT$_1$ models with a conserved U(1) charge, whose basic degrees of freedom are canonical bosons. The Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model -- the first microscopic model that realizes the near-CFT$_1$ dynamics -- is based on random $p$-local interactions among fermions. However, a bosonic near-CFT$_1$ model has remained elusive in the $p$-local approach because such constructions generally suffer from unwanted orderings at low temperatures. Our construction is based on a recent insight that near-CFT$_1$ dynamics can quite generally arise if we place a large amount of random fluxes in a many-body Fock space and $p$-locality is not essential. All such models are essentially solved by chord diagrams regardless of the nature of the underlying degrees of freedom. We further argue that such bosonic models do not suffer from energetic instablities or unwanted low-temperature orderings. For comparison we also consider a second class of charge-conserving models which are based on qubits. The thermodynamic scalings of these models are very similar to those of the double-scaled complex SYK model but are free of certain singularities the latter suffers from. We also show the level statistics of both models are described by random matrix theory universality down to very low energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13131v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiyang Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
