<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 05:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-invertible SPTs: an on-site realization of (1+1)d anomaly-free fusion category symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate (1+1)d symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phases with fusion category symmetries. We emphasize that the UV description of an anomaly-free fusion category symmetry must include the fiber functor, giving rise to a local symmetry action, a charge category and a trivial phase. We construct an ``onsite'' matrix-product-operator (MPO) version of the Hopf algebra symmetry operators in a lattice model with tensor-product Hilbert space. In particular, we propose a systematic framework for classifying and constructing SPTs with non-invertible symmetries. An SPT phase corresponds to a Q-system in the charge category, such that the Q-system becomes a matrix algebra when the symmetry is forgotten. As an example, we provide an explicit microscopic realization of all three $\mathsf{Rep}^\dagger(D_8)$ SPT phases, including a trivial phase, and further demonstrate the $S_3$-duality among these three SPT phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20546v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenqi Meng, Xinping Yang, Tian Lan, Zhengcheng Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>External field induced metal-to-insulator transition in dissipative Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20583v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we develop a non-equilibrium steady-state non-crossing approximation (NESS-NCA) impurity solver applicable to general impurity problems. The choice of the NCA as the impurity solver enables both a more accurate description of correlation effects with larger Coulomb interaction and scalability to multi-orbital systems. Based on this development, we investigate strongly correlated non-equilibrium states of a dissipative lattice system under constant electric fields. Both the electronic Coulomb interaction and the electric field are treated non-perturbatively using dynamical mean-field theory in its non-equilibrium steady-state form (NESS-DMFT) with the NESS-NCA impurity solver. We validate our implementation using a half-filled single-band Hubbard model attached to a fictitious free Fermion reservoir, which prevents temperature divergence. As a result, we identify metallic and insulating phases as functions of the electric field and the Coulomb interaction along with a phase coexistence region amid the metal-to-insulator transition (MIT). We find that the MIT driven by the electric field is qualitatively similar to the equilibrium MIT as a function of temperature, differing from results in previous studies using the iterative perturbation theory (IPT) impurity solver. Finally, we highlight the importance of the morphology of a correlated system under the influence of an electric field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20583v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beomjoon Goh, Junwon Kim, Hongchul Choi, Ji Hoon Shim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic theory of pair density waves in spin-orbit coupled Kondo lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the discommensuration between the Fermi surfaces of a conduction sea and an underlying spin liquid provides a natural mechanism for the spontaneous formation of pair density waves. Using a recent formulation of the Kondo lattice model which incorporates a Yao Lee spin liquid proposed by the authors, we demonstrate that doping away from half-filling induces finite-momentum electron-Majorana pair condensation, resulting in amplitude-modulated PDWs. Our approach provides a precise, analytically tractable pathway for understanding the spontaneous formation of PDWs in higher dimensions and offers a natural mechanism for PDW formation in the absence of a Zeeman field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20647v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaditya Panigrahi, Alexei Tsvelik, Piers Coleman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of disorder on the strain-tuned charge density wave multicriticality in Pd$_x$ErTe$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore, through a combination of x-ray diffraction and elastoresistivity measurements, the effect of disorder on the strain-tuned charge density wave and associated multicriticality in Pd$_x$ErTe$_3$ (x = 0, 0.01, 0.02 and 0.026). We focus particularly on the behavior near the strain-tuned bicritical point that occurs in pristine ErTe$_3$ (x=0). Our study reveals that while Pd intercalation somewhat broadens the signatures of the CDW phase transitions, the line of first-order transitions at which the CDW reorients as a function of applied strain persists in the presence of disorder and still seemingly terminates at a critical point. The critical point occurs at a lower temperature and a lower strain compared to pristine ErTe$_3$. Similarly, the nematic elastoresistance of Pd$_x$ErTe$_3$, though suppressed in magnitude and broadened relative to that of ErTe$_3$, has a markedly more symmetric response around the critical point. These observations point to disorder driving a reduction in the system's electronic orthorhombicity even while the material remains irrevocably orthorhombic due to the presence of a glide plane in the crystal structure. Disorder, it would appear, reinforces the emergence of a "pseudo-tetragonal" electronic response in this fundamentally orthorhombic material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20706v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anisha G. Singh, Matthew Krogstad, Maja D. Bachmann, Paul Thompson, Stephan Rosenkranz, Ray Osborn, Alan Fang, Aharon Kapitulnik, Jong Woo Kim, Philip J. Ryan, Steven A. Kivelson, Ian R. Fisher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic excitations and interactions in the Weyl ferrimagnet NdAlSi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weyl fermions can arise from time-reversal symmetry-breaking magnetism, but their impact on magnetic order is a source of ongoing research. Using high-precision neutron diffraction and spectroscopy, we present a comprehensive exploration of the magnetic structure and excitation spectrum of Weyl semimetal and helical magnet NdAlSi. We use Luttinger-Tisza, classical mean-field, and random-phase approximation techniques to model the dispersive crystal field excitons. We find extended-ranged and sign-changing interactions, suggesting a coupling between conduction electrons and the local moments. We demonstrate that low-symmetry anisotropic Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions, in contrast with higher-symmetry interactions enabled by Weyl fermions, play an important role in stabilizing the complex spin spiral ground state of NdAlSi. Our work provides a first detailed view of microscopic interactions in a Weyl magnet, and constrains the role of Weyl electrons and their chirality on the spiral magnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20743v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris J. Lygouras, Hung-Yu Yang, Xiaohan Yao, Jonathan Gaudet, Yiqing Hao, Huibo Cao, Jose A. Rodriguez-Rivera, Andrey Podlesnyak, Stefan Bl\"ugel, Predrag Nikoli\'c, Fazel Tafti, Collin L. Broholm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-enforced minimal entanglement and correlation in quantum spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between symmetry, entanglement and correlation is an interesting and important topic in quantum many-body physics. Within the framework of matrix product states, in this paper we study the minimal entanglement and correlation enforced by the $SO(3)$ spin rotation symmetry and lattice translation symmetry in a quantum spin-$J$ chain, with $J$ a positive integer. When neither symmetry is spontaneously broken, for a sufficiently long segment in a sufficiently large closed chain, we find that the minimal R\'enyi-$\alpha$ entropy compatible with these symmetries is $\min\{ -\frac{2}{\alpha-1}\ln(\frac{1}{2^\alpha}({1+\frac{1}{(2J+1)^{\alpha-1}}})), 2\ln(J+1) \}$, for any $\alpha\in\mathbb{R}^+$. In an infinitely long open chain with such symmetries, for any $\alpha\in\mathbb{R}^+$ the minimal R\'enyi-$\alpha$ entropy of half of the system is $\min\{ -\frac{1}{\alpha-1}\ln(\frac{1}{2^\alpha}({1+\frac{1}{(2J+1)^{\alpha-1}}})), \ln(J+1) \}$. When $\alpha\rightarrow 1$, these lower bounds give the symmetry-enforced minimal von Neumann entropies in these setups. Moreover, we show that no state in a quantum spin-$J$ chain with these symmetries can have a vanishing correlation length. Interestingly, the states with the minimal entanglement may not be a state with the minimal correlation length.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20765v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kangle Li, Liujun Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ising phase transitions and thermodynamics of correlated fermions in a 2D spin-dependent optical lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a {\it numerically exact} study of the Hubbard model with spin-dependent anisotropic hopping on the square lattice using auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo method. At half-filling, the system undergoes Ising phase transitions upon cooling, leading to the formation of Ising-type antiferromagnetic order for repulsive interactions and charge density wave order for attractive interactions at finite temperatures. By elegantly implementing the sign-problem-free condition and Hubbard-Stratonovich transformations, we achieve significant improvements in precision control of the numerical calculations, and obtain highly accurate results of the transition temperatures from weak to strong interactions across representative anisotropies. We further characterize the system by examining the temperature dependence of various thermodynamic properties, including the energy, double occupancy, specific heat and charge susceptibility. Specifically, we provide unbiased numerical results of the entropy map on temperature-interaction plane, the critical entropy, and the spin, singlon and doublon correlations, all of which are directly measurable in optical lattice experiments. Away from half-filling, we explore the behavior of the sign problem and investigate the possible emergence of stripe spin-density wave order in the system with repulsive interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20843v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuotao Xie, Yu-Feng Song, Yuan-Yao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cascades in transport and optical conductivity of Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using a combined Dynamical Mean Field Theory and Hartree (DMFT+H) calculation we study the transport and optical properties of the 8-band heavy fermion model for Twisted Bilayer Graphene (TBG) in the normal state. We find resistive states around integer fillings which resemble the ones observed in transport experiments. From a Drude fitting of the low frequency optical conductivity, we extract a very strongly doping-dependent Drude weight and scattering rate, resetting at the integers. For most dopings, particularly above the integers, the Drude scattering rate is high but notably smaller than that of the local electrons. This highlights the important role of itinerant electrons in the transport properties, despite their limited spectral weight on the flat bands. At far infrared frequencies, the optical conductivity exhibits cascades characterized by highly asymmetric resets of the intensity and oscillations in the interband peak frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20855v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. J. Calder\'on, A. Camjayi, A. Datta, E. Bascones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transition of Kitaev spin liquid described by quantum geometric tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weinvestigate the topological phase transition of Kitaev spin liquid in an external magnetic field by calculating
  the Berry curvature and the Fubini-Study metric. Employing Jordan-Wigner transformation and effective
  perturbative theory to transform the Hamiltonian into fermionic quadratic form, the Berry curvature is calculated
  by choosing the effective magnetic field as the parameter, and we find that the xy-component of the Berry
  curvature has the same behavior around the critical lines with the phase diagram and the behavior of Berry
  curvature around the critical line will not be influenced by local perturbation, i.e. it has the robustness against
  the local perturbation. Especially, we relate the Berry curvature with the derivative of effective magnetic
  susceptibility which can be regarded as the signature of topological phase transition besides, we related the
  second nonlinear susceptibility with the non-Abelian Berry connection. Then we analytically calculate the
  generalized Berry curvature in the mixed state called mean Uhlmann curvature which can be related with the
  spectral function, the curves that mean Uhlmanncurvaturechangingtemperaturewithdifferentcouplingconstant
  reveal that it will have an extrema when adjust $J_x$ from $A$ phase to $B$ phase. At last we analytically calculate the
  quantum geometric tensor in the effective magnetic field space whose imaginary part is the Berry curvature and
  real part is the Fubini-Study metric, and we find that the zz-component of Fubini-Study metric and the phase
  diagram are highly correlated which will peak at the cross point of three phases, then the Fubini-Study metric
  is extended to the finite temperature with arising an additional term called Fisher-Rao metric caused by mixed
  state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20889v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng-Meng Lu, Zheng-Chuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of alternating interactions and boundary conditions on quantum entanglement of three-leg Heisenberg ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20935v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spin-12 three-leg antiferromagnetic Heisenberg spin ladder is studied under open boundary condition (OBC) and cylinder boundary condition (CBC), using the density matrix renormalization group and matrix product state methods, respectively. Specifically, we calculate the energy density, entanglement entropy, and concurrence while discussing the effects of interleg interaction J2 and the alternating coupling parameter gamma on these quantities. It is found that the introduction of gamma can completely reverse the concurrence distribution between odd and even bonds. Under CBC, the generation of the interleg concurrence is inhibited when gamma=0, and the introduction of gamma can cause interleg concurrence between chains 1 and 3, in which the behavior is more complicated due to the competition between CBC and gamma. Additionally, we find that gamma induces two types of long-distance entanglement (LDE) in the system under OBC: intraleg LDE and inter-leg one. When the system size is sufficiently large, both types of LDE reach similar strength and stabilize at a constant value. The study indicates that the three-leg ladder makes it easier to generate LDE compared with the two-leg system. However, the generation of LDE is inhibited under CBC which the spin frustration exists. In addition, the calculated results of energy, entanglement entropy and concurrence all show that there are essential relations between these quantities and phase transitions of the system. Further, we predict a phase transition point near gamma=0.54 under OBC. The present study provides valuable insights into understanding the phase diagram of this class of systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20935v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qinghui Li, Lizhen Hu, Panpan Zhang, Chuanzheng Miao, Yuliang Xu, Zhongqiang Liu, Xiangmu Kong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of Kitaev interactions in the van der Waals ferromagnet VI3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21003v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Materials manifesting the Kitaev model, characterized by bond-dependent interactions on a honeycomb lattice, can host exotic phenomena like quantum spin liquid states and topological magnetic excitations. However, finding such materials remains a formidable challenge. Here, we report high-resolution inelastic neutron scattering measurements performed on VI3, a van der Waals ferromagnetic Mott insulator, covering a wide range of reciprocal space. Our measurements unveil highly anisotropic magnetic excitations in momentum space. Through a comprehensive comparative analysis of various models that incorporate diverse symmetry-allowed magnetic interactions, we find the observed excitations are well captured by a model with a large bond-dependent Kitaev interaction. These results not only help to understand the intriguing properties of VI3, such as the pronounced anomalous thermal Hall effects and strong pressure/structure dependence of magnetism, but also open a new avenue for exploring Kitaev physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21003v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.246702</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 246702 (2024) Editors' Suggestion</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yiqing Gu, Yimeng Gu, Feiyang Liu, Seiko Ohira-Kawamura, Naoki Murai, Jun Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional quantum Hall states by Feynman's diagrammatic expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fractional quantum Hall (FQH) effect arises from strong electron correlations in a quantising magnetic field, and features exotic emergent phenomena such as electron fractionalisation. Using the diagrammatic Monte Carlo approach with the combinatorial summation algorithm, we obtain results with controlled accuracy for the microscopic model of interacting electrons in the lowest Landau level. As the temperature is lowered, we study the development and emergence of the incompressible 1/3-filled FQH state. By analysing the long-time decay of the Green's function, we find spectral properties consistent with an energy gap near 1/3-filling, while at half-filling an anomalous power law scaling is observed for short-range interaction screening, indicative of a non-Fermi liquid metal. Our work provides the first demonstration that fractionalised phases of matter can be reliably described with Feynman's diagrammatic technique in terms of the fundamental electronic degrees of freedom, while also showing applicability of expansions in the bare Coulomb potential for precision calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21064v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Currie, Evgeny Kozik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced coarsening of charge density waves induced by electron correlation: Machine-learning enabled large-scale dynamical simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The phase ordering kinetics of emergent orders in correlated electron systems is a fundamental topic in non-equilibrium physics, yet it remains largely unexplored. The intricate interplay between quasiparticles and emergent order-parameter fields could lead to unusual coarsening dynamics that is beyond the standard theories. However, accurate treatment of both quasiparticles and collective degrees of freedom is a multi-scale challenge in dynamical simulations of correlated electrons. Here we leverage modern machine learning (ML) methods to achieve a linear-scaling algorithm for simulating the coarsening of charge density waves (CDWs), one of the fundamental symmetry breaking phases in functional electron materials. We demonstrate our approach on the square-lattice Hubbard-Holstein model and uncover an intriguing enhancement of CDW coarsening which is related to the screening of on-site potential by electron-electron interactions. Our study provides fresh insights into the role of electron correlations in non-equilibrium dynamics and underscores the promise of ML force-field approaches for advancing multi-scale dynamical modeling of correlated electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21072v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Yang, Chen Cheng, Yunhao Fan, Gia-Wei Chern</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Z$_2$ topological orders in kagom\'e dipolar systems: Feedback from Rydberg quantum simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mutual feedback between quantum condensed matter and cold atom physics has been quite fruitful throughout history and continues to inspire ongoing research. Motivated by the recent activities on the quantum simulation of topological orders among the ultracold Rydberg atom arrays, we consider the possibility of searching for topological orders among the dipolar quantum magnets and polar molecules with a kagom\'{e} lattice geometry. Together with other quantum interactions such as the transverse field, the dipolar interaction endows the kagom\'e system with a similar structure as the Balents-Fisher-Girvin model and thus fosters the emergence of the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological orders. We construct a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory to access the topological ordered phase and describe the spinon and vison excitations for the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological orders. We explain the spectroscopic consequences for various quantum phases as well as the experimental detection. We further discuss the rare-earth kagom\'{e} magnets, ultracold polar molecules, and cluster Mott insulators for the physical realization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21112v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengwei Zhao, Gang v. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1/5 and 1/3 magnetization plateaux in the spin 1/2 chain system YbAlO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quasi-one-dimensional magnets can host an ordered longitudinal spin-density wave state (LSDW) in magnetic field at low temperature, when longitudinal correlations are strengthened by Ising anisotropies. In the S = 1/2 Heisenberg antiferromagnet YbAlO3 this happens via Ising-like interchain interactions. Here, we report the first experimental observation of magnetization plateaux at 1/5 and 1/3 of the saturation value via thermal transport and magnetostriction measurements in YbAlO3. We present a phenomenological theory of the plateau states that describes them as islands of commensurability within an otherwise incommensurate LSDW phase and explains their relative positions within the LSDW phase and their relative extent in a magnetic field. Notably, the plateaux are stabilised by ferromagnetic interchain interactions in YbAlO3 and consistently are absent in other quasi-1D magnets such as BaCo2V2O8 with antiferromagnetic interchain interactions. We also report a sharp, step-like increase of the magnetostriction coefficient, indicating a phase transition of unknown origin in the high-field phase just below the saturation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21144v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Mokhtari, S. Galeski, U. Stockert, S. E. Nikitin, R. Wawrzynczak, R. Kuechler, M. Brando, L. Vasylechko, O. A. Starykh, E. Hassinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating time in quantum chaotic systems and black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19885v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We characterize new universal features of the dynamics of chaotic quantum many-body systems, by considering a hypothetical task of "time estimation." Most macroscopic observables in a chaotic system equilibrate to nearly constant late-time values. Intuitively, it should become increasingly difficult to estimate the precise value of time by making measurements on the state. We use a quantity called the Fisher information from quantum metrology to quantify the minimum uncertainty in estimating time. Due to unitarity, the uncertainty in the time estimate does not grow with time if we have access to optimal measurements on the full system. Restricting the measurements to act on a small subsystem or to have low computational complexity leads to results expected from equilibration, where the time uncertainty becomes large at late times. With optimal measurements on a subsystem larger than half of the system, we regain the ability to estimate the time very precisely, even at late times.
  Hawking's calculation for the reduced density matrix of the black hole radiation in semiclassical gravity contradicts our general predictions for unitary quantum chaotic systems. Hawking's state always has a large uncertainty for attempts to estimate the time using the radiation, whereas our general results imply that the uncertainty should become small after the Page time. This gives a new version of the black hole information loss paradox in terms of the time estimation task. By restricting to simple measurements on the radiation, the time uncertainty becomes large. This indicates from a new perspective that the observations of computationally bounded agents are consistent with the semiclassical effective description of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19885v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haifeng Tang, Shreya Vardhan, Jinzhao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aharonov-Bohm Interference in Even-Denominator Fractional Quantum Hall States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19886v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Position exchange of non-Abelian anyons affects the quantum state of their system in a topologically-protected way. Their expected manifestations in even-denominator fractional quantum Hall (FQH) systems offer the opportunity to directly study their unique statistical properties in interference experiments. In this work, we present the observation of coherent Aharonov-Bohm interference at two even-denominator states in high-mobility bilayer graphene-based van der Waals heterostructures by employing the Fabry-P\'erot interferometry (FPI) technique. Operating the interferometer at a constant filling factor, we observe an oscillation period corresponding to two flux quanta inside the interference loop, $\Delta\Phi=2\Phi_0$, at which the interference does not carry signatures of non-Abelian statistics. The absence of the expected periodicity of $\Delta\Phi=4\Phi_0$ may indicate that the interfering quasiparticles carry the charge $e^* = \frac{1}{2}e$ or that interference of $e^* = \frac{1}{4}e$ quasiparticles is thermally smeared. Interestingly, at two hole-conjugate states, we also observe oscillation periods of half the expected value, indicating interference of $e^* = \frac{2}{3}e$ quasiparticles instead of $e^* = \frac{1}{3}e$. To probe statistical phase contributions, we operated the FPI with controlled deviations of the filling factor, thereby introducing fractional quasiparticles inside the interference loop. The resulting changes to the interference patterns at both half-filled states indicate that the additional bulk quasiparticles carry the fundamental charge $e^*=\frac{1}{4}e$, as expected for non-Abelian anyons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19886v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jehyun Kim, Himanshu Dev, Amit Shaer, Ravi Kumar, Alexey Ilin, Andr\'e Haug, Shelly Iskoz, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, David F. Mross, Ady Stern, Yuval Ronen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Space Approach to Wannier Pairing and Bogoliubov Orbitals in Square-Octagon Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20054v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Low-energy lattice models are the cornerstone for understanding many-body effects and interactions between systems and measurements. A key challenge is identifying appropriate states that canonically transform between momentum and real space while retaining the correlation, entanglement, and geometric properties - generally called the Wannier obstruction. Here, we introduce a phase-space approach to bypass these obstructions. Instead of treating phase space as a manifold, we embed real space through a Bloch vector space at each momentum. Orbital and spin states are introduced through product states with the Bloch vector, while quantum statistics, correlations, topology, and entanglements are inherited from the Hamiltonian. We apply this framework to explore unconventional pairing symmetry and the Bogoliubov-de-Gennes (BdG) equation in the phase space. Our findings demonstrate that while superconductivity exhibits global coherence in momentum space, the local Wannier orbital symmetry primarily determines the pairing symmetry. We analytically solve the spin-fluctuation mediated pairing symmetry on the phase space by engineering a flat band with artificial gauge fields. We then apply the model to a square-octagon superconductor Lu$_2$Fe$_3$Si$_5$ using density functional theory (DFT) to unravel a coexistence of nodeless $s_{\pm}$ and nodal $s_{z^2}$ pairing symmetries. This phase-space framework provides a robust, obstruction-free lattice model for complex many-body systems and their exotic excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20054v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajesh O. Sharma, Tanmoy Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quantum Kibble-Zurek mechanism: the role of boundary conditions, endpoints and kink types</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20186v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum phase transitions are characterised by the universal scaling laws in the critical region surrounding the transitions. This universality is also manifested in the critical real-time dynamics through the quantum Kibble-Zurek mechanism. In recent experiments on a Rydberg atom quantum simulator, the Kibble-Zurek mechanism has been used to probe the nature of quantum phase transitions.
  In this paper we analyze the caveats associated with this method and develop strategies to improve its accuracy. Focusing on two minimal models -- transverse-field Ising and three-state Potts -- we study the effect of boundary conditions, the location of the endpoints and some subtleties in the definition of the kink operators.
  In particular, we show that the critical scaling of the most intuitive types of kinks is extremely sensitive to the correct choice of endpoint, while more advanced types of kinks exhibit remarkably robust universal scaling. Furthermore, we show that when kinks are tracked over the entire chain, fixed boundary conditions improve the accuracy of the scaling. Surprisingly, the Kibble-Zurek critical scaling appears to be equally accurate whether the fixed boundary conditions are chosen to be symmetric or anti-symmetric. Finally, we show that the density of kinks extracted in the central part of long chains obeys the predicted universal scaling for all types of boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20186v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Soto Garcia, Natalia Chepiga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transport coefficients of dense nucleon matter at low temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Transport properties of cold and dense nucleon matter are important for both nuclear and astrophysics but are relatively less studied than those at finite temperatures. In this paper, we present a primary study of bulk and shear viscosities in the limit $T/\mu_B \ll 1$, where $T$ and $\mu_B$ are the temperature and the baryon chemical potential. The analysis is performed for a generic system where nucleons are dressed by the condensation of both scalar and vector interactions. Under the relaxation time approximation of the Boltzmann equation, we compute the viscosities of the system to leading power in $T/\mu_B$ expansion and establish a relation between the thermodynamic potential and transport coefficients, including bulk viscosity ($\zeta$) and shear viscosity ($\eta$). It is found that hydrodynamic stability ($\zeta&gt;0$) imposes additional constraints on the thermodynamic potential. As an example, these relations are applied to the Walecka model. The fluid properties of the cold and dense nucleon matter are characterized by the dimensionless combination of viscosities times the quasi-Fermi momentum over the enthalpy. Furthermore, we discuss the implication of the stability condition on the range of applicability of the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20454v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianing Li, Weiyao Ke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The electronic structure and disorder effect of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7}$ superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20465v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Determining the electronic structure of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ is an essential step towards uncovering their superconducting mechanism. It is widely believed that the bilayer apical oxygens play an important role in the bilayer La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ electronic structure. Applying the hybrid exchange-correlation functionals, we obtain a more accurate electronic structure of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ at its high-pressure phase, where the binding $d_{z^2}$ band is below the Fermi level owing to apical oxygen. The symmetry properties of this electronic structure and its corresponding tight-binding model are further analyzed. We find the antisymmetric part is highly entangled leading to a minimal nearly degenerate two-orbital model. Then, the apical oxygen vacancies effect is studied using the dynamical cluster approximation. This disorder effect strongly destroys the antisymmetric $\beta$ Fermi surface leading to the possible disappearance of superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20465v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxin Wang, Yi Zhang, Kun Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement as a topological marker in harmonically confined attractive Fermi-Hubbard chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the single-site von Neumann entropy along a harmonically confined superfluid chain, as described by the one-dimensional fermionic Hubbard model with strongly attractive interactions. We find that by increasing the confinement (or equivalently the particle filling) the system undergoes a quantum phase transition from a superfluid (SF) to a non-trivial topological insulator (TI) phase, which is characterized by an insulating bulk surrounded by highly entangled superfluid edges. These highly entangled states are found to be robust against perturbations and topologically protected by the particle-hole symmetry, which is locally preserved. We also find a semi-quantitative agreement between entanglement and superconducting order parameter profiles, confirming then that entanglement can be used as a topological marker and an order parameter in these systems. The charge gap not only confirms the SF-TI transition, but also shows that this transition is mediated by a metallic intermediate regime within the bulk. Using the gap we could depict a phase diagram for which the non-trivial topological insulator can be found in such harmonically confined attractive systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20515v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marina Sanino, Isaac Carvalho, Vivian Fran\c{c}a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cascading from $\mathscr{N}=2$ Supersymmetric Yang-Mills Theory to Confinement and Chiral Symmetry Breaking in Adjoint QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20547v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We argue that adjoint QCD in 3+1 dimensions, with any $SU(N)$ gauge group and two Weyl fermion flavors (i.e. one adjoint Dirac fermion), confines and spontaneously breaks its chiral symmetries via the condensation of a fermion bilinear. We flow to this theory from pure $\mathscr{N}=2$ SUSY Yang-Mills theory with the same gauge group, by giving a SUSY-breaking mass $M$ to the scalars in the $\mathscr{N} = 2$ vector multiplet. This flow can be analyzed rigorously at small $M$, where it leads to a deconfined vacuum at the origin of the $\mathscr{N}=2$ Coulomb branch. The analysis can be extended to all $M$ using an Abelian dual description that arises from the $N$ multi-monopole points of the $\mathscr{N} = 2$ theory. At each such point, there are $N-1$ hypermultiplet Higgs fields $h_m^{i = 1, 2}$, which are $SU(2)_R$ doublets. We provide a detailed study of the phase diagram as a function of $M$, by analyzing the semi-classical phases of the dual using a combination of analytic and numerical techniques. The result is a cascade of first-order phase transitions, along which the Higgs fields $h_m^i$ successively turn on, and which interpolates between the Coulomb branch at small $M$, where all $h_m^i = 0$, and a maximal Higgs branch, where all $h_m^i \neq 0$, at sufficiently large $M$. We show that this maximal Higgs branch precisely matches the confining and chiral symmetry breaking phase of two-flavor adjoint QCD, including its broken and unbroken symmetries, its massless spectrum, and the expected large-$N$ scaling of various observables. The spontaneous breaking pattern $SU(2)_R \to U(1)_R$, consistent with the Vafa-Witten theorem, is ensured by an intricate alignment mechanism for the $h_m^i$ in the dual, and leads to a $\mathbb{C}\mathbb{P}^1$ sigma model of increasing radius along the cascade.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20547v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric D'Hoker, Thomas T. Dumitrescu, Efrat Gerchkovitz, Emily Nardoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Smearing of Quasi-Particles: Signatures in the Entanglement Entropy of Excited Many-Particle Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20812v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The entanglement spectrum serves as a powerful tool for probing the structure and dynamics of quantum many-body systems, revealing key information about symmetry, topology, and excitations. While the entanglement entropy (EE) of ground states typically follows an area law, highly excited states obey a volume law, leading to a striking contrast in their scaling behavior. In this paper, we investigate the crossover between these two regimes, focusing on the role of quasi-particles (QPs) in mediating this transition. By analyzing the energy dependence of EE in various many-body systems, we explore how the presence of long-lived QPs influences the entanglement structure of excited states. We present numerical results for spinless fermions, a spin chain near a many-body localization transition, and the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model, which lacks a conventional QP description. Our findings are complemented by a theoretical model based on Fermi liquid theory, providing insight into the interaction-dependent scaling of EE and its consistency with numerical simulations. We find that a hallmark of QPs is a linear dependence of the eigenstate EE on energy, which breaks down at high energy and in the limit of strong interaction. The slope of this linear dependence reflects the QP weight, which reduces with interaction strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20812v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jagannath Sutradhar, Jonathan Ruhman, Avraham Klein, Dimitri Gutman, Richard Berkovits</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-pressure growth effects on the superconducting properties of Sm-based oxypnictide superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20837v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-pressure synthesis can be an effective method for improving the sample quality of materials as well as their superconducting properties. In this paper, the synthesis process of F- doped SmFeAsO has been optimized by preparing a series of bulk SmFeAsO0.8F0.2 (Sm1111) using the high gas pressure and high-temperature synthesis (HP-HTS) method, considering various growth parameters like growth pressures (0-1 GPa) and heating time (0.5-2 h). Structural, microstructural, Raman spectroscopic, transport, and magnetic measurements are employed to comprehensively analyze these bulks and derive the conclusive findings. The parent SmFeAsO0.8F0.2 prepared by the conventional synthesis process at ambient pressure (CSP) has a transition temperature (Tc) of around 53-54 K, and the critical current density (Jc) of 103 A/cm2 at 5 K with a small amount of the impurity phases (SmOF and SmAs), consistent with previous reports. Interestingly, all bulks synthesized by HP-HTS have almost the same Tc and Jc as the parent sample. The optimal growth conditions are obtained as 900C, 1 hour, and 0.5 GPa with the sealed Ta-tube, which slightly improved the sample quality and the superconducting properties compared to other bulks grown by HP-HTS. Our study confirms that the existence of the impurity phases in the 1111 family is very robust and cannot be reduced by HP-HTS, leading to only a small variation in the observed superconducting properties of Sm1111 whether prepared by CSP or HP-HTS. This is the first comprehensive investigation of the high-pressure development of Sm1111, which shows distinct behaviour from other families of iron-based superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20837v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Azam, Manasa Manasa, Tatiana Zajarniuk, Ryszard Diduszko, Taras Palasyuk, Tomasz Cetner, Andrzej Morawski, Cezariusz Jastrz\k{e}bski, Andrzej Szewczyk, Micha{\l} Wierzbicki, Shiv J. Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parametrized topological phases in 1d and T-duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20905v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There are families of physical systems that cannot be adiabatically evolved to the trivial system uniformly across the parameter space, even if each system in the family belongs to the trivial phase. The obstruction is measured by higher Berry class. We analyze families of topological systems in 1+1d using families of invertible TQFTs and families of RG fixed states of spin chains. We use the generalized matrix-product states to describe RG fixed points of all translation invariant pure splits states on spin chains. Families of such fixed points correspond to bundles of Hilbert-Schmidt operators. There exists a global MPS parametrization of the family if and only if the latter bundle is trivial. We propose a novel duality of parametrized topological phases which is an avatar of the T-duality in string theory. The duality relates families with different parameter spaces and different higher Berry classes. Mathematically, the T-duality is realized by gauging the circle action on the continuous trace algebra generated by parametrized matrix-product tensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20905v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Geiko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital-selective electron correlations in high-$T_{\rm c}$ bilayer nickelates: from a global phase diagram to implications for spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21019v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the high temperature superconductivity observed in the bilayer nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ and the spectroscopic evidences of strong electron correlations in this compound, we address the role of its multiorbital electron correlations by proposing a global phase diagram of a bilayer two-orbital Hubbard model. We find a Mott transition developing at half filling, and identify strong orbital selectivity when the system is at the physical electron count. The orbital selectivity is manifested in the formation of interlayer spin singlets between electrons in the $z^2$ orbitals. These features lead to a strong renormalization of the electronic band structure while sustaining a sizable splitting between the bonding and antibonding $z^2$ bands. The proposed orbital-selective correlations naturally explain a series of features as observed in the angular resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and optical conductivity measurements in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$. Our results provide a basis to understand both the normal state and the high temperature superconductivity of multilayer nickelates and thereby elucidate correlated superconductivity in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21019v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiguang Liao, Yiming Wang, Lei Chen, Guijing Duan, Rong Yu, Qimiao Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3d $\mathcal{N}=4$ Mirror Symmetry, TQFTs, and 't Hooft Anomaly Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21066v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Any local unitary 3d $\mathcal{N}=4$ superconformal field theory (SCFT) has a corresponding "universal" relevant deformation that takes it to a gapped phase. This deformation preserves all continuous internal symmetries, $\mathcal{S}$, and therefore also preserves any 't Hooft anomalies supported purely in $\mathcal{S}$. We describe the resulting phase diagram in the case of SCFTs that arise as the endpoints of renormalization group flows from 3d $\mathcal{N}=4$ Abelian gauge theories with any number of $U(1)$ gauge group factors and arbitrary integer charges for the matter fields. We argue that the universal deformations take these QFTs to Abelian fractional quantum Hall states in the infrared (IR), and we explain how to match 't Hooft anomalies between the non-topological ultraviolet theories and the IR topological quantum field theories (TQFTs). Along the way, we give a proof that 3d $\mathcal{N}=4$ mirror symmetry of our Abelian gauge theories descends to a duality of these TQFTs. Finally, using our anomaly matching discussion, we describe how to connect, via the renormalization group, abstract local unitary 3d $\mathcal{N}=4$ SCFTs with certain 't Hooft anomalies for their internal symmetries to IR phases (partially) described by Abelian spin Chern-Simons theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21066v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahesh K. N. Balasubramanian, Anindya Banerjee, Matthew Buican, Zhihao Duan, Andrea E. V. Ferrari, Hongliang Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure-tunable structural instabilities in single-layer-trilayer La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21150v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Layered nickelates are believed to exhibit superconductivity similar
  to that found in the cuprates. However, the precise crystal
  structure of the superconducting phase of the layered nickelates has
  not been fully clarified. Here, I use first principles calculations
  to study the pressure dependence of the structural instabilities in
  the single-layer-trilayer La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$, which is one member of
  the layered nickelates family that also shows signatures of
  superconductivity. I find a nearly dispersionless nondegenerate
  phonon branch in the parent $P4/mmm$ phase that is unstable along
  the Brillouin zone edge $M$ $(\frac{1}{2}, \frac{1}{2}, 0)$
  $\rightarrow$ $A$ $(\frac{1}{2},\frac{1}{2},\frac{1}{2})$ at all
  investigated pressures up to 30 GPa. Calculations show additional
  doubly-degenerate instabilities along the edge $MA$ at lower
  pressures. I used group-theoretical analysis to identify the
  distinct low-symmetry distortions possible due to these
  instabilities and generated them using the eigenvectors of the
  unstable modes. Structural relaxations show that the lowest energy
  structures at 0 and 10 GPa involve condensation of both the
  nondegenerate and doubly-degenerate instabilities, which is in
  contrast to the experimental refinements that involve condensation
  of only the doubly-degenerate branch. I also find that
  structural distortions are energetically favorable at 20 GPa,
  contrary to the experiments that do not observe any distortions of
  the parent $P4/mmm$ structure at high pressures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21150v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alaska Subedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle-Soliton Degeneracy in 2D Quantum Chromodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21153v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum chromodynamics in two spacetime dimensions admits a finite non-invertible symmetry described mathematically by a fusion category. This symmetry is spontaneously broken at long distances, leading to distinct vacua. When the theory has a mass gap, the spectrum is therefore characterized by particle excitations above a single vacuum and soliton sectors interpolating between vacua. We use anyon condensation and the representation theory of fusion categories to obtain exact results about this spectrum, exhibiting the allowed multiplets. Often, particles and solitons are in the same representation and therefore must have equal masses. Furthermore, the fusion category symmetry frequently implies the existence of certain stable states in the spectrum. The resulting degeneracies are encoded in quiver diagrams where nodes are vacua and arrows are excited states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21153v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clay Cordova, Diego Garc\'ia-Sep\'ulveda, Nicholas Holfester</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Future of the Correlated Electron Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.00584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2010.00584v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A central problem in modern condensed matter physics is the understanding of materials with strong electron correlations. Despite extensive work, the essential physics of many of these systems is not understood and there is very little ability to make predictions in this class of materials. In this manuscript we share our personal views on the major open problems in the field of correlated electron systems. We discuss some possible routes to make progress in this rich and fascinating field. This manuscript is the result of the vigorous discussions and deliberations that took place at Johns Hopkins University during a three-day workshop January 27, 28, and 29, 2020 that brought together six senior scientists and 46 more junior scientists. Our hope, is that the topics we have presented will provide inspiration for others working in this field and motivation for the idea that significant progress can be made on very hard problems if we focus our collective energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2010.00584v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Alexandradinata, N. P. Armitage, Andrey Baydin, Wenli Bi, Yue Cao, Hitesh J. Changlani, Eli Chertkov, Eduardo H. da Silva Neto, Luca Delacretaz, Ismail El Baggari, G. M. Ferguson, William J. Gannon, Sayed Ali Akbar Ghorashi, Berit H. Goodge, Olga Goulko, G. Grissonnanche, Alannah Hallas, Ian M. Hayes, Yu He, Edwin W. Huang, Anshul Kogar, Divine Kumah, Jong Yeon Lee, A. Legros, Fahad Mahmood, Yulia Maximenko, Nick Pellatz, Hryhoriy Polshyn, Tarapada Sarkar, Allen Scheie, Kyle L. Seyler, Zhenzhong Shi, Brian Skinner, Lucia Steinke, K. Thirunavukkuarasu, Tha\'is Victa Trevisan, Michael Vogl, Pavel A. Volkov, Yao Wang, Yishu Wang, Di Wei, Kaya Wei, Shuolong Yang, Xian Zhang, Ya-Hui Zhang, Liuyan Zhao, Alfred Zong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Thermalization: from Fermi Liquid to Incoherent Metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.15666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.15666v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When a system consists of a large subsystem (bath) and a small one (probe), thermalization implies induction of temperature of the bath onto the probe. If both the bath and the probe are described by same microscopic Hamiltonian, thermalization further entails that the probe imbibes the phase of the bath. We refer to this phenomenon as {\it phase thermalization}. However, it is not clear whether this phenomenon is realizable when the probe and the bath are described by different microscopic Hamiltonians. We show {\it phase thermalization} is possible even when the microscopic Hamiltonians differ significantly. We provide an explicit example, where the probe is a Fermi liquid realized by a Majorana chain with $n \gg 1$ fermions per site interacting through random hopping and the bath is an incoherent metal described by another Majorana chain with $N &gt; n$ fermions per site interacting through arbitrarily long range random four-fermion interaction. In deep infrared (\emph{i.e.} at very low energies), the probe turns into an incoherent metal, with Lyapunov spectrum and diffusion coefficient identical to the bath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.15666v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10773-024-05845-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int J Theor Phys 64, 1 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pinaki Banerjee, Bidisha Chakrabarty, Swapnamay Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Wigner-Mott transition at $\nu=1/5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.13355v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electrons can organize themselves into charge-ordered states to minimize the effects of long-ranged Coulomb interactions. In the presence of a lattice, commensurability constraints lead to the emergence of incompressible Wigner-Mott insulators at various rational electron fillings, $\nu~=p/q$. The mechanism for quantum fluctuation-mediated melting of the Mott insulators with increasing electron kinetic energy remains an outstanding problem. Here, using matrix product state techniques, we analyze the bandwidth-tuned transition out of the Wigner-Mott insulator at $\nu=1/5$ in an extended Hubbard model on infinite cylinders of varying circumference. For the two-leg ladder, the transition from the Mott insulator to the Luttinger liquid proceeds via a distinct intermediate phase with gapless Cooper-pairs and gapped electronic excitations. The resulting Luther-Emery liquid is the analog of a strongly fluctuating superconductor. We place these results in the context of a low-energy bosonization based theory for the transition. On the five-leg cylinder, we provide numerical evidence for a direct continuous transition between the Wigner-Mott insulator and a metallic phase across which the spin and charge-gaps vanish simultaneously. We comment on the connections to ongoing experiments in dual-gated bilayer moir\'e transition metal dichalcogenide materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.13355v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.L241112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, L241112 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas G. Kiely, Debanjan Chowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat bands and superconductivity induced by periodic strain in monolayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.02824v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superconductivity in single-layer graphene has attracted considerable interest. Here, using the determinant quantum Monte Carlo method, we study transitions of superconductivity and magnetism in a monolayer graphene with a special periodic strain. Consistent with experiments, the deformation accumulates a series of flat bands, whose robustness under interaction is verified through electron localization in real space. During the reconstruction of the band structure, the superconductivity appears in flat band range with next-nearest neighbor $d+id$ pairing symmetry dominating other modes and is accompanied by ferromagnetism caused by symmetry breaking. We also demonstrate that the strain-induced symmetry breaking would accumulate an energy-gap antiferromagnetic insulating phase at half filling even under the limitation of not strong enough interaction, which shows its potential as a platform that exhibits strongly correlated phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.02824v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.235128</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 235128(2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jingyao Meng, Runyu Ma, Tianxing Ma, Hai-Qing Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopic origin of giant anomalous Hall effect in an interwoven magnetic kagome metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16831v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of a giant anomalous Hall effect (AHE) and its novel mechanism holds significant promise for advancing both fundamental research and practical applications. Magnetic kagome lattice materials are uniquely suited for studying the AHE due to their interplay between electronic structure, topology, and magnetism. However, the geometric frustration inherent in kagome lattices often limits the configuration and tunability of magnetic order. Here, we present a new design strategy for kagome-lattice materials with emergent magnetism, exemplified by the magnetic kagome metal TbTi$_3$Bi$_4$, which features interwoven magnetic Tb zigzag chains and non-magnetic Ti kagome bilayers. This material exhibits a record-high anomalous Hall conductivity (AHC) of 10$^5$ $\Omega^{-1}$ cm$^{-1}$. Spectroscopy measurements reveal a large band folding gap observed via angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, coexisting spin-density-wave (SDW) order detected through spin-polarized scanning tunneling spectroscopy, and a spiral magnetic order with large magnetic moments identified by neutron diffraction. These findings highlight a strong electron-magnetic coupling between itinerant charges and ordered magnetic moments, offering a spectroscopic explanation for the giant AHC in TbTi$_3$Bi$_4$. This work establishes a pathway for innovative material design strategies, unlocking new possibilities for future exploration and applications in quantum and spintronic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16831v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erjian Cheng, Kaipu Wang, Yiqing Hao, Wenqing Chen, Hengxin Tan, Zongkai Li, Meixiao Wang, Wenli Gao, Di Wu, Shuaishuai Sun, Tianping Ying, Simin Nie, Yiwei Li, Walter Schnelle, Houke Chen, Xingjiang Zhou, Ralf Koban, Yulin Chen, Binghai Yan, Yi-feng Yang, Weida Wu, Zhongkai Liu, Claudia Felser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersolid Phase in the Diluted Holstein Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02239v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Holstein model on a square lattice at half-filling has a well-established finite temperature phase transition to an insulating state with long range charge density wave (CDW) order. Because this CDW formation suppresses pairing, a superconducting (SC) phase emerges only with doping. In this work, we study the effects of dilution of the local phonon degrees of freedom in the Holstein model while keeping the system at half filling. We find not only that the CDW remains present up to a dilution fraction $f \sim 0.15$, but also that long range pairing is stabilized with increasing $f$, resulting in a {\it supersolid} regime centered at $f \approx 0.10$, where long range diagonal and off-diagonal correlations coexist. Further dilution results in a purely SC phase, and ultimately in a normal metal. Our results provide a new route to the supersolid phase via the introduction of impurities at fixed positions which both increase quantum fluctuations and also are immune to the competing tendency to phase separation often observed in the doped case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02239v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.L220506</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110,L220506(2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jingyao Meng, Yuxi Zhang, Rafael M. Fernandes, Tianxing Ma, R. T. Scalettar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic, thermodynamic, and dynamical properties of the three-dimensional fermionic Hubbard model: A comprehensive Monte Carlo study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08603v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay between quantum and thermal fluctuations can induce rich phenomena at finite temperatures in strongly correlated fermion systems. Here we report a {\it numerically exact} auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo (AFQMC) study for the finite-temperature properties of three-dimensional repulsive Hubbard model at half filling. We concentrate on the complete temperature-interaction strength phase diagram of the model, which contains the low-temperature antiferromagnetic (AFM) long-range ordered phase and metal-insulator crossover (MIC) in the paramagnetic phase. Enabling access to unprecedented system sizes up to $20^3$, we achieve highly accurate results of the N\'{e}el transition temperature for representative values of on-site interaction $U$ via finite-size analysis of AFM structure factor. To quantitatively characterize the MIC above the N\'{e}el transition, we have developed fully new techniques allowing to compute the thermal entropy versus $U$ at fixed temperature and to directly calculate the $U$-derivative of double occupancy in AFQMC simulations. Then combining variously thermodynamic and dynamical observables, we establish an efficient scheme to precisely determine the boundaries for the MIC by cross-checking different observables. We also demonstrate the temperature dependence of many commonly used observables. Away from half filling, we explore the behavior of the sign problem and AFM spin correlation versus hole doping, and demonstrate the persistance of N\'{e}el AFM ordered phase to finite doping with limited results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08603v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Feng Song, Youjin Deng, Yuan-Yao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermopower across Fermi-volume-changing quantum phase transitions without symmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15330v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We describe the evolution of low-temperature thermopower across Fermi-volume-changing quantum phase transitions in Kondo lattice models without symmetry breaking. This transition moves from a heavy Fermi liquid with a conventional Luttinger-volume large Fermi surface to a 'FL*' state, characterized by a small Fermi surface and a spin liquid with fractionalized excitations. The onset of the large Fermi surface phase is driven by the condensation of a Higgs field that carries a unit gauge charge under an emergent U(1) gauge field. We consider the case with spatially random Kondo exchange, as this leads to strange metal behavior in electrical transport. We find a large asymmetric thermopower. Our findings are consistent with recent observations in heavy fermion compounds (Z.-Y. Cao et al., arXiv:2408.13604), and describe an enhancement of thermopower on the large Fermi surface side as well as a non-monotonic behavior on the small Fermi surface side.
  Our results also apply to single-band Hubbard models and the pseudogap transition in the cuprates. In the ancilla framework, single-band models exhibit an inverted Kondo lattice transition: the small Fermi surface pseudogap state corresponds to the condensed Higgs state. This inversion results in an enhancement of thermopower on the pseudogap side in our theory, consistent with observations in the cuprates (C. Collignon et al., Phys. Rev. B 103, 155102 (2021), arXiv:2011.14927; A. Gourgout et al., Phys. Rev. X 12, 011037 (2022), arXiv:2106.05959). We argue that these observations support a non-symmetry-breaking Fermi-volume-changing transition as the underlying description of the onset of the pseudogap in the cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15330v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Lunts, Aavishkar Patel, Subir Sachdev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel magnetic Ni-N-Ni centers in N-substituted NiO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19250v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following the concept of creating individual centers, we investigate local electronic states and magnetic ordering in nickel oxide (NiO) induced by substituting oxygen (O) with nitrogen (N). Each N introduces an additional N 2p hole and alters the state of the magnetic moment at a neighboring nickel (Ni) cation site, as the exchange interaction between this hole and the Ni eg electrons dominates the superexchange interaction. This leads to the formation of Ni-N-Ni units consisting of five spins that are decoupled from the rest of the antiferromagnetic (AFM) NiO lattice and exhibit degenerate spin states. These centers are studied using density functional theory and confirmed through high-resolution spectroscopy measurements on N-substituted NiO thin films grown by molecular beam epitaxy. This type of magnetic design could potentially advance quantum technologies based on strongly correlated materials, such as quantum sensors and spin-qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19250v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Godin, Ilya S. Elfimov, Fengmiao Li, Bruce A. Davidson, Ronny Sutarto, Jonathan D. Denlinger, Liu Hao Tjeng, George A. Sawatzky, Ke Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge field fluctuation corrected QED3 effective action by fermionic particle-vortex duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06916v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a non-perturbative framework for incorporating gauge field fluctuations into effective actions of QED3 in the infrared using fermionic particle-vortex duality. This approach is demonstrated through the applications to models containing N species of 2-component Dirac fermions in solvable and interpretable electromagnetic backgrounds, focusing on N = 1 or 2. For the N = 1 model, we establish a correspondence between fermion Casimir energy at finite density and the magnetic Euler-Heisenberg Lagrangian, and further evaluate the corrections to their amplitudes. This predicts amplification of charge susceptibility and reduction of magnetic permeability. We additionally provide physical interpretations for each component of our calculation and offer alternative derivations based on energy density measurements in different characteristic lengths. For N = 2, we show that magnetic catalysis is erased in a U(1)xU(1) QED3, indicating no breakdown of chiral symmetry. Reasoning is offered based on the properties of the lowest Landau level wave functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06916v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP05(2024)134</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2024, 134 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Han Hsiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Typical entanglement entropy in systems with particle-number conservation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.19862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.19862v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We calculate the typical bipartite entanglement entropy $\langle S_A\rangle_N$ in systems containing indistinguishable particles of any kind as a function of the total particle number $N$, the volume $V$, and the subsystem fraction $f=V_A/V$, where $V_A$ is the volume of the subsystem. We expand our result as a power series $\langle S_A\rangle_N=a f V+b\sqrt{V}+c+o(1)$, and find that $c$ is universal (i.e., independent of the system type), while $a$ and $b$ can be obtained from a generating function characterizing the local Hilbert space dimension. We illustrate the generality of our findings by studying a wide range of different systems, e.g., bosons, fermions, spins, and mixtures thereof. We provide evidence that our analytical results describe the entanglement entropy of highly excited eigenstates of quantum-chaotic spin and boson systems, which is distinct from that of integrable counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.19862v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.235154</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 235154 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yale Yauk, Rohit Patil, Yicheng Zhang, Marcos Rigol, Lucas Hackl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Switch Driven by the Hidden Half-Ice, Half-Fire State in a Ferrimagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00948v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The notion of "half fire, half ice" was recently introduced to describe an exotic macroscopic ground-state degeneracy emerging in a ferrimagnet under the critical magnetic field, in which the "hot" spins are fully disordered on the sublattice with smaller magnetic moments and the "cold" spins are fully ordered on the sublattice with larger magnetic moments. Here we further point out that this state has a twin named "half ice, half fire" in which the hot and cold spins switch positions. The new state is an excited state -- thus hidden in the ground-state phase diagram -- and is robust with respect to the interactions that destroy the half fire, half ice state. We demonstrate with exact results how this hidden state can drive phase switching at desirable finite temperature, even for the one-dimensional Ising model where phase transition at finite temperature is forbidden. We suggest that our findings may open a new door to the understanding and controlling of phase competition and transition in unconventional frustrated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00948v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.266701</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 266701 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Weiguo Yin, A. M. Tsvelik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement dynamics in 2d HCFTs on the curved background: the case of q-M\"obius Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06594v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We will explore the dynamical property of non-equilibrium phenomena induced by two-dimensional holographic conformal field theory (2d holographic CFT) Hamiltonian on the curved spacetime by studying the time dependence of the entanglement entropy and mutual information. Here, holographic CFT is the CFT having the gravity dual. We will start from the boundary and thermofield double states, evolve the systems in Euclidean time with the Hamiltonian on the curved background, and then evolve them in real-time with the same Hamiltonian. We found that the early- and late-time entanglement structure depends on the curved background, while the entanglement growth does not, and is linear. Furthermore, in the gravity dual for the thermofield double state, this entanglement growth is due to the linear growth of the wormhole, while in the one for the boundary state, it is due to the in-falling of the end of the world brane to the black hole. We discussed the low temperature system can be regarded as the dynamical system induced by the multi-joining quenches. We also discussed the effective description of the high temperature system, called line tension picture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06594v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP12(2024)208</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chen Bai, Akihiro Miyata, Masahiro Nozaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective field theory of the quantum skyrmion Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19565v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by phenomenology of myriad recently-identified topologically non-trivial phases of matter, we introduce effective field theories (EFTs) for the quantum skyrmion Hall effect (QSkHE). We employ a single, unifying generalisation for this purpose: in essence, a lowest Landau level projection defining a non-commutative, fuzzy sphere with position coordinates proportional to SU(2) generators of matrix representation size $N\times N$, may host an intrinsically 2+1 dimensional, topologically non-trivial many-body state for small $N$ as well as large $N$. That is, isospin degrees of freedom associated with a matrix Lie algebra with $N \times N$ generators potentially encode some finite number of spatial dimensions for $N\ge 2$, a regime in which isospin has previously been treated as a label. This statement extends to more general $p$-branes subjected to severe fuzzification as well as membranes. As a consequence of this generalisation, systems with $d$ Cartesian spatial coordinates and isospin degrees of freedom encoding an additional $\delta$ fuzzy coset space coordinates can realise topologically non-trivial states of intrinsic dimensionality up to $d$+$\delta$+1. We therefore identify gauge theories with extra fuzzy dimensions generalised to retain dependence upon gauge fields over fuzzy coset spaces even for severe fuzzification (small $N$), as EFTs for the QSkHE. We furthermore generalise these EFTs to space manifolds with local product structure exploiting the dimensional hierarchy of (fuzzy) spheres. For this purpose, we introduce methods of anisotropic fuzzification and propose formulating topological invariants on fuzzy coset spaces as artifacts of projecting matrix Lie algebras to occupied subspaces. Importantly, we focus on phenomenology indicating the 2+1 D SU(2) gauge theory should be generalised using this machinery, and serves as a minimal EFT of the QSkHE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19565v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinay Patil, Rafael Flores-Calder\'on, Ashley M. Cook</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicative Chern insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19566v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study multiplicative Chern insulators (MCIs) as canonical examples of multiplicative topological phases of matter. Constructing the MCI Bloch Hamiltonian as a symmetry-protected tensor product of two topologically non-trivial parent Chern insulators (CIs), we study two-dimensional (2D) MCIs and introduce 3D mixed MCIs, constructed by requiring the two 2D parent Hamiltonians share only one momentum component. We study the 2D MCI response to time reversal symmetric flux insertion, observing a $4\pi$ Aharonov-Bohm effect, relating these topological states to fractional quantum Hall states via the effective field theory of the quantum skyrmion Hall effect. As part of this response, we observe evidence of quantisation of a proposed topological invariant for compactified many-body states, to a rational number, suggesting higher-dimensional topology may also be relevant. Finally, we study effects of bulk perturbations breaking the symmetry-protected tensor product structure of the child Hamiltonian, finding the MCI evolves adiabatically into a topological skyrmion phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19566v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Archi Banerjee, Micha{\l} J. Pacholski, Ashley M. Cook</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of the quantum skyrmion Hall effect in the Bernevig-Hughes-Zhang model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19568v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given recent discovery of the quantum skyrmion Hall effect, we re-examine the related canonical Bernevig-Hughes-Zhang (BHZ) model for the quantum spin Hall insulator. Within the framework of the quantum skyrmion Hall effect, isospin degree(s) of freedom of the BHZ model encode additional spatial dimensions. Consistent with this framework, we observe phenomena similar to those of the four dimensional Chern insulator, revealed by weakly breaking time-reversal symmetry. Bulk-boundary correspondence of these states includes real-space boundary orbital angular momentum textures and gapless boundary modes that are robust against magnetic disorder, consistent with compactified three dimensional boundary Weyl nodes (WN$_F$s) of the quantum skyrmion Hall effect. These theoretical findings are furthermore consistent with past experimental work reporting unexpected edge conduction in HgTe quantum wells under applied Zeeman and orbital magnetic fields. This past work is therefore potentially the first known experimental observation of signatures of the quantum skyrmion Hall effect beyond the quantum Hall effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19568v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reyhan Ay, Adipta Pal, Ashley M. Cook</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
