<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 04:00:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Three fold Spin valley intertwined Dirac cone in nonmagnetic Weyl Semimetal Pt$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ with the Kagome lattice A theoretical DFT perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experimental and theoretical research in Pt$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ have opened avenues for restoring Dirac dispersion in layered materials. Inspired by this we conducted first-principles DFT calculations unveiling a novel nonmagnetic metal Pt$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ with a robust Dirac dispersion. Under strong SOC and high pressure the Fermi surface topology shifts yielding spin valley intertwined Dirac cones and three fold charge density waves due to inversion symmetry breaking. Thermal conductivity and Seebeck coefficient exhibit an inverse relationship with temperature due to increased phonon collisions attributed to anharmonic phonon phonon interactions via Umklapp processes. Ab initio molecular dynamics and phonon dispersion calculations confirm the dynamic and thermal stability of Pt$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ illuminating the origin of its Dirac cone and electronic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12254v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravi Trivedi, Seetha Lakshmy, Heera T. Nair, Alok Shukla, Brahmananda Chakraborty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Majorana metal from a chiral spin liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12278v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel mechanism to explain the emergence of an intermediate gapless spin liquid phase (IGP) in the antiferromagnetic Kitaev model in an externally applied magnetic field, sandwiched between the well-known gapped chiral spin liquid (CSL) and the gapped partially polarized (PP) phase. We propose in moderate fields $\pi$-fluxes nucleate in the ground state and can trap Majorana zero modes. As these fluxes proliferate with increasing field, the Majorana zero modes overlap creating an emergent Majorana metallic state with a `Fermi surface' at zero energy. We further show that the Majorana spectral function captures the dynamical spin and dimer correlations obtained by the infinite Projected Entangled Pair States (iPEPS) ansatz. We discuss the implications of our results for candidate Kitaev materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12278v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Penghao Zhu, Shi Feng, Kang Wang, Tao Xiang, Nandini Trivedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing fractional Chern insulators via exchange interaction in moir\'e systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12294v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experimental discovery of fractional Chern insulator in moir\'e Chern band in twisted transition metal dichalocogenide homobilayers has sparked intensive interest in exploring the ways of engineering band topology and correlated states in moir\'e systems. In this letter, we demonstrate that, with an additional exchange interaction induced by proximity effect, the topology and bandwidth of the moir\'e minibands of twisted $\mathrm{MoTe_2}$ homobilayers can be easily tuned. Fractional Chern insulators at -2/3 filling are found to appear at enlarged twist angles over a large range of twist angles with enhanced many-body gaps. We further discover a topological phase transition between the fractional Chern insulator, quantum anomalous Hall crystal, and charge density wave. Our results shed light on the interplay between topology and correlation physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12294v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyang Shen, Chonghao Wang, Ruiping Guo, Zhiming Xu, Wenhui Duan, Yong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification of soft modes across the commensurate-to-incommensurate charge density wave transition in 1$T$-TaSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: 1$T$-TaSe$_2$ is a prototypical charge density wave (CDW) material for which electron-phonon coupling and associated lattice distortion play an important role in driving and stabilizing the CDW phase. Here, we investigate the lattice dynamics of bulk 1$T$-TaSe$_2$ using angle-resolved ultralow wavenumber Raman spectroscopy down to 10 cm$^{-1}$. Our high-resolution spectra allow us to identify at least 27 Raman-active modes in the commensurate (CCDW) phase. Contrary to other layered materials, we do not find evidence of interlayer breathing or shear modes, suggestive of $AA$ stacking in the bulk, or sufficiently weak interlayer coupling. Polarization dependence of the mode intensities allows the assignment of their symmetry, which is supported by first-principles calculations of the phonons for the bulk structure using density functional theory. A detailed temperature dependence in the range $T$ = 80 - 500 K allows us to identify soft modes associated with the CDW superlattice. Upon entering the incommensurate (ICCDW) phase above 473 K, we observe a dramatic loss of resolution of all modes, and significant linewidth broadening associated with a reduced phonon lifetime as the charge-order becomes incommensurate with the lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Ruggeri, D. Wolverson, V. Romano, G. Cerullo, C. J. Sayers, G. D'Angelo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of unprecedented fractional magnetization plateaus in a new Shastry-Sutherland Ising compound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Geometrically frustrated magnetic systems, such as those based on the Shastry-Sutherland lattice, offer a rich playground for exploring unconventional magnetic states. The delicate balance between competing interactions in these systems leads to the emergence of novel phases. We present the characterization of Er2Be2GeO7, an SSL compound with Er3+ ions forming orthogonal dimers separated by non-magnetic layers. Neutron scattering reveals an antiferromagnetic dimer structure at zero field, typical of Ising spins on that lattice and consistent with the anisotropic magnetization observed. However, magnetization measurements exhibit fractional plateaus at 1/4 and 1/2 of saturation, by contrast to the expected 1/3 plateau of the SSL Ising model. We show that this behaviour requires spatially anisotropic interactions, and, using a tensor network approach, we show that all properties, including thermodynamics, can be quantitatively explained by an Anisotropic Shastry-Sutherland Ising Model whose microscopic origin can be traced back to Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions. This study highlights Er2Be2GeO7 as a promising platform for investigating exotic magnetic phenomena and potential applications in spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12405v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lalit Yadav, Afonso Rufino, Rabindranath Bag, Clarina dela Cruz, Alexander I. Kolesnikov, V. Ovidiu Garlea, David Graf, Frederic Mila, Sara Haravifard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Giant Anomalous Hall in a Kondo Lattice Ferromagnet UBiTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kondo lattice systems are recognized for potentially hosting a variety of rich topological phases. Several pioneering studies have demonstrated significant anomalous Hall and anomalous Nernst effects in these systems, attributed to the Berry curvature of the hybridization bands. In this study, we investigate UBiTe, a ferromagnetic Kondo lattice system. Our findings reveal that the intrinsic contribution to the anomalous Hall conductivity is closely tied to the Kondo coherence temperature. Moreover, we demonstrate that slight shifts in the Fermi level across three different samples significantly influence this intrinsic contribution, in alignment with the Berry curvature localized within the narrow hybridization bands. This provides a stark contrast to the less pronounced sensitivity observed in weakly correlated Weyl semimetals, underscoring the distinctive electronic properties of Kondo lattice systems. The anomalous Hall conductivity of one samples ranks among the highest reported for topological magnetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12471v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiaozhi Xu, Hasan Siddiquee, Shannon Gould, Jiahui Althena Zhu, David Alonso Martinez, Christopher Broyles, Tai Kong, Sheng Ran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-polarized p-wave superconductivity in the kagome material RbV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of kagome materials has attracted much attention in the past few years due to the presence of many electron-electron interaction-driven phases in a single material.In this work, we report the discovery of intrinsic spin-polarized p-wave superconductivity in the thin-flake kagome material RbV$_3$Sb$_5$. Firstly, when an in-plane magnetic field is swept in opposite directions, we observe a unique form of hysteresis in magnetoresistance which is different from the hysteresis induced by extrinsic mechanisms such as flux-trapping or superheating and supercooling effects. The unconventional hysteresis indicates the emergence of an intrinsic time-reversal symmetry-breaking superconducting phase. Strikingly, at a fixed magnetic field, the finite-resistance state can be quenched to the zero-resistance state by applying a large current. Secondly, at temperatures around 400 mK, the re-entrance of superconductivity occurs during an in-plane field-sweeping process with a fixed sweeping direction. This kind of re-entrance is asymmetric about the zero field axis and observed in all field directions for a fixed current direction, which is different from the re-entrance observed in conventional superconductors. Moreover, the angle-dependent in-plane critical field measurements reveal a two-fold symmetry that deviates from the original, centrosymmetric D$_{6h}$ point group symmetry of the crystal. These findings put very strong constraints on the possible superconducting pairing symmetry of RbV$_3$Sb$_5$. We point out that the pairing symmetry, which is consistent with the crystal symmetry and all the observed novel properties, is a time-reversal symmetry-breaking, p-wave pairing with net spin polarization. Importantly, this p-wave pairing gives rise to a nodal topological superconducting state with Majorana flat bands on the sample edges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12592v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Wang, Xilin Feng, Jing-Zhi Fang, Jia-Peng Peng, Zi-Ting Sun, Jia-Jie Yang, Jingchao Liu, Jia-Ji Zhao, Jian-Kun Wang, Xin-Jie Liu, Ze-Nan Wu, Shengbiao Sun, Ning Kang, Xiao-Song Wu, Zhensheng Zhang, Xuewen Fu, Kam Tuen Law, Ben-Chuan Lin, Dapeng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase diagram of the antiferromagnetic $J_1$-$J_2$ spin-$1$ pyrochlore Heisenberg model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the phase diagram of the antiferromagnetic $J_1$-$J_2$ Heisenberg model on the pyrochlore lattice with $S=1$ spins at zero and finite temperatures. We use a combination of complementary state-of-the-art quantum many-body approaches such as density matrix renormalization group (DMRG), density-matrix purification and pseudo-Majorana functional renormalization group (PMFRG). We present an efficient approach to preserve the applicability of the PMFRG for spin-1 systems at finite temperatures despite the inevitable presence of unphysical spin states. The good performance of our methods is first demonstrated for the nearest-neighbor pyrochlore Heisenberg model where the finite temperature behavior of the specific heat and uniform susceptibility show excellent agreement within PMFRG and density-matrix purification. Including an antiferromagnetic second neighbor coupling we find that the non-magnetic ground-state phase of the nearest neighbor model extents up to $J_2/J_1 \sim 0.02 $ within DMRG, beyond which magnetic $\boldsymbol{k}=0$ long-range order sets in. Our PMFRG calculations find the phase transition in a similar regime $J_2/J_1\sim 0.035(8)$ which, together with the DMRG result, provides a strong argument for the existence of a small but finite non-magnetic ground-state phase in the spin-1 pyrochlore Heisenberg model. We also discuss the origin of discrepancies between different versions of the functional renormalization group concerning the location of this phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12745v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imre Hagym\'asi, Nils Niggemann, Johannes Reuther</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ubiquity of the spin-orbit induced magnon nonreciprocity in ultrathin ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12854v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The propagation of magnons along a symmetry path may depend on the direction of propagation, similar to many other quasiparticles in nature. This phenomenon is commonly referred to as nonreciprocity. In addition to the fact that it is of great interest to understand the fundamental physical mechanism leading to this nonreciprocal propagation, the phenomenon of magnon nonreciprocity may be used to design magnon-based logic devices. Recently, it has been demonstrated that a significantly large spin-orbit coupling can lead to giant nonreciprocity of exchange-dominated terahertz magnons, when they are excited by means of spin-polarized electrons [Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 126702 (2024)]. Here, by providing experimental results on two additional systems we demonstrate the generality of the observed phenomenon. Comparing the results of a Co/Ni bilayer on Ir(001) to those of a Co double layer on Ir(001) and W(110) we unravel the impact of the interfacial electronic hybridization on the observed phenomenon and provide further insights into the microscopic mechanism leading to this nonreciprocal magnon excitation. It was observed that the interfacial electronic hybridization, which is governing the magnetic properties of the interface atomic layer, is somewhat important but is not crucial for the magnon nonreciprocity. On the other hand the choice of the incident energy of the incoming electron beam is decisive for the observation of the effect. Our results indicate that depending on the energy of the incident electron beam and the scattering geometry the magnon nonreciprocity can be tuned and even be inverted for some ranges of the magnon momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12854v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albrecht von Faber, Christopher Hins, Khalil Zakeri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reentrant multiple-$\mathbf{q}$ magnetic order and a "spin-cholesteric" phase in Sr$_3$Fe$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin-nematic and spin-smectic phases have been reported in magnetic materials, which break rotational symmetry while preserving translational symmetry along certain directions. However, until now the analogy to liquid crystals remained incomplete because no magnetic analog of cholesteric order was known. Here we show that the bilayer perovskite Sr$_3$Fe$_2$O$_7$, previously believed to adopt a simple single-$\mathbf{q}$ spin-helical order, hosts two distinct types of multi-$\mathbf{q}$ spin textures and the first "spin-cholesteric". Its ground state represents a novel multi-$\mathbf{q}$ spin texture with unequally intense spin modulations at the two ordering vectors. This is followed in temperature by the new "spin-cholesteric" phase with spontaneously broken chiral symmetry, in which the translational symmetry is broken only along one of the crystal directions while the weaker orthogonal modulation melts, giving rise to intense short-range dynamical fluctuations. Shortly before the transition to the paramagnetic state, vortex-crystal order spanned by two equivalent $\mathbf{q}$ vectors emerges. The "spin-cholesteric" phase completes the spin analogy with liquid crystals and renders Sr$_3$Fe$_2$O$_7$ a touchstone for studying transitions among multiple-$\mathbf{q}$ spin textures in a centrosymmetric host.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12889v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. D. Andriushin, J. Muller, N. S. Pavlovskii, J. Grumbach, S. Granovsky, Y. V. Tymoshenko, O. Zaharko, A. Ivanov, J. Ollivier, M. Doerr, B. Keimer, M. Mostovoy, D. S. Inosov, D. C. Peets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A single crystal study of Kagome metals U$_2$Mn$_3$Ge and U$_2$Fe$_3$Ge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single crystals of U$_2$Mn$_3$Ge and and U$_2$Fe$_3$Ge with a Kagome lattice structure were synthesized using a high-temperature self-flux crystal growth method. The physical properties of these crystals were characterized through measurements of resistivity, magnetism, and specific heat. U$_2$Fe$_3$Ge exhibits ferromagnetic ground state and Anomalous Hall Effect, and U$_2$Mn$_3$Ge demonstrates a complex magnetic structure. Both compounds exhibit large Sommerfeld coefficient, indicating coexistence of heavy Fermion behavior with magnetism. Our results suggest that this U$_2$TM$_3$Ge (TM = Mn, Fe, Co) family is a promising platform to investigate the interplay of magnetism, Kondo physics and the Kagome lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12905v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanyue Lin, Yuchen Wu, Christopher Broyles, Tai Kong, Sheng Ran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out-of-time-order correlators in electronic structure using Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12289v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Operator spreading has profound implications in diverse fields ranging from statistical mechanics and blackhole physics to quantum information. The usual way to quantify it is through out-of-time-order correlators (OTOCs), which are the quantum analog to Lyapunov exponents in classical chaotic dynamics. In this work we explore the phenomenon of operator spreading in quantum simulation of electronic structure in quantum computers. To substantiate our results, we focus on a hydrogen chain $H_4$ and demonstrate that operator spreading is enhanced when the chain is far from its equilibrium geometry. We also investigate the dynamics of bipartite entanglement and its dependence on the partition's size. Our findings reveal distinctive signatures closely resembling area- and volume-laws in equilibrium and far-from-equilibrium geometries, respectively. Our results provide insight of operator spreading of coherent errors in quantum simulation of electronic structure and can be experimentally implemented in various platforms available today.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12289v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. J. Joven, V. M. Bastidas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of fractional quantum Hall liquids coupled to quantum light and emergent graviton-polaritons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent breakthrough experiments have demonstrated how it is now possible to explore the dynamics of quantum Hall states interacting with quantum electromagnetic cavity fields. While the impact of strongly coupled non-local cavity modes on integer quantum Hall physics has been recently addressed, its effects on fractional quantum Hall (FQH) liquids -- and, more generally, fractionalized states of matter -- remain largely unexplored. In this work, we develop a theoretical framework for the understanding of FQH states coupled to quantum light. In particular, combining analytical arguments with tensor network simulations, we study the dynamics of a $\nu=1/3$ Laughlin state in a single-mode cavity with finite electric field gradients. We find that the topological signatures of the FQH state remain robust against the non-local cavity vacuum fluctuations, as indicated by the endurance of the quantized Hall resistivity. The entanglement spectra, however, carry direct fingerprints of light-matter entanglement and topology, revealing peculiar polaritonic replicas of the $U(1)$ counting. As a further response to cavity fluctuations, we also find a squeezed FQH geometry, encoded in long-wavelength correlations. We additionally observe that moving to strong cavity field gradients leads to an instability towards a sliding Tomonaga-Luttinger liquid phase, featuring a strong density modulation in the gradient direction. Finally, by exploring the low-energy excited spectrum inside the FQH phase, we identify a new quasiparticle, the graviton-polariton, arising from the hybridization between quadrupolar FQH collective excitations (known as gravitons) and light. We discuss the experimental implications of our findings and possible extension of our results to more complex scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12292v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeno Bacciconi, Hernan Xavier, Iacopo Carusotto, Titas Chanda, Marcello Dalmonte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement transitions in SU(1, 1) quantum dynamics: applications to Bose-Einstein condensates and periodically driven coupled oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12558v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the entanglement properties in non-equilibrium quantum systems with the SU(1, 1) structure. Through M\"obius transformation, we map the dynamics of these systems following a sudden quench or a periodic drive onto three distinct trajectories on the Poincar\'e disc, corresponding the heating, non-heating, and a phase boundary describing these non-equilibrium quantum states. We consider two experimentally feasible systems where their quantum dynamics exhibit the SU(1, 1) structure: the quench dynamics of the Bose-Einstein condensates and the periodically driven coupled oscillators. In both cases, the heating, non-heating phases, and their boundary manifest through distinct signatures in the phonon population where exponential, oscillatory, and linear growths classify these phases. Similarly, the entanglement entropy and negativity also exhibit distinct behaviors (linearly, oscillatory, and logarithmic growths) characterizing these phases, respectively. Notibly, for the periodically driven coupled oscillators, the non-equilibrium properties are characterized by two sets of SU(1, 1) generators. The corresponding two sets of the trajectories on two Poincar\'e discs lead to a more complex phase diagram. We identify two distinct phases within the heating region discernible solely by the growth rate of the entanglement entropy, where a discontinuity is observed when varying the parameters across the phase boundary within in heating region. This discontinuity is not observed in the phonon population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12558v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng-Hsi Li, Po-Yao Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-dimensional mapping and electronic origin of large altermagnetic splitting near Fermi level in CrSb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, a new kind of collinear magnetism, dubbed altermagnetism, has attracted considerable interests. A key characteristic of altermagnet is the momentum-dependent band and spin splitting without net magnetization. However, finding altermagnetic materials with large splitting near the Fermi level, which necessarily requires three-dimensional k-space mapping and is crucial for spintronic applications and emergent phenomena, remains challenging. Here by employing synchrotron-based angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and model calculations, we uncover a large altermagnetic splitting, up to ~1.0 eV, near the Fermi level in CrSb. We verify its bulk-type g-wave altermagnetism through systematic three-dimensional kspace mapping, which unambiguously reveals the altermagnetic symmetry and associated nodal planes. The ARPES results are well captured by density functional theory calculations. In addition, tight-binding model analysis indicate that the large altermagnetic splitting arises from strong third-nearest-neighbor hopping mediated by Sb ions, which breaks both the space-time reversal symmetry and the translational spin-rotation symmetry. The large band/spin splitting near Fermi level in metallic CrSb, together with its high TN (up to 705 K) and simple spin configuration, paves the way for exploring emergent phenomena and spintronic applications based on altermagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12575v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guowei Yang, Zhanghuan Li, Sai Yang, Jiyuan Li, Hao Zheng, Weifan Zhu, Saizheng Cao, Wenxuan Zhao, Jiawen Zhang, Mao Ye, Yu Song, Lun-Hui Hu, Lexian Yang, Ming Shi, Huiqiu Yuan, Yongjun Zhang, Yuanfeng Xu, Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New regime of the Coulomb blockade in quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12653v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider how the absence of thermalisation affects the classical Coulomb blockade regime in quantum dots. By solving the quantum kinetic equation in the experimentally accessible regime when the dot has two relevant occupation states, we calculate the current-voltage characteristics for arbitrary coupling to the leads. If the couplings are strongly asymmetric, we have found that the Coulomb staircase practically reduces to the first step independent of the charging energy when the latter is larger than the Fermi energy, while the standard thermalised results are recovered in the opposite case. If the couplings are of the same order, the absence of thermalisation has a new, striking signature - a robust additional peak in the differential conductance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12653v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George McArdle, Rose Davies, Igor V. Lerner, Igor V. Yurkevich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated magnetism of moir\'e exciton-polaritons on a triangular electron-spin lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12698v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate evidence of correlated magnetism for exciton-polaritons in a MoSe$_{2}$/WS$_{2}$ moir\'e heterostructure with near-parallel alignment subject to electron doping. In our experiments, interactions between electrons and moir\'e excitons are controlled electrostatically by field-effect doping, and the polaritonic regime of strong light-matter coupling is established in an open cryogenic microcavity. Remarkably, at filling fractions around one electron per moir\'e cell, we observe drastic and nonlinear enhancement of the effective polariton Land\'e factor as a hallmark of correlated magnetism, which is cavity-controlled via resonance tuning of light and matter polariton constituents. Our work establishes moir\'e van der Waals heterostructures as an outstanding platform for studies of correlated phenomena in the presence of strong light-matter coupling and many-body phases of lattice-ordered excitons, charges and spins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12698v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Scherzer, Lukas Lackner, Bo Han, Borislav Polovnikov, Lukas Husel, Jonas G\"oser, Zhijie Li, Jens-Christian Drawer, Martin Esmann, Christoph Bennenhei, Falk Eilenberger, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Anvar S. Baimuratov, Christian Schneider, Alexander H\"ogele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spin Point Groups and their Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.12784v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The spin point groups are finite groups whose elements act on both real space and spin space. Among these groups are the magnetic point groups in the case where the real and spin space operations are locked to one another. The magnetic point groups are central to magnetic crystallography for strong spin-orbit coupled systems and the spin point groups generalize these to the intermediate and weak spin-orbit coupled cases. The spin point groups were introduced in the 1960's and enumerated shortly thereafter. In this paper, we complete the theory of spin point groups by presenting an account of these groups and their representation theory. Our main findings are that the so-called nontrivial spin point groups (numbering 598 groups) have co-irreps corresponding exactly to the (co-)irreps of regular or black and white groups and we tabulate this correspondence for each nontrivial group. However a total spin group, comprising the product of a nontrivial group and a spin-only group, has new co-irreps in cases where there is continuous rotational freedom. We provide explicit co-irrep tables for all these instances. We also discuss new forms of spin-only group extending the Litvin-Opechowski classes. To exhibit the usefulness of these groups to physically relevant problems we discuss a number of examples from electronic band structures of altermagnets to magnons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.12784v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hana Schiff, Alberto Corticelli, Afonso Guerreiro, Judit Romh\'anyi, Paul McClarty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing Lattice Instability and Magnetism on the Surface of Kagome Metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08771v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Only a few magnetic kagome materials exhibit lattice instabilities among the large kagome material array. In this work, we find that kagome magnets $R$Mn$_6$Sn$_6$ ($R$ = rare-earth elements) and their non-magnetic counterparts $R$V$_6$Sn$_6$ exhibit intriguing interplay between magnetism and lattice dynamics on their surfaces. Notably, $R$V$_6$Sn$_6$ surfaces terminated by kagome layers demonstrate pronounced lattice instabilities, manifesting as $\sqrt{3} \times \sqrt{3}$ and $2 \times 2$ surface charge orders (SCOs). These instabilities are absent on corresponding magnetic materials $R$Mn$_6$Sn$_6$. Here, the SCO is suppressed by magnetism. Otherwise, surface distortions would significantly reduce the spin polarization, elevating the energy via Hund's rule. Thus, SCOs are energetically unfavorable on magnetic surfaces. The competition of magnetism and lattice instability is further substantiated by observing SCOs on V-substituted $R$Mn$_6$Sn$_6$ kagome surfaces, contrasting with their absence on Mn-substituted $R$V$_6$Sn$_6$ surfaces. Our findings reveal unexpected surface instability and profound spin-lattice coupling in these kagome magnets, highlighting the complex dynamics hidden within magnetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08771v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.195428</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 195428 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hengxin Tan, Binghai Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral evidence for Dirac spinons in a kagome lattice antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11646v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Emergent quasiparticles with a Dirac dispersion in condensed matter systems can be described by the Dirac equation for relativistic electrons, in analogy with Dirac particles in high-energy physics. For example, electrons with a Dirac dispersion have been intensively studied in electronic systems such as graphene and topological insulators. However, charge is not a prerequisite for Dirac fermions, and the emergence of Dirac fermions without charge degree of freedom has been theoretically predicted to be realized in Dirac quantum spin liquids. These quasiparticles carry a spin of 1/2 but are charge-neutral, and so are called spinons. Here we show that the spin excitations of a kagome antiferromagnet, YCu$_3$(OD)$_6$Br$_2$[Br$_{0.33}$(OD)$_{0.67}$], are conical with a spin continuum inside, which is consistent with the convolution of two Dirac spinons. The predictions of a Dirac spin liquid model with a spinon velocity obtained from the spectral measurements are in agreement with the low-temperature specific heat of the sample. Our results thus provide spectral evidence for the Dirac quantum spin liquid state emerging in this kagome lattice antiferromagnet. However, the locations of the conical spin excitations differ from those calculated by the nearest neighbor Heisenberg model, suggesting the Dirac spinons have an unexpected origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11646v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02495-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Phys. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyuan Zeng, Chengkang Zhou, Honglin Zhou, Lankun Han, Runze Chi, Kuo Li, Maiko Kofu, Kenji Nakajima, Yuan Wei, Wenliang Zhang, Daniel G. Mazzone, Zi Yang Meng, Shiliang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological transitions in the Yao-Lee spin-orbital model and effects of site disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17359v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Yao-Lee model is an example of exactly solvable spin-orbital models that are generalizations of the original Kitaev honeycomb model with extra local orbital degrees of freedom. Similar to the Kitaev model, both spin and orbital degrees of freedom are effectively represented using sets of three-flavored Majorana fermions. The Yao-Lee model exhibits a quantum spin liquid ground state with gapped and immobile $Z_2$ fluxes and three-fold degenerate itinerant Majorana fermions. Our work demonstrated that by introducing different time-reversal symmetry (TRS) breaking fields one can split the degeneracy of Majorana fermions and close the gap for some of the bands, thus changing its topology. We calculated a comprehensive topological phase diagram for the Yao-Lee model by considering various combinations of TRS-breaking fields. This investigation revealed the emergence of distinct topological regions, each separated by nodal lines, signifying an evolution in the model's topological properties. We also investigated the impact of vacancies in the system. Our findings revealed that while vacancies modify the low-energy spectrum of the model, their presence has a limited impact on the topological properties of the model, at least for small enough concentrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17359v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladislav Poliakov, Wen-Han Kao, Natalia B. Perkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplified entanglement witnessed in a quantum critical metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18552v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strong correlations in matter promote a landscape of ground states and associated quantum critical points. For metallic systems, there is increasing recognition that the quantum criticality goes beyond the standard Landau framework and, thus, novel means are needed to characterize the quantum critical fluid. Here we do so by studying the entanglement properties near a quantum critical point of a strongly correlated metal. We calculate the quantum Fisher information of an Anderson/Kondo lattice model across its Kondo destruction quantum critical point. The quantum Fisher information of the spin degree of freedom peaks at the quantum critical point and indicates a strongly entangled ground state. Our results are supported by the quantum Fisher information extracted from inelastic neutron scattering measurements in quantum critical heavy fermion metals. Our work opens a new avenue to advance the understanding of metallic quantum criticality in a broad range of strongly correlated systems, and points to a new regime of quantum matter to realize amplified entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18552v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Fang, Mounica Mahankali, Yiming Wang, Lei Chen, Haoyu Hu, Silke Paschen, Qimiao Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NoRA: A Tensor Network Ansatz for Volume-Law Entangled Equilibrium States of Highly Connected Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16946v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the ground state structure of quantum models with all-to-all interactions such as mean-field quantum spin glass models and the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model, we propose a tensor network architecture which can accomodate volume law entanglement and a large ground state degeneracy. We call this architecture the non-local renormalization ansatz (NoRA) because it can be viewed as a generalization of MERA, DMERA, and branching MERA networks with the constraints of spatial locality removed. We argue that the architecture is potentially expressive enough to capture the entanglement and complexity of the ground space of the SYK model, thus making it a suitable variational ansatz, but we leave a detailed study of SYK to future work. We further explore the architecture in the special case in which the tensors are random Clifford gates. Here the architecture can be viewed as the encoding map of a random stabilizer code. We introduce a family of codes inspired by the SYK model which can be chosen to have constant rate and linear distance at the cost of some high weight stabilizers. We also comment on potential similarities between this code family and the approximate code formed from the SYK ground space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16946v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Val\'erie Bettaque, Brian Swingle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological zero-modes of the spectral localizer of trivial metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01983v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topological insulators are described by topological invariants that can be computed by integrals over momentum space, but also as traces over local, real-space topological markers. These markers are useful to detect topological insulating phases in disordered crystals, quasicrystals and amorphous systems. Among these markers, only the spectral localizer operator can be used to distinguish topological metals, that show zero-modes of the localizer spectrum. However, it remains unclear whether trivial metals also display zero-modes, and if their localizer spectrum is distinguishable from topological ones. Here, we show that trivial metals generically display zero-modes of the localizer spectrum. The localizer zero-modes are determined by the zero-mode solutions of a Dirac equation with a varying mass parameter. We use this observation, valid in any dimension, to determine the difference between the localizer spectrum of trivial and topological metals, and conjecture the spectrum of the localizer for fractional quantum Hall edges. Because the localizer is a local, real-space operator, it may be used as a tool to differentiate between non-crystalline topological and trivial metals, and characterize strongly correlated systems, for which local topological markers are scarce.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01983v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.195107</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 195107 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Selma Franca, Adolfo G. Grushin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalization of Balian-Brezin decomposition for exponentials with linear fermionic part</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13481v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fermionic Gaussian states have garnered considerable attention due to their intriguing properties, most notably Wick's theorem. Expanding upon the work of Balian and Brezin, who generalized properties of fermionic Gaussian operators and states, we further extend their findings to incorporate Gaussian operators with a linear component. Leveraging a technique introduced by Colpa, we streamline the analysis and present a comprehensive extension of the Balian-Brezin decomposition (BBD) to encompass exponentials involving linear terms. Furthermore, we introduce Gaussian states featuring a linear part and derive corresponding overlap formulas. Additionally, we generalize Wick's theorem to encompass scenarios involving linear terms, facilitating the expression of generic expectation values in relation to one and two-point correlation functions. We also provide a brief commentary on the applicability of the BB decomposition in addressing the BCH (Zassenhaus) formulas within the $\mathfrak{so}(N)$ Lie algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13481v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/ad3e44</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 57, 195206 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Seifi Mirjafarlou, A. Jafarizadeh, M. A. Rajabpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State Diagrams to determine Tree Tensor Network Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13433v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work is concerned with tree tensor network operators (TTNOs) for representing quantum Hamiltonians. We first establish a mathematical framework connecting tree topologies with state diagrams. Based on these, we devise an algorithm for constructing a TTNO given a Hamiltonian. The algorithm exploits the tensor product structure of the Hamiltonian to add paths to a state diagram, while combining local operators if possible. We test the capabilities of our algorithm on random Hamiltonians for a given tree structure. Additionally, we construct explicit TTNOs for nearest neighbour interactions on a tree topology. Furthermore, we derive a bound on the bond dimension of tensor operators representing arbitrary interactions on trees. Finally, we consider an open quantum system in the form of a Heisenberg spin chain coupled to bosonic bath sites as a concrete example. We find that tree structures allow for lower bond dimensions of the Hamiltonian tensor network representation compared to a matrix product operator structure. This reduction is large enough to reduce the number of total tensor elements required as soon as the number of baths per spin reaches $3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13433v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard M. Milbradt, Qunsheng Huang, Christian B. Mendl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous time-reversal symmetry breaking by disorder in superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08099v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A growing number of superconducting materials display evidence for spontaneous time-reversal symmetry breaking (TRSB) below their critical transition temperatures. Precisely what this implies for the nature of the superconducting ground state of such materials, however, is often not straightforward to infer. We review the experimental status and survey different theoretical mechanisms for the generation of TRSB in superconductors. In cases where a TRSB complex combination of two superconducting order parameter components is realized, defects, dislocations and sample edges may generate superflow patterns that can be picked up by magnetic probes. However, even single-component condensates that do not break time-reversal symmetry in their pure bulk phases can also support signatures of magnetism inside the superconducting state. This includes, for example, the generation of localized orbital current patterns or spin-polarization near atomic-scale impurities, twin boundaries and other defects. Signals of TRSB may also arise from a superconductivity-enhanced Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida exchange coupling between magnetic impurity moments present in the normal state. We discuss the relevance of these different mechanisms for TRSB in light of recent experiments on superconducting materials of current interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08099v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/fphy.2024.1353425</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Front. Phys. 12, 1353425 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Brian M. Andersen, Andreas Kreisel, P. J. Hirschfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Linear Dynamics and Critical Phenomena in the Holographic Landscape of Weyl Semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06484v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study presents a detailed analysis of critical phenomena in a holographic Weyl semi-metal (WSM) using the $D3/D7$ brane configuration. The research explores the non-linear response of the longitudinal current \( J \) when subjected to an external electric field \( E \) at both zero and finite temperatures. At zero temperature, the study identifies a potential quantum phase transition in the \( J \)-\( E \) relationship, driven by background parameters the particle mass, and axial gauge potential. This transition is characterized by a unique reconnection phenomenon resulting from the interplay between WSM-like and conventional nonlinear conducting behaviors, indicating a quantum phase transition.
  Additionally, at non-zero temperature with dissipation, the system demonstrates first- and second-order phase transitions as the electric field and axial gauge potential are varied. The longitudinal conductivity is used as an order parameter to identify the current-driven phase transition. Numerical analysis reveals critical exponents in this non-equilibrium phase transition that show similarities to mean-field values observed in metallic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06484v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masataka Matsumoto, Mirmani Mirjalali, Ali Vahedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
