<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 02:45:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between local and non-local frustration in the 1D ANNNI chain I -- The even case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the effects of the competition between different sources of frustration in 1D spin chains through the analysis of the paradigmatic ANNNI model, which possesses an extensive amount of frustration of local origin due to the competition between nearest and next-to-nearest neighbor interactions. An additional, non-extensive amount of topological frustration can be added by applying suitable boundary conditions, and we show that this seemingly subdominant contribution significantly affects the model. Choosing periodic boundary conditions with an {\it even} number of sites not divisible by 4 and using the entanglement entropy as a probe, we demonstrate that in one of the model's phases, the ground state can be characterized as hosting two (almost) independent excitations. Thus, not only do we show an intriguing interplay between different types of frustration, but also manage to propose a non-trivial quasi-particle interpretation for it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19449v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianpaolo Torre, Alberto Giuseppe Catalano, Sven Benjamin Ko\v{z}i\'c, Fabio Franchini, Salvatore Marco Giampaolo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel electronic structures from anomalous stackings in NbS$_2$ and MoS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that in some transition metal dichalcogenides, minority regions of the cleaved sample surfaces show - unexpectedly and anomalously - a finite number of 2D electronic states instead of the expected 3D valence bands. In the case of NbS\textsubscript{2}, in addition to the typical spectrum associated with bulk 2Ha stacking, we also find minority regions with electronic structures consistent with few-layers of 3R stacking. In MoS\textsubscript{2} we find areas of both bulk 2Hc and 3R stackings, and regions exhibiting finite-layer quantisation of both types. We further find evidence for a more exotic 4Ha stacking of MoS\textsubscript{2}, in which the valence band maximum is quasi-2D. The results highlight how variation of the interlayer stacking of van der Waals materials beyond the commonly-reported bulk polytypes can yield novel electronic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19793v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew D. Watson, Mihir Date, Alex Louat, Niels B. M. Schr\"oter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of random spin-singlet state in a three-dimensional quantum spin liquid candidate Sr$_3$CuNb$_2$O$_9$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Disorder is ubiquitous in any quantum many-body system and is usually considered to be an obstacle to the elucidation of the underlying physics of complex systems, but its presence can often introduce exotic phases of matter that cannot generally be realized in a clean system. We report here a detailed experimental and theoretical study of magnetic properties of highly disordered Sr$_3$CuNb$_2$O$_9$ material which exhibits random site mixing between Cu and Nb. The magnetic moments (Cu$^{2+}$) are arranged in a quasi-cubic (three-dimensional) manner, leading to a high degree of frustration with a Curie-Weiss temperature ($\theta_{CW}$) of about -60 K without any long-range magnetic ordering down to 466 mK. These observations suggest that Sr$_3$CuNb$_2$O$_9$ is a candidate for a quantum spin liquid. More interestingly, the susceptibility ($\chi = M/\mu_0H$) and the $C_m/T$ ($C_m$ is the magnetic part of the heat capacity) follow a power-law behavior with decreasing temperature. In addition, $M(T,\mu_0H)$ and $C_m(T,\mu_0H)/T$ show scaling relationships over a wide temperature and field range. This unusual behavior with respect to the conventional behavior of a QSL can be discussed qualitatively as the coexistence of a disorder-induced random spin singlet (RSS) state and a QSL state. A quantitative description has been given by numerical calculations considering a power-law probability distribution $P(J) \propto J^{-\gamma}$ ($J$ is the exchange interaction) of random spin singlets. The parameters extracted from the numerical calculations are in excellent agreement with the experimental data. Furthermore, the analytical results are also consistent with the power-law and scaling behavior of $\chi$ and $C_m(T,\mu_0H)/T$ as a whole. Thus, our comprehensive experimental and theoretical analysis provides evidence for the stabilization of the RSS state in a three-dimensional lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19797v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. M. Hossain, S. S. Rahaman, H. Gujrati, Dilip Bhoi, A. Matsuo, K. Kindo, M. Kumar, M. Majumder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathbb{Z}_4$ transitions in quantum loop models on a zig-zag ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.20093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.20093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the nature of quantum phase transitions out of $\mathbb{Z}_4$ ordered phases in quantum loop models on a zig-zag ladder. We report very rich critical behaviour that includes a pair of Ising transitions, a multi-critical Ashkin-Teller point and a remarkably extended interval of a chiral transition. Although plaquette states turn out to be essential to realize chiral transitions, we demonstrate that critical regimes can be manipulated by deforming the model as to increase the presence of leg-dimerized states. This can be done to the point where the chiral transition turns into first order, we argue that this is associated with the emergence of a critical end point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.20093v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowy M. La Rivi\`ere, Natalia Chepiga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ice on curved surfaces: defect rings and differential local dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ice systems are prototypes of locally constrained dynamics. This is exemplified in Coulomb-liquid phases where a large space of configurations is sampled, each satisfying local ice rules. Dynamics proceeds through `flipping' rings, i.e., through reversing arrows running along the edges of a polygon. We examine the role of defect rings in such phases, with square-ice as a testing ground. When placed on a curved surface, the underlying square lattice will form defects such as triangles or pentagons. We show that triangular defects are statistically more `flippable' than the background. In contrast, pentagons and larger polygons are less flippable. In fact, flippability decreases monotonically with ring size, as seen from a Pauling-like argument. As an explicit demonstration, we wrap the square ice model on a sphere. We start from an octahedron and perform repeated rectifications, producing a series of clusters with sphere-like geometry. They contain a fixed number of defect triangles in an otherwise square lattice. We numerically enumerate all ice-rule-satisfying configurations. Indeed, triangles are flippable in a larger fraction of configurations than quadrilaterals. The obtained flippabilities are in broad agreement with the Pauling-like estimates. As a minimal model for dynamics, we construct a Hamiltonian with quantum tunnelling terms that flip rings. The resulting ground state is a superposition of all ice configurations. The dominant contribution to its energy comes from localized resonance within triangles. Our results suggest local dynamics as a promising observable for experiments in spin ice and artificial ice systems. They also point to hierarchical dynamics in materials such as ice V that contain rings of multiple sizes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19453v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adhitya Sivaramakrishnan, R. Ganesh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Injection Route to Magnon Berry Curvature Dipole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Berry curvature of Bloch bands arising in lattice systems can induce a Hall response even in the absence of topology due to the so-called Berry-curvature dipole (BCD). Such a response is universal and, in principle, should occur as a thermal-Hall effect in magnon systems under the application of a temperature gradient. However, this effect intrinsically appears as a non-linear (second-order) response to the temperature gradient making experimental detection difficult. Here, we propose an alternate route to access BCD in magnons. By utilizing the process of spin-injection in conjunction with a temperature gradient, we uncover two previously unreported contributions to the BCD-induced Hall response for magnons -- one that is linear in temperature gradient, and the other is non-linear in the magnon-chemical potential gradient arising from spin injection. As an added benefit of our approach, both these responses extract distinct moments of the genuine BCD distribution over the magnon bands, as opposed to the recently reported extended BCD in magnons. We use Boltzmann transport theory to derive the expression for the magnon-Hall response in the presence of a thermal gradient and spin injection. Furthermore, using this expression, we offer predictions for the BCD-induced magnon-Hall effect to be observed in experiments for ferro, anti-ferro and ferri magnetically-ordered models on various lattices, including the honeycomb lattice, the kagome lattice, and the dice lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19454v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atul Rathor, Saurav Kantha, Arijit Haldar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic phase transition and non-local complexity in generalized $W$ State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19457v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We employ the Stabilizer Renyi Entropy (SRE) to characterize a quantum phase transition that has so far eluded any standard description and can thus now be explained in terms of the interplay between its non-stabilizer properties and entanglement. The transition under consideration separates a region with a unique ground state from one with a degenerate ground state manifold spanned by states with finite and opposite (intensive) momenta. We show that SRE has a jump at the crossing points, while the entanglement entropy remains continuous. Moreover, by leveraging on a Clifford circuit mapping, we connect the observed jump in SRE to that occurring between standard and generalized $W$-states with finite momenta. This mapping allows us to quantify the SRE discontinuity analytically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19457v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Catalano, J. Odavi\'c, G. Torre, A. Hamma, F. Franchini, S. M. Giampaolo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delocalization of Quasiparticle Moir\'e States in Twisted Bilayer hBN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19700v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Twisted bilayers host many emergent phenomena in which the electronic excitations (quasiparticles - QPs) are closely intertwined with the local stacking order. By inspecting twisted hexagonal boron nitride (t-hBN), we show that non-local long-range interactions in large twisted systems cannot be reliably described by the local (high-symmetry) stacking and that the band gap variation (typically associated with the moir\'e excitonic potential) shows multiple minima with variable depth depending on the twist angle. We investigate twist angles of 2.45$^\circ$, 2.88$^\circ$, 3.48$^\circ$ and 5.09$^\circ$ using the GW approximation together with stochastic compression to analyze the QP state interactions. We find that band-edge QP hybridization is suppressed for intermediate angles which exhibit two distinct local minima in the moir\'e potential (at AA region and saddle point (SP)) which become degenerate for the largest system (2.45$^\circ$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19700v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arsineh Apelian, Annabelle Canestraight, Songyuan Liu, Vojtech Vlcek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality constraints on thermal spectra of 3d CFTs and 4d quasinormal modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19790v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermal spectra of correlation functions in holographic 3d large-N CFTs correspond to quasinormal modes of classical gravity and other fields in asymptotically anti-de Sitter black hole spacetimes. Using general properties of such spectra along with constraints imposed by the S-duality (or the particle-vortex duality), we derive a spectral duality relation that all such spectra must obey. Its form is universal in that each such relation (expressed as an infinite product over QNMs) only depends on a single function of a spatial wavevector that corresponds to the bulk algebraically special frequencies. In the process, we also derive a new sum rule constraining products over QNMs. The spectral duality relation, which imposes an infinite set of constraints on the QNMs, is then investigated and a number of well-known holographic examples that demonstrate its validity are examined. Our results also allow us to understand several new aspects of the pole-skipping phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19790v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sa\v{s}o Grozdanov, Mile Vrbica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated insulators in twisted mono-mono-bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19915v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graphene-based moir\'e superlattice featuring flat bands is a promising platform for studying strongly correlated states. By tuning two twist angles and displacement fields in twisted mono-mono-bilayer graphene (TMMBG), we observed a correlated metallic state evolved into a valley-polarized correlated insulator at the filling factor of $\nu = -2$, with the coupling strength between the top two monolayer graphene intensifying. Moreover, the corresponding effective g-factor obtained from fitting the thermal activation gap is enhanced with the coupling strength, suggesting that TMMBG can be harnessed for developing valleytronics devices. In addition, the observation of an unconventional correlated electron-hole insulator suggests that this state might be a candidate for an excitonic insulator, which may generated by the correlation from band nesting, which encourages further research in non-Fermi liquid physics. Our work reveals that tuning multiple twist angles can provide a unique route for studying quantum many-body states in twistronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19915v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Jiang, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Mitali Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous current fluctuations from Euler hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.20091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.20091v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the hydrodynamic origin of anomalous current fluctuations in a family of stochastic charged cellular automata. Using ballistic macroscopic fluctuation theory, we study both typical and large fluctuations of the charge current and reproduce microscopic results which are available for the deterministic single-file limit of the models. Our results indicate that in general initial fluctuations propagated by Euler equations fully characterize both scales of anomalous fluctuations. For stochastic dynamics, we find an additional contribution to typical fluctuations and conjecture the functional form of the probability typical distribution, which we confirm by numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.20091v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takato Yoshimura, \v{Z}iga Krajnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden orders and phase transitions for the fully packed quantum loop model on the triangular lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.04472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.04472v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum loop and dimer models are prototypical correlated systems with local constraints, which are not only intimately connected to lattice gauge theories and topological orders but are also widely applicable to the broad research areas of quantum materials and quantum simulation. Employing our sweeping cluster quantum Monte Carlo algorithm, we reveal the complete phase diagram of the triangular-lattice fully packed quantum loop model. Apart from the known lattice nematic (LN) solid and the even $\mathbb{Z}_2$ quantum spin liquid (QSL) phases, we discover a hidden vison plaquette (VP) phase, which had been overlooked and misinterpreted as a QSL for more than a decade. Moreover, the VP-to-QSL continuous transition belongs to the $(2+1)$D cubic* universality class, which offers a lattice realization of the (fractionalized) cubic fixed point that had long been considered as irrelevant towards the O($3$) symmetry until corrected recently by conformal bootstrap calculations. Our results are therefore of relevance to recent developments in both experiments and theory, and facilitate further investigations of hidden phases and transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.04472v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-024-01680-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications Physics 7, 207 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxue Ran, Zheng Yan, Yan-Cheng Wang, Rhine Samajdar, Junchen Rong, Subir Sachdev, Yang Qi, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral spin state and nematic ferromagnet in the spin-1 Kitaev-$\Gamma$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08382v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The higher-spin Kitaev magnets, in which the Kitaev interaction and off-diagonal exchange couplings are overwhelmingly large, have emerged as a fertile avenue to explore exotic phases and unusual excitations. In this work, we study the quantum phase diagram of the spin-1 Kitaev-$\Gamma$ model on the honeycomb lattice using density-matrix renormalization group. It harbours six distinct phases and the intriguing findings are three magnetically ordered phases in which both time-reversal symmetry and lattice symmetry albeit of different sort are broken spontaneously. The chiral spin state originates from the order-by-disorder effect and exhibits an almost saturated scalar spin chirality at the quantum level. Depending on the relative strength of the two interactions, it also features columnar-like or plaquette-like dimer pattern as a consequence of the translational symmetry breaking. In parallel, the nematic ferromagnets are situated at ferromagnetic Kitaev side and possess small but finite ferromagnetic ordering. The lattice-rotational symmetry breaking enforces nonequivalent bond energy along one of the three bonds. Although the intrinsic difference between the two nematic ferromagnets remains elusive, the discontinuities in the von Neumann entropy, hexagonal plaquette operator, and Wilson loop operator convincingly suggest that they are separated via a first-order phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08382v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Luo, Jize Zhao, Jinbin Li, Xiaoqun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-electron interactions in partially mixed helical states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11080v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically study the effect of electron-electron interactions in one-dimensional partially mixed helical states. These helical states can be realized at the edges of two-dimensional topological insulators with partially broken time-reversal symmetry, resulting in helical gapped states. Using the bosonization method and renormalization group analysis, we identify weak gap, crossover, and strong gap regimes in the phase diagram. We find that strong electron-electron interaction mixes the helicity of the states, leading to the relevant strong gap regime. We investigate the charge and spin density wave correlation functions in different relevancy regimes of the gap mediated by interactions, where in the case of strong repulsive interaction, the spin density wave dominates the charge density wave. Additionally, employing the Memory function technique, we calculate the effect of mixed helicity on the charge transport in a sufficiently long edge. We find a non-uniform temperature dependence for the charge conductivity in both the strong and weak gap regimes with distinct features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11080v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeinab Bakhshipour, Mir Vahid Hosseini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realizing Altermagnetism in Fermi-Hubbard Models with Ultracold Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10151v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Altermagnetism represents a new type of collinear magnetism distinct from ferromagnetism and conventional antiferromagnetism. In contrast to the latter, sublattices of opposite spin are related by spatial rotations and not only by translations and inversions. As a result, altermagnets have spin split bands leading to unique experimental signatures. Here, we show theoretically how a d-wave altermagnetic phase can be realized with ultracold fermionic atoms in optical lattices. We propose an altermagnetic Hubbard model with anisotropic next-nearest neighbor hopping and obtain the Hartree-Fock phase diagram. The altermagnetic phase separates in a metallic and an insulating phase and is robust over a large parameter regime. We show that one of the defining characteristics of altermagnetism, the anisotropic spin transport, can be probed with trap-expansion experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10151v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.263402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters, Vol. 132, Iss. 26 - 28 June 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Purnendu Das, Valentin Leeb, Johannes Knolle, Michael Knap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fate of Entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06677v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement is a fundamentally non-local correlation between particles. In its simplest realisation, a measurement on one particle is affected by a prior measurement on its partner, irrespective of their separation. For multiple particles, purely collective types of entanglement exist but their detection, even theoretically, remains an outstanding open question. Here, we show that all forms of multipartite entanglement entirely disappear during the typical evolution of a system as it heats up, evolves in time, or as its parts become separated. These results follow from the nature of the entanglement-free continent in the space of physical states, and hold in great generality. We illustrate these phenomena with a frustrated molecular quantum magnet in and out of equilibrium. In contrast, if the particles are fermions, such as electrons, another notion of entanglement exists that protects bipartite quantum correlations. However, truly collective fermionic entanglement disappears during typical evolution, thus sharing the same fate as in bosonic systems. These findings provide fundamental knowledge about the structure of entanglement in quantum matter and architectures, paving the way for its manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06677v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gilles Parez, William Witczak-Krempa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional electrons at mirror and twistronic twin boundaries in van der Waals ferroelectrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15040v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Semiconducting transition metal dichalcogenides (MX$_2$) occur in 2H and rhombohedral (3R) polytypes, respectively distinguished by anti-parallel and parallel orientation of consecutive monolayer lattices. In its bulk form, 3R-MX$_2$ is ferroelectric, hosting an out-of-plane electric polarisation, the direction of which is dictated by stacking. Here, we predict that twin boundaries, separating adjacent polarization domains with reversed built-in electric fields, are able to host two-dimensional electrons and holes with an areal density reaching $\sim 10^{13} {\rm cm}^{-2}$. Our modelling suggests that n-doped twin boundaries have a more promising binding energy than p-doped ones, whereas hole accumulation is stable at external surfaces of a twinned film. We also propose that assembling pairs of mono-twin films with a `magic' twist angle $\theta^*$ that provides commensurability between the moir\'e pattern at the interface and the accumulated carrier density, should promote a regime of strongly correlated states of electrons, such as Wigner crystals, and we specify the values of $\theta^*$ for homo- and heterostructures of various TMDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15040v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James G. McHugh, Xue Li, Isaac Soltero, Vladimir I. Fal'ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
