<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>From explicit to spontaneous charge order and the fate of antiferromagnetic quantum Hall state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23367v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The antiferromagnetic quantum Hall insulator (AFQHI) where one of the spin components is in the quantum Hall state and the other in the trivial state is an established phase emerging as a result of the Hubbard repulsion in spinful quantum Hall systems. The stabilization of the AFQHI requires a charge order preventing the effect of the spin-flip transformation on the electronic state to be compensated by a space group operation, and is often induced via an ionic potential. While one would naively expect the nearest-neighbor (NN) density-density interaction favoring spontaneous charge order to result in qualitatively similar phenomena an analysis of the Haldane-Hubbard model extended by the NN interaction finds no AFQHI. Here, by considering an extended version of the Harper-Hofstadter-Hubbard model we go beyond the honeycomb structure and show that the realization of the AFQHI generically requires an explicit charge order and cannot be emerged through a spontaneous charge order. We unveil how the AFQHI disappears upon approaching from the explicit to the spontaneous charge ordering limit. Our findings shine more light on the stabilization conditions of the AFQHI which can guide the future optical lattice experiments searching for this intriguing magnetic topological insulator phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23367v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Hafez-Torbati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Specific heat of Gd$^{3+}$- and Eu$^{2+}$-based magnetic compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have studied theoretically the specific heat of a large number of non-frustrated magnetic structures described by the Heisenberg model for systems with total angular momentum $J=7/2$, which corresponds to the 4f$^7$ configuration of Gd$^{+3}$ and Eu$^{+2}$. For a given critical temperature (controlled by the magnitude of the exchange interactions) we find that to a large accuracy, the specific heat is controlled by two parameters: the effective number of neighbors (which controls the importance of quantum fluctuations) and the axial anisotropy. Using these two parameters we fit the specific heat of four Gd compounds and two Eu compounds obtaining a remarkable agreement. Another Gd compound has been fitted previously. Our work opens the possibility of describing the specific heat of non-frustrated 4f$^7$ systems within a general framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23519v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. J. Garcia, J. G. Sereni, A. A. Aligia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure-dependent magnetotransport measurement in Kagome metal Yb$_{0.5}$Co_3Ge$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome materials are known to be an ideal platform that hosts a plethora of interesting phases such as topological states, electronic correlation, and magnetism, owing to their unique band structure and geometry. We report magnetotransport measurement in Kagome metal Yb$_{0.5}$Co_3Ge$_3$ as a function of pressure. Below $\sim25^\circ$ K the temperature dependence of resistance shows an upturn that is accompanied by a strong negative magnetoresistance, which could be attributed to Kondo effect. Upon pressurization above 1 GPa the resistance shows a reduction as a function of temperature below $4^\circ$ K, along with a further enhanced negative magnetoresistance. This might indicate an onset of a pressure-induced Kondo coherence effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23872v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Cheng, Yaojia Wang, Heng Wu, Mazhar N. Ali, Julia Y. Chan, Semonti Bhattacharyya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Darkness in interlayer and charge density wave states of 2H-TaS2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The wave-like nature of electrons is evident from quantum interference effects observed during the photoemission process. When there are different nuclei in the unit cell of a crystal and/or structural distortions, photo-electron wavefunctions can interfere, giving rise to peculiar intensity modulation of the spectrum, which can also hide energy states in a photoemission experiment. The 2H phase of transition metal dichalcogenides, with two nonequivalent layers per unit cell and charge density wave distortion, is an optimal platform for such effects to be observed. Here, we discover undetectable states in 2H-TaS2, interpreting high-resolution angular resolved photoemission spectroscopy considering interference effects of the correlated electron wave functions. In addition, phase mismatching induced by the charge density wave distortion, results in evident signature of the phase transition in the photoemission spectrum. Our results highlight the importance of quantum interference, electronic correlations and structural distortion to understand the physics of layered materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24086v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Camerano, Dario Mastrippolito, Debora Pierucci, Ji Dai, Massimo Tallarida, Luca Ottaviano, Gianni Profeta, Federico Bisti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosing electronic phases of matter using photonic correlation functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24215v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the past couple of decades, there have been significant advances in measuring quantum properties of light, such as quadratures of squeezed light and single-photon counting. Here, we explore whether such tools can be leveraged to probe electronic correlations in the many-body quantum regime. Specifically, we show that it is possible to probe certain spin, charge, and topological orders in an electronic system by measuring the quadrature and correlation functions of photons scattered off it. We construct a mapping from the correlation functions of the scattered photons to those of a correlated insulator, particularly for Mott insulators described by a single-band Hubbard model at half-filling. We show how frequency filtering before photodetection plays a crucial role in determining this mapping. If the ground state of the insulator is a gapped spin liquid, we show that a $G^{(2)}$ (two-photon coherence) measurement can detect the presence of anyonic excitations with fractional mutual statistics. We also show that homodyne measurements can be used to detect expectation values of static spin chirality operators on both the kagome and triangular lattices, thus being useful in detecting chiral spin liquids. Moreover, a slew of hitherto unmeasured spin-spin and spin-charge correlation functions of the material can be extracted from photonic correlations. This work opens up access to probe correlated materials, beyond the linear response paradigm, by detecting quantum properties of scattered light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24215v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gautam Nambiar, Andrey Grankin, Mohammad Hafezi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body quantum catalysts for transforming between phases of matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23354v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A catalyst is a substance that enables otherwise impossible transformations between states of a system, without being consumed in the process. In this work, we apply the notion of catalysts to many-body quantum physics. In particular, we construct catalysts that enable transformations between different symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phases of matter using symmetric finite-depth quantum circuits. We discover a wide variety of catalysts, including GHZ-like states which spontaneously break the symmetry, gapless states with critical correlations, topological orders with symmetry fractionalization, and spin-glass states. These catalysts are all united under a single framework which has close connections to the theory of quantum anomalies, and we use this connection to put strong constraints on possible pure- and mixed-state catalysts. We also show how the catalyst approach leads to new insights into the structure of certain phases of matter, and to new methods to efficiently prepare SPT phases with long-range interactions or projective measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23354v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David T. Stephen, Rahul Nandkishore, Jian-Hao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An operator algebraic approach to symmetry defects and fractionalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a superselection theory of symmetry defects in 2+1D symmetry enriched topological (SET) order in the infinite volume setting. For a finite symmetry group $G$ with a unitary on-site action, our formalism produces a $G$-crossed braided tensor category $G\mathsf{Sec}$. This superselection theory is a direct generalization of the usual superselection theory of anyons, and thus is consistent with this standard analysis in the trivially graded component $G\mathsf{Sec}_1$. This framework also gives us a completely rigorous understanding of symmetry fractionalization. To demonstrate the utility of our formalism, we compute $G\mathsf{Sec}$ explicitly in both short-range and long-range entangled spin systems with symmetry and recover the relevant skeletal data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23380v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyle Kawagoe, Siddharth Vadnerkar, Daniel Wallick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wormhole-induced effective coupling in SYK chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23397v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inhomogeneous quantum chains have recently been considered in the context of developing novel discrete realizations of holographic dualities. To advance this programme, we explore the ground states of infinite chains with large number $N$ of Majorana fermions on each site, which interact via on-site $q$-body Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) couplings, as well as via additional inhomogeneous hopping terms between nearest-neighbour sites. The hopping parameters are either aperiodically or randomly distributed. Our approach unifies techniques to solve SYK-like models in the large $N$ limit with a real-space renormalization group method known as strong-disorder renormalization group (SDRG). We show that the SDRG decimation of SYK dots linked by a strong hopping induces an effective hopping interaction between their neighbouring sites. If two decimated sites are nearest neighbours, in the large $q$ limit their local ground states admit a holographic dual description in terms of eternal traversable wormholes. At the end of the SDRG procedure, we obtain a factorised ground state of the infinite inhomogeneous SYK chains that we consider, which has a spacetime description involving a sequence of wormholes. This amounts to a local near-boundary description of the bulk geometry in the context of discrete holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23397v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Basteiro, Giuseppe Di Giulio, Johanna Erdmenger, Ren\'e Meyer, Zhuo-Yu Xian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Detection of Strong-To-Weak Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking via the R\'enyi-1 Correlator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23512v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Strong-to-weak spontaneous symmetry breaking (SWSSB) has recently emerged as a universal feature of quantum mixed-state phases of matter. While various information-theoretic diagnostics have been proposed to define and characterize SWSSB phases, relating these diagnostics to observables which can be efficiently and scalably probed on modern quantum devices remains challenging. Here we propose a new observable for SWSSB in mixed states, called the R\'enyi-1 correlator, which naturally suggests a potential route towards scalably detecting SWSSB phases in experiment. Specifically, if the canonical purification (CP) of a given mixed state can be reliably prepared, then SWSSB in the mixed state can be detected via ordinary two-point correlation functions in the CP state. We discuss several simple examples of CP states which can be efficiently prepared on quantum devices, and whose reduced density matrices exhibit SWSSB. The R\'enyi-1 correlator also satisfies several useful theoretical properties: it naturally inherits a stability theorem recently proven for the closely-related fidelity correlator, and it directly defines SWSSB as a particular pattern of ordinary spontaneous symmetry breaking in the CP state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23512v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zack Weinstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning State Preparation Circuits for Quantum Phases of Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23544v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many-body ground state preparation is an important subroutine used in the simulation of physical systems. In this paper, we introduce a flexible and efficient framework for obtaining a state preparation circuit for a large class of many-body ground states. We introduce polynomial-time classical algorithms that take reduced density matrices over $\mathcal{O}(1)$-sized balls as inputs, and output a circuit that prepares the global state. We introduce algorithms applicable to (i) short-range entangled states (e.g., states prepared by shallow quantum circuits in any number of dimensions, and more generally, invertible states) and (ii) long-range entangled ground states (e.g., the toric code on a disk). Both algorithms can provably find a circuit whose depth is asymptotically optimal. Our approach uses a variant of the quantum Markov chain condition that remains robust against constant-depth circuits. The robustness of this condition makes our method applicable to a large class of states, whilst ensuring a classically tractable optimization landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23544v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyun-Soo Kim, Isaac H. Kim, Daniel Ranard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear edge transport in a quantum Hall system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23548v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonlinear transport phenomena in condensed matter reflect the geometric nature, quantum coherence, and many-body correlation of electronic states. Electric currents in solids are classified into (i) Ohmic current, (ii) supercurrent, and (iii) geometric or topological current. While the nonlinear current-voltage $(I$-$V)$ characteristics of the former two categories have been extensive research topics recently, those of the last category remains unexplored. Among them, the quantum Hall current is a representative example. Realized in two-dimensional electronic systems under a strong magnetic field, the topological protection quantizes the Hall conductance in the unit of $e^2/h$ ($e$: elementary charge, $h$: Planck constant), of which the edge transport picture gives a good account. Here, we theoretically study the nonlinear $I$-$V_\text{H}$ characteristic of the edge transport up to third order in $V_\text{H}$. We find that nonlinearity arises in the Hall response from electron-electron interaction between the counterpropagating edge channels with the nonlinear energy dispersions. We also discuss possible experimental observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23548v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/sciadv.ado2704</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. Adv. 10, eado2704 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Isobe, Naoto Nagaosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement scaling and criticality of quantum many-body systems in canonical quantization picture using tensor network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23624v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulating strongly-correlated quantum systems in continuous space belongs to the most challenging and long-concerned issues in quantum physics. This work investigates the quantum entanglement and criticality of the ground-state wave-functions of infinitely-many coupled quantum oscillators (iCQOs). The essential task involves solving a set of partial differential equations (Schr\"odinger equations in the canonical quantization picture) with infinitely-many variables, which currently lacks valid methods. By extending the imaginary-time evolution algorithm with translationally-invariant functional tensor network, we simulate the ground state of iCQOs with the presence of two- and three-body couplings. We determine the range of coupling strengths where there exists a real ground-state energy (dubbed as physical region). With two-body couplings, we reveal the logarithmic scaling law of entanglement entropy (EE) and the polynomial scaling law of correlation length against the virtual bond dimension $\chi$ at the dividing point of physical and non-physical regions. These two scaling behaviors are signatures of criticality, according to the previous results in quantum lattice models, but were not reported in continuous-space quantum systems. The scaling coefficients result in a central charge $c=1$, indicating the presence of free boson conformal field theory (CFT). With three-body couplings where there exist no analytical nor numerical results, we show the breakdown of CFT at the dividing point even with an extremely small strength of three-body terms. Our work uncovers the scaling behaviors of EE in the continuous-space quantum many-body systems, providing numerical evidences for the efficiency of tensor networks in representing the continuous-space quantum many-body ground states in the thermodynamic limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23624v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Hong, Hao-Wei Cui, An-Chun Ji, Shi-Ju Ran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More global randomness from less random local gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Random circuits giving rise to unitary designs are key tools in quantum information science and many-body physics. In this work, we investigate a class of random quantum circuits with a specific gate structure. Within this framework, we prove that one-dimensional structured random circuits with non-Haar random local gates can exhibit substantially more global randomness compared to Haar random circuits with the same underlying circuit architecture. In particular, we derive all the exact eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the second-moment operators for these structured random circuits under a solvable condition, by establishing a link to the Kitaev chain, and show that their spectral gaps can exceed those of Haar random circuits. Our findings have applications in improving circuit depth bounds for randomized benchmarking and the generation of approximate unitary 2-designs from shallow random circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24127v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryotaro Suzuki, Hosho Katsura, Yosuke Mitsuhashi, Tomohiro Soejima, Jens Eisert, Nobuyuki Yoshioka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error Threshold of SYK Codes from Strong-to-Weak Parity Symmetry Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24225v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum error correction (QEC) codes are fundamentally linked to quantum phases of matter: the degenerate ground state manifold corresponds to the code space, while topological excitations represent error syndromes. Building on this concept, the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model, characterized by its extensive quasi-ground state degeneracy, serves as a constant rate approximate QEC code. In this work, we study the impacts of decoherence on the information-theoretic capacity of SYK models and their variants. Such a capacity is closely tied to traversable wormholes via its thermofield double state, which theoretically enables the teleportation of information across a black hole. We calculate the coherent information in the maximally entangled quasi-ground state space of the SYK models under the fermion parity breaking and parity conserving noise. Interestingly, we find that under the strong fermion parity symmetric noise, the mixed state undergoes the strong to weak spontaneous symmetry breaking of fermion parity, which also corresponds to the information-theoretic transition. Our results highlight the degradation of wormhole traversability in realistic quantum scenarios, as well as providing critical insights into the behavior of approximate constant-rate QEC codes under decoherence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24225v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaewon Kim, Ehud Altman, Jong Yeon Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density-matrix renormalization group study of Kitaev-Heisenberg model on the triangular lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1512.02334</link>
      <description>arXiv:1512.02334v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the Kitaev-Heisenberg model on the triangular lattice by using the two-dimensional density-matrix renormalization group method. Calculating the ground-state energy and spin structure factors, we obtain the ground state phase diagram of the Kitaev-Heisenberg model. As suggested by previous studies, we find a 120$^\circ$ antiferromagnetic (AFM) phase, a $\mathbb{Z}_2$-vortex crystal phase, a nematic phase, a dual $\mathbb{Z}_2$-vortex crystal phase (dual counterpart of $\mathbb{Z}_2$-vortex crystal phase), a $\mathbb{Z}_6$ ferromagnetic phase, and a dual ferromagnetic phase (dual counterpart of $\mathbb{Z}_6 $ ferromagnetic phase). Spin correlations discontinuously change at the phase boundaries because of first-order phase transitions. In the (dual) $\mathbb{Z}_6$ ferromagnetic phase, we find that the dominant spin component of the spin structure factors is different on either side of the SU(2) symmetric point, although there is no phase transition. Furthermore, we study the relation among von Neumann entanglement entropy, entanglement spectrum, and phase transitions of the model. We find that the Schmidt gap closes at the phase boundaries and thus the entanglement entropy clearly changes as well. This is different from the Kitaev-Heisenberg model on the honeycomb lattice, where the Schmidt gap and the entanglement entropy are not necessary a good measure of phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1512.02334v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.85.114710</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 85, 114710 (2016)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kazuya Shinjo, Shigetoshi Sota, Seiji Yunoki, Keisuke Totsuka, Takami Tohyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin waves and orbital contribution to ferromagnetism in a topological metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.01457v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Special arrangements of atoms with more than one atom per unit cell, including honeycomb or kagome (woven bamboo mat) lattices, can host propagating excitations with non-trivial topology as defined by their evolution along closed paths in momentum space. Excitations on such lattices can also be momentum-independent, meaning that they are localized notwithstanding strong hopping of the underlying disturbances between neighbouring sites. The associated flat bands are interesting because the interactions between the heavy quasiparticles inhabiting them will become much more important than for strong dispersion, resulting in novel quantum solid and liquid states. Different stackings of two-dimensional lattices, for example twisted graphene bilayers, provide routes to further engineer topology and many-body effects. Here, we report the discovery, using circularly polarized x-rays for the unambiguous isolation of magnetic signals, of a nearly flat spin wave band and large (compared to elemental iron) orbital moment for the metallic ferromagnet Fe3Sn2, built from compact AB-stacked kagome bilayers and which has a topologically non-trivial electronic band structure controllable by modest external magnetic fields. As a function of out-of-plane momentum, the nearly flat optical mode and the global rotation symmetry-restoring acoustic mode are out of phase, consistent with a bilayer exchange coupling that is larger than the already large in-plane couplings. The defining units of this topological metal are therefore a triangular lattice of octahedral iron clusters rather than weakly coupled kagome planes. The spin waves are strongly damped when compared to elemental iron, opening the topic of interactions of topological bosons (spin waves) and fermions (electrons) with the very specific target of explaining boson lifetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.01457v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-53152-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 15, 8905 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wenliang Zhang, Teguh Citra Asmara, Yi Tseng, Junbo Li, Yimin Xiong, Yuan Wei, Tianlun Yu, Carlos William Galdino, Zhijia Zhang, Kurt Kummer, Vladimir N. Strocov, Y. Soh, Thorsten Schmitt, Gabriel Aeppli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phenomenology of bond and flux orders in kagome metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.02528v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite much experimental and theoretical work, the nature of the charge order in the kagome metals belonging to the family of materials AV$_3$Sb$_5$ (A=Cs,Rb,K) remains controversial. A crucial ingredient for the identification of the ordering in these materials is their response to external perturbations, such as strain or magnetic fields. To this end, we provide a comprehensive symmetry classification of the possible charge orders in kagome materials with a $2\times2$ increase of the unit cell. Motivated by the experimental reports of time-reversal-symmetry breaking and rotational anisotropy, we consider the interdependence of flux and bond orders. Deriving the relevant Landau free energy for possible orders, we study the effect of symmetry-breaking perturbations such as strain and magnetic fields. Our results, thus, provide a roadmap for future tests of these intricate orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.02528v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 108, 125136 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Glenn Wagner, Chunyu Guo, Philip J. W. Moll, Titus Neupert, Mark H. Fischer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Hall conductivity of a valence bond solid phase in the square lattice $J_1$-$J_2$ antiferromagnet Heisenberg model with a Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12563v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate the thermal Hall conductivity $\kappa_{xy}$ for the columnar valence-bond solid phase of a two-dimensional frustrated antiferromagnet. In particular, we consider the square lattice spin-$1/2$ $J_1$-$J_2$ antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model with an additional Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction between the spins and in the presence of an external magnetic field. We concentrate on the intermediate parameter region of the $J_1$-$J_2$ model, where a quantum paramagnetic phase is stable, and consider a Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya vector pattern associated with the couplings between the spins in the CuO$_2$ planes of the YBCO compound. We describe the columnar valence-bond solid phase within the bond-operator formalism, which allows us to map the Heisenberg model into an effective interacting boson model written in terms of triplet operators. The effective boson model is studied within the harmonic approximation and the triplon excitation bands of the columnar valence-bond solid phase is determined. We then calculate the Berry curvature and the Chern numbers of the triplon excitation bands and, finally, determine the thermal Hall conductivity due to triplons as a function of the temperature. We find that the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction yields a finite Berry curvature for the triplon bands, but the corresponding Chern numbers vanish. Although the triplon excitations are topologically trivial, the thermal Hall conductivity of the columnar valence-bond solid phase in the square lattice antiferromagnet is finite at low temperatures. We comment on the relations of our results with a {\sl no-go} condition for a thermal Hall effect previously derived for ordered magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12563v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.134405</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lucas S. Buzo, R. L. Doretto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An occupation number quantum subspace expansion approach to compute the single-particle Green function: an opportunity for noise filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13497v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a hybrid quantum-classical algorithm to compute the Green function for strongly correlated electrons on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. The technique consists in the construction of a non-orthogonal excitation basis composed of a set of single-particle excitations generated by occupation number operators. The excited sectors of the Hamiltonian in this basis can then be measured on the quantum device and a classical post-processing procedure yields the Green function in the Lehmann representation. The technique allows for noise filtering, a useful feature for NISQ devices. To validate the approach, we carry out a set of proof-of-principle calculations on the single-band Hubbard model on IBM quantum hardware. For a 2 site system we find good agreement between the results of quantum simulations and the exact result for the local spectral function. This proof-of-principle also shows that the noise filtering provides a reliable way to get rid of satellite peaks present in the spectral weight obtained from a NISQ device. A simulation of a 4 site system carried out on classical hardware suggests that the approach can achieve similar accuracy for larger systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13497v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.032624</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110 (2024) 032624</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>B. Gauthier, P. Rosenberg, A. Foley, M. Charlebois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Category of SET orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15958v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose the representation principle to study physical systems with a given symmetry. In the context of symmetry enriched topological orders, we give the appropriate representation category, the category of SET orders, which include SPT orders and symmetry breaking orders as special cases. For fusion n-category symmetries, we show that the category of SET orders encodes almost all information about the interplay between symmetry and topological orders, in a natural and canonical way. These information include defects and boundaries of SET orders, symmetry charges, explicit and spontaneous symmetry breaking, stacking of SET orders, gauging of generalized symmetry, as well as quantum currents (SymTFT or symmetry TO). We also provide a detailed categorical algorithm to compute the generalized gauging. In particular, we proved that gauging is always reversible, as a special type of Morita-equivalence. The explicit data for ungauging, the inverse to gauging, is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15958v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian Lan, Gen Yue, Longye Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The two-dimensional homogeneous electron gas with symmetric dual-gate screening: exchange-correlation functional and other ground-state properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07445v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The two-dimensional (2D) homogeneous electron gas (HEG) is a fundamental model in quantum many-body physics. It is important to theoretical and computational studies, where exchange-correlation energies computed in it serve as the foundation for density-functional calculations. It is also of direct relevance to a variety of experimental settings, especially with the rapid recent growth in 2D materials and moir\'e systems. In these experiments, metallic gates are often present, which screen the Coulomb interaction between electrons. The effect of the screening can qualitatively change the behavior of the 2D HEG, and requires accurate many-body computations to capture. In this work, we perform state-of-the-art diffusion Monte Carlo (DMC) calculations in the 2D HEG subjected to symmetric dual-gate screening. We systematically compute the correlation energy across a range of densities and gate separations for both spin unpolarized and fully polarized systems. A global fit is obtained for the correlation energy, using these data and imposing various limiting behaviors obtained from perturbation analysis. The new functional will allow density-functional calculations to be performed for a variety of realistic experimental setups which can accurately account for the presence of gates. We also investigate how the gate screening affects the bulk modulus, pair correlation function, and the structure factor of the 2D HEG, which can potentially be probed in experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07445v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiqi Yang, Yubo Yang, Kun Chen, Miguel A. Morales, Shiwei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum spin glasses and Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17824v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A brief survey of some random quantum models with infinite-range couplings is presented. Insights from such models have led to advances in the quantum theory of charged black holes in spatial dimensions $d \geq 3$, and to a universal theory of strange metals in correlated electron materials in $d=2$; these are also briefly reviewed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17824v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subir Sachdev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective excitations in magnetic topological insulators and axion dark matter search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09705v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate collective excitations in magnetic topological insulators (TIs) and their impact on particle axion detection. In the three-dimensional TI model with the Hubbard term, the effective action of magnons and amplitude modes is formulated by dynamical susceptibility under the antiferromagnetic and ferromagnetic states. One of the amplitude modes is identified as ``axionic'' quasi-particle and its effective coupling to the electromagnetic fields turns out to be enhanced by about four orders of magnitude larger than the previous estimate, which may drastically change the sensitivity of the particle axion search using ``axion'' in magnetic TIs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09705v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2024)225</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP10(2024)225</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Koji Ishiwata, Kentaro Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superfluid Stiffness and Flat-Band Superconductivity in Magic-Angle Graphene Probed by cQED</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13740v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The physics of superconductivity in magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG) is a topic of keen interest in moir\'e systems research, and it may provide insight into the pairing mechanism of other strongly correlated materials such as high-$T_{\mathrm{c}}$ superconductors. Here, we use DC-transport and microwave circuit quantum electrodynamics (cQED) to measure directly the superfluid stiffness of superconducting MATBG via its kinetic inductance. We find the superfluid stiffness to be much larger than expected from conventional Fermi liquid theory; rather, it is comparable to theoretical predictions involving quantum geometric effects that are dominant at the magic angle. The temperature dependence of the superfluid stiffness follows a power-law, which contraindicates an isotropic BCS model; instead, the extracted power-law exponents indicate an anisotropic superconducting gap, whether interpreted within the Fermi liquid framework or by considering quantum geometry of flat-band superconductivity. Moreover, a quadratic dependence of the superfluid stiffness on both DC and microwave current is observed, which is consistent with Ginzburg-Landau theory. Taken together, our findings indicate that MATBG is an unconventional superconductor with an anisotropic gap and strongly suggest a connection between quantum geometry, superfluid stiffness, and unconventional superconductivity in MATBG. The combined DC-microwave measurement platform used here is applicable to the investigation of other atomically thin superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13740v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miuko Tanaka, Joel \^I-j. Wang, Thao H. Dinh, Daniel Rodan-Legrain, Sameia Zaman, Max Hays, Bharath Kannan, Aziza Almanakly, David K. Kim, Bethany M. Niedzielski, Kyle Serniak, Mollie E. Schwartz, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Jeffrey A. Grover, Terry P. Orlando, Simon Gustavsson, Pablo Jarillo-Herrero, William D. Oliver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal crossover from a Chern insulator to a fractional Chern insulator in pentalayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10931v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By theoretically analyzing the recent temperature dependent transport data in pentalayer graphene [Lu et al., arXiv:2408.10203], we establish that the experimentally observed transition from low-temperature quantum anomalous Hall effect to higher-temperature fractional quantum anomalous Hall effect is a crossover phenomenon arising from the competition between interaction and disorder energy scales, with the likely zero temperature ground state of the system being either a localized insulator or a Chern insulator with a quantized anomalous Hall effect. In particular, the intriguing suppression of FQAHE in favor of QAHE with decreasing temperature is explained as arising from the low-temperature localization of the carriers where disorder overcomes the interaction effects. We provide a detailed analysis of the data in support of the crossover scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10931v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.155148</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 155148 (2024) - Editors' Suggestion</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sankar Das Sarma, Ming Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating real-time molecular electron dynamics efficiently using the time-dependent density matrix renormalization group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05959v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Compared to ground state electronic structure optimizations, accurate simulations of molecular real-time electron dynamics are usually much more difficult to perform. To simulate electron dynamics, the time-dependent density matrix renormalization group (TDDMRG) has been shown to offer an attractive compromise between accuracy and cost. However, many simulation parameters significantly affect the quality and efficiency of a TDDMRG simulation. So far, it is unclear whether common wisdom from ground state DMRG carries over to the TDDMRG, and a guideline on how to choose these parameters is missing. Here, in order to establish such a guideline, we investigate the convergence behavior of the main TDDMRG simulation parameters, such as time integrator, the choice of orbitals, and the choice of MPS representation for complex-valued non-singlet states. In addition, we propose a method to select orbitals that are tailored to optimize the dynamics. Lastly, we showcase the TDDMRG by applying it to charge migration ionization dynamics in furfural, where we reveal a rapid conversion from an ionized state with a $\sigma$ character to one with a $\pi$ character within less than a femtosecond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05959v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imam S. Wahyutama, Henrik R. Larsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Mutual Gauge Field in Microwave-Shielded Polar Molecular Gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10806v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The recent breakthrough of realizing the Bose-Einstein condensate of polar molecules and degenerate Fermi molecules in three dimensions relies crucially on the microwave shielding technique, which strongly suppresses the collision loss between molecules. In this letter, we show that the cooperation of microwave shielding and dipolar interaction naturally leads to the emergence of a synthetic gauge field. Unlike that studied in cold atoms before, this gauge field couples to the relative motion of every two molecules instead of single-particle motion, therefore being a mutual gauge field. In this case, every molecule carrying a synthetic charge sees the other molecule as carrying the source of the magnetic field, and the spatial distribution of the magnetic field is reminiscent of a solenoid attached to the molecule. In other words, in addition to microwave-shielded interaction, another part of the interaction between two molecules behaves as a charge interacting with a solenoid, which was missed in the previous discussion. We argue that the physical manifestation of this gauge field is breaking time-reversal symmetry in the collective spatial motion of molecules. Finally, we discuss the challenges in quantitatively studying such a quantum many-body system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10806v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bei Xu, Fan Yang, Ran Qi, Hui Zhai, Peng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
