<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 04:01:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Attractive Haldane bilayers for trapping non-Abelian anyons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the interplay between intrinsic topological order and superconductivity in a two-component Haldane bilayer, where the two layers are coupled by an attractive force. We obtain the phase diagram of the model with exact diagonalization in finite-size, and develop arguments to assess the stability of the observed phases in the thermodynamic limit. Our main result is that a finite critical attraction strength is needed to pair fermions forming a fractional topological order. This behavior can be harnessed to create clean interfaces between a fractional topological insulator and a superconductor by gating, wherein non-Abelian parafermionic modes are trapped. We discuss realization of such interfaces in the bulk of double bilayers of transition metal dichalcogenides by inhomogenous electrostatic gating, which should mitigate the spurious effects of disorder and crystalline defects present on physical edges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05622v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentin Cr\'epel, Nicolas Regnault</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipolar magnetism in $5d^2$ vacancy-ordered halide double perovskites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vacancy-ordered halide double perovskites hosting 4d/5d transition metals have emerged as a distinct platform for investigating unconventional magnetism arising out of the interplay of strong atomic spin-orbit coupling (SOC) and Coulomb interactions. Focusing on the $d^2$ system Cs$_2$WCl$_6$, our ab initio electronic structure calculation reveals very narrow electronic bands, fulfilling the necessary condition to realize exotic orders. Using this input, we solve the many-body spin-orbit coupled single-site problem by exact diagonalization and show that the multiplet structure of Cs$_2$WCl$_6$ hosts ground non-Kramers doublets on W, with vanishing dipole moment and a small gap to an excited magnetic triplet. Our work provides the rationale for the observed strong deviation from the classic Kotani behaviour in Cs$_2$WCl$_6$ for the measured temperature dependence of the magnetic moment. The non-Kramers doublets on W exhibit non-zero quadrupolar and octupolar moments, and our calculated two-site exchange supports the dominance of inter-site octupolar exchange over quadrupolar interactions. We predict ferro-octupolar order with a transition temperature $T_c \sim 5$K which may get somewhat suppressed by quantum fluctuations and disorder; this could be tested in future low-temperature experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05633v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koushik Pradhan, Arun Paramekanti, Tanusri Saha-Dasgupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do we learn from impurities and disorder in High Tc cuprates?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We established that the morphology of the phase diagrams is mostly governed by disorder in the various cuprate families. In the minimally disordered YBCO substitutions of Zn or Li spinless impurities on the planar Cu sites control the extent of the spin glass phase and superconducting (SC) dome. NMR data establish that these defects induce in their vicinity a cloud with a Kondo like paramagnetic behavior that differs markedly between the pseudogap and strange metal regimes. We have studied the evolution of transport properties with disorder by introduction of a controlled content of in plane vacancies by electron irradiation. At high T the inelastic scattering of the carriers is surprisingly disorder independent, and governed by the excitations of the correlated electronic state. The low T upturns of the resistivity, that are associated with single impurity Kondo like scattering, agree qualitatively with the local magnetism induced by spinless impurities. Very large defect contents are required to induce Metal Insulator Crossovers. In the SC state, the defect induced reduction of Tc scales quasi linearly with residual resistivity. The paraconductivity due to SC fluctuations, deduced from high field magnetoresistance measurements vanishes beyond a temperature T//c and a field H//c that decrease with increasing defect content. In the pseudogap regime the weaker decrease of T//c with respect to that of Tc reveals a loss of SC phase coherence in presence of disorder. This initiates a discussion of its interplay with pair breaking and allows us to confirm that the family specific dopant induced disorder or order controls the phase diagram. In the ideal disorder free cuprate the 2D SC state would certainly persist at low doping. This ensemble of data provides serious challenges for the theoretical understanding of superconductivity and the normal state in these SC correlated electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05889v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henri Alloul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Spin-Orbit Exciton-Magnon Excitations in FePS$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: FePS$_3$ is a layered van der Waals (vdW) Ising antiferromagnet that has recently been studied in the context of true 2D magnetism, and emerged as an ideal material platform for investigating strong spin-phonon coupling, and non-linear magneto-optical phenomena. In this work, we demonstrate an important unresolved role of spin-orbit coupling (SOC) in the ground state and excitations of this compound. Combining first principles calculations with Linear Flavor Wave Theory (LFWT), we find strong mixing and spectral overlap of different spin-orbital single-ion states. As such, the low-lying excitations form complex mixtures of local degrees of freedom most accurately viewed as hybrid spin-orbit exciton-magnon modes. Complete parameterization of the resulting low-energy model including all such degrees of freedom requires nearly half a million coupling constants. Despite this complexity, we show that such a model can be inexpensively derived using local many-body-based approaches, which yield quantitative agreement with recent experiments. The results highlight the importance of SOC even in first row transition metals, and provide essential insight into the properties of 2D magnets with unquenched orbital moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05958v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ramesh Dhakal, Samuel Griffith, Stephen M. Winter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical generation of skyrmion and bimeron crystals by a circularly polarized electric field in frustrated magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06118v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A skyrmion crystal (SkX) has attracted much attention in condensed matter physics, since topologically nontrivial structures induce fascinating physical phenomena. The SkXs have been experimentally observed in a variety of materials, where the Zeeman coupling to the static magnetic field plays an important role in the formation of the SkXs. In this study, we theoretically propose another route to generate the SkXs by using a circularly polarized electric field. We investigate a non-equilibrium steady state in a classical frustrated Heisenberg magnet under the circularly polarized electric field, where the electric field is coupled to the electric polarization via the spin-current mechanism. By numerically solving the Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert equation at zero temperature, we show that the electric field radiation generates a SkX with a high topological number in the high-frequency regime, where the sign of the skyrmion number is fixed to be negative (positive) under the left (right) circularly polarized field. The intense electric field melts these SkXs and generates isolated skyrmions. We clarify that the microscopic origin is effective electric-field-induced three-spin interactions by adopting the high-frequency expansion in the Floquet formalism. Furthermore, we find that the electric field radiation generates another type of SkXs, a bimeron crystal, in the low-frequency regime. Our results provide a way to generate the SkXs and control the topology by the circularly polarized electric field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06118v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Yambe, Satoru Hayami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Periodically driven three-dimensional Kitaev model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06123v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of a three-dimensional generalization of Kitaev's honeycomb lattice spin model (defined on the hyperhoneycomb lattice) subjected to a harmonic driving of $J_z$, one of the three types of spin-couplings in the Hamiltonian. Using numerical solutions supported by analytical calculations based on a rotating wave approximation, we find that the system responds nonmonotonically to variations in the frequency $\omega$ (while keeping the driving amplitude $J$ fixed) and undergoes dynamical freezing, where at specific values of $\omega$, it gets almost completely locked in the initial state throughout the evolution. However, this freezing occurs only when a constant bias is present in the driving, i.e., when $J_z = J'+ J\cos{\omega t}$, with $J'\neq 0$. Consequently, the bias acts as a switch that triggers the freezing phenomenon. Dynamical freezing has been previously observed in other integrable systems, such as the one-dimensional transverse-field Ising model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06123v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Sasidharan, Naveen Surendran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral Spin-Liquid-Like State in Pyrochlore Iridate Thin Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pyrochlore iridates have become ideal platforms to unravel fascinating correlated and topolog?ical phenomena that stem from the intricate interplay among strong spin-orbit coupling, electronic correlations, lattice with geometric frustration, and itinerancy of the 5d electrons. The all-in-all?out antiferromagnetic state, commonly considered as the magnetic ground state, can be dramatically altered in reduced dimensionality, leading to exotic or hidden quantum states inaccessible in bulk. Here, by means of magnetotransport, resonant elastic and inelastic x-ray scattering experiments, we discover an emergent quantum disordered state in (111) Y2Ir2O7 thin films (thickness less than 30 nm) per?sisting down to 5 K, characterized by dispersionless magnetic excitations. The anomalous Hall effect observed below an onset temperature near 135 K corroborates the presence of chiral short-range spin configurations expressed in non-zero scalar spin chirality, breaking the macroscopic time-reversal symmetry. The origin of this chiral state is ascribed to the restoration of magnetic frustration on the pyrochlore lattice in lower dimensionality, where the competing exchange interactions together with enhanced quantum fluctuations suppress any long-range order and trigger spin-liquid-like behavior with degenerate ground-state manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06170v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoran Liu, Jong-Woo Kim, Yao Wang, Michael Terilli, Xun Jia, Mikhail Kareev, Shiyu Peng, Fangdi Wen, Tsung-Chi Wu, Huyongqing Chen, Wanzheng Hu, Mary H. Upton, Jungho Kim, Yongseong Choi, Daniel Haskel, Hongming Weng, Philip J. Ryan, Yue Cao, Yang Qi, Jiandong Guo, Jak Chakhalian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel quantum spin liquid ground state in the trimer rhodate Ba$_4$NbRh$_3$O$_{12}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Frustrated magnets offer a plethora of exotic magnetic ground states, including quantum spin liquids (QSLs), in which enhanced quantum fluctuations prevent a long-range magnetic ordering of the strongly correlated spins down to lowest temperature. Here we have investigated the trimer based mixed valence hexagonal rhodate Ba$_4$NbRh$_3$O$_{12}$ using a combination of dc and ac magnetization, electrical resistivity, specific heat, and muon spin rotation/relaxation ($\mu$SR) measurements. Despite the substantial antiferromagnetic exchange interactions, as evident from the Weiss temperature ($\theta_{\mathrm{W}}\sim -35$ to -45 K), among the Rh-local moments, neither long-range magnetic ordering nor spin-freezing is observed down to at least 50 mK, in ac-susceptibility, specific heat and ZF-$\mu$SR measurements (down to 0.26 K). We ascribe the absence of any magnetic transition to enhanced quantum fluctuations as a result of geometrical frustration arising out of the edge-sharing equilateral Rh-triangular network in the structure. Our longitudinal-field $\mu$SR result evidences persistent spin fluctuations down to 0.26~K, thus stabilizing a dynamic QSL ground state in Ba$_4$NbRh$_3$O$_{12}$. Furthermore, the magnetic specific heat ($C_{\mathrm{m}}$) data at low-$T$ reveal a significant $T$-linear contribution plus a quadratic $T$-dependence. A $T$-linear behavior is evocative of gapless spin excitations, while the $T^2$-term of $C_{\mathrm{m}}$ may indicate the Dirac QSL phenomenology of the spinon excitations with a linear dispersion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06446v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhisek Bandyopadhyay, S. Lee, D. T. Adroja, G. B. G. Stenning, Adam Berlie, M. R. Lees, R. A. Saha, D. Takegami, A. Melendez-Sans, G. Poelchen, M. Yoshimura, K. D. Tsuei, Z. Hu, Cheng-Wei Kao, Yu-Cheng Huang, Ting-Shan Chan, Kwang-Yong Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Pseudo-Random Number Generators in QMC-SSE Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06450v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) method, the Pseudo-Random Number Generator (PRNG) plays a crucial role in determining the computation time. However, the hidden structure of the PRNG may lead to serious issues such as the breakdown of the Markov process. Here, we systematically analyze the performance of the different PRNGs on the widely used QMC method -- stochastic series expansion (SSE) algorithm. To quantitatively compare them, we introduce a quantity called QMC efficiency that can effectively reflect the efficiency of the algorithms. After testing several representative observables of the Heisenberg model in one and two dimensions, we recommend using LCG as the best choice of PRNGs. Our work can not only help improve the performance of the SSE method but also shed light on the other Markov-chain-based numerical algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06450v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-1056/ad1e69</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Published in Chin. Phys. B 33, 037509 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dong-Xu Liu, Wei Xu, Xue-Feng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$^{27}$Al NMR study of the magnetic Weyl semimetal CeAlGe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the recent observations of electronic correlation effect [M. Corasaniti \textit{et al}., Phys. Rev. B \textbf{104}, L121112 (2021)] and topology-stabilized magnetic fluctuations [N. Drucker \textit{et al}., Nat. Commun. \textbf{14}, 5182 (2023)] in the noncentrosymmetric magnetic Weyl semimetal candidate CeAlGe, we performed systematic studies on the local static and dynamic spin susceptibilities by $^{27}$Al nuclear magnetic resonance. Due to the large spin susceptibility from Ce-$4f$ electrons, the theoretically predicted responses from Weyl fermions are overwhelmed. A Knight-shift anomaly is observed below $T^*\sim50$ K, a signature of the onset of coherent Kondo coupling. In addition, an anomalous peak is found in $1/T_1T$ near 15 K, well above the magnetic ordering temperature $T_N \approx 5$ K, which probably is a consequence of topology-stabilized magnetic fluctuations. These results highlight the interplay among electronic correlation, magnetism and band topology in this family of Kondo Weyl semimetals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06476v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuo Wang, Xiaobo He, Fangjun Lu, Hai Zeng, Shuo Zou, Xiao-Xiao Zhang, Yongkang Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement and logarithmic spirals in a quantum spin-1 many-body system with competing dimer and trimer interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB) with type-B Goldstone modes is investigated in the macroscopically degenerate phase for a quantum spin-1 many-body system with competing dimer and trimer interactions. The SSB involves three distinct patterns. The first occurs at the dimer point, with the pattern from staggered ${\rm SU}(3)$ to ${\rm U}(1)\times{\rm U}(1)$. The second occurs at the trimer point, with the pattern from uniform ${\rm SU}(3)$ to ${\rm U}(1)\times{\rm U}(1)$. The third occurs in the dimer-trimer regime, with the pattern from uniform ${\rm SU}(2)$ to ${\rm U}(1)$. The number of type-B Goldstone modes is thus two, two and one for the three patterns, respectively. The ground state degeneracies arising from the three patterns are exponential with the system size, which may be recognized as sequences of integers relevant to self-similar logarithmic spirals. This in turn is attributed to the presence of an emergent symmetry operation tailored to a specific degenerate ground state. As a consequence, the residual entropy is non-zero, which measures the disorder present in a unit cell of highly degenerate ground state generated from a generalized highest weight state. An exact Schmidt decomposition exists for the highly degenerate ground states, thus exposing the self-similarities underlying an abstract fractal, described by the fractal dimension. The latter is extracted from performing a universal finite system-size scaling analysis of the entanglement entropy, which is identical to the number of type-B Goldstone modes. The model under investigation thus accommodates an exotic scale invariant quantum state of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06825v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huan-Qiang Zhou, Qian-Qian Shi, Ian P. McCulloch, Murray T. Batchelor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal conductivity of nonunitary triplet superconductors: application to UTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There is considerable evidence that the heavy fermion material UTe$_2$ is a spin-triplet superconductor, possibly manifesting time-reversal symmetry breaking, as measured by Kerr effect and muon spin resonance experiments below the critical temperature, in some samples. Such signals can arise due to a chiral orbital state, or possible nonunitary pairing. Although experiments at low $T$ appear to be consistent with point nodes in the spectral gap, the detailed form of the order parameter and even the nodal positions are not yet determined. Thermal conductivity measurements can extend to quite low temperatures, with varying heat current direction can therefore provide information on the order parameter structure. Here we derive a general expression for the thermal conductivity of a spin triplet superconductor, and use it to compare the low-temperature behavior of various states proposed for UTe$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05917v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vivek Mishra, Ge Wang, P. J. Hirschfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Path Integral for Chord Diagrams and Chaotic-Integrable Transitions in Double Scaled SYK</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05980v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study transitions from chaotic to integrable Hamiltonians in the double scaled SYK and $p$-spin systems. The dynamics of our models is described by chord diagrams with two species. We begin by developing a path integral formalism of coarse graining chord diagrams with a single species of chords, which has the same equations of motion as the bi-local ($G\Sigma$) Liouville action, yet appears otherwise to be different and in particular well defined. We then develop a similar formalism for two types of chords, allowing us to study different types of deformations of double scaled SYK and in particular a deformation by an integrable Hamiltonian. The system has two distinct thermodynamic phases: one is continuously connected to the chaotic SYK Hamiltonian, the other is continuously connected to the integrable Hamiltonian, separated at low temperature by a first order phase transition. We also analyze the phase diagram for generic deformations, which in some cases includes a zero-temperature phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05980v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha Berkooz, Nadav Brukner, Yiyang Jia, Ohad Mamroud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>van Hove Singularity-Driven Emergence of Multiple Flat Bands in Kagome Superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06085v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The newly discovered Kagome superconductors AV$_3$Sb$_5$ (A=K, Rb and Cs) continue to bring surprises in generating unusual phenomena and physical properties, including anomalous Hall effect, unconventional charge density wave, electronic nematicity and time-reversal symmetry breaking. Here we report an unexpected emergence of multiple flat bands in the AV$_3$Sb$_5$ superconductors. By performing high-resolution angle-resolved photoemission (ARPES) measurements, we observed four branches of flat bands that span over the entire momentum space. The appearance of the flat bands is not anticipated from the band structure calculations and cannot be accounted for by the known mechanisms of flat band generation. It is intimately related to the evolution of van Hove singularities. It is for the first time to observe such emergence of multiple flat bands in solid materials. Our findings provide new insights in revealing the underlying mechanism that governs the unusual behaviors in the Kagome superconductors. They also provide a new pathway in producing flat bands and set a platform to study the flat bands related physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06085v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hailan Luo, Lin Zhao, Zhen Zhao, Haitao Yang, Yun-Peng Huang, Hongxiong Liu, Yuhao Gu, Feng Jin, Hao Chen, Taimin Miao, Chaohui Yin, Chengmin Shen, Xiaolin Ren, Bo Liang, Yingjie Shu, Yiwen Chen, Fengfeng Zhang, Feng Yang, Shenjin Zhang, Qinjun Peng, Hanqing Mao, Guodong Liu, Jiangping Hu, Youguo Shi, Zuyan Xu, Kun Jiang, Qingming Zhang, Ziqiang Wang, Hongjun Gao, X. J. Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation of artificial Fermi surfaces with a triangular superlattice on a conventional two dimensional electron gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In nearly free electron theory the imposition of a periodic electrostatic potential on free electrons creates the bandstructure of a material, determined by the crystal lattice spacing and geometry. Imposing an artificially designed potential to the electrons confined in a GaAs quantum well makes it possible to engineer synthetic two-dimensional band structures, with electronic properties different from those in the host semiconductor. Here we report the fabrication and study of a tuneable triangular artificial lattice on a GaAs/AlGaAs heterostructure where it is possible to transform from the original GaAs bandstructure and Fermi surface to a new bandstructure with multiple artificial Fermi surfaces simply by altering a gate bias. For weak electrostatic potential modulation magnetotransport measurements reveal quantum oscillations from the GaAs two-dimensional Fermi surface, and classical oscillations due to these electrons scattering from the artificial lattice. Increasing the strength of the modulation reveals new quantum oscillations due to the formation of multiple artificial Fermi surfaces, and ultimately to new classical oscillations of the electrons from the artificial Fermi surface scattering from the superlattice modulation. These results show that low disorder gate-tuneable lateral superlattices can be used to form artificial two dimensional crystals with designer electronic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06426v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.2c04358</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daisy Q. Wang, Zeb Krix, Oleg P. Sushkov, Ian Farrer, David A. Ritchie, Alexander R. Hamilton, Oleh Klochan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional topological mixed-state transition and critical phase induced by self-dual coherent errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A topological phase can undergo a phase transition driven by anyon condensation. A potential obstruction to such a mechanism could arise if there exists a symmetry between anyons that have non-trivial mutual statistics. Here we consider toric code subjected to errors that tend to proliferate anyons with non-trivial mutual statistics. Using triangle inequality, we show that in the presence of electromagnetic duality and a partial-transpose symmetry, a decoherence induced phase transition out of the topological phase must be rather unconventional and lie beyond standard rules of anyon condensation. To explore such physics, we first subject toric code to a self-dual quantum channel where Kraus operators are proportional to X+Z. We find that the topological phase is stable up to the maximal error rate, when viewing density matrix as a pure state in the double Hilbert space. To access an unconventional transition, we then consider a perturbed toric code subjected to the self-dual channel, and find numerical evidence that beyond a critical error rate, the topological phase is destroyed resulting in a critical phase where anyons are only power-law condensed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06553v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Hsueh Chen, Tarun Grover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of magnetic order and ferroelasticity in the spin-orbit coupled antiferromagnet K$_2$ReCl$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.11101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.11101v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The magnetic and structural phase transitions occurring in K$_2$ReCl$_6$ were studied by macroscopic and microscopic techniques. Structural phase transitions associated with rotations of the ReCl$_6$ octahedra lower the symmetry from cubic to monoclinic, form ferroelastic domains, and are visible in susceptibility, specific heat and thermal expansion measurements. In the antiferromagnetically ordered state slightly below $T_{\rm N}$=12\,K these domains can be rearranged by a magnetic field inducing a relative elongation of the polydomain crystal parallel to the field of 0.6\%. At zero field the magnetic structure in K$_2$ReCl$_6$ does not exhibit a weak ferromagnetic component, but at large magnetic field a distinct magnetic structure with a finite weak ferromagnetic component is stabilized. High magnetic fields rearrange the domains in the crystal to align the weak ferromagnetic moment parallel to the field. The altered domain structure with the crystal elongation is abruptly suppressed at lower temperature but persists upon heating to well above $T_{\rm N}$. However, heating above the lowest structural phase transition and successive cooling restore the initial shape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.11101v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Bertin, Tusharkanti Dey, Daniel Br\"uning, Dmitry Gorkov, Kevin Jenni, Astin Krause, Petra Becker, Ladislav Bohaty, Daniel Khomskii, Vladimir Pomjakushin, Lukas Keller, Markus Braden, Thomas Lorenz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified quasiparticle approach to the theory of strongly correlated electron liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.19385v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Landau's quasiparticle formalism is generalized to describe a wide class of strongly correlated Fermi systems, in addition to conventional Fermi liquids. This class includes (i) so-called marginal exemplars and (ii) systems that harbor interaction-driven flat bands, in both of which manifestations of non-Fermi-liquid behavior are well documented. Specifically, the advent of such flat bands is attributed to a spontaneous topological rearrangement of the Landau state that supplements the conventional Landau quasiparticle picture with a different set of quasiparticles, the so-called fermion condensate, whose single-particle spectrum is dispersionless. The celebrated Landau-Luttinger theorem is extended to marginal Fermi liquids, in which the density of the augmented quasiparticle system is shown to coincide with the particle density. On the other hand, the total density of a system hosting an interaction-driven flat band turns out to be the sum of the densities of the two quasiparticle subsystems: the Landau-like component and the fermion condensate. We demonstrate that within the framework of the scenario proposed, a long-standing problem faced by theories of $D$-wave superconductivity in cuprates, namely a consistent explanation of the so-called Uemera plot, can be naturally resolved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.19385v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aop.2024.169622</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Annals of Physics 463 (2024) 169622</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Khodel, J. W. Clark, M. V. Zverev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning reveals features of spinon Fermi surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03143v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With rapid progress in simulation of strongly interacting quantum Hamiltonians, the challenge in characterizing unknown phases becomes a bottleneck for scientific progress. We demonstrate that a Quantum-Classical hybrid approach (QuCl) of mining sampled projective snapshots with interpretable classical machine learning can unveil signatures of seemingly featureless quantum states. The Kitaev-Heisenberg model on a honeycomb lattice under external magnetic field presents an ideal system to test QuCl, where simulations have found an intermediate gapless phase (IGP) sandwiched between known phases, launching a debate over its elusive nature. We use the correlator convolutional neural network, trained on labeled projective snapshots, in conjunction with regularization path analysis to identify signatures of phases. We show that QuCl reproduces known features of established phases. Significantly, we also identify a signature of the IGP in the spin channel perpendicular to the field direction, which we interpret as a signature of Friedel oscillations of gapless spinons forming a Fermi surface. Our predictions can guide future experimental searches for spin liquids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03143v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-024-01542-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun. Phys. 7, 54 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Zhang, Shi Feng, Yuri D. Lensky, Nandini Trivedi, Eun-Ah Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum criticality and entanglement for two dimensional long-range Heisenberg bilayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05465v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of quantum criticality and entanglement in systems with long-range (LR) interactions is still in its early stages, with many open questions remaining. In this work, we investigate critical exponents and scaling of entanglement entropies (EE) in the LR bilayer Heisenberg model using large-scale quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) simulations and the recently developed nonequilibrium increment algorithm for measuring EE. By applying modified (standard) finite-size scaling (FSS) above (below) the upper critical dimension and field theory analysis, we obtain precise critical exponents in three regimes: the LR Gaussian regime with a Gaussian fixed point, the short-range (SR) regime with Wilson-Fisher (WF) exponents, and a LR non-Gaussian regime where the critical exponents vary continuously from LR Gaussian to SR values. We compute the R\'enyi EE both along the critical line and in the N\'eel phase and observe that as the LR interaction is enhanced, the area-law contribution in EE gradually vanishes both at quantum critical points (QCPs) and in the N\'eel phase. The log-correction in EE arising from sharp corners at the QCPs also decays to zero as LR interaction grows, whereas the log-correction for N\'eel states, caused by the interplay of Goldstone modes and restoration of the symmetry in a finite system, is enhanced as LR interaction becomes stronger. We also discuss relevant experimental settings to detect these nontrivial properties in critical behavior and entanglement information for quantum many-body systems with LR interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05465v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, L081114, Vol. 109, Iss. 8, 15 February 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Menghan Song, Jiarui Zhao, Yang Qi, Junchen Rong, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral spin liquid phase in an optical lattice at mean-field level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16466v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study an optical Raman square lattice with $\mathrm{U}(1)$ synthetic gauge flux to show chiral spin liquid (CSL) phase for cold atoms based on slave-rotor theory and spinon mean-field theory, respectively. An effective U($1$) gauge flux generated by Raman potentials plays a major role in realizing the CSL phase. By using slave-rotor techniques we find CSL phase at intermediate on-site Fermi Hubbard interacting regime. For the strong interacting regime we derive an effective spin model including up to the four spin interactions. By spinon mean-field analysis it is shown that CSL phase is stabilized in the case of strong magnetic frustration. The two mean-field approximation methods give consistent phase diagrams and provide qualitative numerical evidence of the CSL phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16466v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Yang, Xiong-Jun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lieb-Schultz-Mattis anomalies as obstructions to gauging (non-on-site) symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.05151v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study 't Hooft anomalies of global symmetries in 1+1d lattice Hamiltonian systems. We consider anomalies in internal and lattice translation symmetries. We derive a microscopic formula for the "anomaly cocycle" using topological defects implementing twisted boundary conditions. The anomaly takes value in the cohomology group $H^3(G,U(1)) \times H^2(G,U(1))$. The first factor captures the anomaly in the internal symmetry group $G$, and the second factor corresponds to a generalized Lieb-Schultz-Mattis anomaly involving $G$ and lattice translation. We present a systematic procedure to gauge internal symmetries (that may not act on-site) on the lattice. We show that the anomaly cocycle is the obstruction to gauging the internal symmetry while preserving the lattice translation symmetry. As an application, we construct anomaly-free chiral lattice gauge theories. We demonstrate a one-to-one correspondence between (locality-preserving) symmetry operators and topological defects, which is essential for the results we prove. We also discuss the generalization to fermionic theories. Finally, we construct non-invertible lattice translation symmetries by gauging internal symmetries with a Lieb-Schultz-Mattis anomaly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.05151v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahand Seifnashri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monopoles in Dirac spin liquids and their symmetries from instanton calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06748v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Dirac spin liquid (DSL) is a two-dimensional (2D) fractionalized Mott insulator featuring massless Dirac spinon excitations coupled to a compact $U(1)$ gauge field, which allows for flux-tunneling instanton events described by magnetic monopoles in (2+1)D Euclidean spacetime. The state-operator correspondence of conformal field theory has been used recently to define associated monopole operators and determine their quantum numbers, which encode the microscopic symmetries of conventional ordered phases proximate to the DSL. In this work, we utilize semiclassical instanton methods not relying on conformal invariance to construct monopole operators directly in (2+1)D spacetime as instanton-induced 't Hooft vertices, i.e., fermion-number-violating effective interactions originating from zero modes of the Euclidean Dirac operator in an instanton background. In the presence of a flavor-adjoint fermion mass, resummation of the instanton gas is shown to select the correct monopole to be proliferated, in accordance with predictions of the state-operator correspondence. We also show that our instanton-based approach is able to determine monopole quantum numbers on bipartite lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06748v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Shankar, Joseph Maciejko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular orbital formation and metastable short-range ordered structure in VO$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10193v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The metal-insulator transition (MIT) in vanadium dioxide VO$_2$ due to V-V dimerization has been extensively discussed for decades. While it is widely acknowledged that electron correlations, Peierls instabilities, and molecular orbital formations are crucial for understanding the MIT of VO$_2$, the primary origin of the MIT remains controversial. In this study, we delve into the crystal structure and orbital state of VO$_2$ through synchrotron x-ray diffraction experiments. The molecular orbital formation corresponding to the V-V dimerization is directly observed in the low-temperature insulating monoclinic phase, called the M1 phase, as indicated by the valence electron density distribution. Moreover, diffuse scattering observed in the high-temperature metal phase of rutile structure suggests the presence of short-range correlation of V displacements, which is not directly attributed to the structural fluctuation of the M1 phase. The short-range order in the rutile phase will be the key to understanding the MIT in this system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10193v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.L100101</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, L100101 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shunsuke Kitou, Akitoshi Nakano, Masato Imaizumi, Yuiga Nakamura, Ichiro Terasaki, Taka-hisa Arima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic Transport and Fermi Surface Topology of Zintl phase Dirac Semimetal SrZn2Ge2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10621v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report a comprehensive study on the electronic transport properties of SrZn$_2$Ge$_2$ single crystals. The in-plane electrical resistivity of the compound exhibits linear temperature dependence for 80 K &lt; T &lt; 300 K, and T^2 dependence below 40 K, consistent with the Fermi liquid behavior. Both the transverse and longitudinal magnetoresistance exhibit a crossover at critical field B* from weak-field quadratic-like to high-field unsaturated linear field dependence at low temperatures (T \leq 50 K). Possible sources of linear magnetoresistance are discussed based on the Fermi surface topology, classical and quantum transport models. The Hall resistivity data establish SrZn$_2$Ge$_2$ as a multiband system with contributions from both the electrons and holes. The Hall coefficient is observed to decrease with increasing temperature and magnetic field, changing its sign from positive to negative. The negative Hall coefficient observed at low temperatures in high fields and at high temperatures over the entire field range suggests that the highly mobile electron charge carriers dominate the electronic transport. Our first-principles calculations show that nontrivial topological surface states exist in SrZn$_2$Ge$_2$ within the bulk gap along the {\Gamma}-M path. Notably, these surface states extend from the valence to conduction band with their number varying based on the Sr and Ge termination plane. The Fermi surface of the compound exhibits a distinct tetragonal petal-like structure, with one open and several closed surfaces. Overall, these findings offer crucial insights into the mechanisms underlying the electronic transport of the compound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10621v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. K. Hooda, A. Chakraborty, S. Roy, A. Agarwal, P. Mandal, S. N. Sarangi, D. Samal, V. P. S. Awana, Z. Hossain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon thermal Hall effect in charge-compensated topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03064v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: From a systematic study of thermal and charge transport in various single crystals of compensated topological insulators we identify the evolution of a large low-temperature thermal Hall effect as a characteristic common feature. In order to separate phononic and electronic contributions in the measured longitudinal and transverse thermal conductivity, the electronic contributions are estimated from corresponding electrical resisivity and Hall effect measurements on the same samples by using the Wiedemann-Franz law. As may be expected for charge-compensated topological insulators the longitudinal thermal conductivity is phonon-dominated in all samples. However, we also find a pronounced field-linear thermal Hall effect that becomes most pronounced in the low-temperature range, where all samples are good electrical insulators. This indicates an underlying phononic mechanism of the thermal Hall effect and in this respect the topological insulators resemble other, mainly ionic, insulators, which have been reported to show a phonon-induced thermal Hall effect, but its underlying phononic mechanism remains to be identified. Our observation of a comparable thermal Hall ratio in topological insulators supports a theoretical scenario that explains a thermal Hall effect through skew scattering on charged impurities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03064v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Sharma, Mahasweta Bagchi, Yongjian Wang, Yoichi Ando, Thomas Lorenz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi Surface Geometry and Optical Conductivity of a 2D Electron Gas near an Ising-Nematic Quantum Critical Point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17392v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze optical conductivity of a clean two-dimensional electron system in a Fermi liquid regime near a $T=0$ Ising-nematic quantum critical point (QCP), and extrapolate the results to a QCP. We employ direct perturbation theory up to the two-loop order to elucidate how the Fermi surface's geometry (convex vs. concave) and fermionic dispersion (parabolic vs. non-parabolic) affect the scaling of the optical conductivity, $\sigma(\omega)$, with frequency $\omega$ and correlation length $\xi$. We find that for a convex Fermi surface the leading terms in the optical conductivity cancel out, leaving a sub-leading contribution $\sigma (\omega) \propto \omega^2 \xi^4 \mathcal{L}$, where $\mathcal{L} = \mathrm{const}$ for a parabolic dispersion and $\mathcal{L} \propto \log{\omega \xi^3}$ in a generic case. For a concave Fermi surface, the leading terms do not cancel, and $\sigma (\omega) \propto \xi^2$. We extrapolate these results to a QCP and obtain $\sigma (\omega) \propto \omega^{2/3}$ for a convex Fermi surface and $\sigma (\omega) \propto 1/\omega^{2/3}$ for a concave Fermi surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17392v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasha Gindikin, Andrey V. Chubukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-driven Roton Condensation in C = 2/3 Fractional Quantum Anomalous Hall State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03258v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay of topological order and charge order exhibits rich physics. Recent experiments that succesfully realized the frational quantum anomalous Hall (FQAH) effect in twisted MoTe$_2$ bilayers and rhombohedral multilayer graphene without external magnetic field further call for deeper understanding of the relation between topological order and charge order in quantum moir\'e materials. In the archetypal correlated flat-band model on checkerboard lattice, a FQAH smectic state with coexistent topological order and smectic charge order has been numerically discovered at filling $\nu$ = 2/3. In this work, we explore the global ground-state phase diagram of the model with competing interactions and find a C = 2/3 FQAH phase surrounded by four different charge density wave (CDW) phases. In particular, we identify a FQAH-CDW transition triggered by roton condensation, in that, the minimal roton gap continues to decrease at the same finite momentum, along with the diverging density flucuations at the transition point, after which the system enters into a CDW metal phase with the same ordered wavevector. Our discovery points out that the charge-neutral roton modes can play a significant role in a transition from FQAH topological order to CDW symmetry-breaking order, discussed in FQH literature while severely neglected in FQAH systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03258v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongyu Lu, Han-Qing Wu, Bin-Bin Chen, Kai Sun, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Negativity and Defect Extremal Surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.05951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.05951v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study entanglement negativity for evaporating black hole based on the holographic model with defect brane. We introduce a defect extremal surface formula for entanglement negativity. Based on partial reduction, we show the equivalence between defect extremal surface formula and island formula for entanglement negativity in AdS$_3$/BCFT$_2$. Extending the study to the model of eternal black hole plus CFT bath, we find that black hole-black hole negativity decreases until vanishing, left black hole-left radiation negativity is always a constant, radiation-radiation negativity increases and then saturates at a time later than Page time. In all the time dependent cases, defect extremal surface formula agrees with island formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.05951v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yilu Shao, Ma-Ke Yuan, Yang Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Transition of Operator Size Growth in Quantum Systems Embedded in an Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.03535v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In closed generic many-body systems, unitary evolution disperses local quantum information into highly non-local objects, resulting in thermalization. Such a process is called information scrambling, whose swiftness is quantified by the operator size growth. However, for quantum systems embedded in an environment, how the couplings to the environment affect the process of information scrambling quests revelation. Here we predict a dynamical transition in quantum systems with all-to-all interactions accompanied by an environment, which separates two phases. In the dissipative phase, information scrambling halts as the operator size decays with time, while in the scrambling phase, dispersion of information persists and the operator size grows and saturates to an $O(N)$ value in the long-time limit with $N$ the number of degrees of freedom of the systems. The transition is driven by the competition between the system intrinsic and environment propelled scramblings and the environment induced dissipation. Our prediction is derived from a general argument based on epidemiological models and demonstrated analytically via solvable Brownian SYK models. We provide further evidence which suggests that the transition is generic to quantum chaotic systems when coupled to an environment. Our study sheds light on the fundamental behavior of quantum systems in the presence of an environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.03535v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.130.250401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 130, 250401 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pengfei Zhang, Zhenhua Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of charge density waves in electron-phonon systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.05667v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that electron-phonon interactions enhance the stability of charge density waves in low-temperature phases of many-electron systems. Our proof method involves an appropriate application of the Pirogov--Sinai theory to electron-phonon systems. Combining our findings with existing results, we obtain rigorous information regarding the low-temperature phase diagram for half-filled electron-phonon systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.05667v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadahiro Miyao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexistence of nematic superconductivity and spin density wave in magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.00346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.00346v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We argue that doped twisted bilayer graphene with magical twist angle can become superconducting. In our theoretical scenario, the superconductivity coexists with the spin-density-wave-like ordering. Numerical mean-field analysis demonstrates that the spin-density-wave order, which is much stronger than the superconductivity, leaves parts of the Fermi surface ungapped. This Fermi surface serves as a host for the superconductivity. Since the magnetic texture at finite doping breaks the point group of the twisted bilayer graphene, the stabilized superconducting order parameter is nematic. We also explore the possibility of a purely Coulomb-based mechanism of superconductivity in the studied system. The screened Coulomb interaction is calculated within the random phase approximation. It is shown that near the half-filling the renormalized Coulomb repulsion indeed induces the superconducting state, with the order parameter possessing two nodes on the Fermi surface. We estimate the superconducting transition temperature, which turns out to be very low. The implications of our proposal are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.00346v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.094505</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 094505 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. O. Sboychakov, A. V. Rozhkov, A. L. Rakhmanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden symmetry of Bogoliubov de Gennes quasi-particle eigenstates and universal relations in flat band superconducting bipartite lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06589v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Unconventional flat band (FB) superconductivity, as observed in van der Waals heterostructures, could open promising avenues towards high-T$_c$ materials. In FBs, pairings and superfluid weight scale linearly with the interaction parameter, such an unusual behaviour justifies and encourages strategies to promote FB engineering. Bipartite lattices (BLs) which naturally host FBs could be particularly interesting candidates. Within Bogoliubov de Gennes theory and in the framework of the attractive Hubbard model in BLs, a hidden symmetry of the quasi-particle eigenstates is revealed. As a consequence, we demonstrate universal relations for the pairings and the superfluid weight that are independent of the characteristics of the hopping term. Remarkably, it is shown that these general properties are insensitive to disorder as long as the bipartite character is protected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06589v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Bouzerar, M. Thumin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On quantum melting of superfluid vortex crystals: from Lifshitz scalar to dual gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13741v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Despite a long history of studies of vortex crystals in rotating superfluids, their melting due to quantum fluctuations is poorly understood. Here we develop a fracton-elasticity duality to investigate a two-dimensional vortex lattice within the fast rotation regime, where the Lifshitz model of the collective Tkachenko mode serves as the leading-order low-energy effective theory. We incorporate topological defects and discuss several quantum melting scenarios triggered by their proliferation. Furthermore, we lay the groundwork for a dual non-linear emergent gravity description of the superfluid vortex crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13741v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dung Xuan Nguyen, Sergej Moroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fracton gravity from spacetime dipole symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01818v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dipole charge conservation forces isolated charges to be immobile fractons. These couple naturally to spatial two-index symmetric tensor gauge fields that resemble a spatial metric. We propose a spacetime Lorentz covariant version of dipole symmetry and study the theory of the associated gauge fields. In the presence of a suitable background field, these contain a massive anti-symmetric and a massless symmetric two-index tensors. The latter transforms only under longitudinal diffeomorphisms, making the massless sector similar to linearized gravity, but with additional modes of lower spin. We show that the theory can be consistently coupled to a curved background metric and study its possible interaction terms with itself and with matter. In addition, we construct a map between solutions of linearized gravity in Kerr-Schild form and solutions of fracton gravity coupled to matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01818v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.065013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 065013, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Afxonidis, Alessio Caddeo, Carlos Hoyos, Daniele Musso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ba6RE2Ti4O17 (RE= Nd, Sm,Gd, Dy-Yb): A family of Rare-earth based layered triangular lattice magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08937v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Rare-earth-based triangular-lattice magnets provide the fertile ground to explore the exotic quantum magnetic state. Herein, we report a new family of RE-based triangular-lattice magnets Ba6RE2Ti4O17(RE= rare earth ions) crystallized into the hexagonal structure with space group of P63 mmc, where magnetic rare earth ions form an ideal triangular lattice within the ab-plane and stack in an AA -type fashion along the c-axis. The low-temperature magnetic susceptibility results reveal all the serial compounds have the dominant antiferromagnetic interactions and an absence of magnetic ordering down to 1.8 K. The magnetization and electron spin resonance results indicate distinct magnetic anisotropy for the compounds with different RE ions. Moreover, Ba6Nd2Ti4O17 single crystal is successfully grown and it exhibits strong Ising like anisotropy with magnetic easy-axis perpendicular to the triangle-lattice plane, being a candidate to explore quantum spin liquid state with dominant Ising-type interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08937v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangyuan Song, Andi Liu, Qiao Chen, Jin Zhou, Jingxin Li, Wei Tong, Shun Wang, Yanhong Wang, Hongcheng Lu, Songliu Yuan, Hanjie Guo, Zhaoming Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reclaiming the Lost Conformality in a non-Hermitian Quantum 5-state Potts Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00852v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Conformal symmetry, emerging at critical points, can be lost when renormalization group fixed points collide. Recently, it was proposed that after collisions, real fixed points transition into the complex plane, becoming complex fixed points described by complex conformal field theories (CFTs). Although this idea is compelling, directly demonstrating such complex conformal fixed points in microscopic models remains highly demanding. Furthermore, these concrete models are instrumental in unraveling the mysteries of complex CFTs and illuminating a variety of intriguing physical problems, including weakly first-order transitions in statistical mechanics and the conformal window of gauge theories. In this work, we have successfully addressed this complex challenge for the (1+1)-dimensional quantum $5$-state Potts model, whose phase transition has long been known to be weakly first-order. By adding an additional non-Hermitian interaction, we successfully identify two conjugate critical points located in the complex parameter space, where the lost conformality is restored in a complex manner. Specifically, we unambiguously demonstrate the radial quantization of the complex CFTs and compute the operator spectrum, as well as new operator product expansion coefficients that were previously unknown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00852v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin Tang, Han Ma, Qicheng Tang, Yin-Chen He, W. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
