<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 14:40:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hasse Diagrams for Gapless SPT and SSB Phases with Non-Invertible Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss (1+1)d gapless phases with non-invertible global symmetries, also referred to as categorical symmetries. This includes gapless phases showing properties analogous to gapped symmetry protected topological (SPT) phases, known as gapless SPT (or gSPT) phases; and gapless phases showing properties analogous to gapped spontaneous symmetry broken (SSB) phases, that we refer to as gapless SSB (or gSSB) phases. We fit these gapless phases, along with gapped SPT and SSB phases, into a phase diagram describing possible deformations connecting them. This phase diagram is partially ordered and defines a so-called Hasse diagram. Based on these deformations, we identify gapless phases exhibiting symmetry protected criticality, that we refer to as intrinsic gapless SPT (igSPT) and intrinsic gapless SSB (igSSB) phases. This includes the first examples of igSPT and igSSB phases with non-invertible symmetries. Central to this analysis is the Symmetry Topological Field Theory (SymTFT), where each phase corresponds to a condensable algebra in the Drinfeld center of the symmetry category. On a mathematical note, gSPT phases are classified by functors between fusion categories, generalizing the fact that gapped SPT phases are classified by fiber functors; and gSSB phases are classified by functors from fusion to multi-fusion categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00905v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lakshya Bhardwaj, Daniel Pajer, Sakura Schafer-Nameki, Alison Warman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetoelectric response of lattice bosonic insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the absence of parity and time-reversal symmetries, insulators can exhibit magnetoelectric responses, in which applied magnetic fields induce charge polarization and, conversely, applied electric fields induce magnetization. While there is a long history of the study of magnetoelectric response in fermionic insulators, the same for bosonic insulators has been limited. We consider the magnetoelectric response in lattice insulators built out of charged bosonic degrees of freedom and derive a bulk formula for the corresponding linear response tensor. The resulting formulae feature several contributions including a Chern-Simons integral over the bands of the bosonic excitations. We construct several minimal microscopic models that illustrate the ingredients required to obtain a sizable bosonic magnetoelectric response. Our formalism can be applied to bosonic Mott insulators subject to synthetic gauge fields and/or tilted potentials as well as to the spinon sector in the Coulomb phase of a $U(1)$ quantum spin liquid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00918v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gautam K. Naik, Michael O. Flynn, Chris R. Laumann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating chiral spin liquids with fermionic Projected Entangled Paired States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral Spin Liquids (CSL) based on spin-1/2 fermionic Projected Entangled Pair States (fPEPS) are considered on the square lattice. First, fPEPS approximants of Gutzwiller-projected Chern insulators (GPCI) are investigated by Variational Monte Carlo (VMC) techniques on finite size tori. We show that such fPEPS of finite bond dimension can correctly capture the topological properties of the chiral spin liquid, as the exact GPCI, with the correct topological ground state degeneracy on the torus. Further, more general fPEPS are considered and optimized (on the infinite plane) to describe the CSL phase of a chiral frustrated Heisenberg antiferromagnet. The chiral modes are computed on the edge of a semi-infinite cylinder (of finite circumference) and shown to follow the predictions from Conformal Field Theory. In contrast to their bosonic analogs the (optimized) fPEPS do not suffer from the replication of the chiral edge mode in the odd topological sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01243v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sasank Budaraju, Didier Poilblanc, Sen Niu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncentrosymmetric Nowotny Chimney Ladder Ferromagnet Cr4Ge7 with a High Curie Temperature of ~ 207 K</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Noncentrosymmetric magnets usually host intriguing magnetic interactions inherent the crystal structure with broken inversion symmetry, which can give rise to rich magnetic behaviors. We report herein the high-pressure synthesis, crystal structure, magnetizations and magnetic structure of a so-called Nowotny chimney ladder compound Cr4Ge7. Our analysis on the powder neutron diffraction data revises the crystal structure as a noncentrosymmetric space group (P-4c2, No.116). It exhibits two magnetic orders within the temperature range of 2 - 400 K. The first order at ~ 207 K associated with a small magnetic moment of ~ 0.75 miuB is assigned to a commensurate ferromagnetic structure with a propagation vector k = (0, 0, 0). The weak itinerant ferromagnet nature should be caused by the complex Cr spin orders from different Wyckoff positions. The second order at ~ 18 K is assumed to arise from a competition between the Dzyaloshinskii-Moria and Heisenberg interactions. The results provide an excellent platform for study on intricate interactions between various magnetic exchanges as well as for the exploration of high temperature exotic magnetic properties which host potential applications in next-generation spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01399v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenhai Yu, Kaijuan Zhou, Xiaofei Hou, Xuejiao Chen, Zhen Tao, Yunguan Ye, Wei Xia, Zhongyang Li, Jinggeng Zhao, Wei Wu, Ziyi Liu, Xia Wang, Na Yu, Jinguang Cheng, Jianlin Luo, Qiang Zhang, Vladimir Pomjakushin, Zhicheng Zhong, Soh Jian Rui, Xingye Lu, Yanfeng Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torus algebra and logical operators at low energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a modular tensor category $\mathscr{C}$, we construct an associative algebra $\mathrm{Tor({\mathscr{C}}})$, which we call the torus algebra. We prove that the torus algebra is semisimple by explicitly constructing all the simple modules. Suppose that a topological ordered phase described by $\mathscr{C}$ is put on a torus. Physically, each simple module over $\mathrm{Tor({\mathscr{C}}})$ consists of the low energy states on the torus with one anyon excitation, or equivalently, the ground states on a punctured torus where the anyon is enclosed by the puncture. Elements in $\mathrm{Tor({\mathscr{C}}})$ can be physically interpreted as anyon hopping processes on the torus. We give the precise formula how an arbitrary logical operator on the low energy states on a torus can be realized by moving anyons on the torus. Our work thus provides a theoretical proposal that the low energy states on a torus can serve as topological qudits and one can arbitrarily manipulate them by moving anyons around.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01577v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Chan, Tian Lan, Linqian Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting and leaking a Majorana bound state through proximity to a Kitaev ring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the existence of a Majorana bound state at one end of a Kitaev chain is unambiguously signaled by observable quantities in a nearby Kitaev ring. When the Kitaev chain is in the topological phase, the band structure of the Kitaev ring breaks chiral symmetry and the ring-Majoranas' spectral functions are even functions of momentum and energy, the latter wielding time-reversal and particle-hole symmetric occupation numbers and, hence, zero current in the ring. Driving a phase transition in the Kitaev chain (e.g., using a backgate to vary the chemical potential of the chain through its critical value), the replacement of the Majorana bound state by a trivial fermion is manifest by chiral symmetry reappearing in the band structure of the ring and by the ring-Majoranas' spectral functions loss of parity, wielding time-reversal and particle-hole symmetry breaking in the occupation numbers and a spontaneous current in the ring. Energy resonance and maximum spectral weight exactly at the resonance energy concur for a high leakage probability between ring-Majoranas' states and the Majorana bound state, whereas the lack of energy resonance makes unlikely any leakage between ring-Majoranas' states and the trivial fermion states. The proposed setup also invites further investigations in the context of braiding and/or fusion of Majorana states, both as detection mechanisms and for quantum computing purposes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01588v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariana Malard, David S. Brand\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal Structure and Magnetism of Actinide Oxides: A Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In actinide systems, the 5f electrons experience a uniquely delicate balance of effects and interactions having similar energy scales, which are often difficult to properly disentangle. This interplay of factors such as the dual nature of 5f-states, strong electronic correlations, and strong spin-orbit coupling results in electronically unusual and intriguing behavior such as multi-k antiferromagnetic ordering, multipolar ordering, mott-physics, mixed valence configurations, and more. Despite the inherent allure of their exotic properties, the exploratory science of even the more basic, binary systems like the actinide oxides has been limited due to their toxicity, radioactivity, and reactivity. In this article, we provide an overview of the available synthesis techniques for selected binary actinide oxides, including the actinide dioxides, sesquioxides, and a selection of higher oxides. For these oxides, we also review and evaluate the current state of knowledge of their crystal structures and magnetic properties. In many aspects, substantial knowledge gaps exist in the current body of research on actinide oxides related to understanding their electronic ground states. Bridging these gaps is vital for improving not only a fundamental understanding of these systems but also of future nuclear technologies. To this end, we note the experimental techniques and necessary future investigations which may aid in better elucidating the nature of these fascinating systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01634v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binod K. Rai, Alex Bretana, Gregory Morrison, Ryan Greer, Krzysztof Gofryk, Hans-Conrad zur Loye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time reversal invariant topological 1D and 2D superconductors: doubling the Sau-Luchtin-Tewari-Sarma and Oreg-Refael-von Oppen proposals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we present a doubled version of the Sam-Luchtin-Tewari-Sarma and Oreg-Refael-von Open proposals thereby obtaining time reversal invariant p-wave superconductivity in both 1D and 2D. This construction is much like the Kane-Mele spin Hall model which is a time reversal invariant doubling of the Haldane model. We show that the low energy effective action for these doubled versions of the Say-Luchtin-Tewari-Sarma and Greg-Refael-von Open models corresponds to a single band p-wave time reversal invariant superconductors with pseudo spin degree of freedom instead of spin degree of freedom. There are Majorana fermions at the ends of wires or in vortex cores of these superconductors. Furthermore these are shown to be stable to small perturbations. In the supplement we present physical realization of the system with cold atoms and show a related "no-go" theorem given in Haim et. al. (2019) has too restrictive assumptions to apply to this proposal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01696v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Garry Goldstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular intercalation in the van der Waals antiferromagnets FePS3 and NiPS3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01714v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have performed electrochemical treatment of the van der Waals antiferromagnetic materials FePS$_3$ and NiPS$_3$ with the ionic liquid EMIM-BF$_4$, achieving significant molecular intercalation. Mass analysis of the intercalated compounds, EMIM$_x$-FePS$_3$ and EMIM$_x$-NiPS$_3$, indicated respective intercalation levels, $x$, of approximately 27\% and 37\%, and X-ray diffraction measurements demonstrated a massive (over 50\%) enhancement of the $c$-axis lattice parameters. To investigate the consequences of these changes for the magnetic properties, we performed magnetic susceptibility and $^{31}$P nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) studies of both systems. For EMIM$_x$-FePS$_3$, intercalation reduces the magnetic ordering temperature from $T_N = 120$~K to 78~K, and we find a spin gap in the antiferromagnetic phase that drops from 45~K to 30~K. For EMIM$_x$-NiPS$_3$, the ordering temperature is almost unaffected (changing from 148~K to 145~K), but a change towards nearly isotropic spin fluctuations suggests an alteration of the magnetic Hamiltonian. Such relatively modest changes, given that the huge extension of the $c$ axes is expected to cause a very strong suppression any interlayer interactions, point unequivocally to the conclusion that the magnetic properties of both parent compounds are determined solely by two-dimensional (2D), intralayer physics. The changes in transition temperatures and low-temperature spin dynamics in both compounds therefore indicate that intercalation also results in a significant modulation of the intralayer magnetic interactions, which we propose is due to charge doping and localization on the P sites. Our study offers chemical intercalation with ionic liquids as an effective method to control not only the interlayer but also the intralayer interactions in quasi-2D magnetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01714v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong Li, Ze Hu, Xiaofei Hou, Sheng Xu, Zhanlong Wu, Kefan Du, Shuo Li, Xiaoyu Xu, Ying Chen, Zeyu Wang, Tiancheng Mu, Tian-Long Xia, Yanfeng Guo, B. Normand, Weiqiang Yu, Yi Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of collective excitations in the quadruple-$Q$ magnetic hedgehog lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hedgehog and antihedgehog spin textures in magnets behave as emergent monopoles and antimonopoles, which give rise to astonishing transport and electromagnetic phenomena. Using the Kondo-lattice model in three dimensions, we theoretically study collective spin-wave excitation modes of magnetic hedgehog lattices which have recently been discovered in itinerant magnets such as MnSi$_{1-x}$Ge$_{x}$ and SrFeO$_3$. It is revealed that the spin-wave modes, which appear in the sub-terahertz regime, have dominant amplitudes localized at Dirac strings connecting hedgehog-antihedgehog pairs and are characterized by their translational oscillations. It is found that their spectral features sensitively depend on the number and configuration of the Dirac strings and, thus, can be exploited for identifying the topological phase transitions associated with the monopole-antimonopole pair annihilations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01765v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rintaro Eto, Masahito Mochizuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field induced resistive switching in M3+xV1-xO2 (M3+= Ga3+, Al3+) single crystals at temperatures below the T - M2 phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The phase diagram of VO2 strained or doped with several trivalent ions consists of four phases; in order of increasing temperatures, three (M1, T and M2) are insulating while the fourth (R), above ~340 K, is metallic. These phases and the three phase transitions have been thoroughly investigated for about half a century by a wide variety of techniques, including electronic transport. While an upwards jump of the resistance of up to a factor of 2 was observed at the T-M2 transition and a drop of several orders of magnitude was observed at the M2-R one, resistive switching at the M1-T transition remained elusive over all these years. Here we report on the investigation of Ga- and Al-doped VO2 single crystals, following the rather surprising appearance of a small and steep drop of a factor of ~ 0.12 in the resistance of Ga-doped VO2 single crystals detected by pulsed and DC I-V measurements carried out at room temperature, below the T-M2 phase transition. Similar results were obtained also from measurements on Al-doped VO2 single crystals. Raman spectra of Ga-, and Al-doped crystals resolved their structures as function of temperature. The accumulated results of the measurements on Ga-, and Al-doped single crystals provide evidence for identifying the resistive switching at T(RS)&lt;T(T-M2) with the M1-T transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01808v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Larisa Patlagan, George M. Reisner, Shani Neyshtadt-Ronel, Yoav Kalcheim, Bertina Fisher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>He-4 monolayer on Graphene: a Quantum Monte Carlo study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of adsorption of a single He-4 layer on graphene, focusing on the commensurate C1/3 crystalline phase, specifically on whether it may possess a nonzero superfluid response, and on the existence of superfluid phases, either (metastable) liquid or vacancy-doped crystalline. We make use of canonical Quantum Monte Carlo simulations at zero and finite temperature, based on a realistic microscopic model of the system. Our results confirm the absence of any superfluid response in the commensurate crystal, and that no thermodynamically stable uniform phase exists at lower coverage. No evidence of a possibly long-lived, metastable superfluid phase at C1/3 coverage is found. Altogether, the results of ground-state projection methods and finite-temperature simulations are entirely consistent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02033v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyuan Yu, Massimo Boninsegni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Monte Carlo study of stripes as a function of doping in the $t-t'$ Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02073v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform variational Monte Carlo simulations of the single-band Hubbard model on the square lattice with both nearest ($t$) and next-nearest ($t'$) neighbor hoppings. Our work investigates the consequences of increasing hole doping on the instauration of stripes and the behavior of the superconducting order parameter, with a discussion on how the two phenomena affect each other. We consider two different values of the next-nearest neighbor hopping parameter, that are appropriate for describing cuprate superconductors. We observe that stripes are the optimal state in a wide doping range; the stripe wavelength reduces at increasing doping, until stripes melt into a uniform state for large values of doping. Superconducting pair-pair correlations, indicating the presence of superconductivity, are always suppressed in the presence of stripes. Our results suggest that the phase diagram for the single-band Hubbard model is dominated by stripes, with superconductivity being possible only in a narrow doping range between striped states and a nonsuperconducting metal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02073v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Lechiara, Vito Marino, Luca F. Tocchio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double magnetic transitions, complex field induce phases, and large magnetocaloric effect in the frustrated garnet compound Mn$_{3}$Cr$_{2}$Ge$_{3}$O$_{12}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A detailed study of the structural and magnetic properties of a garnet compound Mn$_{3}$Cr$_{2}$Ge$_{3}$O$_{12}$ is carried out using x-ray diffraction, magnetization, heat capacity, and neutron diffraction measurements. This compound manifests two successive magnetic transitions at $T_{\rm N1} \simeq 4.5$ K and $T_{\rm N2} \simeq 2.7$ K. Neutron powder diffraction experiments reveal that these two transitions correspond to the orderings of Cr$^{3+}$ and Mn$^{2+}$ sub-lattices, respectively. The ordering at $T_{\rm N1}$ is found to be collinear antiferromagnetic type while the one at $T_{\rm N2}$ is of non-collinear antiferromagnetic type. There appears to be several interactions, both ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic, between two sub-lattices yielding a three-dimensional frustrated pyrochlore geometry. The $H-T$ phase diagram is quite complex and displays multiple phases under magnetic field which can be attributed to the frustrated nature of the spin-lattice. Moreover, it shows a large magnetocaloric effect at low temperatures with a maximum value of isothermal entropy change $\Delta S_{\rm m} \simeq -23$ J/kg-K and adiabatic temperature change $\Delta T_{\rm ad} \simeq 9$ K for a field change of 7~T. Further, a large value of relative cooling power ($RCP \simeq 360$ J/kg) reflects the usefulness of the compound in magnetic refrigeration purpose.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02082v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Mohanty, A. Magar, Vikram Singh, S. S. Islam, S. Guchhait, A. Jain, S. M. Yusuf, R. Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly unusual, doubly-strongly-correlated, altermagnetic, 3D analogue of parent compounds of high-Tc cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Discovery of high-temperature superconductivity (HTSC) in strongly correlated cuprates opened a new chapter in condensed matter physics, breaking existing stereotypes of what is a material base for a good superconductor ("Matthias rules"), at the same time emphasizing richness and challenge of strongly correlated physics, personified by the most strongly correlated 3d ion, Cu2+. A recently reported new compound, CuAg(SO4)2, combines in a fascinating way the same ion with the most strongly correlated 4d one, Ag2+. In this Letter, we present a detailed analysis of electronic and magnetic properties of this material, and show that it is very different from the HTSC cuprates in several different ways, and opens a door into further research of superconductivity and magnetism, in particular altermagnetism, in strongly correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02201v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harald O. Jeschke, Makoto Shimizu, Igor I. Mazin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Weyl-Kondo semimetals induced by quantum fluctuation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kondo effect exemplifies the type of quantum fluctuations driven by strong correlations, and its cooperation with space group symmetries underlies the Weyl-Kondo semimetals. Because the Kondo effect of the $f$-electrons is believed to be suppressed in a magnetic environment, Weyl-Kondo semimetals have so far been confined to paramagnetic settings. Here we develop the theory of magnetic Weyl-Kondo semimetal. The key of the proposed mechanism is that the magnetic order is originated from the conduction $d$ electrons, such that the local moments can still fluctuate. We illustrate the extreme case where the magnetic space group symmetries prevent any magnetization on the sites with the $f$-orbitals. In this case, hourglass Weyl-Kondo nodal lines appear when the space group symmetry acts on the Kondo-driven low-energy excitations. We suggest a third-order nonlinear spontaneous Hall response as a means to diagnose this type of topological crossings. Based on the theoretical mechanism, we explore the interplay between correlations and symmetries in magnetic square-net materials, leading to several candidate materials with a variety of nonlinear Hall responses. Our findings pave the way for future experimental exploration and theoretical investigations in this new and promising materials class as a part of an overarching effort to understand and harness the interplay between strong correlations and topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02295v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Fang, Lei Chen, Qimiao Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable non-Fermi liquid fixed point at the onset of incommensurate $2k_F$ charge density wave order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the emergence of a non-Fermi liquid fixed point in two-dimensional metals at the onset of a quantum phase transition from a Fermi liquid state to an incommensurate charge density wave (CDW) ordered phase. The momentum of the CDW boson is centred at the wavevector $ \boldsymbol{ \mathcal Q} $, which connects a single pair of antipodal points on the Fermi surface with antiparallel tangent vectors. We employ the dimensional regularization technique in which the co-dimension of the Fermi surface is extended to a generic value, while keeping the dimension of Fermi surface itself fixed at one. Although the system is strongly coupled at dimension $d=2$, the interactions become marginal at the upper critical dimension $d=d_c$, whose value is found to be $ 5/2$. Using a controlled perturbative expansion in the parameter $\epsilon = d_c - d $, we compute the critical exponents of the stable infrared fixed point characterizing the quantum critical point. The scalings of the original theory are determined by setting $\epsilon =1/2$, where the fermion self-energy is seen to scale with the frequency with a fractional power law of $2/3$, which is the undisputed signature of a typical non-Fermi liquid phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02322v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling radiative heat flow through cavity electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cavity electrodynamics is emerging as a promising tool to control chemical processes and quantum material properties. In this work we develop a formalism to describe the cavity mediated energy exchange between a material and its electromagnetic environment. We show that coplanar cavities can significantly affect the heat load on the sample if the cavity resonance lies within the frequency region where free-space radiative heat dominates, typically the mid-IR at ambient temperature, while spectral filtering is necessary for having an effect with lower frequency cavities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00851v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Fassioli, Jerome Faist, Martin Eckstein, Daniele Fausti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reclaiming the Lost Conformality in a non-Hermitian Quantum 5-state Potts Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Conformal symmetry, emerging at critical points, can be lost when renormalization group fixed points collide. Recently, it was proposed that after collisions, real fixed points transition into the complex plane, becoming complex fixed points described by complex conformal field theories (CFTs). Although this idea is compelling, directly demonstrating such complex conformal fixed points in microscopic models remains highly demanding. Furthermore, these concrete models are instrumental in unraveling the mysteries of complex CFTs and illuminating a variety of intriguing physical problems, including weakly first-order transitions in statistical mechanics and the conformal window of gauge theories. In this work, we have successfully addressed this complex challenge for the (1+1)-dimensional quantum $5$-state Potts model, whose phase transition has long been known to be weakly first-order. By adding an additional non-Hermitian interaction, we successfully identify two conjugate critical points located in the complex parameter space, where the lost conformality is restored in a complex manner. Specifically, we unambiguously demonstrate the radial quantization of the complex CFTs and compute the operator spectrum, as well as new operator product expansion coefficients that were previously unknown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00852v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin Tang, Han Ma, Qicheng Tang, Yin-Chen He, W. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher vortexability: zero field realization of higher Landau levels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00856v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rise of moir\'{e} materials has led to experimental realizations of integer and fractional Chern insulators in small or vanishing magnetic fields. At the same time, a set of minimal conditions sufficient to guarantee a Abelian fractional state in a flat band were identified, namely "ideal" or "vortexable" quantum geometry. Such vortexable bands share essential features with the lowest Landau level, while excluding the need for more fine-tuned aspects such as flat Berry curvature. A natural and important generalization is to ask if such conditions can be extended to capture the quantum geometry of higher Landau levels, particularly the first (1LL), where non-Abelian states at $\nu = 1/2,2/5$ are known to be competitive. The possibility of realizing these states at zero magnetic field , and perhaps even more exotic ones, could become a reality if we could identify the essential structure of the 1LL in Chern bands. In this work, we introduce a precise definition of 1LL quantum geometry, along with a figure of merit that measures how closely a given band approaches the 1LL. We apply the definition to identify two models with 1LL structure -- a toy model of double bilayer twisted graphene and a more realistic model of strained Bernal graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00856v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manato Fujimoto, Daniel E. Parker, Junkai Dong, Eslam Khalaf, Ashvin Vishwanath, Patrick Ledwith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of Superconductivity in Twisted Graphene Multilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00903v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The group of moir\'e graphene superconductors keeps growing, and by now it contains twisted graphene multilayers and twisted double bilayers. We analyze the contribution of long range charge fluctuations in the superconductivity of twisted double graphene bilayers and helical trilayers, and compare the results to twisted bilayer graphene. We apply a diagrammatic approach which depends on a few, well known parameters. We find that the critical temperature and the order parameter differ significantly between twisted double bilayers and helical trilayers on one hand, and twisted bilayer graphene on the other. We show that this trend, consistent with experiments, can be associated to the role played by moir\'e Umklapp processes in the different systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00903v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Long, Alejandro Jimeno-Pozo, Hector Sainz-Cruz, Pierre A. Pantaleon, Francisco Guinea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Requirements for building effective Hamiltonians using quantum-enhanced density matrix downfolding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01043v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Density matrix downfolding (DMD) is a technique for regressing low-energy effective Hamiltonians from quantum many-body Hamiltonians. One limiting factor in the accuracy of classical implementations of DMD is the presence of difficult-to-quantify systematic errors attendant to sampling the observables of quantum many-body systems on an approximate low-energy subspace. We propose a hybrid quantum-classical protocol for circumventing this limitation, relying on the prospective ability of quantum computers to efficiently prepare and sample from states in well-defined low-energy subspaces with systematically improvable accuracy. We introduce three requirements for when this is possible, including a notion of compressibility that quantifies features of Hamiltonians and low-energy subspaces thereof for which quantum DMD might be efficient. Assuming that these requirements are met, we analyze design choices for our protocol and provide resource estimates for implementing quantum-enhanced DMD on both the doped 2-D Fermi-Hubbard model and an ab initio model of a cuprate superconductor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01043v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivesh Pathak, Antonio E. Russo, Stefan Seritan, Alicia B. Magann, Eric Bobrow, Andrew J. Landahl, Andrew D. Baczewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driven charge density modulation by spin density wave and their coexistence interplay in SmFeAsO: A first-principles study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01111v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use density functional theory to investigate effects of spin-orbit coupling and single- stripe-type antiferromagnetic (sAFM) ordering on the crystal structure and electronic properties of SmFeAsO. The results indicate that AFM ordering causes the crystal structure transition from tetragonal to orthorhombic, along with increase in the height of As atoms from Fe layer due to magnetostriction. It also leads to the opening of partial band gaps, the emergence of a prominent peak near Fermi energy (EF) in the density of states (DOS) and a reduction in Fermi surface nesting. The study finds a correlation between the calculated area under the DOS curve, spanning from EF to the first peak above it, and the optimal electron- doped concentration required for inducing superconductivity in SmFeAsO. The findings suggest that spin and charge density waves can play important roles in the superconducting mechanism of Fe-based superconductors. Our calculations demonstrate that spin-orbit coupling reduces electronic correlation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01111v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physb.2023.415603</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica B: Condensed Matter 674 (2024) 415603</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Toktam Morshedloo, Ali Kazempour, Hamideh Shakeripour, S. Javad Hashemifar, Mojtaba Alaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gapped nodal planes drive a large topological Nernst effect in a chiral lattice antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01113v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The electronic structure of compensated antiferromagnets (CAF) has drawn attention for its ability to create large responses, reminiscent of ferromagnets and suitable for data storage and readout, despite (nearly) net-zero spontaneous magnetization. Many of the striking experimental signatures predicted for CAF, such as giant thermoelectric Nernst effects, are enhanced when two or more electronic bands are nearly degenerate in vicinity of the Fermi energy. Here, we use thermoelectric and electric transport experiments to study the electronic structure of the layered, chiral metal CoNb3S6 in its all-in-all-out CAF ground state and report near-degeneracies of electron bands at the upper and lower boundaries of the first Brillouin zone. Considering non-symmorphic spin-space group symmetries in the non-relativistic approximation for the ordered phase, these near-degeneracies are approximately protected by a lattice translation combined with spin rotation, and are vestiges of nodal planes enforced by a screw axis symmetry in the paramagnetic state. Hot spots of emergent, or fictitious, magnetic fields are formed at the slightly gapped nodal plane, generating the spontaneous Hall and Nernst effects in this CAF. Taking into account more than six hundred Wannier orbitals, our model quantitatively reproduces the observed spontaneous Nernst effect, emphasizes the role of proximate symmetries in the emergent responses of CAF, and demonstrates the promise of ab-initio search for functional responses in a wide class of materials with reconstructed unit cells due to spin or charge correlations order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01113v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. D. Khanh, S. Minami, M. Hirschmann, T. Nomoto, M. C. Jiang, R. Yamada, D. Yamaguchi, Y. Hayashi, Y. Okamura, H. Watanabe, G. Y. Guo, Y. Takahashi, S. Seki, Y. Taguchi, Y. Tokura, R. Arita, M. Hirschberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous impurity effect in the heavy-fermion superconductor CeCu$_2$Si$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01455v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent observations of contradictory impurity effect in the heavy-fermion superconductor CeCu$_2$Si$_2$ at ambient pressure have hindered the identification of its pairing symmetry. Here we perform theoretical analyses with both intraband and interband impurity scatterings for the nodeless $s^\pm$-wave pairing, and report an anomalous nonmonotonic variation of its $T_c$ suppression with the scattering strength. Our results reproduce the prominent reduction of $T_c$ in good agreement with earlier experiments by atomic substitution and explains as well its robustness against electron irradiation. We ascribe the latter to the screening of the interband impurity potential in the strong scattering or unitary region. This resolves the seeming contradiction in different experimental probes and provides an important support to the nodeless $s^\pm$-wave scenario in CeCu$_2$Si$_2$ at ambient pressure. Our theory may be extended to other narrow band systems such as twisted bilayer graphene and the recently discovered bilayer or trilayer nickelate superconductors, and provide a useful way to distinguish different paring candidates thereof.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01455v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shan Zhao, Weifu Liu, Yi-feng Yang, Shiping Feng, Bin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gapless Edge-Modes and Topology in the Qi-Wu-Zhang Model: A Real-Space Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01576v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The topological phase transition in the Qi-Wu-Zhang model is studied, with particular attention to the appearance of chiral edge-modes in the nontrivial phase. Time-reversal symmetry breaking and its role in the topological phase transition is explicitly demonstrated. An effective Hamiltonian for the topologically protected edge-modes in a finite-size system is developed. The topological phase transition is understood in terms of a global perturbation to the system which lifts the degeneracy of the edge-modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01576v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjo Dasgupta, Indra Dasgupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirped amplitude mode in photo-excited superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01589v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the amplitude mode in superconductors exhibits chirped oscillations under resonant excitation and that the chirping velocity increases as we approach the critical excitation strength. The chirped amplitude mode enables us to determine the local modification of the effective potential even when the system is in a long-lived pre-thermal state. We then show that this chirped amplitude mode is an experimentally observable quantity since the photo-induced (super)-current in pump-probe experiments serves as an efficient proxy for the dynamics of the order parameter, including the chirped dynamics. Our result is based on the attractive Hubbard model using dynamical mean-field theory within the symmetry-broken state after a resonant excitation across the superconducting gap. Since the collective response takes place on emergently long timescales, we extend the hierarchical low-rank compression method for nonequilibrium Green's functions to symmetry-broken states and show that it serves as an efficient representation despite long-lived memory kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01589v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Blommel, Jason Kaye, Yuta Murakami, Emanuel Gull, Denis Gole\v{z}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnonic $\varphi$ Josephson Junctions and Synchronized Precession</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01625v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There has been a growing interest in non-Hermitian physics. One of its main goals is to engineer dissipation and to explore ensuing functionality. In magnonics, the effect of dissipation due to local damping on magnon transport has been explored. However, the effects of non-local damping on the magnonic analog of the Josephson effect remain missing, despite that non-local damping is inevitable and has been playing a central role in magnonics. Here, we uncover theoretically that a surprisingly rich dynamics can emerge in magnetic junctions due to intrinsic non-local damping, using analytical and numerical methods. In particular, under microwave pumping, we show that coherent spin precession in the right and left insulating ferromagnet (FM) of the junction becomes synchronized by non-local damping and thereby a magnonic analog of the $\varphi$ Josephson junction emerges, where $\varphi$ stands here for the relative precession phase of right and left FM in the stationary limit. Remarkably, $\varphi$ decreases monotonically from $ \pi$ to $\pi/2$ as the magnon-magnon interaction, arising from spin anisotropies, increases. Moreover, we also find a magnonic diode effect giving rise to rectification of magnon currents. Our predictions are readily testable with current device and measurement technologies at room temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01625v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kouki Nakata, Ji Zou, Jelena Klinovaja, Daniel Loss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopic investigations on trivalent ruthenium ions in ruthenium perovskite oxide thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01853v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The $d^5$ electron configurations under the crystal field, spin-orbit coupling, and Coulomb interaction give rise to a plethora of profound ground states. Ruthenium perovskite oxides exhibit a number of unconventional properties yet the Ru$^{4+}$ state ($4d^4$) is usually stable in these materials. In this regard, Ru$^{3+}$ ions in perovskite materials are expected to be a mesmerising playground of $4d^5$ electron configurations. Here, we report measurements of x-ray photoemission spectroscopy on recently synthesized perovskite ruthenium oxide thin films, LaRuO$_3$ and NdRuO$_3$, whose valence state of the ruthenium ions is trivalent. We discuss correlation and spin-orbit effects from the valence-band spectra, in particular an additional peak structure around 3-5 eV, reminiscent of the so-called 3 eV peak observed in Sr$_2$RuO$_4$. Moreover, we find that the core-level spectra of these materials are quantitatively different from those in other ruthenates which possess Ru$^{4+}$ ions, e.g., SrRuO$_3$. We therefore argue that the core level spectra of LaRuO$_3$ and NdRuO$_3$ are peculiar to the Ru$^{3+}$ states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01853v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Nakata, R. Takahashi, R. Matsumoto, L. -F. Zhang, H. Sumida, S. Suzuki, T. C. Fujita, M. Kawasaki, H. Wadati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete time-crystals in linear potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01912v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Discrete time crystalline (DTC) phases have attracted significant theoretical and experimental attention in the last few years. Such systems require a seemingly impossible combination of non-adiabatic driving and a finite-entropy long-time state, which is, however, possible in non-ergodic systems. Previous works have often relied on disorder for the required non-ergodicity; here, we describe the construction of a discrete time crystal (DTC) phase in non-disordered, non-integrable Ising-type systems. After discussing the conditions for interacting and periodically driven systems to display such phases in general, we propose a concrete model and then provide approximate analytical arguments and direct numerical evidence that it satisfies the conditions and displays a DTC phase robust to local periodic perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01912v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yevgeny Bar Lev, Achilleas Lazarides</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Chaos to Integrability in Double Scaled SYK</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01950v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study thermodynamic phase transitions between integrable and chaotic dynamics. We do so by analyzing models that interpolate between the chaotic double scaled Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) and the integrable $p$-spin systems, in a limit where they are described by chord diagrams. We develop a path integral formalism by coarse graining over the diagrams, which we use to argue that the system has two distinct phases: one is continuously connected to the chaotic system, and the other to the integrable. They are separated by a line of first order transition that ends at a critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01950v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha Berkooz, Nadav Brukner, Yiyang Jia, Ohad Mamroud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-induced valley transport in CrBr$_3$/WSe$_2$/CrBr$_3$ van der Waals heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two dimensional magnetic materials are at the forefront of the next generation of spintronic devices. The possibility to interface them with other van der Waals materials such as transition metal dichalcogenides has opened new possibilities for the observation of new and exiting physical phenomena. Here, we present a proof-of-concept valleytronic device based on CrBr$_3$-encapsulated WSe$_2$ showing an unprecedented valley splitting of $\sim 100$ meV under compressive strain of the WSe$_2$, able to be tuned by the relative magnetization of the encapsulating layers. Multiscale transport simulations performed on this device show a spin-valley current with a polarization higher than 80$\%$ than is maintained in a range of $\sim$ 0.3 V gate voltage in a field-effect transistor configuration. The impact of the stacking configuration on the valley splitting is also evaluated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02188v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Soriano, Damiano Marian, Prabhat Dubey, Gianluca Fiori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal features of entanglement entropy in the honeycomb Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.04334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.04334v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The entanglement entropy is a unique probe to reveal universal features of strongly interacting many-body systems. In two or more dimensions these features are subtle, and detecting them numerically requires extreme precision, a notoriously difficult task. This is especially challenging in models of interacting fermions, where many such universal features have yet to be observed. In this paper we tackle this challenge by introducing a new method to compute the R\'enyi entanglement entropy in auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo simulations, where we treat the entangling region itself as a stochastic variable. We demonstrate the efficiency of this method by extracting, for the first time, universal subleading logarithmic terms in a two dimensional model of interacting fermions, focusing on the half-filled honeycomb Hubbard model at $T=0$. We detect the universal corner contribution due to gapless fermions throughout the Dirac semi-metal phase and at the Gross-Neveu-Yukawa critical point, where the latter shows a pronounced enhancement depending on the type of entangling cut. Finally, we observe the universal Goldstone mode contribution in the antiferromagnetic Mott insulating phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.04334v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.076502</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 076502 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan D'Emidio, Roman Orus, Nicolas Laflorencie, Fernando de Juan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulations of the dynamics of quantum impurity problems with matrix product states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13756v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Anderson impurity model is a paradigmatic example in the study of strongly correlated quantum systems and describes an interacting quantum dot coupled to electronic leads. In this work, we characterize the emergence of the Kondo effect by investigating the model dynamics following a quantum quench based on matrix product state simulations. The relaxation of the impurity magnetization allows for the estimate of the predicted universal scaling of the Kondo temperature as a function of the impurity-lead hybridization and quantum dot repulsion. Additionally, our simulations permit us to evaluate the current in the nonequilibrium quasi-steady state appearing after the quench. Through their values, we examine the dependence of the conductance on the voltage bias $V_b$ and on the impurity chemical potential $V_g$, which displays a zero-bias Kondo peak. Our results are relevant for transport measurements in Coulomb blockaded devices, and, in particular, in quantum dots induced in nanowires.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13756v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.115101</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Matteo M. Wauters, Chia-Min Chung, Lorenzo Maffi, Michele Burrello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A numerical study of bounds in the correlations of fractional quantum Hall states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.14991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.14991v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We numerically compute the guiding center static structure factor $\bar S(\bf k)$ of various fractional quantum Hall (FQH) states to $\mathcal{O}\left((k\ell)^6\right)$ where $k$ is the wavenumber and $\ell$ is the magnetic length. Employing density matrix renormalization group on an infinite cylinder of circumference $L_y$, we study the two-dimensional limit using $L_y/\xi \gg 1$, where $\xi$ is the correlation length. The main findings of our work are: 1) the ground states that deviate away from the ideal conformal block wavefunctions, do not saturate the Haldane bound, and 2) the coefficient of $O\left((k\ell)^6\right)$ term appears to be bounded above by a value predicted by field theories proposed in the literature. The first finding implies that the graviton mode is not maximally chiral for experimentally relevant FQH states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.14991v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prashant Kumar, F. D. M. Haldane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating function for projected entangled-pair states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.08083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.08083v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diagrammatic summation is a common bottleneck in modern applications of projected entangled-pair states, especially in computing low-energy excitations of a two-dimensional quantum many-body system. To solve this problem, here we extend the generating function approach for tensor network diagrammatic summation, a scheme previously proposed in the context of matrix product states. Taking the form of a one-particle excitation, we show that the excited state can be computed efficiently in the generating function formalism, which can further be used in evaluating the dynamical structure factor of the system. Our benchmark results for the spin-$1/2$ transverse-field Ising model and Heisenberg model on the square lattice provide a desirable accuracy, showing good agreement with known results. We then study the spin-$1/2$ $J_1$-$J_2$ model on the same lattice and investigate the dynamical properties of the putative gapless spin liquid phase. We conclude with a discussion on generalizations to multi-particle excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.08083v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PRXQuantum.5.010335</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 5, 010335 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Lin Tu, Laurens Vanderstraeten, Norbert Schuch, Hyun-Yong Lee, Naoki Kawashima, Ji-Yao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-Dimensional Moir\'e Polaronic Electron Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16563v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional moir\'e materials have emerged as the most versatile platforms for realizing quantum phases of electrons. Here, we explore the stability origins of correlated states in WSe2/WS2 moir\'e superlattices. We find that ultrafast electronic excitation leads to melting of the Mott states on time scales five times longer than predictions from the charge hopping integrals and the melting rates are thermally activated, with activation energies of 18 and 13 meV for the one- and two-hole Mott states, respectively, suggesting significant electron-phonon coupling. DFT calculation of the one-hole Mott state confirms polaron formation and yields a hole-polaron binding energy of 16 meV. These findings reveal a close interplay of electron-electron and electron-phonon interactions in stabilizing the polaronic Mott insulators at transition metal dichalcogenide moir\'e interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16563v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric A. Arsenault, Yiliu Li, Birui Yang, Xi Wang, Heonjoon Park, Edoardo Mosconi, Enrico Ronca, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Daniel Gamelin, Andrew Millis, Cory R. Dean, Filippo de Angelis, Xiaodong Xu, X. -Y. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The confluence of fractured resonances at points of dynamical, many--body flare</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.12346v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Resonant transport occurs when there is a matching of frequencies across some spatial medium, increasing the efficiency of shuttling particles from one reservoir to another. We demonstrate that in a periodically driven, many--body titled lattice, there are sets of spatially fractured resonances. These ``emanate'' from two essential resonances due to scattering off internal surfaces created when the driving frequency and many--body interaction strength vary, a scattering reminiscent of lens flare. The confluence of these fractured resonances dramatically enhances transport. At one confluence, the interaction strength is finite and the essential resonance arises due to the interplay of interaction with the counter--rotating terms of the periodic drive. We discuss the origin and structure of the fractured resonances, as well as the scaling of the conductance with system parameters. These results furnish a new example of the richness of open, driven, many--body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.12346v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bitan De, Gabriela W\'ojtowicz, Marek M. Rams, Michael Zwolak, Jakub Zakrzewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instanton confinement-deconfinement transitions: The stability of pseudogap phases and topological order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14424v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the stability of certain many-body quantum states which may exist at zero or finite temperatures, may lack long-range order and even topological order, and still are thermodynamically distinct from uncorrelated disordered phases. We sharply characterize such states by the conservation of topological charge, or equivalently confinement of instantons, using a generalization of the Wilson loop and the correlation length of an emergent gauge field. Our main conclusions are: (i) topological orders can exist at finite temperatures, (ii) relativistic liquids of topological defects can also exist as stable phases at finite temperatures, and (iii) there are two universality classes of instanton suppression. We also relate the instanton dynamics to the problem of the pseudogap state in underdoped cuprates. A universal experimental signature of the instanton deconfinement transition is a change of the quantum noise spectrum, which can perhaps be measured in some situations, for example via a quantum anomaly, or indirectly detected with a specific heat jump. The method of analysis is a functional renormalization group that generalizes the Coulomb gas treatment of Kosterlitz and Thouless to arbitrary interactions and dimensions. In particular, we construct an exact non-perturbative technique for confining interactions between instantons, which introduce irreparable infra-red divergences in the standard perturbative approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14424v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Predrag Nikoli\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reactive Hall and Edelstein effects in a tight-binding model with spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11253v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The reactive Hall constant R_H, described by reactive (nondissipative) conductivities, is analyzed within linear response theory in the presence of spin-orbit interaction. Within a two dimensional tight-binding model the effect of van Hove singularities is studied. Along the same line a formulation of the Edelstein constant is proposed and studied as a function of coupling parameters and fermion filling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11253v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B109, 075168 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Emmanouil K. Kokkinis, Joseph J. Betouras, Xenophon Zotos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair-density-wave and $s\pm \mathrm{i}d$ superconductivity in a strongly coupled, lightly doped Kondo insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17691v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the large Kondo coupling limit of the Kondo-Heisenberg model on one- and two-dimensional lattices. Focusing on the possible superconducting states when slightly doping the Kondo insulator state, we identify different pairing modes to be most stable in different parameter regimes. Possibilities include uniform $s$-wave, pair-density-wave with momentum $\pi$ (in both one and two dimensions) and uniform $s\pm \mathrm{i}d_{x^2-y^2}$-wave (in two dimensions). We attribute these exotic pairing states to the presence of various pair-hopping terms with a ``wrong'' sign in the effective model, a mechanism that is likely universal for inducing pairing states with spatially modulated pair wavefunctions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17691v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.L121101</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, L121101 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fangze Liu, Zhaoyu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ground-State Phase Diagram of (1/2,1/2,1) Mixed Diamond Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01630v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ground-state phases of mixed diamond chains with ($S, \tau^{(1)}, \tau^{(2)})=(1/2,1/2,1)$, where $S$ is the magnitude of vertex spins, and $\tau^{(1)}$ and $\tau^{(2)}$ are those of apical spins, are investigated. The two apical spins in each unit cell are coupled by an exchange coupling $\lambda$. The vertex spins are coupled with the top and bottom apical spins by exchange couplings $1+\delta$ and $1-\delta$, respectively. Although this model has an infinite number of local conservation laws for $\delta=0$, they are lost for finite $\delta$. The ground-state phase diagram is determined using the numerical exact diagonalization and DMRG method in addition to the analytical approximations in various limiting cases. The phase diagram consists of a nonmagnetic phase and several kinds of ferrimagnetic phases. We find two different ferrimagnetic phases without spontaneous translational symmetry breakdown. It is also found that the quantized ferrimagnetic phases with large spatial periodicities present for $\delta=0$ are easily destroyed by small $\delta$ and replaced by a partial ferrimagnetic phase. The nonmagnetic phase is considered to be a gapless Tomonaga-Luttinger liquid phase based on the recently extended Lieb-Schultz-Mattis theorem to the site-reflection invariant spin chains and numerical diagonalization results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01630v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuo Hida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal contributions to charge fluctuations in spin chains at finite temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09548v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: At finite temperature, conserved charges undergo thermal fluctuations in a quantum many-body system in the grand canonical ensemble. The full structure of the fluctuations of the total U(1) charge $Q$ can be succinctly captured by the generating function $G(\theta)=\left\langle e^{i \theta Q}\right\rangle$. For a 1D translation-invariant spin chain, in the thermodynamic limit the magnitude $|G(\theta)|$ scales with the system size $L$ as $\ln |G(\theta)|=-\alpha(\theta)L+\gamma(\theta)$, where $\gamma(\theta)$ is the scale-invariant contribution and may encode universal information about the underlying system. In this work we investigate the behavior and physical meaning of $\gamma(\theta)$ when the system is periodic. We find that $\gamma(\theta)$ only takes non-zero values at isolated points of $\theta$, which is $\theta=\pi$ for all our examples. In two exemplary lattice systems we show that $\gamma(\pi)$ takes quantized values when the U(1) symmetry exhibits a specific type of 't Hooft anomaly with other symmetries. In other cases, we investigate how $\gamma(\theta)$ depends on microscopic conditions (such as the filling factor) in field theory and exactly solvable lattice models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09548v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang-Le Cai, Meng Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor network simulations for non-orientable surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15507v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we explore the geometric construction of the Klein bottle and the real projective plane ($\mathrm{RP}^2$) within the framework of tensor networks, focusing on the implementation of crosscap and rainbow boundaries. Previous investigations have applied boundary matrix product state (BMPS) techniques to study these boundaries. We introduce a novel approach that incorporates such boundaries into the tensor renormalization group (TRG) methodology, facilitated by an efficient representation of a spatial reflection operator. This advancement enables us to compute the crosscap and rainbow free energy terms and the one-point function on $\mathrm{RP}^2$ with enhanced efficiency and for larger system sizes. Additionally, our method is capable of calculating the partition function under isotropic conditions of space and imaginary time. The versatility of this approach is further underscored by its applicability to constructing other (non-)orientable surfaces of higher genus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15507v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruki Shimizu, Atsushi Ueda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface Luttinger surfaces and Luttinger-Lifshitz transitions in topological band structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18820v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The standard paradigm of topological phases posits that the surface two phases with the same symmetries are necessarily separated by a bulk phase transition, while breaking the symmetry unlocks a path in parameter space that allows the phases to be connected adiabatically. Moreover, if the symmetry is broken only on the boundary, single-particle properties are expected to be blind to distinction between the two phases. In this work, we prove that this expectation is incorrect. We first reveal that the single-particle \emph{surface} Green's function contains zeros or ``LSs'' that respect the same bulk-boundary correspondence that the well-known topological surface states do. At non-zero temperatures, these modes contribute negatively to an effective surface specific heat. Remarkably, the LSs survive symmetry-breaking perturbations that destroy the surface states. Thus, a bulk topological phase transition causes a reconstruction of Luttinger surfaces on the surface and manifests as a discontinuity in the surface specific heat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18820v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Chen, Pavan Hosur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystalline axion electrodynamics in charge-ordered Dirac semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00055v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Three-dimensional Dirac semimetals can be driven into an insulating state by coupling to a charge density wave (CDW) order. Here, we consider the quantized crystalline responses of such charge-ordered Dirac semimetals, which we dub Dirac-CDW insulators, in which charge is bound to disclination defects of the lattice. Using analytic and numeric methods we show the following. First, when the CDW is lattice-commensurate, disclination-line defects of the lattice have a quantized charge per length. Second, when the CDW is inversion-symmetric, disclinations of the lattice have a quantized electric polarization. Third, when the CDW is lattice-commensurate and inversion-symmetric, disclinations are characterized by a "disclination filling anomaly" -- a quantized difference in the total charge bound to disclination-lines of Dirac-CDW with open and periodic boundaries. We construct an effective response theory that captures the topological responses of the Dirac-CDW insulators in terms of a total derivative term, denoted the $R\wedge F$ term. The $R\wedge F$ term describes the crystalline analog of the axion electrodynamics that are found in Weyl semimetal-CDW insulators. We also use the crystalline responses and corresponding response theories to classify the strongly correlated topological phases of three-dimensions Dirac-semimetals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00055v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian May-Mann, Mark R. Hirsbrunner, Lei Gioia, Taylor L. Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of charge density waves in electron-phonon systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.05667v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that electron-phonon interactions enhance the stability of charge density waves in low-temperature phases of many-electron systems. Our proof method involves an appropriate application of the Pirogov--Sinai theory to electron-phonon systems. Combining our findings with existing results, we obtain rigorous information regarding the low-temperature phase diagram for half-filled electron-phonon systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.05667v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadahiro Miyao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Charges, Part I: Invertible Symmetries and Higher Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.02660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.02660v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: $q$-charges describe the possible actions of a generalized symmetry on $q$-dimensional operators. In Part I of this series of papers, we describe $q$-charges for invertible symmetries; while the discussion of $q$-charges for non-invertible symmetries is the topic of Part II. We argue that $q$-charges of a standard global symmetry, also known as a 0-form symmetry, correspond to the so-called $(q+1)$-representations of the 0-form symmetry group, which are natural higher-categorical generalizations of the standard notion of representations of a group. This generalizes already our understanding of possible charges under a 0-form symmetry! Just like local operators form representations of the 0-form symmetry group, higher-dimensional extended operators form higher-representations. This statement has a straightforward generalization to other invertible symmetries: $q$-charges of higher-form and higher-group symmetries are $(q+1)$-representations of the corresponding higher-groups. There is a natural extension to higher-charges of non-genuine operators (i.e. operators that are attached to higher-dimensional operators), which will be shown to be intertwiners of higher-representations. This brings into play the higher-categorical structure of higher-representations. We also discuss higher-charges of twisted sector operators (i.e. operators that appear at the boundary of topological operators of one dimension higher), including operators that appear at the boundary of condensation defects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.02660v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lakshya Bhardwaj, Sakura Schafer-Nameki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Monte Carlo for Gauge Fields and Matter without the Fermion Determinant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.08917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.08917v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ab-initio Monte Carlo simulations of strongly-interacting fermionic systems are plagued by the fermion sign problem, making the non-perturbative study of many interesting regimes of dense quantum matter, or of theories of odd numbers of fermion flavors, challenging. Moreover, typical fermion algorithms require the computation (or sampling) of the fermion determinant. We focus instead on the meron cluster algorithm, which can solve the fermion sign problem in a class of models without involving the determinant. We develop and benchmark new meron algorithms to simulate fermions coupled to $\mathbb{Z}_2$ and $U(1)$ gauge fields in the presence of appropriate four-fermi interactions. Such algorithms can be used to uncover potential exotic properties of matter, particularly relevant for quantum simulator experiments. We demonstrate the emergence of the Gauss' Law at low temperatures for a $U(1)$ model in $(1+1)-$d.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.08917v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.L031506</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D (Letter) 109, L031506 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Debasish Banerjee, Emilie Huffman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Lego Expansion Pack: Enumerators from Tensor Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.05152v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide the first tensor network method for computing quantum weight enumerator polynomials in the most general form. If a quantum code has a known tensor network construction of its encoding map, our method is far more efficient, and in some cases exponentially faster than the existing approach. As a corollary, it produces decoders and an algorithm that computes the code distance. For non-(Pauli)-stabilizer codes, this constitutes the current best algorithm for computing the code distance. For degenerate stabilizer codes, it can be substantially faster compared to the current methods. We also introduce novel weight enumerators and their applications. In particular, we show that these enumerators can be used to compute logical error rates exactly and thus construct (optimal) decoders for any i.i.d. single qubit or qudit error channels. The enumerators also provide a more efficient method for computing non-stabilizerness in quantum many-body states. As the power for these speedups rely on a Quantum Lego decomposition of quantum codes, we further provide systematic methods for decomposing quantum codes and graph states into a modular construction for which our technique applies. As a proof of principle, we perform exact analyses of the deformed surface codes, the holographic pentagon code, and the 2d Bacon-Shor code under (biased) Pauli noise and limited instances of coherent error at sizes that are inaccessible by brute force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.05152v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>ChunJun Cao, Michael J. Gullans, Brad Lackey, Zitao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.06442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.06442v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topological semimetals, such as the Weyl and Dirac semimetals, represent one of the most active research fields in modern condensed matter physics. The peculiar physical properties of these systems mainly originate from their underlying symmetries, emergent relativistic dispersion, and band topology. In this paper, we present a novel class of $\textit{geometric semimetals}$ in three dimensions. These semimetals are protected by the generalized chiral and rotation symmetries, but are topologically trivial. Nevertheless, we show that their band geometry is nontrivial, as evidenced by the nonzero quantum metric trace with possible quantization. The possible realization in synthetic-matter experiments is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.06442v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Ping Lin, Giandomenico Palumbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative RG flows in AdS: an \'etude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10031v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss general properties of perturbative RG flows in AdS with a focus on the treatment of boundary conditions and infrared divergences. In contrast with flat-space boundary QFT, general covariance in AdS implies the absence of independent boundary flows. We illustrate how boundary correlation functions remain conformally covariant even if the bulk QFT has a scale. We apply our general discussion to the RG flow between consecutive unitary diagonal minimal models which is triggered by the $\phi_{(1,3)}$ operator. For these theories we conjecture a flow diagram whose form is significantly simpler than that in flat-space boundary QFT. In several stand-alone appendices we discuss two-dimensional BCFTs in general and the minimal model BCFTs in particular. These include both an extensive review as well as the computation of several new BCFT correlation functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10031v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edoardo Lauria, Michael N. Milam, Balt C. van Rees</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge Conservation Beyond Uniformity: Spatially Inhomogeneous Electromagnetic Response in Periodic Solids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11658v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nonlinear electromagnetic response functions have reemerged as a crucial tool for studying quantum materials. Most attention has been paid to responses to spatially uniform electric fields, relevant to optical experiments in conventional materials. However, magnetic and magnetoelectric phenomena are naturally connected by responses to spatially varying electric fields due to Maxwell's equations. Furthermore, in moir\'{e} materials, characteristic lattice scales are much longer, allowing spatial variation of optical electric fields to potentially have a measurable effect in experiments. To address these issues, we develop a formalism for computing linear and nonlinear responses to spatially inhomogeneous electromagnetic fields. Starting with the continuity equation, we derive an expression for the current operator that is manifestly conserved and model independent. Crucially, our formalism makes no assumptions on the form of the microscopic Hamiltonian and so is applicable to model Hamiltonians derived from tight-binding or ab initio calculations. We then develop a diagrammatic Kubo formalism for computing the wavevector dependence of linear and nonlinear conductivities, using Ward identities to fix the value of the diamagnetic current order-by-order in the vector potential. We apply our formula to compute the magnitude of the Kerr effect at oblique incidence for a model of a moir\'{e} Chern insulator and demonstrate the experimental relevance of spatially inhomogeneous fields in these systems. We further show how our formalism allows us to compute the magnetic multipole moments and magnetic susceptibility in insulators. We next use our formalism to compute the second-order transverse response to spatially varying transverse electric fields in our moir\'{e} Chern insulator model, with an eye towards the next generation of experiments in these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11658v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert C. McKay, Fahad Mahmood, Barry Bradlyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Programmable order by disorder effect and underlying phases through dipolar quantum simulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00849v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we study two different quantum simulators through various theoretical and numerical tools. Our first result provides knowledge upon the quantum order by disorder effect of the $S=1/2$ system, which is programmable in a quantum simulator composed of circular Rydberg atoms. When the total magnetization is zero, a set of sub-extensive degenerate ground states is present in the classical limit, composed of continuous strings whose configuration enjoys a large degree of freedom. Among all possible configurations, we focus on the stripe (up and down spins aligning straightly) and kinked (up and down spins forming zigzag spin chains) patterns. Adopting the real space perturbation theory, we estimate the leading order energy correction when the nearest-neighbor spin exchange coupling, $J$, is considered, and the overall model becomes an effective XXZ model with a spatial anisotropy. Our calculation demonstrates a lifting of the degeneracy, favoring the stripe configuration. When $J$ becomes larger, we adopt the infinite projected entangled-pair state and numerically check the effect of degeneracy lifting, showing that even when the spin exchange coupling term is strong the stripe pattern is still favored. Next, we study the dipolar bosonic model with tilted polar angle which can be realized through a quantum simulator composed of cold atomic gas with dipole-dipole interaction in an optical lattice. By placing the atoms in a triangular lattice and tilting the polar angle, the diagonal anisotropy can also be realized in the bosonic system. With our cluster mean-field theory calculation, we provide various phase diagrams with different tilted angles, showing the abundant underlying phases including the supersolid. Our proposals indicate realizable scenarios through quantum simulators in studying the quantum effect as well as extraordinary phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00849v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huan-Kuang Wu, Takafumi Suzuki, Naoki Kawashima, Wei-Lin Tu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of magnetic ions in the thermal Hall effect of the paramagnetic insulator TmVO$_{4}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10643v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In a growing number of materials, phonons have been found to generate a thermal Hall effect, but the underlying mechanism remains unclear. Inspired by previous studies that revealed the importance of Tb$^{3+}$ ions in generating the thermal Hall effect of Tb$_{2}$Ti$_{2}$O$_{7}$, we investigated the role of Tm$^{3+}$ ions in TmVO$_{4}$, a paramagnetic insulator with a different crystal structure. We observe a negative thermal Hall conductivity in TmVO$_{4}$ with a magnitude such that the Hall angle, $|\kappa_{xy}$/$\kappa_{xx}|$, is approximately 1 x 10$^{-3}$ at $H$ = 15 T and $T$ = 20 K, typical for a phonon-generated thermal Hall effect. In contrast to the negligible $\kappa_{xy}$ found in Y$_{2}$Ti$_{2}$O$_{7}$, we observe a negative $\kappa_{xy}$ in YVO$_{4}$ with a Hall angle of magnitude comparable to that of TmVO$_{4}$. This shows that the Tm$^{3+}$ ions are not essential for the thermal Hall effect in this family of materials. Interestingly, at an intermediate Y concentration of 30 % in Tm$_{1-x}$Y$_{x}$VO$_{4}$, $\kappa_{xy}$ was found to have a positive sign, pointing to the possible importance of impurities in the thermal Hall effect of phonons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10643v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashvini Vallipuram, Lu Chen, Emma Campillo, Manel Mezidi, Ga\"el Grissonnanche, Mark P. Zic, Yuntian Li, Ian R. Fisher, Jordan Baglo, Louis Taillefer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances in high-pressure laser floating zone growth: the Laser Optical Kristallmacher II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03671v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The optical floating zone crystal growth technique is a well-established method for obtaining large, high-purity single crystals. While the floating zone method has been constantly evolving for over six decades, the development of high-pressure (up to 1000 bar) growth systems has only recently been realized via the combination of laser-based heating sources with an all-metal chamber. While our inaugural high-pressure laser floating zone furnace design demonstrated the successful growth of new volatile and metastable phases, the furnace design faces several limitations with imaging quality, heating profile control, and chamber cooling power. Here, we present a second-generation design of the high-pressure laser floating zone furnace, "Laser Optical Kristallmacher II" (LOKII), and demonstrate that this redesign facilitates new advances in crystal growth by highlighting several exemplar materials: ${\alpha}$-Fe$_2$O$_3$, $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$, and La$_2$CuO$_{4+{\delta}}$. Notably, for La$_2$CuO$_{4+{\delta}}$, we demonstrate the feasibility and long-term stability of traveling solvent floating zone growth under a record pressure of 700 bar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03671v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven J. Gomez Alvarado, Eli Zoghlin, Azzedin Jackson, Linus Kautzsch, Jayden Plumb, Michael Aling, Andrea N. Capa Salinas, Ganesh Pokharel, Yiming Pang, Reina M. Gomez, Samantha Daly, Stephen D. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficiency of neural quantum states in light of the quantum geometric tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01565v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural quantum state (NQS) ans\"atze have shown promise in variational Monte Carlo algorithms by their theoretical capability of representing any quantum state. However, the reason behind the practical improvement in their performance with an increase in the number of parameters is not fully understood. In this work, we systematically study the efficiency of restricted Boltzmann Machines (RBMs) to represent the ground states in different phases of the spin-1 bilinear-biquadratic model, as the hidden layer density $\alpha$ increases. We train our ansatz by minimizing two different loss functions: 1) energy, and 2) infidelity of the NQS ansatz w.r.t. that of the exact ground state. We observe that the accuracy of our ansatz saturates with $\alpha$ in both cases. We demonstrate that this can be explained by looking at the spectrum of the quantum geometric tensor (QGT). We find that the rank of the QGT saturates beyond a certain $\alpha$, and we emphasize that it corresponds to the \textit{dimension of the relevant manifold} for an optimized NQS. This provides a useful diagnostics for the practical representation power of an NQS ansatz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01565v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sidhartha Dash, Filippo Vicentini, Michel Ferrero, Antoine Georges</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary-induced transitions in M\"obius quenches of holographic BCFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16555v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Boundary effects play an interesting role in finite-size physical systems. In this work, we study the boundary-induced properties of 1+1-dimensional critical systems driven by inhomogeneous M\"obius-like quenches. We focus on the entanglement entropy in BCFTs with a large central charge and a sparse spectrum of low-dimensional operators. We find that the choice of boundary conditions leads to different scenarios of dynamical phase transitions. We also derive these results in a holographic description in terms of intersecting branes in AdS$_3$, and find a precise match.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16555v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice Bernamonti, Federico Galli, Dongsheng Ge</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
