<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the small and large in twisted transition metal dicalcogenide homobilayers: a tight binding model capturing orbital interference and topology across a wide range of twist angles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many of the important phases observed in twisted transition metal dichalcogenide homobilayers are driven by short-range interactions, which should be captured by a local tight binding description since no Wannier obstruction exists for these systems. Yet, published theoretical descriptions have been mutually inconsistent, with honeycomb lattice tight binding models adopted for some twist angles, triangular lattice models adopted for others, and with tight binding models forsaken in favor of band projected continuum models in many numerical simulations. Here, we derive and study a minimal model containing both honeycomb orbitals and a triangular site that represents the band physics across a wide range of twist angles. The model provides a natural basis to study the interplay of interaction and topology in these heterostructures. It elucidates from generic features of the bilayer the sequence of Chern numbers occurring as twist angle is varied, and the microscopic origin of the magic angle at which flat-band physics occurs. At integer filling, the model successfully captures the Chern ferromagnetic and van-Hove driven antiferromagnetic insulators experimentally observed for small and large angles, respectively, and allows a straightforward calculation of the magneto-electric properties of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15546v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentin Cr\'epel, Andrew Millis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fractional quantum Hall nematics on the first Landau level in a tilted field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated the behavior of fractional quantum Hall (FQH) states in a two-dimensional electron system with layer thickness and an in-plane magnetic field. Our comparisons across various filling factors within the first Landau level revealed a crucial observation. A slight in-plane magnetic field specifically enhances the nematic order of the $\nu = 7/3$ FQH state. For this particular filling, through calculating the energy gap, the Ising nematic order parameter, the pair-correlation function, and the static structure factor, we observed that as the in-plane magnetic field increases, the system first enters into an anisotropic FQH phase without closing the spectrum gap, then the FQH nematic (FQHN) phase after neutral gap closing. The system eventually enters a gapless one-dimensional charge density wave (CDW) phase for a large in-plane field. We thus provide a full phase diagram of the $\nu = 7/3$ state in a tilted magnetic field, demonstrating the existence of the FQHN, which aligns with recent resonant inelastic light scattering (RILS) experimental observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15820v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Ye, Chen-Xin Jiang, Zi-Xiang Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conductivity of a nonlinear Luttinger liquid with a large-scaled random potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a calculation of the uniform conductivity of one-dimensional degenerate fermion system with some large-scaled disorder. We use the nonlinear Luttinger liquid model. The only important limitation is that the frequency has to be large enough. Apart from that and few other minor constraints, the calculation is fairly general. For instance, we neither assume the interaction to be point-like nor weak. As a result, we obtain conductivity across a wide range of parameters, the parameters are the disorder scale, frequency, interaction radius and temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15930v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Dontsov, D. N. Aristov, A. P. Dmitriev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Kramers-Wanier Duality from Bilinear Phase Map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the Bilinear Phase Map (BPM), a concept that extends the Kramers-Wannier (KW) transformation to investigate unconventional gapped phases, their dualities, and phase transitions. Defined by a matrix of $\mathbb{Z}_2$ elements, the BPM not only encapsulates the essence of KW duality but also enables exploration of a broader spectrum of generalized quantum phases and dualities. By analyzing the BPM's linear algebraic properties, we elucidate the loss of unitarity in duality transformations and derive general non-invertible fusion rules. Applying this framework to (1+1)D systems yields the discovery of new dualities, shedding light on the interplay between various Symmetry Protected Topological (SPT) and Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking (SSB) phases. Additionally, we construct a duality web that interconnects these phases and their transitions, offering valuable insights into relations between different quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16017v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Yan, Linhao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging quantum interference in a monolayer Kitaev quantum spin liquid candidate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single atomic defects are prominent windows to look into host quantum states because collective responses from the host states emerge as localized states around the defects. Friedel oscillations and Kondo clouds in Fermi liquids are quintessential examples. However, the situation is quite different for quantum spin liquid (QSL), an exotic state of matter with fractionalized quasiparticles and topological order arising from a profound impact of quantum entanglement. Elucidating the underlying local electronic property has been challenging due to the charge neutrality of fractionalized quasiparticles and the insulating nature of QSLs. Here, using spectroscopic-imaging scanning tunneling microscopy, we report atomically resolved images of monolayer $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$, the most promising Kitaev QSL candidate, on metallic substrates. We find quantum interference in the insulator manifesting as incommensurate and decaying spatial oscillations of the local density of states around defects with a characteristic bias dependence. The oscillation differs from any known spatial structures in its nature and does not exist in other Mott insulators, implying it is an exotic oscillation involved with excitations unique to $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$. Numerical simulations can reproduce the observed oscillation by assuming that itinerant Majorana fermions of Kitaev QSL are scattered across the Majorana Fermi surface. The oscillation provides a new approach to exploring Kitaev QSLs through the local response against defects like Friedel oscillations in metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16553v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Kohsaka, S. Akutagawa, S. Omachi, Y. Iwamichi, T. Ono, I. Tanaka, S. Tateishi, H. Murayama, S. Suetsugu, K. Hashimoto, T. Shibauchi, M. O. Takahashi, M. G. Yamada, S. Nikolaev, T. Mizushima, S. Fujimoto, T. Terashima, T. Asaba, Y. Kasahara, Y. Matsuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Dipole Hall effect in tMoTe$_2$ moir\'{e}: magnetoelectricity and contact-free signature of topological transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discover an intrinsic dipole Hall effect in a variety of magnetic insulating states at integer fillings of twisted MoTe$_2$ moir\'e superlattice, including topologically trivial and nontrivial ferro-, antiferro-, and ferri-magnetic configurations. The dipole Hall current, in linear response to in-plane electric field, generates an in-plane orbital magnetization $M_{\parallel}$ along the field, through which an AC field can drive magnetization oscillation up to THz range. Upon the continuous topological phase transitions from trivial to quantum anomalous Hall states in both ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic configurations, the dipole Hall current and $M_{\parallel}$ have an abrupt sign change, enabling contact free detection of the transitions through the magnetic stray field. In configurations where the linear response is forbidden by symmetry, the dipole Hall current and $M_{\parallel}$ appear as a crossed nonlinear response to both in-plane and out-of-plane electric fields. These magnetoelectric phenomena showcase novel functionalities of insulators from the interplay between magnetism, topology and electrical polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16586v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng-Ren Fan, Cong Xiao, Wang Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Order in Honeycomb Layered U$_2$Pt$_6$Ga$_{15}$ Studied by Resonant X-ray and Neutron Scatterings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Antiferromagnetic (AF) order of U$_{2}$Pt$_{6}$Ga$_{15}$ with the ordering temperature $T_{\rm N}$ = 26 K was investigated by resonant X-ray scattering and neutron diffraction on single crystals. This compound possesses a unique crystal structure in which uranium ions form honeycomb layers and then stacks along the $c$-axis with slight offset, which gives rise to a stacking disorder. The AF order can be described with the propagation vector of $q = (1/6, 1/6, 0)$ in the hexagonal notation. The ordered magnetic moments orient perpendicular to the honeycomb layers, indicating a collinear spin structure consistent with Ising-like anisotropy. The magnetic reflections are found to be broadened along $c^*$ indicating that the stacking disorder results in anisotropic correlation lengths. The semi-quantitative analysis of neutron diffraction intensity, combined with group theory considerations based on the crystallographic symmetry, suggests a zig-zag type magnetic structure for the AF ground state, in which the AF coupling runs perpendicular to the stacking offset, characterized as $q = (1, 0, 0)_{\rm orth}$. The realization of the zig-zag magnetic structure implies the presence of frustrating intralayer exchange interactions involving both ferromagnetic (FM) first-neighbor and AF second and third-neighbor interactions in this compound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16672v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chihiro Tabata, Fusako Kon, Kyugo Ota, Ruo Hibino, Yuji Matsumoto, Hiroshi Amitsuka, Hironori Nakao, Yoshinori Haga, Koji Kaneko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite Grassmann Time-Evolving Matrix Product Operator Method in the Steady State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an infinite Grassmann time-evolving matrix product operator method for quantum impurity problems, which directly works in the steady state. The method embraces the well-established infinite matrix product state algorithms with the recently developed GTEMPO method, and benefits from both sides: it obtains numerically exact real-time Green's functions without sampling noises, it is applicable for any temperature without the sign problem, its computational cost is independent of the transient dynamics and does not scale with the number of baths. We benchmark the method on the finite-temperature equilibrium Green's function in the noninteracting limit against exact solutions and in the single-orbital Anderson impurity model against GTEMPO calculations. We also study the zero-temperature non-equilibrium steady state of an impurity coupled to two baths with a voltage bias, obtaining consistent particle currents with existing calculations. The method is ideal for studying steady-state quantum transport, and can be readily used as an efficient real-time impurity solver in quantum embedding methods such as the dynamical mean field theory and its non-equilibrium extension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16700v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chu Guo, Ruofan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raman spectroscopy of Na$_3$Co$_2$SbO$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Raman spectroscopy together with density functional calculations were used to study lattice dynamics in a layered honeycomb cobaltite Na$_3$Co$_2$SbO$_6$, which can host a field-induced phase related with the Kitaev physics. We show that there develops an additional mode well above Neel temperature (at $\approx 200$K) at 525 cm$^{-1}$, which origin can be related to an electronic excitation to one of $j_{3/2}$ doublets. Moreover, our theoretical calculations demonstrate that the highest frequency intensive mode related to the oxygen vibrations is very sensitive to type of the magnetic order. Thus, we propose to use the softening of this mode as a hallmark of the transition to a fully polarized regime, which is stabilized in Kitaev materials in strong magnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16943v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. S. Ponosov, E. V. Komleva, E. A. Pankrushina, D. Mikhailova, S. V. Streltsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locally Purified Density Operators for Symmetry-Protected Topological Phases in Mixed States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a tensor network approach known as the locally purified density operator (LPDO) to investigate the classification and characterization of symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phases in open quantum systems. We extend the concept of injectivity, originally associated with matrix product states and projected entangled pair states, to LPDOs in $(1+1)D$ and $(2+1)D$ systems, unveiling two distinct types of injectivity conditions inherent in short-range entangled density matrices. Within the LPDO framework, we outline a classification scheme for decohered average symmetry-protected topological (ASPT) phases, consistent with earlier results obtained through spectrum sequence techniques. We illustrate our framework with examples of ASPTs protected by fermion parity symmetry in both $(1+1)D$ and $(2+1)D$ systems. In addition, we discuss the classification of ASPT phases for a general group extension. We demonstrate examples of explicit construction of fixed-point LPDOs for ASPT phases including intrinsic ASPTs in $(1+1)D$ systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16978v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Guo, Jian-Hao Zhang, Shuo Yang, Zhen Bi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Chern bands in twisted MoTe$_2$ and possible non-Abelian states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17003v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the moir\'e band structures and possible even denominator fractional quantum Hall state in small angle twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$, using combined large-scale local basis density functional theory calculation and continuum model exact diagonalization. Via large-scale first principles calculations at $\theta=1.89^{\circ}$, we find a sequence of $C=1$ moir\'e Chern bands, in analogy to Landau levels. Constructing the continuum model with multiple Chern bands and uniform Berry curvature in the second moir\'e band, we undertake band-projected exact diagonalization using unscreened Coulomb repulsion to pinpoint possible $\nu=-3/2$ non-Abelian states across a wide range of twist angles below $\theta=2.5^{\circ}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17003v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Xu, Ning Mao, Tiansheng Zeng, Yang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic State Interaction with Large Localized Active Spaces for Multimetallic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15495v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The localized active space self consistent field (LASSCF) method factorizes a complete active space (CAS) wave function into an antisymmetrized product of localized active space wave function fragments. Correlation between fragments is then reintroduced through LAS state interaction (LASSI), in which the Hamiltonian is diagonalized in a model space of LAS states. However, the optimal procedure for defining the LAS fragments and LASSI model space is unknown. We here present an automated framework to explore systematically convergent sets of model spaces, which we call LASSI[$r$,$q$]. This method requires the user to select only $r$, the number of electron hops from one fragment to another and $q$, the number of fragment basis functions per Hilbert space, which converges to CASCI in the limit of $r,q\to\infty$. Numerical tests of this method on the tri-metal complexes [Fe(III)Al(III)Fe(II)($\mu_3$-O)]$^{6+}$ and [Fe(III)$_2$Fe(II)($\mu_3$-O)]$^{6+}$ show efficient convergence to the CASCI limit with 4-10 orders of magnitude fewer states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15495v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valay Agarawal, Daniel King, Matthew R. Hermes, Laura Gagliardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of rare-earth atoms in the anisotropy and antiferromagnetic exchange coupling at a hybrid metal-organic interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic anisotropy and magnetic exchange interactions are crucial parameters that characterize the hybrid metal-organic interface, key component of an organic spintronic device. We show that the incorporation of 4$f$ RE atoms to hybrid metal-organic interfaces of CuPc/REAu$_2$ type (RE= Gd, Ho) constitutes a feasible approach towards on-demand magnetic properties and functionalities. The GdAu$_2$ and HoAu$_2$ substrates differ in their magnetic anisotropy behavior. Remarkably, the HoAu$_2$ surface boosts the inherent out-of-plane anisotropy of CuPc, owing to the match between the anisotropy axis of substrate and molecule. Furthermore, the presence of RE atoms leads to a spontaneous antiferromagnetic (AFM) exchange coupling at the interface, induced by the 3$d$-4$f$ superexchange interaction between the unpaired 3$d$ electron of CuPc and the 4$f$ electrons of the RE atoms. We show that 4$f$ RE atoms with unquenched quantum orbital momentum ($L$), as it is the case of Ho, induce an anisotropic interfacial exchange coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15774v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mar\'ia Blanco-Rey, Rodrigo Castrillo, Khadiza Ali, Pierluigi Gargiani, Max Ilyn, Michele Gastaldo, Markos Paradinas, Miguel A. Valbuena, Aitor Mugarza, J. Enrique Ortega, Frederik Schiller, Laura Fern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractal ground state of ion chains in periodic potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15843v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Trapped ions in a periodic potential are a paradigm of a frustrated Wigner crystal. The dynamics is captured by a long-range Frenkel-Kontorova model. The classical ground state can be mapped to the one of an antiferromagnetic spin chain with long-range interactions in a magnetic field, whose strength is determined by the mismatch between chain's and substrate lattice's periodicity. The mapping is exact when the substrate potential is a piecewise harmonic potential and holds for any two-body interaction decaying as $1/r^\alpha$ with the distance $r$. The ground state is a devil's staircase of regular, periodic structures as a function of the mismatch, whose range of stability depends also on the coefficient $\alpha$. While the staircase is well defined in the thermodynamic limit for $\alpha&gt;1$, for Coulomb interactions, $\alpha=1$, it disappears and the sliding-to-pinned transitions becomes crossovers. However, due to the logarithmic convergence to the thermodynamic limit characteristic of the Coulomb potential, the staircase is found for any finite number of ions. We discuss the experimental parameters as well as the features that allow one to observe and reveal our predictions in experimental platforms. These dynamics are a showcase of the versatility of trapped ion platforms for exploring the interplay between frustration and interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15843v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rapha\"el Menu, Jorge Yago Malo, Vladan Vuleti\'c, Maria Luisa Chiofalo, Giovanna Morigi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local operator quench induced by two-dimensional inhomogeneous and homogeneous CFT Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore non-equilibrium processes in two-dimensional conformal field theories (2d CFTs) due to the growth of operators induced by inhomogeneous and homogeneous Hamiltonians by investigating the time dependence of the partition function, energy density, and entanglement entropy. The non-equilibrium processes considered in this paper are constructed out of the Lorentzian and Euclidean time evolution governed by different Hamiltonians. We explore the effect of the time ordering on entanglement dynamics so that we find that in a free boson CFT and RCFTs, this time ordering does not affect the entanglement entropy, while in the holographic CFTs, it does. Our main finding is that in the holographic CFTs, the non-unitary time evolution induced by the inhomogeneous Hamiltonian can retain the initial state information longer than in the unitary time evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15851v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weibo Mao, Masahiro Nozaki, Kotaro Tamaoka, Mao Tian Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of the dual quantum spin Hall insulator by density-tuned correlations in a van der Waals monolayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15912v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The convergence of topology and correlations represents a highly coveted realm in the pursuit of novel quantum states of matter. Introducing electron correlations to a quantum spin Hall (QSH) insulator can lead to the emergence of a fractional topological insulator and other exotic time-reversal-symmetric topological order, not possible in quantum Hall and Chern insulator systems. However, the QSH insulator with quantized edge conductance remains rare, let alone that with significant correlations. In this work, we report a novel dual QSH insulator within the intrinsic monolayer crystal of TaIrTe4, arising from the interplay of its single-particle topology and density-tuned electron correlations. At charge neutrality, monolayer TaIrTe4 demonstrates the QSH insulator that aligns with single-particle band structure calculations, manifesting enhanced nonlocal transport and quantized helical edge conductance. Interestingly, upon introducing electrons from charge neutrality, TaIrTe4 only shows metallic behavior in a small range of charge densities but quickly goes into a new insulating state, entirely unexpected based on TaIrTe4's single-particle band structure. This insulating state could arise from a strong electronic instability near the van Hove singularities (VHS), likely leading to a charge density wave (CDW). Remarkably, within this correlated insulating gap, we observe a resurgence of the QSH state, marked by the revival of nonlocal transport and quantized helical edge conduction. Our observation of helical edge conduction in a CDW gap could bridge spin physics and charge orders. The discovery of a dual QSH insulator introduces a new method for creating topological flat minibands via CDW superlattices, which offer a promising platform for exploring time-reversal-symmetric fractional phases and electromagnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15912v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-024-07211-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jian Tang, Thomas Siyuan Ding, Hongyu Chen, Anyuan Gao, Tiema Qian, Zumeng Huang, Zhe Sun, Xin Han, Alex Strasser, Jiangxu Li, Michael Geiwitz, Mohamed Shehabeldin, Vsevolod Belosevich, Zihan Wang, Yiping Wang, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, David C. Bell, Ziqiang Wang, Liang Fu, Yang Zhang, Xiaofeng Qian, Kenneth S. Burch, Youguo Shi, Ni Ni, Guoqing Chang, Su-Yang Xu, Qiong Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for a finite-momentum Cooper pair in tricolor $d$-wave superconducting superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16496v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fermionic superfluidity with a nontrivial Cooper-pairing, beyond the conventional Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer state, is a captivating field of study in quantum many-body systems. In particular, the search for superconducting states with finite-momentum pairs has long been a challenge, but establishing its existence has long suffered from the lack of an appropriate probe to reveal its momentum. Recently, it has been proposed that the nonreciprocal {\cred electron} transport is the most {\cred powerful} probe for the finite-momentum pairs, {\cred because it directly couples} to the supercurrents. Here we reveal such a pairing state by the non-reciprocal transport on tricolor superlattices with strong spin-orbit coupling combined with broken inversion-symmetry consisting of atomically thin $d$-wave superconductor CeCoIn$_5$. We find that while the second-harmonic resistance exhibits a distinct dip anomaly at the low-temperature ($T$)/high-magnetic field ($H$) corner in the $HT$-plane for ${\bm H}$ applied to the antinodal direction of the $d$-wave gap, such an anomaly is absent for ${\bm H}$ along the nodal direction. By meticulously isolating extrinsic effects due to vortex dynamics, we reveal the presence of a non-reciprocal response originating from intrinsic superconducting properties characterized by finite-momentum pairs. We attribute the high-field state to the helical superconducting state, wherein the phase of the order parameter is spontaneously spatially modulated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16496v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Asaba, M. Naritsuka, H. Asaeda, Y. Kosuge, S. Ikemori, S. Suetsugu, Y. Kasahara, Y. Kohsaka, T. Terashima, A. Daido, Y. Yanase, Y. Matsuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boson sampling enhanced quantum chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16698v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we give a new variational quantum algorithm for solving electronic structure problems of molecules using only linear quantum optical systems. The variational ansatz we proposed is a hybrid of non-interacting Boson dynamics and classical computational chemistry methods, specifically, the Hartree-Fock method and the Configuration Interaction method. The Boson part is built by a linear optical interferometer which is easier to realize compared with the well-known Unitary Coupled Cluster (UCC) ansatz composed of quantum gates in conventional VQE and the classical part is merely classical processing acting on the Hamiltonian. We called such ansatzes Boson Sampling-Classic (BS-C). The appearance of permanents in the Boson part has its physical intuition to provide different kinds of resources from commonly used single-, double-, and higher-excitations in classical methods and the UCC ansatz to exploring chemical quantum states. Such resources can help enhance the accuracy of methods used in the classical parts. We give a scalable hybrid homodyne and photon number measurement procedure for evaluating the energy value which has intrinsic abilities to mitigate photon loss errors and discuss the extra measurement cost induced by the no Pauli exclusion principle for Bosons with its solutions. To demonstrate our proposal, we run numerical experiments on several molecules and obtain their potential energy curves reaching chemical accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16698v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Xia Shang, Han-Sen Zhong, Yu-Kun Zhang, Cheng-Cheng Yu, Xiao Yuan, Chao-Yang Lu, Jian-Wei Pan, Ming-Cheng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling clean two-dimensional discrete time quasicrystals on a digital quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16718v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In periodically driven (Floquet) systems, evolution typically results in an infinite-temperature thermal state due to continuous energy absorption over time. However, before reaching thermal equilibrium, such systems may transiently pass through a meta-stable state known as a prethermal state. This prethermal state can exhibit phenomena not commonly observed in equilibrium, such as discrete time crystals (DTCs), making it an intriguing platform for exploring out-of-equilibrium dynamics. Here, we investigate the relaxation dynamics of initially prepared product states under periodic driving in a kicked Ising model using the IBM Quantum Heron processor, comprising 133 superconducting qubits arranged on a heavy-hexagonal lattice, over up to $100$ time steps. We identify the presence of a prethermal regime characterised by magnetisation measurements oscillating at twice the period of the Floquet cycle and demonstrate its robustness against perturbations to the transverse field. Our results provide evidence supporting the realisation of a period-doubling DTC in a two-dimensional system. Moreover, we discover that the longitudinal field induces additional amplitude modulations in the magnetisation with a period incommensurate with the driving period, leading to the emergence of discrete time quasicrystals (DTQCs). These observations are further validated through comparison with tensor-network and state-vector simulations. Our findings not only enhance our understanding of clean DTCs in two dimensions but also highlight the utility of digital quantum computers for simulating the dynamics of quantum many-body systems, addressing challenges faced by state-of-the-art classical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16718v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuya Shinjo, Kazuhiro Seki, Tomonori Shirakawa, Rong-Yang Sun, Seiji Yunoki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embedded skyrmion bags in thin films of chiral magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16931v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmions are topologically nontrivial spin configurations that possess particle-like properties. Earlier research was mainly focused on a specific type of skyrmion with topological charge Q = -1. However, theoretical analyses of two-dimensional chiral magnets have predicted the existence of skyrmion bags -- solitons with arbitrary positive or negative topological charge. Although such spin textures are metastable states, recent experimental observations have confirmed the stability of isolated skyrmion bags in a limited range of applied magnetic fields. Here, by utilizing Lorentz transmission electron microscopy, we show the extraordinary stability of skyrmion bags in thin plates of B20-type FeGe. In particular, we show that skyrmion bags embedded within a skyrmion lattice remain stable even in zero or inverted external magnetic fields. A robust protocol for nucleating such embedded skyrmion bags is provided. Our results agree perfectly with micromagnetic simulations and establish thin plates of cubic chiral magnets as a powerful platform for exploring a broad spectrum of topological magnetic solitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16931v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luyan Yang, Andrii S. Savchenko, Fengshan Zheng, Nikolai S. Kiselev, Filipp N. Rybakov, Xiaodong Han, Stefan Bl\"ugel, Rafal E. Dunin-Borkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-enabled symmetry-breaking orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.08828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.08828v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A spontaneous symmetry-breaking order is conventionally described by a tensor-product wave-function of some few-body clusters. We discuss a type of symmetry-breaking orders, dubbed entanglement-enabled symmetry-breaking orders, which cannot be realized by any tensor-product state. Given a symmetry breaking pattern, we propose a criterion to diagnose if the symmetry-breaking order is entanglement-enabled, by examining the compatibility between the symmetries and the tensor-product description. For concreteness, we present an infinite family of exactly solvable gapped models on one-dimensional lattices with nearest-neighbor interactions, whose ground states exhibit entanglement-enabled symmetry-breaking orders from a discrete symmetry breaking. In addition, these ground states have gapless edge modes protected by the unbroken symmetries. We also propose a construction to realize entanglement-enabled symmetry-breaking orders with spontaneously broken continuous symmetries. Under the unbroken symmetries, some of our examples can be viewed as symmetry-protected topological states that are beyond the conventional classifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.08828v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhysCore.7.1.010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. Core 7, 010 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Ju Lin, Liujun Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermionic Isometric Tensor Network States in Two Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.00043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.00043v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We generalize isometric tensor network states to fermionic systems, paving the way for efficient adaptations of 1D tensor network algorithms to 2D fermionic systems. As the first application of this formalism, we developed and benchmarked a time-evolution block-decimation (TEBD) algorithm for real-time and imaginary-time evolution. The imaginary-time evolution produces ground-state energies for gapped systems, systems with a Dirac point, and systems with gapless edge modes to good accuracy. The real-time TEBD captures the scattering of two fermions and the chiral edge dynamics on the boundary of a Chern insulator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.00043v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhehao Dai, Yantao Wu, Taige Wang, Michael P. Zaletel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge order induced Dirac pockets in the nonsymmorphic crystal TaTe$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.00425v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay between charge order (CO) and nontrivial band topology has spurred tremendous interest in understanding topological excitations beyond the single-particle description. In a quasi-one-dimensional nonsymmorphic crystal TaTe$_4$, the (2a$\times$2b$\times$3c) charge ordered ground state drives the system into a space group where the symmetry indicator features the emergence of Dirac fermions and unconventional double Dirac fermions. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and first-principles calculations, we provide evidence of the CO induced Dirac fermion-related bands near the Fermi level. Furthermore, the band folding at the Fermi level is compatible with the new periodicity dictated by the CO, indicating that the electrons near the Fermi level follow the crystalline symmetries needed to host double Dirac fermions in this system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.00425v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.108.155121</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B. 108, 155121 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yichen Zhang, Ruixiang Zhou, Hanlin Wu, Ji Seop Oh, Sheng Li, Jianwei Huang, Jonathan D. Denlinger, Makoto Hashimoto, Donghui Lu, Sung-Kwan Mo, Kevin F. Kelly, Gregory T. McCandless, Julia Y. Chan, Robert J. Birgeneau, Bing Lv, Gang Li, Ming Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The dynamical structure factor of the SU(4) algebraic spin liquid on the honeycomb lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16242v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the momentum resolved dynamical spin structure factor $S(k,\omega)$ of the SU(4) Heisenberg model on the honeycomb lattice assuming the $\pi$-flux Dirac spin liquid ground state by two methods: (i) variationally using Gutzwiller projected particle-hole excitations of the $\pi$-flux Fermi sea and (ii) in the non-interacting parton mean-field picture. The two approaches produce qualitatively similar results. Based on this analogy, we argue that the energy spectrum of the projected excitations is a gapless continuum of fractional excitations. Quantitatively, the Gutzwiller projection shifts the weight from higher to lower energies, thus emphasizing the lower edge of the continuum. In the mean-field approach, we obtained the $1/\text{distance}^4$ decay of the spin correlation function, and the local correlations show $S^{33}_{\text{MF}}(\omega)\propto \omega^3$ behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16242v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D\'aniel V\"or\"os, Karlo Penc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deconfined quantum criticality lost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.02547v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Over the past two decades, the enigma of the deconfined quantum critical point (DQCP) has attracted broad attention across the condensed matter, quantum field theory, and high-energy physics communities, as it is expected to offer a new paradigm in theory, experiment, and numerical simulations that goes beyond the Landau-Ginzburg-Wilson framework of symmetry breaking and phase transitions. However, the nature of DQCP has been controversial. For instance, in the square-lattice spin-1/2 $J$-$Q$ model, believed to realize the DQCP between N\'eel and valence bond solid states, conflicting results, such as first-order versus continuous transition, and critical exponents incompatible with conformal bootstrap bounds, have been reported. The enigma of DQCP is exemplified in its anomalous logarithmic subleading contribution in its entanglement entropy (EE), which was discussed in recent studies. In the current work, we demonstrate that similar anomalous logarithmic behavior persists in a class of models analogous to the DQCP. We systematically study the quantum EE of square-lattice SU($N$) DQCP spin models. Based on large-scale quantum Monte Carlo computation of the EE, we show that for a series of $N$ smaller than a critical value, the anomalous logarithmic behavior always exists in the EE, which implies that the previously determined DQCPs in these models do not belong to conformal fixed points. In contrast, when $N\ge N_c$ with a finite $N_c$ that we evaluate to lie between $7$ and $8$, the DQCPs are consistent with conformal fixed points that can be understood within the Abelian Higgs field theory with $N$ complex components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.02547v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Menghan Song, Jiarui Zhao, Meng Cheng, Cenke Xu, Michael M. Scherer, Lukas Janssen, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nature of the mixed-parity pairing of attractive fermions with spin-orbit coupling in optical lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16657v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The admixture of spin-singlet and spin-triplet pairing states in superconductors can be typically induced by breaking spatial inversion symmetry. Employing the {\it numerically exact} auxiliary-field Quantum Monte Carlo method, we study such mixed-parity pairing phenomena of attractive fermions with Rashba spin-orbit coupling (SOC) in two-dimensional optical lattice at finite temperature. We systematically demystify the evolution of the essential pairing structure in both singlet and triplet channels versus the temperature, fermion filling, SOC and interaction strengths, via computing the condensate fraction and pair wave function. Our numerical results reveal that the singlet channel dominates in the fermion pairing and the triplet pairing has relatively small contribution to the superfluidity for physically relevant parameters. In contrast to the singlet channel mainly consisted of the on-site Cooper pairs, the triplet pairing has plentiful patterns in real space with the largest contributions from several nearest neighbors. As the SOC strengh increases, the pairing correlation is firstly enhanced and then suppressed for triplet pairing while it's simply weakened in singlet channel. We have also obtained the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition temperatures through the finite-size analysis of condensate fraction. Our results can serve as quantitative guide for future optical lattice experiments as well as accurate benchmarks for theories and other numerical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16657v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.094504</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 094504 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Feng Song, Youjin Deng, Yuan-Yao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairing dome from an emergent Feshbach resonance in a strongly repulsive bilayer model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.13040v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A key to understanding unconventional superconductivity lies in unraveling the pairing mechanism of mobile charge carriers in doped antiferromagnets, yielding an effective attraction between charges even in the presence of strong repulsive Coulomb interactions. Here, we study pairing in a mixed-dimensional (mixD) $t-J$ model, featuring robust binding energies -- despite dominant repulsive interactions -- that are strongly enhanced in the finite doping regime. The single and coupled mixD ladders we study, corresponding to bilayers of width $w\leq 2$, feature a crossover from tightly bound pairs of holes (closed channel) at small repulsion, to more spatially extended, correlated pairs of individual holes (open channel) at large repulsion. We derive an effective model for the latter, in which the attraction is mediated by the closed channel, in analogy to atomic Feshbach resonances. Using density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) simulations we reveal a dome of large binding energies at around $30\%$ doping, accompanied by a change of the Fermi surface volume and a crossover from extended to tightly bound hole pairs. Our work provides a microscopic theory of pairing in the doped mixD system with dominant repulsion, closely related to bilayer, Ni-based superconductors, and our predictions can be tested in state-of-the-art quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.13040v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Lange, Lukas Homeier, Eugene Demler, Ulrich Schollw\"ock, Annabelle Bohrdt, Fabian Grusdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterated Perturbation Theory for Mott Insulators in a Static Electric Field with Optical Phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00617v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This manuscript aims to compare the so-called iterated perturbation theory (IPT) and auxiliary master equation approach (AMEA) impurity solvers for a Mott insulating system driven out of equilibrium by a static electric field. Electronic heat bath and optical phonons are employed as dissipation mechanism of the current-induced Joule heat that the excited electrons of the lattice experience as the result of the field's driving. Despite its simplicity, the IPT approach yields results which qualitatively are in good agreement with those obtained within the AMEA impurity solver, although fails to reproduce some correlation effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00617v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/pssb.202300486</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Status Solidi B 2300486 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Maria Mazzocchi, Enrico Arrigoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-living prethermalization in nearly integrable spin ladders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11975v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Relaxation rates in nearly integrable systems usually increase quadratically with the strength of the perturbation that breaks integrability. We show that the relaxation rates can be significantly smaller in systems that are integrable along two intersecting lines in the parameter space. In the vicinity of the intersection point, the relaxation rates of certain observables increase with the fourth power of the distance from this point, whereas for other observables one observes standard quadratic dependence on the perturbation. As a result, one obtains exceedingly long-living prethermalization but with a reduced number of the nearly conserved operators. We show also that such a scenario can be realized in spin ladders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11975v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Pawlowski, M. Panfil, J. Herbrych, M. Mierzejewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second Wilson number from third-order perturbation theory for the symmetric single-impurity Kondo model at low temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05979v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We determine the impurity-induced free energy and the impurity-induced zero-field susceptibility of the symmetric single-impurity Kondo model from weak-coupling perturbation theory up to third order in the Kondo coupling at low temperatures and small magnetic fields. We reproduce the analytical structure of the zero-field magnetic susceptibility as obtained from Wilson's renormalization group method. This permits us to obtain analytically the first two Wilson numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05979v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Bauerbach, Florian Gebhard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A model of non-Fermi liquid with power law resistivity: strange metal with a not-so-strange origin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10878v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a model which exhibits resistivity going as a power law in temperature $T$, as $T^\alpha$ down to the lowest temperature. There is no residual resistivity because we assume the absence of disorder and momentum relaxation is due to umklapp scattering. Our model consists of a quantum spin liquid state with spinon Fermi surface and a hole Fermi surface made out of doped holes. The key ingredient is a set of singular $2k_F$ modes living on a ring in momentum space. Depending on parameters, $\alpha$ may be unity (strange metal) or even smaller. The model may be applicable to a doped organic compound, which has been found to exhibit linear T resistivity. We conclude that it is possible to obtain strange metal behavior starting with a model which is not so strange.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10878v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick A. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field induced resistive switching in M$^{3+}_x$V$_{1-x}$O$_2$ (M$^{3+}$= Ga$^{3+}$, Al$^{3+}$) single crystals at temperatures below the T $\to$ M2 phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01808v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The phase diagram of VO$_2$ strained or doped with several trivalent ions consists of four phases; in order of increasing temperatures, three (M1, T and M2) are insulating while the fourth (R), above ~340 K, is metallic. These phases and the three phase transitions have been thoroughly investigated for about half a century by a wide variety of techniques, including electronic transport. While an upwards jump of the resistance of up to a factor of 2 was observed at the T-M2 transition and a drop of several orders of magnitude was observed at the M2$\to$R one, resistive switching at the M1$\to$T transition remained elusive over all these years. Here we report on the investigation of Ga- and Al-doped VO$_2$ single crystals, following the rather surprising appearance of a small and steep drop of a factor of ~ 0.12 in the resistance of Ga-doped VO$_2$ single crystals detected by pulsed and DC I-V measurements carried out at room temperature, below the T$\to$M2 phase transition. Similar results were obtained also from measurements on Al-doped VO2 single crystals. Raman spectra of Ga-, and Al-doped crystals resolved their structures as function of temperature. The accumulated results of the measurements on Ga-, and Al-doped single crystals provide evidence for identifying the resistive switching at T$_{\rm RS}$&lt;T$_{\rm T\to M2}$ with the M1$\to$T transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01808v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Larisa Patlagan, George M. Reisner, Shani Neyshtadt-Ronel, Yoav Kalcheim, Bertina Fisher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantics Tensor Cross Interpolation for High-Resolution, Parsimonious Representations of Multivariate Functions in Physics and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11819v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multivariate functions of continuous variables arise in countless branches of science. Numerical computations with such functions typically involve a compromise between two contrary desiderata: accurate resolution of the functional dependence, versus parsimonious memory usage. Recently, two promising strategies have emerged for satisfying both requirements: (i) The quantics representation, which expresses functions as multi-index tensors, with each index representing one bit of a binary encoding of one of the variables; and (ii) tensor cross interpolation (TCI), which, if applicable, yields parsimonious interpolations for multi-index tensors. Here, we present a strategy, quantics TCI (QTCI), which combines the advantages of both schemes. We illustrate its potential with an application from condensed matter physics: the computation of Brillouin zone integrals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11819v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.056501</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 056501 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marc K. Ritter, Yuriel N\'u\~nez Fern\'andez, Markus Wallerberger, Jan von Delft, Hiroshi Shinaoka, Xavier Waintal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Criticality in Open Quantum Spin Chains with Nonreciprocity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03714v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of nonreciprocity on universality and critical phenomena in open quantum interacting many-body systems. Nonreciprocal open quantum systems often have an exotic spectral sensitivity to boundary conditions, known as the Liouvillian skin effect (LSE). By considering an open quantum XXZ spin chain that exhibits LSE, we demonstrate the existence of a universal scaling regime that is not affected by the presence of the LSE. We resolve the critical exponents, which differ from those of free fermions, via tensor network methods and demonstrate that observables exhibit a universal scaling collapse, irrespective of the reciprocity. We find that the LSE only becomes relevant when a healing length scale $\xi_{\rm heal}$ at the system's edge (which is different to the localization length of the eigenstate of the Liouvillian) exceeds the system size, allowing edge properties to dominate the physics. We expect this result to be a generic feature of nonreciprocal models in the vicinity of a critical point. The driven-dissipative quantum criticality we observe has no classical analogue and stems from the existence of multiple dark states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03714v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.120401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 132, 120401 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Samuel E. Begg, Ryo Hanai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairing from repulsion in a two-dimensional Fermi gas with soft-core interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.17362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.17362v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate a model many-body system of spinless Fermi gas in two dimensions, where the bare two-body interaction is repulsive and takes the form of a soft-core disk potential. We obtain the zero temperature phase diagram of this model by numerical functional renormalization group (FRG), which retains the effective interaction vertices in all channels to provide a detailed picture of how Cooper pairing emerges under the renormalization flow. The repulsion drives the system to a series of superfluid states with higher angular momentum paring, for example in the $f$- and $h$-wave channels instead of the $p$-wave channel. This is in sharp contrast to the original Kohn-Luttinger mechanism where pairing of very large angular momenta and exponentially small transition temperature was predicted. We trace the stabilization and enhancement of $f$- and $h$-wave pairing back to the momentum dependence of the bare interaction. A perturbative calculation is carried out to show that while the second order Kohn-Luttinger diagrams provide a qualitative understanding of the onsets of the various superfluid phases, they are unable to accurately capture the phase boundaries predicted by FRG. Our findings suggest that tuning the shape of the interaction potential offers a promising route to achieve stronger ``pairing glue" and to realize nontrivial superfluid phases in repulsive Fermi gases beyond the scope of the original Kohn-Luttinger analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.17362v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.054519</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 054519 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ahmet Keles, Xiaopeng Li, Erhai Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
