<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 02:50:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Coupling Theory of Superconductivity and Ferroelectric Quantum Criticality in metallic SrTiO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05374v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconductivity in doped SrTiO$_3$ has remained an enduring mystery for over 50 years. The material's status as a ``quantum" ferroelectric metal, characterized by a soft polar mode, suggests that quantum criticality could play a pivotal role in the emergence of its superconducting state. We show that the system is amenable to a strong coupling (Eliashberg) pairing analysis, with the dominant coupling to the soft mode being a ``dynamical'' Rashba coupling. We compute the expected $T_c$ for the entire phase diagram, all the way to the quantum critical point and beyond. We demonstrate that the linear coupling is sufficient to obtain a rough approximation of the experimentally measured phase diagram, but that nonlinear coupling terms are crucial in reproducing the finer features in the ordered phase. The primary role of nonlinear terms at the peak of the superconducting dome is to enhance the effective linear coupling induced by the broken order, shifting the dome's maximum into the ordered phase. Our theory quantitatively reproduces the three-dimensional experimental phase diagram in the space of carrier density, distance from the quantum critical point and temperature, and allows us to estimate microscopic parameters from the experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05374v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudip Kumar Saha, Maria N. Gastiasoro, Jonathan Ruhman, Avraham Klein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Newly discovered magnetic phase: A brief review on Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05377v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, a new magnetic phase, termed altermagnetism, has caught the attention of the magnetism and spintronics community. This newly discovered magnetic phenomenon differs from traditional ferromagnetism and antiferromagnetic. It generally lacks net magnetization and is characterized by unusual non-relativistic spin-splitting and broken time-reversal symmetry. This leads to novel transport properties such as the anomalous Hall effect, the crystal Nernst effect, and spin-dependent phenomena that cannot be fully explained by traditional magnetic theories. Spin-dependent phenomena such as spin currents, spin-splitter torques, and high-frequency dynamics emerge as key characteristics in altermagnets. This paper reviews the main aspects pertaining to altermagnets by providing an overview of theoretical investigations and experimental realizations. We discuss the most recent developments in altermagnetism, its comparison to other magnetic orders, and future prospects for exploiting its unique properties in next-generation devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05377v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Tamang, Shivraj Gurung, D. P. Rai, Samy Brahimi, Samir Lounis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of dynamic Jahn-Teller effect on magnetic excitations, lattice vibration, and thermal conductivity in UxTh1-xO2 system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vibrational and magnetic properties of single-crystal uranium-thorium dioxide (UxTh1-xO2) with a full range of 0&lt;x&lt;1 is investigated. Thorium dioxide is a diamagnet whose thermal properties are governed by lattice vibration. The addition of paramagnetic uranium ion leads to the emergence of magnetic effects that alter the thermophysical properties noticeably even at room temperature. The interaction of phonons with magnetic moments of uranium 5f electrons mediated by magnetoelastic coupling results in an anomalous low-temperature thermal conductivity profile. Analysis of the magnetic susceptibility measurements indicates a uranium-concentration-dependent reduction in effective magnetic moment previously associated with the dynamic Jahn-Teller (DJT) effect. The T2g Raman peak position follows a nonlinear trend as a function of uranium concentration and hints that these Raman active optical modes play a role in either DJT or mediating quadrupole-quadrupole interactions. A first principle-based thermal transport model is implemented to explain the low-temperature transport measurements, where the anomalous reduction is attributed to phonon-spin resonant scattering. The interplay between spins and phonons is also captured using high-resolution inelastic X-ray scattering (IXS) measurements of phonon linewidths. Our results provide new insights into the phonon interactions with the magnetic excitations governing DJT effect and impacting the low-temperature thermal transport processes in this material system. These findings have implications for understanding low-temperature thermal transport and magnetic properties in advanced materials for information processing and energy applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05448v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saqeeb Adnan, Zilong Hua, Puspa Upreti, Hao Ma, Erika Nosal, Shuxiang Zhou, Sabin Regmi, Timothy A Prusnick, Karl Rickert, Krzysztof Gofryk, J Matthew Mann, David H Hurley, Michael E Manley, Marat Khafizov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new pathway to impact ionization in a photo-excited one-dimensional ionic Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the time-dependent Lanczos method, we study the non-equilibrium dynamics of the half-filled one-dimensional ionic Hubbard model, deep within the Mott insulating regime, under the influence of a transient laser pulse. In equilibrium, increasing the staggered potential in the Mott regime reduces the Mott gap and broadens the Hubbard bands, creating favorable conditions for impact ionization. After laser excitation, impact ionization is observed, with its occurrence depending on both the staggered potential and the laser pump frequency. By analyzing the time evolution of the kinetic, ionic, and Coulomb interaction energies, we identify a novel mechanism for impact ionization, in which excess ionic potential energy is converted into additional double occupancy-distinct from the conventional mechanism where excess kinetic energy drives this process. We further show that impact ionization arises from interference between excited states driven by photon excitation of the same order. These results present a new pathway for realizing impact ionization in strongly correlated electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05798v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyu Cheng, Li Yang, Xiang Hu, Hantao Lu, Zhongbing Huang, Liang Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetic and Noncentrosymmetric Metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A theoretical description of altermagnets in the normal and superconducting states is presented. It was made in comparison with metals that do not have spatial inversion symmetry. Having a formally similar mathematical description, these two classes of metals have qualitatively different physical properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05875v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. P. Mineev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying an effective model for the two-stage-Kondo regime: Numerical renormalization group results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A composite impurity in a metal can explore different configurations, where its net magnetic moment may be screened by the host electrons. An example is the two-stage Kondo (TSK) system, where screening occurs at successively smaller energy scales. Alternatively, impurities may prefer a local singlet disconnected from the metal. This competition is influenced by the system's couplings. A double quantum dot T-shape geometry, where a "hanging" dot is connected to current leads only via another dot, allows experimental exploration of these regimes. Differentiating the two regimes has been challenging. This study provides a method to identify the TSK regime in such a geometry. The TSK regime requires a balance between the inter-dot coupling ($t_{01}$) and the coupling of the quantum dot connected to the Fermi sea ($\Gamma_0$). Above a certain ratio, the system transitions to a molecular regime, forming a local singlet with no Kondo screening. The study identifies a region in the $t_{01}$--$\Gamma_0$ parameter space where a pure TSK regime occurs. Here, the second Kondo stage properties can be described by a single impurity Anderson model with effective parameters. By examining the magnetic susceptibility of the hanging quantum dot, a single parameter, $\Gamma_{\rm eff}$, can simulate this susceptibility accurately. This effective model also provides the hanging quantum dot's spectral function accurately within a limited parameter range, defining the true TSK regime. Additionally, spin correlations between the quantum dots show universal behavior in this parameter range. These findings can guide experimental groups in selecting parameter values to place the system in either the TSK regime or the crossover to the molecular regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05930v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. A. Almeida, E. Vernek, E. V. Anda, S. E. Ulloa, G. B. Martins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-induced phases in the half-filled Bernevig-Hughes-Zhang model in one dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the ground-state properties of a one-dimensional model with two orbitals per site, where, in addition to atomic energies $\pm M$, intra- and inter-orbital hoppings, the intra-orbital Hubbard ($U$) and nearest-neighbor density-density ($V$) repulsions are included. Our results are primarily based upon a Jastrow-Slater wave function and variational Monte Carlo methods, but also corroborated by density-matrix renormalization group calculations. In the non-interacting limit, when varying $M&gt;0$, a gapless point separates a trivial phase from a topological one. The inclusion of a finite Hubbard-$U$ repulsion does not give rise to any phase transition within the topological region, inducing a smooth crossover into a Haldane (spin gapped) insulator; notably, the string-order parameter, which characterizes the latter phase, is already finite in the non-interacting limit. Most importantly, at finite values of $U$, the transition between the trivial and topological states is not direct, since an emergent insulator, which shows evidence of sustaining gapless spin excitations, intrudes between them. A small $V$ interaction further stabilizes the intermediate insulator, while a sufficiently large value of this nearest-neighbor repulsion gives rise to two different charge-density wave insulators, one fully gapped and another still supporting gapless spin excitations. Our results demonstrate the richness of multi-orbital Hubbard models, in presence of a topologically non-trivial band structure, and serve as a basis for future investigations on similar two-dimensional models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05975v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberta Favata, Davide Piccioni, Alberto Parola, Federico Becca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental observation of repulsively bound magnons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06350v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stable composite objects, such as hadrons, nuclei, atoms, molecules and superconducting pairs, formed by attractive forces are ubiquitous in nature. By contrast, composite objects stabilized by means of repulsive forces were long thought to be theoretical constructions owing to their fragility in naturally occurring systems. Surprisingly, the formation of bound atom pairs by strong repulsive interactions has been demonstrated experimentally in optical lattices. Despite this success, repulsively bound particle pairs were believed to have no analogue in condensed matter owing to strong decay channels. Here we present spectroscopic signatures of repulsively bound three-magnon states and bound magnon pairs in the Ising-like chain antiferromagnet BaCo$_2$V$_2$O$_8$. In large transverse fields, below the quantum critical point, we identify repulsively bound magnon states by comparing terahertz spectroscopy measurements to theoretical results for the Heisenberg-Ising chain antiferromagnet, a paradigmatic quantum many-body model. Our experimental results show that these high-energy repulsively bound magnon states are well separated from continua, exhibit significant dynamical responses and, despite dissipation, are sufficiently long-lived to be identified. As the transport properties in spin chains can be altered by magnon bound states, we envision such states could serve as resources for magnonics based quantum information processing technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06350v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-024-07599-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 631, 760 - 764 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Wang, Catalin-Mihai Halati, Jean-S\'ebastien Bernier, Alexey Ponomaryov, Denis I. Gorbunov, Sandra Niesen, Oliver Breunig, J. Michael Klopf, Sergei Zvyagin, Thomas Lorenz, Alois Loidl, Corinna Kollath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ising dual-reflection interface: $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry, Majorana strong zero modes and SPT phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06377v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate an interface in the transverse field quantum Ising chain connecting an ordered ferromagnetic phase and a disordered paramagnetic phase that are Kramers-Wannier duals of each other. Unlike prior studies focused on non-invertible defects, this interface exhibits a symmetry that combines Kramers-Wannier transformation with spatial reflection. We demonstrate that, under open boundary conditions, this setup gives rise to a discrete $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry, encompassing the conventional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ Ising parity as a subgroup, while in a closed geometry a non-invertible symmetry emerges. Using the Jordan-Wigner transformation, we map the spin chain onto a solvable quadratic Majorana fermion system. In this formulation, the $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry is realized manifestly as a parity-dependent reflection operation with respect to a Majorana site, in contrast to the conventional reflection which mirrors with respect to the central link of the Majorana chain. Additionally, we construct Majorana strong zero modes that retain the $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry, ensure degeneracies of all energy eigenstates, and are robust under generic local symmetry-preserving perturbations of the fermion model, including interactions. In an open geometry of the studied model, we identify two regimes that exhibit different degeneracy patterns. We discuss whether this is a manifestation of distinct fermion symmetry-protected topological orders protected by the $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06377v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juliane Graf, Federica Maria Surace, Marcus Berg, Sergej Moroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commensurate to Incommensurate Transition of Three Dimensional Charge Density Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Charge density wave (CDW) is a widely concerned emergent phenomenon in condensed matter physics. To establish a systematic understanding of CDW, we develop a diagrammatic self-consistent-field approach for cubic Holstein model employing fluctuation exchange approximation, and explore the emergence and transition of three-dimensional CDWs. Commensurate CDW (c-CDW) locked at $(\pi,\pi,\pi)$ is favored near half-filling, and the transition temperature is predicted around half of the nearest-neighbor hopping. Large hole doping leads to a suppression of CDW transition temperature and the emergence of incommensurate CDW (i-CDW), which is evidenced by a drifting of the ordering vector away from $(\pi,\pi,\pi)$ towards $(\pi,\pi,0)$. Phonon frequency significantly impacts the transition temperature and the phase boundary between c-CDW and i-CDW, and the optimal frequency for enlarging the CDW regime is also predicted near half of the nearest-neighbor hopping. These new theoretical results provide a systematic understanding of CDW and a fresh perspective on emergent phenomena dominated by electron-phonon interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06459v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Wang, Qiang Luo, Ji Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Critical Scaling of Specific Heat in a Quasicrystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In strongly correlated systems, interactions give rise to critical fluctuations surrounding the quantum critical point (QCP) of a quantum phase transition. Quasicrystals allow the study of quantum critical phenomena in aperiodic systems with frustrated magnetic interactions. Here, we study the magnetic field and temperature scaling of the low-temperature specific heat for the quantum critical Yb-Au-Al quasicrystal. We devise a scaling function that encapsulates the limiting behaviors as well as the area where the system goes from a temperature-limited to a field-limited quantum critical region, where magnetic field acts as a cutoff for critical fluctuations. The zero-field electronic specific heat is described by a power-law divergence, ${C_{el}/T \propto T^{-0.54}}$, aligning with previously observed ac-susceptibility and specific heat measurements. The field dependence of the electronic specific heat at high magnetic fields shows a similar power-law ${C_{el}/T \propto B^{-0.50}}$. In the zero-field and low-field region, we observe two small but distinct anomalies in the specific heat, located at 0.7 K and 2.1 K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06558v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Khansili, Y. -C. Huang, U. H\"aussermann, C. Pay Gomez, A. Rydh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The boundary entropy function for interface conformal field theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05381v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 1+1 dimensional conformal field theory with a boundary the boundary contribution to the entanglement entropy is determined by a single number $g$ effectively counting the boundary degrees of freedom. In contrast, in 1+1 dimensional interface CFTs the corresponding quantity is a non-trivial {\it function} depending on the position of the interval relative to the interface, giving access to much more detailed information about the defect. In this work we determined this $g$-function in several examples using holography, derive some of its basic properties as well as its behavior under RG flows from holography and strong subadditivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05381v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Afxonidis, Andreas Karch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal approach to light driven "superconductivity" via preformed pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While there are many different mechanisms which have been proposed to understand the physics behind light induced "superconductivity", what seems to be common to the class of materials in which this is observed are strong pairing correlations, which are present in the normal state. Here we argue, that the original ideas of Eliashberg are applicable to such a pseudogap phase and that with exposure to radiation the fermions are redistributed to higher energies where they are less deleterious to pairing. What results then is a photo-induced state with dramatically enhanced number of nearly condensed fermion pairs. In this phase, because the a.c. conductivity, $\sigma(\omega) = \sigma_1(\omega) + i \sigma_2(\omega)$, is dominated by the bosonic contribution, it can be computed using conventional (Aslamazov Larkin) fluctuation theory. We, thereby, observe the expected fingerprint of this photoinduced "superconducting" state which is a $1/\omega$ dependence in $\sigma_2$ with fits to the data of the same quality as found for the so-called photo-enhanced (Drude) conductivity scenario. Here, however, we have a microscopic understanding of the characteristic low energy scale which appears in transport and which is necessarily temperature dependent. This approach also provides insight into recent observations of concomitant diamagnetic fluctuations. Our calculations suggest that the observed light-induced phase in these strongly paired superconductors has only short range phase coherence without long range superconducting order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05420v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke Wang, Zhiqiang Wang, Qijin Chen, K. Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological entanglement entropy meets holographic entropy inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05484v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological entanglement entropy (TEE) is an efficient way to detect topological order in the ground state of gapped Hamiltonians. The seminal work of Kitaev and Preskill~\cite{preskill-kitaev-tee} and simultaneously by Levin and Wen~\cite{levin-wen-tee} proposed information quantities that can probe the TEE. In the present work, we explain why the subtraction schemes in the proposed information quantities~\cite{levin-wen-tee,preskill-kitaev-tee} work for the computation of TEE and generalize them for arbitrary number of subregions by explicitly noting the necessary conditions for an information quantity to capture TEE. Our conditions differentiate the probes defined by Kitaev-Preskill and Levin-Wen into separate classes. While there are infinitely many possible probes of TEE, we focus particularly on the cyclic quantities $Q_{2n+1}$ and multi-information $I_n$. We also show that the holographic entropy inequalities are satisfied by the quantum entanglement entropy of the non-degenerate ground state of a topologically ordered two-dimensional medium with a mass gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05484v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joydeep Naskar, Sai Satyam Samal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective theory for strongly attractive one-dimensional fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05915v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a one-dimensional system of two-component fermions in the limit of strong attractive particle-particle interactions. First, we analyze scattering in the corresponding few-body problem, which is analytically solvable via Bethe ansatz. This allows us to engineer effective interactions between the system's effective degrees of freedom: fermions and bosonic dimers (tightly bound pairs of fermions). We argue that, although these interactions are strong, the resulting effective problem can be mapped onto a weakly interacting one, paving the way for the use of perturbation theory. This finding simplifies studies of many-fermion systems under confinement that are beyond reach of state-of-the-art numerical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05915v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy G. Backert, Fabian Brauneis, Matija \v{C}ufar, Joachim Brand, Hans-Werner Hammer, Artem G. Volosniev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ASb3Mn9O19 (A = K or Rb): New Mn-Based Two-Dimensional Magnetoplumbites with Geometric and Magnetic Frustration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05944v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetoplumbites are one of the most broadly studied families of hexagonal ferrites, typically with high magnetic ordering temperatures, making them excellent candidates for permanent magnets. However, magnetic frustration was rarely observed in magnetoplumbites. Herein, we report the discovery, synthesis and characterization of the first Mn-based magnetoplumbite, as well as the first magnetoplumbite involving pnictogens (Sb), ASb3Mn9O19 (A = K or Rb). The Mn3+ (S = 2) cations, further confirmed by DC magnetic susceptibility and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy, construct three geometrically frustrated sublattices, including Kagome, triangular and puckered honeycomb lattices. Magnetic properties measurements revealed strong antiferromagnetic spin-spin coupling as well as multiple low-temperature magnetic features. Heat capacity data did not show any prominent lambda-anomaly, suggesting minimal associated magnetic entropy. Moreover, neutron powder diffraction implied the absence of long-range magnetic ordering in KSb3Mn9O19 down to 3 K. However, several magnetic peaks were observed in RbSb3Mn9O19 at 3 K, corresponding to an incommensurate magnetic structure. Interestingly, strong diffuse scattering was seen in the neutron powder diffraction patterns of both compounds at low angles, and was analyzed by reverse Monte Carlo refinements, indicating short-range spin ordering related to frustrated magnetism as well as two-dimensional magnetic correlations in ASb3Mn9O19 (A = K or Rb).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05944v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianyi Chen, Stuart Calder, Joseph A. M. Paddison, Gina Angelo, Liana Klivansky, Jian Zhang, Huibo Cao, Xin Gui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of superconducting fitness in pairing from fluctuating order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06156v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In many unconventional superconductors the pairing interaction is believed to be mediated by a fluctuating order. Although this is typically taken to be magnetic in origin, the role of other fluctuating orders has recently been considered. In this work we examine the weak-coupling pairing interaction produced by a general fluctuating order, and seek to identify the leading pairing instability. For a given pairing channel, we show that the superconducting fitness with the associated static order appears prominently in the expression for the coupling constant. We consequently argue that fit gaps (for which the static order is not pair-breaking) should have an attractive interaction, whereas unfit gaps (for which the static order is pair-breaking) have a repulsive interaction. We propose a simple heuristic test for the tendency of a given pairing state to have an attractive interaction. We show the validity of this test in the case of pairing caused by fluctuating density-wave order, and use it to probe the superconducting state generated by a fluctuating noncolinear magnetic order on the pyrochlore lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06156v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yufei Zhu, P. M. R. Brydon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving stabilizer approximation with quantum strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06320v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a quantum strategy from nonlocal games to improve the stabilizer approximation we proposed previously. The resulting approach turns out to be a qubit-by-qubit gauging procedure for standard stabilizers, which could involve discrete or continuous gauge parameters. We take examples from many-body physics and quantum chemistry to show such a procedure leads to an improvement of the performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06320v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fen Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional Magnetic Oscillations in Kagome Mott Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07989v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In metals, electrons in a magnetic field undergo cyclotron motion, leading to oscillations in physical properties called quantum oscillations. This phenomenon has never been seen in a robust insulator because there are no mobile electrons. We report the first exception to this rule. We study a Mott insulator on a kagome lattice which does not order magnetically down to milli-Kelvin temperatures despite antiferromagnetic interactions. We observe a plateau at magnetization equal to 1/9 Bohr magneton per magnetic ion, accompanied by oscillations in the magnetic torque, reminiscent of quantum oscillations in metals. The temperature dependence obeys Fermi distribution. These phenomena are consistent with a quantum spin liquid state whose excitations are fermionic spinons with a Dirac-like spectrum coupled to an emergent gauge field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07989v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoxin Zheng, Yuan Zhu, Kuan-Wen Chen, Byungmin Kang, Dechen Zhang, Kaila Jenkins, Aaron Chan, Zhenyuan Zeng, Aini Xu, Oscar A. Valenzuela, Joanna Blawat, John Singleton, Patrick A. Lee, Shiliang Li, Lu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott Transition and Volume Law Entanglement with Neural Quantum States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.05749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.05749v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay between delocalisation and repulsive interactions can cause electronic systems to undergo a Mott transition between a metal and an insulator. Here we use neural network hidden fermion determinantal states (HFDS) to uncover this transition in the disordered, fully-connected Hubbard model. Whilst dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) provides exact solutions to physical observables of the model in the thermodynamic limit, our method allows us to directly access the wave function for finite system sizes well beyond the reach of exact diagonalisation. We demonstrate how HFDS are able to obtain more accurate results in the metallic regime and in the vicinity of the transition than calculations based on a Matrix Product State (MPS) ansatz, for which the volume law of entanglement exhibited by the system is prohibitive. We use the HFDS method to calculate the energy and double occupancy, the quasi-particle weight and the energy gap and, importantly, the amplitudes of the wave function which provide a novel insight into this model. Our work paves the way for the study of strongly correlated electron systems with neural quantum states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.05749v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chlo\'e Gauvin-Ndiaye, Joseph Tindall, Javier Robledo Moreno, Antoine Georges</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bosonic Quantum Breakdown Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04309v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a bosonic quantum breakdown Hubbard model, which generalizes the Bose-Hubbard model by adding an asymmetric breakdown interaction turning one boson into two between adjacent sites. When the normal hopping is zero, this model has a global exponential U(1) symmetry, and we show that the ground state undergoes a first-order phase transition from Mott insulator (MI) to a spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB) breakdown condensate as the breakdown interaction increases. Surprisingly, the SSB breakdown condensate does not have a gapless Goldstone mode, which invalidates the Mermin-Wagner theorem and leads to stable SSB in 1D. Moreover, we show that the quench dynamics of a boson added to MI exhibits a dynamical transition from dielectric to breakdown phases, which happens at a larger breakdown interaction than the ground state phase transition. Between these two transitions, the MI (dielectric) state is a false vacuum stable against dynamical breakdown. Our results reveal that quantum models with unconventional symmetries like the exponential symmetry can exhibit unexpected properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04309v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Min Hu, Biao Lian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersolid Phase in the Diluted Holstein Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02239v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Holstein model on a square lattice at half-filling has a well-established finite temperature phase transition to an insulating state with long range charge density wave (CDW) order. Because this CDW formation suppresses pairing, a superconducting (SC) phase emerges only with doping. In this work, we study the effects of dilution of the local phonon degrees of freedom in the Holstein model while keeping the system at half filling. We find not only that the CDW remains present up to a dilution fraction $f \sim 0.15$, but also that long range pairing is stabilized with increasing $f$, resulting in a {\it supersolid} regime centered at $f \approx 0.10$, where long range diagonal and off-diagonal correlations coexist. Further dilution results in a purely SC phase, and ultimately in a normal metal. Our results provide a new route to the supersolid phase via the introduction of impurities at fixed positions which both increase quantum fluctuations and also are immune to the competing tendency to phase separation often observed in the doped case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02239v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyao Meng, Yuxi Zhang, Rafael M. Fernandes, Tianxing Ma, R. T. Scalettar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of Meron Kekul\'e lattices in twisted N\'eel antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05616v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A Kekul\'e lattice is an exotic, distorted lattice structure exhibiting alternating bond lengths, distinguished from naturally formed atomic crystals. Despite its evident applicability, the formation of a Kekul\'e lattice from topological solitons in magnetic systems has remained elusive. Here, we propose twisted bilayer easy-plane N\'eel antiferromagnets as a promising platform for achieving a "Meron Kekul\'e lattice"--a distorted topological soliton lattice comprised of antiferromagnetic merons as its lattice elements. We demonstrate that the cores of these merons are stabilized into the Kekul\'e-O pattern with different intracell and intercell bond lengths across moir\'e supercells, thereby forming a Meron Kekul\'e lattice. Moreover, the two bond lengths of the Meron Kekul\'e lattice can be fine-tuned by adjusting the twist angle and specifics of the interlayer exchange coupling, suggesting extensive control over the meron lattice configuration in contrast to conventional magnetic systems. These discoveries pave the way for exploring topological solitons with distinctive Kekul\'e attributes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05616v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyoung-Min Kim, Se Kwon Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermionic Mean-Field Theory as a Tool for Studying Spin Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02125v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Jordan--Wigner transformation permits one to convert spin $1/2$ operators into spinless fermion ones, or vice versa. In some cases, it transforms an interacting spin Hamiltonian into a noninteracting fermionic one which is exactly solved at the mean-field level. Even when the resulting fermionic Hamiltonian is interacting, its mean-field solution can provide surprisingly accurate energies and correlation functions. Jordan--Wigner is, however, only one possible means of interconverting spin and fermionic degrees of freedom. Here, we apply several such techniques to the XXZ and $J_1\text{--}J_2$ Heisenberg models, as well as to the pairing or reduced BCS Hamiltonian, with the aim of discovering which of these mappings is most useful in applying fermionic mean-field theory to the study of spin Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02125v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas M. Henderson, Brent Harrison, Ilias Magoulas, Jason Necaise, Andrew M. Projansky, Francesco A. Evangelista, James D. Whitfield, Gustavo E. Scuseria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Easy-plane ferromagnetic ordering and crystal-field ground state in the Kondo lattice CeCuSi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12054v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the successful growth of CeCuSi single crystals using a metallic flux method and the physical properties using structural, magnetic, electrical transport, optical, and heat capacity measurements. CeCuSi crystallizes in a hexagonal-bar shape, and single crystal x-ray diffraction confirms the ZrBeSi-type structure (space group $P6_{3}/mmc$). CeCuSi orders ferromagnetically below $T_\textrm{C}=15.5$ K with easy magnetization direction within the basal plane. The Ce$^{3+}$ ions are situated within a triangular lattice with a point group of $D_{3d}$. We perform a detailed crystalline electric field (CEF) analysis of the anisotropic magnetic susceptibility, the Schottky anomaly in heat capacity, and the Raman-active excitations. The results indicate a ground state doublet with magnetic moment primarily in the basal plane, and a ferromagnetic interaction along both directions. The exponential behavior in resistivity and in heat capacity below $T_\textrm{C}$ can also be well explained by the ferromagnetic magnon model. We found that CeCuSi does not exhibit the CEF hard axis ordering observed in many ferromagnetic Kondo lattice (FM-KL) compounds. Our CEF analysis suggests that the exchange interactions along both axes are ferromagnetic, potentially explaining the absence of hard-axis ordering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12054v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.245114</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 110, 245114 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hanshang Jin, Owen Moulding, James C. Fettinger, Yingzheng Gao, Peter Klavins, Marie-Aude M\'easson, Valentin Taufour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Aspects of Dirac Fermions in a Kagom\'e Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Dirac fermion with linear dispersion in the kagom\'e lattice governs the low-energy physics of different valleys at two inequivalent corners of hexagonal Brillouin zone. The effective Hamiltonian based on the cyclic permutation symmetry of sublattices is constructed to show that the topology of Dirac fermions at these two valleys is characterized by opposite winding numbers. For spinless fermions, the many-particle interactions produce intervalley scattering and drive an intervalley coherent state with spontaneous translation symmetry breaking. The Dirac fermions acquire a mass term from the simultaneous charge and bond orderings. In this phase, the developed bond texture underlies a hollow-star-of-David pattern in a tripled Wigner-Seitz cell of kagom\'e lattice. It is further demonstrated that the twisting of Dirac mass with vorticity leads to zero Dirac modes at the vortex core, which are intimately related to fractionalization. The hollow-star-of-David phase is shown to have a distinct $\mathbb{Z}_6$ Berry phase with its sign-change counterpart of Dirac mass, i.e. the hexagonal phase, shedding light on the topological origin of zero Dirac modes around the vortex core.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04010v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyuan Zhou, Ziqiang Wang, Hua Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudogap in electron-doped cuprates: Strong correlation leading to band splitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1801.04247</link>
      <description>arXiv:1801.04247v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The pseudogap phenomena have been a long-standing mystery of the cuprate high-temperature superconductors. The pseudogap in the electron-doped cuprates has been attributed to band folding due to antiferromagnetic (AFM) long-range order or short-range correlation. We performed an angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) study of the electron-doped cuprates Pr$_{1.3-x}$La$_{0.7}$Ce$_x$CuO$_4$ showing spin-glass, disordered AFM behaviors, and superconductivity at low temperatures and, by measurements with fine momentum cuts, found that the gap opens on the unfolded Fermi surface rather than the AFM Brillouin zone boundary. The gap did not show a node, following the full symmetry of the Brillouin zone, and its magnitude decreased from the zone-diagonal to ($\pi$,0) directions, opposite to the hole-doped case. These observations were reproduced by cluster dynamical-mean-field-theory (CDMFT) calculation, which took into account electron correlation precisely within a (CuO$_2$)$_4$ cluster. The present experimental and theoretical results are consistent with the mechanism that electron or hole doping into a Mott insulator creates an in-gap band that are separated from the upper or lower Hubbard band by the pseudogap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1801.04247v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Horio, S. Sakai, H. Suzuki, Y. Nonaka, M. Hashimoto, D. Lu, Z. -X. Shen, T. Ohgi, T. Konno, T. Adachi, Y. Koike, M. Imada, A. Fujimori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protecting information in a parametrically driven hybrid quantum system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.14354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.14354v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The transfer and storage of quantum information in a hybrid quantum system, consisting of an ensemble of atoms or spins interacting with a cavity, is adversely affected by the inhomogeneity of the spins, which negates the coherent exchange of excitations between the physical components. Using a full quantum treatment based on variational renormalization group, we show how quantum information encoded in the states of a parametrically driven hybrid system is strongly protected against any decoherence that may arise due to the inhomogeneity in the spin-ensemble.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.14354v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Tiwary, Harsh Sharma, Himadri Shekhar Dhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic phases of electron-doped infinite-layer Sr$_{1-x}$La$_x$CuO$_2$ from first-principles density functional calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.10659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.10659v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The magnetic phases of electron-doped infinite-layer Sr$_{1-x}$La$_x$CuO$_2$ are elucidated by first-principles density functional calculations. The antiferromagnetic parent state, metallic transition, as well as lattice evolution with doping and pressure are found to be consistent with experiments. The specific heat coefficient $\gamma$, magnetic exchange coupling $J$, as well as the density of states at Fermi level $N(0)$ of low-energy states with multiple magnetic configurations are investigated. We highlight a subset of such states in which we note an increase in $N(0)$ to suggest the interesting effects of magnetic fluctuations and La substitution on the electronic structure of this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.10659v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.165134</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 165134 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alpin N. Tatan, Jun Haruyama, Osamu Sugino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient preparation of the AKLT State with Measurement-based Imaginary Time Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06031v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum state preparation plays a crucial role in several areas of quantum information science, in applications such as quantum simulation, quantum metrology and quantum computing. However, typically state preparation requires resources that scale exponentially with the problem size, due to their probabilistic nature or otherwise, making studying such models challenging. In this article, we propose a method to prepare the ground state of the Affleck-Lieb-Kennedy-Tasaki (AKLT) model deterministically using a measurement-based imaginary time evolution (MITE) approach. By taking advantage of the special properties of the AKLT state, we show that it can be prepared efficiently using the MITE approach. Estimates based on the convergence of a sequence of local projections, as well as direct evolution of the MITE algorithm suggest a constant scaling with respect to the number of AKLT sites, which is an exponential improvement over the naive estimate for convergence. We show that the procedure is compatible with qubit-based simulators, and show that using a variational quantum algorithm for circuit recompilation, the measurement operator required for MITE can be well approximated by a circuit with a much shallower circuit depth compared with the one obtained using the default Qiskit method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06031v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianqi Chen, Tim Byrnes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing magnetic states on the surface of multilayer ABC-stacked graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16345v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study interaction-mediated magnetism on the surface of ABC-multilayer graphene driven by its zero-energy topological flat bands. Using the random-phase approximation we treat onsite Hubbard repulsion and find multiple competing magnetic states, due to both intra- and inter-valley scattering, with the latter causing an enlarged magnetic unit cell. At half-filling and when the Hubbard repulsion is weak, we observe two different ferromagnetic orders. Once the Hubbard repulsion becomes more realistic, new ferrimagnetic orders arise with distinct incommensurate intra- or inter-valley scattering vectors depending on interaction strength and doping, leading to a multitude of competing magnetic states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16345v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.L241401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, L241401 (2024) - Editor's Suggestion</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lauro B. Braz, Tanay Nag, Annica M. Black-Schaffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Abelian fractionalization in topological minibands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00059v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the recent discovery of fractional quantum anomalous Hall states in moir\'e systems, we consider the possibility of realizing non-Abelian phases in topological minibands. We study a family of moir\'e systems, skyrmion Chern band models, which can be realized in two-dimensional semiconductor-magnet heterostructures and also capture the essence of twisted transition metal dichalcogenide homobilayers. We show using many-body exact diagonalization that, in spite of strong Berry curvature variations in momentum space, the non-Abelian Moore-Read state can be realized at half filling of the second miniband. These results demonstrate the feasibility of non-Abelian fractionalization in moir\'e systems without Landau levels and shed light on the desirable conditions for their realization. In particular, we highlight the prospect of realizing the Moore-Read state in twisted semiconductor bilayers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00059v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.166503</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aidan P. Reddy, Nisarga Paul, Ahmed Abouelkomsan, Liang Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Walking behavior induced by $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry breaking in a non-Hermitian $\rm XY$ model with clock anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17373v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A quantum system governed by a non-Hermitian Hamiltonian may exhibit zero temperature phase transitions that are driven by interactions, just as its Hermitian counterpart, raising the fundamental question how non-Hermiticity affects quantum criticality. In this context we consider a non-Hermitian system consisting of an $\rm XY$ model with a complex-valued four-state clock interaction that may or may not have parity-time-reversal ($\mathcal{PT}$) symmetry. When the $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry is broken, and time-evolution becomes non-unitary, a scaling behavior similar to the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless phase transition ensues, but in a highly unconventional way, as the line of fixed points is absent. From the analysis of the $d$-dimensional RG equations, we obtain that the unconventional behavior in the $\mathcal{PT}$ broken regime follows from the collision of two fixed points in the $d\to 2$ limit, leading to walking behavior or pseudocriticality. For $d=2+1$ the near critical behavior is characterized by a correlation length exponent $\nu=3/8$, a value smaller than the mean-field one. These results are in sharp contrast with the $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric case where only one fixed point arises for $2&lt;d&lt;4$ and in $d=1+1$ three lines of fixed points occur with a continuously varying critical exponent $\nu$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17373v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.224505</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 224505 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eduard Naichuk, Jeroen van den Brink, Flavio S. Nogueira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-broken metallic orders in spin-orbit-coupled Bernal bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09612v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore Bernal bilayer graphene in the presence of long-range Coulomb interactions, short-range Hund's coupling, and proximity-induced Ising spin-orbit coupling using self-consistent Hartree-Fock simulations. We show that the interplay between these three ingredients produces an intricate phase diagram comprising a multitude of symmetry-broken metallic states tunable via doping and applied displacement field. In particular, we find intervalley coherent and spin-canted ground states that may hold the key to understanding spin-orbit-enabled superconductivity observed in this platform. We also investigate various phase transitions where a continuous $\mathrm{U}(1)$ symmetry is broken to ascertain the possible role of critical fluctuations on pairing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09612v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.245118</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 245118 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jin Ming Koh, Alex Thomson, Jason Alicea, \'Etienne Lantagne-Hurtubise</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent symmetries in prethermal phases of periodically driven quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20764v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Periodically driven closed quantum systems are expected to eventually heat up to infinite temperature reaching a steady state described by a circular orthogonal ensemble (COE). However, such finite driven systems may exhibit sufficiently long prethermal regimes; their properties in these regimes are qualitatively different from that in their infinite temperature steady states. These, often experimentally relevant, prethermal regimes host a wide range of phenomena; they may exhibit dynamical localization and freezing, host Floquet scars, display signatures of Hilbert space fragmentation, and exhibit time crystalline phases. Such phenomena are often accompanied by emergent approximate dynamical symmetries which have no analogue in equilibrium systems. In this review, we provide a pedagogical introduction to the origin and nature of these symmetries and discuss their role in shaping the prethermal phases of a class of periodically driven closed quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20764v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tista Banerjee, K. Sengupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Negativity and Replica Symmetry Breaking in General Holographic States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13009v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The entanglement negativity $\mathcal{E}(A:B)$ is a useful measure of quantum entanglement in bipartite mixed states. In random tensor networks (RTNs), which are related to fixed-area states, it was found in [arXiv:2101.11029] that the dominant saddles computing the even R\'enyi negativity $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ generically break the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry. This calls into question previous calculations of holographic negativity using 2D CFT techniques that assumed $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry and proposed that the negativity was related to the entanglement wedge cross section. In this paper, we resolve this issue by showing that in general holographic states, the saddles computing $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ indeed break the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry. Our argument involves an identity relating $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ to the $k$-th R\'enyi entropy on subregion $AB^*$ in the doubled state $|{\rho_{AB}}\rangle_{AA^*BB^*}$, from which we see that the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry is broken down to $\mathbb{Z}_{k}$. For $k&lt;1$, which includes the case of $\mathcal{E}(A:B)$ at $k=1/2$, we use a modified cosmic brane proposal to derive a new holographic prescription for $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ and show that it is given by a new saddle with multiple cosmic branes anchored to subregions $A$ and $B$ in the original state. Using our prescription, we reproduce known results for the PSSY model and show that our saddle dominates over previously proposed CFT calculations near $k=1$. Moreover, we argue that the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ symmetric configurations previously proposed are not gravitational saddles, unlike our proposal. Finally, we contrast holographic calculations with those arising from RTNs with non-maximally entangled links, demonstrating that the qualitative form of backreaction in such RTNs is different from that in gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13009v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Dong, Jonah Kudler-Flam, Pratik Rath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truncation-Free Quantum Simulation of Pure-Gauge Compact QED Using Josephson Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11413v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum simulation is one of the methods that have been proposed and used in practice to bypass computational challenges in the investigation of lattice gauge theories. While most of the proposals rely on truncating the infinite dimensional Hilbert spaces that these models feature, we propose a truncation-free method based on the exact analogy between the local Hilbert space of lattice QED and that of a Josephson junction. We provide several proposals, mostly semi-analog, arranged according to experimental difficulty. Our method can simulate a quasi-2D system of up to $2\times N$ plaquettes, and we present an approximate method that can simulate the fully-2D theory, but is more demanding experimentally and not immediately feasible. This sets the ground for analog quantum simulation of lattice gauge theories with superconducting circuits, in a completely Hilbert space truncation-free procedure, for continuous gauge groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11413v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guy Pardo, Julian Bender, Nadav Katz, Erez Zohar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic theory of spin friction and dissipative spin dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16003v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The real-time dynamics of local magnetic moments exchange coupled to a metallic system of conduction electrons is subject to dissipative friction even in the absence of spin-orbit coupling. Phenomenologically, this is usually described by a local Gilbert damping constant. Here, we use both linear response theory and adiabatic response theory to derive the spin friction microscopically for a generic single-band tight-binding model of the electronic structure. The resulting Gilbert damping is time-dependent and nonlocal. For a one-dimensional model, we compare the emergent relaxation dynamics as obtained from LRT and ART against each other and against the full solution of the microscopic equations of motion and demonstrate the importance of nonlocality, while the time dependence turns out to be irrelevant. In two dimensions and for a few magnetic moments in different geometries, it is found that the inclusion of nonlocal Gilbert damping can counterintuitively lead to longer relaxation times. Besides the distance dependence, the directional dependence of the nonlocal Gilbert damping turns out as very important. Our results are based on an expression relating the nonlocal Gilbert damping to the nonlocal tight-binding density of states close to the Fermi energy. This is exact in case of noninteracting electrons. Effects due to electronic correlations are studied within the random-phase approximation. For the Hubbard model at half filling and with increasing interaction strength, we find a strong enhancement of the nonlocality of spin friction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16003v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Lenzing, David Kr\"uger, Michael Potthoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder-Order Interface Propagating over the Ferromagnetic Ground State in the Transverse Field Ising Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04089v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider time evolution of order parameters and entanglement asymmetries in the ferromagnetic phase of the transverse-field Ising chain. One side of the system is prepared in a ferromagnetic ground state and the other side either in equilibrium at higher temperature or out of equilibrium. We focus on the disorder-order interface in which the order parameter attains a nonzero value, different from the ground state one. In that region, correlations follow a universal behaviour. We analytically compute the asymptotic scaling functions of the one- and two-point equal time correlations of the order parameter and provide numerical evidence that also the non-equal time correlations are universal. We analyze the R\'enyi entanglement asymmetries of subsystems and obtain a prediction that is expected to hold also in the von Neumann limit. Finally, we show that the Wigner-Yanase skew information of the order paramerter in subsystems within the interfacial region scales as their length squared. We propose a semiclassical approximation that is particularly effective close to the edge of the lightcone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04089v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vanja Mari\'c, Florent Ferro, Maurizio Fagotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-commuting SYK model: building quantum chaos from integrable blocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12806v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a new family of quantum chaotic models by combining multiple copies of integrable commuting SYK models. As each copy of the commuting SYK model does not commute with others, this construction breaks the integrability of each commuting SYK and the family of models demonstrates the emergence of quantum chaos. We study the spectrum of this model analytically in the double-scaled limit. As the number of copies tends to infinity, the spectrum becomes compact and equivalent to the regular SYK model. For finite $d$ copies, the spectrum is close to the regular SYK model in UV but has an exponential tail $e^{E/T_c}$ in the IR. We identify the reciprocal of the exponent in the tail as a critical temperature $T_c$, above which the model should be quantum chaotic. $T_c$ monotonically decreases as $d$ increases, which expands the chaotic regime over the non-chaotic regime. We propose the existence of a new phase around $T_c$, and the dynamics should be very different in two phases. We further carry out numeric analysis at finite $d$, which supports our proposal.
  Given any finite dimensional local Hamiltonian, by decomposing it into $d$ groups, in which all terms in one group commute with each other but terms from different groups may not, our analysis can give an estimate of the critical temperature for quantum chaos based on the decomposition. We also comment on the implication of the critical temperature to future quantum simulations of quantum chaos and quantum gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12806v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ping Gao, Han Lin, Cheng Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying Logical Gates in Quantum Codes via Cohomology Operations and Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15848v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically construct and classify fault-tolerant logical gates implemented by constant-depth circuits for quantum codes using cohomology operations and symmetry. These logical gates are obtained from unitary operators given by symmetry-protected topological responses, which correspond to generators of group cohomology and can be expressed explicitly on the lattice using cohomology operations including cup product, Steenrod squares and new combinations of higher cup products called higher Pontryagin powers. Our study covers most types of the cohomology operations in the literature. This hence gives rise to several new classes of diagonal and non-diagonal logical gates in increasing Clifford hierarchies beyond the usual color code paradigm corresponding to an $n$-fold cup product, including the logical $R_k$ and multi-controlled $C^m R_k$ gates for codes defined in projective spaces. Implementing these gates could make it more efficient to compile specific types of quantum algorithms such as Shor's algorithm. We further extend the construction to quantum codes with boundaries, which generalizes the folding approach in color codes. We also present a formalism for addressable and parallelizable logical gates in LDPC codes via higher-form symmetries and apply it to construct addressable logical Clifford gates in expander-based codes including the asymptotically good LDPC codes and hypergraph-product codes. As a byproduct, we find new topological responses of finite higher-form symmetries using higher Pontryagin powers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15848v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Po-Shen Hsin, Ryohei Kobayashi, Guanyu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal microscopic descriptions for statistics of particles and extended excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01886v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Statistics of excitations play an essential role in understanding phases of matter. In this paper, we introduce a universal method for studying the generalized statistics of Abelian particles and extended excitations in lattices of any dimension. We compute the statistics using the Berry phase of a sequence of unitary operators that transports the excitations while canceling local ambiguities at each step. The sequence is derived from locality, using the Smith normal form. We show that the statistics are quantized invariants. Our method unifies the statistics for the braiding and fusion of particles and loops, and leads to the discovery of novel statistics for membrane excitations. The statistics can be interpreted as the quantum anomaly of a generalized global symmetry, which manifests as an obstruction to gauging the symmetry on lattices. Furthermore, we show that non-trivial statistics forbid short-range entangled states, establishing the dynamical consequence of anomalies in microscopic lattice models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01886v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryohei Kobayashi, Yuyang Li, Hanyu Xue, Po-Shen Hsin, Yu-An Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inhomogeneous reduction-annealing effects on the electron-doped cuprate superconductor revealed by micro-focused angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04790v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The development of the protect-annealing method has extended the superconductivity of the electron-doped cuprate Pr$_{1.3-x}$La$_{0.7}$Ce$_{x}$CuO$_{4}$ (PLCCO) into lower Ce concentrations, while the superconducting volume fraction decreases with underdoping. Employing angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy with a micro-focused beam, we investigated the electronic structure of protect-annealed PLCCO ($x=0.08$) with small superconducting volume fraction. Significant spatial variation of Fermi surface area and shape was observed, suggesting inhomogeneity in electron concentrations and the pseudogap that competes with superconductivity. By performing measurements at dozens of different sample positions, negative and non-monotonic correlation was found between the electron concentration and pseudogap magnitude. The established correlation illustrates a systematic annealing dependence of the electronic structure where a pseudogap abruptly opens with insufficient oxygen reduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04790v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Miyamoto, M. Horio, K. Moriya, A. Takahashi, J. Osiecki, B. Thiagarajan, C. M. Polley, Y. Koike, T. Adachi, T. Mizokawa, I. Matsuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
