<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 01:44:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Duality-preserving deformation of 3+1d lattice $\mathbb Z_2$ gauge theory with exact gapped ground states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose and analyze a deformation of the 3+1d lattice $\mathbb Z_2$ gauge theory that preserves the non-invertible Wegner duality symmetry at the self-dual point. We identify a frustration-free point along this deformation where there are nine exactly degenerate ground states (on a periodic cubic lattice) even at finite volume. One of these ground states is a trivial product state and the rest are the topologically-ordered ground states of the 3+1d toric code. We also prove that the frustration-free point is gapped in the thermodynamic limit. Our model, therefore, realizes a gapped phase with spontaneously broken Wegner duality symmetry. Furthermore, by imposing the Gauss law constraints energetically, all the above features can be realized on a tensor product Hilbert space. Finally, we discuss a generalization of this deformation to the 3+1d lattice $\mathbb Z_N$ gauge theory and conjecture the possible phase diagram.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10612v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranay Gorantla, Tzu-Chen Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immortal quantum correlation in quasiperiodic quasi-1D system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The prevailing view on long-range correlations is that they typically attenuate uniformly with distance and temperature, as most interactions either exhibit short-range dominance or decay following a power law. In contrast to this belief, this study demonstrates that the intricate interplay between quasiperiodicity and the quasi-1D nature of subbands can result in strong long-range coupling without attenuation, a phenomenon referred to as an immortal interaction. Exemplifying a periodically stacked Fibonacci chain, we uncover an immortal interaction with greatly enhanced, persistent long-range coupling. Using negativity, it is shown that this interaction creates stable entanglement that endures over long distances and remains robust at finite temperatures. Additionally, unconventional logarithmic scaling entanglement is revealed, deviating from the traditional area law. These findings offer quasiperiodic quasi-1D systems as a novel platform for sustaining stable entanglement across exceptionally long distances, even in the presence of finite temperature effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10614v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junmo Jeon, SungBin Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface-mediated ultra-strong cavity coupling of two-dimensional itinerant electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Engineering phases of matter in cavities requires effective light-matter coupling strengths that are on the same order of magnitude as the bare system energetics, coined the ultra-strong coupling regime. For models of itinerant electron systems, which do not have discrete energy levels, a clear definition of this regime is outstanding to date. Here we argue that a change of the electronic mass exceeding $10\%$ of its bare value may serve as such a definition. We propose a quantitative computational scheme for obtaining the electronic mass in relation to its bare vacuum value and show that coupling to surface polariton modes can induce such mass changes. Our results have important implications for cavity design principles that enable the engineering of electronic properties with quantum light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10615v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian J. Eckhardt, Andrey Grankin, Dante M. Kennes, Michael Ruggenthaler, Angel Rubio, Michael A. Sentef, Mohammad Hafezi, Marios H. Michael</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping the Quantum Hall problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The bootstrap method aims to solve problems by imposing constraints on the space of physical observables, which often follow from physical assumptions such as positivity and symmetry. Here, we employ a bootstrap approach to study interacting electrons in the lowest Landau level by minimizing the energy as a function of the static structure factor subject to a set of constraints, bypassing the need to construct the full many-body wavefunction. This approach rigorously lower bounds the ground state energy, making it complementary to conventional variational upper bounds. We show that the lower bound we obtain is relatively tight, within at most 5\% from the ground state energy computed with exact diagonalization (ED) at small system sizes, and generally gets tighter as we include more constraints. In addition to energetics, our results reproduce the correct power law dependence of the pair correlation function at short distances and the existence of a large entanglement gap in the two-particle entanglement spectra for the Laughlin states at $\nu = 1/3$. We further identify signatures of the composite Fermi liquid state close to half-filling. This shows that the bootstrap approach is capable, in principle, of describing non-trivial gapped topologically ordered, as well as gapless, phases. At the end, we will discuss possible extensions and limitations of this approach. Our work establishes numerical bootstrap as a promising method to study many-body phases in topological bands, paving the way to its application in moir\'e platforms where the energetic competition between fractional quantum anomalous Hall, symmetry broken, and gapless states remains poorly understood.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10619v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Gao, Ryan A. Lanzetta, Patrick Ledwith, Jie Wang, Eslam Khalaf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic vs. phononic thermal transport in Cr-doped V2O3 thin films across the Mott transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10748v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the thermal conductivity of chromium doped V2O3 is crucial for optimizing the design of selectors for memory and neuromorphic devices. We utilized the time-domain thermoreflectance technique to measure the thermal conductivity of chromium doped V2O3 across varying concentrations, spanning the doping induced metal-insulator transition. In addition, different oxygen stoichiometries and film thicknesses were investigated in their crystalline and amorphous phases. Chromium doping concentration (0%-30%) and the degree of crystallinity emerged as the predominant factors influencing the thermal properties, while the effect of oxygen flow (600-1400 ppm) during deposition proved to be negligible. Our observations indicate that even in the metallic phase of V2O3, the lattice contribution is the dominant factor in thermal transport with no observable impact from the electrons on heat transport. Finally, the thermal conductivity of both amorphous and crystalline V2O3 was measured at cryogenic temperatures (80-450 K). Our thermal conductivity measurements as a function of temperature reveal that both phases exhibit behavior similar to amorphous materials, indicating pronounced phonon scattering effects in the crystalline phase of V2O3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10748v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Mohr, Kiumars Aryana, Md. Rafiqul Islam, Dirk J. Wouters, Rainer Waser, Patrick E. Hopkins, Joyeeta Nag, Daniel Bedau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shot Noise near Quantum-Criticality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shot-noise measures the correlations of fluctuations of current for a voltage applied much larger than the temperature and reveals aspects of correlations in fermions beyond those revealed in the conductivity. Recent measurements of shot-noise in the quantum-critical region of the heavy-fermion compound YbRh$_2$Si$_2$ (YRS) have presented a conceptual challenge to old theory and those devised following the experiments. Since the measured resistivity and the specific heat in YRS follow the predictions of marginal Fermi liquid (MFL) theory, we use it to calculate noise using the method developed by Nagaev. We get fair agreement with the magnitude and temperature dependence in the experiments using parameters from resistivity measurements. To achieve this, we find it necessary that the collisions between fermions by exchanging the MFL fluctuations conserve energy but lose momentum through Umklapp scattering and that the fermions and their fluctuations are locally in mutual equilibrium. %and that the self-energy rides the local chemical potential. At low temperatures, impurity scattering determines the noise and at high temperatures the MFL scattering. We show that the noise for MFL scattering for high T alone is the same as the Johnson-Nyquist noise, which in this case is temperature independent. Therefore the Fano factor crosses over to $0$ at high temperatures independent of the voltage applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10798v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srinivas Raghu, Chandra M. Varma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soliton penetration from edges in a monoaxial chiral magnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The magnetic solitons such as chiral solitons, magnetic skyrmions, and magnetic hopfions, exhibiting particlelike nature widely emerge in magnets depending on spatial dimension. As their number directly gives rise to an impact on magnetic properties and electronic properties, it is of great importance to control the number of solitons. However, a systematic study on dynamical processes to control the number of solitons, particularly by adding the desired number of solitons to the ground state exhibiting periodic arrangements of solitons, has been limited thus far. Here, we theoretically perform the systematic analysis for the dynamical control of the number of chiral solitons in monoaxial chiral magnets by effectively utilizing the edge modes whose excitation is localized near the edges. By studying the dynamical process associated with this edge mode in an applied rotating magnetic field by using the Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert equation, we show that multiple soliton penetrations can take place until the system reaches the nonequilibrium steady state, and the number of infiltrated solitons successively increases with the amplitude of the rotating magnetic field after surpassing the threshold. We also clarify that the threshold amplitude of the rotating magnetic field can be reduced through the static magnetic field. Our results reveal that the desired number of solitons can be added within a certain range by taking advantage of the edge modes that appear without any special processing at the edges of the system. These results contribute to the development of an experimental way to control the number of solitons and are expected to be further applied to a wide range of magnetic solitons, not limited to chiral solitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10842v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kotaro Shimizu, Shun Okumura, Yasuyuki Kato, Yukitoshi Motome</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crosscap states and duality of Ising field theory in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose two distinct crosscap states for the two-dimensional (2D) Ising field theory. These two crosscap states, identifying Ising spins or dual spins (domain walls) at antipodal points, are shown to be related via the Kramers-Wannier duality transformation. We derive their Majorana free field representations and extend bosonization techniques to calculate correlation functions of the 2D Ising conformal field theory (CFT) with different crosscap boundaries. We further develop a conformal perturbation theory to calculate the Klein bottle entropy as a universal scaling function [Phys. Rev. Lett. 130, 151602 (2023)] in the 2D Ising field theory. The formalism developed in this work is applicable to many other 2D CFTs perturbed by relevant operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11046v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueshui Zhang, Ying-Hai Wu, Lei Wang, Hong-Hao Tu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Natural anomalous cyclotron response in a hydrodynamic local quantum critical metal in a periodic potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11095v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study DC magnetotransport in a quantum critical metal in the presence of a lattice. In the regime where the transport is hydrodynamical the interplay of the Lorentz force and the lattice gives rise to a natural anomalous contribution to the cyclotron frequency that changes it from its canonical charge-to-mass ratio. The size of this effect is universal as it is determined only by thermodynamic quantities. Remarkably the Drude weight changes in such a way that to first subleading order in the lattice strength the Hall resistivity and Hall coefficient do not change, though the Hall angle does change. We confirm our results with numerical simulations in a holographic model of a strange metal. For weak lattice strength these hydrodynamic effects are shown to be present. The numerical simulations also suggest that strong lattice effects beyond a hydrodynamic regime may provide a resolution to the experimentally observed anomalous Hall response of cuprate strange metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11095v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Chagnet, Sam Arend, Floris Balm, Martijn Janse, Joshua Saldi, Koenraad Schalm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical expression for $\pi$-ton vertex contributions to the optical conductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vertex corrections from the transversal particle-hole channel, so-called $\pi$-tons, are generic in models for strongly correlated electron systems and can lead to a displaced Drude peak (DDP). Here, we derive the analytical expression for these $\pi$-tons, and how they affect the optical conductivity as a function of correlation length $\xi$, fermion lifetime $\tau$, temperature $T$, and coupling strength to spin or charge fluctuations $g$. In particular, for $T\rightarrow T_c$, the critical temperature for antiferromagnetic or charge ordering, the dc vertex correction is algebraic $\sigma_{VERT}^{dc}\propto \xi \sim (T-T_c)^{-\nu}$ in one dimension and logarithmic $\sigma_{VERT}^{dc}\propto \ln\xi \sim \nu \ln (T-T_c)$ in two dimensions. Here, $\nu$ is the critical exponent for the correlation length. If we have the exponential scaling $\xi \sim e^{1/T}$ of an ideal two-dimensional system, the DDP becomes more pronounced with increasing $T$ but fades away at low temperatures where only a broadening of the Drude peak remains, as it is observed experimentally. Further, we find the maximum of the DPP to be given by the inverse lifetime: $\omega_{DDP} \sim 1/\tau$. These characteristic dependencies can guide experiments to evidence $\pi$-tons in actual materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11158v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juraj Krsnik, Anna Kauch, Karsten Held</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge and spin properties of a generalized Wigner crystal realized in the moir\'e WSe$_2$/WS$_2$ heterobilayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the charge and spin properties of an effective single-band model representing a moir\'e superlattice of the WSe$_{2}$/WS$_{2}$ heterobilayer. We focus on the $2/3$ electron filling, which refers to the formation of a generalized Wigner crystal, as evidenced experimentally. Our approach is based on the extended-Hubbard model on a triangular lattice with non-interacting part effectively describing a spin-split band due to Ising-type spin-orbit coupling. We investigate the system in the regime of strong on-site Coulomb repulsion and the ground state of the Hamiltonian is obtained with the use of the Density Matrix Renormalization Group formulated within the Matrix Product State approach. According to our analysis, based on the density-density correlation functions resolved in the momentum space, a transition from the metallic to the insulating state appears with increasing intersite electron-electron interactions. This transition is identified as being concomitant with the emergence of a generalized Wigner crystal that realizes the honeycomb lattice pattern. We investigate the magnetic properties of such a Wigner crystal state and find that the presence of spin-valley polarization and the increased intersite repulsion induce spin canting of the out-of-plane antiferromagnetic ordering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11202v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej Biborski, Micha{\l} Zegrodnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scrambling in the Charging of Quantum Batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10590v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exponentially fast scrambling of an initial state characterizes quantum chaotic systems. Given the importance of quickly populating higher energy levels from low-energy states in quantum battery charging protocols, this Letter investigates the role of quantum scrambling in quantum batteries and its effect on optimal power and charging times. We adopt a bare representation with normalized bandwidths to suppress system energy dependence. To our knowledge, this is the first in-depth exploration of quantum scrambling in the context of quantum batteries. By analyzing the dynamics of out-of-time-order correlators, our findings indicate that quantum scrambling does not necessarily lead to faster charging, despite its potential for accelerating the process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10590v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebasti\'an V. Romero, Yongcheng Ding, Xi Chen, Yue Ban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UV complete local field theory of persistent symmetry breaking in 2+1 dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10606v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spontaneous symmetry breaking can persist at all temperatures in certain biconical $\mathrm{O}(N)\times \mathbb{Z}_2$ vector models when the underlying field theories are ultraviolet complete. So far, the existence of such theories has been established in fractional dimensions for local but nonunitary models or in 2+1 dimensions but for nonlocal models. Here, we study local models at zero and finite temperature directly in 2+1 dimensions employing functional methods. At zero temperature, we establish that our approach describes the quantum critical behaviour with high accuracy for all $N\geq 2$. We then exhibit the mechanism of discrete symmetry breaking from $\mathrm{O}(N)\times \mathbb{Z}_2\to \mathrm{O}(N)$ for increasing temperature near the biconical critical point when $N$ is finite but large. We calculate the corresponding finite-temperature phase diagram and further show that the Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner theorem is fully respected within this approach, i.e., symmetry breaking only occurs in the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ sector. Finally, we determine the critical $N$ above which this phenomenon can be observed to be $N_c \approx 15$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10606v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bilal Hawashin, Junchen Rong, Michael M. Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenoperator approach to Schrieffer-Wolff perturbation theory and dispersive interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10656v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern quantum physics is very modular: we first understand basic building blocks (``XXZ Hamiltonian'' ``Jaynes-Cummings'' etc.) and then combine them to explore novel effects. A typical example is placing known systems inside an optical cavity. The Schrieffer-Wolff perturbation method is particularly suited for dealing with these problems, since it casts the perturbation expansion in terms of operator corrections to a Hamiltonian, which is more intuitive than energy level corrections, as in traditional time-independent perturbation theory. However, the method lacks a systematic approach.% and has largely remained a niche topic. In these notes we discuss how \emph{eigenoperator decompositions}, a concept largely used in open quantum systems, can be employed to construct an intuitive and systematic formulation of Schrieffer-Wolff perturbation theory. To illustrate this we revisit various papers in the literature, old and new, and show how they can instead be solved using eigenoperators. Particular emphasis is given to perturbations that couple two systems with very different transition frequencies (highly off-resonance), leading to the so-called dispersive interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10656v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel T. Landi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional superconductivity in altermagnets with spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10712v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate some possible symmetries of the superconducting state that emerges in three-dimensional altermagnets in the presence of spin-orbit coupling. We demonstrate within a weak-coupling approach that altermagnetic fluctuations with form factor $\boldsymbol{g}_{\mathbf{k}}$ promote spin-triplet superconductivity described by gap functions $\boldsymbol{d}(\mathbf{k}) = \boldsymbol{u}(\mathbf{k}) \times \boldsymbol{g}_{\mathbf{k}}$, such that $\boldsymbol{u}(\mathbf{k}) = - \boldsymbol{u}(-\mathbf{k})$. Consequently, this singles out $f$-wave spin-triplet superconductivity as the most favorable pairing state to appear in the vicinity of $d$-wave altermagnetism. Furthermore, we obtain that the combination of spin-singlet superconducting states with altermagnetism gives rise to Bogoliubov-Fermi surfaces, which are protected by a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological invariant. Using a Ginzburg-Landau analysis, we show that, for a class of spin-orbit coupled altermagnetic models, a superconducting phase is expected to appear at low temperatures as an intertwined $d + if$ state, thus breaking time-reversal symmetry spontaneously.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10712v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vanuildo S. de Carvalho, Hermann Freire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Crystals from single-molecule magnet arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10816v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Time crystals, a unique non-equilibrium quantum phenomenon with promising applications in current quantum technologies, mark a significant advance in quantum mechanics. Although traditionally studied in atom-cavity and optical lattice systems, pursuing alternative nanoscale platforms for time crystals is crucial. Here we theoretically predict discrete time-crystals in a periodically driven molecular magnet array, modeled by a spin-S Heisenberg Hamiltonian with significant quadratic anisotropy, taken with realistic and experimentally relevant physical parameters. Surprisingly, we find that the time-crystal response frequency correlates with the energy levels of the individual magnets and is essentially independent of the exchange coupling. The latter is unexpectedly manifested through a pulse-like oscillation in the magnetization envelope, signaling a many-body response. These results show that molecular magnets can be a rich platform for studying time-crystalline behavior and possibly other out-of-equilibrium quantum many-body dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10816v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhajit Sarkar, Yonatan Dubi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto transport and first principle study of strong topological insulator gray Arsenic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11016v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we report the synthesis of a single crystalline gray Arsenic (As) via the Bismuth flux method. The as-grown sample has a Rhombohedral structure as the most stable one. Its XRD (X-ray Diffractometry) pattern ensures a single phase of the grown crystal with space group R-3m. The observed sharp XRD peaks on mechanically exfoliated thin flakes ensured the high crystallinity with growth direction along the c-axis. The EDAX (Energy Dispersive X-ray Analysis) endorses the stoichiometric purity of the as-grown As single crystal. To study the vibrational mode, the Raman spectra are recorded, which show peaks at 196.2 cm-1 and 255.74 cm-1, identified as Eg and A1g modes by DFT calculations. The sample is further characterized by electronic and magneto-transport measurements. The resistivity vs temperature measurement illustrates its metallic nature in the temperature range of 2K to 300K. The measured residual resistivity ratio of the sample is 180, which endorses the high quality of the as-synthesized As single crystal. The RH measurement elucidates huge observed magnetoresistance (MR), along with SdH oscillations, which indicate the presence of topological surface states. The topological nature of As is also confirmed by first principle calculations. Not only orbit projected bands show signatures of band inversion but also the Z2invariant value(1,111) calculated by Wilson loop method affirms As to be a strong topological insulator (TI).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11016v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. K. Karn, Kapil Kumar, Geet Awana, Kunal Yadav, S. Patnaik, V. P. S. Awana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universally non-diverging Gr\"uneisen parameter at critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11086v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: According to Boltzmann-Gibbs (BG) statistical mechanics, the thermodynamic response, such as the isothermal susceptibility, at critical points (CPs) presents a divergent-like behavior. An appropriate parameter to probe both classical and quantum CPs is the so-called Gr\"uneisen ratio $\Gamma$. Motivated by the results reported in Phys. Rev. B $\textbf{108}$, L140403 (2023), we extend the quantum version of $\Gamma$ to the non-additive $q$-entropy $S_q$. Our findings indicate that using $S_q$ at the unique value of $q$ restoring the extensivity of the entropy, $\Gamma$ is universally non-diverging at CPs. We unprecedentedly introduce $\Gamma$ in terms of $S_q$, being BG recovered for $q \rightarrow 1$. We thus solve a long-standing problem related to the $\textit{illusory}$ diverging susceptibilities at CPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11086v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel M. Soares, Lucas Squillante, Henrique S. Lima, Constantino Tsallis, Mariano de Souza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallic holography for $\mathcal{N}=2$ SCFTs in 4d</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11118v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We build up the notion of metallic holography for $\mathcal{N}=2$ SCFTs in four dimensions, in the presence of a finite $U(1)$ chemical potential. We compute two point correlation functions and study their properties in the regime of low frequency and low momentum. The color sector reveals gapless excitations, one of which propagates with a finite phase velocity while the other mode attenuates through scattering. The flavour sector, on the other hand, reveals spectrum that contains quasiparticle excitations which propagate with a definite phase velocity together with modes that propagate with a finite group velocity which quantum attenuates quite similar in spirit as that of Landau's zero sound modes. We also compute associated AC conductivities, which exhibit different characteristics for different (color and flavour) sectors of $\mathcal{N}=2$ SCFTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11118v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibakar Roychowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling a frustrated Ising square lattice with the D-Wave Quantum Annealer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11259v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Ising model with nearest-neighbor interactions on a two-dimensional (2D) square lattice is one of the simplest models for studying ferro-magnetic to para-magnetic transitions. Extensive results are available in the literature for this model, which has become a paradigm for the study of magnetic phase transitions in materials, both theoretically and numerically. After a brief review of the main results obtained with a classical computer, we show how to implement on the D- Wave quantum annealer a more complex Ising model with the addition of competing antiferromagnetic interactions between the diagonal next-to-nearest neighbors with two coupling constants J1 and J2. The dynamics of this system, owing to frustration, are richer than those of the simple Ising model and exhibit a third striped (or antiferromagnetic) phase in addition to the ferro- and para-magnetic phases. In this work, we observed all three phases on the D-Wave hardware, studied the behavior of the solution with different annealing parameters, such as the chain strength and annealing time, and showed how to identify the phase transition by varying the ratio between the ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic couplings. The same system is studied on a classical computer, with the possibility of taking into account the temperature (fixed on D-Wave) as a free parameter and to explore the full phase diagram: some comparative conclusions with D-Wave are drawn.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11259v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Marin, A. Fontana, V. Bellani, F. Pederiva, A. Quaranta, F. Rossella, A. Salamon, G. Salina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Universality from Conserved Superoperators in Unitary Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An important result in the theory of quantum control is the "universality" of $2$-local unitary gates, i.e. the fact that any global unitary evolution of a system of $L$ qudits can be implemented by composition of $2$-local unitary gates. Surprisingly, recent results have shown that universality can break down in the presence of symmetries: in general, not all globally symmetric unitaries can be constructed using $k$-local symmetric unitary gates. This also restricts the dynamics that can be implemented by symmetric local Hamiltonians. In this paper, we show that obstructions to universality in such settings can in general be understood in terms of superoperator symmetries associated with unitary evolution by restricted sets of gates. These superoperator symmetries lead to block decompositions of the operator Hilbert space, which dictate the connectivity of operator space, and hence the structure of the dynamical Lie algebra. We demonstrate this explicitly in several examples by systematically deriving the superoperator symmetries from the gate structure using the framework of commutant algebras, which has been used to systematically derive symmetries in other quantum many-body systems. We clearly delineate two different types of non-universality, which stem from different structures of the superoperator symmetries, and discuss its signatures in physical observables. In all, our work establishes a comprehensive framework to explore the universality of unitary circuits and derive physical consequences of its absence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11407v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Lastres, Frank Pollmann, Sanjay Moudgalya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Avoided metallicity in a hole-doped Mott insulator on a triangular lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17139v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Doping of a Mott insulator gives rise to a wide variety of exotic emergent states, from high-temperature superconductivity to charge, spin, and orbital orders. The physics underpinning their evolution is, however, poorly understood. A major challenge is the chemical complexity associated with traditional routes to doping. Here, we study the Mott insulating CrO$_2$ layer of the delafossite PdCrO$_2$, where an intrinsic polar catastrophe provides a clean route to doping of the surface. From scanning tunnelling microscopy and angle-resolved photoemission, we find that the surface stays insulating accompanied by a short-range ordered state. From density functional theory, we demonstrate how the formation of charge disproportionation results in an insulating ground state of the surface that is disparate from the hidden Mott insulator in the bulk. We demonstrate that voltage pulses induce local modifications to this state which relax over tens of minutes, pointing to a glassy nature of the charge order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17139v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-52007-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Commun. 15, 8098 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chi Ming Yim, Gesa-R. Siemann, Srdjan Stavri\'c, Seunghyun Khim, Izidor Benedi\v{c}i\v{c}, Philip A. E. Murgatroyd, Tommaso Antonelli, Matthew D. Watson, Andrew P. Mackenzie, Silvia Picozzi, Phil D. C. King, Peter Wahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nature of Topological Phase Transition of Kitaev Quantum Spin Liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.12610v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the nature of the topological quantum phase transition between the gapless and gapped Kitaev quantum spin liquid phases away from the exactly solvable point. The transition is driven by anisotropy of the Kitaev couplings. At the critical point the two Dirac points of the gapless Majorana modes merge, resulting in the formation of a semi-Dirac point with quadratic and linear band touching directions. We derive an effective Gross-Neveu-Yukawa type field theory that describes the topological phase transition in the presence of additional magnetic interactions. We obtain the infrared scaling form of the propagator of the dynamical Ising order parameter field and perform a renormalization-group analysis. The universality of the transition is found to be different to that of symmetry-breaking phase transitions of semi-Dirac electrons. However, as in the electronic case, the Majorana fermions acquire an anomalous dimension, indicative of the breakdown of the fractionalized quasiparticle description.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.12610v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huanzhi Hu, Frank Kr\"uger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin dynamics and possible topological magnons in non-stoichiometric pyrochlore iridate Tb$_2$Ir$_2$O$_7$ studied by RIXS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03829v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report a resonant inelastic X-ray scattering study on a single crystal of a non-stoichiometric pyrochlore iridate Tb$_{2+x}$Ir$_{2-x}$O$_{7-y}$ ($x \simeq 0.25$) that magnetically orders at $T_{\rm{N}}\simeq 50$ K. We find that the strength of the spin-orbit coupling and the trigonal distortion of the IrO$_6$ octahedra are comparable with the ones obtained in other pyrochlore iridates. We observe a propagating gapped magnon mode at low energy, and model it using a Hamiltonian consisting of a Heisenberg exchange [$J = 16.2(9)$ meV] and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions [$D = 5.2(3)$ meV], which shows the robustness of interactions despite Tb-stuffing at the Ir-site. Strikingly, the ratio $D/J = 0.32(3)$ supports possible non-trivial topological magnon band crossing. This material may thus host coexisting fermionic and bosonic topology, with potential for manipulating electronic and magnonic topological bands thanks to the $d-f$ interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03829v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Q. Faure, A. Toschi, J. R. Soh, E. Lhotel, B. Detlefs, D. Prabhakaran, D. F. McMorrow, C. J. Sahle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum oscillation study of the large magnetoresistance in Mo substituted WTe$_2$ single crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00498v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The list of interesting electrical properties exhibited by transition metal dichalcogenides has grown with the discovery of extremely large magnetoresistance (MR) and type-II Weyl semimetal behaviour in WTe$_2$ and MoTe$_2$. The extremely large MR in WTe$_2$ is still not adequately understood. Here, we systematically study the effect of Mo substitution on the quantum oscillations in the MR in WTe$_2$. The MR decreases with Mo substitution, however, the carrier concentrations extracted from the quantum oscillations show that the charge compensation improves. We believe that earlier interpretations based on the two-band theory, which attribute the decrease in MR to charge imbalance, could be incorrect due to over-parametrization. We attribute the decrease in MR in the presence of charge compensation to a fall in transport mobility, which is evident from the residual resistivity ratio data. The quantum scattering time and the effective masses do not change within experimental errors upon substitution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00498v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourabh Barua, M. R. Lees, G. Balakrishnan, P. A. Goddard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metal-insulator transition of spinless fermions coupled to dispersive optical bosons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14187v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Including the previously ignored dispersion of phonons we revisit the metal-insulator transition problem in one-dimensional electron-phonon systems on the basis of a modified spinless fermion Holstein model. Using matrix-product-state techniques we determine the global ground-state phase diagram in the thermodynamic limit for the half-filled band case, and show that in particular the curvature of the bare phonon band has a significant effect, not only on the transport properties characterized by the conductance and the Luttinger liquid parameter, but also on the phase space structure of the model as a whole. While a downward curved (convex) dispersion of the phonons only shifts the Tomonaga-Luttinger-liquid to charge-density-wave quantum phase transition towards stronger EP coupling, an upward curved (concave) phonon band leads to a new phase-separated state which, in the case of strong dispersion, can even completely cover the charge-density wave. Such phase separation does not occur in the related Edwards fermion-boson model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14187v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-024-68811-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Scientific Reports 14, 18050 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Florian Lange, Holger Fehske</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
