<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 04:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Finite temperature magnetic interactions from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Density functional theory has demonstrated remarkable predictive power in calculating magnetic properties at zero temperature. At finite temperatures, thermally excited phonons may affect magnetism. Efficient ab-initio methods to calculate the temperature dependence of magnetic exchange interactions are still lacking despite the importance of room temperature magnetism for applications. Exchange is controlled by an interplay between metal-ligand hybridization, Hubbard repulsion, band gap, interatomic distances and bond angles, all of which change with temperature. Here we present a method to calculate the exchange interactions at finite temperatures from first principles using only two supercell calculations and quantify these mechanisms. Changes in bond angles and the band gap are identified as a primary factors. In NiO with 180-degree bonds exchange decreases with temperature, while in Cr$_2$O$_3$ with the bond angles away from 180 degrees the exchange increases by 10% at room temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16143v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravi Kaushik, Ryota Ono, Sergey Artyukhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity-induced coherent magnetization and polaritons in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets feature antiparallel spin sublattices with $d$-, $g$-, or $i$-wave spin order, yielding nonrelativistic spin splitting without net magnetization. We show that embedding a two-dimensional $d$-wave altermagnet in a driven optical cavity induces a finite, tunable magnetization. Coherent photon driving couples selectively to electronic sublattices, and the resulting altermagnets' symmetry-broken spin texture yields a pronounced steady-state spin imbalance -- coherent magnetization -- absent in conventional antiferromagnets for the same lattice configuration. A mean-field Lindblad analysis reveals the dominance of quadratic over linear couplings. In the strong-coupling regime, distinct polariton signatures emerge in the steady state of induced magnetization. This work demonstrates cavity control of altermagnets for spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16248v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Yarmohammadi, Libor \v{S}mejkal, James K. Freericks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoinduced melting dynamics and collective mode in a correlated charge-order system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the transient spectral function during the photoinduced melting of charge order in a correlated electron system, to unravel the dynamical processes triggered by different initial excitations. We employ a one-dimensional interacting spinless fermion model introducing a pulsed laser light, and perform a comparative study by the Hartree-Fock approximation and by the exact diagonalization method to numerically solve the time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation. We find characteristic behavior in the transient spectral function, whose features strongly depend on the pump light frequency $\omega_p$. When $\omega_p$ is resonant with the collective phase mode of frequency $\Omega_c\simeq \Delta_{\rm CO}/2$, where $\Delta_{\rm CO}$ is the charge gap, the transient spectral function exhibits a photoinduced in-gap weight which triggers large responses. With increasing the laser intensity, the development of in-gap weight directly turns into the collapse of the gap. This charge-order destabilization process is in sharp contrast to the case of $\omega_p&gt;\Delta_{\rm CO}$, where the photoirradiation induces interband electron-hole excitations giving rise to a shrinkage of the gap. The impact of quantum fluctuations and spatial inhomogeneity on the photoinduced dynamics is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16855v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasuhiro Tanaka, Hitoshi Seo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Dependence of the Momentum-Resolved Static Spin Susceptibility in a Mott-Proximate Cuprate Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the temperature dependence of the static spin susceptibility at $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, \pi)$ and $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, 0)$ in a Mott-proximate cuprate model with an antinodal pseudogap -- a model system for high-temperature superconducting (HTSC) cuprates.
  The results show the susceptibility onset temperature tracks the critical temperature ($T_c$) of HTSCs with a comparable scale across the electron filling factor. Also, as the electron filling decreases and the chemical potential approaches the antinodal van Hove region, the susceptibility at $\mathbf{q}=(\pi,0)$ -- the axial particle-hole response -- grows markedly.
  The emergence of cuprate superconductivity correlates with a suppression of low-energy antinodal spin response and associated particle-hole excitations, which would otherwise dephase $d$-wave pairing, commonly attributed to spin fluctuations. In this context, the pseudogap partially suppresses antinodal spectral weight near $\omega = 0$, thereby reducing the low-$\omega$ particle-hole phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16884v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keishichiro Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Random Bond Disorder on Quantum Skyrmions in a spin-half Quantum Heisenberg Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of random bond disorder on quantum skyrmions using a spin-half quantum Heisenberg model on the square lattice with Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction, Heisenberg anisotropy, and boundary-pinned magnetic field. Utilizing the neural network quantum state technique, we explore the influence of disorder on spin textures, topological properties, and quantum entanglement. We show that the disorder reduces the stability of quantum skyrmions, ultimately causing them to collapse at high disorder strengths. In addition, our results reveal two key insights. First, the presence of disorder, rather than simply degrading skyrmion order, significantly enhances local quantum entanglement, as evidenced by the rise in second R\'enyi entropy. Second, our calculations show that the topological entanglement entropy calculated using the second R\'enyi entropy remains negligible across all the disorder strengths. This suggests long-range entanglement is absent and the skyrmion phase is not detectable using this specific probe. Overall, our work provides new insights into how disorder constructively influences quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16929v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Kumar, Kalpataru Pradhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnon edge states of skyrmion crystal in non-uniform magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A regular lattice of magnetic skyrmions is the ground state of thin ferromagnetic films with Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction in a relatively wide range of external magnetic fields. It was previously theoretically shown that upon the increase of magnetic field a topological transition in the magnon spectrum of such skyrmion crystal (SkX) may occur. Non-uniform magnetic field may lead to localized magnon states emerging at the interface between two half-planes of SkX. Using semiclassical quantization and the stereographic projection approach, we study such appearing edge states both in a full band structure calculation and in simplified effective model. The latter effective model described by extended Dirac equation is applicable to two relevant magnon bands near $\Gamma$ point. We show that both the chirality of emerging edge states and the degree of its localization at the interface is controlled by magnetic field profile. We demonstrate that the localization length may be as small as a few inter-skyrmion distances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16970v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. E. Timofeev, D. N. Aristov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Field Torque Magnetometry on the Kagome Antiferromagnet Karpenkoite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report torque magnetometry results on single crystals of karpenkoite Co3(V2O7)(OH)2 2H2O, a model candidate for the kagome antiferromagnet. No field-induced phase transition is detected up to 45 T for B||c and B||a. Instead, the torque reveals a continuous spin reorientation toward saturation, most likely governed by a dominant Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17050v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hibiki Kunisawa, Ryuya Watanabe, Jun-ichi Yamaura, Yoshimitsu Kohama, Toshihiro Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott vs Kondo: Influence of Various Density Functional Based Methods on the Ce Isostructural Phase Transition Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cerium iso-structural phase transition (gamma to alpha) is dominated by f-electron localization changes that results in a magnetic ordering change and a volume collapse. Generally, these physics are difficult to capture with ab initio and first principles methods. However, previous works have shown various methods to be successful in predicting at least some of the physics of the gamma to alpha phase transition. Therefore, here, we perform a broad survey of density functional based methods across three levels of theory and types of functions (GGA, MetaGGA, and Hybrid functionals) and compare the results, focusing on hydrostatic compression across the phase boundary at zero Kelvin. For the methods that best reproduce experimental results, we directly probe the predicted mechanisms and frame the results in the Mott/Kondo debate, assessing how the underlying methods and assumptions of different functionals can assess the physical drivers in the phase transition, providing insight into the governing dynamics of this unique phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17755v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brenden W. Hamilton, Alexander R. Mu\~noz, Travis E. Jones, Benjamin T. Nebgen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-Principles Approach to Spin Excitations in Noncollinear Magnetic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14405v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a first-principles method based on density functional theory and many-body perturbation theory for computing spin excitations in magnetic systems with noncollinear spin textures. Traditionally, the study of magnetic excitations has relied on spin models that assume magnetic moments to be localized. Beyond this restriction, recent $ab~initio$ methods based on Green's functions within the local spin-density approximation have emerged as a general framework for calculating magnetic susceptibilities. However, their application has so far been largely limited to collinear ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic systems. In this work, we extend this framework and enable the treatment of large-scale noncollinear magnetic systems by leveraging a Wannier-basis representation and implementing an ansatz potential method to reduce computational cost. We apply our method to the spin-spiral state of LiCu$_2$O$_2$, successfully capturing its steady-state spin-rotation pitch in agreement with the experimental measurement and resolving the characteristic magnon dispersion. We further analyze the interplay between the spiral spin structure and the on-site spin-exchange splitting, and elucidate the crucial role of magnetic dipoles on ligand ions in mediating effective ferromagnetic interaction among the primary spins on Cu$^{2+}$ ions. Finally, we provide a theoretical prediction of the magnon dispersion on top of the helical spin background in high agreement with the experimental measurement. Overall, this work establishes a general and computationally efficient framework for simulating collective spin dynamics in noncollinear magnetic systems from first principles, exemplified by -- but not limited to -- spin-spiral states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14405v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsiao-Yi Chen, Ryotaro Arita, Yusuke Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-loop Corrected Holographic Shear Viscosity to Entropy Density Ratio at Low Temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16100v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Near-extremal black holes are known to contain strong quantum fluctuations in their near-horizon near-AdS$_2$ throat region governed by an effective action that includes Schwarzian modes. These fluctuations lead to one-loop corrections in the gravitational path integral that are essential in understanding the thermodynamics of near-extremal black holes at low temperatures where they become more dominant that the semi-classical answer. We explore the implications of these quantum fluctuations for near-extremal asymptotically AdS$_4$ black branes in the context of the AdS/CFT correspondence. We note that at one-loop level there is a coupling of the shear gravitational fluctuations to one of the would-be zero modes. This coupling affects the retarded Green's function in a way that leads to a low temperature violation of the shear viscosity to entropy density bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16100v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leopoldo A. Pando Zayas, Jingchao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Brownian SYK-Hubbard Model: from Spectral Function to Quantum Chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the emergence of complex correlations in strongly interacting systems remains a fundamental challenge in quantum many-body physics. One fruitful approach is to develop solvable toy models that encapsulate universal properties shared by realistic systems. In this work, we introduce the Brownian SYK-Hubbard model, which combines the all-to-all random interactions of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model with on-site Hubbard-type interactions. This hybrid construction enables the study of the interplay between nonlocal random dynamics and local correlation effects: (1) As the interaction strength increases, the single-particle spectrum exhibits a transition from a single peak to a two-peak structure, signaling the onset of Mottness. (2) The spectral form factor undergoes a sequence of dynamical transitions as the evolution time increases before reaching the plateau in the long-time limit under strong Hubbard interactions. (3) The out-of-time-order correlator is computed by summing a series of modified ladder diagrams, which determines the quantum Lyapunov exponent and reveals a violation of the bound on branching time. Our results establish a new analytically tractable platform for exploring the effects of Hubbard interactions in chaotic many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16401v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Sun, Peng Zhang, Pengfei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Complexity in Constrained Many-Body Models: Scars, Fragmentation, and Chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16570v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kinetic constraints in quantum many-body systems give rise to quantum states, whose behavior strongly depends on the choice of initial conditions. In recent years, these systems have drawn increasing interest because they provide insight into the mechanisms of thermalization and the situations where it can fail. In this work, we study a family of kinetically constrained models, including the celebrated Quantum Game of Life, from the perspective of quantum complexity, with a focus on entanglement, nonstabilizerness, and signatures of quantum chaos. By applying spectral diagnostics such as level statistics and spectral form factors, we demonstrate that these models show robust chaotic behavior while also supporting Hilbert space fragmentation and quantum many-body scar states. Remarkably, we find that even certain symmetry-resolved fragmented sectors can themselves host scarred eigenstates, highlighting the unexpected coexistence of chaos, scars, and fragmentation within the same family of Hamiltonians. To better understand these fragmented subspaces, we further characterize them using their quantum resource generation ability. In particular, we demonstrate that characterization of entanglement and the ability to generate nonstabilizerness can be instrumental in distinguishing different dynamically disconnected sectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16570v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arkaprava Sil, Sudipto Singha Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-temperature signatures of underlying superconductivity in the electron-doped Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16616v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We perform numerically exact determinant quantum Monte Carlo simulations of the Hubbard model and analyze pairing tendencies by evaluating correlation functions at the imaginary-time midpoint ($\tau=\beta/2$), which suppresses high-frequency weight and emphasizes low-energy physics. Using this diagnostic, we identify clear finite-temperature signatures of underlying $d$-wave superconductivity for electron doping, while finding no clear indication upon cooling for hole doping. Our analysis enables direct comparison with ground-state DMRG, revealing consistent real-space pairing patterns. These results provide a practical route to bridge the gap between finite-temperature and ground-state numerically exact simulations of the Hubbard model despite the fermion sign problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16616v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen O. Wang, Thomas P. Devereaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning macroscopic phase frustration in multiorbital superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16843v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Time-reversal symmetry-breaking (TRSB) superconductivity has been reported in a growing number of materials. In some cases, TRSB arises naturally from chiral superconductivity, but in many low-symmetry systems this explanation is not viable. In these latter cases, TRSB is often attributed to phase frustration among multiple superconducting gaps on different Fermi surfaces. Yet, the microscopic conditions enabling such frustration remain poorly understood. Here, inspired by the TRSB reported in the superconducting state of iron-based materials, we demonstrate that a minimal two-orbital model can support a TRSB superconducting state via phase frustration. We identify the key microscopic parameters that stabilize TRSB in d-electron systems with orthorhombic symmetry and provide a framework to systematically enlarge the region of parameter space within which TRSB is expected in materials with other electronic content and crystalline symmetries. Our results offer a simple and experimentally relevant route to understand and control TRSB in multiorbital superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16843v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilaria Maccari, Aline Ramires</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetically-induced bound states in a frustrated Rydberg tweezer array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17183v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding how particles bind into composite objects is a ubiquitous theme in physics, from the formation of molecules to hadrons in quantum chromodynamics and the pairing of charge carriers in superconductors. The formation of bound states usually originates from attractive interactions between particles. However, the binding can also arise purely from the motion of dopants due to kinetic frustration, which is potentially related to unconventional pairing in moir\'e materials. Here, we report the first direct observation of kinetically-induced bound states between holes and magnons using a Rydberg atom array quantum simulator of the bosonic $t$-$J$ model in frustrated ladders and 2D lattices. First, we demonstrate the formation of mobile one-hole-one-magnon bound states. We then construct three-particle one-hole-two-magnon bound states and reveal the underlying binding mechanism by observing kinetically-induced singlet correlations. Finally, we investigate how mobile dopants structure their magnetic environment in a spin-balanced 2D triangular lattice, showing that a hole induces $120^\circ$ antiferromagnetic order, while a doublon dopant generates in-plane ferromagnetic correlations. Our results demonstrates compelling evidence of kinetically-induced binding, opening a new avenue to understand novel pairing mechanisms in correlated quantum materials like superconductors in moir\'e superlattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17183v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mu Qiao, Romain Martin, Lukas Homeier, Ivan Morera, Bastien G\'ely, Lukas Klein, Yuki Torii Chew, Daniel Barredo, Thierry Lahaye, Eugene Demler, Antoine Browaeys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-stabilizerness as a Diagnostic of Criticality and Exceptional Points in Non-Hermitian Spin Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17248v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate non-stabilizerness, also known as ``magic,'' to understand criticality and exceptional points in non-Hermitian quantum many-body systems. Our focus is on parity-time ($\mathcal{PT}$) symmetric spin chains, specifically the non-Hermitian transverse-field Ising and XX models. We calculate stabilizer R\'enyi entropies in their ground states using non-Hermitian matrix product state methods. Our findings show that magic exhibits unique and model-specific signs of phase transitions. In the Ising chain, it peaks along the regular Hermitian-like critical line but disappears across exceptional points. In contrast, in the XX chain, it reaches its maximum at the exceptional line where $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry is broken. Finite-size scaling reveals that these effects become more pronounced with larger systems, highlighting non-stabilizerness as a sensitive marker for both quantum criticality and non-Hermitian spectral degeneracies. We also investigate magic in momentum space for the XX model analytically and find that is reaches a minimum around exceptional points. Our results indicate that magic takes extremal values at the exceptional points and serves as a valuable tool for examining complexity, criticality, and symmetry breaking in non-Hermitian quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17248v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\u{a}t\u{a}lin Pa\c{s}cu Moca, Doru Sticlet, Bal\'azs D\'ora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Sum Rule from Higher-Form Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17317v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove an entanglement sum rule for $(d{-}1)$-dimensional quantum lattice models with finite abelian higher-form symmetries, obtained by minimally coupling a sector on $p$-simplices carrying a $p$-form $G$ symmetry to a sector on $(p{+}1)$-simplices carrying the dual $(d{-}p{-}2)$-form $\widehat G$ symmetry (with $\widehat G$ the Pontryagin dual of $G$). The coupling is introduced by conjugation with a symmetry-preserving operator $\mathcal{U}$ that dresses symmetry-invariant operators with appropriate Wilson operators. On the symmetry-invariant subspace, $\mathcal{U}$ is well-defined and unitary, and the coupled Hamiltonian is obtained from the decoupled one by conjugation with $\mathcal{U}$. Our main result concerns symmetric eigenstates of the coupled model that arise by acting with $\mathcal{U}$ on direct-product, symmetric eigenstates of the decoupled model: provided a topological criterion formulated via the Mayer--Vietoris sequence holds for the chosen bipartition, $\mathcal{U}$ factorizes across the cut when acting on the symmetric state, and the bipartite entanglement entropy equals the sum of the entropies of the two sectors. The framework explains and generalizes known examples in fermion-$\mathbb{Z}_2$ gauge theory, identifies when topology obstructs the factorization, and provides a procedure to construct new examples by gauging higher-form symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17317v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Yao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective dynamics in holographic fractonic solids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17404v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fractonic phases of matter, a class of states in which collective excitations with constrained mobility exist, have recently emerged as a novel avenue for ergodicity breaking and garnered broad interest in condensed matter physics. In this work, we consider a (3+1)-dimensional holographic model of fractonic solids and investigate the low-energy collective dynamics systematically. By computing the quasinormal modes of black holes, we obtain all the hydrodynamic excitations on the boundary, including two acoustic phonons, a longitudinal diffusive mode as well as a fractonic subdiffusive mode with the dispersion $\omega \sim-ik^4$. In addition, it is found that the fracton mode remains gapless when translational symmetry is explicitly broken. These results suggest that fractonic excitations are inherently protected by the crystal-dipole symmetry in solids and are qualitatively unaffected by broken spacetime symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17404v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ling-Zheng Xia, Lixin Xu, Wei-Jia Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Superconducting Diode Effect in the Asymmetric Hatsugai-Kohmoto Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17452v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The superconducting diode effect (SDE), characterized by a nonreciprocal supercurrent, has attracted significant attention in recent years due to its potential applications. However, most studies have focused on weakly correlated models, leaving the impact of strong electron-electron interactions on the SDE largely unexplored. In this work, we bridge this gap by investigating the SDE in asymmetric band metals with Hatsugai-Kohmoto (HK) interaction, which are exactly solvable due to their locality in Bloch momentum space. Through a combination of low-energy analysis and a numerical self-consistent approach, we demonstrate that HK interaction can enhance the SDE's quality factor. Our findings shed light on the role of strong electron-electron correlations in shaping the SDE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17452v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Chen, Pavan Hosur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiphoton Spectroscopy of a Dynamical Axion Insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.00064v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The unusual magnetoelectric transport present in Weyl semimetals and 3D topological insula- tors can be compactly understood as manifestations of a background axion field, which itself is determined by the microscopic band structure. In the presence of correlations, an additional axion quasiparticle may emerge as the collective excitations on top of the mean background field. Such modes couple nonlinearly to electric and magnetic fields, giving rise to a dynamical magnetoelectric response. However, unambiguous identification of this collective axion mode is challenging due to its inherent nonlinear dynamics. Here, we propose an all-optical protocol that utilizes a pump-probe setup for verifying and characterizing the transient dynamics of axion fields in three-dimensional insulator systems. In particular, we show that nonlinear Raman processes induce dynamical oscillations of the axion field that depend on the geometry of the incident electromagnetic fields. These oscillations manifest in the polarization and magnetization of the material, hence, can be subsequently measured using time-resolved Kerr rotation spectroscopy. Our results open a pathway towards using multi-photon and quantum pair spectroscopies to identify new correlated phases of quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.00064v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3zkg-95b3</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Olivia Liebman, Jonathan Curtis, Ioannis Petrides, Prineha Narang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Hall conductivity of electron-doped cuprates: Electrons and phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.15892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.15892v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has recently become clear that phonons generate a sizable thermal Hall effect in cuprates, whether they are undoped, electron-doped or hole-doped (inside the pseudogap phase). At higher doping, where cuprates are reasonably good metals, mobile electrons also generate a thermal Hall effect, the thermal equivalent of the standard electrical Hall effect. Here we show that in the cleanest crystals of the electron-doped cuprate Nd$_{2-x}$Ce$_{x}$CuO$_{4}$, at high doping, the phonon and electron contributions to the thermal Hall conductivity $\kappa_{\rm {xy}}$ are of comparable magnitude, but of opposite sign. In samples of lower quality, phonons dominate $\kappa_{\rm {xy}}$, resulting in a negative $\kappa_{\rm {xy}}$ at all temperatures. The fact that the negative phononic $\kappa_{\rm {xy}}$ in the metallic state is similar in magnitude and temperature dependence to that found in the insulating state at lower doping rules out any mechanism based on skew scattering of phonons off charged impurities, since a local charge should be screened in the metallic regime. The phononic $\kappa_{\rm {xy}}$ is found to persist over the entire doping range where antiferromagnetic correlations are known to be significant, suggesting that such correlations may play a role in generating the phonon thermal Hall effect in electron-doped cuprates. If the same mechanism is also at play in hole-doped cuprates, the presence of a phononic $\kappa_{\rm {xy}}$ below (and only below) the critical doping $p^{\star}$ would be evidence that spin correlations are a property of the pseudogap phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.15892v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marie-Eve Boulanger, Lu Chen, Vincent Oliviero, David Vignolles, Ga\"el Grissonnanche, Kejun Xu, Zhi-Xun Shen, Cyril Proust, Jordan Baglo, Louis Taillefer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo Study of Critical Fermi Surface with Spatially Disordered Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13858v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-Fermi liquids are an important topic in condensed matter physics, as their characteristics challenge the framework of traditional Fermi liquid theory and reveal the complex behavior of electrons in strongly interacting systems. Both the experimentally observed smeared region and the theoretically predicted marginal Fermi liquid suggest that spatial disorder seems to be an important driver of these phenomena. By performing large-scale determinant quantum Monte Carlo (DQMC) simulations in the ferromagnetic spin-fermion model at finite $N$, beyond the large-$N$ used in previous theoretical work, we investigated the role of spatial disorder in the critical Fermi surface (FS) of this model. We proposed a corrected theory of our system, which is based on a modified Eliashberg theory and a universal theory of strange metals. This theory agrees well with the data obtained from DQMC, particularly in capturing the $\omega \ln \omega$ type self-energy characteristic of marginal Fermi liquid behavior, and observing the linear-in-temperature resistivity. Our findings offer strong and unbiased validation of the universal theory of strange metals, broaden the applicability of the modified Eliashberg theory, and provide insights for numerically searching for marginal Fermi liquid and linear-in-temperature resistivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13858v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tu Hong, Xiao Yan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fitness landscape for quantum state tomography from neutron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, a direct connection between static structure factors and quantum ground states for two-spin interaction Hamiltonians was proven. This suggests the possibility of quantum state tomography from neutron scattering. Here, we investigate the associated fitness landscape numerically. We find a linear relationship between the mean square distances of the structure factors and the associated state overlaps, implying a well-behaved fitness landscape. Furthermore, we find evidence suggesting that the approach can be generalized to thermal equilibrium states. We also extend the arguments to the cases of applied magnetic fields and finite clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10502v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/x9mb-x1gz</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B, 112, L140402 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tymoteusz Tula, Jorge Quintanilla, Gunnar M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractionalized Prethermalization in the One-Dimensional Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09708v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Prethermalization phenomena in driven systems are generally understood via a local Floquet Hamiltonian obtained from a high-frequency expansion. Remarkably, recently it has been shown that a driven Kitaev spin liquid with fractionalized excitations can realize a quasi-stationary state that is not captured by this paradigm. Instead distinct types of fractionalized excitations are characterized by vastly different temperatures-a phenomenon dubbed "fractionalized prethermalization". In our work, we analyze fractionalized prethermalization in a driven one-dimensional Hubbard model at strong coupling which hosts spin-charge fractionalization. At intermediate frequencies quasi-steady states emerge which are characterized by a low spin and high charge temperature with lifetimes set by two competing processes: the lifetime of the quasiparticles determined by Fermi's Golden rule and the exponentially long lifetime of a Floquet prethermal plateau. We classify drives into three categories, each giving rise to distinct (fractional) prethermalization dynamics. Resorting to a time-dependent variant of the Schrieffer-Wolff transformation, we systematically analyze how these drive categories are linked to the underlying driven Hubbard model, thereby providing a general understanding of the emergent thermalization dynamics. We discuss routes towards an experimental realization of this phenomenon in quantum simulation platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09708v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Romen, Johannes Knolle, Michael Knap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Strong-to-Weak Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking in Decohered One Dimensional Critical States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14221v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symmetry breaking has been a central theme in classifying quantum phases and phase transitions. Recently, this concept has been extended to the mixed states of open systems, attracting considerable attention due to the emergence of novel physics beyond closed systems. In this work, we reveal a new type of phase transition in mixed states, termed \emph{quantum} strong-to-weak spontaneous symmetry breaking (SWSSB). Using a combination of field theory calculations and large-scale matrix product state simulations, we map out the global phase diagram of the XXZ critical spin chain under local strong symmetry preserving decoherence, which features an SWSSB phase and a trivial Luttinger liquid phase, separated by a straight critical line that belongs to the boundary Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless universality class with a varying effective central charge. Importantly, we analyze this transition from two complementary perspectives: on one hand, through the behavior of order parameters that characterize the symmetry breaking; on the other hand, from a quantum information viewpoint by studying entropic quantities and the concept of quantum recoverability. Remarkably, the SWSSB transition in our case is \emph{purely quantum} in the sense that it can only be driven by tuning the Hamiltonian parameter even under arbitrary decoherence strength, fundamentally distinguishing it from the decoherence-driven SWSSB transitions extensively discussed in previous literature. Importantly, our unified theoretical framework is applicable to a broad class of one-dimensional quantum systems, including spin chains and fermionic systems, whose low-energy physics can be described by Luttinger liquid theory, under arbitrary symmetry-preserving decoherence channels. Finally, we also discuss the experimental relevance of our theory on quantum simulator platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14221v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4vs5-l54f</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 6, 040311, 16 October, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Guo, Sheng Yang, Xue-Jia Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emulation of quantum correlations by classical dynamics in a spin-1/2 Heisenberg chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19975v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We simulate the dynamical spin structure factor (DSSF) S(q,w) of the spin-1/2 Heisenberg antiferromagnetic chain using classical simulations. By employing Landau-Lifshitz Dynamics, we emulate quantum correlations through temperature-dependent corrections, including rescaling of magnetic dipoles and renormalization of exchange interactions. Our results demonstrate that the quantum-equivalent DSSF closely matches Quantum Monte-Carlo calculations for kBT/J ~ 1, extending the applicability of classical dynamics to the challenging case of gapless excitations. At higher temperatures, our simulations comply with general predictions for uncorrelated paramagnetic fluctuations in the infinite temperature limit. Entanglement witnesses derived from the quantum-equivalent DSSF act as sensitive diagnostics for the quantum-to-classical crossover. Their reliability stems from their dependence on spectral features alone, enabling classical dynamics to emulate quantum thresholds without genuine entanglement. This framework also reproduces transverse spin correlations in finite magnetic fields, in agreement with quantum simulations. Together, our results establish quantum-corrected classical dynamics as a scalable and predictive tool for interpreting scattering experiments and exploring quantum correlations in strongly correlated spin systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19975v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaebin Kim, Martin Mourigal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summing Real Time Feynman Paths of Lattice Polaron with Matrix Product States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07648v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study numerically the real time dynamics of lattice polarons by combining the Feynman path integral and the matrix product state (MPS) approach. By constructing and solving a flow equation, we show that the integrand, viewed as a multivariable function of polaron world line parameters, can be compressed as a low bond dimension MPS, thereby allowing for efficient evaluation of various dynamical observables. We establish the effectiveness of our method by benchmarking the calculated polaron spectral function in one dimension against available results. We further demonstrate its potential by presenting the polaron spectral function in two dimensions and simulating polaron diffusion in both one and two dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07648v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5sdf-fnl5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 165121 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qi Gao, Yuan Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of the charge fluctuations by nonlocal correlations close to the Mott transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13288v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the impact of nonlocal correlations on charge fluctuations in the two-dimensional single-band Hubbard model close to the Mott metal-to-insulator transition, employing the ladder dynamical vertex approximation. At half filling and for interaction strengths and temperatures where the system is in the Mott insulating phase, charge fluctuations are strongly suppressed. Under these conditions, dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) calculations predict a strong enhancement of the charge susceptibility at small (electron or hole) doping. However, these DMFT results include only the effects of purely local correlations despite the importance of nonlocal correlations in two-dimensional systems. We have, hence, carried out ladder dynamical vertex approximation (lD$\Gamma$A) simulations which allow for the inclusion of such nonlocal correlation effects while retaining the local ones of DMFT. Our lD$\Gamma$A numerical data show that close to half filling the large uniform charge susceptibility of DMFT is strongly suppressed by nonlocal fluctuations but gradually increases with (electron) doping. At a certain doping value, charge fluctuations eventually become larger in lD$\Gamma$A with respect to DMFT, indicating that the absence of nonlocal correlations underestimates the mobility of the charge carriers in this parameter regime. This metallization effect is also reflected in an enhancement of the lD$\Gamma$A kinetic and potential energies and a corresponding reduction of the (absolute value of the) lD$\Gamma$A Matsubara self-energy with respect to DMFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13288v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/n2g3-nv58</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155125 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Irakli Titvinidze, Julian Stobbe, Marvin Leusch, Georg Rohringer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Many-Body Perturbation Framework for Moir\'e Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19764v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Moir\'e superlattices host a rich variety of correlated topological states, including interaction-driven integer and fractional Chern insulators. A common approach to study interacting ground states at integer fillings is the Hartree-Fock mean-field method. However, this method neglects dynamical correlations, which often leads to an overestimation of spontaneous symmetry breaking and fails to provide quantitative descriptions of single-particle excitations. This work introduces a general many-body perturbation framework for moir\'e systems, combining all-band Hartree-Fock calculations with random phase approximation (RPA) correlation energies and $GW$ quasiparticle corrections. We apply this framework to hexagonal boron nitride aligned rhombohedral pentalayer graphene and magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene. We show that incorporating RPA correlation energy and $GW$ self-energy corrections yields phase diagrams and single-particle spectra that quantitatively align with experimental measurements. Our versatile framework provides a systematic beyond-mean-field approach applicable to generic moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19764v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Lu, Yuanfan Yang, Zhongqing Guo, Jianpeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing the Impact of Quenched Disorder on 2D Electron Wigner Solids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electron Wigner solids (WSs)1-12 provide an ideal system for understanding the competing effects of electron-electron and electron-disorder interactions, a central unsolved problem in condensed matter physics. Progress in this topic has been limited by a lack of single-defect-resolved experimental measurements as well as accurate theoretical tools to enable realistic experiment-theory comparison. Here we overcome these limitations by combining atomically-resolved scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) with quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) simulation of disordered 2D electron WSs. STM was used to image the electron density ($n_e$) dependent evolution of electron WSs in gate-tunable bilayer MoSe$_2$ devices with varying long-range ($n_\mathrm{LR}$) and short-range ($n_\mathrm{SR}$) disorder densities. These images were compared to QMC simulations using realistic disorder maps extracted from experiment, thus allowing the roles of different disorder types to be disentangled. We identify two distinct physical regimes for disordered electron WSs that depend on the magnitude of $n_\mathrm{SR}$. For $n_\mathrm{SR} \lesssim n_e$ the WS behavior is dominated by long-range disorder and features extensive mixed solid-liquid phases, a new type of re-entrant melting-crystallization, and prominent Friedel oscillations. In contrast, when $n_\mathrm{SR} \gg n_e$ these features are suppressed and a more robust amorphous WS phase emerges that persists to higher $n_e$, highlighting the importance of short-range disorder in this regime. Our work establishes a new framework for studying disordered quantum solids via a combined experimental-theoretical approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12009v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhehao Ge, Conor Smith, Zehao He, Yubo Yang, Qize Li, Ziyu Xiang, Jianghan Xiao, Wenjie Zhou, Salman Kahn, Melike Erdi, Rounak Banerjee, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Seth Ariel Tongay, Miguel A. Morales, Shiwei Zhang, Feng Wang, Michael F. Crommie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal Andreev transport through a quantum dot in a magnetic field: Interplay between Kondo, Zeeman, and Cooper-pair correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11434v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the nonlocal magnetotransport through a strongly correlated quantum dot, connected to multiple terminals consisting of two normal and one superconducting (SC) leads. Specifically, we present a comprehensive view on the interplay between the crossed Andreev reflection (CAR), the Kondo effect, and the Zeeman splitting at zero temperature in the large SC gap limit. The ground state of this network shows an interesting variety, which varies continuously with the system parameters, such as the coupling strength $\Gamma_S^{}$ between the SC lead and the quantum dot, the Coulomb repulsion $U$, the impurity level $\varepsilon_d^{}$, and the magnetic field $b$. We show, using the many-body optical theorem which is derived from the Fermi-liquid theory, that the nonlocal conductance is determined by the transmission rate of the Cooper pairs $\mathcal{T}_{\mathrm{CP}}^{} = \frac{1}{4} \sin^2 \Theta\, \sin^2 \bigl(\delta_{\uparrow}+ \delta_{\downarrow})$ and that of the Bogoliubov particles $\mathcal{T}_{\mathrm{BG}}^{}= \frac{1}{2}\sum_{\sigma} \sin^2 \delta_{\sigma}^{}$. Here, $\delta_\sigma^{}$ is the phase shift of the renormalized Bogoliubov particles, and $\Theta \equiv \cot^{-1} (\xi_d^{}/ \Gamma_S^{})$ is the Bogoliubov-rotation angle in the Nambu pseudo spin space, with $\xi_d^{} =\varepsilon_d^{}+U/2$. It is also demonstrated, using Wilson's numerical renormalization group approach, that the CAR is enhanced in the crossover region between the Kondo regime and the SC-proximity-dominated regime at zero magnetic field. The magnetic fields induce another crossover between the Zeeman-dominated regime and the SC-dominated regime. We find that the CAR is enhanced and becomes less sensitive to magnetic fields in the SC-dominated regime close to the crossover region spreading over the angular range of $\pi/4 \lesssim \Theta \lesssim 3\pi/4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11434v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.035404</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 035404 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Masashi Hashimoto, Yasuhiro Yamada, Yoichi Tanaka, Yoshimichi Teratani, Takuro Kemi, Norio Kawakami, Akira Oguri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximately-symmetric neural networks for quantum spin liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17541v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose and analyze a family of approximately-symmetric neural networks for quantum spin liquid problems. These tailored architectures are parameter-efficient, scalable, and significantly outperform existing symmetry-unaware neural network architectures. Utilizing the mixed-field toric code and PXP Rydberg Hamiltonian models, we demonstrate that our approach is competitive with the state-of-the-art tensor network and quantum Monte Carlo methods. Moreover, at the largest system sizes (N = 480 for toric code, N=1584 for Rydberg PXP), our method allows us to explore Hamiltonians with sign problems beyond the reach of both quantum Monte Carlo and finite-size matrix-product states. The network comprises an exactly symmetric block following a non-symmetric block, which we argue learns a transformation of the ground state analogous to quasiadiabatic continuation. Our work paves the way toward investigating quantum spin liquid problems within interpretable neural network architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17541v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/pgnx-11ph</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 056702 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dominik S. Kufel, Jack Kemp, DinhDuy Vu, Simon M. Linsel, Chris R. Laumann, Norman Y. Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anyon condensation in mixed-state topological order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14320v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss anyon condensation in mixed-state topological order. The phases were recently conjectured to be classified by pre-modular fusion categories. Just like anyon condensation in pure-state topological order, a bootstrap analysis shows condensable anyons are given by connected \'etale algebras. We explain how to perform generic anyon condensation including non-invertible anyons and successive condensations. Interestingly, some condensations lead to pure-state topological orders. We clarify when this happens. We also compute topological invariants of equivalence classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14320v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhysCore.8.4.072</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. Core 8, 072 (2025), 38</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ken Kikuchi, Kah-Sen Kam, Fu-Hsiang Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic study of shear viscosity and butterfly velocity for magnetic field-driven quantum criticality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10584v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the shear viscosity and butterfly velocity of a magnetic field-induced quantum phase transition in five dimensional Einstein-Maxwell-Chern-Simons theory, which is holographically dual to a class of strongly coupled quantum field theories with chiral anomalies. Our analysis reveals that the ratio of longitudinal shear viscosity to entropy density $\eta_\parallel/s$ exhibits a pronounced non-monotonic dependence on temperature $T$ when the magnetic field $B$ is slightly below the critical value $B_c$ of the quantum phase transition. In particular, it can develop a distinct minimum at an intermediate temperature. This contrasts sharply with the monotonic temperature scaling observed at and above $B_c$, where $\eta_\parallel/s$ follows the scaling $T^{2/3}$ at $B=B_c$ and transitions to $T^2$ for $B&gt;B_c$ as $T\to0$. The non-vanishing of $\eta_\parallel/s$ for $B&lt;B_c$ in the zero temperature limit suggests that it could serve as a good order parameter of the quantum phase transition. We also find that all butterfly velocities change dramatically near the quantum phase transition, and thus their derivatives with respect to $B$ can be independently used to detect the quantum critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10584v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2025)131</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 10 (2025) 131</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Kun Zhao, Li Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observing Spatial Charge and Spin Correlations in a Strongly-Interacting Fermi Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01885v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we explore two-dimensional attractive Fermi gases at the microscopic level by probing spatial charge and spin correlations in situ. Using atom-resolved continuum quantum gas microscopy, we directly observe fermion pairing and study the evolution of two- and three-point correlation functions as inter-spin attraction is increased. The precision of our measurement allows us to reveal nonlocal anticorrelations in the pair correlation function, fundamentally forbidden by the mean-field result based on Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) theory but whose existence we confirm in exact auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo calculations. We demonstrate that the BCS prediction is critically deficient not only in the superfluid crossover regime but also deep in the weakly attractive side. Guided by our measurements, we find a remarkable relation between two- and three-point correlations that establishes the dominant role of pair-correlations. Finally, leveraging local single-pair losses, we independently characterize the short-range behavior of pair correlations, via the measurement of Tan's Contact, and find excellent agreement with numerical predictions. Our measurements provide an unprecedented microscopic view into two-dimensional Fermi gases and constitute a paradigm shift for future studies of strongly-correlated fermionic matter in the continuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01885v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyprien Daix, Maxime Dixmerias, Yuan-Yao He, Joris Verstraten, Tim de Jongh, Bruno Peaudecerf, Shiwei Zhang, Tarik Yefsah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal avalanches in isolated many-body localized systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04834v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many-body localization is a profound phase of matter affecting the entire spectrum which emerges in the presence of disorder in interacting many-body systems. Recently, the stability of many-body localization has been challenged by the avalanche mechanism, in which a small thermal region can spread, destabilizing localization and leading to global thermalization of the system. A key unresolved question is the critical competition between the thermal region's influence and the disorder strength required to trigger such an avalanche. Here, we numerically investigate many-body localization stability in an isolated Heisenberg spin chain of size $L$ subjected to a disordered magnetic field. By embedding a tunable thermal region of size $P$, we analyze the system's behavior in both static and dynamical regimes using entanglement entropy and the gap ratio. Our study yields two main findings. Firstly, for strong disorder, the avalanche only occurs if the thermal region scales with system size, specifically when $P/L$ exceeds a threshold value. Secondly, at strong disorder, we identify an intermediate phase between many-body localization and ergodic behavior as $P$ increases. This intermediate phase leaves its finger print in both static and dynamic properties of the system and tends to vanish in the thermodynamic limit. Although our simulations are restricted to finite system sizes, the analysis suggests that these results hold in the thermodynamic limit for isolated many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04834v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/fvgj-byp7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155140 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Sajid, Rozhin Yousefjani, Abolfazl Bayat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-circular Raman optical activity of axial multipolar order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09237v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multipolar order, such as octupolar order, is a key concept in condensed matter physics, particularly in light of elusive hidden orders. However, its experimental identification remains challenging due to the absence of direct coupling to conventional external stimuli. In this study, we propose that dual-circular Raman scattering serves as a probe of multipolar anisotropies. By combining symmetry analysis with microscopic calculations, we demonstrate that both time-reversal-even ($\theta$-even) and time-reversal-odd ($\theta$-odd) axial multipolar phases exhibit the Raman optical activity as a direct consequence of mirror symmetry breaking. Furthermore, we demonstrated that a multipolar phonon, a three-dimensional and alternating displacement resembling the chiral phonon, plays a vital role in the proposed optical phenomena. Our findings open a pathway for identifying multipolar orders in various materials through dual-circular Raman spectroscopy as a sensitive and versatile probe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09237v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hikaru Watanabe, Rikuto Oiwa, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resource complexity of Symmetry Protected Topological phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08053v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We pursue the identification of quantum resources carried by topological order, by evaluating quantum magic, quantified through the rank-$2$ Stabilizer R\'enyi entropy $\mathcal{M}_2$, in one-dimensional systems hosting symmetry-protected topological phases (SPTP). Focusing on models with an exact duality between an SPTP and a trivial one, namely the dimerized XX and the Cluster-Ising chains, we show that dual points exhibit identical amounts of magic, even thought they belong to distinct topological sectors. A subextensive asymmetry arises only under open boundary conditions, where edge effects break the duality, but this correction is non-topological and depends on microscopic parameters. These results stand in contrast to the case of topological frustration, where delocalized excitations enhance the magic logarithmically with system size. They also complement recent analyses in the literature, showing that the total magic is largely insensitive to the presence of topological order, hence suggesting that topological order is not necessarily a genuine computational resource.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08053v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Giuseppe Catalano, Sven Benjamin Ko\v{z}i\'c, Gianpaolo Torre, Carola Ciaramelletti, Simone Paganelli, Fabio Franchini, Salvatore Marco Giampaolo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-universal Thermal Hall Responses in Fractional Quantum Hall Droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14058v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analytically compute the thermal Hall conductance (THC) of fractional quantum Hall droplets under realistic conditions that go beyond the idealized linear edge theory with conformal symmetry. Specifically, we consider finite-size effects at low temperature, nonzero self-energies of quasiholes, and general edge dispersions. We derive measurable corrections in THC that are consistent with the experimental observables. Although the quantized THC is commonly regarded as a topological invariant that is independent of edge confinement, our results show that this quantization remains robust only for arbitrary edge dispersion in the thermodynamic limit. Furthermore, the THC contributed by Abelian modes can become extremely sensitive to finite-size effects and irregular confining potentials in any realistic experimental system. In contrast, non-Abelian modes show robust THC signatures under perturbations, indicating an intrinsic stability of non-Abelian anyons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14058v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Tan, Yuzhu Wang, Xinghao Wang, Bo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning Magnetic and Electronic Properties of Double Perovskite La$_2$CoIr$_{1-x}$Ti$_x$O$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18038v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The La$_2$CoIr$_{1-x}$Ti$_x$O$_6$ double perovskite series serves as an effective platform for investigating the evolution of magnetic and electronic properties as a function of chemical pressure (doping) or hydrostatic pressure due to the interplay between the electrons correlation and spin-orbit coupling. In this study, the substitution of nonmagnetic Ti$^{4+}$ at the magnetic Ir$^{4+}$-site leads to a systematic decrease in unit cell volume keeping the monoclinic symmetry throughout, reflecting the effect of chemical pressure along with a gradual suppression of magnetic interactions. The parent compound ($x =$ 0) exhibits a ferromagnetic-like state with a Curie temperature of 92 K, which continuously evolves into an antiferromagnetic ground state upon full Ti substitution ($x =$ 1) with a Neel temperature of 14.6 K. Isothermal magnetization measurements reveal a hysteresis behavior with step-like feature at zero field, indicative of a noncollinear magnetic ordering. Additionally, the enhancement of magnetization under hydrostatic pressure on La$_2$CoIrO$_6$ suggests the presence of piezomagnetic behavior. Thermal expansion measurements on La$_2$CoIrO$_6$ highlight a coupling between spin and lattice degrees of freedom. The pressure dependence of the transition temperature in the zero-pressure limit, calculated using Ehrenfest's relation, shows good agreement with magnetization data under applied pressure. First-principles density functional theory (DFT) calculations preformed for $x =$ 0, 0.5 and 1, further reveal that strong SOC associated with Ir plays a decisive role in shaping the electronic band structure, with the insulating gap progressively widening as Ti content increases from 0.28 eV ($x =$ 0), 0.44 eV ($x =$ 0.5), and 1.01 eV ($x =$ 1). The magnetic moment decreased more than 50\% for $x =$ 0.5, showing the decrease in magnetic exchange pathways.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18038v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/w97v-k9j5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155144 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sromona Nandi, Vineeta Yadav,  Sheetal, C. S. Yadav, Bikash Das, Subhadeep Datta, Kapildeb Dolui, Rudra Sekhar Manna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong enhancement of d-wave superconductivity in an extended checkerboard Hubbard ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24415v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By employing the density-matrix renormalization group method, we study an extended checkerboard Hubbard model on the two-leg ladder, which includes an intraplaquette nearest-neighbour attraction V. The simulated results show that V plays a significant role in enhancing the d-wave superconductivity when the electron density is close to half-filling. In the homogeneous case t'=t (t and t' are the intraplaquette and interplaquette hopping integrals), large critical |Vc| is required to induce the superconducting ground state. With decreasing t', |Vc| is substantially diminished and the pair state has a nearly C4 symmetry. In the extremely inhomogeneous case t'&lt;0.2t, the system transits to the d-wave superconducting phase at V\sim-0.3t and V\sim-0.4t for U=8t and U=12t, respectively, accompanying with a shift of spin and single-particle excitations from gapless to gapped type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24415v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xichen Huang, Saisai He, Jize Zhao, Zhong-Bing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalization of Chern-Simons Wilson Loops via Flux Quantization in Cohomotopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25336v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the practice of physics model building, the process of renormalization, resummation, and anomaly cancellation is to incrementally repair initially ill-defined Lagrangian quantum field theories. Impressive as this is, one would rather have concisely defined complete theories to begin with, and understand these choices as emergent from fundamental principles. As an instructive example, we recall renormalization choices for Wilson loop observables in abelian Chern-Simons theory. Then we show that these emerge in a novel non-Lagrangian topological completion of 5D Maxwell-Chern-Simons QFT, by means of proper flux quantization in 2-Cohomotopy. This result is a modest cousin, with applications to topologically ordered quantum materials, of the more ambitious flux quantization of 11D supergravity in 4-Cohomotopy ("Hypothesis H").</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25336v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hisham Sati, Urs Schreiber</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
