<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 05:00:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Coexistence of superconductivity and excitonic pairing in a doped-biased double-layer system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The subject of the present study is the double-layer square-lattice system with the intralayer phonon modulations. We investigate the superconducting and excitonic pairings, as well as their coexistence, as functions of various physical parameters in the system. These parameters include temperature, intralayer and interlayer Coulomb interactions, the electron-phonon coupling parameter, doping and the applied electric field. The existence of superconductivity is demonstrated by considering the influence of intralayer phonons on the total charge density leading to the modification of the total energy of the electrons. Our results provides insights into the long-standing problem of the mechanism of superconductivity in high-$T_c$ cuprate superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16696v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Apinyan, M. Sahakyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiparticle Variational Quantum Eigensolver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16721v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a momentum-space based variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) framework for simulating quasiparticle excitations in interacting quantum many-body systems on near-term quantum devices. Leveraging translational invariance and other symmetries of the Hamiltonian, we reconstruct the momentum-resolved quasiparticle excitation spectrum through targeted simulation of low-lying excited states using VQE. We construct a translationally symmetric variational ansatz designed to evolve a free-fermion particle-hole excited state with definite momentum $q$ to an excited state of the interacting system at the same momentum, employing a fermionic fast Fourier transform (FFFT) circuit coupled to a Hamiltonian Variational Ansatz (HVA) circuit. Even though the particle number is not explicitly conserved in the variational ansatz, the correct quasiparticle state is reached by energetic optimization. We benchmark the performance of the proposed VQE implementation on the XXZ Hamiltonian, which maps onto the Tomonaga-Luttinger liquid in the fermionic representation. Our numerical results show that VQE can capture the low-lying excitation spectrum of the bosonic quasiparticle/two-spinon dispersion of this model at various interaction strengths. We estimate the renormalized velocity of the quasiparticles by calculating the slope of the dispersion near zero momentum using the VQE-optimized energies at different system sizes, and demonstrate that it closely matches theoretical results obtained from Bethe ansatz. Finally, we highlight extensions of our proposed VQE implementation to simulate quasiparticles in other interacting quantum many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16721v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saavanth Velury, Yuxuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excited states from local effective Hamiltonians of matrix product states and their entanglement spectrum transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solving excited states is a challenging task for interacting systems. For one-dimensional critical systems, however, excited states can be directly accessed from the eigenvectors of the local effective Hamiltonian that is constructed from the ground state obtained by variational matrix product state (MPS) optimization. Despite its numerical success, the theoretical mechanism underlying this method has remained largely unexplored. In this work, we provide a conformal field theory (CFT) perspective that helps elucidate this connection. The key insight is that this construction effectively uses a truncated basis of ground-state Schmidt vectors to represent excited states, where the contribution of each Schmidt vector can be expressed as a CFT correlation function and shown to decay with increasing Schmidt index. The CFT analysis further predicts an entanglement-spectrum transition of excited states as the ratio of the subsystem size to the total system size is varied. Our numerical results support this picture and demonstrate a reorganization of the entanglement spectrum into distinct conformal towers as this ratio changes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16746v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denise Cocchiarella, Mingru Yang, Yueshui Zhang, Mari Carmen Ba\~nuls, Hong-Hao Tu, Yuhan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakdown of adiabaticity in topological quantum liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the temporal behavior of topological quantum fluids with strong long-range couplings under slow external perturbations, whose rate $\delta$ approaches the quasi-static limit $\delta\to 0$. As expected, due to strong long-range interactions, the system lies in the mean-field universality and the density of defects for drives across the quantum critical point is adiabatic $n_{\rm exc}\propto \delta^{2}$. However, if the drive is instead terminated precisely at the edge of the topological non-trivial phase, the number of generated excitations becomes extensive $n_{\rm exc}\propto O(1)$. This result fundamentally breaks the established universal behavior observed in local topological quantum fluids and demonstrates a novel mechanism for the breakdown of adiabaticity in fermionic systems with strong long-range interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16818v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carola Ciaramelletti, Daniel Arrufat-Vicente, Simone Paganelli, Nicolo Defenu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron Hydrodynamics: Viscosity Tensor and effects of a Magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transport due to electrons in ultra-clean two dimensional systems can be hydrodynamic in nature with the momentum of the electrons being conserved in the bulk. This hydrodynamic behavior coupled with effects of Berry curvature arising from band structure can give rise to novel vortical transport coefficients relating the stress tensor to gradients in the electrostatic potential and temperature. These coefficients have been calculated in the absence of a magnetic field and have been shown to depend only on the equilibrium distribution function~\cite{Chadha_Mukerjee2024}. In this paper, we first obtain an expression for the viscosity tensor and show that the Berry curvature generates odd components of the viscosity tensor arising from the intrinsic angular momentum of the Bloch wavepackets. We calculate the viscosity tensor for a two-dimensional microscopic model of tilted Dirac cones. We next obtain the vortical coefficients and the viscosity tensor in the presence of a magnetic field and extend the Onsager relations for them to include both the magnetic field and the Berry curvature. We show that the field dependence of the coefficients manifests itself in the non-equilibrium part of the distribution function and calculate them to second order in the electron-electron scattering time. We explicitly show that the expressions we obtain are consistent with the Onsager relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17088v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anubhav Srivastava, Subroto Mukerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anyon Quasilocalization in a Quasicrystalline Toric Code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An exactly solvable model of a quantum spin liquid on a quasicrystal, akin to Kitaev's honeycomb model, was introduced in Kim \textit{et al.}, \href{https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevB.110.214438}{\text{Phys. Rev. B} \textbf{110}, 214438 (2024)}. It was shown that in contrast to the translationally invariant models, such a spin liquid stabilizes a gapped ground state with a finite irrational flux density. In this work, we analyze the strong bond-anisotropic limit of the model and demonstrate that the aperiodic lattice geometry naturally generates a hierarchy of exponentially separated coupling constants in the resulting toric code Hamiltonian. Furthermore, a perturbative magnetic field leads to anomalous localization properties where an anyonic excitation sequentially delocalizes over subsets of sites forming equipotential contours in the quasicrystal. In addition, certain background flux configurations, together with the underlying geometry, give rise to strictly localized eigenstates that remain decoupled from the rest of the spectrum. Using numerical studies, we uncover the key mechanisms responsible for this unconventional localization behavior. Our study highlights that topologically ordered phases, in the presence of geometrical constraints can lead to highly anomalous localization properties of fractionalized charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17144v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Sur, Mohammad Saad, Adhip Agarwala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Boundary Spins in the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studying boundary excitations provides a powerful approach to probe correlations in topological phases. We propose that localized spins near the ends of a Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-Hubbard chain embedded in an insulating environment can be detected experimentally using scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) combined with electron spin resonance (ESR). When the STM tip is in the contact regime, the tip-end-spin coupling realizes an effective Anderson impurity problem, giving rise to a Kondo peak at low bias. Spatially resolving the Kondo resonance width as the STM tip approaches the chain ends provides an indirect yet clear signature of these localized spins. To support this proposal, we use density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) to calculate the spin gap and spin projection of end states for chains of various lengths and interaction strengths $U$ at half-filling. In the non-interacting limit ($U=0$), we derive simple analytical expressions that reproduce the numerical results for sufficiently long chains. We also discuss how the correlated phase of the isolated chain is characterized by boundary zeros in its single-particle Green's function, and briefly comment on their localization properties in relation to the boundary spins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17173v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armando A. Aligia, Alejandro M. Lobos, Lucila Peralta Gavensky, Claudio J. Gazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical BKT dynamics in the archetypal 2D spin system Ba$_2$CuSi$_2$O$_6$Cl$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17381v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the spin dynamics in the quasi-2D spin-$1/2$ dimer compound Ba$_2$CuSi$_2$O$_6$Cl$_2$, which exhibits a magnetic field-induced Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC) of triplons. Using nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spin-lattice relaxation rate ($T_1^{-1}$) measurements combined with large-scale quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) simulations, we investigate critical fluctuations across the field-temperature phase diagram. Bridging the behavior observed in 1D and 3D systems, the $T_1^{-1}$ relaxation rate shows a pronounced peak extending well above the N\'eel temperature $T_N$, indicating strong two-dimensional Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT)-type fluctuations. A quantitative match between experimental and theoretical BEC phase boundaries validates an effective XXZ model. The study determines the intrinsic BKT transition temperature $T_{\mathrm{BKT}}$ from QMC, revealing a nearly field-independent $T_{\mathrm{BKT}}/T_N \approx 0.74$. Scaling analysis of the relaxation rate shows critical exponents consistent with 2D universality, and a narrow temperature window is identified where 2D physics dominates. These findings establish Ba$_2$CuSi$_2$O$_6$Cl$_2$ as a model system for exploring BKT dynamics in quantum magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17381v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. M. Ranjith, Maxime Dupont, Steffen Kr\"amer, Sylvain Capponi, Edmond Orignac, Nicolas Laflorencie, Nobuyuki Kurita, Hidekazu Tanaka, Mladen Horvati\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Anyonic Exchange Phases Using Two-Dimensional Coherent Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Identifying experimental signatures of anyons, which exhibit fractional exchange statistics, remains a central challenge in the study of two-dimensional topologically ordered systems. Previous theoretical work has shown that the threshold behavior in linear response spectroscopy can reveal the fractional exchange statistics between an anyon and its antiparticle. In this work, we extend this framework to nonlinear, two-dimensional coherent spectroscopy. We demonstrate by analyzing time-ordered four-point correlation functions that the threshold behavior of nonlinear response functions encodes the fractional statistics between general pairs of anyons that can combine to any composite topological charge. This feature in particular provides a powerful probe for unambiguously distinguishing non-Abelian anyons, which can form multiple composite charges with distinct nontrivial braid statistics. Our approach is validated using numerical simulations that are consistent with the correct fractional exchange statistics for both the Abelian anyons in the toric code and non-Abelian Ising anyons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17420v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nico Kirchner, Wonjune Choi, Frank Pollmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermalization of exact quantum many-body scars in spin-1 XY chain under perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum many-body scars are special eigenstates that violate the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis while residing at finite energy density along with thermalizing eigenstates. The spin-1 XY model is known to host a family of such exceptional states originating from long-lived quasiparticle excitations that exhibit anomalously low entanglement entropy and long-time periodic revivals, resulting in weak ergodicity breaking. We study the stability of these scarred states against typical U(1) symmetry preserving perturbations in the XY chain. While perturbation theory can describe the deformed scar states at small system sizes, finite-size scaling of the perturbation matrix elements indicates that the scars ultimately thermalize in larger chains. Nonetheless, we demonstrate that the long-range order associated with the scars decays under the perturbation, and we estimate the relaxation timescale of oscillatory dynamics in certain local observables to be of order $\lambda^{-2}$, where $\lambda$ is the perturbation strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17476v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himadri Halder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Chern insulator edges: crystalline effects and optical measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Edge states of chiral topologically ordered phases are commonly described by chiral Luttinger liquids, effective theories that are exact only in the hydrodynamic limit. Motivated by recent bulk observations of fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in two-dimensional materials and by synthetic realizations in ultracold atoms, we revisit this framework and quantify deviations from the hydrodynamic limit due to lattice effects. Using a combination of analytical arguments and numerical simulations, we disentangle universal from nonuniversal edge properties. We outline experimental probes in excitonic FCIs and in ultracold atom systems, and in particular propose time-resolved edge spectroscopy to directly access the predicted exponents and velocities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17494v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Qi Wang, Johannes Motruk, Andrey Grankin, Mohammad Hafezi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Evolution of Multi-Party Entanglement Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the real-time dynamics of multi-party entanglement signals in chaotic quantum many-body systems including but not necessarily restricted to holographic conformal field theories. We find that scrambling dynamics generates multiparty entanglement with rich structure including: (a) qualitatively different dynamical behaviours for different signals, likely reflecting different dynamics for different kinds of entanglement patterns, (b) discontinuities indicating dynamical phase transitions in the entanglement structure, (c) transient and non-monotonic multiparty entanglement, and (d) periods during which the extensive entanglement of some regions is entirely multipartite. Our main technical tool is the membrane theory of entanglement dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16729v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vijay Balasubramanian, Hanzhi Jiang, Simon F. Ross</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Quantum Computational Science: A Perspective from Block-Encodings and Polynomial Transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16738v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Significant developments made in quantum hardware and error correction recently have been driving quantum computing towards practical utility. However, gaps remain between abstract quantum algorithmic development and practical applications in computational sciences. In this Perspective article, we propose several properties that scalable quantum computational science methods should possess. We further discuss how block-encodings and polynomial transformations can potentially serve as a unified framework with the desired properties. We present recent advancements on these topics including construction and assembly of block-encodings, and various generalizations of quantum signal processing (QSP) algorithms to perform polynomial transformations. We also highlight the scalability of QSP methods on parallel and distributed quantum architectures. Promising applications in simulation and observable estimation in chemistry, physics, and optimization problems are presented. We hope this Perspective serves as a gentle introduction of state-of-the-art quantum algorithms to the computational science community, and inspires future development on scalable quantum computational science methodologies that bridge theory and practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16738v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin J. Joven, Elin Ranjan Das, Joel Bierman, Aishwarya Majumdar, Masoud Hakimi Heris, Yuan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the degeneracy of bound magnon crystals from magnetic and thermodynamic features of the spin-1/2 Heisenberg octahedral chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17296v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic, thermodynamic, and magnetocaloric properties of a spin-1/2 Heisenberg octahedral chain with three distinct exchange interactions are investigated in an external magnetic field using the variational method, extended localized-magnon approach, and exact diagonalization. Variational arguments rigorously establish two distinct fragmented phases in the frustrated regime. In the former phase all four spins of each square plaquette form a collective plaquette singlet, whereas in the latter phase two dimer singlets are formed along diagonals of each square plaquette. These bound two-magnon states, supplemented with three localized one-magnon states, enable us to elaborate a generalized localized-magnon theory that is applicable in a frustrated regime across the entire field range as confirmed by comparison with exact diagonalization data. The concept of localized magnons provides a consistent description of low-temperature magnetization curves featuring intermediate one-fifth and three-fifths plateaus, which intersect each other at temperature-independent crossing points determined by the relative degeneracies of competing bound-magnon phases. Field variations of the specific heat reveal a pronounced double-peak structure near each field-driven transition with peak heights depending on the relative degeneracies of the respective bound-magnon states. Our results demonstrate that the system supports highly efficient cooling via adiabatic demagnetization, making it a promising candidate for magnetocaloric refrigeration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17296v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jozef Strecka, Michal Nemcik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal Growth and Physical Properties of Orthorhombic Kagome Lattice Magnets $R$Fe$_6$Ge$_6$ ($R$=Y, Tb, Dy)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17398v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kagome magnets represent a promising class of materials that exhibit intriguing electronic and magnetic properties, and they have recently garnered significant attention. While most kagome-lattice compounds are hexagonal, here we report the single-crystal growth and physical property measurements of similar compounds $R$Fe$_6$Ge$_6$ ($R$ = Y, Dy, Tb), which crystallize in an orthorhombic structure. The structure can be derived from a hexagonal prototype $R$Fe$_3$Ge$_2$ by replacing every other $R$ atom with a covalent Ge$_2$ dimer. Ordering of the latter makes the structure orthorhombic the kagome net slightly distorted, and the three Fe sites formally inequivalent. The iron and rare-earth sublattices order independently: the Fe moments order above 400 K having, with ferromagnetic Kagome planes stacked antiferromagnetically, while the rare-earth moments order below 9 K. While TbFe$_6$Ge$_6$ exhibits a single magnetic ordering transition associated with the Tb atoms, DyFe$_6$Ge$_6$ shows two distinct magnetic phase transitions, which are strongly influenced by crystal electric field effects on the Dy$^{3+}$ ions. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations show that the ferromagnetic ordering of the Fe planes is driven by a high density of states at the Fermi energy. They also reveals three dramatically different structural energy scales: $R$ and Ge$_2$ form alternating 1D chains perpendicular to the kagome planes, and violating this alternation incurs a huge energy cost. Aligning these chains is less costly, and actual 2D order of anti-aligned chains costs very little. These compounds represent a unique class of materials, offering new possibilities to investigate the interplay between the distinct crystal lattice geometry and the underlying electronic and magnetic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17398v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijeet Nayak, Sk Jamaluddin, Fan Wu, Emily Rapp, Resham Babu Regmi, Mohamed El Gazzah, Bence G. M\'arkus, L\'aszl\'o Forr\'o, Madhav P. Ghimire, Allen Oliver, Kateryna Foyevtsova, Igor I. Mazin, Nirmal J. Ghimire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure-Induced B1 to B2 Phase Transition in CeN Studied by ab initio Correlation Matrix Renormalization Theory Calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14085v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We apply correlation matrix renormalization theory (CMRT) to cerium nitride (CeN) under pressure. For B1 (NaCl-type) phase, CMRT gives an equation of state consistent with ambient pressure experiments. It produces electronic density-of-state (DOS) characterized by a sharp 4f quasi-particle resonance peak pinned at the Fermi level and two subbands formed by strong hybridization between the localized Ce-4f electrons and the itinerant Ce-5d and N-2p electrons below the Fermi level, consistent with XPS experiments. Upon compression, CMRT predicts a first-order B1 to B2 (CsCl-type) transition with ~11% volume collapse in agreement with experiments. Across the transition, the 4f spectral weight broadens, the 4f orbital occupancy increases, and the hybridization with conduction states enhances, signaling a crossover from partially localized to more itinerant 4f behavior. These features are in excellent agreement with experimental observations, demonstrating that CMRT provides a parameter-free description and prediction of correlation-driven structural and electronic transitions in rare-earth compounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14085v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Liu, Jianhua Zhang, Yongxin Yao, Kai-Ming Ho, Cai-Zhuang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise Electrometry of Polar and Dielectric Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.09315v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A qubit sensor with an electric dipole moment acquires an additional contribution to its depolarization rate when it is placed in the vicinity of a polar or dielectric material as a consequence of electrical noise arising from polarization fluctuations in the latter. Here, we characterize this relaxation rate as a function of experimentally tunable parameters such as sample-probe distance, probe-frequency, and temperature, and demonstrate that it offers a window into dielectric properties of insulating materials over a wide range of frequencies and length scales. We discuss the experimental feasibility of our proposal and illustrate its ability to probe a variety of phenomena, ranging from collective polar excitations to phase transitions and disorder-dominated physics in relaxor ferroelectrics. Our proposal paves the way for a novel table-top probe of polar and dielectric materials in a parameter regime complementary to existing tools and techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.09315v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Sahay, Pavel A. Volkov, Satcher Hsieh, Eric Parsonnet, Lane W. Martin, Ramamoorthy Ramesh, Norman Y. Yao, Shubhayu Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of electronic correlations on the superconductivity of high-pressure CeH$_9$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12506v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Rare-earth superhydrides have attracted considerable attention because of their high critical superconducting temperature under extreme pressures. They are known to have localized valence electrons, implying strong electronic correlations. However, such many-body effects are rarely included in first-principles studies of rare-earth superhydrides because of the complexity of their high-pressure phases. In this work, we use a combined density functional theory and dynamical mean-field theory approach to study both electrons and phonons in the prototypical rare-earth superhydride CeH$_9$, shedding light on the impact of electronic correlations on its critical temperature for phonon-mediated superconductivity. Our findings indicate that electronic correlations result in a larger electronic density at the Fermi level, a bigger superconducting gap, and softer vibrational modes associated with hydrogen atoms. Together, the inclusion of these correlation signatures increases the Migdal-Eliashberg superconducting critical temperature from 47 K to 96 K, close to the measured 95 K. Our results reconcile experimental observations and theoretical predictions for CeH$_9$ and herald a path towards the quantitative modeling of phonon-mediated superconductivity for interacting electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12506v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyu Chen, Yao Wei, Bartomeu Monserrat, Jan M. Tomczak, Samuel Ponc\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity in multi-qubit and many-body systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22246v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Characterizing complexity and criticality in quantum systems requires diagnostics that are both computationally tractable and physically insightful. We introduce a measure of quantum state complexity for n-qubit systems, defined as the divergence between the Shannon or von Neumann entropy of the computational basis distribution and the second-order R\'enyi entropy. This quantity is particularly powerful as the latter R\'enyi entropy is directly related to state purity, linear entropy, and the inverse participation ratio, providing a clear physical grounding. While other R\'enyi orders could be used, the second order offers a deep and established connection to these key physical quantities. We first validate the measure in canonical noise channels, showing it peaks at the boundary between quantum and classical regimes. We then demonstrate its power in many-body physics. For systems exhibiting a many-body localization transition - including deformed random matrix ensembles and a disordered Heisenberg spin chain - the complexity measure reliably signals the crossover from integrable/localized to quantum-chaotic/ergodic phases. Crucially, the maximum complexity occurs in the non-ergodic yet extended states at the transition, precisely capturing the critical region where the system is neither fully localized nor thermalized. Furthermore, within the chaotic phase, the measure correlates with the survival probability of local excitations, revealing a spectrum of thermalization properties. Our results establish that the entropic complexity is a simple, versatile, and effective probe for identifying nontrivial quantum regimes and transitions giving a new and alternative insight into such systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22246v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imre Varga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerically "exact" charge transport dynamics in a dissipative electron-phonon model rationalizing the success of the transient localization scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14447v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Optical conductivity in molecular semiconductors is suppressed in the terahertz region, featuring the displaced Drude peak that reflects carriers' transient localization (TL) by slow intermolecular vibrations. Meanwhile, recent computations in minimal models evidence optical-conductivity enhancements below the characteristic vibrational frequency, which cannot be captured by the TL phenomenology. These models assume that the carrier's hopping amplitude is modulated by a single undamped vibration. The modulation is, however, by many low-frequency modes, whose net effect can be approximated using a few effective damped oscillators. Here, we employ the dissipaton equations of motion (DEOM) method to compute the finite-temperature real-time current autocorrelation function in a one-dimensional model with Brownian-oscillator spectral density of nonlocal carrier-phonon interaction. We exploit the dissipaton algebra to handle the phonon-assisted current, reduce the method's computational requirements by working in momentum space, and confirm that numerically stable transport dynamics are virtually independent of a specific DEOM closing scheme. With increasing damping, we find that DEOM optical-conductivity profiles become increasingly qualitatively similar to TL predictions. For parameters representative of room-temperature hole transport in single-crystal rubrene, we conclude that the TL phenomenology is established already in the underdamped-oscillator regime. Reasonable variations in the damping constant weakly affect the carrier mobility, which remains within experimental bounds. Overall, our results strongly suggest that optical-conductivity enhancements at very low frequencies are artifacts of the assumed delta-like phonon spectrum and rationalize the success of the TL phenomenology in describing experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14447v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0299359</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 163, 194116 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Veljko Jankovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genuine multi-entropy, dihedral invariants and Lifshitz theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00593v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multi-invariants are local-unitary invariants of state replicas introduced as potential probes of multipartite entanglement and correlations in quantum many-body systems. In this paper, we investigate two multi-invariants for tripartite pure states, namely multi-entropy and dihedral invariant. We compute the (genuine) multi-entropy for Lifshitz groundstates, and obtain its analytical continuation to noninteger values of R\'enyi index. We show that the genuine multi-entropy can be expressed in terms of mutual information and logarithmic negativity, a relation that also holds for stabilizer states. For general tripartite pure states, we demonstrate that dihedral invariants are related to R\'enyi reflected entropies. In particular, we show that the dihedral permutations of replicas are equivalent to the reflected construction, or alternatively to the realignment of density matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00593v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Berthi\`ere, Paul Gaudin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From single-particle to many-body chaos in Yukawa--SYK: theory and a cavity-QED proposal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04762v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding how quantum systems transition from integrable to fully chaotic behavior remains a central open problem in physics. The Sachdev--Ye--Kitaev (SYK) model provides a paradigmatic framework for studying many-body chaos and holography, yet it captures only the strongly correlated limit, leaving intermediate regimes unexplored. Here, we investigate the Yukawa--SYK (YSYK) model, where bosonic fields mediate random fermionic interactions, and demonstrate that it naturally bridges single-particle and many-body chaos. Using spectral and dynamical chaos markers, we perform a comprehensive finite-size characterization of the YSYK model. We show that the interaction strength acts as a tunable control parameter interpolating between the SYK$_2$ and SYK$_4$ limits, and introduce a framework enabling direct and quantitative comparison with these benchmark models. In the intermediate regimes, we uncover distinct dynamical regimes marked by partial ergodicity breaking, prethermalization plateaus, and incomplete scrambling. Finally, we propose a feasible optical-cavity implementation of the YSYK model using ultra-cold atoms. Our results establish the YSYK model as a unifying platform connecting single-particle and many-body chaos, paving the way for experimental observation of these phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04762v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Pascual Solis, Alex Windey, Soumik Bandyopadhyay, Andrea Legramandi, Philipp Hauke</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
