<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing Spin Hamiltonians of 2D Gutzwiller-Projected Wavefunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15034v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We apply the correlation matrix Hamiltonian reconstruction technique to the two-dimensional Gutzwiller-projected Fermi sea and {\pi}-flux states on finite-sized square and triangular lattices. Our results indicate no spin Hamiltonian with simple local interaction terms stabilizes such states for finite system sizes. We develop a quantitative assessment of the importance of local interactions to the stabilization of these liquid states. Lastly, we systematically assess arguments for the origin of local terms driving a Gutzwiller-projected ground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15034v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Z. Brito, J. B. Marston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Orbital-Selective Flat Bands in Transition-Metal Oxychlorides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flat electronic bands, which amplify electron correlations by quenching kinetic energy, provide an ideal foundation for exotic quantum phases. However, prevailing strategies -- including geometrically frustrated lattices, moire superlattices and heavy-fermion physics -- suffer from inherent trade-offs among robustness, tunability and orbital selectivity, limiting their broad applicability. Here, we unveil an intrinsic orbital-selective flat-band mechanism in the van der Waals materials NbOCl2 and TaOCl2, directly observed by angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and understood through density functional theory (DFT) and Wannier analysis. Crucially, we experimentally demonstrate that this momentum-independent flat band exhibits remarkable robustness, surviving from the bulk crystal down to the few-layer limit at room temperature. Our theoretical analysis traces its origin to the hybridization between Nb-dz2 orbital chains and the Lieb-like dx2-y2 sublattice, which is further reinforced by Peierls dimerization. Our findings not only establish transition-metal oxychlorides as a robust and tunable platform for flat-band-driven correlated phases under ambient conditions, but also uncover a new orbital-selective design principle for realizing flat bands in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15080v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyu Luo, Ludovica Zullo, Sahaj Patel, Dongjin Oh, Qian Song, Asish K. Kundu, Anil Rajapitamahuni, Elio Vescovo, Natalia Olszowska, Rafal Kurleto, Dawid Wutke, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Riccardo Comin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unusual critical points between atomic insulating phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a class of quantum phase transitions between featureless bosonic atomic insulators in $(2+1)$ dimensions, where each phase exhibits neither topological order nor protected edge modes. Despite their lack of topology, these insulators may be ``obstructed'' in the sense that their Wannier centers are not pinned to the physical atomic sites. These insulators represent distinct phases, as no symmetry-preserving adiabatic path connects them. Surprisingly, we find that the critical point between these insulators can host a conformally invariant state described by quantum electrodynamics in $(2+1)$ dimensions (QED$_3$). The emergent electrodynamics at the critical point can be stabilized if the embedding of the microscopic lattice symmetries suppresses the proliferation of monopoles, suggesting that even transitions between trivial phases can harbor rich and unexpected physics. We analyze the mechanism behind this phenomenon, discuss its stability against perturbations, and explore the embedding of lattice symmetries into the continuum through anomaly matching. In all the models we analyze, we confirm that the QED$_3$ is indeed emergeable, in the sense that it is realizable from a local lattice Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15111v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunchao Zhang, T. Senthil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-Spin Interactions as a Route to Multiple-Q Topological Magnetic Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the role of four-spin interactions in stabilizing exotic multiple-$Q$ topological spin textures and demonstrate their ability to realize a skyrmion crystal. While such higher-order interactions are known to be important, their intricate nature makes systematic model construction significantly challenging. To address this issue, we develop a theoretical framework that connects microscopic real-space four-spin couplings to their effective interactions in momentum space, providing a clear route to engineer target magnetic phases. Applying this framework to a frustrated Heisenberg model with designed four-spin interactions, we identify the stabilization of the zero-field skyrmion crystal with a topological number of two via simulated annealing. Furthermore, our momentum-space analysis reveals the intrinsic mechanism by which the well-known ring-exchange interaction also favors the skyrmion crystal. Our findings not only present a concrete model for a higher-order skyrmion crystal but also offer a general methodology for understanding and designing a wide range of complex multiple-$Q$ magnetic orders driven by multi-spin interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15158v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Okigami, Satoru Hayami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Types of Non-Fermi-Liquid Fixed Point for a Triplet Quantum Impurity in a Cubic Metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In cubic metals, a local, magnetic moment with a triplet ground state coupled to $\Gamma_8$ conduction electrons can give rise to various non-Fermi liquid (NFL) quantum critical behaviors. To date, only those exchange couplings have been studied that are spherically symmetric already in the high-temperature, local moment regime. Namely, only the effects of potential scattering, spin exchange and quadrupolar exchange couplings were considered, and two types of NFL fixed points have been identified. However, in cubic symmetry, six independent exchange couplings can be present in the Hamiltonian: in addition to the spherically symmetric potential scattering and spin exchange, there is a spherical symmetry breaking, dipolar exchange interaction, and three spherical symmetry breaking, quadrupolar terms. While all of them flow to fixed points where rotational invariance is recovered, we found that one of the quadrupolar couplings flows to a so far unidentified NFL fixed point. We derive the cubic symmetry allowed exchanged couplings, solve them with the numerical renormalization group, and present three types of NFL excitation, one of which is novel, at least in the context of a quantum impurity with a triplet ground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15163v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna I. T\'oth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic destruction of magnetic order in a quantum Ising chain with oscillating transverse field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15224v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamic response of magnetic domain walls in low-lying excited states of an Ising chain to an oscillating transverse field. Based on the exact instantaneous eigenstates, we find that when the frequency of the external field is in off-resonant regions, the domain wall exhibits Bloch oscillation, maintaining the magnetic order. However, the magnetic order is destroyed when the field is at resonant frequency. Numerical simulations of the dynamics of magnetization and entanglement entropy for initial states with single and double domain walls accord with the predictions. These findings reveal the nontrivial effect of a monochromatic electromagnetic field on quantum spin dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15224v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. S. Ma, Z. Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic fluctuations and anisotropy in UTe2: a multi-orbital study based on GGA+U and RPA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pressure-induced changes in the magnetic and superconducting properties of a spin-triplet superconductor candidate UTe2 have attracted considerable interest, underscoring the need for microscopic theoretical insight. In this paper, we investigate magnetic fluctuations and their anisotropy at ambient pressure and under pressure using density functional theory (DFT) combined with the random phase approximation (RPA). For each pressure, we perform DFT+U calculations for several values of the Coulomb interaction U, construct a 72-orbital periodic Anderson model, and calculate magnetic susceptibilities with use of the RPA. For U = 2 eV, the Fermi surfaces have a quasi-two-dimensional shape, antiferromagnetic fluctuations develop with the wave vector along the a* axis, and the magnetic anisotropy follows $\chi^b &gt; \chi^a &gt; \chi^c$. The antiferromagnetic fluctuations are suppressed under pressure because of a reduced density of states at the Fermi level, while the magnetic anisotropy is weakened. In contrast, for U = 1 eV, where Fermi surfaces are more three-dimensional, antiferromagnetic fluctuations with Q2 = 0.22 b* appear, accompanied by anisotropy $\chi^a &gt; \chi^c &gt; \chi^b$, consistent with experiments. Under pressure, antiferromagnetic fluctuations around Q2 are enhanced, the magnetic wave vector tilts slightly toward the a* direction due to Fermi-surface distortion, and the magnetic anisotropy is suppressed. These results demonstrate that the pressure evolution of magnetism in UTe2 is governed by the momentum-space distribution of U-5f states and the density of states at the Fermi level, providing a microscopic basis for understanding the magnetic and superconducting properties of UTe2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15322v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Makoto Shimizu, Youichi Yanase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subdimensional entanglement entropy: from virtual response to mixed-state holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entanglement entropy (EE) serves as a key diagnostic of quantum phases and phase transitions through bipartitions of the full system. However, recent studies on various topological phases of matter show that EE from bipartitions alone cannot effectively distinguish geometric from topological contributions. Motivated by this limitation, we introduce the \textit{subdimensional entanglement entropy} (SEE), defined for lower-dimensional \textit{subdimensional entanglement subsystems} (SESs), as a response theory characterizing many-body systems via \textit{virtual} deformations of SES geometry and topology. Analytical calculations for cluster states, discrete Abelian gauge theories, and fracton orders reveal distinct subleading SEE terms that sharply differentiate geometric and topological responses. Viewing the reduced density matrix on an SES as a mixed state, we establish a correspondence between stabilizers and mixed-state symmetries, identifying \textit{strong} and \textit{weak} classes. For SESs with nontrivial SEE, weak symmetries act as \textit{transparent patch operators} of the strong ones, forming robust \textit{transparent composite symmetries} (TCSs) that remain invariant under finite-depth quantum circuits and yield \textit{strong-to-weak spontaneous symmetry breaking} (SW-SSB). By bridging entanglement, mixed-state and categorical symmetries, holographic principles of topological order, and geometric-topological responses, SEE provides a unified framework that invites further theoretical and numerical exploration of correlated quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15766v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng-Yuan Li, Peng Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry of common semiconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum geometric properties of typical diamond-type (C, Si, Ge) and zincblende-type (GaAs, InP, etc) semiconductors are investigated by means of the $sp^{3}s^{\ast}$ tight-binding model, which allows to calculate the quantum metric of the valence band states throughout the entire Brillouin zone. The global maximum of the metric is at the $\Gamma$ point, but other differential geometric properties like Ricci scalar, Ricci tensor, and Einstein tensor are found to vary significantly in the momentum space, indicating a highly distorted momentum space manifold. The momentum integration of the quantum metric further yields the gauge-invariant part of the spread of valence band Wannier function, whose value agrees well with that experimentally extracted from an optical sum rule of the dielectric function. Furthermore, the dependence of these geometric properties on the energy gap offers a way to quantify the quantum criticality of these common semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15853v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Porlles, Wei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Order Without Band Topology in Moir\'e Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15027v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The discovery of zero-field fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in moir\'e materials has attracted intense interest in the interplay between topology and correlations. Here, we demonstrate that fractionalized topological order can emerge under realistic conditions even within a topologically trivial moir\'e band. By projecting long-range Coulomb interactions into a trivial band of twisted multilayer graphene, we identify a set of incompressible FCI ground states exhibiting fractional quantized Hall conductance. Their Laughlin-like behavior is further confirmed through the particle-cut entanglement spectrum. We trace the origin of this phase to the strongly inhomogeneous distribution of quantum geometry within the moir\'e Brillouin zone, which reshapes interaction effects independently of the band topology. Extending this heuristic quantum geometric mechanism, we demonstrate that similarly unexpected Laughlin-like FCIs can also be stabilized in higher-Chern-number moir\'e bands under experimentally accessible conditions. Our results establish realistic scenarios under which many-body topological order can emerge independently of single-particle band topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15027v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui Liu, Raul Perea-Causin, Zhao Liu, Emil J. Bergholtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity suppression and bilayer decoupling in Pr substituted YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15078v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The mechanism behind superconductivity suppression induced by Pr substitutions in YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$ (YBCO) has been a mystery since its discovery: in spite of being isovalent to Y$^{3+}$ with a small magnetic moment, it is the only rare-earth element that has a dramatic impact on YBCO's superconducting properties. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and DFT+$U$ calculations, we uncover how Pr substitution modifies the low-energy electronic structure of YBCO. Contrary to the prevailing Fehrenbacher-Rice (FR) and Liechtenstein-Mazin (LM) models, the low energy electronic structure contains no signature of any $f$-electron hybridization or new states. Yet, strong electron doping is observed primarily on the antibonding Fermi surface. Meanwhile, we reveal major electronic structure modifications to Cu-derived states with increasing Pr substitution: a pronounced CuO$_2$ bilayer decoupling and an enhanced CuO chain hopping, implying indirect electron-release pathways beyond simple 4$f$ state ionization. Our results challenge the long-standing FR/LM mechanism and establish Pr substituted YBCO as a potential platform for exploring correlation-driven phenomena in coupled 1D-2D systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15078v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinming Yang, Zheting Jin, Siqi Wang, Camilla Moir, Mingyu Xu, Brandon Gunn, Xian Du, Zhibo Kang, Keke Feng, Makoto Hashimoto, Donghui Lu, Jessica McChesney, Shize Yang, Wei-Wei Xie, Alex Frano, M. Brian Maple, Sohrab Ismail-Beigi, Yu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open system dynamics in local Lindbladians with chaotic spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15193v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the physical consequences of having a spectrum that satisfies random matrix theory (RMT) for generic Lindbladians, and compare its consequences for spatially local and completely random Lindblad dynamics in one spatial dimension. We find that Lindbladians whose spectrum is described by RMT exhibit quasi-universal early-time dynamics for quantities non-linear in the density matrix, in the sense that for generic, highly entangled initial states, the early time evolution is independent of the choice of initial state. We numerically investigate how locality generically imposes constraints on the size-dependence of Lindblad eigenoperators. This size dependence implies that linear observables, such as expectation values of local operators, are highly sensitive to eigenmodes outside the bulk of the spectrum in the thermodynamic limit, and plays a central role in limiting operator growth in the presence of dissipation. We find that when single-site dissipation dominates, an operator's decoherence scales approximately linearly with its Pauli weight, even in the presence of 2-site jump operators. When two-site only dissipation dominates, however, this generic trend in operator size can be violated, leading to long-lived high Pauli-weight operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15193v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanket Chirame, Fiona J. Burnell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Moire Matter? Critical Moire Dependence with Quantum Fluctuations in Graphene Based Integer and Fractional Chern Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15309v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rhombohedral multilayer graphene has emerged as a powerful platform for investigating flat-band-driven correlated phenomena, yet most aspects remain not understood. In this work, we systematically study the moire-dependent band topology in rhombohedral hexalayer graphene. For the first time we demonstrate that the moire twist angle plays a crucial role in the formation of the moire Chern insulators in rhombohedral hexalayer graphene/hexagonal boron nitride (RHG/hBN) moire superlattices. In the moire-distant regime at filling factor v = 1, only systems with a twist angle {\theta} &lt; 1.1{\deg} exhibit an integer moire Chern insulator, while the fractional Chern insulator at v = 2/3 requires smaller twist angle to be stabilized. Our theoretical modelling, which includes quantum fluctuations and exact diagonalization results, suggests that mean-field theory, which has been widely adopted, does not explain the twist-angle dependence of the v = 1 phase diagram, and that correlation effects are crucial. Moreover, we realize two distinct stacking configurations ( /Xi=0 and /Xi=1) between graphene and hBN, and find that both cases can yield a Chern insulator at v = 1. Our experimental work upends the current mean-field paradigm, illuminates how quantum fluctuations and moir\'e effects shape the RHG/hBN phase diagram, and paves the way for future understanding and engineering of topological correlated states in rhombohedral graphene moire systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15309v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Huo, Wenxuan Wang, Jian Xie, Yves H. Kwan, Jonah Herzog-Arbeitman, Zaizhe Zhang, Qiu Yang, Min Wu, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Kaihui Liu, Nicolas Regnault, B. Andrei Bernevig, Xiaobo Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement complexification transition driven by a single non-Hermitian impurity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15370v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While non-Hermitian bulk systems and their sensitivity to boundary conditions have been extensively studied, how a non-Hermitian boundary affects the entanglement structure of Hermitian critical systems remains largely unexplored. Here we present a fully analytical framework by exactly solving a Hermitian gapless chain with a single non-Hermitian impurity acting as a non-Hermitian boundary. When the entanglement cut is placed at the impurity, we uncover a sharp \emph{entanglement complexification transition}: the logarithmic entanglement entropy retains its scaling form, but the effective central charge evolves from real to complex values, accompanied by a spectral collapse of the correlation matrix. We demonstrate that the real regime follows analytic continuation from a unitary defect conformal field theory (CFT), whereas the complex regime lies entirely beyond this framework. For the latter, we derive an analytical formula in perfect agreement with numerics. Our results reveal that a single non-Hermitian impurity can drive a Hermitian critical system into a nonunitary defect-CFT phase, establishing a rare analytically solvable platform for boundary non-Hermiticity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15370v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yao Zhou, Peng Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Quantum Hall Wedding Cakes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work investigates the coexistence of distinct topologically ordered phases within a single setup. We demonstrate this concept through tensor network simulations of the Hofstadter-Bose-Hubbard model under a spatially modulated chemical potential. Focusing on cylindrical geometries, we realize regions exhibiting the Laughlin-1/2 phase and its particle-hole conjugate, and confirm their topological character via the local St\v{r}eda's response and Laughlin's flux insertion protocol. Our approach offers a new pathway for experimentally and numerically charting entire phase diagrams within a single system, possibly eliminating the need for independent parameter scans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15472v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chlo\'e Van Bastelaere, Felix A. Palm, Botao Wang, Nathan Goldman, Laurens Vanderstraeten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Truncated Hankel Correlator Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15500v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new method to approximate Euclidean correlation functions by exponential sums. The Truncated Hankel Correlator (THC) method builds a Hankel matrix from the full correlator data available and truncates the eigenspectrum of said Hankel matrix. It proceeds by applying the Prony generalised eigenvalue method to the thus obtained low-rank approximation. A large number of algebraic correlator analysis methods including (block) Prony (and equivalently (block) Lanczos) and the generalised eigenvalue problem (GEVP) can be reproduced as sub-optimal special cases of the THC method. Weights, for instance inverse square errors, can be included in the analysis, so that the result has a close to optimal $\chi^2$-value. This makes the THC method very similar in spirit to a closed form solution to multi-state fits, naturally including the case of matrix-valued correlators. We show that, in general, finding approximations better than those provided by the THC method is exponentially hard in the number of exponentials. Moreover, the THC method is robust against noise and requires comparably little human oversight. Finally, when applied to symmetric data, the obtained energy spectrum is guaranteed to be symmetric up to machine precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15500v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johann Ostmeyer, Carsten Urbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of Dynamical Heterogeneity in a Supercooled Magnetic Monopole Fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00460v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dynamical heterogeneity, in which transitory local fluctuations occur in the conformation and dynamics of constituent particles, is widely hypothesized to be essential to evolution of supercooled liquids into the glass state. Yet its microscopic spatiotemporal phenomenology has remained unobservable in virtually all molecular glass forming liquids. Because recent theoretical advances predict that corresponding dynamical heterogeneity could occur in supercooled magnetic monopole fluids, we searched for such phenomena in Dy2Ti2O7. By measuring its microsecond-resolved spontaneous magnetization fluctuations $M(t,T)$ we discovered a sharp bifurcation in monopole noise characteristics below $T \approx 1500$ mK, with the appearance of powerful spontaneous monopole current bursts. This intense dynamics emerges upon entering the supercooled monopole fluid regime, reaches maximum strength near $T \approx 750$ mK and then collapses along with coincident loss of ergodicity below $T \lesssim 500$ mK. Moreover, the four-point dynamical susceptibility $\chi_4(T, t)$ is determined directly from temperature dependence of correlations in $M(t,T)$, it evolves as predicted when dynamical heterogeneity is present, clearly revealing its simultaneously diverging length and time scales, $\xi(T)$. and $\tau_4(T)$. This overall phenomenology greatly expands our empirical knowledge of supercooled monopole fluids and, more generally, demonstrates direct detection of the time sequence, magnitude, statistics and correlations of dynamical heterogeneity, access to which may greatly accelerate fundamental vitrification studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00460v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jahnatta Dasini, Chaia Carroll, Hiroto Takahashi, Jack Murphy, Chun-Chih Hsu, Sudarshan Sharma, Catherine Dawson, Fabian Jerzembeck, Stephen J. Blundell, Graeme Luke, J. C. S\'eamus Davis, Jonathan Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct amplitude mode dynamics upon resonant and off-resonant excitation across the charge density wave energy gap in LaTe3 investigated by time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13604v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-equilibrium states generated by ultrafast laser pulses are characterized by specific phenomena that are not accessible in static measurements. Previous time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (TARPES) studies on rare-earth tritelluride materials have revealed the laser-driven melting of the charge density wave order as well as its collective amplitude mode excitation. Variation of the excess energy deposited by optical pumping in the material promises pathways to control the dynamic material response. To this end, we use an optical parametric amplifier to generate a tunable pump photon energy. Studying LaTe3 we compare the dynamics driven by pumping resonantly across the charge density wave energy gap with the effect of pumping at a twice higher photon energy in a TARPES pump-probe experiment. We clearly identify a pump photon energy dependent behavior. At the larger pump photon energy, the excess electronic energy generates lattice heating mediated by e-ph coupling and softening of the amplitude mode frequency from 3 to 2 THz. Remarkably, the resonant pumping across the CDW gap results in a time-independent amplitude mode frequency. We conclude that the resonant excitation across the energy gap excites the amplitude mode selectively while additional electronic excess energy deposited at higher pump photon energy modifies the crystal properties transiently by incoherent dissipative processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13604v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.104706</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 104706 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kecheng Liu, Takeshi Suzuki, Yigui Zhong, Teruto Kanai, Jiro Itatani, Linda Ye, Maya Martinez, Anisha Singh, Ian R. Fisher, Uwe Bovensiepen, Kozo Okazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projected and Solvable Topological Heavy Fermion Model of Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14039v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the topological heavy-fermion (THF) model of magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG) in the projected limit, where only the flat bands are present in the low-energy spectrum. Such limit has been previously analyzed in momentum-space Bistritzer-MacDonald-type continuum models, but not in a real-space formalism. In this regime, the Hubbard interaction ($U_1$) of the $f$-electrons is larger than the bandwidth ($2M$) of the flat bands but smaller than the gap ($\gamma$) between the flat and remote bands. In the THF model, concentrated charge (in real space) and concentrated Berry curvature (in momentum space) are respectively realized by exponentially localized $f$-orbitals and itinerant Dirac $c$-electrons. Local moments naturally arise from $f$-orbitals. Hybridizing the $f$-electrons with $c$-electrons produces power-law tails of the flat-band Wannier functions, raising the question of relevance of the local moment picture in the projected $U_1\ll \gamma$ limit. Nonetheless, we find that the local moments remain stable as long as $U_1 \gg \Delta(\omega)$ for $|\omega|\lesssim U_1$, where $\Delta(\omega)\sim \gamma^2 N(\omega)$ is the hybridization function seen by each $f$-site, and $N(\omega)$ is the density of states of the Dirac $c$-bands. Notably, the comparison between $U_1$ and $\gamma$ is irrelevant to the local moment formation if $N(\omega)$ is unknown. Within the framework of THF, we also derive the correlated self-energy of the flat bands using the Hubbard-I approximation and estimate the coupling strength between the local moments. Finally, we comment that, in the regime of extremely concentrated Berry curvature, the single-particle gap between flat bands and remote bands vanishes and the interaction is always larger than the gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14039v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Hu, Zhi-Da Song, B. Andrei Bernevig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of a gapped phase in the one-dimensional $S = {\frac{1}{2}}$ Heisenberg antiferromagnetic chain Cu(Ampy)ClBr</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10290v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spin-1/2 Heisenberg antiferromagnetic frustrated spin chain systems display exotic ground states with unconventional excitations and distinct quantum phase transitions as the ratio of next-nearest-neighbor to nearest-neighbor coupling is tuned.
  We present a comprehensive investigation of the structural, magnetic, and thermodynamics properties of the spin-1/2 compound, Cu(Ampy)ClBr (Ampy= C$_6$H$_8$N$_2$ = 2-(Aminomethyl)pyridine) via x-ray diffraction, magnetization, specific heat, $^1$H nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), electron spin resonance (ESR), and muon spin relaxation ($\mu$SR) techniques. The crystal structure features an anisotropic triangular chain lattice of magnetic Cu$^{2+}$ ions. Our bulk and local probe experiments detect neither long-range magnetic ordering nor spin freezing down to 0.06 K despite the presence of moderate antiferromagnetic interaction between Cu$^{2+}$ spins as reflected by a Curie-Weiss temperature of about $-9$ K from the bulk susceptibility data. A broad maximum is observed at about 9 K in magnetic susceptibility and specific heat data, indicating the onset of short-range spin correlations. At low temperatures, the zero-field magnetic specific heat and the $^1$H NMR spin-lattice relaxation rate follow an exponential temperature dependence, indicating the presence of gapped magnetic excitations.
  Furthermore, persistent spin dynamics down to 0.088 K observed by zero-field $\mu$SR evidences lack of any static magnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10290v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikat Nandi, Monika Jawale, Sanjay Bachhar, Rahul Kumar, Marlis Schuller, Rabindranath Bag, J. Wilkinson, J\"org Sichelschmidt, A. Sundaresan, Sara Haravifard, N. B\"uttgen, A. V. Mahajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compressing local vertex functions from the multipoint numerical renormalization group using quantics tensor cross interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13359v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The multipoint numerical renormalization group (mpNRG) is a powerful impurity solver that provides accurate spectral data useful for computing local, dynamic correlation functions in imaginary or real frequencies non-perturbatively across a wide range of interactions and temperatures. It gives access to a local, non-perturbative four-point vertex in imaginary and real frequencies, which can be used as input for subsequent computations such as diagrammatic extensions of dynamical mean--field theory. However, computing and manipulating the real-frequency four-point vertex on large, dense grids quickly becomes numerically challenging when the density and/or the extent of the frequency grid is increased. In this paper, we compute four-point vertices in a strongly compressed quantics tensor train format using quantics tensor cross interpolation, starting from discrete partial spectral functions obtained from mpNRG. This enables evaluations of the vertex on frequency grids with resolutions far beyond the reach of previous implementations. We benchmark this approach on the four-point vertex of the single-impurity Anderson model across a wide range of physical parameters, both in its full form and its asymptotic decomposition. For imaginary frequencies, the full vertex can be represented to an accuracy on the order of $2\cdot 10^{-3}$ with maximum bond dimensions not exceeding 120. The more complex full real-frequency vertex requires maximum bond dimensions not exceeding 170 for an accuracy of $\lesssim 2\%$. Our work marks another step toward tensor-train-based diagrammatic calculations for correlated electronic lattice models starting from a local, non-perturbative mpNRG vertex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13359v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/jx7h-lsqk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 043032 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Markus Frankenbach, Marc Ritter, Mathias Pelz, Nepomuk Ritz, Jan von Delft, Anxiang Ge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott metal-insulator transition in a modified periodic Anderson model: Insights from entanglement entropy and role of short-range spatial correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16533v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Mott transition is a paradigmatic phenomenon where Coulomb interactions between electrons drive a metal-insulator phase transition. It is extensively studied within the Hubbard model, where a quantum critical transition occurs at a finite temperature second-order critical point. This work investigates the Mott transition in a modified periodic Anderson model that may be viewed as a three-orbital lattice model including an interacting, localized orbital coupled to a delocalized conduction orbital via a second conduction orbital. Within the dynamical mean field theory, this model possesses a strictly zero temperature quantum critical point separating a Fermi liquid and a Mott insulating phase. By employing a simplified version of the dynamical mean field theory, namely, the two-site or linearized dynamical mean field theory, an analytical estimate is provided for the critical parameter strengths at which the transition occurs at zero temperature. An analytical estimate of the single-site von Neumann entanglement entropy is also provided. This measure can be used as a robust identifier for the phase transition. These calculations are extended to their cluster version to incorporate short-range, spatial correlations and discuss their effects on the transition observed in this model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16533v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adts.202501224</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Theory Simul. 2025, e01224</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ankur Majumder, Sudeshna Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Transformer Backflow for Solving Momentum-Resolved Ground States of Strongly Correlated Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09275v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strongly correlated materials host a rich variety of exotic quantum phases but remain challenging to solve due to strong interactions. We introduce the Neural Transformer Backflow (NTB) framework, a powerful neural-network ansatz formulated within a multi-band projection formalism. NTB is mean-field transcendental, parameter-efficient and fermionic intrinsic, exhibiting superior performance compared with existing neural ansatzes. By naturally enforcing momentum conservation, NTB enables direct computation of momentum-resolved many-body ground states, providing detailed access to degeneracies and energy gaps. It achieves high accuracy on small systems and scales efficiently to larger sizes and higher-band truncations far beyond the reach of exact diagonalization. We demonstrate the power of NTB in capturing diverse correlated phases in twisted MoTe$_2$, including charge density waves, fractional Chern insulators, and anomalous Hall Fermi liquids, within a unified framework. This approach offers a generic, scalable route towards understanding and discovering quantum phases in strongly correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09275v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lixing Zhang, Di Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudogap-induced change in the nature of the Lifshitz transition in the two-dimensional Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09783v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the behavior of the density of states and the $B_{1g}$ nematic susceptibility extracted from Raman response data across the doping-driven Lifshitz transition comparing the weak and strong interaction cases. Our results were obtained using cluster dynamical mean field theory for the two-dimensional Hubbard model. In the weakly correlated Fermi liquid regime, both quantities are approximately symmetric around the Lifshitz transition doping $p_{LT}$. In the strongly correlated regime, the low-doping pseudogap leads to an asymmetric, discontinuous evolution when the Fermi surface changes from hole-like to electron-like at $p_{LT}$. The Lifshitz transition thus changes character because it is tied to the pseudogap-Fermi-liquid transition. These results are consistent with available observations and should foster further experimental investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09783v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria C. O. Aguiar, Helena Bragan\c{c}a, Indranil Paul, Marcello Civelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing phase transitions in non-Hermitian systems with quantum entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25703v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the quantum entanglement and quantum phase transition of the non-Hermitian anisotropic spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ XY model and XXZ model with the staggered imaginary field by analytical methods and numerical exact diagonalization, respectively. Various entanglement measures, including concurrence, negativity, mutual information, and quantum coherence, and both biorthogonal and self-normal quantities are investigated. Both the biorthogonal and self-normal entanglement quantities, except the biorthogonal concurrence, are found to be capable of detecting the first-order and $\mathcal{PT}$ transitions in the XXZ model, as well as the Ising and $\mathcal{RT}$ transitions in the XY model. In addition, we introduce the unconstrained concurrence and demonstrate its effectiveness in detecting these transitions. On the other hand, the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) transition in the XXZ model is revealed through concurrence and negativity at small non-Hermiticity strengths. Notably, the critical points observed in the Hermitian limit evolve into exceptional points as the strength of the non-Hermiticity increases. Furthermore, we find that the first-order transition survives up to a higher non-Hermiticity strength compared to the BKT transition within the $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric regime of the XXZ model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25703v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ling-Feng Zhang, Wing Chi Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect mediated quantum melting of charge ordered insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00099v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2d) electronic systems on a lattice at fractional filling $\nu = p/q$ exhibit a competition between charge ordered insulators, called Wigner-Mott insulators (WMIs), at large Coulomb repulsion and Fermi-liquid metals at large electronic kinetic energy. When those two energy scales are roughly equal, insulating states that restore the lattice translation symmetry, which we call quantum charge liquids (QCLs), may emerge. When gapped, these QCLs must exhibit topological order. In this work, we show that the allowed topological ordered phases that are proximate to the WMI strongly depend on the charge ordering in the WMI. In particular, we show that when $q$ is even, no direct transition exists between a WMI with the smallest allowed unit cell size from filling constraints, i.e., the "minimal" WMI, and the topological order with the smallest ground state degeneracy on a torus allowed by filling constraints, i.e., the "minimal" TO. Furthermore, we describe the quantum melting transition of the WMIs to the proximate QCLs in terms of the proliferation of the topological defects of the WMIs. The field theory of this transition in terms of the topological defects reveals their role as precursors to the anyon excitations in the QCLs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00099v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abijith Krishnan, Ajesh Kumar, T. Senthil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement dynamics from universal low-lying modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16763v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Information-theoretic quantities such as Renyi entropies show a remarkable universality in their late-time behaviour across a variety of chaotic many-body systems. Understanding how such common features emerge from very different microscopic dynamics remains an important challenge. In this work, we address this question in a class of Brownian models with random time-dependent Hamiltonians and a variety of different microscopic couplings. In any such model, the Lorentzian time-evolution of the $n$-th Renyi entropy can be mapped to evolution by a Euclidean Hamiltonian on 2$n$ copies of the system. We provide evidence that in systems with no symmetries, the low-energy excitations of the Euclidean Hamiltonian are universally given by a gapped quasiparticle-like band. The eigenstates in this band are plane waves of locally dressed domain walls between ferromagnetic ground states associated with two permutations in the symmetric group $S_n$. These excitations give rise to the membrane picture of entanglement growth, with the membrane tension determined by their dispersion relation. We establish this structure in a variety of cases using analytical perturbative methods and numerical variational techniques, and extract the associated dispersion relations and membrane tensions for the second and third Renyi entropies. For the third Renyi entropy, we argue that phase transitions in the membrane tension as a function of velocity are needed to ensure that physical constraints on the membrane tension are satisfied. Overall, this structure provides an understanding of entanglement dynamics in terms of a universal set of gapped low-lying modes, which may also apply to systems with time-independent Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16763v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreya Vardhan, Sanjay Moudgalya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A recipe for local simulation of strongly-correlated fermionic matter on quantum computers: the 2D Fermi-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14543v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The simulation of quantum many-body systems, relevant for quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics, is one of the most promising applications of near-term quantum computers before fault-tolerance. However, since the vast majority of quantum computing technologies are built around qubits and discrete gate-based operations, the translation of the physical problem into this framework is a crucial step. This translation will often be device specific, and a suboptimal implementation will be punished by the exponential compounding of errors on real devices. The importance of an efficient mapping is already revealed for models of spinful fermions in two or three dimensions, which naturally arise when the relevant physics relates to electrons. Using the most direct and well-known mapping, the Jordan-Wigner transformation, leads to a non-local representation of local degrees of freedom, and necessities efficient decompositions of non-local unitary gates into a sequence of hardware accessible local gates. In this paper, we provide a step-by-step recipe for simulating the paradigmatic two-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model on a quantum computer using only local operations. To provide the ingredients for such a recipe, we briefly review the plethora of different approaches that have emerged recently but focus on the Derby-Klassen compact fermion mapping in order to make our discussion concrete. We provide a detailed recipe for an end-to-end simulation including embedding on a physical device, preparing initial states such as ground states, simulation of unitary time evolution, and measurement of observables and spectral functions. We explicitly compute the resource requirements for simulating a global quantum quench and conclude by discussing the challenges and future directions for simulating strongly-correlated fermionic matter on quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14543v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.043018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 043018 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arash Jafarizadeh, Frank Pollmann, Adam Gammon-Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic suppression of supersonic quantum transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19788v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a broad class of strongly interacting quantum lattice gases, including the Fermi-Hubbard and Bose-Hubbard models. We focus on macroscopic particle clusters of size $\theta N$, with $\theta\in(0,1)$ and $N$ the total particle number, and we study the quantum probability that such a cluster is transported across a distance $r$ within time $t$. Conventional effective light cone arguments yield a bound of the form $\exp(v t-r)$. We report a substantially stronger bound $\exp(\theta N(vt-r))$, which provides exponential suppression that scales with system size. Our result establishes a universal dynamical large deviation principle: macroscopic suppression of supersonic macroscopic transport (MASSMAT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19788v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\'emy Faupin, Marius Lemm, Israel Michael Sigal, Jingxuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
