<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 02:55:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Gauging non-invertible symmetries on the lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02925v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a general prescription for gauging finite non-invertible symmetries in 1+1d lattice Hamiltonian systems. Our primary example is the Rep(D$_8$) fusion category generated by the Kennedy-Tasaki transformation, which is the simplest anomaly-free non-invertible symmetry on a spin chain of qubits. We explicitly compute its lattice F-symbols and illustrate our prescription for a particular (non-maximal) gauging of this symmetry. In our gauging procedure, we introduce two qubits around each link, playing the role of "gauge fields" for the non-invertible symmetry, and impose novel Gauss's laws. Similar to the Kramers-Wannier transformation for gauging an ordinary $\mathbb{Z}_2$, our gauging can be summarized by a gauging map, which is part of a larger, continuous non-invertible cosine symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02925v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahand Seifnashri, Shu-Heng Shao, Xinping Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-temperature quantum topological order in three dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We identify a three-dimensional system that exhibits long-range entanglement at sufficiently small but nonzero temperature--it therefore constitutes a quantum topological order at finite temperature. The model of interest is known as the fermionic toric code, a variant of the usual 3D toric code, which admits emergent fermionic point-like excitations. The fermionic toric code, importantly, possesses an anomalous 2-form symmetry, associated with the space-like Wilson loops of the fermionic excitations. We argue that it is this symmetry that imbues low-temperature thermal states with a novel topological order and long-range entanglement. Based on the current classification of three-dimensional topological orders, we expect that the low-temperature thermal states of the fermionic toric code belong to an equilibrium phase of matter that only exists at nonzero temperatures. We conjecture that further examples of topological orders at nonzero temperatures are given by discrete gauge theories with anomalous 2-form symmetries. Our work therefore opens the door to studying quantum topological order at nonzero temperature in physically realistic dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02928v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu-Tong Zhou, Meng Cheng, Tibor Rakovszky, Curt von Keyserlingk, Tyler D. Ellison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vestigial Order from an Excitonic Mother State in Kagome Superconductors $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alongside high-temperature charge order and superconductivity, kagome metals exhibit signatures of time-reversal symmetry breaking and nematicity which appear to depend strongly on external perturbations such as strain and magnetic fields, posing a fundamental challenge for conceptual reconciliation. We develop a theory of vestigial order descending from an excitonic mother state in $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ ($A$=K,Rb,Cs), which develops around $T_* \approx 40$ K. The application of external fields stabilises a subset of the phase-melted order parameter manifold, referred to as a vestigial state, producing a symmetry-breaking response which depends on the applied probe. Our theory reproduces the observations of piezomagnetism, electric magnetic chiral anisotropy, absence of Kerr rotation, unusual elastoresistance response, and superconducting diode effect. Our proposed excitonic mother state accounts for probe-dependent symmetry breaking patterns without fine-tuning, and predicts additional signatures accessible through optical spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02929v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Ingham, Ronny Thomale, Harley D. Scammell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering excitonic metal-insulator transitions in ultra-thin doped copper sulfides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exciton condensation in the absence of optical excitation is proposed in 1960s to occur in a semiconductor at low temperatures when the binding energy of excitons overcomes the band gap or in a semimetal with weakly screened coulomb interaction, giving rise to an excitonic insulating state. However, it has been challenging to establish experimental realization in a natural material as the interacting electron-hole pockets rely on the band structures which are difficult to be delicately controlled. Here, we demonstrate an excitonic insulating phase formed in ultra-thin copper sulfide films by effectively tuning the band structure via changing the composition of Cu and S in the system. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), we observed a continuous band renormalization and opening of a full gap at low temperatures over a wide range of doping. The electronic origin of the metal-insulator transition is supported by scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) and low energy electron diffraction (LEED) measurements, which show no indication of superlattice modulation and lattice symmetry breaking. The evidence of excitonic insulator is further provided by carrier density dependent transitions, a combined effect of electron screening and Coulomb interaction strength. Our findings demonstrate the tunability of the band structure of copper sulfides, allowing for new opportunities to study exotic quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03407v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haiyang Chen, Yufeng Liu, Yashi Jiang, Changcang Qiao, Tao Zhang, Jianyang Ding, Zhengtai Liu, Zhenhua Chen, Yaobo Huang, Jinfeng Jia, Shiyong Wang, Peng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti Kibble-Zurek behavior in the quantum XY spin-1/2 chain driven by correlated noisy magnetic field and anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the non-adiabatic dynamics across a quantum phase transition, the Kibble-Zurek paradigm describes that the average number of topological defects is suppressed as a universal power law with the quench time scale. A conflicting observation, which termed anti-Kibble-Zurek dynamics has been reported in several studies, specifically in the driven systems with an uncorrelated stochastic (white) noise. Here, we study the defect generation in the driven transverse field/anisotropy quantum $XY$ model in the presence of a correlated (colored) Gaussian noise. We propose a generic conjecture that properly capture the noise-induced excitation features, which shows good agreement with the numerical simulations. We show that, the dynamical features of defect density are modified by varying the noise correlation time. Our numerical simulations confirm that, for fast noises, the dynamics of the defect density is the same as that of the uncorrelated (white) noise, as is expected. However, the larger ratio of noise correlation time to the annealing time results in larger defects density formation and reforms the universal dynamical features. Our finding reveals that, the noise-induced defects scale linearly with the annealing time for fast noises, while in the presence of the slow noises, the noise-induced defects scale linearly with the square of the annealing time. The numerical simulations confirm that, the optimal annealing time, at which the defects density is minimum, scales linearly in logarithmic scale with the total noise power having different exponents for the fast and slow noises.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03409v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Sadeghizade, R. Jafari, A. Langari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo-like behavior in a mixed valent oxypnictide $\mathrm{La_{3}Cu_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have synthesized and characterized the physical properties of a layered, mixed valent oxypnictide $\mathrm{La_{3}Cu_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$ via magnetization, electrical resistivity, and specific heat measurements. Although $\mathrm{La_{3}Cu_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$ does not exhibit superconductivity down to T = 0.5 K, it demonstrates an intriguing resistivity minimum observed at $\mathrm{T_{min}}$ = 13.7 K. Disappearance of the resistivity minimum under an applied magnetic field of $\mathrm{\mu_{0}H}$ = 9 T together with the negative magnetoresistance at low and positive at high temperatures are observed, which are typical for both Kondo-like spin-dependent scattering and 3D weak localization. We argue that the Kondo scattering is a more plausible explanation due to the low-temperature deviation from a Curie-Weiss law observed in the magnetic susceptibility, consistent with the presence of magnetic interactions between paramagnetic $\mathrm{Cu^{2+}}$ ions and Kondo screening of these $\mathrm{Cu^{2+}}$ moments. We supplemented the experimental characterization with a detailed description of chemical bonding, employing density functional theory (DFT) calculations and crystal orbital Hamilton population (COHP) analysis for $\mathrm{La_{3}Cu_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$ and isostructural $\mathrm{La_{3}Ni_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$, which is a superconductor with $\mathrm{T_c = 2.2}$ K. Based on the calculations performed, we present the difference between $\mathrm{La_{3}Cu_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$ and $\mathrm{La_{3}Ni_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$ in the character of electronic states at the Fermi level. This discrepancy impacts structural stability and may cause a lack of superconductivity in $\mathrm{La_{3}Cu_{4}P_{4}O_{2}}$ down to T = 0.5 K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03447v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-025-89706-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci Rep 15, 7019 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Szymon Kr\'olak (Faculty of Applied Physics and Mathematics and Advanced Materials Centre, Gdansk University of Technology, Gda\'nsk, Poland), Micha{\l} J. Winiarski (Faculty of Applied Physics and Mathematics and Advanced Materials Centre, Gdansk University of Technology, Gda\'nsk, Poland), Duygu Yazici (Faculty of Applied Physics and Mathematics and Advanced Materials Centre, Gdansk University of Technology, Gda\'nsk, Poland, The Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey, Ankara, Turkey), Soohyeon Shin (PSI Center for Neutron and Muon Sciences, Paul Scherrer Institut, Villigen, Switzerland), Tomasz Klimczuk (Faculty of Applied Physics and Mathematics and Advanced Materials Centre, Gdansk University of Technology, Gda\'nsk, Poland)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beginner's Lecture Notes on Quantum Spin Chains, Exact Diagonalization and Tensor Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aimed at introducing readers to the physics of strongly correlated many-body systems, these notes focus on numerical methods, with detailed discussions on implementing working code for exact diagonalization. A brief introduction to tensor network methods is also included. Prepared for the Summer School Quantumandu, held at Tribhuvan University (Kathmandu, Nepal) from 25 to 31 July 2024, as part of the ICTP's Physics Without Frontiers program, these notes are primarily intended for readers encountering this field for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03564v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guglielmo Lami, Mario Collura, Nishan Ranabhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital textures and evolution of correlated insulating state in monolayer 1T phase transition metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strong electron-electron interaction can induce Mott insulating state, which is believed to host unusual correlated phenomena such as quantum spin liquid when quantum fluctuation dominates and unconventional superconductivity through doping. Transition metal compounds as correlated materials provide a versatile platform to engineer the Mott insulating state. Previous studies mostly focused on the controlling of the repulsive interaction and bandwidth of the electrons by gating or doping. Here, we performed angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) on monolayer 1T phase NbSe2, TaSe2, and TaS2 and directly observed their band structures with characteristic lower Hubbard bands. By systematically investigating the orbital textures and temperature dependence of the energy gap of the materials in this family, we discovered that hybridization of the chalcogen p states with lower Hubbard band stabilizes the Mott phase via tuning of the bandwidth, as shown by a significant increase of the transition temperature (TC) at a stronger hybridization strength. Our findings reveal a mechanism for realizing a robust Mott insulating phase and establish monolayer 1T phase transition metal dichalcogenide family as a promising platform for exploring correlated electron problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03597v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Gao, Haiyang Chen, Wen-shin Lu, Yang-hao Chan, Zhenhua Chen, Yaobo Huang, Zhengtai Liu, Peng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intermediate band analysis in Green's functions calculations of quasiparticle interference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The measurement of quasiparticle scattering patterns on material surfaces using scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) is now an established technique for accessing the momentum-resolved electronic band structure of solids. However, since these quasiparticle interference (QPI) patterns reflect spatial variations related to differences in the band momenta rather than the momenta themselves, their interpretation often relies on comparisons with simple geometrical models such as the joint density of states (JDOS) or with the convolution of Green's functions. In this paper, we highlight non-intuitive differences between Green's function and JDOS results. To understand the origin of these discrepancies, we analyze the convolution of Green's functions using the Feynman parametrization technique and introduce a framework that we call the intermediate band analysis. This approach allows us to derive simple selection rules for interband QPI, based on electron group velocities. Connecting the intermediate band analysis with the experiment, we consider experimental Bogoliubov QPI patterns measured for FeSe1-xSx, which were recently used to demonstrate a highly anisotropic superconducting gap, indicating superconductivity mediated by nematic fluctuations [1]. The calculated Green's functions convolutions reproduce the particle-hole asymmetry in the intensity of QPI patterns across the Fermi level observed in experiments. Finally, we demonstrate the utility of intermediate band analysis in tracing the origin of this asymmetry to a coherence factor effect of the superconducting state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03674v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinze Yang, Alexander F. Kemper, Adrian Gozar, Eduardo H. da Silva Neto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry and local moment swapover in correlated graphene heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene-based multilayer systems serve as versatile platforms for exploring the interplay between electron correlation and topology, thanks to distinctive low-energy bands marked by significant quantum metric and Berry curvature from graphene's Dirac bands. Here, we investigate Mott physics and local spin moments in Dirac bands hybridized with a flat band of localized orbitals in functionalized graphene. Via hybridization control, a topological transition is realized between two symmetry-distinct site-selective Mott states featuring local moments in different Wyckoff positions, with a geometrically enforced metallic state emerging in between. We find that this geometrically controlled local moment ``swapover'' and associated metal-insulator physics may be realized through proximity coupling of epitaxial graphene on SiC(0001) with group IV intercalants, where the Mott state faces geometrical obstruction in the large-hybridization limit. Our work shows that chemically functionalized graphene provides a correlated electron platform, very similar to the topological heavy fermions in graphene moir\'e systems but at significantly enhanced characteristic energy scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03700v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Witt, Siheon Ryee, Lennart Klebl, Jennifer Cano, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Tim O. Wehling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of intertwined spin and charge density waves in a layered altermagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03716v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets recently came into the spotlight as a new class of magnetic materials, arising as a consequence of specific crystal symmetries. They are characterized by a spin-polarized electronic band structure similar to ferromagnets, but with net zero magnetization, and touted as a promising platform to host a slew of exotic properties, many of which are yet to be explored. Using spectroscopic-imaging scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) and spin-polarized STM, we discover intertwined spin and charge density waves in a layered triangular lattice altermagnet, Co-intercalated NbSe$_2$. STM topographs and differential conductance maps in the altermagnetic state show tri-directional modulations with a 2$a_0$ wave length that are robustly present and non-dispersive in a wide range of imaging biases, suggesting a charge ordering origin of the modulations. Spin-polarized STM measurements further reveal that the amplitude of the charge modulations is sensitive to the spin polarization of the tip. This observation demonstrates an additional spin modulation associated with the density wave modulations. Our work uncovers the first density wave instability involving both charge and spin degrees of freedom in an altermagnetic system, accomplished by providing elusive atomic-scale insights. Our experiments thus set the foundation for the studies of correlated electronic states in altermagnets, and motivate comprehensive explorations of intercalated quasi-2D transition metal dichalcogenides in the search for novel phenomena in altermagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03716v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Candelora, Muxian Xu, Siyu Cheng, Alessandro De Vita, Davide Romanin, Chiara Bigi, My Bang Petersen, Alexander LaFleur, Matteo Calandra, Jill Miwa, Younghun Hwang, Ziqiang Wang, Federico Mazzola, Ilija Zeljkovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum effects on pyrochlore higher-rank U(1) spin liquids: pinch-line singularities, spin nematics, and connections to oxide materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the magnetism of pyrochlore oxides, we consider the effect of quantum fluctuations in the most general symmetry-allowed nearest-neighbor Kramers exchange Hamiltonian on the pyrochlore lattice. At the classical level, this Hamiltonian exhibits a rich landscape of classical spin liquids and a variety of non-conventional magnetic phases. In contrast, much remains unclear for the quantum model, where quantum fluctuations have the potential to alter the classical landscape and stabilize novel magnetic phases. Employing state-of-the-art pseudo-fermion functional renormalization group (pf-FRG) calculations for the spin-$1/2$ model, we determine the quantum phase diagram at relevant cross-sections, where the classical model hosts an algebraic nodal rank-2 spin liquid and a spin nematic order. We find large regions in parameter space where dipolar magnetic order is absent and, based on known fingerprints in the correlation functions, suggest that this non-conventional region is composed of an ensemble of distinct phases stabilized by quantum fluctuations. Our results hint at the existence of a spin nematic phase, and we identify the quantum analogue of the classical rank-2 spin liquid. Furthermore, we highlight the importance of assessing the subtle interplay of quantum and thermal fluctuations in reconciling the experimental findings on the nature of magnetic order in Yb$_2$Ti$_2$O$_7$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03749v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lasse Gresista, Daniel Lozano-G\'omez, Matthias Vojta, Simon Trebst, Yasir Iqbal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum oscillation studies of the nodal line semimetal Ni3In2S2-xSex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ternary shandite compounds with the general formula T3M2X2 (T = Ni, Co, Rh or Pd; M = Sn, In or Pb and X = S or Se) have emerged as a large pool of topological semimetals. This family of compounds hosts different topological phases for various combinations of T, M and X. This paper reports the observation of quantum oscillations under the high magnetic fields in Ni3In2S2-xSex single crystals. Angular dependence of oscillation frequency suggests an evolution of the Fermi surface from three-dimensional to two-dimensional on Se substitution for S in Ni3In2S2. The effective mass obtained for each composition by fitting the oscillation amplitude with the Lifshitz-Kosevich formula, shows no significant change, suggesting that the topological phase might be relatively robust against enhanced SOC upon Se doping in Ni3In2S2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02964v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.actamat.2025.120884</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Acta Materialia 289, 120884 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. M. Sharma, Santosh Karki Chhetri, Gokul Acharya, David Graf, Dinesh Upreti, Sagar Dahal, Md Rafique Un Nabi, Sumaya Rahman, Josh Sakon, Hugh O. H. Churchill, Jin Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisting in h-BN bilayers and their angle-dependent properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we systematically investigate the structural and electronic properties of twisted h-BN bilayers to understand the role of the twisting angle. Using first-principles methods with relaxation taken into account, we simulate h-BN bilayers with commensurate supercells with the smallest angle being $2.88^{\circ}$ until $60^{\circ}$. We find that the interlayer separation is not constant throughout each bilayer because of the various stacking patterns of AA, AA', AB, AB', and A'B throughout the layers, which also play a significant role in their unique charge redistribution. The calculations for the 110 generated structures show the existence of flat bands in several twisted h-BN bilayers, as well as the emergence of different trends in their properties as a function of the twist angle. These results are useful for establishing a systematic base line of registry-dependent relations for the development of more advanced computational methods to access incommensurate h-BN bilayers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03099v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diem Thi-Xuan Dang, Dai-Nam Le, Lilia M. Woods</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interfacial spin-orbit-coupling-induced strong spin-to-charge conversion at an all-oxide ferromagnetic /quasi-two-dimensional electron gas interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Functional oxides and hybrid structures with interfacial spin orbit coupling and the Rashba-Edelsterin effect (REE) are promising materials systems for thermal tolerance spintronic device applications. Here, we demonstrate efficient spin-to-charge conversion through enhanced interfacial spin orbit coupling at the all-oxide interface of La1-xCaxMnO3 with quasi-two-dimensional (quasi-2D) SrTiO3 (LCMO/STO). The quasi-2D interface is generated via oxygen vacancies at the STO surface. We obtain a spin-to-charge conversion efficiency of ~ 2.32 +- 1.3 nm, most likely originating from the inverse REE, which is relatively large versus all-metallic spin-to-charge conversion materials systems. The results highlight that the LCMO/STO 2D electron gas is a potential platform for spin-based memory and transistor applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03292v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mi-Jin Jin, Guang Yang, Doo-Seung Um, Jacob Linder, Jason W. A. Robinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back-action effects in charge detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03416v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Charge detection offers a powerful probe of mesoscopic structures based on quantum dots, but it also invariably results in measurement back-action (MBA). If strong, MBA can be detrimental to the physical properties being probed. In this work, we focus on the effects of MBA on an Anderson impurity model in which the impurity is coupled electrostatically to a detector. Introducing a novel non-perturbative method, we explore the interplay of coherent dynamics, strong correlations and non-equilibrium conditions. The effects of MBA can be seen most clearly in the temperature derivative of occupation. In the non-equilibrium case, we identify this as arising due to an energy flow from the detector to the impurity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03416v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarath Sankar, Matan Lotem, Joshua Folk, Eran Sela, Yigal Meir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual spectroscopy of quantum simulated Fermi-Hubbard systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03477v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum gas microscopy with atoms in optical lattices provides remarkable insights into the real space properties of many-body systems, but does not directly reveal the nature of their fundamental excitation spectrum. Here, we demonstrate that radio-frequency spectroscopy can reveal the quasi-particle nature of doped quantum many-body systems, crucial for our understanding of, e.g., high-temperature superconductors. In particular, we showcase how the existence and energy of magnetic polaron quasi-particles in doped Fermi-Hubbard systems may be probed, revealed by hallmark peaks in the spectroscopic spectrum. In combination with fundamental dualities of the Fermi-Hubbard model, we describe how these findings may be tested using several experimental platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03477v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Knakkergaard Nielsen, M. Zwierlein, G. M. Bruun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement generation and scaling from noisy quenches across a quantum critical point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03584v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the impact of noise on the dynamics of entanglement in the transverse-field Ising chain, with the field quenched linearly across one or both of the quantum critical points of the model. Taking concurrence as a measure of entanglement, we find that a quench generates entanglement between nearest- and next-nearest-neighbor spins, with noise reducing the amount of entanglement. Focusing on the next-nearest-neighbor concurrence, known to exhibit Kibble-Zurek scaling with the square root of the quench rate in the noiseless case, we find a different result when noise is present: The concurrence now scales logarithmically with the quench rate, with a noise-dependent amplitude. This is also different from the ``anti-Kibble-Zurek" scaling of defect density with quench rate when noise is present, suggesting that noisy entanglement generation is largely independent from the rate of defect formation. Intriguingly, the critical time scale beyond which no entanglement is produced by a noisy quench scales as a power law with the strength of noise, with the same exponent as that which governs the optimal quench time for which defect formation is at a minimum in a standard quantum annealing scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03584v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Jafari, J. Naji, A. Langari, Vahid Karimipour, Henrik Johannesson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Models and Cluster Multipole Method: Application to Kagome Magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03624v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a multi-scale computational approach that combines atomistic spin models with the cluster multipole (CMP) method. The CMP method enables a systematic and accurate generation of complex non-collinear magnetic structures using symmetry-adapted representations. The parameters of the spin model are derived from density functional theory using the magnetic force theorem, with the paramagnetic state as a reference. The energy landscape of CMP-generated structures is inspected at the model Hamiltonian level, and sets of low-energy magnetic structures are identified for each material candidate. The inclusion of relativistic antisymmetric and anisotropic pair interactions lifts partially the degeneracy among these most stable structures. To demonstrate the applicability and predictive capability of the method, we apply it to the non-collinear Mn3X and collinear Fe3X (X = Ga, Ge, and Sn) kagome compounds. The computational efficiency of the method in identifying low-energy structures among multiple CMP configurations highlights its potential for high-throughput screening of complex magnets with unknown magnetic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03624v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juba Bouaziz, Takuya Nomoto, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-Body Localization and Particle Statistics in Disordered Bose-Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03712v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the potential influence of the particle statistics on the stability of the many-body localization in the disordered Bose-Hubbard model. Within the higher-energy section of the dynamical phase diagram, we find that there is no apparent finite-size boundary drift between the thermal phase and the many-body localized regime. We substantiate this observation by introducing the Van Vleck perturbation theory into the field of many-body localization. The appropriateness of this method rests largely on the peculiar Hilbert-space structure enabled by the particles' Bose statistics. The situation is reversed in the lower-energy section of the dynamical phase diagram, where the significant finite-size boundary drift pushes the putative many-body localized regime up to the greater disorder strengths. We utilize the algebraic projection method to make a connection linking the disordered Bose-Hubbard model in the lower-energy section to an intricate disordered spin chain model. This issue of the finite-size drift could hence be analogous to what happens in the disordered Heisenberg chain. Both trends might be traced back to the particles' intrinsic or emergent Fermi statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03712v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Chen, Chun Chen, Xiaoqun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision reconstruction of rational CFT from exact fixed point tensor network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.18005v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The novel concept of entanglement renormalization and its corresponding tensor network renormalization technique have been highly successful in developing a controlled real space renormalization group (RG) scheme. Numerically approximate fixed-point (FP) tensors are widely used to extract the conformal data of the underlying conformal field theory (CFT) describing critical phenomena. In this paper, we present an explicit analytical construction of the FP tensor for 2D rational CFT. We define it as a correlation function between the "boundary-changing operators" (BCO) on triangles. Our construction fully captures all the real-space RG conditions. We also provide concrete examples, such as Ising, Yang-Lee and Tri-critical Ising models to compute the scaling dimensions explicitly based on the corresponding FP tensor. The BCO descendants turn out to be an optimal basis such that truncation in bond dimensions naturally produces comparable accuracies with the leading existing FP algorithms. Interestingly, our construction of FP tensors is closely related to a strange correlator, where the holographic picture naturally emerges. Our results also open a new door towards understanding CFT in higher dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.18005v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gong Cheng, Lin Chen, Zheng-Cheng Gu, Ling-Yan Hung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frustrated phonon with charge density wave in vanadium Kagome metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06913v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The formation of a star of David CDW superstructure, resulting from the coordinated displacements of vanadium ions on a corner sharing triangular lattice, has garnered significant attention to comprehend the influence of electron phonon interaction within geometrically intricate lattice of Kagome metals, specifically AV3Sb5 (where A represents K, Rb, or Cs). However, understanding of the underlying mechanism behind CDW formation, coupled with symmetry protected lattice vibrations, remains elusive. Here, from femtosecond time resolved X ray scattering experiments, we reveal that the phonon mode, associated with Cs ions out-of-plane motion, becomes frustrated in the CDW phase. Furthermore, we observed the photoinduced emergence of a metastable CDW phase, facilitated by alleviating the frustration. By not only elucidating the longstanding puzzle surrounding the intervention of phonons but introducing the phononic frustration, this research offers fresh insights into the competition between phonons and periodic lattice distortions, a phenomenon widespread in other correlated quantum materials including layered high TC superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06913v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung-Phil Heo, Choongjae Won, Heemin Lee, Hanbyul Kim, Eunyoung Park, Sung Yun Lee, Junha Hwang, Hyeongi Choi, Sang-Youn Park, Byungjune Lee, Woo-Suk Noh, Hoyoung Jang, Jae-Hoon Park, Dongbin Shin, Changyong Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnon Spectra of Cuprates beyond Spin Wave Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20501v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The usual starting point for understanding magnons in cuprate antiferromagnets such as La$_2$CuO$_4$ is a spin model incorporating cyclic exchange, which descends from a one-band Hubbard model, and has parameters taken from fits based on non-interacting spin wave theory. Here we explore whether this provides a reliable description of experiment, using matrix product states (MPS) to calculate magnon spectra beyond spin wave theory. We find that analysis based on low orders of spin wave theory leads to systematic overestimates of exchange parameters, with corresponding errors in estimates of Hubbard $t/U$. Once these are corrected, the ''standard'' model provides a good account of magnon dispersion and lineshape in La$_2$CuO$_4$, but fails to fully capture the continuum observed at high energies. The extension of this analysis to CaCuO$_2$ and Sr$_2$IrO$_4$ is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20501v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.L012053</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, L012053 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiahui Bao, Matthias Gohlke, Jeffrey G. Rau, Nic Shannon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signature of preformed pairs in angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14490v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) and variational exact diagonalization (VED) to calculate the single-electron removal spectral weight for the Hubbard-Holstein model at low electron densities. Tuning the strength of the electron-phonon coupling and of the Hubbard repulsion allows us to contrast the results for a liquid of polarons versus a liquid of bipolarons. The former shows spectral weight up to the Fermi energy, as expected for a metal. The latter has a gap in its spectral weight, set by the bipolaron binding energy, although this is also a (strongly correlated) metal. This difference suggests that angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy could be used to identify liquids of pre-formed pairs. Furthermore, we show that the one-dimensional liquid of incoherent bipolarons is well approximated by a "Bose sea" of bosons that are hard-core in momentum space, occupying the momenta inside the Fermi sea but otherwise non-interacting. This new proposal for a strongly-correlated many-body wavefunction opens the way for studying various other properties of incoherent (non-superconducting) liquids of pre-formed pairs in any dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14490v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.096502</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 096502 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Klemen Kova\v{c}, Alberto Nocera, Andrea Damascelli, Janez Bon\v{c}a, Mona Berciu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Metastability driven Anomalous Hall Effect in Fe$_{x}$TaS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17453v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report here the observation of robust thermoremanent magnetization (TRM) in Fe-intercalated TaS$_2$ single crystal Fe$_{x}$TaS$_2$, which develops upon cooling under a moderate magnetic field of 500 Oe or higher. The thermoremanence is found to exist in a zero magnetic field up to a temperature as high as 160 K, which is well above the ferromagnetic Curie point ($T_C =$ 90 K) of the sample. The TRM in this compound can be traced back to the strong Ising character and the quasi-two-dimensional nature of the spins. The analysis of the magnetization data indicates the presence of short-range magnetic correlation in the form of a Griffiths singularity above $T_C$ to a temperature as high as 2$T_C$. The TRM is further manifested in the form of a large anomalous Hall effect (AHE) in zero magnetic field. In contrast to TRM, which exists well above $T_C$, the thermoremanent Hall effect vanishes as soon as the sample is heated above $T_C$. This may be an indication that a long-range ordered phase is essential for the emergence of AHE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17453v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamad Numan, Prasanta Chowdhury, Sanat Adhikary, Saurav Giri, Jhuma Sannigrahi, Matthias Gutmann, Souvik Chatterjee, Subham Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible quantum spin liquid state of CeTa$_7$O$_{19}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00752v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: CeTa$_7$O$_{19}$ is a recently found two-dimensional triangular lattice antiferromagnet without showing magnetic order. We grew high-quality CeTa$_7$O$_{19}$ single crystals and studied the low-temperature magnetic susceptibility, specific heat and thermal conductivity. The dc magnetic susceptibility and magnetization reveal its nature of effective spin-1/2, easy axis anisotropy, and antiferromagnetic spin coupling. The ultralow-temperature ac susceptibility and specific heat data indicate the absence of any phase transition down to 20 mK. The ultralow-temperature thermal conductivity ($\kappa$) at zero magnetic field exhibits a non-zero residual term $\kappa_0/T =$ 0.0056 W/K$^2$m. Although the magnetic field dependence of $\kappa$ is rather weak, the 14 T thermal conductivity shows an essential zero residual term. All these results point to a possible ground state of quantum spin liquid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00752v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Li, A. Rutherford, Y. Y. Wang, H. Liang, Y. Zhou, Y. Sun, D. D. Wu, P. F. Chen, Q. J. Li, H. Wang, W. Xie, E. S. Choi, S. Z. Zhang, M. Lee, H. D. Zhou, X. F. Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete Active Space Iterative Coupled Cluster Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06070v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the possibility of improving multireference-driven coupled cluster (CC) approaches with an algorithm that iteratively combines complete active space (CAS) calculations with tailored CC and externally corrected CC. This is accomplished by establishing a feedback loop between the CC and CAS parts of a calculation through similarity transformation of the Hamiltonian with those CC amplitudes that are not encompassed by the active space. We denote this approach the complete active space iterative coupled cluster (CASiCC) ansatz. We investigate its efficiency and accuracy in the singles and doubles approximation by studying the prototypical molecules H4, H8, H2O, and N2. Our results demonstrate that CASiCC systematically improves on the single-reference CCSD and the ecCCSD methods across entire potential energy curves, while retaining modest computational costs. However, the tailored coupled cluster method shows superior performance in the strong correlation regime suggesting that its accuracy is based on error compensation. We find that the iterative version of externally corrected and tailored coupled cluster methods converge to the same results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06070v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jpca.4c02316</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Chem. A 2024, 128, 8615-8627</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Robin Feldmann, Max M\"orchen, Jakub Lang, Micha{\l} Lesiuk, Markus Reiher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of fractional quantum Hall liquids coupled to quantum light and emergent graviton-polaritons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12292v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent breakthrough experiments have demonstrated how it is now possible to explore the dynamics of quantum Hall states interacting with quantum electromagnetic cavity fields. While the impact of strongly coupled non-local cavity modes on integer quantum Hall physics has been recently addressed, its effects on fractional quantum Hall (FQH) liquids -- and, more generally, fractionalized states of matter -- remain largely unexplored. In this work, we develop a theoretical framework for the understanding of FQH states coupled to quantum light. In particular, combining analytical arguments with tensor network simulations, we study the dynamics of a $\nu=1/3$ Laughlin state in a single-mode cavity with finite electric field gradients. We find that the topological signatures of the FQH state remain robust against the non-local cavity vacuum fluctuations, as indicated by the endurance of the quantized Hall resistivity. The entanglement spectra, however, carry direct fingerprints of light-matter entanglement and topology, revealing peculiar polaritonic replicas of the $U(1)$ counting. As a further response to cavity fluctuations, we also find a squeezed FQH geometry, encoded in long-wavelength correlations. By exploring the low-energy excited spectrum inside the FQH phase, we identify a new neutral quasiparticle, the graviton-polariton, arising from the hybridization between quadrupolar FQH collective excitations (known as gravitons) and light. Pushing the light-matter interaction to ultra-strong coupling regimes we find other two important effects, a cavity vacuum-induced Stark shift for charged quasi-particles and a potential instability towards a density modulated stripe phase, competing against the phase separation driven by the Stark shift. Finally, we discuss the experimental implications of our findings and possible extension of our results to more complex scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12292v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeno Bacciconi, Hernan Xavier, Iacopo Carusotto, Titas Chanda, Marcello Dalmonte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Chern-Simons-Maxwell Theory and its Chirality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11034v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We define and solve the $\text{U(1)}$ Chern-Simons-Maxwell theory on spacetime lattice, with an emphasis on the chirality of the theory. Realizing Chern-Simons theory on lattice has been a problem of interest for decades, and over the years it has gradually become clear that there are two key points: 1) Some non-topological term, such as a Maxwell term, is necessary -- this is true even in the continuum, but more manifestly on the lattice; 2) the $\text{U(1)}$ gauge field should be implemented in the Villainized form to retain its topological properties. Putting the two ideas together seriously, we show all interesting properties of a chiral Chern-Simons theory are reproduced in an explicitly regularized manner on the lattice. These include the bosonic and fermionic level quantization, the bulk and chiral edge spectrum, the Wilson loop flux attachment (with point-split framing or geometric framing depending on the Maxwell coupling), the Wilson loop spin, the ground state degeneracy, and, most non-trivially, the chiral gravitational anomaly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11034v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ze-An Xu, Jing-Yuan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on 2501.17230 and 2502.00103 "Phonon-mediated electron attraction in SrTiO3 via the generalized Frohlich and deformation potential mechanisms" and "Theory of ab initio downfolding with arbitrary range electron-phonon coupling"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00041v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This comment critically examines the claims made in arXiv papers arXiv:2501.17230 and arXiv:2502.00103, which argue that a multiplicity of polar optical phonons can generate a long-range attractive interaction via a generalized Frohlich coupling. I identify a fundamental flaw in their derivation, showing that their result relies on an unphysical assumption--specifically, neglecting the intermode Coulomb interactions between different polar optical phonons. By restoring these missing interactions I show the screened Coulomb interaction is always repulsive in the static limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00041v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Ruhman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
