<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.str-el updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el</link>
    <description>cond-mat.str-el updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.str-el" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 05:00:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Soft symmetries of topological orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: (2+1)D topological orders possess emergent symmetries given by a group $\text{Aut}(\mathcal{C})$, which consists of the braided tensor autoequivalences of the modular tensor category $\mathcal{C}$ that describes the anyons. In this paper we discuss cases where $\text{Aut}(\mathcal{C})$ has elements that neither permute anyons nor are associated to any symmetry fractionalization but are still non-trivial, which we refer to as soft symmetries. We point out that one can construct topological defects corresponding to such exotic symmetry actions by decorating with a certain class of gauged SPT states that cannot be distinguished by their torus partition function. This gives a physical interpretation to work by Davydov on soft braided tensor autoequivalences. This has a number of important implications for the classification of gapped boundaries, non-invertible spontaneous symmetry breaking, and the general classification of symmetry-enriched topological phases of matter. We also demonstrate analogous phenomena in higher dimensions, such as (3+1)D gauge theory with gauge group given by the quaternion group $Q_8$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03314v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryohei Kobayashi, Maissam Barkeshli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-Induced Ordered Phases in Anisotropic Spin-1/2 Kitaev Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by intense research on two-dimensional spin-1/2 Kitaev materials, Kitaev spin chains and ladders, though geometrically limited, have been studied for their numerical simplicity and insights into extended Kitaev models. The phase diagrams under the magnetic field were also explored for these quasi-one dimensional models. For an isotropic Kitaev chain, it was found that a magnetic field polarizes the ground state except along the symmetric field angle, where the chain is found to remain gapless up to a critical field strength where it enters an intriguing soliton phase before reaching the polarized state at higher field strengths. Here we study an anisotropic Kitaev chain under a magnetic field using the density matrix renormalization group technique, where the ground state has a macroscopic degeneracy with a finite gap in the absence of the magnetic field. When the field is mainly aligned parallel to the strong bond, four-site and large unit-cell ordered phases arise. In a certain angle of the field, another ordered phase characterized by a uniform chirality with six-site periodicity emerges. We employ a perturbation theory to understand such field-induced ordered phases. The effective model uncovers the presence of transverse Ising and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions between unit cells, as well as further-neighbor Ising interaction induced by the magnetic field, which collectively explain the mechanisms behind these ordered states. Open questions and challenges are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03329v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mandev Bhullar, Haoting Xu, Hae-Young Kee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallisation of the Mott Insulator Ca$_{2}$RuO$_{4}$ using Electric Double-Layer Gating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03591v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To verify whether the Mott insulator Ca2RuO4 can be switched by applying electric-field alone, regardless of current flow, we employ metallisation using electric double-layer gating (EDLG). The resistance change due to EDLG occurs only when positive gate-voltage above +3 V is applied. The amplitude of the reduction, reaching ~97% of the initial value, is difficult to interpret as surface metallisation and is likely related to structural change in bulk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03591v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuhiro Sakami, Hiroki Ogura, Akihiro Ino, Takumi Ouchi, Tsutomu Nojima, Fumihiko Nakamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic magnetism and spin fluctuations in the triangular-lattice spin-liquid candidate NaYbSe$_2$: a single-crystal $^{23}$Na and $^{77}$Se NMR study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ytterbium-based delafossite NaYbSe$_2$ is discussed as a prototype for a spin-orbit entangled, effective spin-1/2 triangular spin lattice with emerging antiferromagnetic correlations and a quantum-spin-liquid (QSL) ground state. We report on a comprehensive study of the static and dynamic anisotropic magnetism in single-crystalline samples of NaYbSe$_2$, using NMR spectroscopy as a local-probe technique. We performed $^{23}$Na and $^{77}$Se NMR measurements in magnetic fields up to 16 T, applied along the in-plane and out-of-plane crystallographic directions and at temperatures from 300 down to 0.3 K. We could determine the anisotropic hyperfine contributions from the angular dependence of the $^{23}$Na and $^{77}$Se NMR spectra. In the paramagnetic regime, we probed the temperature dependence of the $^{23}$Na and $^{77}$Se spectral shift and the hyperfine coupling constants for fields applied along the principal crystal axes. The spin-lattice relaxation-rate data indicate critical spin fluctuations and the absence of long-range magnetic order at low magnetic fields and temperatures down to 0.3 K, evidenced by a monotonic increase of $1/T_1$ and associated spectral broadening. This is a clear proof of the evolution of a critical QSL ground state with residual fluctuations down to lowest temperatures. At elevated fields, we observe the emergence of long-range order, as the temperature-dependent $1/T_1$ rate passes through a pronounced maximum at $T_N$ at given field, followed by a decrease at lower temperatures. Further, we find an inhomogeneous broadening of the $^{23}$Na spectra below $T_N$, probing the histogram of the local-field distribution in the presence of the field-induced order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03634v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.214440</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 214440 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Luther, K. M. Ranjith, Th. Doert, J. Wosnitza, H. K\"uhne, M. Baenitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terahertz-driven ultrafast dynamics of rare-earth nickelates by controlling only the charge degree of freedom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03650v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An important strategy for understanding the microscopic physics of strongly correlated systems and enhancing their technological potential is to selectively drive the fundamental degrees of freedom out of equilibrium. Intense terahertz (THz) pulses with photon energies of a few meV, can not only serve this purpose but also unravel their electronic and quantum nature. Here, we present THz-driven ultrafast dynamics of rare-earth nickelates $\text{RNiO}_{\text{3}}$, $\text{R}$ = rare-earth atom) - a prototype system to study the Mott insulator-metal transition (IMT). The THz drive of its Mott insulating state induces instantaneous IMT via quantum tunneling of valence electrons across the bandgap while the THz drive of its correlated metallic state leads to overall heating of the conduction electrons. The subsequent relaxations of excited electrons in these two states occur via a two-step process (electron-phonon thermalization and recovery of the charge-ordered insulating state) and a one-step process (electron-phonon scattering), respectively. The relaxation dynamics of the electrons and the absence of acoustic phonon modes, in particular, suggest that the THz photons drive only the charge degree of freedom. The purely electronic, ultrafast and local nature of the THz-induced IMT offers its applications in opto-electronics with enhanced performance and minimal device size and heat dissipation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03650v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gulloo Lal Prajapati, Sergey Kovalev, Igor Ilyakov, Atiqa Arshad, Gaurav Dubey, Ketan S. Navale, Dhanvir Singh Rana, Jan-Christoph Deinert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transport in integrable and perturbed easy-axis Heisenberg chain: Thouless approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study transport in the spin chains by employing the Thouless approach based on the level sensitivity to the boundary conditions, $R$. Although spin transport in the integrable easy-axis XXZ model is diffusive, corresponding $R$ is much closer to ballistic chains than to chaotic diffusive systems. In the case of the grand canonical ensemble this observation can be rigorously justified, while in the case of the canonical ensemble it can be demonstrated by numerical calculations. Integrability breaking perturbation (IBP) strongly reduces $R$ which reveals a pronounced minimum at the crossover from anomalous diffusive to normal dissipative transport. This minimum coincides with the onset of the universality of the random matrix theory. Results for various IBP suggest a discontinuous jump of the spin conductivity in the thermodynamic limit, and moreover that its value universally decreases when the strength of IBP decreases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03735v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Pawlowski, M. Mierzejewski, P. Prelovsek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gapless Symmetry-Protected Topological States in Measurement-Only Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurement-only quantum circuits offer a versatile platform for realizing intriguing quantum phases of matter. However, gapless symmetry-protected topological (gSPT) states remain insufficiently explored in these settings. In this Letter, we generalize the notion of gSPT to the critical steady state by investigating measurement-only circuits. Using large-scale Clifford circuit simulations, we investigate the steady-state phase diagram across several families of measurement-only circuits that exhibit topological nontrivial edge states at criticality. In the Ising cluster circuits, we uncover a symmetry-enriched non-unitary critical point, termed symmetry-enriched percolation, characterized by both topologically nontrivial edge states and string operator. Additionally, we demonstrate the realization of a steady-state gSPT phase in a $\mathbb Z_4$ circuit model. This phase features topological edge modes and persists within steady-state critical phases under symmetry-preserving perturbations. Furthermore, we provide a unified theoretical framework by mapping the system to the Majorana loop model, offering deeper insights into the underlying mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03851v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xue-Jia Yu, Sheng Yang, Shuo Liu, Hai-Qing Lin, Shao-Kai Jian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slow convergence of spin-wave expansion and magnon dispersion in the 1/3 plateau of the triangular XXZ antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03887v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experiments on the quantum magnet K$_{2}$Co(SeO$_{3}$)$_{2}$, we study theoretically the excitation spectrum of the nearest-neighbour triangular XXZ model in the limit of strong easy-axis anisotropy, within the up-up-down (1/3-plateau) phase. We make an expansion in $\alpha =J_{xy}/J_{zz}$ instead of $1/S$ and calculate the magnon dispersion for any value of the spin $S$ at second order in $\alpha$, with two important conclusions: (i) the 1/S expansion converges very slowly for S=1/2, making spin-wave theory quantitatively inaccurate up to very large orders; (ii) compared to the linear spin-wave predictions, our magnon dispersion presents a much better agreement with experimental results on K$_{2}$Co(SeO$_{3}$)$_{2}$, for which $\alpha \simeq 0.08$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03887v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achille Mauri, Fr\'ed\'eric Mila</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical signatures of quenched and thermal disorder in the dynamics of correlated spin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutron scattering is frequently used to look for evidence of features indicative of quantum-entangled phases of matter such as continua from fractionalisation or quantised excitations. However, the non-specificity of these features and difficulty of both fully quantum treatments and semiclassical models of disorder, make the diagnosis of such states problematic. Here, we demonstrate the feasibility of semiclassical treatments of disordered systems for supercells of $\sim 10,000$ spins. By examining a number of classically disordered models we show the presence of quantised excitations, broad continua and anomalous damping originating from quenched disorder or large classical degeneracies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03980v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry Lane, Kipton Barros, Martin Mourigal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichotomy of electron-phonon interactions in the delafossite PdCoO$_2$: From weak bulk to polaronic surface coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03730v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The metallic delafossites host ultra-high mobility carriers in the bulk, while at their polar surfaces, intrinsic electronic reconstructions stabilise markedly distinct electronic phases, from charge-disproportionated insulators, to Rashba-split heavy-hole gases and ferromagnetic metals. The understanding of these phases has been strongly informed by surface spectroscopic measurements, but previous studies have been complicated by the presence of spatially varying terminations of the material surface. Here, we demonstrate the potential of microscopic-area angle-resolved photoemission to overcome these challenges. Our measurements of the model compound PdCoO$_2$ yield extremely high-quality spectra of the electronic structure, which allows us to place new experimental constraints on the weak electron-phonon coupling in the bulk of PdCoO$_2$, while revealing much stronger interactions at its surfaces. While the CoO$_2$-terminated surface exhibits a conventional weak-coupling behavior, our measurements reveal surprising spectroscopic signatures of polaron formation at the Pd-terminated surface, despite its pronounced metallicity. Together, our findings reveal how mode and symmetry-selective couplings can markedly tune the electron-phonon interactions in a single host material, here opening routes to stabilise surprisingly persistent polaronic quasiparticles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03730v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gesa-R. Siemann, Philip A. E. Murgatroyd, Tommaso Antonelli, Edgar Abarca Morales, Seunghyun Khim, Helge Rosner, Matthew D. Watson, Andrew P. Mackenzie, Phil D. C. King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic structure factor of Calogero-Sutherland fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03762v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The effective extended conformal field theory with symmetry W_infinity*{bar W_infinity} that describes the thermodynamic limit of the Calogero-Sutherland model is considered. The dynamic structure factor of the chiral component in the repulsive regime is determined and compared with the corresponding one of the free bosonic theory, given that both share isomorphic Hilbert spaces but differ in the time evolution of quantum states. In either case, a sharp response function peaked at only one resonant frequency is found, and the physical implications of this outcome are addressed. Furthermore, a detailed comparison between this result and the corresponding one obtained in the first quantized formulation of the Calogero-Sutherland model is provided. Complete agreement in the parameter region in which both results overlap is found. This outcome provides further support to the equivalence between the first and second quantized treatments of the Calogero-Sutherland model, in which the computational advantages from integrability in the first formulation are paralleled by those from the algebraic structure of the second.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03762v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fedrico L. Bottesi, Guillermo R. Zemba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical behavior of Non-Hermitian Kondo effect in a pseudogap system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17586v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A combined study of non-Hermitian physics and strong correlations can yield numerous intriguing effects. Authors of a previous study on the non-Hermitian Kondo model in the ultracold atoms reported the reversion of the renormalization group (RG) flow. In this paper, we investigate the non-Hermitian Kondo effect in the system with a specific form of density of states $\rho (\omega) \sim |\omega|^{r}(r&gt;0)$, known as the pseudogap system. We find that, for $r&lt;\frac{1}{2}$, our results from perturbative RG are consistent with those of the Hermitian pseudogap Kondo effect. For $r=\frac{1}{2}$, a fixed point with the reversion property emerges in the RG flow. For $r&gt;\frac{1}{2}$, an unstable fixed point appears in the complex plane of the parameter space. Furthermore, through the large-$N$ expansion, we validate the RG results for $r &lt; \frac{1}{2}$, finding that the self-consistent equations have non-trivial solutions in a specific region of the complex plane of the parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17586v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiasong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Models for Phases and Transitions with Non-Invertible Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05964v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-invertible categorical symmetries have emerged as a powerful tool to uncover new beyond-Landau phases of matter, both gapped and gapless, along with second order phase transitions between them. The general theory of such phases in (1+1)d has been studied using the Symmetry Topological Field Theory (SymTFT), also known as topological holography. This has unearthed the infrared (IR) structure of these phases and transitions. In this paper, we describe how the SymTFT information can be converted into an ultraviolet (UV) anyonic chain lattice model realizing, in the IR limit, these phases and transitions. In many cases, the Hilbert space of the anyonic chain is tensor product decomposable and the model can be realized as a quantum spin-chain Hamiltonian. We also describe operators acting on the lattice models that are charged under non-invertible symmetries and act as order parameters for the phases and transitions. In order to fully describe the action of non-invertible symmetries, it is crucial to understand the symmetry twisted sectors of the lattice models, which we describe in detail. Throughout the paper, we illustrate the general concepts using the symmetry category $\mathsf{Rep}(S_3)$ formed by representations of the permutation group $S_3$, but our procedure can be applied to any fusion category symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05964v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lakshya Bhardwaj, Lea E. Bottini, Sakura Schafer-Nameki, Apoorv Tiwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ambipolar doping of a charge-transfer insulator in the Emery model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19545v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the similarities and differences between adding or removing electrons from a charge-transfer insulator may provide insights about the origin of the electron-hole asymmetry found in cuprates. Here we study with cellular dynamical mean-field theory the Emery model set in the charge-transfer insulator regime, and dope it with either electrons or holes. We consider the normal state only and focus on the doping evolution of the orbital character of the dopants and on the nature of the doping driven transition. Regarding the orbital character of the dopants, we found an electron-hole asymmetry: doped electrons mostly enter the copper orbitals, whereas doped holes mostly enter the oxygen orbitals. Regarding the nature of the doping driven transition, we found no qualitative electron-hole asymmetry: upon either electron or hole doping, there is a two-stage transition from a charge-transfer insulator to a strongly correlated pseudogap and then to a metal. This shows that a strongly correlated pseudogap is an emergent feature of doped correlated insulators in two dimensions, in qualitative agreement with recent experiments on ambipolar Sr$_{1-x}$La$_{x}$CuO$_{2+y}$ cuprate films. Our results indicate that merely doping with holes or electrons a charge-transfer insulator is not sufficient for explaining the electron-hole asymmetry observed in the normal state phase diagram of cuprates. Our work reinforces the view that actual hole-doped cuprates are more correlated than their electron-doped counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19545v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.045117</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 045117 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. Sordi, G. L. Reaney, N. Kowalski, P. S\'emon, A. -M. S. Tremblay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current Correlations and Conductivity in SYK-Like Systems: An Analytical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20733v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a functional-based approach to compute thermal expectation values for actions expressed in the $G-\Sigma$ formalism, applicable to any time sequence ordering. Utilizing this framework, we analyze the linear response to an electric field in various Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) chains. We consider the SYK chain where each dot is a complex $q/2$-body interacting SYK model, and we allow for $r/2$-body nearest-neighbor hopping where $r=\kappa q$. We find exact analytical expressions in the large-$q$ limit for conductivities across all temperatures at leading order in $1/q$ for three cases, namely $\kappa = \{ 1/2, 1, 2\}$. When $\kappa = \{1/2, 1\}$, we observe linear-in-temperature $T$ resistivities at low temperatures, indicative of strange metal behavior. Conversely, when $\kappa = 2$, the resistivity diverges as a power law at low temperatures, namely as $1/T^2$, resembling insulating behavior. As $T$ increases, there is a crossover to Fermi liquid behavior ($\sim T^2$) at the minimum resistivity. Beyond this, another crossover occurs to strange metal behavior ($\sim T$). In comparison to previous linear-in-$T$ results in the literature, we also show that the resistivity behavior exists even below the MIR bound, indicating a true strange metal instead of a bad metal. In particular, we find for the $\kappa = 2$ case a smooth crossover from an insulating phase to a Fermi liquid behavior to a true strange metal and eventually becoming a bad metal as temperature increases. We extend and generalize previously known results on resistivities to all temperatures, do a comparative analysis across the three models where we highlight the universal features and invoke scaling arguments to create a physical picture out of our analyses. Remarkably, we find a universal maximum DC conductivity across all three models when the hopping coupling strength becomes large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20733v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.045111</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 045111 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Jha, Stefan Kehrein, Jan C. Louw</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Failure of the Crystalline Equivalence Principle for Weak Free Fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07203v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Interacting crystalline SPT phases were first classified by Thorngren and Else through the crystalline equivalence principle, suggesting that a spatial group symmetry can be treated as if it were an internal symmetry group. Using techniques from topology we elucidate how this principle holds for one of the proposals for the interacting bosonic case and yet fails for weak free fermion phases. Last we show how a variant of the principle does hold for strong crystalline free fermion phases, showing that it is not necessary for the cohomology theory to be of Borel type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07203v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Sheinbaum, Omar Antol\'in-Camarena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous Magnetotransport in the Paramagnetic State of a Magnetic Kagome Metal EuTi$_3$Bi$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02743v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the electrical transport properties of a magnetic kagome metal EuTi$_3$Bi$_4$, which undergoes magnetic ordering below $T_\mathrm{c}=10.5$ K. Unlike typical magnets showing anomalous magnetotransport in their ordered states, EuTi$_3$Bi$_4$ exhibits unusual magnetotransport behaviors in its paramagnetic phase. Specifically, the magnetoconductivity shows a linear dependence on magnetic field at low fields below $\sim 1$ T, and the Hall conductivity undergoes a sign change below about 2 T. These behaviors resemble those observed in the charge density wave (CDW) phase of kagome metals $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ ($A$ = K, Rb, Cs). The anomalous magnetotransport in $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ has commonly been attributed to the possible emergence of a time-reversal symmetry breaking chiral CDW order. However, given the absence of CDW in EuTi$_3$Bi$_4$ and its manifestation exclusively in the paramagnetic state, the anomalous magnetotransport observed in EuTi$_3$Bi$_4$ is likely associated with multiband transport and/or the van Hove singularities near the Fermi level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02743v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun Shu, Xinrun Mi, Yuhao Wei, Sixue Tao, Aifeng Wang, Yisheng Chai, Dashuai Ma, Xiaolong Yang, Mingquan He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong and weak symmetries and their spontaneous symmetry breaking in mixed states emerging from the quantum Ising model under multiple decoherence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12738v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Discovering and categorizing quantum orders in mixed many-body systems are currently one of the most important problems. Specific types of decoherence applied to typical quantum many-body states can induce a novel kind of mixed state accompanying characteristic symmetry orders, which has no counterparts in pure many-body states. We study phenomena generated by interplay between two types of decoherence applied to the one-dimensional transverse field Ising model (TFIM). We show that in the doubled Hilbert space formalism, the decoherence can be described by filtering operation applied to matrix product states (MPS) defined in the doubled Hilbert system. The filtering operation induces specific deformation of the MPS, which approximates the ground state of a certain parent Hamiltonian in the doubled Hilbert space. In the present case, such a parent Hamiltonian is the quantum Ashkin-Teller model, having a rich phase diagram with a critical lines and quantum phase transitions. By investigating the deformed MPS, we find various types of mixed states emergent from the ground states of the TFIM, and clarify phase transitions between them. In that study, strong and weak $Z_2$ symmetries play an important role, for which we introduce efficient order parameters, such as R\'{e}nyi-2 correlators, entanglement entropy, etc., in the doubled Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12738v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Orito, Yoshihito Kuno, Ikuo Ichinose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum many-body dynamics for fermionic t-J model simulated with atom arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00552v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The fermionic t-J model has been widely recognized as a canonical model in understanding various strongly correlated phases like cuprate high-Tc superconductivity. Simulating this model with controllable quantum platforms offers new possibilities to probe high-Tc physics, yet suffering challenges. Here we propose a novel scheme to realize the t-J model in a programmable Rydberg-dressed tweezer array. By properly engineering the Rydberg-dressed dipole-dipole interaction and inter-tweezer couplings, a highly tunable fermionic t-J model with next-nearest-neighbour hopping terms is achieved. We particularly explore quantum many-body dynamics in the large J/t limit, a regime far beyond the conventional optical lattices and cuprates. Notably, we predict a nontrivial self-pinning effect enforced by local quantum entanglement that characterizes a novel type of Hilbert space fragmentation. This effect leads to the breakdown of Krylov restricted thermalization. Our prediction opens a new horizon in exploring exotic quantum many-body dynamics with t-J model in tweezer arrays, and shall also make a step towards simulating the high-Tc physics in cold atom systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00552v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye-bing Zhang, Xin-Chi Zhou, Bao-Zong Wang, Xiong-Jun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetoelectric effect in van der Waals magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02070v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The magnetoelectric (ME) effect is a fundamental concept in modern condensed matter physics and represents the electrical control of magnetic polarisations or vice versa. Two-dimensional (2D) van-der-Waals (vdW) magnets have emerged as a new class of materials and exhibit novel ME effects with diverse manifestations. This review emphasizes some important recent discoveries unique to vdW magnets: multiferroicity on two dimensions, spin-charge correlation, atomic ME effect and current-induced intrinsic spin-orbit torque, and electrical gating control and magnetic control of their electronic properties. We also highlight the promising route of utilizing quantum magnetic hetero- or homo-structures to engineer the ME effect and corresponding spintronic and optoelectronic device applications. Due to the intrinsic two-dimensionality, vdW magnets with those ME effects are expected to form a new, exciting research direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02070v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>npj Quantum Materials XX, XXXX (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kai-Xuan Zhang, Giung Park, Youjin Lee, Beom Hyun Kim, Je-Geun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
