<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.acc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.acc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 04:02:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Alternative scenarios for the LHC based electron-proton collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00115v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Construction of the ERLC (twin LC) collider tangential to LHC will give opportunity to investigate ep collisions at essentially higher center-of-mass energies than ERL50 and LHC based ep collider. Luminosity estimations show that values well exceeding 10^{34} cm^{-2}s^{-1} can be achieved for ERLC and HL-LHC based ep colliders. Certainly, proposed ep colliders have great potential for clarifying QCD basics and new physics search in addition to providing precise PDFs for adequate interpretation of LHC experimental data. Another alternative to the ERL50 is to construct an e-ring with the same energy and length. In this case, 4.2x10^{33} cm^{-2}s^{-1} luminosity can be reached. The advantage of this option is that the {\mu}-ring can be installed instead of the e-ring as a next stage, which will allow it to reach a much higher center of mass energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00115v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. N. Akay, B. Dagli, B. Ketenoglu, A. Ozturk, S. Sultansoy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subrelativistic Alternating Phase Focusing Dielectric Laser Accelerators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.02434v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate a silicon-based electron accelerator that uses laser optical near fields to both accelerate and confine electrons over extended distances. Two dielectric laser accelerator (DLA) designs were tested, each consisting of two arrays of silicon pillars pumped symmetrically by pulse front tilted laser beams, designed for average acceleration gradients 35 and 50 MeV/m respectively. The DLAs are designed to act as alternating phase focusing (APF) lattices, where electrons, depending on the electron-laser interaction phase, will alternate between opposing longitudinal and transverse focusing and defocusing forces. By incorporating fractional period drift sections that alter the synchronous phase between $\pm 60^\circ$ off crest, electrons captured in the designed acceleration bucket experience half the peak gradient as average gradient while also experiencing strong confinement forces that enable long interaction lengths. We demonstrate APF accelerators with interaction lengths up to 708 ${\mu}$m and energy gains up to 23.7 $\pm$ 1.07 keV FWHM, a 25$\%$ increase from starting energy, demonstrating the ability to achieve substantial energy gains with subrelativistic DLA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.02434v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Payton Broaddus, Thilo Egenolf, Dylan S. Black, Melanie Murillo, Clarisse Woodahl, Yu Miao, Uwe Niedermayer, Robert L. Byer, Kenneth J. Leedle, Olav Solgaard</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
