<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.acc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.acc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 04:01:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>High-dimensional maximum-entropy phase space tomography using normalizing flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00236v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Particle accelerators generate charged particle beams with tailored distributions in six-dimensional (6D) position-momentum space (phase space). Knowledge of the phase space distribution enables model-based beam optimization and control. In the absence of direct measurements, the distribution must be tomographically reconstructed from its projections. In this paper, we highlight that such problems can be severely underdetermined and that entropy maximization is the most conservative solution strategy. We leverage \textit{normalizing flows} -- invertible generative models -- to extend maximum-entropy tomography to 6D phase space and perform numerical experiments to validate the model performance. Our numerical experiments demonstrate that flow-based entropy estimates are consistent with 2D maximum-entropy solutions and that normalizing flows can fit complex 6D phase space distributions to large measurement sets in reasonable time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00236v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Austin Hoover, Jonathan C. Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Performance Operation of a Direct-Current and Superconducting Radio-Frequency Combined Photocathode Gun</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting radio-frequency (SRF) guns are promising candidates to deliver high brightness continuous-wave (CW) electron beams for new generations of coherent linac light sources, ultrafast electron diffractions, MeV pulsed beam applications, etc. To solve the compatibility problem of semiconductor photocathodes, a hybrid gun combining a direct-current gap and an SRF cavity has been developed. The gun, employing K2CsSb photocathodes driven by a green laser, has been brought into stable CW operation with a dark current below 100 pA, delivering electron beams at an energy gain of 2.4 MeV, an electron bunch charge of 100 pC, and a repetition rate of 1 MHz. A normalized beam emittance of 0.54 mm-mrad has been achieved at the bunch charge of 100 pC and peak current of about 6 A. CW operation at 81.25 MHz repetition rate has also been tested with the maximum average beam current reaching 3 mA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00659v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Jia, T. Li, T. Wang, Y. Zhao, X. Zhang, H. Xu, Z. Liu, J. Liu, L. Lin, H. Xie, L. Feng, F. Wang, F. Zhu, J. Hao, S. Quan, K. Liu, S. Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerator system parameter estimation using variational autoencoded latent regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Particle accelerators are time-varying systems whose components are perturbed by external disturbances. Tuning accelerators can be a time-consuming process involving manual adjustment of multiple components, such as RF cavities, to minimize beam loss due to time-varying drifts. The high dimensionality of the system ($\sim$100 amplitude and phase RF settings in the LANSCE accelerator) makes it difficult to achieve optimal operation. The time-varying drifts and the dimensionality make system parameter estimation a challenging optimization problem. In this work, we propose a Variational Autoencoded Latent Regression (VALeR) model for robust estimation of system parameters using 2D unique projections of a charged particle beam's 6D phase space. In VALeR, VAE projects the phase space projections into a lower-dimensional latent space, and a dense neural network maps the latent space onto the space of system parameters. The trained network can predict system parameters for unseen phase space projections. Furthermore, VALeR can generate new projections by randomly sampling the latent space of VAE and also estimate the corresponding system parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01532v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahindra Rautela, Alan Williams, Alexander Scheinker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards latent space evolution of spatiotemporal dynamics of six-dimensional phase space of charged particle beams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01535v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Addressing the charged particle beam diagnostics in accelerators poses a formidable challenge, demanding high-fidelity simulations in limited computational time. Machine learning (ML) based surrogate models have emerged as a promising tool for non-invasive charged particle beam diagnostics. Trained ML models can make predictions much faster than computationally expensive physics simulations. In this work, we have proposed a temporally structured variational autoencoder model to autoregressively forecast the spatiotemporal dynamics of the 15 unique 2D projections of 6D phase space of charged particle beam as it travels through the LANSCE linear accelerator. In the model, VAE embeds the phase space projections into a lower dimensional latent space. A long-short-term memory network then learns the temporal correlations in the latent space. The trained network can evolve the phase space projections across further modules provided the first few modules as inputs. The model predicts all the projections across different modules with low mean squared error and high structural similarity index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01535v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahindra Rautela, Alan Williams, Alexander Scheinker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure Spike in The LBNF Absorber Core s Gun Drilled Cooling Channel from an Accident Beam Pulse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19448v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The LBNF Absorber consists of thirteen 6061-T6 aluminum core blocks. The core blocks are water cooled with de-ionized (DI) water which becomes radioactive during beam operations. The cooling water flows through gun-drilled channels in the core blocks. The cooling water is supplied by the LBNF Absorber Radioactive Water (RAW) cooling system which is designed as per ASME B31.3 Normal Fluid Service [1]. An uninhibited beam accident pulse striking the water channels was identified as a credible accident scenario. In this study, it is assumed that the beam pulse hits the Absorber directly without interacting with any of the other upstream beamline components. The beam parameters used for the LBNF beam are 120 GeV, 2.4 MW with a 1.2 s cycle time. The accident pulse lasts for 10 {\mu}s. The maximum energy is deposited in the 3rd aluminum core block. For the sake of simplicity, it is assumed that the accident pulse strikes the 1 in. ID water channel directly. The analysis here simulates the pressure rise in the water during and after the beam pulse and its effects on the aluminum piping components that deliver water to the core blocks. The weld strengths as determined by the Load and Resistance Factor Design (LRDF) and the Allowable Strength Design (ASD) are compared to the forces generated in the weld owing to the pressure spike. A transient structural analysis was used to determine the equivalent membrane, peak, and bending stresses and they were com-pared to allowable limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19448v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.18429/JACoW-IPAC2024-THPS42</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JACoW IPAC2024 (2024) THPS42</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Deshpande (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), P. Hurh (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), J. Hylen (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), A. Lee (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), J. Lewis (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), I. Rakhno (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), V. I. Sidorov (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), Z. Tang (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA), S. Tariq I. Tropin (FNAL, Batavia, IL, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian optimization scheme for the design of a nanofibrous high power target</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19490v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High Power Targetry (HPT) R&amp;D is critical in the context of increasing beam intensity and energy for next generation accelerators. Many target concepts and novel materials are being developed and tested for their ability to withstand extreme beam environments; the HPT R&amp;D Group at Fermilab is developing an electrospun nanofiber material for this purpose. The performance of these nanofiber targets is sensitive to their construction parameters, such as the packing density of the fibers. Lowering the density improves the survival of the target, but reduces the secondary particle yield. Optimizing the lifetime and production efficiency of the target poses an interesting design problem, and in this paper we study the applicability of Bayesian optimization to its solution. We first describe how to encode the nanofiber target design problem as the optimization of an objective function, and how to evaluate that function with computer simulations. We then explain the optimization loop setup. Thereafter, we present the optimal design parameters suggested by the algorithm, and close with discussions of limitations and future refinements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19490v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.18429/JACoW-IPAC2024-TUPS45</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JACoW IPAC2024 (2024) TUPS45</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>W. Asztalos (Illinois Institute of Technology), Y. Torun (Illinois Institute of Technology), S. Bidhar (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory), F. Pellemoine (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory), P. Rath (Indian Institute of Technology Bhubaneswar)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
