<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.acc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.acc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 05:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental verification of space-charge saturation scaling laws in high-gradient photocathode RF guns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the limits of photoemission yield in a high-gradient S-band radiofrequency photoinjector in the space-charge-dominated regime. Using an RF phase-scan technique, where the emitted charge is measured as a function of the RF-field phase in the gun, we directly monitor photoemission over a range of launch fields and laser parameters, enabling quantitative characterization of space-charge saturation. Measurements, supported by simulations and analytic modeling, confirm the characteristic charge-field scaling laws for pancake beams and provide the first experimental verification of cigar-regime scaling in an RF photogun. These results establish a predictive framework for identifying the onset of space-charge saturation and guide the optimization of photoinjectors for ultrafast electron diffraction, microscopy, and high-brightness light sources operating at ultra-high gradients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02035v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Denham, David Garcia, Atharva Kulkarni, Brian Schaap, Ziteng Liu, Pietro Musumeci, Daniele Filippetto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plasma Processing of FRIB Low-Beta Cryomodules using Higher-Order-Modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Improvement in SRF accelerator performance after in-tunnel plasma processing has been seen at SNS and CEBAF. Plasma processing development for FRIB quarter-wave and half-wave resonators (QWRs, HWRs) was initiated in 2020. Plasma processing on individual QWRs (beta = 0.085) and HWRs (beta = 0.53) has been found to significantly reduce field emission. A challenge for the FRIB cavities is the relatively weak fundamental power coupler (FPC) coupling strength (chosen for efficient continuous-wave acceleration), which produces a lot of mismatch during plasma processing at room temperature. For FRIB QWRs, driving the plasma with higher-order modes (HOMs) is beneficial to reduce the FPC mismatch and increase the plasma density. The first plasma processing trial on a spare FRIB QWR cryomodule was done in January 2024, with before-and-after bunker tests and subsequent installation into the linac tunnel. The first in-tunnel plasma processing trial was completed in September 2025. For both cryomodules, before-and-after cold tests showed a significant increase in the average accelerating gradient for field emission onset after plasma processing for some cavities. In parallel with the cryomodule trials, the use of dual-drive plasma is being explored with the goal of improving the effectiveness of plasma processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02151v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Tutt, W. Chang, K. Elliott, W. Hartung, S. Kim, K. Saito, T. Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Model of Heated Plasma Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02028v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the need to predict plasma density and temperature distributions created in the early stages of high-intensity laser-plasma interactions, we develop a fluid model of plasma expansion into vacuum that incorporates external heating. We propose a new three-parameter family of self-similar solutions for plasma expansion that models a wide range of spatiotemporal variations of the electron temperature. Depending on the relative scales of the heated plasma domain $L$, the Debye length $\lambda_D$ and an emergent ion-acoustic correlation length $\lambda_s$, characterized by the parameters $\lambda_s/\lambda_D$ and $L/\lambda_s$, a spectrum of dynamical behaviors for the expanding plasma are identified. The behavior is classified into five dynamical regimes, ranging from nearly quasineutral expansion to the formation of bare ion slabs susceptible to Coulomb explosion. The limiting self-similar solutions are analyzed, and the dynamics in the five asymptotic limits in the parameter space are detailed. Scaling relations for the length scales and energies of the expanding plasma are proposed. The self-similar framework is applied to laser-plasma interactions, specifically addressing the plasma dynamics at a target surface during prepulse-target interactions. The results offer insights into the expansion behavior based on the laser-plasma parameters, and scaling relations for optimizing laser-plasma schemes and guiding experimental designs in high-intensity laser experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02028v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ritwik Sain, Lance Labun, Ou Z. Labun, Bjorn Manuel Hegelich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEP3: A High-Luminosity e+e- Higgs and ElectroweakFactory in the LHC Tunnel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00541v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As stated in the 2019 European Strategy for Particle Physics (ESPP), it is of the utmost importance that the HL-LHC upgrade of the accelerator and the experiments be successfully completed in a timely manner. All necessary efforts should be devoted to achieving this goal. We also recall two of the principal recommendations of the 2019 ESPP for future accelerator initiatives, namely that 1) An electron-positron Higgs factory is the highest priority for the next collider (Rec. c). 2) Europe, together with its international partners, should investigate the technical and financial feasibility of a future hadron collider at CERN with a centre-of-mass energy of at least 100 TeV and with an electron-positron Higgs and electroweak factory as a possible first stage (Rec. e). A major objective in particle physics is always to operate an accelerator that allows a leap of an order of magnitude in the constituent centre-of-mass energy with respect to the previous one. We support FCC-ee and FCC-hh as the preferred option for CERN future, as it addresses both of the above recommendations.
  The guidance for the 2025 ESPP requests, in addition to the preferred option, the inclusion of ``prioritised alternatives to be pursued if the chosen preferred option turns out not to be feasible or competitive''. Proposed alternatives to the preferred FCC option include linear, muon colliders and LHeC accelerators. In response to this request we propose reusing the existing LHC tunnel for an electron-positron collider, called LEP3, as a back-up alternative if the FCC cannot proceed. LEP3 leverages much of the R\&amp;D conducted for FCC-ee, offers high-precision studies of Z, W, and Higgs bosons below the tt threshold, and offers potential physics performance comparable or superior to other fallback options at a lower cost while supporting continued R\&amp;D towards a next-generation energy frontier machine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00541v3</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Anastopoulos, R. Assmann, A. Ball, O. Bruning, O. Buchmueller, T. Camporesi, P. Collier, J Dainton, G. Davies, J. R. Ellis, B. Goddard, L. Gouskos, M. Klute, M. Koratzinos, G. Landsberg, K. Long, L. Malgeri, F. Maltoni, F. Moortgat, C. Mariotti, S. Myers, J. A. Osborne, M. Pierini, D. R. Tovey, D. Treille, T. S. Virdee, N. Wardle, M. Zanetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
