<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.acc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.acc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 05:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cryogenics of a superconducting LINAC : SPIRAL2 from commissioning to operation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The SPIRAL2 superconducting linear accelerator (LINAC), which has been operational since 2019, employs superconducting, independently phased RF resonators to deliver a wide range of particle beams. Designed for flexibility in particle types, intensities, and energies, it utilizes superconducting quarter-wave resonators (QWRs), whose performances are critically dependent on the reliability of the cryogenic operation. This paper reviews the evolution from commissioning to the routine operation of the SPIRAL2 cryogenic system, initially commissioned in 2017. It highlights the key challenges encountered, including thermo-acoustic oscillations, thermal management, and abnormal behavior of cavities. Furthermore, it explores the integration of thermodynamic modeling and machine learning techniques to enhance system control and diagnose issues. This work serves as a comprehensive resource for advancing the cryogenic operation and performance of superconducting LINACs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01196v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adnan Ghribi, Muhammad Aburas, Pierre-Emmanuel Bernaudin, Patrick Bonnay, Fran\c{c}ois Bonne, Fr\'ed\'eric Bouly, Marco Di Giacomo, Charly Lassalle, David Longuevergne, Fran\c{c}ois Millet, Jean-Pierre Thermeau, Arnaud Trudel, Quentin Tura, Adrien Vassal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Unruh effect for hyperbolic observers in spacetimes of maximal proper acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18155v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, after the introduction of the notion of spacetime of maximal proper acceleration and its associated fundamental geometric and kinematic properties, the Unruh temperature formula is generalized to the case of hyperbolic observers in spacetimes of maximal proper acceleration. Such a generalization implies the existence of a maximal value for the Unruh temperature. We discuss this result for an electrodynamic model of point charged particle in a spacetime of maximal proper acceleration. It is shown that according to this mathematical model, the maximal Unruh temperature must be of order $10^5\, K$ for current high acceleration gradient laser-plasma acceleration experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18155v5</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Gallego Torrom\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
