<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.acc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.acc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.acc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 05:01:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Standards and Safety: an Overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This note is intended to provide an overview of the implications of regulations and standards on the safety of mechanical equipment, with a focus on accelerator components. Each research facility has different internal rules and standards which are applicable to specific cases; however, the main reference legal frame in Europe is everywhere based on the applicable European Directives. After a brief introduction to the 'safety' for mechanical systems, the process of 'risk analysis' will be introduced. The majority of this note will then deal with regulations and standards for pressure and cryogenic equipment. The European Pressure Equipment Directive (PED) will be briefly described, together with the concept of 'harmonized standards' and their implications on the entire lifecycle of a pressure equipment, with some hints at the peculiarities of accelerator components. In the second part of this note, regulations and standards for machinery, load-lifting accessories and buildings will be briefly mentioned to complete the picture of the most common cases in an accelerator facility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17173v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Dassa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward a Fully Autonomous, AI-Native Particle Accelerator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This position paper presents a vision for self-driving particle accelerators that operate autonomously with minimal human intervention. We propose that future facilities be designed through artificial intelligence (AI) co-design, where AI jointly optimizes the accelerator lattice, diagnostics, and science application from inception to maximize performance while enabling autonomous operation. Rather than retrofitting AI onto human-centric systems, we envision facilities designed from the ground up as AI-native platforms. We outline nine critical research thrusts spanning agentic control architectures, knowledge integration, adaptive learning, digital twins, health monitoring, safety frameworks, modular hardware design, multimodal data fusion, and cross-domain collaboration. This roadmap aims to guide the accelerator community toward a future where AI-driven design and operation deliver unprecedented science output and reliability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17536v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Tennant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power attenuation in millimeter-wave and terahertz superconducting rectangular waveguides: linear response, TLS loss, and Higgs-mode nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17000v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superconducting waveguides are a promising platform for ultralow-loss transmission in the millimeter-wave to terahertz band under cryogenic conditions, with potential applications in astronomical instrumentation and emerging quantum technologies. We develop a framework, based on microscopic superconductivity theory, to evaluate the power-flow attenuation constant $\alpha$ of superconducting rectangular waveguides in the $100~\mathrm{GHz}$--THz range, applicable to arbitrary electronic mean free paths $\ell$ from the dirty limit $\ell\ll\xi_0$ to the clean limit $\ell\gg\xi_0$. We also derive an analytical expression for two-level-system (TLS)-induced attenuation $\alpha_{\rm TLS}$ in thin native oxide layers within the standard TLS model. Using this framework, we perform numerical evaluations of $\alpha$ for representative materials over standard waveguide sizes from WR15 to WR1. In the high-frequency regime $f \gtrsim 0.5 \Delta/h$, low attenuation favors the clean regime $\ell\gtrsim\xi_0$, indicating that high-purity materials can achieve very low attenuation below their gap frequency. For the TLS contribution, using parameter values representative of native Nb oxides, we find that $\alpha_{\rm TLS}$ can become relevant at sufficiently low temperatures $T/T_c\lesssim 0.1$-0.2, where quasiparticle dissipation is exponentially suppressed. Finally, we extend the discussion to the strong-excitation regime using a recently developed nonlinear-response theory within the Keldysh--Usadel framework of nonequilibrium superconductivity and show that nonlinear dissipation produces a Higgs-mode peak in $\alpha$ near $f\simeq \Delta/h$ via a Kerr-type nonlinearity of the dissipative conductivity. This peak provides a distinct hallmark of the Higgs mode that has been largely overlooked so far.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17000v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Kubo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tolerances to driver-witness misalignment in a quasilinear plasma wakefield accelerator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Plasma-based accelerators offer high accelerating gradients and scalability through staging or long plasma sources, which makes them good candidates for future accelerator and collider concepts. Proton-driven accelerators in particular have the potential to bring particles to high energy in a single stage. In the quasilinear regime - where the plasma wake is only partially evacuated - a witness bunch of electrons drives a cavitated wake, which acts to preserve the emittance of the portion of the witness inside this self-blowout. In the case of a misalignment between the driver and witness, this behaviour can persist, but its effectiveness is reduced. In this paper, we study transverse witness dynamics in this regime, and develop analytical models to describe the witness motion, and develop a metric to estimate emittance preservation based on a single parameter which estimates the density of the witness after phase mixing. Particle in cell simulations using the AWAKE Run 2c baseline parameters show excellent agreement with the predictive models developed. This work allows alignment constraints to be set both for the AWAKE experiment and other wakefield acceleration schemes operating in the quasilinear regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17468v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. C. Wilson, J. Farmer, K. Lotov, A. Pukhov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Alloy/Ferrite cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1201.1154</link>
      <description>arXiv:1201.1154v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: RF cavities loaded with magnetic alloy (MA) or ferrite ring cores are used in synchrotrons and storage rings if the maximum RF frequency is in the order of a few MHz. A simple model for the description of cavities of this type is derived. The most important parameters are defined, and some properties of the material and of the cavity are summarized. Different cavity configurations, development aspects, and several practical topics are covered. A few specific ferrite- and MA-loaded cavity systems are discussed as examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1201.1154v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harald Klingbeil (Technische Universit\"at Darmstadt,GSI Helmholtzzentrum f\"ur Schwerionenforschung GmbH)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
