<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.BM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM</link>
    <description>q-bio.BM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 04:02:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Electroporation-mediated Metformin for effective anticancer treatment of triple-negative breast cancer cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this research, we investigated the efficacy of Metformin, the most commonly administered type-2 diabetes drug for triple negative breast cancer (TNBC) treatment, due to its various anticancer properties. It is a plant-based bio-compound, synthesized as a novel biguanide, called dimethyl biguanide or metformin. One of the ways it operates is by hindering electron transport chain-complex I, in mitochondria, which causes a drop-in energy (ATP) generation. This eventually builds energetic stress and a decline in energy. Therefore, the natural cellular processes and proliferating tumor cells are obstructed. Here, we used electroporation, where, the MDA-MB-231, human TNBC cells were subjected to high intensity, short-duration electrical pulses (EP) in the presence of Metformin. The cell viability results indicate lower cell viability of 43.45% as compared to 85.20% with drug alone at 5mM concentration. This indicates that Metformin, the most common diabetes drug could also be explored for cancer treatment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14353v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Praveen Sahu, Ignacio G. Camarillo, Pragatheiswar Giri, Raji Sundararajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved cryo-EM Pose Estimation and 3D Classification through Latent-Space Disentanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.04956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.04956v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Due to the extremely low signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) and unknown poses (projection angles and image shifts) in cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) experiments, reconstructing 3D volumes from 2D images is very challenging. In addition to these challenges, heterogeneous cryo-EM reconstruction requires conformational classification. In popular cryo-EM reconstruction algorithms, poses and conformation classification labels must be predicted for every input cryo-EM image, which can be computationally costly for large datasets. An emerging class of methods adopted the amortized inference approach. In these methods, only a subset of the input dataset is needed to train neural networks for the estimation of poses and conformations. Once trained, these neural networks can make pose/conformation predictions and 3D reconstructions at low cost for the entire dataset during inference. Unfortunately, when facing heterogeneous reconstruction tasks, it is hard for current amortized-inference-based methods to effectively estimate the conformational distribution and poses from entangled latent variables. Here, we propose a self-supervised variational autoencoder architecture called "HetACUMN" based on amortized inference. We employed an auxiliary conditional pose prediction task by inverting the order of encoder-decoder to explicitly enforce the disentanglement of conformation and pose predictions. Results on simulated datasets show that HetACUMN generated more accurate conformational classifications than other amortized or non-amortized methods. Furthermore, we show that HetACUMN is capable of performing heterogeneous 3D reconstructions of a real experimental dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.04956v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weijie Chen, Yuhang Wang, Lin Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric-Facilitated Denoising Diffusion Model for 3D Molecule Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02683v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Denoising diffusion models have shown great potential in multiple research areas. Existing diffusion-based generative methods on de novo 3D molecule generation face two major challenges. Since majority heavy atoms in molecules allow connections to multiple atoms through single bonds, solely using pair-wise distance to model molecule geometries is insufficient. Therefore, the first one involves proposing an effective neural network as the denoising kernel that is capable to capture complex multi-body interatomic relationships and learn high-quality features. Due to the discrete nature of graphs, mainstream diffusion-based methods for molecules heavily rely on predefined rules and generate edges in an indirect manner. The second challenge involves accommodating molecule generation to diffusion and accurately predicting the existence of bonds. In our research, we view the iterative way of updating molecule conformations in diffusion process is consistent with molecular dynamics and introduce a novel molecule generation method named Geometric-Facilitated Molecular Diffusion (GFMDiff). For the first challenge, we introduce a Dual-Track Transformer Network (DTN) to fully excevate global spatial relationships and learn high quality representations which contribute to accurate predictions of features and geometries. As for the second challenge, we design Geometric-Facilitated Loss (GFLoss) which intervenes the formation of bonds during the training period, instead of directly embedding edges into the latent space. Comprehensive experiments on current benchmarks demonstrate the superiority of GFMDiff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02683v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1609/aaai.v38i1.27787</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence 38, no. 1 (March 25, 2024): 338-346</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Can Xu, Haosen Wang, Weigang Wang, Pengfei Zheng, Hongyang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
