<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.BM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM</link>
    <description>q-bio.BM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 04:01:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Molecular Ground-State Conformation via Conformation Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Predicting ground-state conformation from the corresponding molecular graph is crucial for many chemical applications, such as molecular modeling, molecular docking, and molecular property prediction. Recently, many learning-based methods have been proposed to replace time-consuming simulations for this task. However, these methods are often inefficient and sub-optimal as they merely rely on molecular graph information to make predictions from scratch. In this work, considering that molecular low-quality conformations are readily available, we propose a novel framework called ConfOpt to predict molecular ground-state conformation from the perspective of conformation optimization. Specifically, ConfOpt takes the molecular graph and corresponding low-quality 3D conformation as inputs, and then derives the ground-state conformation by iteratively optimizing the low-quality conformation under the guidance of the molecular graph. During training, ConfOpt concurrently optimizes the predicted atomic 3D coordinates and the corresponding interatomic distances, resulting in a strong predictive model. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ConfOpt significantly outperforms existing methods, thus providing a new paradigm for efficiently and accurately predicting molecular ground-state conformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09795v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fanmeng Wang, Minjie Cheng, Hongteng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systems-Structure-Based Drug Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in generative deep learning have transformed small molecule design, but most methods lack biological systems context, focusing narrowly on specific protein pockets. We introduce a non-differentiable diffusion guidance method that integrates systems biology models, enhancing small molecule generation with pathway context. Using the Bone Morphogenetic Protein (BMP) pathway, we generate small molecules specific to one protein over competing proteins. This method enhances the precision and efficiency of small molecule drug discovery by incorporating systems biology insights into generative models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10108v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent D. Zaballa, Elliot E. Hui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examining the Link Between Peroxiredoxin Proteins and Mutually Exclusive Transcription Factor Activation With a Mathematical Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Oxidative stress is a fundamental stimulus to which eukaryotic cells respond via many channels. Among these channels are both protein systems that process oxidative stress, such as the 2-Cys peroxiredoxin-thioredoxin system (PTRS), as well as changes in transcriptional activity that target outcomes such as growth, damage control and repair, or cell death. Recent work has revealed connections between the PTRS and temporal phases of transcriptional activity involving famous transcription factors like p53 and FOXO1. To examine potential mechanisms for these connections, we implement an existing dynamical systems mathematical model for the PTRS. We hypothesize that dose-dependent hyperoxidation events enact ultrasensitive switches by which the PTRS can categorize stress severity and activate appropriate transcriptional responses. Using numerical simulations of the PTRS in human cells, we provide a proof of principle for staggered, switchlike hyperoxidation of peroxiredoxins (Prx) as well as an underlying mechanism requiring simultaneous signaling by Prx I and II. Then, we use our model to make testable predictions about individual Prx knockouts as well as the affinity for hydrogen peroxide of Prx across oxidation states. This study provides direction for future experimental work and sheds light into the mechanisms underlying oxidative stress response in human cells.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10145v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Schlamowitz, Andrew L. Paek, Kevin K. Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boltzmann-Aligned Inverse Folding Model as a Predictor of Mutational Effects on Protein-Protein Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09543v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Predicting the change in binding free energy ($\Delta \Delta G$) is crucial for understanding and modulating protein-protein interactions, which are critical in drug design. Due to the scarcity of experimental $\Delta \Delta G$ data, existing methods focus on pre-training, while neglecting the importance of alignment. In this work, we propose the Boltzmann Alignment technique to transfer knowledge from pre-trained inverse folding models to $\Delta \Delta G$ prediction. We begin by analyzing the thermodynamic definition of $\Delta \Delta G$ and introducing the Boltzmann distribution to connect energy with protein conformational distribution. However, the protein conformational distribution is intractable; therefore, we employ Bayes' theorem to circumvent direct estimation and instead utilize the log-likelihood provided by protein inverse folding models for $\Delta \Delta G$ estimation. Compared to previous inverse folding-based methods, our method explicitly accounts for the unbound state of protein complex in the $\Delta \Delta G$ thermodynamic cycle, introducing a physical inductive bias and achieving both supervised and unsupervised state-of-the-art (SoTA) performance. Experimental results on SKEMPI v2 indicate that our method achieves Spearman coefficients of 0.3201 (unsupervised) and 0.5134 (supervised), significantly surpassing the previously reported SoTA values of 0.2632 and 0.4324, respectively. Futhermore, we demonstrate the capability of our method on binding energy prediction, protein-protein docking and antibody optimization tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09543v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoran Jiao, Weian Mao, Wengong Jin, Peiyuan Yang, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barlow Twins Deep Neural Network for Advanced 1D Drug-Target Interaction Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00040v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of drug-target interactions is critical for advancing drug discovery. By reducing time and cost, machine learning and deep learning can accelerate this laborious discovery process. In a novel approach, BarlowDTI, we utilise the powerful Barlow Twins architecture for feature-extraction while considering the structure of the target protein. Our method achieves state-of-the-art predictive performance against multiple established benchmarks using only one-dimensional input. The use of gradient boosting machine as the underlying predictor ensures fast and efficient predictions without the need for substantial computational resources. We also investigate how the model reaches its decision based on individual training samples. By comparing co-crystal structures, we find that BarlowDTI effectively exploits catalytically active and stabilising residues, highlighting the model's ability to generalise from one-dimensional input data. In addition, we further benchmark new baselines against existing methods. Together, these innovations improve the efficiency and effectiveness of drug-target interaction predictions, providing robust tools for accelerating drug development and deepening the understanding of molecular interactions. Therefore, we provide an easy-to-use web interface that can be freely accessed at https://www.bio.nat.tum.de/oc2/barlowdti .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00040v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian G. Schuh, Davide Boldini, Annkathrin I. Bohne, Stephan A. Sieber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endhered patterns in matchings and RNA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18802v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An endhered (end-adhered) pattern is a subset of arcs in matchings, such that the corresponding starting points are consecutive and the same holds for the ending points. Such patterns are in one-to-one correspondence with the permutations. We focus on the occurrence frequency of such patterns in matchings and native (real-world) RNA structures with pseudoknots. We present combinatorial results related to the distribution and asymptotic behavior of the pattern 21, which corresponds to two consecutive base pairs frequently encountered in RNA, and the pattern 12, representing the archetypal minimal pseudoknot. We show that in matchings these two patterns are equidistributed, which is quite different from what we can find in native RNAs. We also examine the distribution of endhered patterns of size 3, showing how the patterns change under the transformation called endhered twist. Finally, we compute the distributions of endhered patterns of size 2 and 3 in native secondary RNA structures with pseudoknots and discuss possible outcomes of our study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18802v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'elia Biane, Greg Hampikian, Sergey Kirgizov, Khaydar Nurligareev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
