<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.BM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM</link>
    <description>q-bio.BM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 02:58:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Expert LLMs Guided Multi-Objective Molecular Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03503v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular optimization is a crucial yet complex and time-intensive process that often acts as a bottleneck for drug development. Traditional methods rely heavily on trial and error, making multi-objective optimization both time-consuming and resource-intensive. Current AI-based methods have shown limited success in handling multi-objective optimization tasks, hampering their practical utilization. To address this challenge, we present MultiMol, a collaborative large language model (LLM) system designed to guide multi-objective molecular optimization. MultiMol comprises two agents, including a data-driven worker agent and a literature-guided research agent. The data-driven worker agent is a large language model being fine-tuned to learn how to generate optimized molecules considering multiple objectives, while the literature-guided research agent is responsible for searching task-related literature to find useful prior knowledge that facilitates identifying the most promising optimized candidates. In evaluations across six multi-objective optimization tasks, MultiMol significantly outperforms existing methods, achieving a 82.30% success rate, in sharp contrast to the 27.50% success rate of current strongest methods. To further validate its practical impact, we tested MultiMol on two real-world challenges. First, we enhanced the selectivity of Xanthine Amine Congener (XAC), a promiscuous ligand that binds both A1R and A2AR, successfully biasing it towards A1R. Second, we improved the bioavailability of Saquinavir, an HIV-1 protease inhibitor with known bioavailability limitations. Overall, these results indicate that MultiMol represents a highly promising approach for multi-objective molecular optimization, holding great potential to accelerate the drug development process and contribute to the advancement of pharmaceutical research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03503v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiajun Yu, Yizhen Zheng, Huan Yee Koh, Shirui Pan, Tianyue Wang, Haishuai Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Iodine Deficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02981v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a four-unit, four-component mathematical model of iodine metabolism and its impact on thyroid hormone levels in the body. We focus on the relationships between iodine (I-), triiodothyronine (T3), thyroxine (T4), and thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) through the mixer, thyroid, sensor (pituitary gland), and metabolism. Iodine plays a fundamental role in maintaining metabolic homeostasis, as it is essential for the synthesis of T3 and T4, which regulate weight, energy, and other physiological functions. Iodine deficiency, which is one of the most common nutrient deficiencies in the world, can lead to hypothyroidism, a condition characterized by fatigue, weight gain, and cognitive impairments [1].
  Our model tracks the movement of iodine through dietary intake, thyroid absorption, hormone synthesis, feedback regulation via TSH, and deiodization in metabolism. By evaluating different forms of the accounting equation governing these processes, we have concluded three key results. 1) Iodide availability directly impacts levels of T3 and T4 production, with both component flow rates declining at day 70 in a mildly diseased state, and day 60 in a severely diseased state. 2) TSH is an early diagnostic indicator of thyroid issues, with TSH levels rising to magnitudes of 25x in just ten days, nearly six times quicker than other biological indicators. 3) There is a 5 day difference in iodine storage depletion between mild and severe iodide deficiency. Understanding these results quantitatively provides insights into thyroid disorders and informs strategies for managing iodine deficiency on both individual and public health levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02981v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Fong, Albert Li, Zoe Meadows, Rati Pillai, Chelsea Proutt, Alex Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent DFT-based study of bacteriochlorophyll a optical properties within the B800 part of Rhodoblastus acidophilus light-harvesting complex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use time-dependent density functional theory-based approaches, TD-DFT and TD-DFTB, to investigate the optical absorption of B800 part of Rhodoblastus acidophilus light-harvesting complex 2 (LH2). Both methods are shown to give qualitative agreement with experimental spectra for a single BChl a molecule and for the optimized structure of B800 complex containing nine of such molecules. We proved the absence of any sizable effects originating from the interaction between adjacent molecules, thus optical features of B800 LH2 part should not be attributed to the structural organization of pigments. In addition, time-dependent procedure itself was found to be crucial for the correct description of BChl a absorption spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03246v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evgenia A. Kovaleva, Lyudmila V. Begunovich, Maxim M. Korshunov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RNA-FrameFlow: Flow Matching for de novo 3D RNA Backbone Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13839v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce RNA-FrameFlow, the first generative model for 3D RNA backbone design. We build upon SE(3) flow matching for protein backbone generation and establish protocols for data preparation and evaluation to address unique challenges posed by RNA modeling. We formulate RNA structures as a set of rigid-body frames and associated loss functions which account for larger, more conformationally flexible RNA backbones (13 atoms per nucleotide) vs. proteins (4 atoms per residue). Toward tackling the lack of diversity in 3D RNA datasets, we explore training with structural clustering and cropping augmentations. Additionally, we define a suite of evaluation metrics to measure whether the generated RNA structures are globally self-consistent (via inverse folding followed by forward folding) and locally recover RNA-specific structural descriptors. The most performant version of RNA-FrameFlow generates locally realistic RNA backbones of 40-150 nucleotides, over 40% of which pass our validity criteria as measured by a self-consistency TM-score &gt;= 0.45, at which two RNAs have the same global fold. Open-source code: https://github.com/rish-16/rna-backbone-design</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13839v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Anand, Chaitanya K. Joshi, Alex Morehead, Arian R. Jamasb, Charles Harris, Simon V. Mathis, Kieran Didi, Bryan Hooi, Pietro Li\`o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling the Complex Multiplexed DIA Spectra in De Novo Peptide Sequencing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15684v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Data-Independent Acquisition (DIA) was introduced to improve sensitivity to cover all peptides in a range rather than only sampling high-intensity peaks as in Data-Dependent Acquisition (DDA) mass spectrometry. However, it is not very clear how useful DIA data is for de novo peptide sequencing as the DIA data are marred with coeluted peptides, high noises, and varying data quality. We present a new deep learning method DIANovo, and address each of these difficulties, and improves the previous established system DeepNovo-DIA by from 25% to 81%, averaging 48%, for amino acid recall, and by from 27% to 89%, averaging 57%, for peptide recall, by equipping the model with a deeper understanding of coeluted DIA spectra. This paper also provides criteria about when DIA data could be used for de novo peptide sequencing and when not to by providing a comparison between DDA and DIA, in both de novo and database search mode. We find that while DIA excels with narrow isolation windows on older-generation instruments, it loses its advantage with wider windows. However, with Orbitrap Astral, DIA consistently outperforms DDA due to narrow window mode enabled. We also provide a theoretical explanation of this phenomenon, emphasizing the critical role of the signal-to-noise profile in the successful application of de novo sequencing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15684v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Ma, Zeping Mao, Ruixue Zhang, Jiazhen Chen, Lei Xin, Paul Shan, Ali Ghodsi, Ming Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aligning Large Language Models and Geometric Deep Models for Protein Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05316v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Latent representation alignment has become a foundational technique for constructing multimodal large language models (MLLM) by mapping embeddings from different modalities into a shared space, often aligned with the embedding space of large language models (LLMs) to enable effective cross-modal understanding. While preliminary protein-focused MLLMs have emerged, they have predominantly relied on heuristic approaches, lacking a fundamental understanding of optimal alignment practices across representations. In this study, we explore the alignment of multimodal representations between LLMs and Geometric Deep Models (GDMs) in the protein domain. We comprehensively evaluate three state-of-the-art LLMs (Gemma2-2B, LLaMa3.1-8B, and LLaMa3.1-70B) with four protein-specialized GDMs (GearNet, GVP, ScanNet, GAT). Our work examines alignment factors from both model and protein perspectives, identifying challenges in current alignment methodologies and proposing strategies to improve the alignment process. Our key findings reveal that GDMs incorporating both graph and 3D structural information align better with LLMs, larger LLMs demonstrate improved alignment capabilities, and protein rarity significantly impacts alignment performance. We also find that increasing GDM embedding dimensions, using two-layer projection heads, and fine-tuning LLMs on protein-specific data substantially enhance alignment quality. These strategies offer potential enhancements to the performance of protein-related multimodal models. Our code and data are available at https://github.com/Tizzzzy/LLM-GDM-alignment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05316v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dong Shu, Bingbing Duan, Kai Guo, Kaixiong Zhou, Jiliang Tang, Mengnan Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
