<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.BM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM</link>
    <description>q-bio.BM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 02:58:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>TEMPO: Temporal Multi-scale Autoregressive Generation of Protein Conformational Ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the dynamic behavior of proteins is critical to elucidating their functional mechanisms, yet generating realistic, temporally coherent trajectories of protein ensembles remains a significant challenge. In this work, we introduce a novel hierarchical autoregressive framework for modeling protein dynamics that leverages the intrinsic multi-scale organization of molecular motions. Unlike existing methods that focus on generating static conformational ensembles or treat dynamic sampling as an independent process, our approach characterizes protein dynamics as a Markovian process. The framework employs a two-scale architecture: a low-resolution model captures slow, collective motions driving major conformational transitions, while a high-resolution model generates detailed local fluctuations conditioned on these large-scale movements. This hierarchical design ensures that the causal dependencies inherent in protein dynamics are preserved, enabling the generation of temporally coherent and physically realistic trajectories. By bridging high-level biophysical principles with state-of-the-art generative modeling, our approach provides an efficient framework for simulating protein dynamics that balances computational efficiency with physical accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05510v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaoyao Xu, Di Wang, Zihan Zhou, Tianshu Yu, Mingchen Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular Dynamics Simulations of Membrane Selectivity of Star Peptides Across Different Bacterial and Mammalian Bilipids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Structurally nanoengineered antimicrobial peptide polymers (SNAPPs) are emerging as promising selective agents against bacterial membranes. In this study, we used all atom molecular dynamics simulation techniques to investigate the interaction of a promising cationic SNAPP architecture (Alt-SNAPP with 8 arms made of alternating lysine and valine residues) with modelled Gram-negative, Gram-positive, mammalian, and red blood cell membranes. Alt-SNAPP exhibited rapid and stable binding to bacterial membranes, driven by electrostatic interactions with anionic lipids such as phosphatidylglycerol (PG) and cardiolipin (CL), and supported by membrane fluidity. In contrast, mammalian and red blood cell membranes, enriched in zwitterionic lipids and cholesterol, resisted peptide association entirely. Analyses of center of mass distance, partial density, hydrogen bonding, and interaction energy confirmed that SNAPP remains fully excluded from host like membranes while forming stable, multivalent interactions with bacterial bilayers. These findings provide mechanistic insight into membrane selectivity of SNAPP and offer a molecular framework for designing next generation antimicrobial polymers with minimal off target toxicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05513v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amal Jayawardena, Andrew Hung, Greg Qiao, Neil OBrien-Simpson, Elnaz Hajizadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Biomolecular Motion: The Physics-Informed Machine Learning Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The convergence of statistical learning and molecular physics is transforming our approach to modeling biomolecular systems. Physics-informed machine learning (PIML) offers a systematic framework that integrates data-driven inference with physical constraints, resulting in models that are accurate, mechanistic, generalizable, and able to extrapolate beyond observed domains. This review surveys recent advances in physics-informed neural networks and operator learning, differentiable molecular simulation, and hybrid physics-ML potentials, with emphasis on long-timescale kinetics, rare events, and free-energy estimation. We frame these approaches as solutions to the "biomolecular closure problem", recovering unresolved interactions beyond classical force fields while preserving thermodynamic consistency and mechanistic interpretability. We examine theoretical foundations, tools and frameworks, computational trade-offs, and unresolved issues, including model expressiveness and stability. We outline prospective research avenues at the intersection of machine learning, statistical physics, and computational chemistry, contending that future advancements will depend on mechanistic inductive biases, and integrated differentiable physical learning frameworks for biomolecular simulation and discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06585v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaryesh Deshpande</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>De Novo Design of SIK3 Inhibitors via Feedback-Driven Fine-Tuning of Seq2Seq-VAE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alzheimers disease (AD), a progressive neuro-degenerative disorder, currently lacks effective therapeutic strategies that can modify disease progression. Recent studies have highlighted the circadian rhythm critical role in AD pathophysiology, implicating circadian clock kinases, such as the Salt-Inducible Kinase 3 (SIK3), as promising therapeutic target. Generative AI models have surpassed traditional methods of drug discovery, untapping the vast unexplored chemical space of drug-like molecules. We present a sequence-to-sequence Variational Autoencoder (Seq2Seq-VAE) model guided by an Active Learning (AL) approach to optimize molecular generation. Our pipeline iteratively guided a pre-trained Seq2Seq-VAE model towards the pharmacological landscape relevant to SIK3 using a two-step framework, an inner loop that iteratively improves physiochemical properties profile, drug likeliness and synthesizability, followed by an outer loop that steer the latent space towards high-affinity ligands for SIK3. Our approach introduces feedback-driven optimization without requiring large labeled datasets, making it particularly suited for early-stage drug discovery in under-explored therapeutic targets. Our results demonstrate the models convergence toward SIK3-specific small molecules with desired properties and high binding affinity. This work highlights the use of generative AI combined with AL for rational drug discovery that can be extended to other protein targets with minimal modifications, offering a scalable solution to the molecular design bottleneck in drug design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06930v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>ShahZeb Khan, Chiara Pallara, Barbara Monti, Alexis Molina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A critical assessment of the role of topology on protein thermal stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07024v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For several decades, experimental and computational studies have been used to investigate the potential functional role of knots in protein structures. A property that has attracted considerable attention is thermal stability, i.e., the extent to which a protein retains its native conformation and biological activity at high temperatures, without undergoing denaturation or aggregation. Thermal stability is quantified by the melting temperature $T_m$, an equilibrium property that corresponds to the peak of heat capacity in differential scanning calorimetry experiments. Since protein energy does not depend on the topological state, equilibrium properties such as $T_m$ should not depend on the topology, provided that the exploration of the equilibrium space is ergodic. However, experimental and computational results reported in the literature provide conflicting views on this problem, with some studies reporting an enhancement of thermal stability for certain knotted proteins. Here, we use extensive Monte Carlo simulations of a simple C-alpha protein model of protein YibK to show in a comprehensive manner that $T_m$ does not depend on the topological state of the protein.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07024v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao N. C. Especial, Beatriz P. Teixeira, Ana Nunes, Miguel Machuqueiro, Patr\'icia F. N. Fa\'isca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>edible polysaccharides as stabilizers and carriers for the delivery of phenolic compounds and pigments in food formulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07264v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Food polysaccharides have emerged as suitable carriers of active substances and as additives to food and nutraceutical formulations, showing potential to stabilize bioactive compounds during the storage of microencapsulate preparations, even in the gastrointestinal tract following the intake of bioactive compounds, thereby improving their bioaccessibility and bioavailability. This review provides a comprehensive overview of the main polysaccharides employed as wall materials, including starch, maltodextrin, alginate, pectin, inulin, chitosan, and gum arabic, and discusses how structural interactions and physicochemical properties can benefit the microencapsulation of polyphenols and pigments. The main findings and principles of the major encapsulation techniques, including spray drying, freeze drying, extrusion, emulsification, and coacervation, related to the production of microparticles, were briefly described. Polysaccharides can entrap hydrophilic and hydrophobic compounds by physical interactions, forming a barrier around the nucleus or binding to the bioactive compound. Intermolecular binding between polysaccharides in the wall matrix, polyphenols, and pigments in the nucleus can confer up to 90% of encapsulation efficiency, governed mainly by hydrogen bonds and electrostatic interactions. The mixture of wall polysaccharides in the microparticles synthesis favors the encapsulation solubility, storage stability, bioaccessibility, and bioactivity of the microencapsulate compounds. Clinical trials on the bioefficacy of polyphenols and pigments loaded in polysaccharide microparticles are scarce and require further evidence to reinforce the use of this technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07264v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liliane Siqueira de Oliveira, Davi Vieira Teixeira da Silva, Lucileno Rodrigues da Trindade, Diego dos Santos Bai\~ao, Cristine Couto de Almeida, Vitor Francisco Ferreira, Vania Margaret Flosi Paschoalin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reaction Prediction via Interaction Modeling of Symmetric Difference Shingle Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06356v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chemical reaction prediction remains a fundamental challenge in organic chemistry, where existing machine learning models face two critical limitations: sensitivity to input permutations (molecule/atom orderings) and inadequate modeling of substructural interactions governing reactivity. These shortcomings lead to inconsistent predictions and poor generalization to real-world scenarios. To address these challenges, we propose ReaDISH, a novel reaction prediction model that learns permutation-invariant representations while incorporating interaction-aware features. It introduces two innovations: (1) symmetric difference shingle encoding, which computes molecular shingle differences to capture reaction-specific structural changes while eliminating order sensitivity; and (2) geometry-structure interaction attention, a mechanism that models intra- and inter-molecular interactions at the shingle level. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ReaDISH improves reaction prediction performance across diverse benchmarks. It shows enhanced robustness with an average improvement of 8.76% on R$^2$ under permutation perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06356v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runhan Shi, Letian Chen, Gufeng Yu, Yang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entangled Schr\"odinger Bridge Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulating trajectories of multi-particle systems on complex energy landscapes is a central task in molecular dynamics (MD) and drug discovery, but remains challenging at scale due to computationally expensive and long simulations. Previous approaches leverage techniques such as flow or Schr\"odinger bridge matching to implicitly learn joint trajectories through data snapshots. However, many systems, including biomolecular systems and heterogeneous cell populations, undergo dynamic interactions that evolve over their trajectory and cannot be captured through static snapshots. To close this gap, we introduce Entangled Schr\"odinger Bridge Matching (EntangledSBM), a framework that learns the first- and second-order stochastic dynamics of interacting, multi-particle systems where the direction and magnitude of each particle's path depend dynamically on the paths of the other particles. We define the Entangled Schr\"odinger Bridge (EntangledSB) problem as solving a coupled system of bias forces that entangle particle velocities. We show that our framework accurately simulates heterogeneous cell populations under perturbations and rare transitions in high-dimensional biomolecular systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07406v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sophia Tang, Yinuo Zhang, Pranam Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
