<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.BM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM</link>
    <description>q-bio.BM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 04:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral interactions between tropocollagen molecules determine the collagen microfibril structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21484v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Collagen is the most abundant structural protein in animals, forming hierarchically organised fibrils that provide mechanical support to tissues. Despite detailed structural studies, the physical principles that govern the formation of the characteristic axially-periodic collagen microfibril remain poorly understood. Here, we present a theoretical framework that links the amino acid sequence of tropocollagen to its supramolecular organisation. By combining statistical modeling of residue geometry with sequence-informed interaction potentials, we show that the chiral arrangement of outward-facing residues induces directional intermolecular interactions that drive molecular supercoiling. These interactions favour the formation of right-handed, pentameric microfibrils with a staggered axial periodicity of approximately 67 nm. Our simulations reveal that this structure emerges across a wide range of mammalian collagen sequences as a global energy minimum robust to biochemical noise. These findings provide a mechanistic explanation for collagen's supramolecular chirality and offer design principles for engineering synthetic collagen-mimetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21484v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Art'om Zolotarjov, Roland Kr\"oger, Dmitri O. Pushkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decision Tree for Protein Biomarker Selection for Clinical Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.08179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.08179v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Discovery of novel protein biomarkers for clinical applications is an active research field across a manifold of diseases. Despite some successes and progress, the biomarker development pipeline still frequently ends in failure as biomarker candidates cannot be validated or translated to immunoassays. Selection of strong disease biomarker candidates that further constitute suitable targets for antibody binding in immunoassays is thus important. This essential selection step can be supported and rationalized using bioinformatics tools such as protein databases. Here, I present a workflow in the form of decision trees to computationally investigate biomarker candidates and their available affinity reagents in depth. This analysis can identify the most promising biomarker candidates for assay development while minimal time and effort is required.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.08179v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-1-0716-4298-6_21</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>In: Islam Williams, T. (eds) Tissue Proteomics. Methods in Molecular Biology, vol 2884. Humana, New York, NY (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Katharina Waury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven Discovery of Biophysical T Cell Receptor Co-specificity Rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13722v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The biophysical interactions between the T cell receptor (TCR) and its ligands determine the specificity of the cellular immune response. However, the immense diversity of receptors and ligands has made it challenging to discover generalizable rules across the distinct binding affinity landscapes created by different ligands. Here, we present an optimization framework for discovering biophysical rules that predict whether TCRs share specificity to a ligand. Applying this framework to TCRs associated with a collection of SARS-CoV-2 peptides we systematically characterize how co-specificity depends on the type and position of amino-acid differences between receptors. We also demonstrate that the inferred rules generalize to ligands highly dissimilar to any seen during training. Our analysis reveals that matching of steric properties between substituted amino acids is more important for receptor co-specificity red than the hydrophobic properties that prominently determine evolutionary substitutability. Our analysis also quantifies the substantial importance of positions not in direct contact with the peptide for specificity. These findings highlight the potential for data-driven approaches to uncover the molecular mechanisms underpinning the specificity of adaptive immune responses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13722v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew G. T. Pyo, Yuta Nagano, Martina Milighetti, James Henderson, Curtis G. Callan Jr., Benny Chain, Ned S. Wingreen, Andreas Tiffeau-Mayer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Hierarchical Interaction for Accurate Molecular Property Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20127v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Discovering molecules with desirable molecular properties, including ADMET (Absorption, Distribution, Metabolism, Excretion, and Toxicity) profiles, is of great importance in drug discovery. Existing approaches typically employ deep learning models, such as Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) and Transformers, to predict these molecular properties by learning from diverse chemical information. However, these models often fail to efficiently capture and utilize the hierarchical nature of molecular structures, and lack mechanisms for effective interaction among multi-level features. To address these limitations, we propose a Hierarchical Interaction Message Passing Mechanism, which serves as the foundation of our novel model, HimNet. Our method enables interaction-aware representation learning across atomic, motif, and molecular levels via hierarchical attention-guided message passing. This design allows HimNet to effectively balance global and local information, ensuring rich and task-relevant feature extraction for downstream property prediction tasks, such as Blood-Brain Barrier Permeability (BBBP). Extensive experiments on multiple benchmark datasets demonstrate that HimNet achieves the best or near-best performance in most molecular property prediction tasks. Furthermore, our method exhibits promising hierarchical interpretability, aligning well with chemical intuition on representative molecules. We believe that HimNet offers an accurate and efficient solution for molecular activity and ADMET property prediction, contributing significantly to advanced decision-making in the early stages of drug discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20127v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huiyang Hong, Xinkai Wu, Hongyu Sun, Chaoyang Xie, Qi Wang, Yuquan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
