<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.BM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM</link>
    <description>q-bio.BM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.BM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 02:43:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Efficient Molecular Property Optimization with Graph Energy Based Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12219v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimizing chemical properties is a challenging task due to the vastness and complexity of chemical space. Here, we present a generative energy-based architecture for implicit chemical property optimization, designed to efficiently generate molecules that satisfy target properties without explicit conditional generation. We use Graph Energy Based Models and a training approach that does not require property labels. We validated our approach on well-established chemical benchmarks, showing superior results to state-of-the-art methods and demonstrating robustness and efficiency towards de novo drug design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12219v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Miglior, Lorenzo Simone, Marco Podda, Davide Bacciu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniMatch: Universal Matching from Atom to Task for Few-Shot Drug Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Drug discovery is crucial for identifying candidate drugs for various diseases.However, its low success rate often results in a scarcity of annotations, posing a few-shot learning problem. Existing methods primarily focus on single-scale features, overlooking the hierarchical molecular structures that determine different molecular properties. To address these issues, we introduce Universal Matching Networks (UniMatch), a dual matching framework that integrates explicit hierarchical molecular matching with implicit task-level matching via meta-learning, bridging multi-level molecular representations and task-level generalization. Specifically, our approach explicitly captures structural features across multiple levels, such as atoms, substructures, and molecules, via hierarchical pooling and matching, facilitating precise molecular representation and comparison. Additionally, we employ a meta-learning strategy for implicit task-level matching, allowing the model to capture shared patterns across tasks and quickly adapt to new ones. This unified matching framework ensures effective molecular alignment while leveraging shared meta-knowledge for fast adaptation. Our experimental results demonstrate that UniMatch outperforms state-of-the-art methods on the MoleculeNet and FS-Mol benchmarks, achieving improvements of 2.87% in AUROC and 6.52% in delta AUPRC. UniMatch also shows excellent generalization ability on the Meta-MolNet benchmark.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12453v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruifeng Li, Mingqian Li, Wei Liu, Yuhua Zhou, Xiangxin Zhou, Yuan Yao, Qiang Zhang, Hongyang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MotifBench: A standardized protein design benchmark for motif-scaffolding problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12479v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The motif-scaffolding problem is a central task in computational protein design: Given the coordinates of atoms in a geometry chosen to confer a desired biochemical function (a motif), the task is to identify diverse protein structures (scaffolds) that include the motif and maintain its geometry. Significant recent progress on motif-scaffolding has been made due to computational evaluation with reliable protein structure prediction and fixed-backbone sequence design methods. However, significant variability in evaluation strategies across publications has hindered comparability of results, challenged reproducibility, and impeded robust progress. In response we introduce MotifBench, comprising (1) a precisely specified pipeline and evaluation metrics, (2) a collection of 30 benchmark problems, and (3) an implementation of this benchmark and leaderboard at github.com/blt2114/MotifBench. The MotifBench test cases are more difficult compared to earlier benchmarks, and include protein design problems for which solutions are known but on which, to the best of our knowledge, state-of-the-art methods fail to identify any solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12479v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoqi Zheng, Bo Zhang, Kieran Didi, Kevin K. Yang, Jason Yim, Joseph L. Watson, Hai-Feng Chen, Brian L. Trippe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NExT-Mol: 3D Diffusion Meets 1D Language Modeling for 3D Molecule Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: 3D molecule generation is crucial for drug discovery and material design. While prior efforts focus on 3D diffusion models for their benefits in modeling continuous 3D conformers, they overlook the advantages of 1D SELFIES-based Language Models (LMs), which can generate 100% valid molecules and leverage the billion-scale 1D molecule datasets. To combine these advantages for 3D molecule generation, we propose a foundation model -- NExT-Mol: 3D Diffusion Meets 1D Language Modeling for 3D Molecule Generation. NExT-Mol uses an extensively pretrained molecule LM for 1D molecule generation, and subsequently predicts the generated molecule's 3D conformers with a 3D diffusion model. We enhance NExT-Mol's performance by scaling up the LM's model size, refining the diffusion neural architecture, and applying 1D to 3D transfer learning. Notably, our 1D molecule LM significantly outperforms baselines in distributional similarity while ensuring validity, and our 3D diffusion model achieves leading performances in conformer prediction. Given these improvements in 1D and 3D modeling, NExT-Mol achieves a 26% relative improvement in 3D FCD for de novo 3D generation on GEOM-DRUGS, and a 13% average relative gain for conditional 3D generation on QM9-2014. Our codes and pretrained checkpoints are available at https://github.com/acharkq/NExT-Mol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12638v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Liu, Yanchen Luo, Han Huang, Enzhi Zhang, Sihang Li, Junfeng Fang, Yaorui Shi, Xiang Wang, Kenji Kawaguchi, Tat-Seng Chua</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
