<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 04:00:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Demonstration of Controllable PT and anti-PT Coupling in a non-Hermitian Metamaterial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-Hermiticity has recently emerged as a rapidly developing field due to its exotic characteristics related to open systems, where the dissipation plays a critical role. In the presence of balanced energy gain and loss with environment, the system exhibits parity-time (PT) symmetry, meanwhile as the conjugate counterpart, anti-PT symmetry can be achieved with dissipative coupling within the system. Here, we demonstrate the coherence of complex dissipative coupling can control the transition between PT and anti-PT symmetry in an electromagnetic metamaterial. Notably, the achievement of the anti-PT symmetric phase is independent of variations in dissipation. Furthermore, we observe phase transitions as the system crosses exceptional points in both anti-PT and PT symmetric metamaterial configurations, achieved by manipulating the frequency and dissipation of resonators. This work provides a promising metamaterial design for broader exploration of non-Hermitian physics and practical application with controllable Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05922v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.156601</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 156601 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chang Li, Ruisheng Yang, Xinchao Huang, Quanhong Fu, Yuancheng Fan, Fuli Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Application of Tailored Fields for Studying Chirality and Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultrashort laser pulses pose unique tools to trigger and probe the fastest charge dynamics in matter, allowing the investigation of fundamental physical phenomena with unprecedented resolution in space, time, and energy. One of the most fascinating opportunities that ultrashort pulses offer is the possibility of modulating and investigating symmetries by tailoring the properties of the laser beam in the spatial and polarization domains, effectively controlling symmetry breaking on multiple levels. In particular, this allows probing chiral matter and ultrafast chiral dynamics. In recent years, the development of highly sensitive approaches for studying chirality has been a hot topic in physics and chemistry that has developed largely separately from the field of tailored light. This perspective discusses the individual and joint evolution of these fields with an emphasis on how the fields have already cross-fertilized, opening new opportunities in science. We outline a future outlook of how the topics are expected to fully merge and mutually evolve, emphasizing outstanding open issues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05923v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dino Habibovi\'c, Kathryn R. Hamilton, Ofer Neufeld, Laura Rego</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Map Optical Properties to Subwavelength Structures Directly via a Diffusion Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Subwavelength photonic structures and metamaterials provide revolutionary approaches for controlling light. The inverse design methods proposed for these subwavelength structures are vital to the development of new photonic devices. However, most of the existing inverse design methods cannot realize direct mapping from optical properties to photonic structures but instead rely on forward simulation methods to perform iterative optimization. In this work, we exploit the powerful generative abilities of artificial intelligence (AI) and propose a practical inverse design method based on latent diffusion models. Our method maps directly the optical properties to structures without the requirement of forward simulation and iterative optimization. Here, the given optical properties can work as "prompts" and guide the constructed model to correctly "draw" the required photonic structures. Experiments show that our direct mapping-based inverse design method can generate subwavelength photonic structures at high fidelity while following the given optical properties. This may change the method used for optical design and greatly accelerate the research on new photonic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05959v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijie Rao, Kaiyu Cui, Yidong Huang, Jiawei Yang, Yali Li, Shengjin Wang, Xue Feng, Fang Liu, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passive Non-line-of-sight imaging of moving targets using Physical embedding and Event-based vision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Passive Non-line-of-sight (NLOS) imaging has shown promising applications in imaging occluded objects around corners. However, this inverse problem is highly ill-posed and results in poor reconstruction with traditional physical retrieval methods, particularly in moving target imaging. With the development of neural networks, data-driven methods have greatly improved accuracy, however, heavy reliance on data volume has put great pressure on data collection and dataset fabrication. We propose a physical embedded passive NLOS imaging prototype with event-based vision (PNPE), which induces an event camera for feature extraction of dynamic diffusion spot and leverages simulation dataset to pre-train the physical embedded model before fine-tuning with limited real-shot data. The proposed PNPE is verified by simulation and real-world experiments, and the comparisons of data paradigms also validate the superiority of event-based vision in passive NLOS imaging for moving targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05977v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Conghe Wang, Xia Wang, Yujie Fang, Changda Yan, Xin Zhang, Yifan Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passive None-line-of-sight imaging with arbitrary scene condition and detection pattern in small amount of prior data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06015v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Passive Non-Line-of-Sight (NLOS) imaging requires to reconstruct objects which cannot be seen in line without using external controllable light sources. It can be widely applied in areas like counter-terrorism, urban-Warfare, autonomous-driving and robot-vision. Existing methods for passive NLOS typically required extensive prior information and significant computational resources to establish light transport matrices or train neural networks. These constraints pose significant challenges for transitioning models to different NLOS scenarios. Thus, the pressing issue in passive NLOS imaging currently lies in whether it is possible to estimate the light transport matrices which corresponding to relay surfaces and scenes, as well as the specific distribution of targets, with a small amount of prior knowledge. In this work, we hypothesized a high-dimensional manifold and mathematically proved its existence. Within this high-dimensional manifold, the structural information of obscured targets is minimally disrupted. Therefore, we proposed a universal framework named High-Dimensional Projection Selection (HDPS) which can establish this high-dimensional manifold and output its projection onto corresponding surfaces on low-dimensional. HDPS can be applied to most mature network architectures and estimate the distribution of target and light spot obtained by camera with only minimal prior data. Certainly, with the help of the estimated information, it can establish a high-dimensional manifold consisting of target and input. As demonstrated in experiment, our framework, even when applied to the most basic network structures, can achieve higher accuracy results with significantly smaller amounts of prior data. Thereby, our approach enables passive NLOS scenarios to reconstruct target by limited prior data and computational resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06015v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunting Gui, Yuegang Fu, Xueming Xiao, Meibao Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Berry phase effect in topological surface states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have observed the Berry phase effect associated with interband coherence in topological surface states (TSSs) using two-color high-harmonic spectroscopy. This Berry phase accumulates along the evolution path of strong field-driven election-hole quasiparticles in electronic bands with strong spin-orbit coupling. By introducing a secondary weak field, we perturb the evolution of Dirac fermions in TSSs and thus provide access to the Berry phase. We observe a significant shift in the oscillation phase of the even-order harmonics from the spectral interferogram. We reveal that such a modulation feature is linked to the geometric phase acquired in the nonperturbative dynamics of TSSs. Furthermore, we show that the overwhelming Berry phase effect can significantly deform the quantum paths of electron-hole pairs, thus enhancing the ability to harness electron spin using lightwaves in quantum materials with strong spin-orbit interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06086v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya Bai, Yang Jiang, Wenyang Zheng, Jiayin Chen, Shuo Wang, Candong Liu, Ruxin Li, Peng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Loss Silicon Directional Coupler with Arbitrary Coupling Ratios for Broadband Wavelength Operation Based on Bent Waveguides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate a design for a high-performance $2 \times 2$ splitter meeting the essential requirements of broadband coupling, support for arbitrary coupling ratio, ultra low-loss, high fabrication tolerance, and a compact footprint.
  This is achieved based on a rigorous coupled mode theory analysis of the broadband response of the bent directional coupler (DC) and by demonstrating a full coupling model, with measured broadband values of 0.4, 0.5, 0.6, and 0.7.
  As a benchmark, we demonstrate a 0.5:0.5 splitter that significantly reduces coupling variation from 0.391 in the traditional DC to just 0.051 over an 80 nm wavelength span.
  This represents a remarkable 7.67 times reduction in coupling variation.
  Further, newly-invented low-loss bends were used in the proposed design leading to an ultra low-loss design with negligible excess loss ($\mathrm{0.003 \pm 0.013 \ dB}$).
  The proposed 0.5:0.5 silicon strip waveguide-based design is tolerant and shows consistently low coupling variation over a full 300 mm wafer showcasing a maximum cross coupling variation of 0.112 over 80 nm wavelength range, at the extreme edge of the wafer.
  Futhermore, we augmented the wafer mapping with a waveguide width fabrication tolerance study, confirming the tolerance of the device with a mere 0.061 maximum coupling variation with a waveguide width deviation of $\pm 20$ nm over 80 nm wavelength range.
  These specs make the proposed splitter an attractive component for practical applications with mass production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06117v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed H. El-Saeed, Alaa Elshazly, Hakim Kobbi, Rafal Magdziak, Guy Lepage, Chiara Marchese, Javad Rahimi Vaskasi, Swetanshu Bipul, Dieter Bode, Marko Ersek Filipcic, Dimitrios Velenis, Maumita Chakrabarti, Peter De Heyn, Peter Verheyen, Philippe Absil, Filippo Ferraro, Yoojin Ban, Joris Van Campenhout, Wim Bogaerts, Qingzhong Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly reflective and high-$Q$ thin resonant subwavelength gratings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the design of thin subwavelength gratings possessing high-reflectivity and high-$Q$ resonances when illuminated at normal incidence by a Gaussian beam. We compare the performances of single-period and dual-period rectangular gratings using Finite Element Method-based optimization and predict one to two orders of magnitude improvement in their transmission loss-linewidth product, which is the relevant figure of merit for e.g. resonant mirror-based microcavity applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06143v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gurpreet Singh, Trishala Mitra, S{\o}ren P. Madsen, Aur\'elien Dantan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shock wave generation and propagation in dissipative and nonlocal nonlinear Rydberg media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06183v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the generation of optical shock waves in strongly interacting Rydberg atomic gases with a spatially homogeneous dissipative potential. The Rydberg atom interaction induces an optical nonlocal nonlinarity. We focus on local nonlinear ($R_b\ll R_0$) and nonlocal nonlinear ($R_b\sim R_0$) regimes, where $R_b$ and $R_0$ are the characteristic length of the Rydberg nonlinearity and beam width, respectively. In the local regime, we show spatial width and contrast of the shock wave change monotonically when increasing strength of the dissipative potential and optical intensity. In the nonlocal regime, the characteristic quantity of the shock wave depend on $R_b/R_0$ and dissipative potential nontrivially and on the intensity monotonically. We find that formation of shock waves dominantly takes place when $R_b$ is smaller than $R_0$, while the propagation dynamics is largely linear when $R_b$ is comparable to or larger than $R_0$. Our results reveal nontrivial roles played by dissipation and nonlocality in the generation of shock waves, and provide a route to manipulate their profiles and stability. Our study furthermore opens new avenues to explore non-Hermitian physics, and nonlinear wave generation and propagation by controlling dissipation and nonlocality in the Rydberg media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06183v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu Qin, Chao Hang, Guoxiang Huang, Weibin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intra- and intercycle analysis of intraband high-order harmonic generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study intraband high-order harmonic generation arising from a band-gap material driven by a linearly polarized laser field. We factorize the intraband high-order harmonic-generation signal into intracycle and intercycle terms. The intracycle term uniquely determines the spectral characteristics whereas the intercycle term merely modulates the spectral features by imposing energy conservation in the long-pulse limit. Through analysis of the intracycle interference, the cutoff is identified, and the origin of the harmonic selection rules is revealed. Further, it is outlined how different components of the bandstructure contribute to different regions of the harmonic spectrum, giving rise to non-trivial intensity scaling of individual harmonics in the plateau region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06237v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asbj{\o}rn Torn{\o}e Andersen, Simon Vendelbo Bylling Jensen, Lars Bojer Madsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated electro-optics on thin-film lithium niobate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06398v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electro-optics serves as the crucial bridge between electronics and photonics, unlocking a wide array of applications ranging from communications and computing to sensing and quantum information. Integrated electro-optics approaches in particular enable essential electronic high-speed control for photonics while offering substantial photonic parallelism for electronics. Recent strides in thin-film lithium niobate photonics have ushered revolutionary advancements in electro-optics. This technology not only offers the requisite strong electro-optic coupling but also boasts ultra-low optical loss and high microwave bandwidth. Further, its tight confinement and compatibility with nanofabrication allow for unprecedented reconfigurability and scalability, facilitating the creation of novel and intricate devices and systems that were once deemed nearly impossible in bulk systems. Building upon this platform, the field has witnessed the emergence of various groundbreaking electro-optic devices surpassing the current state of the art, and introducing functionalities that were previously non-existent. This technological leap forward provides a unique framework to explore various realms of physics as well, including photonic non-Hermitian synthetic dimensions, active topological physics, and quantum electro-optics. In this review, we present the fundamental principles of electro-optics, drawing connections between fundamental science and the forefront of technology. We discuss the accomplishments and future prospects of integrated electro-optics, enabled by thin-film lithium niobate platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06398v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaowen Hu, Di Zhu, Shengyuan Lu, Xinrui Zhu, Yunxiang Song, Dylan Renaud, Daniel Assumpcao, Rebecca Cheng, CJ Xin, Matthew Yeh, Hana Warner, Xiangwen Guo, Amirhassan Shams-Ansari, David Barton, Neil Sinclair, Marko Loncar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent Heat Transfer Leads to Genuine Quantum Enhancement in Performances of Continuous Engines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05799v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The conventional continuous quantum heat engines rely on incoherent heat transfer with the baths and, thus, have limited capability to outperform their classical counterparts. In this work, we introduce distinct continuous quantum heat engines that utilize coherent heat transfer with baths, yielding significant quantum enhancement in performance. These continuous engines, termed as coherent engines, consist of one qutrit system and two photonic baths and enable coherent heat transfer via two-photon transitions involving three-body interactions between the system and hot and cold baths. The closest quantum incoherent analogs are those that only allow incoherent heat transfer between the qutrit and the baths via one-photon transitions relying on two-body interactions between the system and hot or cold baths. We demonstrate that coherent engines deliver much higher power output and a much lower signal-to-noise ratio in power, where the latter signifies the reliability of an engine, compared to incoherent engines. Coherent engines manifest more non-classical features than incoherent engines because they violate the classical thermodynamic uncertainty relation by a greater amount and for a wider range of parameters. Importantly, coherent engines can operate close to or at the fundamental lower limit on reliability given by the quantum version of the thermodynamic uncertainty relation, making them highly reliable. These genuine enhancements in performance by hundreds of folds over incoherent engines and the saturation of the quantum limit by coherent engines are directly attributed to its capacity to harness higher energetic coherence which is, again, a consequence of coherent heat transfer. The experimental feasibility of coherent engines and the improved understanding of how quantum properties can enhance performance may find important implications in emerging quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05799v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brij Mohan, Rajeev Gangwar, Tanmoy Pandit, Mohit Lal Bera, Maciej Lewenstein, Manabendra Nath Bera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstration of Lossy Linear Transformations and Two-Photon Interference on a Photonic Chip</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06056v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Studying quantum correlations in the presence of loss is of critical importance for the physical modeling of real quantum systems. Here, we demonstrate the control of spatial correlations between entangled photons in a photonic chip, designed and modeled using the singular value decomposition approach. We show that engineered loss, using an auxiliary waveguide, allows one to invert the spatial statistics from bunching to antibunching. Furthermore, we study the photon statistics within the loss-emulating channel and observe photon coincidences, which may provide insights into the design of quantum photonic integrated chips.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06056v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Wang, Simon J. U. White, Alexander Szameit, Andrey A. Sukhorukov, Alexander S. Solntsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterising and tackling thermally induced zero-drift in displacement measuring interferometry using temperature-controlled enclosure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06184v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Our research efforts in displacement measurement interferometry focused on long-term drifts initiated an extended experimental investigation in the interferometric assemblies of our design. We aimed to analyze, characterize and tackle the long-term measurement stability, expressed as the zero-drift, with special attention to the thermal effects. For the experimentation, we developed a thermostatic chamber equipped with an active temperature regulation, array of sensors and control electronics. With either the finely stabilized temperature or with the thermal cycling, we are able to carry out a range of investigations: verification of modified design or prototype interferometers, testing of production pieces, characterization of integrated assemblies and units in terms of the zero drift and the susceptibility to thermal effect - the temperature sensitivity, expressed as $\delta L / \delta T$ in nm.K$^{-1}$.
  Note: This is the version of the article before peer review or editing, as submitted by an author to Measurement Science and Technology. IOP Publishing Ltd is not responsible for any errors or omissions in this version of the manuscript or any version derived from it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06184v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Rerucha, Miroslava Hola, Jindrich Oulehla, Josef Lazar, Bretislav Mikel, Ondrej Cip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of topological frequency combs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15547v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: On-chip generation of optical frequency combs using nonlinear ring resonators has opened the route to numerous novel applications of combs that were otherwise limited to mode-locked laser systems. Nevertheless, even after more than a decade of development, on-chip nonlinear combs still predominantly rely on the use of single-ring resonators. Recent theoretical investigations have shown that generating combs in a topological array of resonators can provide a new avenue to engineer comb spectra. Here, we experimentally demonstrate the generation of such a novel class of frequency combs, topological frequency combs, in a two-dimensional (2D) lattice of hundreds of nonlinear ring resonators. Specifically, the lattice hosts topological edge states that exhibit fabrication-robust linear dispersion and spatial confinement at the boundary of the lattice. Upon optical pumping of the topological edge band, these unique properties of the edge states lead to the generation of a nested frequency comb that is spectrally confined within the edge bands across $\approx$40 longitudinal modes. Moreover, using spatial imaging of our topological lattice, we confirm that light generated in the comb teeth is indeed spatially confined at the lattice edge, characteristic of linear topological systems. Our results bring together the fields of topological photonics and optical frequency combs, providing an opportunity to explore the interplay between topology and nonlinear systems in a platform compatible with commercially available nanofabrication processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15547v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher J. Flower, Mahmoud Jalali Mehrabad, Lida Xu, Gregory Moille, Daniel G. Suarez-Forero, Ogulcan Orsel, Gaurav Bahl, Yanne Chembo, Kartik Srinivasan, Sunil Mittal, Mohammad Hafezi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast dynamic beam steering with optical frequency comb arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04732v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficient spatiotemporal control of optical beams is of paramount importance in diverse technological domains. Conventional systems focusing on quasi-static beam control demand precise phase or wavelength tuning for steering. This work presents a time-efficient solution for dynamic beam steering, emphasizing high-duty-cycle operation with fast scan rates, and eliminating the need for active tuning of the beam direction. We achieve 100%-duty-cycle scans at a rate of $\sim$9.8 GHz within an angular range of $\sim$1$^\circ$. Furthermore, leveraging the dispersion characteristics of a virtually imaged phased array (VIPA), we devise a broadband source array that seamlessly transitions from continuous-angular steering to pulsed discrete-angular operation, unlocking possibilities for high-sensitivity angle-, range-, and time-resolved imaging. We also elucidate the adaptability of integrated photonic designs incorporating wavelength-selective switches and spectral dispersers, for enabling a versatile on-chip realization of the proposed beam steering schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04732v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suparna Seshadri, Jie Wang, Andrew M. Weiner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Harmonic Generation by Bright Squeezed Vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15337v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We observe non-perturbative high harmonic generation in solids driven by a macroscopic quantum state of light, bright squeezed vacuum (BSV), which we generate in a single spatiotemporal mode. The BSV-driven process is considerably more efficient in the generation of high harmonics than classical light of the same mean intensity. Due to its broad photon-number distribution, covering states from $0$ to $2 \times 10^{13}$ photons per pulse, and sub-cycle electric field fluctuations over $\pm1\hbox{V}/\hbox{\r{A}}$, BSV provides access to free carrier dynamics within a much broader range of peak intensities than accessible with classical light. Our findings contribute to recent developments of quantum optics with extreme intensities, moving beyond its traditional focus on low photon numbers, and providing a new method for exploring extreme nonlinearities in solids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15337v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Rasputnyi, Zhaopin Chen, Michael Birk, Oren Cohen, Ido Kaminer, Michael Kr\"uger, Denis Seletskiy, Maria Chekhova, Francesco Tani</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
