<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 04:00:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Multilayer Thin Film Structure Inverse Design: From Optimization to Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17199v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical multilayer thin film structures have been widely used in numerous photonic domains and applications. The key component to enable these applications is the inverse design. Different from other photonic structures such as metasurface or waveguide, multilayer thin film is a one-dimensional structure, which deserves its own treatment for the design process. Optimization has always been the standard design algorithm for decades. Recent years have witnessed a rapid development of integrating different deep learning algorithms to tackle the inverse design problems. A natural question to ask is: how do these algorithms differ from each other? Why do we need to develop so many algorithms and what type of challenges do they solve? What is the state-of-the-art algorithm in this domain? Here, we review recent progress and provide a guide-tour through this research area, starting from traditional optimization to recent deep learning approaches. Challenges and future perspectives are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17199v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taigao Ma, Mingqian Ma, L. Jay Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic Geared Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The miniaturization of mechanical machines is critical for advancing nanotechnology and reducing device footprints. Traditional efforts to downsize gears and micromotors have faced limitations at around 0.1 mm for over thirty years due to the complexities of constructing drives and coupling systems at such scales. Here, we present an alternative approach utilizing optical metasurfaces to locally drive microscopic machines, which can then be fabricated using standard lithography techniques and seamlessly integrated on the chip, achieving sizes down to tens of micrometers with movements precise to the sub-micrometer scale. As a proof of principle, we demonstrate the construction of microscopic gear trains powered by a single driving gear with a metasurface activated by a plane light wave. Additionally, we develop a versatile pinion and rack micromachine capable of transducing rotational motion, performing periodic motion, and controlling microscopic mirrors for light deflection. Our on-chip fabrication process allows for straightforward parallelization and integration. Using light as a widely available and easily controllable energy source, these miniaturized metamachines offer precise control and movement, unlocking new possibilities for micro- and nanoscale systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17284v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gan Wang, Marcel Rey, Antonio Ciarlo, Mahdi Shanei, Kunli Xiong, Giuseppe Pesce, Mikael K\"all, Giovanni Volpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Dynamics of Coupled-Resonator Kerr-Combs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17343v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nonlinear interaction of a microresonator pumped by a laser has revealed complex dynamics including soliton formation and chaos. Initial studies of coupled-resonator systems reveal even more complicated dynamics that can lead to deterministic modelocking and efficient comb generation. Here we perform theoretical analysis and experiments that provide insight into the dynamical behavior of coupled-resonator systems operating in the normal group-velocity-dispersion regime. Our stability analysis and simulations reveal that the strong mode-coupling regime, which gives rise to spectrally-broad comb states, can lead to an instability mechanism in the auxiliary resonator that destabilizes the comb state and prevents mode-locking. We find that this instability can be suppressed by introducing loss in the auxiliary resonator. We investigate the stability of both single- and multi-pulse solutions and verify our theoretical predictions by performing experiments in a silicon-nitride platform. Our results provide an understanding for accessing broad, efficient, relatively flat high-power mode-locked combs for numerous applications in spectroscopy, time-frequency metrology, and data communications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17343v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swarnava Sanyal, Yoshitomo Okawachi, Yun Zhao, Bok Young Kim, Karl J. McNulty, Michal Lipson, Alexander L. Gaeta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub-100 Hz Intrinsic Linewidth 852 nm Silicon Nitride External Cavity Laser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate an external cavity laser with intrinsic linewidth below 100 Hz around an operating wavelength of 852 nm, selected for its relevance to laser cooling and manipulation of cesium atoms. This system achieves a maximum CW output power of 24 mW, wavelength tunability over 15 nm, and a side-mode suppression ratio exceeding 50 dB. This performance level is facilitated by careful design of a low-loss integrated silicon nitride photonic circuit serving as the external cavity combined with commercially available semiconductor gain chips. This approach demonstrates the feasibility of compact integrated lasers with sub-kHz linewidth centering on the needs of emerging sensor concepts based on ultracold atoms and can be further extended to shorter wavelengths via selection of suitable semiconductor gain media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17382v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hani Nejadriahi, Eric Kittlaus, Debapam Bose, Nitesh Chauhan, Jiawei Wang, Mathieu Fradet, Mahmood Bagheri, Andrei Isichenko, David Heim, Siamak Forouhar, Daniel Blumenthal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Skyrmions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Skyrmions are important topologically non-trivial fields characteristic of models spanning scales from the microscopic to the cosmological. However, the Skyrmion number can only be defined for fields with specific boundary conditions, limiting its use in broader contexts. Here, we address this issue through a generalized notion of the Skyrmion derived from the De Rham cohomology of compactly supported forms. This allows for the definition of an entirely new $\coprod_{i=1}^\infty \mathbb{Z}^i$-valued topological number that assigns a tuple of integers $(a_1, \ldots, a_k)\in \mathbb{Z}^k$ to a field instead of a single number, with no restrictions to its boundary. The notion of the generalized Skyrmion presented in this paper is completely abstract and can be applied to vector fields in any discipline, not unlike index theory within dynamical systems. To demonstrate the power of our new formalism, we focus on the propagation of optical polarization fields and show that our newly defined generalized Skyrmion number significantly increases the dimension of data that can be stored within the field while also demonstrating strong robustness. Our work represents a fundamental paradigm shift away from the study of fields with natural topological character to engineered fields that can be artificially embedded with topological structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17390v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>An Aloysius Wang, Zimo Zhao, Yifei Ma, Yuxi Cai, Stephen Morris, Honghui He, Lin Luo, Zhenwei Xie, Peng Shi, Yijie Shen, Anatoly Zayats, Xiaocong Yuan, Chao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zak Phase Induced Topological Nonreciprocity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological physics provides novel insights for designing functional photonic devices, such as magnetic-free optical diodes, which are important in optical engineering and quantum information processing. Past efforts mostly focus on the topological edge modes in two-dimensional (2D) photonic Chern lattices, which, however, require delicate fabrication and temporal modulation. In particular, the 1D nonreciprocal edge mode needs to be embedded in a 2D lattice, contradicting with the compactness of integrated photonics. To address these challenges, we investigate the optical nonreciprocity of the 1D Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) superradiance lattices in room-temperature atoms. The probe fields propagating in two opposite directions perceive two different SSH topological phases, which have different absorption spectra due to the interplay between the Zak phase and the thermal motion of atoms, resulting in optical nonreciprocity. Our findings reveal the relationship between 1D topological matter and optical nonreciprocity, simplifying the design of topologically resilient nonreciprocal devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17559v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Liu, Jiefei Wang, Ruosong Mao, Huizhu Hu, Shi-Yao Zhu, Xingqi Xu, Han Cai, Da-Wei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Wavelength DFB Laser Based on Sidewall Third Order Four Phase-Shifted Sampled Bragg Grating with Uniform Wavelength Spacing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first demonstration of a 1550 nm multi-wavelength distributed feedback (MW-DFB) laser employing a third-order, four-phase-shifted sampled sidewall grating. By utilizing linearly chirped sampled gratings and incorporating multiple true {\pi}-phase shifts within the cavity, we achieved and experimentally validated a four-wavelength laser with a channel spacing of 0.4 nm. The device operates stably and uniformly across a wide range of injection currents from 280 mA to 350 mA. The average wavelength spacing was measured at 0.401 nm with a standard deviation of 0.0081 nm. Additionally, we demonstrated a 0.3 nm MW-DFB laser with a seven-channel output, achieving a wavelength spacing of 0.274 nm and a standard deviation of 0.0055 nm. This MW-DFB laser features a ridge waveguide with sidewall gratings, requiring only one metalorganic vapor-phase epitaxy (MOVPE) step and a single III-V material etching process. This streamlined fabrication approach simplifies device manufacturing and is well-suited for dense wavelength division multiplexing (DWDM) systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17719v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Sun, Zhibo Li, Yizhe Fan, Mohanad Jamal Al-Rubaiee, John H. Marsh, Anthony E Kelly, Stephen. J. Sweeney, Lianping Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially resolved spin angular momentum mediated by spin-orbit interaction in tightly focused spinless vector beams in optical tweezers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate an effective and optimal strategy for generating spatially resolved longitudinal spin angular momentum (LSAM) in optical tweezers by tightly focusing first-order azimuthally radially polarized (ARP) vector beams with zero intrinsic angular momentum into a refractive index (RI) stratified medium. The stratified medium gives rise to a spherically aberrated intensity profile near the focal region of the optical tweezers, with off-axis intensity lobes in the radial direction possessing opposite LSAM (helicities corresponding to $\sigma = +1$ and -1) compared to the beam centre. We trap mesoscopic birefringent particles in an off-axis intensity lobe as well as at the beam center by modifying the trapping plane, and observe particles spinning in opposite directions depending on their location. The direction of rotation depends on particle size with large particles spinning either clockwise (CW) or anticlockwise (ACW) depending on the direction of spirality of the polarization of the ARP vector beam after tight focusing, while smaller particles spin in both directions depending on their spatial location. Numerical simulations support our experimental observations. Our results introduce new avenues in spin-orbit optomechanics to facilitate novel yet straightforward avenues for exotic and complex particle manipulation in optical tweezers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17856v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ram Nandan Kumar, Sauvik Roy, Subhasish Dutta Gupta, Nirmalya Ghosh, Ayan Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A liquid crystal geometric phase hyperbolic lens with a positive focal length for arbitrary circularly polarized incidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the design and experimental validation of a liquid crystal geometric phase hyperbolic lens (LCHL) with positive focal lengths for arbitrary circularly polarized light. Utilizing Pancharatnam-Berry phase modulation, the lens enables isotropic focusing for both left- and right-handed circular polarization. We fabricated and characterized two lenses with different focal lengths, and their diffraction patterns were analyzed experimentally. The results exhibit strong agreement with theoretical simulations, highlighting the lens's capability for precise optical field modulation. The proposed LCHL demonstrates significant potential for detecting weak polarization states, making it a promising tool for advanced applications in biomedical imaging, optical vortex generation, and multifocal optical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17919v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyuan Li, Xiaoqian Wang, Kean Zhu, Dong Shen, Zhigang Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low Photon Number Non-Invasive Imaging Through Time-Varying Diffusers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scattering poses a significant challenge in optical imaging. In microscopy, it leads to progressive degradation of image quality preventing sample examination at increasing depths. As the thickness of the sample increases, the number of photons that can successfully pass through it decreases, leading to a reduced signal and preventing us from obtaining clear images. Imaging becomes even more difficult with dynamic scatterers like biological tissues that change over time. We demonstrate non-invasive imaging of fluorescent objects hidden behind dynamic diffusers. Our reconstruction uses a stack of images recorded for different diffuser realizations and works even when individual camera frames contain small photon numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18072v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Makowski, Wojciech Zwolinski, Pawel Szczypkowski, Bernard Gorzkowski, Sylvain Gigan, Radek Lapkiewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural refractive index field: Unlocking the Potential of Background-oriented Schlieren Tomography in Volumetric Flow Visualization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14722v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Background-oriented Schlieren tomography (BOST) is a prevalent method for visualizing intricate turbulent flows, valued for its ease of implementation and capacity to capture three-dimensional distributions of a multitude of flow parameters. However, the voxel-based meshing scheme leads to significant challenges, such as inadequate spatial resolution, substantial discretization errors, poor noise immunity, and excessive computational costs. This work presents an innovative reconstruction approach termed neural refractive index field (NeRIF) which implicitly represents the flow field with a neural network, which is trained with tailored strategies. Both numerical simulations and experimental demonstrations on turbulent Bunsen flames suggest that our approach can significantly improve the reconstruction accuracy and spatial resolution while concurrently reducing computational expenses. Although showcased in the context of background-oriented schlieren tomography here, the key idea embedded in the NeRIF can be readily adapted to various other tomographic modalities including tomographic absorption spectroscopy and tomographic particle imaging velocimetry, broadening its potential impact across different domains of flow visualization and analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14722v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanzhe He, Yutao Zheng, Shijie Xu, Chang Liu, Di Peng, Yingzheng Liu, Weiwei Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retinal arterial blood flow measured by real-time Doppler holography at 33,000 frames per second</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17180v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study presents a novel quantitative estimation method for total retinal arterial blood flow utilizing real-time Doppler holography at an unprecedented frame rate of 33,000 frames per second. This technique, leveraging high-speed digital holography, enables non-invasive angiographic imaging of the retina, providing detailed blood flow contrasts essential for assessing retinal health. The proposed quantitative analysis method consists of segmenting primary in-plane retinal arteries and calculating local blood velocity using Doppler frequency broadening. The analysis integrates a forward scattering model to achieve blood flow estimation. Our findings highlight the potential of Doppler holography as a powerful tool for diagnosing and monitoring the treatment of retinal vascular conditions, complementary to existing imaging methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17180v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yann Fischer, Zacharie Auray, Olivier Martinache, Marius Dubosc, No\'e Top\'eza, Chlo\'e Magnier, Maxime Boy-Arnould, Michael Atlan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Transient Trion Induced by Ultrafast Charge Transfer in Graphene/MoS2 Heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17752v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Van der Waals (Vdw) heterostructures constructed from TMDCs provide an ideal platform for exploring various quasiparticle behaviors, with trion-composed of neutral exciton and charged carrier-being a notable example. There are typically three methods to generate trion: electrical doping, chemical doping, and direct optical doping. The first two methods generate static trion, while the last gives rise to transient trion. Here, we present an indirect optical doping approach to generate transient trion via ultrafast charge transfer (CT) and achieve control over the trion-to-exciton ratio by adjusting CT in Gr/MoS2 heterostructure. Furthermore, we demonstrated that dynamics of the transient trion generated with this method, which shows slightly longer lifetime than that of exciton accounted for the Coulomb interactions between trion and charged defect. This study provides fresh perspectives on the construction of new quasiparticles, dynamical characterization and the control of the many-body interaction in two-dimensional structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17752v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Wang, Yu Chen, Qiushi Ma, Peng Suo, Kaiwen Sun, Yifan Cheng, Xian Lin, Weimin Liu, Guohong Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Codesigned counterdiabatic quantum optimization on a photonic quantum processor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17930v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Codesign, an integral part of computer architecture referring to the information interaction in hardware-software stack, is able to boost the algorithm mapping and execution in the computer hardware. This well applies to the noisy intermediate-scale quantum era, where quantum algorithms and quantum processors both need to be shaped to allow for advantages in experimental implementations. The state-of-the-art quantum adiabatic optimization algorithm faces challenges for scaling up, where the deteriorating optimization performance is not necessarily alleviated by increasing the circuit depth given the noise in the hardware. The counterdiabatic term can be introduced to accelerate the convergence, but decomposing the unitary operator corresponding to the counterdiabatic terms into one and two-qubit gates may add additional burden to the digital circuit depth. In this work, we focus on the counterdiabatic protocol with a codesigned approach to implement this algorithm on a photonic quantum processor. The tunable Mach-Zehnder interferometer mesh provides rich programmable parameters for local and global manipulation, making it able to perform arbitrary unitary evolutions. Accordingly, we directly implement the unitary operation associated to the counterdiabatic quantum optimization on our processor without prior digitization. Furthermore, we develop and implement an optimized counterdiabatic method by tackling the higher-order many-body interaction terms. Moreover, we benchmark the performance in the case of factorization, by comparing the final success probability and the convergence speed. In conclusion, we experimentally demonstrate the advantages of a codesigned mapping of counterdiabatic quantum dynamics for quantum computing on photonic platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17930v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Wen Shang, Xuan Chen, Narendra N. Hegade, Ze-Feng Lan, Xuan-Kun Li, Hao Tang, Yu-Quan Peng, Enrique Solano, Xian-Min Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Abbe's diffraction limit with harmonic deactivation microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06617v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonlinear optical microscopy provides elegant means for label-free imaging of biological samples and condensed matter systems. The widespread areas of application could even be increased if resolution was improved, which is currently limited by the famous Abbe diffraction limit. Super-resolution techniques can break the diffraction limit but rely on fluorescent labeling. This makes them incompatible with (sub-)femtosecond temporal resolution and applications that demand the absence of labeling. Here, we introduce harmonic deactivation microscopy (HADES) for breaking the diffraction limit in non-fluorescent samples. By controlling the harmonic generation process on the quantum level with a second donut-shaped pulse, we confine the third harmonic generation to three times below the original focus size and use this pulse for scanning microscopy. We demonstrate that resolution improvement by deactivation is more efficient for higher harmonic orders, and only limited by the maximum applicable deactivation-pulse fluence. This provides a route towards sub-100~nm resolution in a regular nonlinear microscope. The new capability of label-free super-resolution can find immediate applications in condensed matter physics, semiconductor metrology, and biomedical imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06617v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Murzyn, Maarten L. S. van der Geest, Leo Guery, Zhonghui Nie, Pieter van Essen, Stefan Witte, Peter M. Kraus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser Printing of Silver and Silver Oxide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09340v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that direct laser writing (DLW) in aqueous silver nitrate with a 1030 nm femtosecond (fs) laser results in deposition of a mixture of silver oxide and silver, in contrast to the pure silver deposition previously reported with 780 nm fs DLW. However, adding photoinitiator prevents silver oxide formation in a concentration-dependent manner. As a result, the resistivity of the material can also be controlled by photoinitiator concentration with resistivity being reduced from approximately 9e-3 $\Omega m$ to 3e-7 $\Omega m$. Silver oxide peaks dominate the X-ray diffraction spectra when no photoinitiator is present, while the peaks disappear with photoinitiator concentrations above 0.05wt%. While femtosecond pulses are needed to initiate deposition, a continues-wave laser when well overlapped with the previously written material and supplying enough average power can lead to further printing, suggesting thermal deposition can also occur where the photoinitiator molecule also acts as a general reducing agent that prevents oxide formation. We also compare the surface quality of printed lines for different photoinitiator concentrations and laser printing conditions. A THz polarizer and metamaterial are printed as a demonstration of silver oxide printing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09340v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan M. Adams, Daniel Heligman, Ryan O'Dell, Christine Y. Wang, Daniel Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic QED and noise currents in time-varying media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11873v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Macroscopic QED (MQED) is the field theory for computing quantum electromagnetic effects in dispersive media. Here we extend MQD to treat time-varying, dispersive media. For a time dependent Drude model, we find that the expected replacement ${\epsilon}({\omega}) {\to} {\epsilon}(t,{\omega})$ within standard MQED leads to nonphysical polarization currents, becoming singular in the limit of a step change in the carrier density. We show this singular behaviour can be removed through modifying the reservoir dynamics, quantizing the resulting theory and finding the non-equilibrium, time-varying noise currents, which exhibit extra correlations due to temporal reflections within the material dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11873v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. A. R. Horsley, R. K. Baker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concatenation of Kerr solitary waves in Ceramic YAG: application to coherent Raman imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17040v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A coherent concatenation of multiple Townes solitons may lead to a stable infrared and visible broadband filament in ceramic YAG polycrystal. This self-trapped soliton train helps implement self-referenced multiplex coherent anti-Stokes Raman scattering imaging. Simulations and experiments are presented in this work that help enhance the understanding of the filamentation process and the concatenation of focusing-defocusing cycles in Ceramic and Crystal YAG. Simulations and experiments are presented that examine the dependence of the filamentation onset location and supercontinuum generation upon peak input power. Understanding this dependence is a necessary component of SR-M-CARS implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17040v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Bagley, Sahar Wehbi, Tigran Mansuryan, R\'emy Boulesteix, Alexandre Ma\^itre, Yago Arosa Lobato, Mario Ferraro, Fabio Mangini, Yifan Sun, Katarzyna Krupa, Benjamin Wetzel, Vincent Couderc, Stefan Wabnitz, Alejandro Aceves, Alessandro Tonello</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
