<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 04:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Wigner function and intensity moments of spatio-temporal light fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Wigner distribution function and the its spatial-angular moments (intensity-moments) are known as efficient instruments for characterization of complex quasimonochromatic light beams and their transformations. In this paper, the generalization of the WF-based approach to spatio-temporal (ST) light fields (wave packets, short pulses) is considered. It is shown that the ST intensity moments are related with the important characteristics of the wave-packet structure, especially, with the transverse orbital angular momentum (OAM) being a specific feature of the ST optical vortices (STOV). The ST moments' transformations in a paraxial optical system obey simple and unified rules involving the ray-transfer ABCD-matrix of the system. On this base, and with simple examples of the OAM-carrying optical pulses, the schemes and mechanisms of the STOV generation and transformation are presented. Examples of non-vortex ST wave packets with the transverse OAM and their possible realizations are discussed. The regular and unified formalism, developed in this paper, can be generalized and applied to more complex situations where the ST field propagates through inhomogeneous and random (scattering) media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06708v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandr Bekshaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentanglement of mixed interference fringes in optical interferometers: theory and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06716v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical interferometric imaging enables astronomical observation at extremely high angular resolution. The necessary optical information for imaging, such as the optical path differences and visibilities, is easy to extract from fringes generated by the combination of two beams. With more than two apertures, the image-plane interference pattern becomes an increasingly indistinguishable mixture of fringe spacings and directions. For decades, the state-of-the-art approaches for obtaining two-aperture fringes from an interferometer array composed of many apertures are limited to pairwise combinations using bulk optics. Here, we derive and demonstrate a fringe disentanglement theory that can digitally transform the interference pattern of N apertures to N(N-1)/2 pairwise fringes without any optics, thus providing straightforward methods of information acquisition for interferometers. We demonstrate applications of our technique by both simulation and experiment, showing that this theory can be used for simultaneously sensing pistons and determining the individual visibilities of all combining apertures. Furthermore, we use the proposed theory to phase a 1.5-meter segmented flat telescope, demonstrating its validity for engineering implementation. This theory may not only benefit optical imaging but also interferometry-based measurements, by providing an exceptional capability to simplify the interferometric output generated by a system of many apertures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06716v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaiyuan Yang, Weilong Wei, Xiafei Ma, Botao Chen, Junqiu Chu, Xinling Liu, Yuhua Cheng, Hu Yang, Haotong Ma, Bo Qi, Zongliang Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mid-infrared Brillouin laser using ultra-high-Q on-chip resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultra-high-Q optical resonators have facilitated recent advancements in on-chip photonics by effectively harnessing nonlinear phenomena providing useful functionalities. While these breakthroughs, primarily focused on the near-infrared region, have extended interest to longer wavelengths holding importance for monitoring and manipulating molecules, the absence of ultra-high-Q resonators in this region remains a significant challenge. Here, we have developed on-chip microresonators with a remarkable Q-factor of 38 million, surpassing previous mid-infrared records by over 30 times. Employing innovative fabrication techniques, including the spontaneous formation of light-guiding geometries during material deposition, resonators with internal multilayer structures have been seamlessly created and passivated with chalcogenide glasses within a single chamber. Major loss factors, especially airborne-chemical absorption, were thoroughly investigated and mitigated by extensive optimization of resonator geometries and fabrication procedures. This allowed us to access the fundamental loss performance offered by doubly purified chalcogenide glass sources, as demonstrated in their fiber form. Exploiting this ultra-high-Q resonator, we successfully demonstrated Brillouin lasing on a chip for the first time in the mid-infrared, with a threshold power of 91.9 {\mu}W and a theoretical Schawlow-Townes linewidth of 83.45 Hz, far surpassing carrier phase noise. Our results showcase the effective integration of cavity-enhanced optical nonlinearities into on-chip mid-infrared photonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06764v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiyoung Ko, Daewon Suk, Dohyeong Kim, Soobong Park, Betul Sen, Dae-Gon Kim, Yingying Wang, Shixun Dai, Xunsi Wang, Rongping Wang, Byung Jae Chun, Kwang-Hoon Ko, Peter T. Rakich, Duk-Yong Choi, Hansuek Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aluminium nanoparticle-based ultra-wideband high-performance polarizer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The polarizer-based device industry is expanding quickly, requiring high-quality research on nanoscale wideband polarizers. Here, we investigated the possibility of utilizing Al dimer nanostructures on broad-band polarizers. Metals are always considered promising candidates for reflection-based polarizer development because of their high extinction ratio. This study proposes a nanoparticle polarizer comprised of semi-immersed Al nanodimers with a 200 nm radius on a CaF_2 substrate. Our proposed polarizer has effective polarization anisotropy in the near-infrared (NIR) and THz range. This study includes calculating performance parameters for the extraction of the proposed polarizer, including insertion loss, extinction ratio (ER), Mueller matrix values, and polarization ellipse diagram. The finite-difference time-domain (FDTD) simulation-based results suggested obtaining more than 55 dB extinction ratio for the 0.2 to 9 THz range. The average extinction ratio and insertion loss over the 1-1665 micrometer wavelength were 29.01 dB and ~1 dB, respectively. We have reviewed recent reports of similar nanoparticle and wire grid-based polarizers to evaluate our Al nanodimer-based polarizer and performed a comparative analysis. The idea of Al dimer and the insight gained from the results extracted from the rigorous simulation report suggested a great opportunity for developing micro-scale metallic wideband polarizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06873v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md. Shariful Islam, Ahmed Zubair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nano vacuum gauge based on second-order coherence in optical levitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate measurement of pressure with a wide dynamic range holds significant importance for various applications. This issue can be realized with a mechanical nano-oscillator, where the pressure-related collisions with surrounding molecules induce its energy dissipation. However, this energy dissipation of the nano-oscillator may be overshadowed by other processes. Here, we apply the second-order coherence analysis to accurately characterize those distinct dissipation processes. Based on an optically levitated nano-oscillator, we successfully obtain precise measurements of the air pressure surrounding the particles from atmosphere to 7E-6 mbar, over 8 orders of magnitude. It proves that the mechanical nano-oscillator is an extremely promising candidate for precision pressure sensing applications. Moreover, the second-order coherence analysis method on a classical system can pave the way to characterize the dynamic properties of an oscillator, which will benefit microscopic thermodynamics, precision measurement, and macroscopic quantum research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06907v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lyu-Hang Liu, Yu Zheng, Yuan Tian, Long Wang, Guang-Can Guo, Fang-Wen Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral Chaos Enhanced Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chirality refers to the property that an object and its mirror image cannot overlap each other by spatial rotation and translation, and can be found in various research fields. We here propose chiral chaos and construct a chiral chaotic device via coupled whispering gallery mode resonators, where routes to chaos exhibit pronounced chirality for two opposite pumping directions. The mechanism responsible for this phenomenon is that time-reversal symmetry of the traveling-wave light fields is broken by the Rayleigh scatterers inserted in resonators. Combining with the Lyapunov exponents, we propose metrics to measure the symmetry and chirality between different chaotic dynamics. We find that such a chiral chaotic device can be applied to achieve sensing with high sensitivity, wide detectable range, and strong robustness to the phase and orientation randomness of weak signals. Our work presents a promising candidate for on-chip sensing and may have applications in quantum networks and chaotic communications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07019v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun-Qiu Ge, Zhe Wang, Qian-Chuan Zhao, Jing Zhang, Yu-xi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication Tolerant Multi-Layer Integrated Photonic Topology Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimal multi-layer device design requires consideration of fabrication uncertainties associated with inter-layer alignment and conformal layering. We present layer-restricted topology optimization (TO), a novel technique which mitigates the effects of unwanted conformal layering for multi-layer structures and enables TO in multi-etch material platforms. We explore several approaches to achieve this result compatible with density-based TO projection techniques and geometric constraints. Then, we present a robust TO formulation to design devices resilient to inter-layer misalignment. The novel constraint and robust formulation are demonstrated in 2D grating couplers and a 3D polarization rotator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07104v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Probst, Arjun Khurana, Joel B. Slaby, Alec M. Hammond, Stephen E. Ralph</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photonic next-generation reservoir computer based on distributed feedback in optical fiber</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reservoir computing (RC) is a machine learning paradigm that excels at dynamical systems analysis. Photonic RCs, which perform implicit computation through optical interactions, have attracted increasing attention due to their potential for low latency predictions. However, most existing photonic RCs rely on a nonlinear physical cavity to implement system memory, limiting control over the memory structure and requiring long warm-up times to eliminate transients. In this work, we resolve these issues by demonstrating a photonic next-generation reservoir computer (NG-RC) using a fiber optic platform. Our photonic NG-RC eliminates the need for a cavity by generating feature vectors directly from nonlinear combinations of the input data with varying delays. Our approach uses Rayleigh backscattering to produce output feature vectors by an unconventional nonlinearity resulting from coherent, interferometric mixing followed by a quadratic readout. Performing linear optimization on these feature vectors, our photonic NG-RC demonstrates state-of-the-art performance for the observer (cross-prediction) task applied to the R\"ossler, Lorenz, and Kuramoto-Sivashinsky systems. In contrast to digital NG-RC implementations, this scheme is easily scalable to high-dimensional systems while maintaining low latency and low power consumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07116v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Cox, Joseph Murray, Joseph Hart, Brandon Redding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Res-U2Net: Untrained Deep Learning for Phase Retrieval and Image Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06657v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Conventional deep learning-based image reconstruction methods require a large amount of training data which can be hard to obtain in practice. Untrained deep learning methods overcome this limitation by training a network to invert a physical model of the image formation process. Here we present a novel untrained Res-U2Net model for phase retrieval. We use the extracted phase information to determine changes in an object's surface and generate a mesh representation of its 3D structure. We compare the performance of Res-U2Net phase retrieval against UNet and U2Net using images from the GDXRAY dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06657v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/JOSAA.511074</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of the Optical Society of America A, Vol. 41, Issue 5, pp. 766-773 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Osorio Quero, Daniel Leykam, Irving Rondon Ojeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemical Interface Damping by Electrochemical Gold Oxidation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06799v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chemical interface damping is a change in the effective collision frequency of conduction band electrons in metal originating from a chemical change of the metal interface. In this work, we present in-situ ellipsometric measurements that reveal the chemical interface damping effect from electrochemical oxidation of single crystal and polycrystalline gold films. We observe an increase in collision frequency of up to 21 meV for single-crystalline gold. To compare to results obtained with thiols and metal-oxides on gold nanoparticles, we normalize the collision frequency by the electron mean free path to the surface of the structure. We show that electrochemical gold oxidation provides a stronger effect on collision frequency than these coatings. Similar ellipsometric experiments have previously been conducted to investigate the optical properties of gold oxide, but without taking chemical interface damping into account. The change in reflection from oxidation of gold was solely attributed to the oxide coating. We also show that the chemical interface damping effect saturates at a larger effective oxide thickness, which is attributed to the stabilization of the gold-oxide interface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06799v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurice Pfeiffer, Xinyan Wu, Fatemeh Ebrahimi, Nadiia Mameka, Manfred Eich, Alexander Petrov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steady-State Micro-Bunching based on Transverse-Longitudinal Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06920v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, three specific scenarios of a novel accelerator light source mechanism called steady-state micro-bunching (SSMB) have been studied, i.e., longitudinal weak focusing, longitudinal strong focusing and generalized longitudinal strong focusing (GLSF). Presently, GLSF is the most promising among them in realizing high-power short-wavelength coherent radiation with a mild requirement on the modulation laser power. Its essence is to exploit the ultrasmall natural vertical emittance in a planar electron storage ring for efficient microbunching formation, like a partial transverse-longitudinal emittance exchange at the optical laser wavelength range. By invoking such a scheme, the laser modulator of an SSMB storage ring can work in a continuous wave or high duty cycle mode, thus allowing a high filling factor of microbunched electron beam in the storage ring and high average output radiation power. The backbone of it is the precision transverse-longitudinal phase space coupling dynamics, which is analyzed in depth in this paper. Based on the investigation, an example parameters set of a GLSF SSMB storage ring which can deliver 1 kW-average-power EUV light is presented. The presented work here, like the analysis on theoretical minimum emittances, transverse-longitudinal coupling dynamics, derivation of bunching factor and modulation strengths, is expected to be useful not only for the development of SSMB, but also future accelerator light sources in general which demand more and more precise electron beam phase space manipulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06920v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiujie Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restoring the topological edge states in a finite optical superlattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the emergence of edge states in a finite optical lattice and show that the boundaries of the lattice play a decisive role for their location in the corresponding energy spectrum. We introduce a simple parametrisation of the boundaries of the optical lattice and demonstrate the existence of an optimal choice of the values of the parameters which lead to an approximate restoration of chiral symmetry. A crucial property of this optimization is the suppression of tunneling between next-nearest neighboring wells of the lattice. This in turn allows the mapping of the optical lattice set-up to a finite SSH model. The topological character of the emerging edge states is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06924v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Katsaris, I. A. Englezos, C. Weitenberg, F. K. Diakonos, P. Schmelcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Net 835-Gb/s/{\lambda} Carrier- and LO-Free 100-km Transmission Using Channel-Aware Phase Retrieval Reception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07092v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We experimentally demonstrate the first carrier- and LO-free 800G/{\lambda} receiver enabling direct compatibility with standard coherent transmitters via phase retrieval, achieving net 835-Gb/s transmission over 100-km SMF and record 8.27-b/s/Hz net optical spectral efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07092v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanzi Huang, Haoshuo Chen, Qian Hu, Di Che, Yetian Huang, Brian Stern, Nicolas K. Fontaine, Mikael Mazur, Lauren Dallachiesa, Roland Ryf, Zhengxuan Li, Yingxiong Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature stabilization of a lab space at $10\,\mathrm{mK}$-level over a day</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07101v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Temperature fluctuations over long time scales ($\gtrsim 1\,\mathrm{h}$) are an insidious problem for precision measurements. In optical laboratories, the primary effect of temperature fluctuations is drifts in optical circuits over spatial scales of a few meters and temporal scales extending beyond a few minutes. We present a lab-scale environment temperature control system approaching $10\, \mathrm{mK}$-level temperature instability across a lab for integration times above an hour and extending to a few days. This is achieved by passive isolation of the laboratory space from the building walls using a circulating air gap and an active control system feeding back to heating coils at the outlet of the laboratory HVAC unit. The latter achieves 20 dB suppression of temperature fluctuations across the lab, approaching the limit set by statistical coherence of the temperature field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07101v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Fife, Dong-Chel Shin, Vivishek Sudhir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser driven melt pool resonances through dynamically oscillating energy inputs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spatially selective melting of metal materials by laser irradiation allows for the precise welding as well as the 3D printing of complex metal parts. However, the simple scanning of a conventional Gaussian beam typically results in a melt track with randomly distributed surface features due to the complex and dynamic behavior of the melt pool. In this study, the implications of utilizing a dynamically oscillating energy input on driving melt track fluctuations is investigated. Specifically, the laser intensity and/or intensity distribution is sinusoidally modulated at different scan speeds, and the effect of modulation frequency on the resulting surface features of the melt track is examined. The formation of periodically oriented surface features indicates an evident frequency coupling between the melt pool and the modulation frequency. Moreover, such a frequency coupling becomes most prominent under a specific modulation frequency, suggesting resonant behavior. The insights provided in this study will enable the development of novel methods, allowing for the control and/or mitigation of inherent fluctuations in the melt pool through laser-driven resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07195v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Rupp, Karen Schwarzkopf, Markus Doering, Shuichiro Hayashi, Michael Schmidt, Craig B. Arnold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low Polarization Sensitive O-band SOA on InP Membrane for Advanced Photonic Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14429v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Managing insertion losses, polarizations and device footprint is crucial in developing large-scale photonic integrated circuits (PICs). This paper presents a solution to these critical challenges by designing a semiconductor optical amplifier (SOA) in the O-band with reduced polarization sensitivity, leveraging the ultra-compact InP Membrane on Silicon (IMOS) platform. The platform is compatible with close integration atop electronics, via densely populated vertical interconnects. The SOA incorporates a thin tensile-strained bulk active layer to mitigate polarization sensitivity. The developed 500 um long SOA has a peak gain of 11.5 dB at 1350 nm and an optimal polarization dependency of less than 1 dB across a 25 nm bandwidth, ranging from 1312 nm to 1337 nm. The device is practical for integrated circuits where multiple amplifiers work in cascades with a minimal 6.5 dB noise figure (NF) measured at the gain peak. The designed vertical active-passive transition, achieved through inverse tapering, allows for effective field coupling in the vertical direction resulting in a transmission efficiency of over 95% at the transition and minimal polarization sensitivity of less than 3%. The device yields significant gain at a small current density of less than 3 kA/cm2 as the result of minimalist gain medium structure, reducing joule heating and improving energy efficiency. This is especially relevant in applications such as optical switching, where multiple SOAs populate the PIC within a small area. Consequently, the simulated and fabricated low polarization sensitive O-band SOA is a suitable candidate for integration into large-scale, ultra-compact photonic integrated circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14429v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JLT.2024.3369232</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Lightwave Technology</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Desalegn Wolde Feyisa, Salim Abdi, Rene van Veldhoven, Nicola Calabretta, Yuqing Jiao, Ripalta Stabile</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superresolution with the zero-phase imaging condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01013v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Wave-based imaging techniques use wavefield data from receivers on the boundary of a domain to produce an image of the underlying structure in the domain of interest. These images are defined by the imaging condition, which maps recorded data to their reflection points in the domain. In this paper, we introduce a nonlinear modification to the standard imaging condition that can produce images with resolutions greater than that ordinarily expected using the standard imaging condition. We show that the phase of the integrand of the imaging condition, in the Fourier domain, has a special significance in some settings that can be exploited to derive a super-resolved modification of the imaging condition. Whereas standard imaging techniques can resolve features of a length scale of $\lambda$, our technique allows for resolution level $R &lt; \lambda$, where the super-resolution factor (SRF) is typically $\lambda/R$. We show that, in the presence of noise, $R \sim \sigma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01013v2</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah Greer, Laurent Demanet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient activation of telecom emitters in silicon upon ns pulsed laser annealing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.10132v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The recent demonstration of optically active telecom emitters makes silicon a compelling candidate for solid state quantum photonic platforms. Particularly fabrication of the G center has been demonstrated in carbon-rich silicon upon conventional thermal annealing. However, the high-yield controlled fabrication of these emitters at the wafer-scale still requires the identification of a suitable thermodynamic pathway enabling its activation following ion implantation. Here we demonstrate the efficient activation of G centers in high-purity silicon substrates upon ns pulsed laser annealing. The proposed method enables the non-invasive, localized activation of G centers by the supply of short non-stationary pulses, thus overcoming the limitations of conventional rapid thermal annealing related to the structural metastability of the emitters. A finite-element analysis highlights the strong non-stationarity of the technique, offering radically different defect-engineering capabilities with respect to conventional longer thermal treatments, paving the way to the direct and controlled fabrication of emitters embedded in integrated photonic circuits and waveguides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.10132v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s43246-024-00486-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>G. Andrini, G. Zanelli, S. Ditalia Tchernij, E. Corte, E. Nieto Hernandez, A. Verna, M. Cocuzza, E. Bernardi, S. Virz\`i, P. Traina, I. P. Degiovanni, M. Genovese, P. Olivero, J. Forneris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid, antibiotic incubation-free determination of tuberculosis drug resistance using machine learning and Raman spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05653v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tuberculosis (TB) is the world's deadliest infectious disease, with over 1.5 million deaths annually and 10 million new cases reported each year. The causative organism, Mycobacterium tuberculosis (Mtb) can take nearly 40 days to culture, a required step to determine the pathogen's antibiotic susceptibility. Both rapid identification of Mtb and rapid antibiotic susceptibility testing (AST) are essential for effective patient treatment and combating antimicrobial resistance. Here, we demonstrate a rapid, culture-free, and antibiotic incubation-free drug susceptibility test for TB using Raman spectroscopy and machine learning. We collect few-to-single-cell Raman spectra from over 25,000 cells of the MtB complex strain Bacillus Calmette Guerin (BCG) resistant to one of the four mainstay anti-TB drugs, isoniazid, rifampicin, moxifloxacin and amikacin, as well as a pan susceptible wildtype strain. By training a neural network on this data, we classify the antibiotic resistance profile of each strain, both on dried samples and in patient sputum samples. On dried samples, we achieve &gt;98% resistant versus susceptible classification accuracy across all 5 BCG strains. In patient sputum samples, we achieve ~79% average classification accuracy. We develop a feature recognition algorithm in order to verify that our machine learning model is using biologically relevant spectral features to assess the resistance profiles of our mycobacterial strains. Finally, we demonstrate how this approach can be deployed in resource-limited settings by developing a low-cost, portable Raman microscope that costs &lt;$5000. We show how this instrument and our machine learning model enables combined microscopy and spectroscopy for accurate few-to-single-cell drug susceptibility testing of BCG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05653v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Babatunde Ogunlade, Loza F. Tadesse, Hongquan Li, Nhat Vu, Niaz Banaei, Amy K. Barczak, Amr. A. E. Saleh, Manu Prakash, Jennifer A. Dionne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric Transmission Through a Classical Analogue of the Aharonov-Bohm Ring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.14712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.14712v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been predicted that new physics and technology are enabled for quantum systems that suffer from partial decoherence, in the intermediate range between coherent quantum evolution and incoherent classical physics. We explore the asymmetric transmission through a classical analogue of the Aharonov-Bohm (AB) mesoscopic ring that supports a 3:1 asymmetry in transmission times, augmented with lossy features that act preferentially on the longer-lingering waves. Such a device is realized as a linear microwave graph utilizing a gyrator to create the 3:1 transmission time delay asymmetry, along with both homogeneous and localized losses, to produce an imbalance in wave transmission through the device. We demonstrate asymmetric transmission through the microwave-ring graph as a function of loss in both simulation and experiment, and in both the frequency- and time-domain. The microwave ring-graph results are compared to a numerical simulation representative of a class of recent models proposing dephasing-induced transport asymmetry in few-channel quantum systems, and parallels are noted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.14712v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Chen, Isabella L. Giovannelli, Nadav Shaibe, Steven M. Anlage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Theory for Non-linear Superconducting Microwave Systems: Extracting Relaxation Rates and Mode Hybridization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.03435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.03435v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The accurate modeling of mode hybridization and calculation of radiative relaxation rates have been crucial to the design and optimization of superconducting quantum devices. In this work, we introduce a spectral theory for the electrohydrodynamics of superconductors that enables the extraction of the relaxation rates of excitations in a general three-dimensional distribution of superconducting bodies. Our approach addresses the long-standing problem of formulating a modal description of open systems that is both efficient and allows for second quantization of the radiative hybridized fields. This is achieved through the implementation of finite but transparent boundaries through which radiation can propagate into and out of the computational domain. The resulting spectral problem is defined within a coarse-grained formulation of the electrohydrodynamical equations that is suitable for the analysis of the non-equilibrium dynamics of multiscale superconducting quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.03435v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dung N. Pham, Richard D. Li, Hakan E. T\"ureci</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
