<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 01:42:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optically Switchable Fluorescence Enhancement at Critical Interparticle Distances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Plasmonic nanostructures provide local field enhancement to be used as efficiency-boosting tools in fluorescence-based applications. For photostable quantum dots (QDs) to have enhanced emission, their size and exact location in the proximity of plasmonic nanostructure become key parameters while constructing light emitting devices. However, plasmonic nanostructures mostly suffer from non-radiative energy transfer at close proximity, which hinders the ultimate performance of fluorophores. In this work, we provided critical interparticle distances through finite difference time domain (FDTD) simulations, where the radiative decay rate is equalized to the non-radiative counterpart for light emitting QD-based technologies. To show the promises of the QD placement at a critical distance, we demonstrate an optical switch for the fluorescence efficiency of a CdSe/ZnS core-shell QD (CSQD) by optically exciting the silver nanoparticle (AgNP) placed at a critical distance. While the provided single particle spectroscopy allows for the observation of heterogeneity in CSQD-AgNP coupling that is often masked in ensemble measurements, our benchmark study serves as a base reference for the development of QD-based light emitting technologies by resolving the optically switchable active tuning of radiative decay rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11541v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arda Gulucu, Emre Ozan Polat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental evidence of a strange nonchaotic attractor in a Nd:YVO4 laser with saturable absorber</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11548v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The diode-pumped Nd: Vanadate laser is one of the most widely used lasers in the near-infrared range. Using passive Q-switching with a Cr:YAG saturable absorber (SA), it generates nanosecond pulses at tens of kilohertz. This laser is known to exhibit low-dimensional deterministic chaos. In this letter, we present experimental evidence of a strange nonchaotic attractor (SNA). SNAs exhibit complex dynamical behavior that is neither periodic nor chaotic, making them difficult to detect in real-world systems. They are typically observed in systems modeled by equations and arise through a route to chaos. By experimentally obtaining time series of two laser variables, we reconstruct the underlying attractor. For a certain position of the SA, we find that all Lyapunov exponents are negative and that the energy spectra exhibit a broad frequency range, indicating that the attractor is nonchaotic and lacks periodicity. Using Higuchi's method, we estimate the fractal dimension df and find that 13% of the nonchaotic time series exhibit a well-defined non-integer df, confirming the presence of an SNA. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first experimental observation of a strange nonchaotic attractor in a complex optical system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11548v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juliana Bourdieu, M\'onica Ag\"uero, Marcelo Kovalsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-localized ultrafast pencil beam for volumetric multiphoton imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The formation of organized optical states in multidimensional systems is crucial for understanding light-matter interaction and advancing light-shaping technologies. Here, we report the observation of a self-localized, ultrafast pencil beam near the critical power in a standard multimode fiber (MMF) and demonstrate its application in volumetric multiphoton imaging. We show that self-focusing in step-index MMFs, traditionally considered detrimental, can facilitate the formation of a nonlinear spatiotemporal localized state with a sidelobe-suppressed Bessel-like beam profile, exhibiting markedly improved stability and noise characteristics. By simply launching an overfilled on-axis Gaussian beam into a standard MMF, a high-quality ultrafast pencil beam can be generated through a self-localized process and readily integrated into an existing multiphoton point-scanning microscope. Moreover, in contrast to existing focus extension methods limited to low NA ($\le$0.7), this approach readily produces pencil beams compatible with high-NA (1.05) multiphoton imaging systems, exhibiting significantly reduced sidelobes and enhanced aberration robustness. Finally, we apply this self-localized pencil beam to two-photon imaging of intact mouse enteric nervous systems, benchmarking with diffraction-limited Gaussian beams and outperforming conventional Bessel beams. Our findings provide new insights into the nonlinear dynamics of multidimensional optical systems and offer a promising approach for generating high-quality ultrafast pencil beams for various beam-shaping applications, including microscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11618v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Honghao Cao, Li-Yu Yu, Kunzan Liu, Federico Presutti, Subhash Kulkarni, Sixian You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization-Tunable Colorimetric Metasurfaces for All-Optical and Non-Destructive Structural Characterization of Polymeric Nanofibers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metasurfaces have pioneered significant improvements in sensing technology by tailoring strong optical responses to weak signals. When designed with anisotropic subwavelength geometries, metasurfaces can tune responses to varying polarization states of light. Leveraging this to quantify structural alignment in fibrous materials unveils an alternative to destructive characterization methods. This work introduces metasurface-enhanced polarized light microscopy (Meta-PoL), which employs polarization-tunable, guided-mode-resonant colorimetric metasurfaces to characterize molecular and bulk alignment of poly({\epsilon}-caprolactone) (PCL) nanofibers in a far-field configuration. PCL nanofibers drawn at 0%, 400%, and 900% ratios were interfaced with the studied metasurfaces. Metasurface resonances coinciding with the intrinsic drawn nanofiber resonances - confirmed by Stokes Polarimetry - produced the strongest colorimetric enhancement, resultant from alignment-specific nanofiber reflectivity. The enhancement degree corresponded with molecular and bulk alignments for each draw ratio, as measured through differential scanning calorimetry and scanning electron microscopy, respectively. Thus, Meta-PoL presents an all-optical, non-destructive, and quantitative measurement of nanofiber alignment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11657v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paula Kirya, Justin D. Hochberg, Han Sol Kim, Zaid Haddadin, Samantha Bordy, Jiuk Byun, Jonathan K. Pokorski, Lisa V. Poulikakos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated photonics incorporating 2D materials for practical applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: On-chip integration of 2D materials with exceptional optical properties provides an attractive solution for next-generation photonic integrated circuits to address the limitations of conventional bulk integrated platforms. Over the past two decades, significant advancements have been made in the interdisciplinary field of 2D material integrated photonics, greatly narrowing the gap between laboratory research and industrial applications. In this paper, we provide a perspective on the developments of this field towards industrial manufacturing and commercialization. First, we review recent progress towards commercialization. Next, we provide an overview of cutting-edge fabrication techniques, which are categorized into large-scale integration, precise patterning, dynamic tuning, and device packaging. Both the advantages and limitations of these techniques are discussed in relation to industrial manufacturing. Finally, we highlight some important issues related to commercialization, including fabrication standards, recycling, service life, and environmental implications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11668v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0249703</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Physics Letters Photonics Volume 10, (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David J. Moss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infrared Imaging of Photochromic Contrast in Thiazolothiazole-Embedded Polymer Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11690v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing demand for optical technologies with dynamic spectral control has driven interest in chromogenic materials, particularly for applications in tunable infrared metasurfaces. Phase-change materials such as vanadium dioxide and germanium-antimony-tellurium, for instance, have been widely used in the infrared regime. However, their reliance on thermal and electrical tuning introduces challenges such as high power consumption, limited emissivity tuning, and slow modulation speeds. Photochromic materials may offer an alternative approach to dynamic infrared metasurfaces, potentially overcoming these limitations through rapid, light-induced changes in optical properties. This manuscript explores the potential of thiazolothiazole-embedded polymers, known for their reversible photochromic transitions and strong infrared absorption changes, for tunable infrared metasurfaces. The material exhibits low absorption and a strong photochromic contrast in the spectral range from 1500 cm-1 to 1700 cm-1, making it suitable for dynamic infrared light control. This manuscript reports on infrared imaging experiments demonstrating photochromic contrast in thiazolothiazole-embedded polymer and thereby provides compelling evidence for their potential applications for dynamic infrared metasurfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11690v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuren Z. Shuchi, Tyler J. Adams, Naz F. Tumpa, Dustin Louisos, Glenn D. Boreman, Michael G. Walter, Tino Hofmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional spatiotemporal optical vortices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spatiotemporal optical vortices (STOVs) with spiral phase in the space-time domain, which carry intrinsic transverse orbital angular momentum (OAM), introduce a new degree of freedom to light beams and exhibit unique properties. While integer and fractional spatial vortices have been extensively studied and widely applied, and research on integer STOVs have grown prosperously, fractional STOVs (FSTOVs), classified as STOVs with fractional spiral phases are rarely explored due to the challenges in characterizing rapidly varying spatiotemporal phases. Furthermore, approaches for the rapid recognition of FSTOVs are lacking. Herein, we experimentally and theoretically demonstrate the generation of FSTOVs in the far field. The generation, evolution, and diffraction rules of FSTOVs are revealed. Furthermore, a self-referential method for the rapid recognition of FSTOVs based on the energy ratio between the two end lobes of their diffraction patterns is proposed. This work will promote the development of the theory of light with transverse OAM, and open new opportunities for the applications of STOV, such as STOV-based optical communication and quantum information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11697v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunlin Huang, Peng Wang, Yilin Xu, Jun Liu, Ruxin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-channel Single-Pixel Imaging for a Composite Motion Target</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11742v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single-pixel imaging (SPI) exhibits cost-effectiveness, broad spectrum, and stable sub-Nyquist sampling reconstruction, enabling applications across diverse imaging fields.However, due to the inherent reconstruction mechanism, SPI is not well-suited for high-speed moving targets. To address these challenges, we propose a novel, universal SPI configuration for tracking and imaging moving objects.Unlike traditional motion compensation methods, our approach enables the recovery of targets undergoing arbitrary motion, including translation, rotation, periodic, or non-periodic movements, within a two-dimensional plane without increasing the number of modulation frames.By leveraging the centroid positions from multiple wavelength channels, we determine the target's motion state from a kinematic perspective. Moreover, we developed an adapted reconstruction method, the (P-IT) pseudo-inverse transformation method, which allows for the efficient reconstruction of objects with composite motion. With a maximum flip rate of 20 kHz for the digital micromirror device (DMD), the theoretical perception frame rate can reach up to 2222 Hz, comparable to that of conventional motion-compensated SPI for purely translational objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11742v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shao Chongwu, Cao Yue, Zhao Qing, Yao Xuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-fast and accurate multimode waveguide design based on dataset-based eigenmode expansion method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a dataset-based photonic simulation framework for multimode waveguide design, enabling ultra-fast simulations with high accuracy. Compared to conventional approaches, our method offers two to three orders of magnitude speed-up in complex multimode waveguide designs. Based on this approach, we demonstrate a silicon multimode waveguide bend with an effective radius of $30\,\mu\mathrm{m}$ under one second, with accuracy validated against commercial 3D finite-difference time-domain method. We further explore its utility for device optimization by designing a $20\,\mu \mathrm{m}$-radius, arbitrary power splitting ratio bends through thousands of optimization iterations, completed in just 68 minutes on a standard desktop CPU. This framework enables the rapid design and engineering of large-scale multimode photonic devices, making computationally intensive simulations more accessible to many photonic circuit designers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11801v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaesung Song, Young-Ik Sohn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refractive Index, Its Chromatic Disper-sion, and Thermal Coefficients of Four Less Common Glycols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report comprehensive measurements of the refractive index as a function of wavelength and temperature for four less commonly studied glycols: pentaethylene glycol, hexaethylene glycol, dipropylene glycol (mixture of isomers), and tripropylene glycol. The measurements cover the spectral range of 390-1070 nm and temperatures from 1{\deg}C to 45{\deg}C. The data were modeled using a two-pole Sellmeier equation, with temperature dependence captured by wavelength-dependent thermal coefficients. The resulting fit parameters are provided in tabulated form. Experimental uncertainties in refractive index, wavelength, and temperature were rigorously evaluated and incorporated into the analysis. The influence of sample purity - including residual water content and manufacturer-reported impurities - was assessed and accounted for in the uncertainty estimates. To our knowledge, this is the first dataset to systematically characterize both chromatic dispersion and thermal variation of the refractive index for these glycols over such a broad spectral and temperature range. The validated fitting equations and parameters are suitable for use in optical modeling, materials characterization, and related applications. All raw data are available in a publicly accessible repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11819v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasiya Derkachova, Daniel Jakubczyk, Gennadiy Derkachov, Kwasi Nyandey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Profile control of fibre-based micro-mirrors using adaptive laser shooting with $\textit{in situ}$ imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fibre Fabry-Perot cavities (FFPCs) are used in various studies in cavity quantum electrodynamics (CQED) and quantum technologies due to the cavity's small mode volume and compact integration with optical fibres. We develop a novel $\text{CO}_2$ laser machining method that produces well-controlled surface profiles on the end facets of cleaved optical fibres. Using multiple shots in distinct spatial distribution patterns, our method employs a shooting algorithm that adaptively changes laser ablation parameters during the shooting to suppress deviations from the desired profile. This is made possible by $\textit{in situ}$ imaging of the machined profile, its inspection and the usage of the information in the subsequent steps. Underlying this algorithm is a newly found laser ablation parameter, the pause between shots, which controls the accumulation of heat in between successive laser shots and as a result determines the area of impact made by an individual ablation sequence. We fabricate fibre-based micro-mirrors with radii of curvature ranging from 250 $\mu$m to 700 $\mu$m with an effective mirror diameter of 60 $\mu$m in either Gaussian or spherical profiles. Due to the self-correcting nature of our adaptive algorithm, we achieve a near 100\% success rate in the production of desired profiles with low ellipticity. After furnishing the laser machined fibre end facets with high reflectivity coating, FFPCs are formed to demonstrate a high finesse up to 150,000 at an optical wavelength of 854 nm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11824v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaobo Gao, Vishnu Kavungal, Shuma Oya, Daichi Okuno, Ezra Kassa, William J. Hughes, Peter Horak, Hiroki Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bloch phonon-polaritons with anomalous dispersion in polaritonic Fourier crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11842v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recently suggested concept of a polaritonic Fourier crystal (PFC) is based on a harmonically-corrugated mirror substrate for a thin pristine polaritonic crystal layer. The propagating polaritons in PFC experience a harmonic and mode-selective momentum modulation leading to a manifestation of Bloch modes with practically zero inter-mode scattering. PFC was first demonstrated for the hyperbolic phonon-polaritons in hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) within its Type II Reststrahlen band (RB-II) where the in-plane components of the dielectric permittivity tensor are isotropic and negative, while the out-of-plane component is positive. By contrast, a Type I Reststrahlen band (RB-I) is characterized by negative out-of-plane and positive in-plane permittivity components, and consequently, the inversion of field symmetry of phonon-polaritons compared to RB-II. Behavior of such RB-I modes in a polaritonic crystal is yet to be explored. Here, we employ a biaxial crystal alpha-phase molybdenum trioxide ({\alpha}-MoO3) and near-field imaging to study polaritonic Bloch modes in a one-dimensional PFC within the RB-I where the mid-infrared phonon-polaritons in {\alpha}-MoO3 have anomalous dispersion and negative phase velocity. Surprisingly, we observe a manifestation of Bloch waves as a dispersionless near-field pattern across the first Brillouin zone, in contrast to RB-II case demonstrated with in-plane isotropic hBN. We attribute this difference to the opposite field symmetry of the lowest-order phonon-polariton mode in the two RBs, leading to a different momentum modulation regime in the polaritonic Fourier crystal. Our results reveal the importance of mode symmetry for polaritonic crystals in general and for the emerging field of Fourier crystals in particular, which promise new ways to manipulate the nanolight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11842v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey G. Menabde, Yongjun Lim, Alexey Y. Nikitin, Pablo Alonso Gonzalez, Jacob T. Heiden, Heerin Noh, Seungwoo Lee, Min Seok Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-induced topological edge states in a lattice with onsite nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11964v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological edge states typically arise at the boundaries of topologically nontrivial structures or at interfaces between regions with differing topological invariants. When topological systems are extended into the nonlinear regime, linear topological edge states bifurcate into nonlinear counterparts, and topological gap solitons emerge in the bulk of the structures. Despite extensive studies of these two types of nonlinear states, self-induced topological edge states localized at the physical boundaries of originally nontopological structures remain underexplored. Unlike the previously reported self-induced topological transitions driven by nonlinear couplings, which are conceptually straightforward but less common in realistic interacting systems, here we experimentally realize self-induced topological edge states in a lattice with onsite nonlinearity. Leveraging the strong and tunable nonlinearity of electrical circuits, we systematically investigate the localized states in a nonlinear Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model. Besides revisiting the nonlinear topological edge states and topological gap solitons, we uncover a novel type of self-induced topological edge states which exhibit the hallmark features of linear topological edge states, including sublattice polarization, phase jumps, and decaying tails that approach zero. A distinctive feature of these states is the boundary-induced power threshold for existence. Our results are broadly applicable and can be readily extended to photonic and cold atomic systems, where onsite nonlinearities naturally arise from interparticle interactions. Our work unveils new opportunities for exploring novel correlated topological states of light and matter, and paves the way for the development of robust photonic devices and topological quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11964v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rujiang Li, Wencai Wang, Xiangyu Kong, Ce Shang, Yongtao Jia, Gui-Geng Liu, Ying Liu, Baile Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mode locking via delayed orthogonal-polarization reinjection in semiconductor lasers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate harmonic mode-locking in a semiconductor laser using orthogonal-polarization reinjection via an external ring cavity integrated with a rotatable $\lambda$/2-plate. By tuning the plate angle $\theta$, we achieve precise control over pulse multiplicity and repetition rates in orthogonal TE/TM modes. For the TE mode, increasing $\theta$ transitions the system from low amplitude and disordered quasi-periodic states to fundamental (single-pulse) mode locking and harmonic dual-pulse regimes. Polarization resolved measurements and cross-correlation analyses reveal polarization-mediated dynamics, achieving coherent pulse alignment at half the cavity roundtrip time. This work establishes orthogonal polarization feedback as a compact, versatile mechanism for tailoring ultrafast pulse trains, enabling applications in polarization-multiplexed communications, dual-comb spectroscopy, and high-repetition-rate photonic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11965v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Wang, Y. Ma, Z. Li, Y. Li, Z. Tu, Y. Zhang, G. Xu, S. Baland, S. Xiang, Y. Hao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-orientable Exceptional Points in Twisted Boundary Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11983v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-orientable manifolds, such as the M\"obius strip and the Klein bottle, defy conventional geometric intuition through their twisted boundary conditions. As a result, topological defects on non-orientable manifolds give rise to novel physical phenomena. We study the adiabatic transport of exceptional points (EPs) along non-orientable closed loops and uncover distinct topological responses arising from the lack of global orientation. Notably, we demonstrate that the cyclic permutation of eigenstates across an EP depends sensitively on the loop orientation, yielding inequivalent braid representations for clockwise and counterclockwise encirclement; this is a feature unique to non-orientable geometries. Orientation-dependent geometric quantities, such as the winding number, cannot be consistently defined due to the absence of a global orientation. However, when a boundary is introduced, such quantities become well defined within the local interior, even though the global manifold remains non-orientable. We further demonstrate the adiabatic evolution of EPs and the emergence of orientation-sensitive observables in a Klein Brillouin zone, described by an effective non-Hermitian Hamiltonian that preserves momentum-space glide symmetry. Finally, we numerically implement these ideas in a microdisk cavity with embedded scatterers using synthetic momenta.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11983v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jung-Wan Ryu, Jae-Ho Han, Moon Jip Park, Hee Chul Park, Chang-Hwan Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-stage hollow-core fiber-based compression of Yb:KGW lasers to the single-cycle regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The generation of intense, waveform-controlled, single-cycle pulses based on Yb:KGW amplifiers is central to integrating these lasers with attosecond metrology and spectroscopy. Here, we demonstrate single-stage, multi-octave (~ 2.4 octaves) spectral broadening of Yb:KGW amplified pulses in a neon-pressurized hollow-core fiber (HCF) capillary and their compression to the single-cycle regime (1.1 cycles at 880 nm) using chirped mirrors. Utilizing Homochromatic Attosecond Streaking (HAS), we characterize the field waveforms of the generated pulses and demonstrate precise control of their carrier-envelope phase. Our results provide a simplified route to single-cycle pulse generation using Yb:KGW technology, previously possible only with Ti:Sapphire-based front ends. This work paves the way for advanced applications in attosecond science, strong-field physics, and spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12064v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Pi, A. B. Enders, D. Vaso, E. Goulielmakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtually structured illumination for terahertz super-resolution imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12092v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate structured illumination super-resolution imaging in the Terahertz (THz) frequency band using the Virtually Structured Detection (VSD) method. Leveraging our previously reported high-speed, high-sensitivity atomic-based THz imager, we achieve a resolution enhancement of 74(3)% at 0.55 THz, without the aid of deconvolution methods. We show a high-speed THz imaging system is compatible with the use of advanced optical techniques, with potential disruptive effects on applications requiring both high speed and high spatial resolution imaging in the THz range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12092v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James P. Fleming, Lucy A. Downes, John M. Girkin, Kevin J. Weatherill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent EUV scatterometry of 2D periodic structure profiles with mathematically optimal experimental design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extreme ultraviolet (EUV) scatterometry is an increasingly important metrology that can measure critical parameters of periodic nanostructured materials in a fast, accurate, and repeatable manner and with high sensitivity to nanoscale structure and material composition. Because of this, EUV scatterometry could support manufacturing of semiconductor devices or polymer metamaterials, addressing the limitations of traditional imaging methods such as resolution and field of view, sample damage, throughput, or low sensitivity. Here we use EUV scatterometry to measure the profile of an industrially relevant 2D periodic interconnect structure, using $\lambda = 29$ nm light from a table-top high harmonic generation source. We show that EUV scatterometry is sensitive to out-of-plane features with single-nanometer sensitivity. Furthermore, we also apply a methodology based on the Fisher information matrix to optimize experimental design parameters, such as incidence angles and wavelength, to show how measurement sensitivity can be maximized. This methodology reveals the strong dependence of measurement sensitivity on both incidence angle and wavelength $-$ even in a simple two-parameter case. Through a simultaneous optimization of incidence angles and wavelength, we determine that the most sensitive measurement of the quantities of interest can be made at a wavelength of $\sim$14 nm. In the future, by reducing sample contamination due to sample preparation, deep sub-nanometer sensitivity to axial profiles and 2D structures will be possible. Our results are an important step in guiding EUV scatterometry towards increased accuracy and throughput with a priori computations and by leveraging new experimental capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12133v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clay Klein, Nicholas W. Jenkins, Yunzhe Shao, Yunhao Li, Seungbeom Park, Wookrae Kim, Henry C. Kapteyn, Margaret M. Murnane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Optical Spanner: Twisting Superconductors with Vortex Beam via Higgs Mode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11883v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Light carrying orbital angular momentum (OAM)--known as vortex beams--has broadened the scope of understanding and applications of light's angular momentum. Optical tweezers using OAM, often referred to as optical spanners, have significantly expanded the tunability of optical manipulation. A key frontier now lies in understanding how vortex beams interact with quantum states of matter. In this work, we numerically investigate the dynamics of a superconductor under vortex beam illumination and demonstrate the transfer of angular momentum from light to the superconducting collective mode, resulting in mechanical rotation. Our findings open a pathway for optical manipulation in the quantum regime, which we term the quantum optical spanner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11883v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daemo Kang, Sota Kitamura, Takahiro Morimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A LINAC-based, compact x-ray source by inverse Compton scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11897v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we present the first measured x-rays produced with a compact, tunable, inverse Compton scattering-based x-ray source. The experimental flux was $1.2 \cdot 10^3$ photons per shot, which was comparable to simulations. Additionally, the continuous tunability of photon energy and x-ray polarization control possible with the source are shown. The measured x-ray pulse length was in the picosecond range. By increasing experimental parameters, implementing improvements and further conditioning of the accelerator structure, an expected brilliance of $10^{12}$ photons/(s $\times$ mrad$^2$ $\times$ mm${^{2}}$ $\times$ 0.1\% BW) is expected, while maximum photon energies can go to 40 keV. Since the complete electron beamline will fit on a single optical table, it is suitable as in-house x-ray source for e.g. research institutes, companies, museums, and hospitals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11897v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. J. M. van Elk, C. W. Sweers, D. F. J. Nijhof, R. G. W. van den Berg, T. G. Lucas, X. F. D. Stragier, P. Tack, M. N. Boone, O. J. Luiten, P. H. A. Mutsaers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-time soliton dynamics via a coarse-grained space-time method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12286v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the long-time dynamics of the Sine-Gordon (SG) model under a class of perturbations whose quantum field theoretic analog - via bosonization - corresponds to the massive Schwinger model describing 1+1D relativistic QED of Dirac fermions. Classical SG solutions offer critical insight into non-perturbative effects in this quantum theory, but capturing their long-time behavior poses significant numerical challenges. To address this, we extend a coarse-graining method to spacetime using a dual-mesh construction based on the Minkowski-metric. We first validate the approach against the well-studied variant of the SG model describing magnetic fluxon dynamics in Josephson transmission lines (JTLs), where analytical and numerical benchmarks exist. We then apply the method to the Schwinger-inspired SG model and uncover long-lived bound states - "Schwinger atoms" - in which a soliton is trapped by a fixed central charge. In certain regimes, the system exhibits limit cycles that give rise to positronium-like states of oppositely charged solitons, while in others such formation is suppressed. Accessing such long-time solutions requires a rigorous implementation of outgoing boundary conditions on a finite computational domain that provide radiative dissipation to allow relaxation toward states that exist only in an infinite domain. Here we provide such a construction. Our results also suggest the possibility of analog quantum simulation of relativistic quantum field theories with JTLs. These results demonstrate the utility of spatio-temporal coarse-graining methodology for probing non-perturbative structure formation in non-linear field theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12286v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dung N. Pham, Zoe Zager, Wentao Fan, Hakan E. T\"ureci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal toroidal light beams with arbitrary polarization and orientation through a multimode fiber</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13246v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optical toroidal beams, with donut-shaped intensity profiles and orbital angular momentum (OAM), are promising for applications such as optical manipulation, metrology, and advanced light-matter interactions. However, practical implementations are limited by challenges in controlling their full 3D geometry and the orientation of their OAM. In this paper, we experimentally demonstrate high-dimensional, polarization-resolved, programmable 3D spatiotemporal toroidal beams with arbitrary 3D geometry. The beams are delivered after propagation through an optical multimode fiber (MMF) that supports 90 spatial/polarization modes. However, if desired, this system can also deliver these beams directly into free space as well. Our approach leverages 25,000 programmable spatiotemporal and polarization degrees of freedom to achieve precise manipulation of the amplitude, phase, polarization and temporal properties of toroidal beams. These beams feature highly customizable 3D geometries, allowing independent control of their aspect ratio and orientation. We further demonstrate the generation of beams with arbitrary OAM orientation, with beam rotations about any 3D spatiotemporal axis. These beams are delivered through an MMF which enables their transport deep into scattering materials and into otherwise hard-to-access regions which could include biological tissues. Hence, this device could enable the application of completely customizable optical manipulations, including rotations, deep within these materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13246v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew V. Komonen, Nicolas K. Fontaine, Martin Pl\"oschner, Marcos Maestre Morote, David T. Neilson, Joel Carpenter, Mickael Mounaix</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Inverse Design Wavelength Demultiplexer for On-Chip Photoluminescence Sorting in TMDC Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Emerging two-dimensional transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDCs) offer a promising platform for on-chip integrated photonics because of their unique optical and electronic properties. Their naturally passivated surfaces make them highly tolerant to lattice mismatch, enabling seamless heterogeneous integration by stacking different van der Waals materials, a crucial step in the development of advanced photonic devices. Here, we demonstrate the use of an inverse design wavelength demultiplexing waveguides for on-chip sorting and routing of distinct photoluminescence from the heterojunction formed by WS2 and WSe2 monolayers. The integrated nanophotonic chip splits and sorts excitonic emission into individual waveguides at room temperature. Our demonstration opens up new perspectives for integrating light sources in van der Waals materials with functional integrated photonics, offering a versatile platform for both fundamental research and practical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14261v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasiia Zalogina, Chi Li, Ivan Zhigulin, Nathan Coste, Hossein Alijani, Otto Cranwell Schaeper, Hugo Charlton, Joseph Ward, Haoran Ren, Igor Aharonovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Fields Formulation for Electromagnetic Waves Confined in Dielectric Rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17745v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an easy-to-implement numerical method for analyzing electromagnetic wave propagation in dielectric rings. Our approach employs a finite-difference-based solver in cylindrical coordinates, solving a mixed electric-magnetic field formulation to accurately enforce boundary conditions and compute resonant modes. The method avoids geometric transformations; instead, it directly discretizes the Helmholtz wave equation in cylindrical coordinates and solves the resulting generalized eigenvalue problem. We validate our model against commercial solvers for various structures, including a Si3N4 ring embedded in SiO2, a ring on a thin-film-coated substrate, and a torus, achieving agreement in effective refractive indices within 0.3%. The formulation accurately captures field confinement, curvature effects, and dispersion, enabling precise determination of propagation constants and mode profiles. As an application, we model optical frequency comb generation in a high-Q microresonator, predicting a free spectral range of 99.6 GHz and a loaded quality factor of 1.6 million, corroborated by experimental measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17745v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ergun Simsek, Alioune Niang, Raonaqul Islam, Logan Courtright, Gary Carter, Curtis R. Menyuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simple, robust and cost-effective method to achieve dispersion matching in swept source OCT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11184v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optical path length and dispersion matching in both measurement and reference arms of an OCT system is critical for achieving bandwidth-limited axial resolution. To minimize or eliminate dispersion mismatch, most, if not all, fiber-based OCT realisations employ a reference arm configuration that is as closely identical to the measurement arm as possible. This typically includes a collimator, dispersion compensating material (or sometimes a set of lenses), as well as a mirror (or retro-reflector) mounted on a translation stage. However, this solution makes the total instrument cost higher and the setup bulkier than necessary and it also renders the reference arm mechanically unstable. Here, a simple yet robust, low-cost reference arm setup is presented and its ability to compensate for measurement arm dispersion is demonstrated. We use a single-mode fiber cleaved and polished perpendicular to the fiber axis to construct the reference arm. The length and material of the fibre is determined by considering the optical path length and dispersion of the measurement arm. Experimental images demonstrate the operation of the novel reference arm in our Swept-source Optical Coherence Tomography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11184v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shau Poh Chong, Peter T\"or\"ok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective nuclear excitation and pulse propagation in single-mode x-ray waveguides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06508v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Waveguides offer a means to controllably couple atomic ensembles to the electromagnetic field therein. Here, we demonstrate x-ray propagation in planar thin-film waveguides coupled to M\"ossbauer nuclei under collective resonant excitation by short pulses of synchrotron radiation. We record x-ray photons that have been emitted into resonant modes of the waveguide. Depending on the geometry and mode of excitation, two fundamentally different signatures of the collective emission are observed, for which we present a unifying theoretical model. Our results form a new platform for waveguide quantum electrodynamics in the hard x-ray regime with the potential to provide a coherent narrowband source of x-rays on the nanometer scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06508v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leon M. Lohse, Petar Andreji\'c, Sven Velten, Malte Vassholz, Charlotte Neuhaus, Ankita Negi, Anjali Panchwanee, Ilya Sergeev, Adriana P\'alffy, Tim Salditt, Ralf R\"ohlsberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity-Vacuum-Induced Chiral Spin Liquids in Kagome Lattices: Tuning and Probing Topological Quantum Phases via Cavity Quantum Electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08121v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topological phases in frustrated quantum magnetic systems have captivated researchers for decades, with the chiral spin liquid (CSL) standing out as one of the most compelling examples. Featured by long-range entanglement, topological order, and exotic fractional excitations, the CSL has inspired extensive exploration for practical realizations. In this work, we demonstrate that CSLs can emerge in a kagome lattice driven by vacuum quantum fluctuations within a single-mode chiral cavity. The chiral cavity imprints quantum fluctuations with time-reversal symmetry breaking, fostering chiral interactions among electrons and stabilizing a robust CSL phase without external laser excitation. Moreover, we identify experimentally accessible observables -- such as average photon number and transport properties -- that reveal connections between photon dynamics and the emergent chiral order. Our findings establish a novel pathway for creating, controlling, and probing topological and symmetry-breaking quantum phases in strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08121v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenan Wei, Liu Yang, Qing-Dong Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast room-temperature valley manipulation in silicon and diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11591v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Some semiconductors have more than one degenerate minimum of the conduction band in their band structure. These minima-known as valleys-can be used for storing and processing information, if it is possible to generate a difference in their electron populations. However, to compete with conventional electronics, it is necessary to develop universal and fast methods for controlling and reading the valley quantum number of the electrons. Even though selective optical manipulation of electron populations in inequivalent valleys has been demonstrated in two-dimensional crystals with broken time-reversal symmetry, such control is highly desired in many technologically important semiconductor materials, including silicon and diamond. We demonstrate an ultrafast technique for the generation and read-out of a valley-polarized population of electrons in bulk semiconductors on subpicosecond timescales. The principle is based on the unidirectional intervalley scattering of electrons accelerated by an oscillating electric field of linearly polarized infrared femtosecond pulses. Our results are an advance in the development of potential room-temperature valleytronic devices operating at terahertz frequencies and compatible with contemporary silicon-based technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11591v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-025-02862-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Phys. (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adam Gindl, Martin \v{C}mel, Franti\v{s}ek Troj\'anek, Petr Mal\'y, Martin Koz\'ak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of edge solitons and transitions between them in a trimer circuit lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09932v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In nonlinear topological systems, edge solitons either bifurcate from linear topological edge modes or emerge as nonlinearity-induced localized states without topological protection. While electric circuits (ECs) provide a platform for realizing various types of topological insulators, observation of edge solitons and transitions between them in EC lattices remains a challenging problem. Here, we realize quench dynamics in nonlinear ECs to experimentally demonstrate both topological and nontopological edge solitons in a trimer EC lattice and transitions between them. In the weakly-nonlinear regime, we observe antisymmetric (alias staggered) and symmetric (alias unstaggered) edge solitons bifurcating from the respective topological edge states in the linear limit. Under the action of strong nonlinearity, nontopological edge solitons with antisymmetric, symmetric, and asymmetric (strongly confined) internal structures are discovered. This work suggests new possibilities for exploring sophisticated nonlinear states and transitions between them in nonlinear topological systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09932v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rujiang Li, Xiangyu Kong, Wencai Wang, Yixi Wang, Yongtao Jia, Huibin Tao, Pengfei Li, Ying Liu, Boris A. Malomed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum enhanced beam tracking surpassing the Heisenberg uncertainty limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14104v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Determining a beam's full trajectory requires tracking both its position and momentum (angular) information. However, the product of position and momentum uncertainty in a simultaneous measurement of the two parameters is bound by the Heisenberg uncertainty limit (HUL). In this work, we present a proof-of-principle demonstration of a quantum-enhanced beam tracking technique, leveraging the inherent position and momentum entanglement between photons produced via spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC). We show that quantum entanglement can be exploited to achieve a beam tracking accuracy beyond the HUL in a simultaneous measurement. Moreover, with existing detection technologies, it is already possible to achieve near real-time beam tracking capabilities at the single-photon level. The technique also exhibits high resilience to background influences, with negligible reduction in tracking accuracy even when subjected to a disruptive beam that is significantly brighter than SPDC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14104v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingwen Zhang, Duncan England, Noah Lupu-Gladstein, Frederic Bouchard, Guillaume Thekkadath, Philip J. Bustard, Ebrahim Karimi, Benjamin Sussman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
