<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 04:01:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-layer 5D Optical Data Storage: Mathematical Modeling and Deep Learning-Based Reconstruction of Birefringent Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Five-dimensional (5D) optical data storage has emerged as a promising technology for ultra-high-density, long-term data archiving. However, its practical realization is hindered by noise and interference during data readout. In this work, we develop a high-precision mathematical model for multi-layer 5D optical storage, grounded in the Jones matrix framework, to accurately capture polarization transformations induced by stacked birefringent nanostructures. Building on this model, we propose a 20-frame FiLM-conditioned U-Net algorithm to reconstruct birefringence parameters--specifically, slow-axis orientation and retardance magnitude-directly from measured intensity patterns. Trained on both ideal and noisy datasets, the network demonstrates robust reconstruction performance under challenging measurement conditions. Compared with conventional frame-based retrieval approaches, our method achieves over an order-of-magnitude improvement in reconstruction accuracy. The proposed model and algorithm can be readily integrated into existing 5D optical readout systems, offering both a solid theoretical foundation and practical tools for precise data recovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20106v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye Zhang, Qiao Zhu, Rongkuan Zhou, Tatiana Lysak, Chao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichography: Two-frame Ultrafast Imaging from a Single Diffraction Pattern</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20153v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: X-ray free-electron lasers can nowadays deliver pairs of ultrabright, ultrashort light pulses with controllable delays at different photon energies. When combined with diffraction experiments, the interaction of these pulses with a sample at different times can produce two snapshots of an evolving system, enabling spatial and temporal resolution of ultrafast dynamics in nanomatter at and beyond the terahertz time scale. However, light detectors are orders of magnitude slower. The diffraction signals from the two pulses overlap in the recorded data and cannot be separated using currently available analysis methods. Here, we address this challenge by introducing Dichography, a diffraction imaging technique that restores the two unique views of the sample from superimposed scattering signals. We apply Dichography to experimental diffraction patterns of isolated xenon-doped superfluid helium nanodroplets, imaged using time-delayed, two-color X-ray pulses at intensities near the detection limit. The reconstructed images provide evidence of the survival of the xenon structures up to 750 fs after the interaction with the first shot. The capabilities of Dichography are further explored by applying the method to data from a second experiment, in which we retrieve the images of two distinct silver nanoparticles intercepted by the same light pulse. Dichography enables a new class of experiments for spatially and temporally resolving ultrafast phenomena, making a significant step toward the original promise of X-ray free-electron lasers to capture ultrafast movies of nanomatter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20153v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linos Hecht, Andre Al Haddad, Bj\"orn Bastian, Thomas M. Baumann, Johan Bielecki, Christoph Bostedt, Subhendu De, Alberto De Fanis, Simon Dold, Thomas Fennel, Fanny Goy, Christina Graf, Robert Hartmann, Georg Jakobs, Maximilian Joschko, Gregor Knopp, Katharina Kolatzki, Sivarama Krishnan, Bj\"orn Kruse, Asbj{\o}rn {\O}. L{\ae}gdsmand, Bruno Langbehn, Suddhasattwa Mandal, Tommaso Mazza, Michael Meyer, Christian Peltz, Thomas Pfeifer, Safi Rafie-Zinedine, Antoine Sarracini, Mario Sauppe, Florian Schenk, Kirsten Schnorr, Bj\"orn Senfftleben, Keshav Sishodia, Frank Stienkemeier, Zhibin Sun, Rico Mayro P. Tanyag, Paul T\"ummler, Sergey Usenko, Carl Frederic Ussling, Vanessa Wood, Xinhua Xie, Maksym Yarema, Olesya Yarema, Nuri Yazdani, Hankai Zhang, Bernd von Issendorff, Yevheniy Ovcharenko, Marcel Mudrich, Daniela Rupp, Alessandro Colombo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low Loss Aluminum Nitride Waveguide Fabrication: Propagation Loss Reduction Through ALD and RTA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20245v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aluminum nitride (AlN) has emerged as a leading platform for integrated photonics in the visible and ultraviolet spectral ranges, particularly for quantum information applications involving trapped atoms. However, achieving low propagation loss in tightly confining single-mode AlN waveguides remains a challenge, especially at sub-micron wavelengths where scattering losses scale unfavorably. In this work, we present a reproducible and detailed fabrication process for low-loss AlN waveguides on sapphire, achieving a record loss of 2~dB/cm at 852~nm. Our results are enabled by systematic process optimization including high-resolution electron beam lithography with shape-based proximity effect correction, atomic layer deposition (ALD) of \ce{Al2O3} for waveguide surface passivation, and post-fabrication rapid thermal annealing (RTA). We provide a study of the contributions of each technique to propagation loss reduction and support our findings with quantitative loss measurements and comparison with an exhaustive literature review. This work represents the first detailed report of ALD passivation and post-cladding RTA applied to AlN waveguides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20245v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolay Videnov, Matthew L. Day, Michal Bajcsy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photonic restricted Boltzmann machine for content generation tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The restricted Boltzmann machine (RBM) is a neural network based on the Ising model, well known for its ability to learn probability distributions and stochastically generate new content. However, the high computational cost of Gibbs sampling in content generation tasks imposes significant bottlenecks on electronic implementations. Here, we propose a photonic restricted Boltzmann machine (PRBM) that leverages photonic computing to accelerate Gibbs sampling, enabling efficient content generation. By introducing an efficient encoding method, the PRBM eliminates the need for computationally intensive matrix decomposition and reduces the computational complexity of Gibbs sampling from $O(N)$ to $O(1)$. Moreover, its non-Von Neumann photonic computing architecture circumvents the memory storage of interaction matrices, providing substantial advantages for large-scale RBMs. We experimentally validate the photonic-accelerated Gibbs sampling by simulating a two-dimensional Ising model, where the observed phase transition temperature closely matches the theoretical predictions. Beyond physics-inspired tasks, the PRBM demonstrates robust capabilities in generating and restoring diverse content, including images and temporal sequences, even in the presence of noise and aberrations. The scalability and reduced training cost of the PRBM framework underscore its potential as a promising pathway for advancing photonic computing in generative artificial intelligence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20472v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Luo, Yisheng Fang, Wanyi Zhang, Zhichao Ruan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological photonics in nanoscaled systems with far field radiation and polarization singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topology is a powerful framework for controlling and manipulating light, minimizing detrimental perturbations on the photonic properties. Combining nanophotonics with topological concepts presents opportunities for both fundamental physics and technological applications. Although most topological photonic realizations have been inspired by condensed-matter analogue models, new topological ideas have just begun to be realized at the nanoscale. Nanophotonics is characterized by subtle phenomena that are not usually considered in other topological models' realizations, such as nonlocality, strong field confinement, and light radiating to the far-field continuum. In this perspective, we will discuss how standard topological band theory for photonic crystals needs to be extended by a more comprehensive approach that properly treats such nanophotonic intrinsic effects and, in particular, the interplay of polarization and far-field radiation. We highlight the emerging role that polarization singularities might play in defining the topological invariants in the far field, which are not fully captured by bulk observables alone. We conclude by outlining a set of open questions and promising directions for exploring novel concepts in topological nanophotonics and shaping next-generation photonic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20487v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0283167</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 127, 080501 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Grazia Salerno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact polarization-independent non-volatile optical switches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20490v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Compact, non-volatile optical switches on silicon platforms are essential for reconfigurable photonics, but the strong anisotropy of silicon waveguides leads to polarization-dependent performance. In this paper, we propose a polarization-independent, non-volatile optical switch utilizing low-loss phase change material (PCM) Sb2S3. By incorporating Sb2S3 into a multimode slot waveguide, multimode interference can be efficiently tuned for both TE and TM polarizations, owing to enhanced light-PCM interaction. Polarization-independent switching is achieved through the optimal design of the multimode slot waveguide region. The proposed non-volatile switch demonstrates a crosstalk (CT) &lt; -21.9 dB and insertion loss (IL) &lt; 0.12 dB at 1550 nm with a multimode section length of 9.67 {\mu}m, which may find promising applications in reconfigurable photonic circuits for on-chip optical signal processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20490v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangfa Bao, Jiakai Ruan, Weijia Li, Wei Zhang, Guoxiang Wang, Xiang Shen, Yixiao Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stacked Time-Varying Metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spatiotemporal metasurfaces offer unique opportunities for wave manipulation, however, their practical realization is often constrained by the requirement for in-plane spatial modulation, which necessitates a large number of time-varying elements. In this work, we introduce an alternative architecture based on a cascade of spatially uniform metasurfaces subjected to periodic temporal modulation. Although all metasurfaces share the same modulation frequency, their individual modulation functions are independently engineered to achieve a desired complex electromagnetic response. We develop a general theoretical framework for the design and optimization of such stacked metasurface systems, composed of dense arrays of cylindrical meta-atoms with time-varying plasma and/or collision frequencies. The effectiveness of the approach is demonstrated through the optimization of metasurface designs that enable magnet-free isolation at the fundamental frequency and a temporal analogue of circulators. Furthermore, we show that a metasurface stack can be implemented using only a few time-modulated elements embedded within a parallel-plate waveguide, opening new avenues for extremely compact, versatile, and scalable spatiotemporal platforms for next-generation photonic and microwave systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20506v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mostafa Movahediqomi, Sergei Tretyakov, Viktar Asadchy, Xuchen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transformation of topological optical states via spiral modulation in fractional-diffraction systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a scheme for manipulations of a variety of topological states in fractional optical systems through spiral modulation of the local refraction index. An analytical approximation, based on a truncated finite-mode system, and direct simulations reveal that the spiral modulation supports direct mutual conversion between eigenmodes with topological-charge difference \Delta m=1, driven by the resonant coupling between the modes and the underlying spiral modulation. The conversion between eigenmodes with \Delta m=2 requires involvement of an intermediary mode and precise tuning of the resonance condition. We further explore the conversion of degenerate modes under the action of azimuthal modulation. Modulated degenerate modes exhibit incomplete conversion, evolving into intermediate states with odd parity symmetry. Finally, we examine nonlinear effects on the spiral-modulation-induced mode conversion, identifying an essential nonlinearity-induced resonance-frequency shift that critically affects the conversion efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20651v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongdong Wang, Xueqing He, Rujiang Li, Dumitru Mihalache, Boris A. Malomed, Pengfei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric-field metrology of a terahertz frequency comb using Rydberg atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Terahertz radiation finds an increasing number of applications, yet efficient generation and detection remain a challenge and an active area of research. In particular, the precise detection of weak and narrowband terahertz signals is notoriously difficult. Here, we employ a novel type of single-photon detector based on Rydberg atoms to both detect and calibrate a terahertz frequency comb over an octave-spanning range, yet with a MHz-level selectivity. We calibrate the intensity of the electric field of the comb against the fundamental atomic properties, while achieving the intensity (power) sensitivity down to 35.9 $\mathrm{fW\ cm^{-2}\ Hz^{-0.5}}$ (1.46 $\mathrm{fW\ Hz^{-0.5}}$) within a single mode of the frequency comb, all in a room-temperature operated setup. Our results elucidate the transition of terahertz frequency combs into the quantum regime, enabling high-precision and high-sensitivity spectroscopy. This breakthrough allows terahertz science to better leverage revolutionary techniques developed for optical frequency combs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20698v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wiktor Krokosz, Jan Nowosielski, Bartosz Kasza, Sebastian Bor\'owka, Mateusz Mazelanik, Wojciech Wasilewski, Micha{\l} Parniak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward triggered generation of indistinguishable single-photons from MoTe$_2$ quantum emitters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single-photon sources operating in the telecom band are fundamental components for long-distance optical quantum communication and information processing. Two-dimensional (2D) transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) offer a promising platform for such sources, but their development has been hindered by limited spectral range and poor single-photon indistinguishability. Here, we demonstrate a reproducible and systematic approach for generating near-infrared (1090-1200 nm) quantum emitters in bilayer MoTe$_2$ using deterministic strain and defect engineering. These emitters exhibit strong linear polarization (DOLP $&gt;70\%$), sub-nanosecond lifetimes ($\tau \leqslant$ ~450 ps), high single-photon purity ($g^{(2)}(0)&lt;0.1$), and resolution-limited emission ($\sim$200 $\mu$eV). Electrostatic biasing enables Stark tuning over a $\sim$3 meV range, reduced photon bunching, and significantly shortened radiative lifetimes, yielding narrow emission with ratios of experimental to transform-limited linewidths as low as $R\sim55$. Most notably, two-photon interference measurements reveal a Hong-Ou-Mandel visibility of $V_\text{HOM}\sim $10$\%$, and up to $V_\text{HOM}\sim$ 40$\%$ with post-selection by temporal filtering, representing the highest reported indistinguishability for any TMD quantum emitters and the first such demonstration in the near-infrared regime. These results establish MoTe$_2$ as a viable platform for tunable, low-noise, high-purity single-photon sources with promising indistinguishability, paving the way for their integration into telecom-compatible quantum photonic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20743v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawe{\l} Wyborski, Athanasios Paralikis, Pietro Metuh, Martin A. Jacobsen, Christian Ruiz, Niels Gregersen, Battulga Munkhbat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Driven Programming of Photonic Integrated Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Programming photonic integrated hardware often reveals as a challenging task because of the presence of non-idealities in the photonic chip. These include fabrication imper- fections and parasitic effects such as thermal crosstalk, which cause unwanted coupling between control signals. Traditional control methods based on idealized models often fail to account for these phenomana, leading to significant discrepancies between the desired and actual circuit behaviour. In this work, we propose a data-driven approach for control- ling meshes of thermally tuneable Mach Zehnder interferometers (MZIs), which exploits a machine learning (ML) model trained to compensate for these non-idealities by pre- adjusting the electrical power given to integrated phase shifters. The proposed ML system is assessed using synthetic datasets and experimentally validated on a 3 x 3 triangular MZI mesh. Results demonstrate that the data-driven controller significantly improves program- ming accuracy, offering a robust solution for accurate programming of photonic integrated circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20882v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Cavicchioli, Gabriele Masini, Francesco Maria Sances, Francesco Morichetti, Andrea Melloni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A three-dimensional polarization-insensitive grating coupler tailored for 3D nanoprinting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20894v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficiently coupling light from optical fibers into photonic integrated circuits is a key step toward practical photonic devices. While a notable coupling can be achieved by out of plane couplers such as grating couplers, their basic planar geometry typically tends to be sensitive to the polarization of light. This is partly due to the fact that the design spaces of such grating structures typically fabricated with techniques such as electron beam lithography are only two dimensional with a simple extrusion into the vertical dimension. This makes it challenging to optimize for both polarizations simultaneously, as performance typically degrades when trying to achieve high efficiency in both. As a result, conventional approaches either suffer from increased losses or require additional filtering components to account for different polarizations. In this work, we present a fully three dimensional, polarization insensitive grating coupler which has a highly efficient simulated coupling efficiency of over 80% in both polarizations. This performance matches that of state of the art couplers that are performant for one polarization only. This comes at the cost of a moderately larger size due to the lower refractive index materials typically available in 3D nanoprinting. Our design method uses density based topology optimization with a multi objective approach that combines electromagnetic simulations with a fictitious heat conduction model acting as a soft constraint to promote structural integrity. This ensures that the designed structures are feasible for fabrication. Our work opens new possibilities for robust 3D photonic devices, enabling advanced integration, fabrication, and applications across next generation photonics and electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20894v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Kuster, Yannick Augenstein, Carsten Rockstuhl, Thomas Jebb Sturges</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse-electric Cherenkov Radiation for TeV-Scale Particle Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cherenkov radiation enables high-energy particle identification through its velocity-dependent emission angle, yet conventional detectors fail to detect momenta beyond tens of GeV/c owing to the absence of natural materials with near-unity refractive indices. We overcome this limitation by demonstrating directional Cherenkov radiation from transverse-electric (TE) graphene plasmons, excited by a swift charged particle travelling above suspended monolayer graphene. Crucially, TE graphene plasmons exhibit a near-unity mode index, sustaining high sensitivity of the Cherenkov angle to relativistic velocities up to the TeV/c regime. The radiation further maintains exceptional robustness against particle-graphene separation changes, enabled by the TE mode's low transverse decay rate. This ultracompact platform is electrically tunable, allowing on-chip, reconfigurable detection of ultrahigh-energy particles and extending measurable momenta by two orders of magnitude beyond existing detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20896v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhixiong Xie, Xiao Lin, Song Zhu, Chunyu Huang, Yu Luo, Hao Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-cone-proximal quasi-BICs for chiral lasing at grazing angles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral quasi-bound states in the continuum (q-BICs) have recently emerged in metaphotonics as resonances that combine ultrahigh quality factors with near-unity circular polarization. However, these states are typically confined to the Gamma-point (normal incidence) due to their symmetry-protected origins. We propose a new mechanism for realizing light-cone-proximal chiral q-BICs at large oblique angles, enabled by the divergence of the radiative local density of states near the light cone. Using dielectric metasurfaces with a monoclinic lattice and broken in-plane mirror symmetry, we demonstrate that tuning the lattice angle allows for robust control of these resonances. The resulting chiral q-BICs exhibit near-unity circular dichroism in transmission and fully circularly polarized emission at angles exceeding 50 degrees from normal. This approach paves the way for directional chiral lasing at grazing angles and for photonic devices operating efficiently in off-normal geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20915v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitrii Gromyko, Cheng-Wei Qiu, Kirill Koshelev, Lin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice-induced spin dynamics in Dirac magnet CoTiO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20354v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spin-lattice coupling is crucial for understanding the spin transport and dynamics for spintronics and magnonics applications. Recently, cobalt titanate (CoTiO3), an easy-plane antiferromagnet, has been found to host axial phonons with a large magnetic moment, which may originate from spin-lattice coupling. Here, we investigate the effect of light-driven lattice dynamics on the magnetic properties of CoTiO3 using time-resolved spectroscopy with a THz pump and a magneto-optic probe. We found resonantly driven Raman active phonons, phonon-polariton-induced excitation of the antiferromagnetic magnons, and a slow increase in the polarization rotation of the probe, all indicating symmetry breaking that is not intrinsic to the magnetic space group. The temperature dependence confirmed that the observed spin dynamics is related to the magnetic order, and we suggest surface effects as a possible mechanism. Our results of THz-induced spin-lattice dynamics signify that extrinsic symmetry breaking may contribute strongly and unexpectedly to light-driven phenomena in bulk complex oxides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20354v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey Baydin, Jiaming Luo, Zhiren He, Jacques Doumani, Tong Lin, Fuyang Tay, Jiaming He, Jianshi Zhou, Guru Khalsa, Junichiro Kono, Hanyu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diamond-loaded polyimide aerogel scattering filters and their applications in astrophysical and planetary science observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Infrared-blocking, aerogel-based scattering filters have a broad range of potential applications in astrophysics and planetary science instruments in the far-infrared, sub-millimeter, and microwave regimes. This paper demonstrates the ability of conductively-loaded, polyimide aerogel filters to meet the mechanical and science instrument requirements for several experiments, including the Cosmology Large Angular Scale Surveyor (CLASS), the Experiment for Cryogenic Large-Aperture Intensity Mapping (EXCLAIM), and the Sub-millimeter Solar Observation Lunar Volatiles Experiment (SSOLVE). Thermal multi-physics simulations of the filters predict their performance when integrated into a cryogenic receiver. Prototype filters have survived cryogenic cycling to 4\,K with no degradation in mechanical properties. Measurement of total hemispherical reflectance and transmittance, as well as cryogenic tests of the aerogel filters in a full receiver context, allow estimates of the integrated infrared emissivity of the filters. Knowledge of the emissivity will help instrument designers incorporate the filters into future experiments in planetary science, astrophysics, and cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20406v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyle R. Helson, Carol Yan Yan Chan, Stefan Arseneau, Alyssa Barlis, Charles L. Bennett, Thomas M. Essinger-Hileman, Haiquan Guo, Tobias Marriage, Manuel A. Quijada, Ariel E. Tokarz, Stephanie L. Vivod, Edward J. Wollack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed neural network enhanced multispectral single-pixel imaging with a chip spectral sensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20566v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multispectral imaging (MSI) captures data across multiple spectral bands, offering enhanced informational depth compared to standard RGB imaging and benefiting diverse fields such as agriculture, medical diagnostics, and industrial inspection. Conventional MSI systems, however, suffer from high cost, complexity, and limited performance in low-light conditions. Moreover, data-driven MSI methods depend heavily on large, labeled training datasets and struggle with generalization. In this work, we present a portable multispectral single-pixel imaging (MS-SPI) method that integrates a chip-sized multispectral sensor for system miniaturization and leverages an untrained physics-informed neural network (PINN) to reconstruct high-quality spectral images without the need for labeled training data. The physics-informed structure of the network enables the self-corrected reconstruction of multispectral images directly with the input of raw measurements from the multispectral sensor. Our proof-of-concept prototype achieves the reconstruction of 12-channel high-quality spectral images at the sampling rate of 10%. We also experimentally validate its performance under varying sampling rate conditions, by comparing it with conventional compressive sensing algorithms. Furthermore, we demonstrate the application of this technique to an MSI-based image segmentation task, in which spatial regions are discriminated according to their characteristic spectral signatures. This compact, high-fidelity, and portable approach offers promising pathways to lightweight and cost-effective spectral imaging on mobile platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20566v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muchen Zhu, Baolei Liu, Yao Wang, Linjun Zhai, Jiaqi Song, Nana Liu, Zhaohua Yang, Lei Ding, Fan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terahertz control of relativistic electron beams for femtosecond bunching and laser-synchronized temporal locking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20685v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Femtosecond relativistic electron bunches and micro-bunch trains synchronised with femtosecond precision to external laser sources are widely sought for next-generation accelerator and photonic technologies, from extreme UV and X-ray light sources for materials science, to ultrafast electron diffraction and future high-energy physics colliders. While few-femtosecond bunches have been demonstrated, achieving the control, stability and femtosecond-level laser synchronisation remains critically out of reach. Here we demonstrate a concept for laser-driven compression of high-energy (35.5 MeV) electron bunches with temporal synchronisation to a high-power (few-TW) laser system. Laser-generated multi-cycle terahertz (THz) pulses drive periodic electron energy modulation, enabling subsequent magnetic compression capable of generating tuneable picosecond-spaced bunch trains with 30 pC total charge and 50 A peak currents, or to compress a single bunch by a factor of 27 down to 15 fs duration. The THz-driven compression simultaneously drives temporal-locking of the bunch to the THz drive laser, providing a route to femtosecond-level synchronisation, overcoming the timing jitter inherent to radio-frequency accelerators and high-power laser systems. This THz technique offers compact and flexible bunch control with unprecedented temporal synchronisation, opening a pathway to unlock new capabilities for free electron lasers, ultrafast electron diffraction and novel plasma accelerators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20685v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Morgan T. Hibberd, Christopher T. Shaw, Joseph T. Bradbury, Daniel S. Lake, Connor D. W. Mosley, Sergey S. Siaber, Laurence J. R. Nix, Beatriz Higuera-Gonz\'alez, Thomas H. Pacey, James K. Jones, David A. Walsh, Robert B. Appleby, Graeme Burt, Darren M. Graham, Steven P. Jamison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Response by Time-Varying Plasmonic Nanoparticles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21009v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The temporal modulation of material parameters enables optical amplification within linear media. Here we consider the fundamental building block of plasmonics, a subwavelength metal nanoparticle, and study how temporal modulation alters the optical response of the frequency-dispersive scatterers. We show that modulating in time leads to Floquet replicas of the localized surface plasmon resonance of the nanoparticle, which can result in light amplification. We propose a model based on a point-like dipole description of the time-varying frequency-dispersive nanoparticle that fully captures the radiative and amplifying properties of the system in the subwavelength regime. By comparing our simplified model to full Floquet-Mie scattering calculations, we demonstrate that the optical scattering by the nanoparticle is accurately described by an analytical two-band model. This allows us to introduce a two-frequency effective polarizability that fully incorporates the properties of the localized surface plasmon and its amplifying replica, as well as their interaction. In addition, we analyze the emergence of the parametric amplification condition for the modulated nanoparticle, showing that amplification can be obtained in a broad range of parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21009v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Verde, Paloma A. Huidobro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super-sensing: 100-Fold enhancement in THz time-domain spectroscopy contrast via superoscillating waveform shaping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12665v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superoscillations are a phenomenon where a band-limited wave may locally oscillate faster than its highest Fourier component. They are a product of destructive interference between the wave's constituent harmonics. In this article, we demonstrate that superoscillations enable a new functionality in linear optical sensing -- the 100-fold enhancement in the optical contrast of the terahertz wave passing through two similar samples. To achieve this enhancement, we optimize the optical contrast in the time domain in a short observation window by varying the relative phases between the fundamental harmonics that make up the input terahertz wave. We find that the contrast is maximized when the wave intensity is minimized locally within the observation window, which naturally leads to the emergence of the superoscillations. We observe the 100-fold contrast enhancement both in our numerical simulations with Gaussian time-domain harmonics and in our experimental realization with narrow-band quasi-sinusoidal terahertz harmonics. Our results will have profound influence on terahertz sensing and imaging applications in medicine, pharmaceuticals, stand-off hazard detection, and nondestructive evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12665v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0271556</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>APL Photonics 1 August 2025; 10 (8): 086107</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Peisong Peng, Dusty R. Lindberg, Gerard McCaul, Denys I. Bondar, Diyar Talbayev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MINFLUX -- molecular resolution with minimal photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15902v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optical super-resolution microscopy is a key technology for structural biology that offers high imaging contrast and live-cell compatibility. Minimal (fluorescence) photons flux microscopy, or MINFLUX, is an emerging super-resolution technique that localizes single fluorophores with high spatiotemporal precision by targeted scanning of a patterned excitation beam featuring a minimum. MINFLUX offers super-resolution imaging with nanometer resolution. When tracking single fluorophores, MINFLUX can achieve nanometer spatial and sub-millisecond temporal resolution over long tracks, greatly outperforming camera-based techniques. In this review, we present the basic working principle of MINFLUX and explain how it can reach high photon efficiencies. We then outline the advantages and limitations of MINFLUX, describe recent extensions and variations of MINFLUX and, finally, provide an outlook for future developments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15902v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41566-025-01625-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Photon. 19, 238-247 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Scheiderer, Zach Marin, Jonas Ries</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon State Evolution in Arbitrary Time-Varying Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04836v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the instantaneous eigenstate method to study the evolution of quantum states in media with arbitrary time-varying permittivity and permeability. This method leverages the Heisenberg equation to bypass the Schr\"odinger equation, which leads to a complicated infinite set of coupled differential equations. Instead, the method allows the computation of the state evolution by solving only two coupled differential equations. Using this approach, we draw general conclusions about photon statistics in time-varying media. Our findings reveal that the maximum probability of generating a single photon pair from vacuum in such media is 25%, while Bell states can be created with a maximum probability of 84%. Additionally, we demonstrate that the spectral profile of emitted photons can be precisely controlled through the temporal profiles of permittivity and permeability. These results provide deeper insights into photon state manipulation in time-varying media. Furthermore, the instantaneous eigenstate method opens new opportunities to study state evolution in other systems where the Heisenberg equation offers a more tractable solution than the Schr\"odinger equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04836v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Artuur Stevens, Christophe Caloz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding passive, reciprocal metasurfaces for arbitrary wave transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20880v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a general design method for finding the passive, reciprocal surface impedance tensor required to enact any wave transformation. We do this through characterising the surface in terms of a tensorial surface impedance, showing that a large family of impedance distributions can be found that perform an identical wave transformation. Even when the conditions of reciprocity and passivity are imposed, there still remain many solutions to the design problem.} We exploit this as a design method for metasurfaces, giving two examples where the metasurface rotates the input polarization and reshapes the output field, showing we can parameterize the set of equivalent reciprocal metasurfaces in terms of a single complex parameter. \hl{In addition, through allowing dissipation and gain within the response, the surface can have many different functionalities in the orthogonal polarization, opening up a new route for the design of multiplexed metasurfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20880v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. O. Arnold, C. Hooper, J. Smith, N. Clow, A. P. Hibbins, J. R. Sambles, S. A. R. Horsley</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
