<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the optical properties of organometallic nanoparticles with a scale-bridging method: The importance of the embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It remains a prime question of how to describe the optical properties of large molecular clusters accurately. Quantum chemical methods capture essential electronic details but are infeasible for entire clusters, while optical simulations handle cluster-scale effects but miss crucial quantum effects. To overcome such limitations, we apply here a multi-scale modeling approach, combining precise quantum chemistry calculations with Maxwell scattering simulations, to study the linear and nonlinear optical response of finite-size supramolecular gold-cysteine nanoparticles dispersed in water. In this approach, every molecular unit that forms the cluster is represented by a polarizability and a hyperpolarizability, and the overall response is obtained from solving an optical multiple scattering problem. We particularly demonstrate how important it is to accurately consider the environment of the individual molecular units when computing their polarizability and hyperpolarizability. In our quantum chemical simulations, we do so at the level of a static partial charge field that represents the presence of other molecular units. Without correctly considering these effects of the embedding, predictions would deviate from experimental observations even qualitatively. Our findings pave the way for more accurate predictions of the optical response of complex molecular systems, which is crucial for advancing applications in nanophotonics, biosensing, and molecular optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07904v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariia Poleva, Benedikt Zerulla, Christof Holzer, Vlasta Bona\v{c}i\'c-Kouteck\'y, Anna Pniakowska, Joanna Olesiak-Banska, Rodolphe Antoine, Ivan Fernandez-Corbaton, Carsten Rockstuhl, Marjan Krsti\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear optical response in kagome lattice with inversion symmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08289v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The kagome lattice is a fundamental model structure in condensed matter physics and materials science featuring symmetry-protected flat bands, saddle points, and Dirac points. This structure has emerged as an ideal platform for exploring various quantum physics. By combining effective model analysis and first-principles calculations, we propose that the synergy among inversion symmetry breaking, flat bands, and saddle point-related van Hove singularities within the kagome lattice holds significant potential for generating strong second-order nonlinear optical response. This property provides an inspiring insight into the practical application of the kagome-like materials, which is helpful for a comprehensive understanding of kagome lattice-related physics. Moreover, this work offers an alternative approach for designing materials with strong a second-order nonlinear optical response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08289v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsnano.4c17371</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyang Liu, Junwen Lai, Jie Zhan, Tianye Yu, Peitao Liu, Seiji Yunoki, Xing-Qiu Chen, Yan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Germanium-Based Mid-Infrared Photonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mid-infrared (mid-IR) spectral range is a part of the electromagnetic spectrum in which most of the molecules have vibrational and rotational resonances. Ge-based photonic integrated circuits in this wavelength range have thus seen a burst of interest in the recent years, mainly driven by applications related with the detection of chemical and biological substances. Here we review the motivations and the recent developments in this field, from the different material platforms to active and nonlinear devices. We also discuss a few demonstrations of sensing that have already been conducted, attesting the potential applications of such devices. Finally, we conclude by discussing the challenges that have to be solved to transition from lab demonstrations to practical industrial devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08519v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Delphine Marris-Morini, Goran Z. Mashanovich, Milos Nedeljkovic, Carlos Alonso-Ramos, Laurent Vivien, Jacopo Frigerio, Giovanni Isella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-orbit interactions induced by light drag in moving media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin-orbit interactions (SOIs) of light are manifestations of coupling between components of light's angular momentum. They are at play in most basic optical processes, offering opportunities both to understand their fundamental origin and to control light in novel ways. Because SOIs become significant at subwavelength scale, they have largely been explored in the context of inhomogeneous materials exhibiting wavelength-scale structures, and notably metamaterials. Here we demonstrate that spin-orbit interactions can in fact analogously emerge in moving matter through the well-known light-dragging effects. SOIs in moving media are shown to manifest through a Berry phase induced by vorticity, which then leads to a rotation of the wave's polarization. In bringing together electrodynamics of moving media and SOIs of light, our work not only paves the way for the discovery of new fundamental effects but also uncovers novel means to harness SOIs to control light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08621v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aymeric Braud, Renaud Gueroult</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal electronic synthesis by microresonator-soliton photomixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Access to electrical signals across the millimeter-wave (mmW) and terahertz (THz) bands offers breakthroughs for high-performance applications. Despite generations of revolutionary development, integrated electronics are challenging to operate beyond 100 GHz. Therefore, new technologies that generate wideband and tunable electronic signals would advance wireless communication, high-resolution imaging and scanning, spectroscopy, and network formation. Photonic approaches have been demonstrated for electronic signal generation, but at the cost of increased size and power consumption. Here, we describe a chip-scale, universal mmW frequency synthesizer, which uses integrated nonlinear photonics and high-speed photodetection to exploit the nearly limitless bandwidth of light. We use a photonic-integrated circuit to generate dual, microresonator-soliton frequency combs whose interferogram is fundamentally composed of harmonic signals spanning the mmW and THz bands. By phase coherence of the dual comb, we precisely stabilize and synthesize the interferogram to generate any output frequency from DC to &gt;1000 GHz. Across this entire range, the synthesizer exhibits exceptional absolute fractional frequency accuracy and precision, characterized by an Allan deviation of 3*10^(-12) in 1 s measurements. We use a modified uni-traveling-carrier (MUTC) photodiode with an operating frequency range to 500 GHz to convert the interferogram to an electrical signal, generating continuously tunable tones across the entire mmW band. The synthesizer phase noise at a reference frequency of 150 GHz is -83 dBc/Hz at 100 kHz offset, which exceeds the intrinsic performance of state-of-the-art CMOS electronics. Our work harnesses the coherence, bandwidth, and integration of photonics to universally extend the frequency range of current, advanced-node CMOS microwave electronics to the mmW and THz bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08707v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jizhao Zang, Travis C. Briles, Jesse S. Morgan, Andreas Beling, Scott B. Papp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full-volume aberration-space holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simultaneous, diffraction-limited control of multiple optical beams is crucial for applications ranging from lithography to optogenetics, deep tissue imaging, and tweezer-based manipulation of cells, particles, or atoms. Despite the desire to address wider fields of view, deeper volumes, and increasingly-disordered media, spatially-varying aberrations currently restrict parallelized steering to a limited "isoplanatic" region over which the point spread function is invariant. Here, we overcome this limitation by combining individual propagation kernels accounting for site-specific aberrations into a single spatial light modulator (SLM) hologram. This "aberration-space holography" unlocks precise, parallel holographic shaping over the SLM's entire Nyquist-limited volume, enabling us to realize full-field, anisoplanatic aberration compensation for the first time. By simultaneously correcting 50 isoplanatic patches with 8 principal aberration modes, we demonstrate a full-field optical tweezer array with 8x larger field of view than the best isoplanatic correction. Extending to 3D, we increase the volume of a multiphoton volumetric display by 12x. These performance enhancements are immediately accessible to a diverse range of applications through our open-source software implementation, which combines aberration-space holography with automated experimental feedback, wavefront calibration, and alignment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08777v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Christen, Christopher Panuski, Thomas Propson, Dirk Englund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrahigh-speed digital holography for quantitative Doppler imaging of the human retina</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07823v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-speed digital holography reveals local blood flow contrasts in the eye fundus through deterministic signal analysis, leveraging a forward scattering model of dynamically diffused light. This approach enables the estimation of absolute blood flow in primary in-plane retinal arteries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07823v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zacharie Auray, Yann Fischer, Olivier Martinache, Michael Atlan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-correlation scheme for quantum optical coherence tomography based on Michelson interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08095v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum optical coherence tomography (QOCT) offers a simple way to cancel dispersion broadening in a sample while also providing twice the resolution compared to classical OCT. However, to achieve these advantages, a bright and broadband source of entangled photon pairs is required. A simple implementation uses collinear spontaneous parametric down-conversion in a Michelson interferometer (MI), yet this autocorrelation scheme suffers from parasitic terms and sensitivity to phase noise. Here, we introduce a cross-correlation MI-based QOCT that overcomes these drawbacks, significantly advancing QOCT toward practical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08095v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Romanova, Vadim Rodimin, Konstantin Katamadze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of Multilayer Coating Thickness on Interwoven Carbon-Fiber-Reinforced Polymers Using the Terahertz PHASR Scanner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Coating thickness measurement and inspection of defects beneath optically opaque surfaces are among the most promising commercial applications of the terahertz (THz) imaging technology. However, there are two main sources of complexity in THz spectral measurements that have resulted in reduced accuracy and high uncertainty in the determination of coating thicknesses. These factors include: 1. The need for \textit{a priori} knowledge of the complex index of refraction of each coating layer, and 2. The complex and polarization-sensitive reflectivity of samples with carbon-fiber-reinforced polymer (CFRP) substrates. In this paper, we propose a combined hardware and software solution to address these two limitations. We employ the polarimetric version of our Portable HAndheld Spectral Reflection (PHASR) Scanner and use a novel training model on time-of-flight measurements obtained by sparse deconvolution of the THz time-domain pulses. Our method does not depend on separate measurement of the index of refraction of the coating layers; rather, it relies on a physics-based linear model, trained using a small subset of the sample data. We show that thickness measurements with mean square error of about 10 $\mu$m and accuracy of more than 92\% can be achieved when the useful bandwidth of the scanner is limited to about 1.5 THz using photoconductive antenna emitters and detectors. We show that the anisotropic response of the carbon fiber bundles and the weave pattern structure of the substrate can significantly influence the accuracy of the coating measurement, and therefore a polarimetric imaging approach should be used for inspection of similar samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08172v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arash Karimi, Zachery B. Harris, Erica Heller, Paul Vahey, M. Hassan Arbab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden quantum-classical correspondence in chaotic billiards revealed by mutual information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08205v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Avoided level crossings, commonly associated with quantum chaos, are typically interpreted as signatures of eigenstate hybridization and spatial delocalization, often viewed as ergodic spreading. We show that, contrary to this expectation, increasing chaos in quantum billiards enhances mutual information between conjugate phase space variables, revealing nontrivial correlations. Using an information-theoretic decomposition of eigenstate entropy, we demonstrate that spatial delocalization may coincide with increased mutual information between position and momentum. These correlations track classical invariant structures in phase space and persist beyond the semiclassical regime, suggesting a robust information-theoretic manifestation of quantum-classical correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08205v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyu-Won Park, Soojoon Lee, Kabgyun Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the first quantization and quantum diversity of photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum theory of photons based on the first quantization technique, similar to that used by Schroedinger in the formulation of quantum mechanics, is considered. First, scalar quantum mechanics of photons operating with the photon wave functions is discussed. Using the first quantization, the wave equation, the Schroedinger-like equations, and the Dirac equation for photons are derived. Then, vector quantum mechanics of photons is introduced, which defines the electromagnetic vector fields. Using the first quantization, the Maxwell equations for photons in magneto-dielectric medium are obtained. Since the photon electric and magnetic fields satisfy the Maxwell equations, all what is known about the classical optical fields can be directly transferred to photons demonstrating their quantum diversity. Relationships between the scalar and vector quantum mechanics of photons and between the Dirac and Maxwell equations are analyzed. To describe the propagation of photons in dispersive media novel equations are introduced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08369v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Chichkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broadband Visible Wavelength Microcomb Generation In Silicon Nitride Microrings Through Air-Clad Dispersion Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01577v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The development of broadband microresonator frequency combs at visible wavelengths is pivotal for the advancement of compact and fieldable optical atomic clocks and spectroscopy systems. Yet, their realization necessitates resonators with anomalous dispersion, an arduous task due to the prevailing normal dispersion regime of materials within the visible spectrum. In this work, we evince that silicon nitride microring resonators with air cladding on top and sides -- a deviation from the frequently employed silica-embedded resonators -- allows for the direct generation of broadband microcombs in the visible range. We experimentally demonstrate combs pumped at 1060~nm (283~THz) that reach wavelengths as short as 680~nm (440 THz), and combs pumped at 780~nm (384 THz) that reach wavelengths as short as 630 nm (475 THz). We further show through simulations that microcombs extending to wavelengths as low as 461 nm (650 THz) should be accessible in this platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01577v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/lpor.202401746</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Laser &amp; Photonics Reviews, 202401746, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gregory Moille, Daron Westly, Rahul Shrestha, Khoi Tuan Hoang, Kartik Srinivasan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-Chip Parametric Synchronization of a Dissipative Kerr Soliton Microcomb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05388v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Synchronization of oscillators is ubiquitous in nature. Often, the synchronized oscillators couple directly, yet in some cases synchronization can arise from their parametric interactions. Here, we theoretically predict and experimentally demonstrate the parametric synchronization of a dissipative Kerr soliton frequency comb. We specifically show that the parametric interaction between the soliton and two auxiliary lasers permits the entrainment of the frequency comb repetition rate. Besides representing the first prediction and demonstration of parametric synchronization of soliton frequency combs, our scheme offers significant flexibility for all-optical metrological-scale stabilization of the comb.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05388v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.193802</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 193802, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gregory Moille, Pradyoth Shandilya, Miro Erkintalo, Curtis R. Menyuk, Kartik Srinivasan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Up Purcell-Enhanced Self-Assembled Nanoplasmonic Perovskite Scintillators into the Bulk Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18477v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scintillators convert high-energy radiation into detectable photons and play a crucial role in medical imaging and security applications. The enhancement of scintillator performance through nanophotonics and nanoplasmonics, specifically using the Purcell effect, has shown promise but has so far been limited to ultrathin scintillator films because of the localized nature of this effect. This study introduces a method to expand the application of nanoplasmonic scintillators to the bulk regime. By integrating 100-nm-sized plasmonic spheroid and cuboid nanoparticles with perovskite scintillator nanocrystals, we enable nanoplasmonic scintillators to function effectively within bulk-scale devices. We experimentally demonstrate power and decay rate enhancements of up to (3.20 $\pm$ 0.20) and (4.20 $\pm$ 0.31) folds for plasmonic spheroid and cuboid nanoparticles, respectively, in a 5-mm thick CsPbBr$_{3}$ nanocrystal-polymer scintillator at RT. Theoretical modeling also predicts similar enhancements of up to (2.26 $\pm$ 0.31) and (3.02 $\pm$ 0.69) folds for the same nanoparticle shapes and dimensions. Moreover, we demonstrate a (2.07 $\pm$ 0.39) fold increase in light yield under $^{241}$Am $\gamma$-excitation. These findings provide a viable pathway for utilizing nanoplasmonics to enhance bulk scintillator devices, advancing radiation detection technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18477v5</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adma.202417874</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advanced Materials 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michal Makowski, Wenzheng Ye, Dominik Kowal, Francesco Maddalena, Somnath Mahato, Yudhistira Tirtayasri Amrillah, Weronika Zajac, Marcin Eugeniusz Witkowski, Konrad Jacek Drozdowski,  Nathaniel, Cuong Dang, Joanna Cybinska, Winicjusz Drozdowski, Ferry Anggoro Ardy Nugroho, Christophe Dujardin, Liang Jie Wong, Muhammad Danang Birowosuto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin photonic topological metasurface based on kagome lattice and leaky-wave application</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03193v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The emerging field of topological metasurfaces offers unique advantages, particularly in robustness against backscattering in low-profile structures. The lattice configuration of these structures significantly influences the ability to achieve sharp turns in the propagation path. One of the most studied lattices in condensed matter physics is the kagome lattice, characterized by its hexagonal Brillouin zone, which displays a Dirac cone in its dispersion diagram. Previous research on kagome lattices in photonic topological insulators has primarily focused on valley types of insulators. This article introduces a spin topological metasurface based on the kagome lattice and its unit cell, enabling a broad range of sharp turns and propagation paths. The unit cell is compared to its hexagonal and 60-degree rhombic counterparts, and a parametric study of its dimensions is conducted. As a result of this research, a new X-band leaky-wave antenna designed in the kagome lattice with an armchair arrangement interface has been developed. This antenna provides two forward and two backward beams, each pair achieving an approximately 50-degree scan within the 8.8 to 11.1 GHz bandwidth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03193v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ACCESS.2025.3567182</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sayyed Ahmad Abtahi, Mohsen Maddahali, Ahmad Bakhtafrouz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detuning-symmetric laser cooling of many mechanical modes with a photothermally modified cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08989v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We simultaneously cool $\gtrsim$100 mechanical modes of a membrane with a photothermally modified optical cavity driven by a single blue-detuned laser. In contrast to radiation pressure and bolometric forces applied directly to the mechanical system, this cooling effect does not depend on the sign of detuning, allowing for single-laser stabilization (i.e., simultaneous positive optical spring and damping) that is especially effective at room temperature and high laser power. We also provide intuition about the competing thermal processes, and propose two simple modifications to the mirror coatings that can strongly enhance this effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08989v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas J. Clark, Jiaxing Ma, Jack C. Sankey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum, spin, and orbital angular momentum of electromagnetic, acoustic, and water waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23235v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Waves of various types carry momentum, which is associated with their propagation direction, i.e., the phase gradient. The circulation of the wave momentum density gives rise to orbital angular momentum (AM). Additionally, for waves described by vector fields, local rotation of the wavefield produces spin AM (or simply, spin). These dynamical wave properties become particularly significant in structured (i.e., inhomogeneous) wavefields. Here we provide an introduction and overview of the momentum and AM properties for a variety of classical waves: electromagnetic, sound, elastic, plasma waves, and water surface waves. A unified field-theory approach, based on Noether's theorem, offers a general framework to describe these diverse physical systems, encompassing longitudinal, transverse, and mixed waves with different dispersion characteristics. We also discuss observable manifestations of the wave momentum and AM providing clear physical interpretations of the derived quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23235v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin Y. Bliokh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybridization of edge modes with substrate phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08082v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Surface plasmons or phonons propagating on a two-dimensional (2D) material can exhibit coupling with resonant excitations in its substrate, and the resulting coupled modes were extensively studied. Similar coupling of edge modes propagating along a boundary of 2D material with the substrate excitations remains unexplored. This paper aims to bridge this gap by investigating the edge-substrate hybrid modes using the exact Wiener-Hopf analytical approach. We analyze dispersions, decay rate, and confinement of such hybrid modes both without magnetic field (plasmon-phonon and phonon-phonon hybrid modes) and in quantizing magnetic field where edge magnetoplasmons hybridize with substrate phonons. The hybrid modes are predicted to occur in THz and far-IR ranges for several combinations of quasi-2D materials (single- and bilayer graphene, quantum wells, thin-film semiconductors) and substrates with polar-phonon resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08082v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azat F. Aminov, Alexey A. Sokolik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interleaved dual-species arrays of single atoms using a passive optical element and one trapping laser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20261v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate trapping of individual rubidium (Rb) and cesium (Cs) atoms in an interleaved array of bright tweezers and dark bottle-beam traps, using a microfabricated optical element illuminated by a single laser beam and a 4F system with spatial filtering. Our approach exploits the opposite-sign dynamic polarizabilities of Rb and Cs, ensuring each species is exclusively trapped in either bright or dark sites. The passive optical mask creates optimal trap depths for both species using three transmittance levels while minimizing the optical phase difference, implemented using a variable-thickness absorbing layer of amorphous germanium. This trapping architecture achieves atom loading rates close to 50% while reducing system complexity compared to conventional methods using active optoelectronic components and/or multiple laser wavelengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20261v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengyu Fang, Jared Miles, Jonathan Goldwin, Martin Lichtman, Matthew Gillette, Michael Bergdolt, Sanket Deshpande, Sam A. Norrell, Preston Huft, Mikhail A. Kats, Mark Saffman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of Berry curvature derivatives in the optical activity of time-invariant crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03684v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum geometry and topology are fundamental concepts of modern condensed matter physics, underpinning phenomena ranging from the quantum Hall effect to protected surface states. The Berry curvature, a central element of this framework, is well established for its key role in electronic transport, whereas its impact on the optical properties of crystals remains comparatively unexplored. Here, we derive a relation between optical activity, defined by the gyration tensor, and the k-derivatives of the Berry curvature at optical resonances in the Brillouin zone. We systematically determine which of these derivatives are non-zero or constrained by symmetry across all time-reversal-invariant crystal classes. In particular, we analytically demonstrate that circular dichroism emerges in chiral crystal classes as a result of a non-zero Berry curvature k-derivative along the optical axis, and we interpret this finding based on the conservation of angular momentum in light-matter interactions. This work establishes a quantum-geometric framework for optical activity in solids and it opens new routes to probe quantum geometry via linear and nonlinear optics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03684v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giancarlo Soavi, Jan Wilhelm</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
