<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 01:45:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Comb-based Colorless Coherent WDM Transmitter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a comb-based WDM transmitter capable of modulating independent signals to comb lines without demultiplexing them and prove its concept and potential scalability in a WDM transmitter consisting of a Kerr microcomb and a silicon I/Q modulator array.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21607v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Che, Brian Stern, Kwangwoong Kim, Cagri Ozdilek, Timofey Shpakovsky, John D. Jost, Maxim Karpov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced bandwidth in radiation sensors operating at the fundamental temperature fluctuation noise limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Temperature-based radiation detectors are an essential tool for long optical wavelengths detection even if they often suffer from important bandwidth limitations. Their responsivity, and hence their noise equivalent power (NEP), typically degrade at frequencies exceeding the cutoff set by their characteristic thermal response time ($\tau_\text{th}$), i.e., at $\omega &gt; \tau_\text{th}^{-1}$. Here we show that this bandwidth limitation can be broken when a radiation sensor operates at its fundamental temperature fluctuation noise limit. The key enabler of this demonstration is a nanomechanical sensor in which frequency stability is limited by fundamental temperature fluctuations over an unprecedentedly large bandwidth of 54 $\text{Hz}$. In this range, the sensor performance remains within a factor 3 from its peak detectivity ($D_T^* = 7.4 \times 10^9~\mathrm{cm \cdot Hz^{1/2} W^{-1}}$) even though the thermal cutoff frequency is 30 times lower (i.e., $1/2\mathrm{\pi} \tau_\text{th} = 1.8~\text{Hz}$). We also derive and validate experimentally closed-form expression predicting maximum bandwidth enhancement in the context of nanomechanical resonators interfaced with a closed-loop frequency tracking scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21678v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Zhang, Zachary Louis-Seize, Maxime Brazeau, Timothy Hodges, Mathis Turgeon-Roy, Raphael St-Gelais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compressive Fourier-Domain Intensity Coupling (C-FOCUS) enables near-millimeter deep imaging in the intact mouse brain in vivo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-photon microscopy is a powerful tool for in vivo imaging, but its imaging depth is typically limited to a few hundred microns due to tissue scattering, even with existing scattering correction techniques. Moreover, most active scattering correction methods are restricted to small regions by the optical memory effect. Here, we introduce compressive Fourier-domain intensity coupling for scattering correction (C-FOCUS), an active scattering correction approach that integrates Fourier-domain intensity modulation with compressive sensing for two-photon microscopy. Using C-FOCUS, we demonstrate high-resolution imaging of YFP-labeled neurons and FITC-labeled blood vessels at depths exceeding 900 um in the intact mouse brain in vivo. Furthermore, we achieve transcranial imaging of YFP-labeled dendritic structures through the intact adult mouse skull. C-FOCUS enables high-contrast fluorescence imaging at depths previously inaccessible using two-photon microscopy with 1035 nm excitation, enhancing fluorescence intensity by over 20-fold compared to uncorrected imaging. C-FOCUS provides a broadly applicable strategy for rapid, deep-tissue optical imaging in vivo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21822v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renzhi He, Yucheng Li, Brianna Urbina, Jiandi Wan, Yi Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization-Independent Zero Directional Scattering Without Geometric Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21834v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As the characteristic feature of generalized Kerker effect in Mie theory, directional scattering elimination has been playing a pivotal role in nanophotonics and many other photonic disciplines, such as singular optics and topological photonics. Generally, zero directional scattering can be obtained only for a specific incident polarization, and to make it fully independent of arbitrary polarizations would require scatterers that exhibit geometric (\textit{e.g.} mirror) symmetries. Here we revisit the generalized Kerker effect and directional scattering elimination from the perspective of not the conventional electromagnetic multipoles, but rather quasi-normal modes supported by non-Hermitian systems. We reveal how to obtain zero directional scattering that is independent of arbitrary incident polarizations, even for scattering structures that do not exhibit the required geometric symmetries. Such geometric symmetry-free and polarization-independent responses are made accessible through a synchronous exploitation of electromagnetic reciprocity and geometric phase. Our discovery can stimulate fundamental explorations and practical applications in not only photonics, but also many other wave physics branches where scattering and geometric phase are pervasive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21834v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunchao Wen, Zhichun Qi, Jianfa Zhang, Shiqiao Qin, Zhihong Zhu, Wei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning assisted speckle and OAM spectrum analysis for enhanced turbulence characterisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atmospheric turbulence presents a major obstacle to the performance of free-space optical (FSO) communication and environmental sensing. While most studies focused on robust detection and recognition of transmitted structured light in turbulent media, a critical, yet often underexplored, avenue involves leveraging the structure of light itself to detect and characterize the medium itself. Here we introduce a deep learning framework that synergistically leverages post-transmission intensity speckle patterns and orbital angular momentum (OAM) spectral data to enhance turbulence state classification, essential for applications such as energy delivery, effective adaptive optics and communications. The proposed architecture builds upon an enhanced InceptionNet backbone optimized for multi-scale feature extraction from complex optical inputs, where we demonstrate that multiple degree of freedom analysis outperforms the conventional single parameter approaches, reaching validation accuracies in excess of 80%. Our approach is benchmarked against standard implementations and found to be superior in handling diverse turbulence scenarios, demonstrating enhanced stability across varying turbulence conditions defined by different Reynolds numbers and Fried parameters. Our method offers a scalable, data-efficient solution for precise atmospheric turbulence detection, with strong potential for deployment in real-world optical sensing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21878v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenjie Jiang, Mingjian Cheng, Lixin Guo, Xiang Yi, Jiangting Li, Junli Wang, Andrew Forbes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-Polarization SHG Interferometry for Imaging Antiparallel Domains and Stacking Angles of 2D Heterocrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical second-harmonic generation (SHG) enables orientational polarimetry for crystallographic analysis and domain imaging of various materials. However, conventional intensity polarimetry, which neglects phase information, fails to resolve antiparallel domains and to describe two-dimensional heterostructures, which represent a new class of van der Waals-bound composite crystals. In this work, we report dual-polarization spectral phase interferometry (DP-SPI) and establish a generalized SHG superposition model that incorporates the observables of DP-SPI. Antiparallel domains of monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) were successfully imaged with distinction, validating the interferometric polarimetry. From DP interferograms of TMD heterobilayers, the orientation of each layer could be determined, enabling layer-resolved probing. By employing the superposition model, we also demonstrate the photonic design and fabrication of ternary TMD heterostructures for circularly polarized SHG. These methods, providing comprehensive SHG measurements and theoretical description, can be extended to heterostructures consisting of more than two constituent layers and are not limited to TMDs or 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21922v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juseung Oh, Wontaek Kim, Gyouil Jeong, Yeri Lee, Jihun Kim, Hyeongjoon Kim, Hyeon Suk Shin, Sunmin Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified Transfer Matrix Method for the Extraction of Material Properties via Terahertz Time-Domain Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Terahertz Time-Domain Spectroscopy is a powerful technique for extracting the low-frequency optical properties of materials. However, the optical constants are difficult to determine directly from the experimental transfer function, such that various numerical approximations must be implemented to describe specific conditions. Here, we introduce a modified Transfer Matrix Method that uses a genetic algorithm for optimization to determine the refractive index of materials in the THz regime. We show that this approach is generally applicable across a wide range of refractive indices, structures, and frequency ranges. Our method is intuitive and yields accurate results compared to leading methods across a wide spectral range (1-15 THz).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21924v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamyar Rashidi, Matthew Y. Sfeir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant electro-optic coefficient in single crystal barium titanate on oxide insulator based Mach-Zehnder interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electro-optic modulators are indispensable components of modern day photonic integrated circuits (PICs). Recently lithium niobate has emerged as a key material to realize large-bandwidth high-speed modulation, but next-generation modulators require high-density integration, low cost, low power and high performance simultaneously, which are difficult to achieve with established integrated lithium niobate photonics platforms due to its limited electro-optic coefficient. Leveraging its exceptional Pockels coefficient, barium titanate (BTO) in the thin film form has emerged as a promising alternative but the electro-optic coefficients reported in thin-film BTO often fall short of bulk values due to challenges in film growth and waveguide fabrication. Here, we report, to the best of our knowledge, the largest Pockels coefficient (r42) of 1268 pm/V in thin film BTO platform, which is very close to the bulk value. We measure it by using an unbalanced Mach-Zehnder interferometer, fabricated by an optimized wet-etching method for realising single-mode waveguides in single-crystal barium titanate-on-insulator grown by pulsed laser deposition. This giant r42 is extracted from a device in which the optical mode is fully confined within a single-crystal BTO waveguide. This approach contrasts with previous designs where the core material - typically silicon or silicon nitride - supports only partial confinement, resulting in an evanescent overlap with a multi-crystalline BTO layer. This highly confined BTO on insulator electro-optic modulation technology may significantly advance the field of ultra-low-power integrated photonic devices and allows for the realization of next-generation efficient and compact photonic circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21927v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Lin Lin, Pragati Aashna, Yu Cao, Aaron Danner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-order virtual gain for optical loss compensation in plasmonic metamaterials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metamaterials exhibit extraordinary properties yet suffer from pronounced wave dissipation, particularly in optical imaging and sensing systems. Recent advances leveraging complex frequency wave excitations with virtual gain effect, synthesized by multi-monochromatic waves, offer promising solutions for optical loss compensation. However, this approach faces limitations in extreme loss scenarios. The complex frequency wave requires sufficient virtual gain, i.e., temporal attenuation, to offset material loss, inevitably triggering rapid signal decay to zero before reaching a quasi-static state. To address this challenge, we introduce synthetic waves of high-order virtual gain to slow down the decay rate while preserving the loss compensation efficiency. We experimentally demonstrate 20-fold noise suppression in plasmonic resonance systems compared to conventional complex frequency excitations. This approach exhibits broad applicability across diverse fields, including imaging, biosensing, and integrated photonic signal processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21976v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fuxin Guan, Zemeng Lin, Sixin Chen, Xinhua Wen, Shuang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum and spin dynamics of photon in linear dielectric medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The momentum of light in dielectric media has been a century-long controversy that continues to attract significant interest. In a linear dielectric medium with refractive index $n$, the momentum is predicted to be smaller by a factor of $n$ according to Max Abraham, and larger by the same factor according to Hermann Minkowski. By studying the coupled dynamics of photons and dipoles in a dielectric medium, we show that the change in momentum of the dipole corresponds to the Abraham momentum. On the other hand, the Minkowski momentum determines the direction of propagation and the precession of the photon spin, which is described by an SO(3) rotation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22270v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam B. Cahaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the terahertz-laser velocity effect during air filamentation via travelling-wave-antenna model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22297v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: During femtosecond laser filamentation in air, the velocity ratio (K) between the terahertz (THz) phase velocity and the laser group velocity plays a crucial role in THz waves generation. However, K is typically assumed to be unity and its impact has been long overlooked due to the more attention paid to the more easily controlled filament length. Here, we investigate the obscured contribution of K to the THz radiation characteristics by using the improved travelling-wave-antenna (TWA) model. It has been found that, under both single- and two-color laser pumping schemes, K significantly determines the far-field spatial distribution of forward or backward THz radiation, as well as a transition from Bessel- to Cherenkov-type THz emission patterns. These results establish the TWA model as a reliable theoretical tool for studying the mechanisms of THz beam shaping via the designed K. Moreover, for cases of K not being controlled, its value can also be inferred by the proposed TWA model, which could be an effective method to confirm whether the laser ionization front is superluminal or subluminal compared with the generated THz waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22297v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiajun Yang, Xiaofeng Li, Linlin Yuan, Li Lao, Jiayu Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Area Fabrication-aware Computational Diffractive Optics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Differentiable optics, as an emerging paradigm that jointly optimizes optics and (optional) image processing algorithms, has made innovative optical designs possible across a broad range of applications. Many of these systems utilize diffractive optical components (DOEs) for holography, PSF engineering, or wavefront shaping. Existing approaches have, however, mostly remained limited to laboratory prototypes, owing to a large quality gap between simulation and manufactured devices. We aim at lifting the fundamental technical barriers to the practical use of learned diffractive optical systems. To this end, we propose a fabrication-aware design pipeline for diffractive optics fabricated by direct-write grayscale lithography followed by nano-imprinting replication, which is directly suited for inexpensive mass production of large area designs. We propose a super-resolved neural lithography model that can accurately predict the 3D geometry generated by the fabrication process. This model can be seamlessly integrated into existing differentiable optics frameworks, enabling fabrication-aware, end-to-end optimization of computational optical systems. To tackle the computational challenges, we also devise tensor-parallel compute framework centered on distributing large-scale FFT computation across many GPUs. As such, we demonstrate large scale diffractive optics designs up to 32.16 mm $\times$ 21.44 mm, simulated on grids of up to 128,640 by 85,760 feature points. We find adequate agreement between simulation and fabricated prototypes for applications such as holography and PSF engineering. We also achieve high image quality from an imaging system comprised only of a single DOE, with images processed only by a Wiener filter utilizing the simulation PSF. We believe our findings lift the fabrication limitations for real-world applications of diffractive optics and differentiable optical design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22313v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaixuan Wei, Hector A. Jimenez-Romero, Hadi Amata, Jipeng Sun, Qiang Fu, Felix Heide, Wolfgang Heidrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-free estimation of the Cram\'er-Rao bound for deep-learning microscopy in complex media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial neural networks have become important tools to harness the complexity of disordered or random photonic systems. Recent applications include the recovery of information from light that has been scrambled during propagation through a complex scattering medium, especially in the challenging case where the deterministic input-output transmission matrix cannot be measured. This naturally raises the question of what the limit is that information theory imposes on this recovery process, and whether neural networks can actually reach this limit. To answer these questions, we introduce a model-free approach to calculate the Cram\'er-Rao bound, which sets the ultimate precision limit at which artificial neural networks can operate. As an example, we apply this approach in a proof-of-principle experiment using laser light propagating through a disordered medium, evidencing that a convolutional network approaches the ultimate precision limit in the challenging task of localizing a reflective target hidden behind a dynamically-fluctuating scattering medium. The model-free method introduced here is generally applicable to benchmark the performance of any deep-learning microscope, to drive algorithmic developments and to push the precision of metrology and imaging techniques to their ultimate limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22330v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41566-025-01657-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Photonics (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Starshynov, Maximilian Weimar, Lukas M. Rachbauer, G\"unther Hackl, Daniele Faccio, Stefan Rotter, Dorian Bouchet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oblique Multiple Scattering by Gyrotropic Cylinders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we develop a full-wave vectorial solution for the 2.5-dimensional (2.5-D), i.e., at oblique plane wave incidence, electromagnetic (EM) multiple scattering (MS) by a collection of gyrotropic cylinders. All cylinders are infinitely long and share a common $z$-axis. However, each cylinder can have a different cross-section with an arbitrary shape and different gyrotropic material properties, i.e., both gyroelectric and gyromagnetic anisotropies are considered. The solution to the problem combines the following three elements: (i) development of a superpotentials-based cylindrical vector wave function (CVWF) expansion to express the EM field in the gyrotropic region; (ii) utilization of the extended boundary condition method (EBCM) to account for non-circular cylinders; (iii) use of Graf's formulas, specifically adapted for the CVWFs, to apply the EBCM at each cylinder. The developed theory allows us to calculate various scattering characteristics, including the scattering and extinction cross-sections and the multipole decomposition, enabling the design and in-depth investigation of various contemporary engineering and physics applications. The method is exhaustively validated with analytical techniques and COMSOL Multiphysics. The computational performance is also discussed. Finally, we study a potential microwave application of the MS by ferrite configurations, and demonstrate broadband forward scattering by introducing oblique incidence and anisotropy. Our method may be used to analyze, design, and optimize contemporary microwave, optical, and photonic applications by beneficially tailoring the scattering properties via oblique incidence and anisotropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22432v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigorios P. Zouros, Konstantinos Delimaris, Carsten Rockstuhl, Georgios D. Kolezas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inline calibration of spatial light modulators in nonlinear microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a method for calibrating the response of a phase-only spatial light modulator in nonlinear microscopy. Our method uses the microscope image itself as calibration measurement and requires no additional hardware components. Our method is adapted to the nonlinear signals encountered in multi-photon excitation fluorescence microscopes, and works well even under low light conditions and with strong photobleaching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22482v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dani\"el W. S. Cox, Harish Sasikumar, Ivo M. Vellekoop</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Graph-Based Laser Path Solver Algorithm for Virtual Reality Laboratory Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22540v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: femtoPro is an interactive virtual reality (VR) laser laboratory balancing the contrasting challenges of accuracy and computational efficiency in optics simulations. It can simulate linear and nonlinear optical phenomena in real time, a task that pushes the boundaries of current consumer hardware. This paper details the concept, implementation, and evaluation of a dynamic graph-based solution tailored to the specific requirements and challenges of the simulation. Resource usage is optimized through a selective updating strategy that identifies and preserves laser paths unchanged between simulation frames, eliminating the need for unnecessary recalculations. Benchmarking of real-world scenarios confirms that our approach delivers a smooth user experience, even on mobile VR platforms with limited computing power. The methodologies, solutions and insights outlined in this paper may be applicable to other interactive, dynamic graph-based real-time simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22540v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas M\"uller, Stefan Mueller, Tobias Brixner, Sebastian von Mammen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Optical Design of the Carbon Investigation(Carbon-I) Imaging Spectrometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The proposed Carbon Investigation (Carbon-I) Imaging Spectrometer is designed to measure variations of greenhouse gases in Earth's atmosphere. The instrument will survey the Earth from its own spacecraft at an altitude of approximately 610 km. It will use a coarse ground sampling distance (GSD) of &lt;400 m in global mode for land and coastal monitoring and finer 35 m GSD in target mode to sample key regions. The identification and quantification of greenhouse gases require continuous spectral sampling over the 2040-2380 nm wavelength range with &lt;1 nm spectral sampling. The proposed design builds upon Jet Propulsion Laboratory's (JPL) experience of spaceflight Dyson imaging spectrometers to achieve spectral sampling of 0.7 nm per pixel. This paper presents the proposed Carbon-I optical design comprised of a freeform three-mirror anastigmat telescope that couples to a F/2.2, highly uniform Dyson-inspired imaging spectrometer. The high uniformity and throughput enables Carbon-I to measure Earth's greenhouse gas concentrations with unprecedented precision and spatial sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22545v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christine L. Bradley, Rami W. Wehbe, Matthew Smith, Sharmila Padmanabhan, Valerie Scott, David R. Thompson, Daniel W. Wilson, Pantazis Mouroulis, Robert O. Green, Christian Frankenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EvidenceMoE: A Physics-Guided Mixture-of-Experts with Evidential Critics for Advancing Fluorescence Light Detection and Ranging in Scattering Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fluorescence LiDAR (FLiDAR), a Light Detection and Ranging (LiDAR) technology employed for distance and depth estimation across medical, automotive, and other fields, encounters significant computational challenges in scattering media. The complex nature of the acquired FLiDAR signal, particularly in such environments, makes isolating photon time-of-flight (related to target depth) and intrinsic fluorescence lifetime exceptionally difficult, thus limiting the effectiveness of current analytical and computational methodologies. To overcome this limitation, we present a Physics-Guided Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) framework tailored for specialized modeling of diverse temporal components. In contrast to the conventional MoE approaches our expert models are informed by underlying physics, such as the radiative transport equation governing photon propagation in scattering media. Central to our approach is EvidenceMoE, which integrates Evidence-Based Dirichlet Critics (EDCs). These critic models assess the reliability of each expert's output by providing per-expert quality scores and corrective feedback. A Decider Network then leverages this information to fuse expert predictions into a robust final estimate adaptively. We validate our method using realistically simulated Fluorescence LiDAR (FLiDAR) data for non-invasive cancer cell depth detection generated from photon transport models in tissue. Our framework demonstrates strong performance, achieving a normalized root mean squared error (NRMSE) of 0.030 for depth estimation and 0.074 for fluorescence lifetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21532v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ismail Erbas, Ferhat Demirkiran, Karthik Swaminathan, Naigang Wang, Navid Ibtehaj Nizam, Stefan T. Radev, Kaoutar El Maghraoui, Xavier Intes, Vikas Pandey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Interference Effect in Strong-field Electronic Coherence Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21788v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have investigated strong-field-induced electronic coherences in argon and molecular nitrogen ions created by high-intensity, few-cycle infrared laser pulses. This is a step toward the long-sought goal of strong-field coherent control in molecular chemistry. We employed high-intensity, few-cycle infrared laser pulses in a pump-probe setup to investigate a recent prediction that electronic coherences in nitrogen molecules change the ion yields vs. pump-probe delay. [Yuen and Lin, Phys. Rev. A 109, L011101 (2024)]. The predicted coherence signals in molecular nitrogen could not be resolved above the optical interference of the pump and probe pulses; a simultaneous measurement clearly resolved the induced cation fine-structure coherence in strong-field-ionized argon. The results of our comparison with simulations suggest that optical interference effects manifest differently in each ionic species and must be carefully accounted for when interpreting experimental data. We found that nonsequential double ionization in the low-intensity region of the focal volume can reduce the visibility of coherence generated by two-pulse sequential ionization, and we quantify the importance of pulse shape and spectral characteristics for isolating the desired coherence signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21788v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleanor Weckwerth, Andrew J. Howard, Chuan Cheng, Ian Gabalski, Aaron M. Ghrist, Salma A. Mohideen, Chii-Dong Lin, Chi-Hong Yuen, Philip H. Bucksbaum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface plasmons in metamaterial cavities: Scattering by obstacles with negative wave speed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22253v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study scattering by metamaterials with negative indices of refraction, which are known to support \emph{surface plasmons} -- long-lived states that are highly localized at the boundary of the cavity. This type of states has found uses in a variety of modern technologies. In this article, we study surface plasmons in the setting of non-trapping cavities; i.e. when all billiard trajectories outside the cavity escape to infinity. We characterize the indices of refraction which support surface plasmons, show that the corresponding resonances lie super-polynomially close to the real axis, describe the localization properties of the corresponding resonant states, and give an asymptotic formula for their number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22253v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Long Fang, Jeffrey Galkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enantiosensitive locking of photoelectron spin and cation orientation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22433v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: When electrons pass through chiral molecules, their transmission is strongly influenced by the orientation of their spin: molecules with opposite handedness preferentially transmit electrons with oppositely aligned spins. The underlying nature of this striking phenomenon, known as chirality-induced spin selectivity (CISS), remains controversial: its observed strength far surpasses predictions based on the typically weak spin-orbit interaction. A significant fraction of CISS phenomena are driven by light, and thus could be controlled at the ultrafast scale, and impact chemical change following photoionization or photoexcitation. To date, most studies of spin-selective enantio-sensitive photodynamics have concentrated on the influence of the magnetic field component of light. Here, we establish dynamical and geometric mechanisms of spin-selective photo-induced dynamics that arise purely from electric dipole interactions. Using one-photon ionization as an example, we report a new effect: enantio-sensitive locking of molecular cation orientation to the spins of the photoelectron and the hole in the parent molecule. One-photon ionization is an ubiquitous process, where CISS has already been found in oriented samples. Remarkably, the new effect that we report here emerges upon photoionization of randomly oriented chiral molecules, establishing CISS in amorphous chiral media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22433v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Caesar M. Flores, Stefanos Carlstr\"om, Serguei Patchkovskii, Andres F. Ordonez, Olga Smirnova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Coherent Ferrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22559v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Excitation of ordered phases produces quasiparticles and collective modes, as exemplified by magnons that emerge from magnetic order, with applications in information transmission and quantum interconnects. Extending this paradigm to ferroelectric materials suggests the existence of ferrons, i.e. fundamental quanta of the collective excitation of ferroelectric order5 developed theoretically by Bauer and coworkers. While coherent magnons are observed in a broad range of experiments, coherent ferrons have eluded experimental detection. This discrepancy is particularly intriguing given that electric dipole interactions (FE) are inherently stronger than their magnetic counterparts. Here, we report the generation and transport of coherent ferrons in the van der Waals (vdW) ferroelectric material NbOI2. By launching collective oscillations of the ferroelectric dipoles using a short laser pulse, we identify coherent ferrons from intense and narrow-band terahertz (THz) emission and observe their propagations along the polar direction at extremely hypersonic velocities exceeding 10^5 m/s. The THz emission is a second-order nonlinear process that requires ferroelectric order, as is confirmed in the structurally related ferroelectric WO2Br2 and non-ferroelectric TaOBr2. The discovery of coherent ferrons paves the way for numerous applications, including narrow-band THz emission, ferronic information processing, and quantum interconnects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22559v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeongheon Choe, Taketo Handa, Chun-Ying Huang, Andr\'e Koch Liston, Jordan Cox, Jonathan Stensberg, Yongseok Hong, Daniel G. Chica, Ding Xu, Fuyang Tay, Vinicius da Silveira Lanza Avelar, Eric A. Arsenault, James McIver, Dmitri N. Basov, Milan Delor, Xavier Roy, X. -Y. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High efficiency second harmonic generation in transverse orientation patterned gallium phosphide waveguides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15754v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Achieving high conversion efficiencies in second-order nonlinear optical processes is a key challenge in integrated photonics for both classical and quantum applications. This paper presents the first demonstration of Transverse Orientation-Patterned gallium phosphide (TOP-GaP) waveguides showing high-efficiency second harmonic generation. In such devices, first order modal phase matching is unlocked and optimized through the inversion of the nonlinear susceptibility along the vertical direction. We discuss here the theory behind modal phase matching in TOP structures, describe the fabrication process, and present linear and nonlinear characterizations of the TOP-GaP waveguides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15754v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Lemoine, Brieg Le Corre, Lise Morice, Abdelmouna\"im Harouri, Luc Le Gratiet, Gr\'egoire Beaudoin, Julie Le Pouliquen, Karine Tavernier, Arnaud Grisard, Sylvain Combri\'e, Bruno G\'erard, Charles Cornet, Yannick Dumeige, Konstantinos Pantzas, Isabelle Sagnes, Yoan L\'eger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical neuromorphic computing via temporal up-sampling and trainable encoding on a telecom device platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03429v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mapping input signals to a high-dimensional space is a critical concept in various neuromorphic computing paradigms, including models such as Reservoir Computing (RC) and Extreme Learning Machines (ELM). We propose using commercially available telecom devices and technologies developed for high-speed optical data transmission to implement these models through nonlinear mapping of optical signals into a high-dimensional space where linear processing can be applied. We manipulate the output feature dimension by applying temporal up-sampling (at the speed of commercially available telecom devices) of input signals and a well-established wave-division-multiplexing (WDM). Our up-sampling approach utilizes a trainable encoding mask, where each input symbol is replaced with a structured sequence of masked symbols, effectively increasing the representational capacity of the feature space. This gives remarkable flexibility in the dynamical phase masking of the input signal. We demonstrate this approach in the context of RC and ELM, employing readily available photonic devices, including a semiconductor optical amplifier and nonlinear Mach-Zender interferometer (MZI). We investigate how nonlinear mapping provided by these devices can be characterized in terms of the increased controlled separability and predictability of the output state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03429v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1515/nanoph-2024-0614</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Egor Manuylovich, Dmitrii Stoliarov, David Saad, Sergei K. Turitsyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised neural-implicit laser absorption tomography for quantitative imaging of unsteady flames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08337v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel neural-implicit approach to laser absorption tomography (LAT) with an experimental demonstration. A coordinate neural network is used to represent thermochemical state variables as continuous functions of space and time. Unlike most existing neural methods for LAT, which rely on prior simulations and supervised training, our approach is based solely on LAT measurements, utilizing a differentiable observation operator with line parameters provided in a standard spectroscopy database format. Although reconstructing scalar fields from multi-beam absorbance data is an inherently ill-posed, nonlinear inverse problem, our continuous space-time parameterization supports physics-inspired regularization strategies and enables data assimilation. Synthetic and experimental tests are conducted to validate the method, demonstrating robust performance and reproducibility. We show that our neural-implicit approach to LAT can capture the dominant spatial modes of an unsteady flame from very sparse measurement data, indicating its potential to reveal combustion instabilities in measurement domains with minimal optical access.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08337v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph P. Molnar, Jiangnan Xia, Rui Zhang, Samuel J. Grauer, Chang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calibration features of a polarimetric backscattering setup with a beamsplitter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10763v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We address the problem of calibrating a polarimetric backscattering setup that includes a beamsplitter, taking its optical properties into account. Using Fisher information, we justify a specific calibration configuration involving reference optical elements for the maximum likelihood method and demonstrate its effectiveness through Monte Carlo simulations. This approach leads to higher precision, as the described set of measurements allows the beamsplitter to be treated as an integral part of the setup, without requiring separate processing or reconfiguration of the setup for the beamsplitter calibration. Furthermore, we emphasize the significance of considering the beamsplitter's optical properties by proposing a test to estimate the error that arises from neglecting these properties during the calibration procedure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10763v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/OE.562403</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Opt. Express 33 (2025) 23452-23464</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. Stefanov, B. P. Singh, A. Stefanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological linear and nonlinear gap modes in defected dimer lattice with fourth-order diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14639v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the optical properties of linear and nonlinear topological in-phase, out-of-phase, and edge modes in a defected dimer lattice with fourth-order diffraction, encompassing their bifurcation characteristics, localized field distributions, and stability properties. Both focusing and defocusing nonlinearities are considered. Within the nontrivial regime, in-phase, out-of-phase, and edge modes can emerge within the gap. Numerical results reveal that three types of topological gap solitons bifurcate from their corresponding linear localized modes. The dimerization parameter can be tuned to drive the system from a trivial to a nontrivial configuration. We observe that as the strength of the fourth-order diffraction increases, the size of the spectral gap also enlarges, with this parameter effectively broadening the stability window for solitons. Our findings offer novel insights into the properties of both linear and nonlinear modes in topologically defected structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14639v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.chaos.2025.116435</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chaos, Solitons and Fractals 197 (2025) 116435</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyang Wang, Qidong Fu, Changming Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TorchGDM: A GPU-Accelerated Python Toolkit for Multi-Scale Electromagnetic Scattering with Automatic Differentiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09545v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present "torchGDM", a numerical framework for nano-optical simulations based on the Green's Dyadic Method (GDM). This toolkit combines a hybrid approach, allowing for both fully discretized nano-structures and structures approximated by sets of effective electric and magnetic dipoles. It supports simulations in three dimensions and for infinitely long, two-dimensional structures. This capability is particularly suited for multi-scale modeling, enabling accurate near-field calculations within or around a discretized structure embedded in a complex environment of scatterers represented by effective models. Importantly, torchGDM is entirely implemented in PyTorch, a well-optimized and GPU-enabled automatic differentiation framework. This allows for the efficient calculation of exact derivatives of any simulated observable with respect to various inputs, including positions, wavelengths or permittivity, but also intermediate parameters like Green's tensors. We anticipate that this toolkit will be valuable for applications merging nano-photonics and machine learning, as well as for solving nano-photonic optimization and inverse problems, such as the global design and characterization of metasurfaces, where optical interactions between structures are critical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09545v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sofia Ponomareva, Adelin Patoux, Cl\'ement Majorel, Antoine Az\'ema, Aur\'elien Cuche, Christian Girard, Arnaud Arbouet, Peter R. Wiecha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roadmap for Quantum Nanophotonics with Free Electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14678v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Over the past century, continuous advancements in electron microscopy have enabled the synthesis, control, and characterization of high-quality free-electron beams. These probes carry an evanescent electromagnetic field that can drive localized excitations and provide high-resolution information on material structures and their optical responses, currently reaching the sub-{\aa}ngstr\"om and few-meV regime. Moreover, combining free electrons with pulsed light sources in ultrafast electron microscopy adds temporal resolution in the sub-femtosecond range while offering enhanced control of the electron wave function. Beyond their exceptional capabilities for time-resolved spectromicroscopy, free electrons are emerging as powerful tools in quantum nanophotonics, on par with photons in their ability to carry and transfer quantum information, create entanglement within and with a specimen, and reveal previously inaccessible details on nanoscale quantum phenomena. This Roadmap outlines the current state of this rapidly evolving field, highlights key challenges and opportunities, and discusses future directions through a collection of topical sections prepared by leading experts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14678v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Javier Garc\'ia de Abajo, Albert Polman, Cruz I. Velasco, Mathieu Kociak, Luiz H. G. Tizei, Odile St\'ephan, Sophie Meuret, Takumi Sannomiya, Keiichirou Akiba, Yves Auad, Armin Feist, Claus Ropers, Peter Baum, John H. Gaida, Murat Sivis, Hugo Louren\c{c}o-Martins, Luca Serafini, Johan Verbeeck, Beatrice Matilde Ferrari, Cameron J. R. Duncan, Maria Giulia Bravi, Irene Ostroman, Giovanni Maria Vanacore, Andrea Kone\v{c}n\'a, Nahid Talebi, Ethan Nussinson, Ron Ruimy, Yuval Adiv, Arthur Niedermayr, Ido Kaminer, Valerio Di Giulio, Ofer Kfir, Zhexin Zhao, Roy Shiloh, Yuya Morimoto, Martin Koz\'ak, Peter Hommelhoff, Francesco Barantani, Fabrizio Carbone, Fatemeh Chahshouri, Wiebke Albrecht, Sergio Rey, Toon Coenen, Erik Kieft, Hoelen L. Lalandec Robert, Frank de Jong, Magdalena Sol\`a-Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Efficiency Plasma-Based Compressor for Ultrafast Soft X-ray Free-Electron Lasers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16768v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The generation of intense, femtosecond-scale X-ray pulses is crucial for probing matter under extreme temporal and field conditions. Current chirped-pulse amplification (CPA) techniques in free-electron lasers (FELs), however, face efficiency limitations in the soft X-ray regime due to the inherent constraints of conventional optical compressors. To address this challenge, we propose a high-efficiency plasma-based compressor utilizing highly ionized noble gas plasma. Exploiting strong refractive index dispersion near ionic resonances, this scheme achieves over 70% transmission efficiency around 5.2 nm, and is extendable to other highly charged ions for operation across the soft X-ray to vacuum ultraviolet range. Simulations demonstrate that a 25 fs FEL pulse can be compressed to 1.4 fs with peak power boosted to over 100 GW, while maintaining high energy throughput. This approach overcomes the long-standing efficiency bottleneck of soft X-ray CPA and opens a scalable path toward compact, high-brightness attosecond FEL sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16768v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingchang Wang, Li Zeng, Bingbing Zhang, Qinghao Zhu, Xiaozhe Shen, Xiaofan Wang, Qinming Li, Weiqing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
