<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Light's symmetry, asymmetry, and their role in nonlinear optics and ultrafast phenomena</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The analysis of symmetries is extremely useful across science. In Physics, symmetries are used to derive conservation laws and selection rules for transitions in interacting systems. In the early days of nonlinear optics (NLO), symmetries were used to formulate a set of rules for photonic processes according to the medium's symmetries that are reflected in the NLO coefficient tensor. While this approach was believed to be complete and closed, the field has recently reignited as multi-color ultrashort laser pulses with tailored polarization and spatiotemporal structures become standard in NLO. A more complete theory has been recently emerging, which aims to incorporate all possible dynamical degrees of freedom of light: spin and orbital angular momentum, spatial structure, time-dependent polarizations, temporal envelopes, etc., in addition to the symmetries of the medium. This theoretical development is also accompanied by experimental advances that rely on tailored light beams that can now be generated with ever-increasing complexity, including topologies in real and a variety of synthetic dimensions, carrying poly-chromatic carrier waves, time-dependent varying angular momenta, local-chirality, and more. The nonlinear interactions between light fields with unique symmetries (or asymmetries) and matter is especially appealing, since that holds the key for developing new ultrafast spectroscopies with sub-femtosecond resolution, for exerting exact control over matter, and improving our fundamental understanding of how light and matter interact. We review these recent advances in this expanding field, focusing on the theory, its implications, and seminal experiments. We aim to establish a comprehensive database of symmetries and selection rules governing NLO light-matter interactions within the emerging new formalism, and invite the scientific community to contribute to this effort.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19433v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ofer Neufeld, Matan Even Tzur, Ofer Kfir, Avner Fleischer, Oren Cohen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Solution of the Two-Reflector Optical System Meeting Herschel's Condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exact solution of stigmatic two-reflector optical system in presence of Herschel's condition is demonstrated. Details of how the solution is calculated are reported. Ray tracing verification on different optical systems validates the obtained results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19522v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Orlando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design of Energy-Efficient Cross-coupled Differential Photonic-SRAM (pSRAM) Bitcell for High-Speed On-Chip Photonic Memory and Compute Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19544v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a novel differential photonic static random access memory (pSRAM) bitcell design using fabrication-friendly photonic components. The proposed pSRAM overcomes the key limitations of traditional electrical SRAMs, which struggle with speed and power efficiency due to increasing bitline/wordline capacitance and interconnect resistance associated with long electrical wires as technology scales. By utilizing cross-coupled micro-ring resonators and differential photodiode structures, along with optical waveguides instead of traditional wordlines and bitlines, our pSRAM exhibits high-speed, and energy-efficient performance. The pSRAM bitcell demonstrates a read/write speed of 40 GHz, with a switching (static) energy consumption of approximately 0.6 pJ (0.03 pJ) per bit and a footprint of 330x290 um^2 using the GlobalFoundries 45SPCLO process node. These bitcells can be arranged into a 2D memory array, enabling large-scale, on-chip photonic memory subsystems ideal for high-speed memory, data processing and computing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19544v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Abdullah-Al Kaiser, Sugeet Sunder, Clynn Mathew, Michal Rakowski, Ajey P. Jacob, Akhilesh R. Jaiswal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light switching based on half space invisible states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate a method for controlling light scattering based on the excitation of non-radiating states in a half-space through a tailored choice of incident radiation. For a fixed particle geometry, we demonstrate that small variations in the refractive index can lead to a significant redistribution of scattered light between two half spaces while keeping the incident illumination unchanged. This effect is particularly relevant for dynamic beam shaping and optical signal routing at the microscale. Our study focuses on spherical semiconductor particles of varying radii illuminated in the visible range, with refractive index modulation achieved via charge carrier injection. Using AlGaAs and InP as model materials, we analyze the feasibility of achieving efficient directional control of scattering. These results provide insight into all-optical manipulation of light using tunable semiconductor structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19560v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. R. Bekirov, A. F. Uspenskiy, V. A. Sitnyansky, B. S. Lukyanchuk, A. A. Fedyanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Valley optoelectronics based on meta-waveguide photodetectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In transition metal dichalcogenides, the valley degree of freedom directly couples valley-polarised excitons - excited by circularly polarised light - to valley-dependent chiral photons, enabling ultrafast light-driven valleytronics. However, achieving fully integrated valley optoelectronics - incorporating on-chip generation, selective routing, and electrical readout of valley-dependent chiral photons - remains an unresolved challenge. We present a valley-driven hybrid nanophotonic-optoelectronic circuit that integrates chirality-selective meta-waveguide photodetectors with transition metal dichalcogenides. At room temperature, our purposely designed meta-waveguide device generates near-unity valley-dependent chiral photons in the second harmonic generation from an encapsulated tungsten disulfide monolayer and selectively couples them to unidirectional waveguide modes, achieving an exceptional polarisation selectivity of 0.97. These valley-dependent waveguide modes were subsequently detected by atomically thin few-layer tungsten diselenide photodetectors, exclusively responsive to the above-bandgap upconverted photons, thereby enabling all-on-chip processing of valley-multiplexed images. Our demonstration bridges a critical gap in lightwave valleytronics, paving the way for compact, scalable valley information processing and fostering the development of light-based valleytronic quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19565v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi Li, Kaijian Xing, Wenhao Zhai, Luca Sortino, Andreas Tittl, Igor Aharonovich, Michael S. Fuhrer, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Qingdong Ou, Zhaogang Dong, Stefan A. Maier, Haoran Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast all-optical switching in nonlinear 3R-MoS$_2$ van der Waals metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19590v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Second-order nonlinear optical processes are fundamental to photonics, spectroscopy, and information technologies, with material platforms playing a pivotal role in advancing these applications. Here, we demonstrate the exceptional nonlinear optical properties of the van der Waals crystal 3R-MoS$_2$, a rhombohedral polymorph exhibiting high second-order optical susceptibility ($\chi^{(2)}$) and remarkable second-harmonic generation (SHG) capabilities. By designing high quality factor resonances in 3R-MoS$_2$ metasurfaces supporting quasi-bound states in the continuum (qBIC), we first demonstrate SHG efficiency enhancement exceeding 10$^2$. Additionally, by using degenerate pump-probe spectroscopy, we harness the C$_{3v}$ system's symmetry to realize ultrafast SHG polarization switching with near-unity modulation depth. The operation speeds are limited only by the excitation pulse duration, allowing its characterization via the nonlinear autocorrelation function. These findings establish 3R-MoS$_2$ as a transformative platform for nanoscale nonlinear optics, offering large conversion efficiencies and ultrafast response times for advanced pulse measurement devices, integrated photonics, and quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19590v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Levin Seidt, Thomas Weber, Albert A. Seredin, Thomas Possmayer, Roman Savelev, Mihail A. Petrov, Stefan A. Maier, Andreas Tittl, Leonardo de S. Menezes, Luca Sortino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>femtoPro: Real-time linear and nonlinear optics simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Real-time optics and spectroscopy simulations ideally provide results at update rates of ~120 Hz or more without any noticeable delay between changing input parameters and the calculated results. Such calculations require models of sufficient speed yet adequate level of detail in the physical approximations to contain the essential features of the simulated phenomena. We discuss a representation of femtosecond laser pulses in which fast phase oscillations due to carrier frequency and due to spatial propagation are separated out and amplitude modulations due to Gaussian beam propagation are also separated and treated explicitly. We derive simplified expressions for the spatial modulations of laser beams. Further, we derive visibility and beam-overlap factors describing multi-pulse interference. We obtain simplified expressions for radius and curvature of nonlinear signal beams in the case of fundamental beams with different convergence, different beam waist, and imperfect mutual overlap. The described model is implemented in the virtual-reality laser laboratory simulation "femtoPro," but the derived equations can be used independently for other applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19627v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Brixner, Stefan Mueller, Andreas M\"uller, Sebastian von Mammen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Electro-Optic Dual Comb Detection of Ultrasound Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-resolution ultrasound based imaging techniques like photoacoustic (PA) imaging that require fast detection of acoustic waves, are often coupled with an opto-mechanical sensor like a Fabry-Perot cavity (FPC) for enhanced sensitivity at high frequency. Due to the inherent inhomogeneity of the FPC thickness, the resonance of the cavity can exhibit a spatial distribution, requiring dynamic adjustment of the interrogation wavelength when raster-scanning the sensor with a probe beam. To avoid this, we propose in this work the use of an electro-optically modulated dual-comb light source for rapid acoustic wave sensing within a specified bandwidth. Utilizing a dual-comb vibrometry approach, we demonstrated a proof-of-principle of the technique, with real-time detection of 10 MHz acoustic waves simultaneously with three different teeth (separated by 10 GHz) of the dual-frequency comb, achieving a 20 ns temporal resolution. We also investigated the system's sensitivity limit in terms of the strength of the detected acoustic waves, opening new possibilities for ultrafast PA imaging modalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19659v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debanuj Chatterjee, Louis Etien, Simon Boivinet, Herv\'e Rigneault, Thomas Chaigne, Arnaud Mussot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Programmable on-chip nonlinear photonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonlinear photonics uses coherent interactions between optical waves to engineer functionality that is not possible with purely linear optics. Traditionally, the function of a nonlinear-optical device is determined during design and fixed during fabrication. In this paper, we present a photonic device with highly programmable nonlinear functionality: an optical slab waveguide with an arbitrarily reconfigurable two-dimensional distribution of $\chi^{(2)}$ nonlinearity. The nonlinearity is realized using electric-field-induced $\chi^{(2)}$ in a $\chi^{(3)}$ material. The programmability is engineered by massively parallel control of the electric-field distribution within the device using a photoconductive layer and optical programming with a spatial light pattern. To showcase the versatility of our device, we demonstrated spectral, spatial, and spatio-spectral engineering of second-harmonic generation by tailoring arbitrary quasi-phase-matching (QPM) grating structures in two dimensions. Second-harmonic light was generated with programmable spectra, enabled by real-time in situ inverse design of QPM gratings. Flexible spatial control was also achieved, including the generation of complex waveforms such as Airy beams and the simultaneous engineering of spectral and spatial features. This allowed us to create distinct spatial light profiles across multiple wavelengths. The programmability also allowed us to demonstrate in situ, real-time compensation of fluctuations in pump laser wavelength. Our work shows that we can transcend the conventional one-device--one-function paradigm, expanding the potential applications of nonlinear optics in situations where fast device reconfigurability is not merely practically convenient but essential -- such as in programmable optical quantum gates and quantum light sources, all-optical signal processing, optical computation, and structured light for sensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19861v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryotatsu Yanagimoto, Benjamin A. Ash, Mandar M. Sohoni, Martin M. Stein, Yiqi Zhao, Federico Presutti, Marc Jankowski, Logan G. Wright, Tatsuhiro Onodera, Peter L. McMahon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time all-optical signal equalisation with silicon photonic recurrent neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Communication through optical fibres experiences limitations due to chromatic dispersion and nonlinear Kerr effects that degrade the signal. Mitigating these impairments is typically done using complex digital signal processing algorithms. However, these equalisation methods require significant power consumption and introduce high latencies. Photonic reservoir computing (a subfield of neural networks) offers an alternative solution, processing signals in the analog optical Domain. In this work, we present to our knowledge the very first experimental demonstration of real-time online equalisation of fibre distortions using a silicon photonics chip that combines the recurrent reservoir and the programmable readout layer. We successfully equalize a 28 Gbps on-off keying signal across varying power levels and fibre lengths, even in the highly nonlinear regime. We obtain bit error rates orders of magnitude below previously reported optical equalisation methods, reaching as low as 4e-7 , far below the generic forward error correction limit of 5.8e-5 used in commercial Ethernet interfaces. Also, simulations show that simply by removing delay lines, the system becomes compatible with line rates of 896 Gpbs. Using wavelength multiplexing, this can result in a throughput in excess of 89.6 Tbps. Finally, incorporating non-volatile phase shifters, the power consumption can be less than 6 fJ/bit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19911v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruben Van Assche, Sarah Masaad, Emmanuel Gooskens, Stijn Sackesyn, Joris Van Kerrebrouck, Xin Yin, Peter Bienstman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light trajectories and wave dynamics in optical wormholes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the optical properties of a wormhole geometry characterized by a constant negative Gaussian curvature. This distinctive optical structure is modeled using the optical metric of the static BTZ black hole, corresponding to the hyperbolic wormhole framework. Within this model, we derive the arbitrary geodesics and the associated effective potential. Our analysis reveals that the effective potential becomes increasingly narrow as the curvature radius of the optical wormhole decreases, with all possible trajectories converging at the optical origin \(\rho = 0\). We further analyze the wave modes governing light propagation on this curved surface, demonstrating that the effective potential is purely repulsive in both the small and large \(\rho\) limits. While the potential remains finite in both regimes, its behavior differs markedly. Near the optical origin, the magnetic quantum number (\(m\)) exerts a significant influence on the effective repulsive potential, particularly for large values of \(m\), where the potential resembles a typical barrier. However, this effect diminishes with increasing optical distance. Using this framework, we compute the reflection and transmission coefficients for \(m \neq 0\). Our findings indicate that the optical properties of the background are predominantly governed by the curvature radius of the optical wormhole, highlighting its critical role in shaping light propagation in such geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18967v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Semra Gurtas Dogan, Abdullah Guvendi, Omar Mustafa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Silicon-Integrated Next-Generation Plasmonic Devices for Energy-Efficient Semiconductor Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19235v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Silicon-based integrated photonics has demonstrated significant advances in miniaturization and performance, yet critical challenges remain in achieving efficient on-chip communication at high bandwidths. Plasmonic devices on silicon and silicon-on-insulator substrates offer a promising solution, enabling subwavelength light confinement and enhanced light-matter interactions through hybrid modes. However, integrating traditional plasmonic materials like gold and silver into silicon-based platforms presents significant challenges, particularly due to their incompatibility with standard silicon processing techniques and their increased optical losses at longer wavelengths, which can hinder performance in near-infrared applications. Plasmonic devices, leveraging advances in device architectures, have the potential to close these performance gaps and enable the next generation of high-speed, on-chip data communication. This review explores recent progress in silicon-integrated hybrid-mode plasmonic devices, highlighting the potential of transparent conductive oxides like indium tin oxide for low-loss and tunable operation. Key device topologies including coupled hybrid plasmonic waveguides and dielectric-based heterostructures are examined, along with fabrication techniques and practical considerations. By critically comparing various plasmonic approaches and identifying their respective advantages and limitations, a path toward realizing the full potential of plasmonics in shaping the future of high-performance, silicon-based integrated photonics is charted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19235v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nasir Alfaraj, Amr S. Helmy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamentals of heterodyne wave mixing spectroscopy: a tutorial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19750v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This tutorial provides a joint theoretical and experimental overview of heterodyne wave mixing spectroscopy, focusing mainly on four-wave mixing (FWM). This powerful and versatile time-resolved nonlinear optical spectroscopy technique enables the investigation of individual localized single photon emitters, as well as microscopy of extended samples, e.g., two-dimensional transition metal dichalcogenides. Starting with the fundamental theory of optically driven two-level systems, we motivate the utility of wave mixing spectroscopy via a discussion on homogeneous and inhomogeneous linewidths which can be independently measured using FWM. We then provide a detailed overview of the heterodyne wave mixing setup operated by one of the authors (JK) at Institut N\'eel in Grenoble, supported by theoretical modeling of the signal detection process. Throughout the paper we elaborate on important benefits of heterodyne wave mixing spectroscopy, e.g., background-free detection, measurement of the full signal field including amplitude and phase, and investigation of coupling mechanisms in few-level systems. Within the context of the latter point we discuss the significance of two-dimensional (2D) FWM spectra. This tutorial is dedicated to students, young researchers, as well as experts in the field of nonlinear spectroscopy in general and FWM in particular. It explains the fundamental concepts and building blocks required to operate a heterodyne wave mixing experiment both from the experimental and theoretical side. This joint approach is helpful for theoreticians who want to accurately and quantitatively model wave mixing signals, as well as for experimentalists who aim to interpret their recorded data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19750v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Groll, Thilo Hahn, Pawe{\l} Machnikowski, Tilmann Kuhn, Jacek Kasprzak, Daniel Wigger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact and stable source of polarization-entangled photon-pairs based on a folded linear displacement interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The realization of quantum networks requires the development of robust low size, weight and power (SWaP) systems suitable for operation under harsh environments in remote and mobile nodes such as satellites. We present a source of polarization-entangled photon-pairs in a folded linear displacement interferometer based on spontaneous parametric down conversion using a Type-0 periodically poled potassium titanyl phosphate crystal. Featuring a compact and stable double-pass geometry using a corner-cube retroreflector, the source has a detected pair rate of 2.5 M pairs/s/mW with a Bell state fidelity of 94.1% +/- 2.1%. The quality and demonstrated performance of the source are suitable for deployment in entanglement-based quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19838v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah. E. McCarthy, Ali Anwar, Daniel K. L. Oi, Loyd J. McKnight</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barium Titanate and Lithium Niobate Permittivity and Pockels Coefficients from MHz to Sub-THz Frequencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03443v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Pockels effect is essential for controlling optical signals at the highest speeds, particularly for electro-optic modulators in photonic integrated circuits. Lithium niobate (LN) and barium titanate (BTO) are two excellent Pockels materials to this end. Here, we measure the Pockels coefficients and permittivity in LN and BTO over a continuous frequency range from 100 MHz to 330 GHz. These properties are constant across this frequency range in LN but have a significant frequency dependence in BTO. Still, our measurements show that BTO has remarkably large electro-optic properties compared to LN. Furthermore, we show how BTO devices can be designed with a flat electro-optic frequency response despite the Pockels coefficient dispersion. Finally, we expound our method for broadband characterization of these vital electro-optic properties, utilizing specialized integrated electro-optic phase shifters. Altogether, this work empowers the design of high-speed BTO devices and the development of new electro-optic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03443v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41563-025-02158-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Chelladurai, Manuel Kohli, Joel Winiger, David Moor, Andreas Messner, Yuriy Fedoryshyn, Mohammed Eleraky, Yuqi Liu, Hua Wang, Juerg Leuthold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced TM-Mode 3D Coupled Wave Theory for Photonic Crystal Surface-Emitting Terahertz Quantum Cascade Lasers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10331v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we propose and develop an enhanced three-dimensional coupled wave theory (3D CWT) to investigate the optical field behavior in photonic crystal surface-emitting terahertz quantum cascade lasers (THz-QCLs). By incorporating an effective permittivity enhancement (EP) model and a self-consistent iteration (SCI) method, we successfully address the numerical dispersion issues encountered in analytical methods when dealing with metallic waveguide structures. The results demonstrate that the EP and SCI-enhanced 3D TM mode CWT achieves computational accuracy comparable to traditional numerical simulation methods such as finite-difference time-domain (FDTD), while significantly reducing the required computational resources, including time and memory, to just tens of minutes. Moreover, this method provides a clear physical insight, revealing the reasons behind the current low extraction efficiency in surface-emitting THz-QCLs. Our study showcases the potential of the EP and SCI-enhanced 3D CWT as a powerful simulation tool in the research of photonic crystal surface-emitting lasers, offering a new theoretical foundation and optimization direction for future laser designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10331v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingxi Chen, Tsung-Tse Lin, Li Wang, Hideki Hirayama, Chiko Otani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Radiation Force and Torque on Moving Nanostructures with Anisotropic Optical Response</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17791v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nanoscale objects moving relative to a thermal radiation bath experience a drag force due to the imbalance in their interaction with the blue- and redshifted components of the electromagnetic field. Here, we show that, in addition to this drag force, moving nanostructures with an anisotropic optical response experience a lateral force and a torque that substantially modify their trajectory. These phenomena emerge from the additional coupling between the electromagnetic field components polarized parallel and perpendicular to the trajectory, enabled by the anisotropic response of the nanostructure. This work unveils the intricate dynamics of anisotropic nanostructures moving in a thermal radiation bath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17791v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.113604</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 134, 113604 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Juan R. Deop-Ruano, Alejandro Manjavacas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A GHz fiber comb on silica</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16249v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a 1 GHz Yb-fiber laser frequency comb built on silica substrates, utilizing "optical cubes" to house all optical components, ensuring long-term stability and practical operation. Both the femtosecond laser and f-to-2f interferometer are constructed on silica bricks, with a compact footprint of 290 mm $\times$ 250 mm, and a total weight of 1.8 kg. This system provides a stable repetition rate, offset frequency, and a supercontinuum spanning 460-1560 nm without requiring amplification. The carrier-envelop offset frequency exhibits exceptional stability, with a fractional frequency instability of $3.07\times 10^{-18}$ at a 1 second averaging time, improving to $2.12\times 10^{-20}$ at a 10,000 second, maintaining uninterrupted operation for over 60 hours. This work demonstrates a high-performance GHz fiber-based frequency comb, paving the way for applications beyond laboratory environments, including dual-comb spectroscopy, astronomical spectrograph calibration, and portable optical clocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16249v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruoao Yang, Xingang Jin, Ya Wang, Minghe Zhao, Zhendong Chen, Xinpeng Lin, Fei Meng, Duo Pan, Qian Li, Jingbiao Chen, Aimin Wang, Zhigang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal emission of hydrogenated amorphous silicon microspheres in the mid-infrared</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14229v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hydrogenated amorphous silicon microspheres feature a pronounced phononic peak around 2000 cm-1 when they are thermally excited by means of a blue laser. This phononic signature corresponds to vibrational modes of silicon-hydrogen bonds and its emitted light can be coupled to Mie modes defined by the spherical cavity. The signal is apparently quite stable at moderate excitation intensities although there appeared some signs pointing to hydrides bonds reconfiguration and even hydrogen emission. Above a certain excitation threshold, a phase change from amorphous to poly-crystalline silicon occurs that preserves the good structural quality of the microspheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14229v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Fenollosa, Fernando Ramiro-Manzano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Frequency Detection in a Subsystem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10359v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we systematically explore the non-Hermitian skin effect (NHSE) and its associated complex-frequency detection in the context of a frequency-dependent non-Hermitian Hamiltonian. This Hamiltonian arises from the self-energy correction of the subsystem and can be calculated exactly within our theoretical model, without the need for any approximations. Additionally, complex frequency detection, which encompasses complex frequency excitation, synthesis, and fingerprint, enables us to detect the physical responses induced by the complex driving frequencies. Our calculations reveal that both complex frequency excitation and synthesis are incompatible with the non-Hermitian approximation and are unable to characterize the presence or abscence of the NHSE. In contrast, the complex-frequency fingerprint successfully detects the novel responses induced by the NHSE through the introduction of a double-frequency Green's function. Our work provides a platform for studying non-Hermitian physics and their novel response in quantum systems rigorously without relying on any approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10359v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juntao Huang, Jiangping Hu, Zhesen Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twin-Polaritons: Classical versus Quantum Features in Polaritonic Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11968v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding whether a polaritonic phenomenon is inherently quantum or classical is essential for developing accurate models and optimizing experimental designs. We investigate this question in the context of polaritonic rotational-vibrational spectra and report a new feature, the twin-polariton, an additional splitting beyond the usual primary resonant polariton splitting that arises from light-matter entanglement. Through ab-initio calculations of HCl molecules and a corresponding model system coupled to a cavity, we demonstrate that the twin-polariton persists in the many-molecule case and follows the same linear dependence on coupling strength as the primary resonant polariton splitting. This finding reveals a novel mechanism to tune a quantum feature using a classical one, offering new insights into the fundamental nature of polaritonic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11968v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iren Simko, Norah M. Hoffmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
