<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.optics updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics</link>
    <description>physics.optics updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.optics" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 05:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>MxDiffusion: A Physics-Aware Maxwells Law-Guided Diffusion Model Strategy for Inverse Photonic Metasurface Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce MxDiffusion, a hybrid physics- and data-driven diffusion-based framework that enables efficient and highly accurate generation of photonic structures from target optical properties. The improved accuracy is achieved through a two-stage generation strategy, in which the first diffusion model is explicitly trained with Maxwells equation-based loss to embed physical insight directly into the inverse design process, while the second model maps the physically consistent intermediate representation to the final structural geometry with significantly higher fidelity than solely data-driven approaches. The performance of MxDiffusion is validated on two representative applications: gold nanostructures patterned on a silica substrate and a highly tunable bandpass filter based on phase change material. In both cases, the proposed framework consistently outperforms a conventional data-driven diffusion model benchmark, particularly for out-of-training-distribution design targets and highly constrained resonance conditions. These results demonstrate the efficacy and superiority of MxDiffusion as a general physics-guided inverse design paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16851v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujoy Mondal, Taehyuk Park, Sudipta Biswas, Alan X. Wang, Wenshan Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-referenced, drift-tolerant dipole-resolved population inversion using degeneracy-lifted dual quasinormal modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17021v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Photoluminescence intensity is widely used to infer exciton populations, yet the detected signal inherently convolves occupancy with radiative-rate modification and collection efficiency, making quantitative inversion vulnerable to pump and system drifts. Here we realize a dual-channel self-referenced scheme enabled by two nearly degenerate quasinormal modes in a hybrid microcavity. Their shared optical path provides common-mode observables (i.e., overall spectral and intensity drift) that track global thermo-optic and pump fluctuations, while their differential-mode observables (i.e., spectral splitting and mode-contrasted emission) remain highly sensitive to local gap dielectric perturbations and dipole-dependent radiative weights. Using temperature as a control parameter in monolayer WSe$ _2 $, we exploit this common/differential-mode framework to robustly invert the relative populations of excitons with out-of-plane ($ \perp $) and in-plane ($ \parallel $) dipole transitions without external absolute calibration. At the temperature of $\sim$50 K, we obtain $ N_\perp/N_\parallel \approx 200 $, coincident with the expected accumulation in the out-of-plane-emitting dark manifold. This internally referenced approach provides a practical route to drift-tolerant, dipole-resolved population metrology in nanogap photonic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17021v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxin Yu, Xinyu Zhang, Guangyu Dai, Shuai Xing, Minghui Yang, Fuxing Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Photonic Polarization Synthesizer and Analyzer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17024v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polarization-resolved control and measurement of the optical field are essential for a wide range of photonic systems, including coherent communication, polarimetric sensing, and quantum information processing. We present a photonic integrated circuit that enables the generation and analysis of arbitrary polarization states. The device provides reconfigurable access to the full polarization degree of freedom of coherent light within a single integrated platform. We experimentally demonstrate arbitrary polarization state generation spanning the Poincare sphere, as well as Stokes vector measurement on chip. Unlike conventional Stokes measurements that rely on direct detection, polarization analysis utilizing this architecture is intrinsically non-destructive, preserving the optical signal for further optical domain processing. The devices are fabricated in a commercial foundry using CMOS-compatible processes, enabling scalable and reproducible integration. By combining polarization generation and analysis in a compact and stable photonic circuit, this work eliminates the need for external polarization optics and provides a foundation for robust, polarization-enabled photonic integrated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17024v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carson G. Valdez, Anne R. Kroo, Anna J. Miller, Charles Roques-Carmes, David A. B. Miller, Olav Solgaard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum cascade laser roadmap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum cascade lasers (QCLs) are unipolar semiconductor lasers first demonstrated in 1994. Since then, they have played a central role in advancing mid-infrared and terahertz photonics, becoming among the most reliable light sources in these regions of the electromagnetic spectrum. Their importance is further reinforced by their ability to generate self-starting optical frequency combs, whose investigation is motivated both by fundamental physics and by a wide range of applications, including molecular spectroscopy and free-space optical communications. This Roadmap provides a unified overview of current advances and emerging directions in QCL research. The chapters are organized into three main sections: device design and technology; frequency combs and pulse formation; and applications of QCLs. Each chapter reviews the relevant background, summarizes the current state of the art, and identifies key challenges and future directions within its specific research area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17042v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Silvestri, Aleksandar D. Raki\'c, Dragan Indjin, Ali Khalatpour, Christian Jirauschek, Aleksandar Demic, Zoran Ikonic, Paul Dean, Nikola Vukovi\'c, Jelena Radovanovi\'c, Lianhe Li, Edmund Linfield, Michael Jaidl, Karl Unterrainer, Giacomo Scalari, J\'er\^ome Faist, Lorenzo Luigi Columbo, Massimo Brambilla, Marco Piccardo, Sukhdeep Dhillon, Mithun Roy, David Burghoff, Karl Bertling, Jari Torniainen, Xiaoqiong Qi, Thomas Taimre, Olivier Spitz, Fr\'ed\'eric Grillot, Marilena Giglio, Angelo Sampaolo, Pietro Patimisco, Vincenzo Spagnolo, Eva A. A. Pogna, Xiao Guo, Rainer Hillenbrand, Mengkun Liu, Michael Br\"unig, Adrian Cernescu, Alexander A. Govyadinov, Tecla Gabbrielli, Jacopo Pelini, Irene La Penna, Alessia Sorgi, Paolo De Natale, Davide Mazzotti, Iacopo Galli, Luigi Consolino, Francesco Cappelli, Simone Borri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full-Field Metasurface Characterization with Polarization Sensitive Coherent Modulation Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17061v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Characterizing the intensity, phase, and polarization of engineered light is fundamental to understanding and applying metasurfaces. However, existing characterization frameworks are hindered by several limitations, most notably their inability to account for the polarization of the field. Here, we report polarization sensitive coherent modulation imaging (PS-CMI), a light-weight but robust, high-resolution platform for the full-field characterization of metasurface-modulated light. By supplementing the orthogonal x- and y- complex amplitude components with an additional 45{\deg}-component, this approach calculates the retardance between two orthogonal polarization components while eliminating phase offsets, thereby enabling the subsequent recovery of the complete polarization state. We demonstrate the versatility of our method by characterizing light fields produced by a United States Air Force (USAF) target, two kinds of complex polarization field, and a metalens. This compact solution addresses a critical gap in metasurface metrology and is broadly applicable to other fields requiring the mapping of complex, polarized light distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17061v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinjie Sun, Xin Liu, Zixin Cai, Yanghui Li, Xu Liu, Xiang Hao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cryogenic piezoelectric effects in thin film strontium titanate devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Next generation quantum technologies will need to rely on efficient transduction between electrical, optical, and mechanical quantum degrees of freedom to generate large-scale entanglement over large distances. The performance of such transducers is fundamentally limited by the cryogenic properties of the underlying materials. Here, we demonstrate that engineering strain in ferroelectric thin-film strontium titanate ($\mathrm{SrTiO_3}$) not only results in an exceptionally large Pockels coefficient, but also in a robust linear piezoelectric response at cryogenic temperatures, surpassing previous thin-film benchmarks. We measure piezoelectric tensor elements of $d_{15} = 151.8 \pm 1.5$ pm/V and $d_{33} = 54.8 \pm 4$ pm/V, and an effective photoelastic coefficient of $p_{\mathrm{eff}}$ = 0.56 at 5~K. Utilizing these enhanced properties, we demonstrate the first $\mathrm{SrTiO_3}$-on-oxide acousto-optic modulator with a voltage-length product ($V_{\pi}L$) of $0.874 \pm 0.084$ V.cm, outperforming state-of-the-art unreleased modulators that typically feature a $V_{\pi}L$ of a few V.cm. Our results establish thin-film $\mathrm{SrTiO_3}$ as a promising material system for integrated quantum photonics operating at cryogenic temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17152v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Khalil, Anja Ulrich, Kamal Brahim, Andries Boelen, Danut-Valentin Dinu, Halil Cuma, Ioannis Petrides, Sandeep Seema Saseendran, Xavier Rottenberg, Pol Van Dorpe, Kristiaan De Greve, Oskar Painter, Clement Merckling, Fr\'ed\'eric Peyskens, Christian Haffner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering correlated disorder for exotic light scattering diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Diffuse scattering of light from disordered assemblies is traditionally viewed as an uncontrollable broadband scattering background resulting in whitish hues. Here, we demonstrate that correlated disorder enables precise engineering of light scattering from 2D arrays of emitters resulting in strong observable colors. Our analytical framework shows that introducing controlled noise, with tunable probability density functions and correlations, generates three distinct scattering components: diffraction orders, diffuse background, and correlation halos. Correlation halos, often mistaken for broadened diffraction peaks, are independent features whose positions depend on correlation range and can appear between Bragg peaks. Crucially, they persist far beyond the regime where diffraction orders vanish. The noise probability density function provides an additional control: specific diffraction orders can be selectively suppressed while preserving others. This approach reproduces the scattering signatures of natural photonic structures, e.g. found in Morpho butterflies, and reveals multiple pathways from order to disorder, each with distinct optical properties. Our work provides a practical method for inverse design -finding the disorder that produces desired scattering patterns. This establishes diffuse scattering as a designable quantity, expanding the toolkit for metasurfaces and structural color beyond periodic and hyperuniform structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17208v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Langevin, Emma Bosbaty-Galliot, Emmanuel Centeno, Pauline Bennet, R\'emi Carminati, Bodo D. Wilts, Patrick Bouchon, Antoine Moreau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Far-field heat transfer and monochromatic thermal currents in a cylindrical nonreciprocal cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Breaking Kirchhoff's law of thermal radiation yields new opportunities in one-way radiative thermal transport and circuitry. We investigate its consequences in the far-field regime in cylindrical cavities, by employing a specular ray-tracing algorithm. At thermal equilibrium, we show that violation of Kirchhoff's law yields non-vanishing heat rectification coefficients within different sections of the cavity, which can be tuned for perfect rectification and circulation, while internal monochromatic currents vanish due to the intrinsic coupling between emission and absorption at specular surfaces. This constraint is lifted under nonequilibrium conditions, where rotational heat fluxes within the cavity can be precisely controlled by appropriately combining reciprocal and nonreciprocal materials. These findings open new avenues for thermal management and provide design principles for nonreciprocal photonic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17313v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillem Masdemont, Julien Legendre, Georgia T. Papadakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-optical reconfiguration of far-field singularities in a photonic-crystal laser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Singular optics has emerged as an important research area with diverse applications, yet controlling optical singularities in nanophotonic emitters is typically limited by fixed subwavelength geometries and diffraction-limited control. Here, we circumvent this limitation and demonstrate an all-optical mechanism for reconfiguring far-field singularities in a photonic crystal laser. The underlying principle involves optical pumping, which creates a mesoscopic potential landscape whose spatial variations are slow compared to the lattice period. Such a potential localizes a Bloch band into trapped states whose envelope functions, and thus far-field singularity textures, are defined by the pump geometry. Using a honeycomb photonic crystal that supports a symmetry-protected bound state in the continuum, we achieve room-temperature telecom-band lasing with real-space polarisation singularities that are reconfigurable in both number and position, while the intrinsic momentum-space singularity at the $\Gamma$-point is preserved. The experimental observations align quantitatively with an analytical framework that combines the Bloch mode of the structure and envelope function theory, establishing envelope engineering as a versatile route to programmable singular-light emission in active photonic lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17368v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Padhy, Zhiyi Yuan, Mohammed Hamdad, Panagiotis Nianios, Romane Houvenaghel, Aziz Benamrouche, Nicolas Roy, Thanh Phong Vo, Christian Seassal, Xavier Letartre, Lotfi Berguiga, Micha\"el Lobet, S\'egol\`ene Callard, Hai Son Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stimulated interactions of low-energy free-electrons with light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17463v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Free-electron interactions with light and matter have long served as a cornerstone for exploring the quantum and ultrafast dynamics of material excitation. In recent years, this paradigm has evolved from a classical description of radiation and acceleration toward a fully quantum framework, transforming our understanding of light-matter interactions at the single-electron level. These advances have opened new opportunities in high-resolution imaging, ultrafast spectroscopy, interferometry, and the coherent shaping of electron wavepackets. This review surveys stimulated interactions between slow electrons and light, encompassing free-space and near-field mediated mechanisms. We discuss how free-space optical fields coherently modulate electron momentum and energy, and how near-field coupling in nanophotonic and plasmonic structures enables strong, phase-matched, efficient momentum exchange with the electron wavepacket. We further describe electron recoil, which is significant in the slow-electron regime, and temporal and spatial wavepacket shaping that enhances coupling efficiency and extends access to quantum-coherent regimes. Building on these foundations, we outline emerging frameworks including hybrid optical-electrostatic modulation, ponderomotive laser-based aberration correction, and optical electron interferometry. By unifying these developments, stimulated electron-light interactions provide a versatile route to precise beam control, quantum-state engineering, and tailored light-matter coupling, with implications for ultrafast spectroscopy, nanoscale metrology, attosecond pulse generation, electron-photon entanglement, and the creation of nonclassical states of light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17463v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Chahshouri, Sven Ebel, Mitja Funk, Nahid Talebi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Self-Attention with Exact Fourier Propagation for Phase-Only Far-Field Holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17624v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Phase-only computer-generated holography (CGH) seeks a phase pattern for a spatial light modulator (SLM) whose propagated optical field reproduces a desired intensity distribution. In the far-field (Fraunhofer) regime, optical propagation reduces to a Fourier transform, such that each hologram pixel contributes to the entire reconstructed intensity distribution. When restricted to phase-only modulation, intensity must be shaped through global phase interference effects, making the inverse mapping from target intensity to phase highly non-linear and sensitive to local minima. We present a proof-of-concept physics-in-the-loop approach in which a transformer maps a target intensity image to a phase-only SLM field and is trained end-to-end through exact FFT-based propagation embedded directly within optimization. We further observe that patch tokenization strongly shapes the optimization geometry: coarse tokenization acts as an implicit spectral regularizer that stabilizes training and suppresses checkerboard-like attractors, while finer tokenization increases spatial degrees of freedom but benefits from curriculum or hierarchical refinement. Despite training on limited primitives and restricted digit subsets, the learned generator exhibits out-of-distribution (OOD) generalization to unseen digits and hand-drawn target patterns. These results suggest that transformer architectures, whose self-attention enables global token interactions, are a natural fit for far-field holography and provide a viable foundation for scalable physics-grounded hologram generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17624v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dilawer Singh, Antoni J. Wojcik, Timothy D. Wilkinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon-enhanced strain sensitivity of quantum dots in two-dimensional semiconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17212v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional semiconductors have attracted considerable interest for integration into emerging quantum photonic networks. Strain engineering of monolayer transition-metal dichalcogenides (ML-TMDs) enables the tuning of light-matter interactions and associated optoelectronic properties, and generates new functionalities, including the formation of quantum dots (QDs). Here, we combine spatially resolved micro-photoluminescence ($\mu$-PL) spectroscopy from cryogenic (4$\text{-}$94 K) to room temperature with micro-Raman spectroscopy at room temperature to investigate the strain-dependent emission energies of thousands of individual QDs in ML-WS$_2$ and ML-WSe$_2$, integrated across multiple heterostructures and a piezoelectric device. Compared with delocalized excitons, QDs in both materials exhibit enhanced strain sensitivities of their emission energies $-$ approximately fourfold in WS$_2$ and twofold in WSe$_2$ $-$ leading to pronounced broadening of the ensemble emission linewidth. Temperature-dependent $\mu$-PL spectroscopy combined with dynamic strain tuning experiments further reveal that the enhanced strain sensitivity of individual QDs originates from strengthened interactions with low-energy phonons induced by quantum confinement. Our results demonstrate a versatile strain-engineering approach with potential for spectral matching across solid-state, atomic, and hybrid quantum photonic networks, and provide new insights into phonon-QD interactions in two-dimensional semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17212v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumitra Shit, Yunus Waheed, Jithin Thoppil Surendran, Indrajeet Dhananjay Prasad, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Santosh Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Organic molecules as single-photon sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17428v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The development of single-photon sources has been nothing but rapid in recent years, with quantum emitter-based systems showing especially impressive progress. In this article, we give an overview of the developments in single-photon sources based on single molecules. We will introduce polycyclic hydrocarbons as the most commonly used emitter systems for the realization of an organic solid-state single-photon source. At cryogenic temperatures this special class of fluorescent molecules demonstrates remarkable optical properties such as negligible dephasing, indefinite photostability, and high photon rates, which make them attractive as fundamental building blocks in emerging quantum technologies. To better understand the general properties and limitations of these molecules, we discuss sample preparation, light collection strategies and relevant emitter parameters such as absorption and emission spectra, lifetime, and dephasing. We will also give an overview of light extraction strategies as a crucial part of a single-photon source. Finally, we conclude with a look into the future, displaying current challenges and possible solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17428v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Shkarin, Stephan G\"otzinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative sensing of nanoscale materials with millimeter-wave photonic crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17527v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce millimeter-wave silicon photonic crystal cavities as a versatile platform for the perturbative sensing of nanoscale materials. This dielectric-based platform is compatible with strong magnetic fields, opening avenues for studying quantum materials in extreme environments where superconducting cavities cannot operate. To establish the platform's performance, we cryogenically characterize a silicon photonic crystal cavity at 4.3 K, achieving a total quality factor exceeding $10^5$ for a 96 GHz mode. As a proof-of-concept for its sensing capabilities, we position a hexagonal boron nitride-multilayer graphene (hBN-MLG) heterostructure at an electric-field antinode of the cavity and measure the perturbative response at room temperature. The heterostructure induces a significant change in the cavity's resonance, from which we extract a total sample conductivity of approximately $5.1\times10^6$~S/m. These results establish silicon photonic crystal cavities as a promising platform for sensitive, on-chip spectroscopy of nanoscale materials at millimeter-wave frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin K. S. Multani, Zhurun Ji, Wentao Jiang, Siyuan Qi, Akasha G. Hayden, Gitanjali Multani, Sharon Ruth S. Platt, Emilio A. Nanni, Zhi-Xun Shen, Amir H. Safavi-Naeini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subluminal and superluminal velocities of free-space photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17576v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider rectilinear free-space propagation of electromagnetic wavepackets using electromagnetic field theory, scalar wavepacket propagation, and quantum-mechanical formalism. We demonstrate that spatially localized wavepackets are inherently characterized by a subluminal group velocity and a superluminal phase velocity, whose product equals $c^2$. These velocities are also known as the 'energy' and 'momentum' velocities, introduced by K. Milton and J. Schwinger. We illustrate general conclusions by explicit calculations for Gaussian beams and wavepackets, and also highlight subtleties of the quantum-mechanical description based on the 'photon wavefunction'.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17576v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin Y. Bliokh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser interferometry as a robust neuromorphic platform for machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18047v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a method for implementing an optical neural network using only linear optical resources, namely field displacement and interferometry applied to coherent states of light. The nonlinearity required for learning in a neural network is realized via an encoding of the input into phase shifts allowing for far more straightforward experimental implementation compared to previous proposals for, and demonstrations of, $\textit{in situ}$ inference. Beyond $\textit{in situ}$ inference, the method enables $\textit{in situ}$ training by utilizing established techniques like parameter shift rules or physical backpropagation to extract gradients directly from measurements of the linear optical circuit. We also investigate the effect of photon losses and find the model to be very resilient to these.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18047v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amanuel Anteneh, Kyungeun Kim, J. M. Schwarz, Israel Klich, Olivier Pfister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting self-seeding mechanism by generating vector ultraviolet N$_2^{+}$ lasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01414v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An intense femtosecond laser pulse can generate ultraviolet air lasing, offering a promising remote light source. A long-standing hypothesis is whether it is seeded by a self-generated spectral component, such as the second harmonic that is inevitably produced by the plasma gradient. Here, we report the generation of both radially and azimuthally polarized N$_2^+$ lasing driven by a single 800-nm cylindrical vector beam. Meanwhile, the same vector pump was applied to drive the generation of vector second harmonics in plasma. The radially polarized pump produces radially polarized second harmonics while the azimuthally polarized pump yields no second harmonic generation owing to the radial direction of plasma gradient. The absence of the azimuthally polarized second harmonic rules out the hypothesis of self-seeding by second harmonics, as both radially and azimuthally polarized N$_2^+$ lasing are observed with comparable intensities. By characterizing the spatial phase distribution of vector 391-nm lasing, we concluded that its phase is synchronized with the pump. These results suggest that amplified spontaneous emissions are the origin of N$_2^+$ lasing under the most common condition of low gas pressure, which was effectively demonstrated by theoretical simulations. Our work provides a promising method for remotely generating vector ultraviolet light sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01414v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-026-02535-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jingsong Gao, Yang Wang, Jiahao Dong, Yi Liu, Chengyin Wu, Hongbing Jiang, Meng Han, Yunquan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrary state preparation in quantum harmonic oscillators using neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04598v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Preparing quantum states is a fundamental task in various quantum algorithms. In particular, state preparation in quantum harmonic oscillators (HOs) is crucial for the creation of qudits and the implementation of high-dimensional algorithms. In this work, we develop a methodology for preparing quantum states in HOs. The HO is coupled to an auxiliary qubit to ensure that any state can be prepared in the oscillator [J. Math. Phys. 59, 072101]. By applying a sequence of square pulses to both the qubit and the HO, we drive the system from an initial state to a target state. To determine the required pulses, we use a neural network that predicts the pulse parameters needed for state preparation. Specifically, we present results for preparing qubit and qutrit states in the HO, achieving average fidelities of 99.9% and 97.0%, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04598v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Parra-A, Vladimir Vargas-Calder\'on, Herbert Vinck-Posada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiresonator quantum memory with atomic ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04865v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The theory of multiresonator quantum memory with atomic ensembles has been developed. Using the obtained analytical solutions, the basic physical properties of such memory are analyzed and optimal conditions for its implementation are determined. Advantages of this quantum memory and its experimental implementation in integrated optical schemes are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04865v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. A. Moiseev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Trapped-Ion Thermometry Using Cavity-Based EIT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12823v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a technique for measuring ion temperature using cavity-based electromagnetically induced transparency (EIT) applicable for cavity-qed systems in the strong coupling regime. This method enables efficient extraction of the ion's phonon occupation number following sub-Doppler cooling close to the motional ground state. The proposed method relies on monitoring the cavity probe transmission while scanning the probe laser frequency once cavity EIT is established using the control beam, significantly simplifying the measurement procedure. We theoretically establish a model that demonstrates the influence of the thermal state of the trapped ion vis-a-vis the EIT linewidth measured. We show how the cavity EIT transmission may be used as a thermometry tool to deduce the ion temperature as well as the motional state for an ion in the sub-Doppler cooling regime, even for systems that are in the weak coupling regime. The current method can only be used for operation in the resolved-sideband regime, where individual motional states can be selectively addressed for all relevant transitions either by selecting appropriate energy levels for the three-level system or by employing strong confinement with high secular frequencies ($\sim 10 MHz$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12823v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijit Kundu, Vijay Bhatt, Arijit Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
