<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GN</link>
    <description>math.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Alexander polynomials of ribbon knots and virtual knots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.07128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.07128v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We find that Alexander polynomial of a ribbon knot in $ \mathbb{Z}HS^3 $ is determined by the intrinsic singularity information of its ribbon, and give a formula to calculate Alexander polynomial of a ribbon knot by that. We define half Alexander polynomial $ A_R (t) $, an invariant of oriented ribbons, and in fact the Alexander polynomial of the ribbon knot is $ A_R (t) A_R (t^{-1}) $. We give two useful simplified formulas for half Alexander polynomial. We characterize completely the polynomials arising as half Alexander polynomials of ribbons. The above study unexpectedly leads us to discover new formulas for Alexander polynomial of general knots and virtual knots in terms of Gauss diagrams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.07128v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng Bai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular homology of roots of unity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00660v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend some basic results from the singular homology theory of topological spaces to the setting of \v{C}ech's closure spaces. We prove analogues of the excision and Mayer-Vietoris theorems and the Hurewicz theorem in dimension one. We use these results to calculate examples of singular homology groups of spaces that are not topological but are often encountered in applied topology, such as simple undirected graphs. We focus on the singular homology of roots of unity with closure structures arising from considering nearest neighbors. These examples can then serve as building blocks along with our Mayer-Vietoris and excision theorems for computing the singular homology of more complex closure spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00660v4</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikola Mili\'cevi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
