<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GN</link>
    <description>math.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Better Subtopologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study conditions under which a space that has a good property and a courser topology with another good property admits a continuous bijection onto a space with both properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16254v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Arhangel'skii, Raushan Buzyakova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peano Quotients of Metric Continua</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For any compact, connected metric space $(M,d)$ the set of points where $M$ is not weakly locally connected is shown to define a partition $\sP$ of $M$ for which the corresponding quotient metric space $(\sQ, \nabla_\sQ)$ is a Peano continuum with $\sQ = \sP$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16580v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. F Toland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Metrizability, Completeness and Compactness in Modular Pseudometric Topologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16787v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Building on the recent work of Mushaandja and Olela-Otafudu~\cite{MushaandjaOlela2025} on modular metric topologies, this paper investigates extended structural properties of modular (pseudo)metric spaces. We provide necessary and sufficient conditions under which the modular topology $\tau(w)$ coincides with the uniform topology $\tau(\mathcal{V})$ induced by the corresponding pseudometric, and characterize this coincidence in terms of a generalized $\Delta$-condition. Explicit examples are given where $\tau(w)\subsetneq\tau(\mathcal{V})$, demonstrating the strictness of inclusion. Completeness, compactness, separability, and countability properties of modular pseudometric spaces are analysed, with functional-analytic analogues identified in Orlicz-type modular settings. Finally, categorical and fuzzy perspectives are explored, revealing structural invariants distinguishing modular from fuzzy settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16787v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philani Rodney Majozi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Structure of Sequentially Complete Locally Minimal Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17186v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generalizing results from \cite{DTk,DU} we study the fine structure of locally minimal (locally) precompact Abelian groups (these are the locally essential subgroups $G$ of LCA groups $L$, i.e., such that $G$ non-trivially meets all ``small" closed subgroup of $L$). More precisely we prove that if $G$ is a dense locally minimal and sequentially closed subgroup of a LCA group $L$, then the connected component $c(G)$ of $G$ has the same weight as $c(L)$. Moreover, when $w(c(G))$ is not Ulam measurable, then $c(G) = c(L)$. We provide an extended discussion illustrating how this result fails in various ways in the non-abelian case (even for nilpotent groups of class 2).
  Motivated by the above result, we study further those locally minimal precompact Abelian groups $G$, termed {\em critical locally minimal},such that $c(G) =c(K)$ (where $K$ is the compact completion of $G$) and $G/c(G)$ is not locally minimal. Such a group cannot be compact, neither connected, nor totally disconnected. We provide a proper class of critical locally minimal groups with additional compactness-like properties and we study the class $\CCC$ of compact Abelian groups with a dense critical locally minimal subgroup. In particular, we completely describe the connected components of the finite-dimensional groups belonging to $\CCC$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17186v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dikran Dikranjan, Wei He, Dekui Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On edge-direction and compact edge-end spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19088v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Directions of graphs were originally introduced in the study of a cops-and-robbers kind of game, while the study of end spaces has been used to generalize classical graph-theoretical results to infinite graphs, such as Halin's generalization of Menger's theorem. An edge-analogue of end spaces, where finite sets of edges are used instead of vertices as separator agents to form the so-called edge-end space, has been recently used to obtain an edge-analogue of this later result. Inspired by Diestel's correspondence between directions and ends of a graph, we tackle in this paper an edge-analogue of directions, its relation with line graphs, and an edge-analogue of Diestel's correspondence. The results of this study had some implications over edge-end space compactness, which then became a target of inquiry: we thus show an edge-analogue of Diestel's combinatorial characterization for compact end spaces. Non-edge-dominating vertices play an important role in our characterization, which motivated the study of ends and directions using now finite sets of these vertices as separator agents, as done previously for edges, giving rise to other topological spaces associated with graphs. These new direction and end spaces once again motivate an analogue of Diestel's correspondence result, and further generalizations are obtained. All of these constructions define topological space-classes associated with graphs such as edge-end spaces and edge-direction spaces of graphs. The paper organizes these topological space-classes appearing throughout the text with representation results, as it was done by Pitz and Kurkofka, as well as Aurichi, Real and Magalh\~aes J\'unior. Most notably, we show that every compact edge-end space can be represented as the edge-direction space of a connected graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19088v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo Boska, Matheus Duzi, Paulo Magalh\~aes J\'unior</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
