<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GN</link>
    <description>math.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 01:22:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Infinite Library</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The purpose of this note is to describe a space that is regular but not completely regular, but only barely so: all closed sets are $G_\delta$-sets and every singleton is a zero-set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13325v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaas Pieter Hart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suitable sets for topological groups revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A discrete subset $S$ of a topological group $G$ is called a {\it suitable set} for $G$ if $S\cup \{e\}$ is closed in $G$ and the subgroup generated by $S$ is dense in $G$, where $e$ is the identity element of $G$. In this paper, the existence of suitable sets in topological groups is studied. It is proved that, for a non-separable $k_{\omega}$-space $X$ without non-trivial convergent sequences, the $snf$-countability of $A(X)$ implies that $A(X)$ does not have a suitable set, which gives a partial answer to \cite[Problem 2.1]{TKA1997}. Moreover, the existence of suitable sets in some particular classes of linearly orderable topological groups is considered, where Theorem~\ref{t4} provides an affirmative answer to \cite[Problem 4.3]{ST2002}. Then, topological groups with an $\omega^{\omega}$-base are discussed, and every linearly orderable topological group with an $\omega^{\omega}$-base being metrizable is proved; thus it has a suitable set. Further, it follows that each topological group $G$ with an $\omega^{\omega}$-base has a suitable set whenever $G$ is a $k$-space, which gives a generalization of a well-known result in \cite{CM}. Finally, some cardinal invariant of topological groups with a suitable set are provided. Some results of this paper give some partial answers to some open problems posed in~\cite{DTA} and~\cite{TKA1997} respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13443v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fucai Lin, Jiamin He, Jiajia Yang, Chuan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Typed Topological Structures Of Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14008v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A datatset $X$ on $R^2$ is a finite topological space. Current research of a dataset focuses on statistical methods and the algebraic topological method \cite{carlsson}. In \cite{hu}, the concept of typed topological space was introduced and showed to have the potential for studying finite topological spaces, such as a dataset. It is a new method from the general topology perspective. A typed topological space is a topological space whose open sets are assigned types. Topological concepts and methods can be redefined using open sets of certain types. In this article, we develop a special set of types and its related typed topology on a dataset $X$. Using it, we can investigate the inner structure of $X$. In particular, $R^2$ has a natural quotient space, in which $X$ is organized into tracks, and each track is split into components. Those components are in a order. Further, they can be represented by an integer sequence. Components crossing tracks form branches, and the relationship can be well represented by a type of pseudotree (called typed-II pseudotree). Such structures provide a platform for new algorithms for problems such as calculating convex hull, holes, clustering and anomaly detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14008v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanjun Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflecting compact $T_1$-spaces into bounded distributive lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13482v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a contravariant reflection of the compact $T_1$-spaces with arrows given by closed continuous functions into the category of bounded distributive lattices with arrows given by closed subfit morphisms. This reflection extends both Stone duality and Isbell's duality between frames and sober spaces for those compact $T_1$-spaces that fall within each of these dualities, that is, respectively, zero-dimensional compact Hausdorff spaces, and compact sober $T_1$-spaces. On the topological side, we allow all compact $T_1$-spaces rather than just sober ones and we identify points in these with minimal prime filters on some base. On the lattice side, the shift goes from the notion of frame homomorphism to that of closed subfit morphism between bounded distributive lattices (closed subfit morphisms are defined by a natural and first order expressible constraint). The reflection becomes a duality when one restricts on the algebraic side to the complete and compact subfit lattices (i.e. compact subfit frames). Furthermore, restricting our duality on the topological side to the subcategory of compact $T_2$-spaces with all continuous maps, we obtain a duality for these with the category of complete, compact and normal lattices, thus recovering a classical result of Cornish. We also relate our adjunction to the duality introduced by Maruyama between $T_1$-spaces with continuous maps and a category having as objects a particular type of subfit frames and as arrows a certain type of morphism, of which we give an alternative and explicit algebraic characterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13482v3</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mai Gehrke, Elena Pozzan, Matteo Viale</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
