<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA</link>
    <description>cs.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven identification of stable differential operators using constrained regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Identifying differential operators from data is essential for the mathematical modeling of complex physical and biological systems where massive datasets are available. These operators must be stable for accurate predictions for dynamics forecasting problems. In this article, we propose a novel methodology for learning sparse differential operators that are theoretically linearly stable by solving a constrained regression problem. These underlying constraints are obtained following linear stability for dynamical systems. We further extend this approach for learning nonlinear differential operators by determining linear stability constraints for linearized equations around an equilibrium point. The applicability of the proposed method is demonstrated for both linear and nonlinear partial differential equations such as 1-D scalar advection-diffusion equation, 1-D Burgers equation and 2-D advection equation. The results indicated that solutions to constrained regression problems with linear stability constraints provide accurate and linearly stable sparse differential operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00198v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aviral Prakash, Yongjie Jessica Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Unstructured Mesh Reaction-Drift-Diffusion Master Equation with Reversible Reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a convergent reaction-drift-diffusion master equation (CRDDME) to facilitate the study of reaction processes in which spatial transport is influenced by drift due to one-body potential fields within general domain geometries. The generalized CRDDME is obtained through two steps. We first derive an unstructured grid jump process approximation for reversible diffusions, enabling the simulation of drift-diffusion processes where the drift arises due to a conservative field that biases particle motion. Leveraging the Edge-Averaged Finite Element method, our approach preserves detailed balance of drift-diffusion fluxes at equilibrium, and preserves an equilibrium Gibbs-Boltzmann distribution for particles undergoing drift-diffusion on the unstructured mesh. We next formulate a spatially-continuous volume reactivity particle-based reaction-drift-diffusion model for reversible reactions of the form $\textrm{A} + \textrm{B} \leftrightarrow \textrm{C}$. A finite volume discretization is used to generate jump process approximations to reaction terms in this model. The discretization is developed to ensure the combined reaction-drift-diffusion jump process approximation is consistent with detailed balance of reaction fluxes holding at equilibrium, along with supporting a discrete version of the continuous equilibrium state. The new CRDDME model represents a continuous-time discrete-space jump process approximation to the underlying volume reactivity model. We demonstrate the convergence and accuracy of the new CRDDME through a number of numerical examples, and illustrate its use on an idealized model for membrane protein receptor dynamics in T cell signaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00283v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Zhang, Samuel A. Isaacson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a new class of BDF and IMEX schemes for parabolic type equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When applying the classical multistep schemes for solving differential equations, one often faces the dilemma that smaller time steps are needed with higher-order schemes, making it impractical to use high-order schemes for stiff problems. We construct in this paper a new class of BDF and implicit-explicit (IMEX) schemes for parabolic type equations based on the Taylor expansions at time $t^{n+\beta}$ with $\beta &gt; 1$ being a tunable parameter. These new schemes, with a suitable $\beta$, allow larger time steps at higher-order for stiff problems than that is allowed with a usual higher-order scheme. For parabolic type equations, we identify an explicit uniform multiplier for the new second- to fourth-order schemes, and conduct rigorously stability and error analysis by using the energy argument. We also present ample numerical examples to validate our findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00300v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fukeng Huang, Jie Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified least squares method and a review of its applications in machine learning and fractional differential/integral equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The least squares method provides the best-fit curve by minimizing the total squares error. In this work, we provide the modified least squares method based on the fractional orthogonal polynomials that belong to the space $M_{n}^{\lambda} := \text{span}\{1,x^{\lambda},x^{2\lambda},\ldots,x^{n\lambda}\},~\lambda \in (0,2]$. Numerical experiments demonstrate how to solve different problems using the modified least squares method. Moreover, the results show the advantage of the modified least squares method compared to the classical least squares method. Furthermore, we discuss the various applications of the modified least squares method in the fields like fractional differential/integral equations and machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00382v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Kumar Singh, Mani Mehra, Anatoly A. Alikhanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Error Estimates for Augmented Subspace Method with Crouzeix-Raviart Element</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present some enhanced error estimates for augmented subspace methods with the nonconforming Crouzeix-Raviart (CR) element. Before the novel estimates, we derive the explicit error estimates for the case of single eigenpair and multiple eigenpairs based on our defined spectral projection operators, respectively. Then we first strictly prove that the CR element based augmented subspace method exhibits the second-order convergence rate between the two steps of the augmented subspace iteration, which coincides with the practical experimental results. The algebraic error estimates of second order for the augmented subspace method explicitly elucidate the dependence of the convergence rate of the algebraic error on the coarse space, which provides new insights into the performance of the augmented subspace method. Numerical experiments are finally supplied to verify these new estimate results and the efficiency of our algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00399v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhijin Guan, Yifan Wang, Hehu Xie, Chenguang Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bona-Smith-type systems in bounded domains with slip-wall boundary conditions: Theoretical justification and a conservative numerical scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Considered herein is a class of Boussinesq systems of Bona-Smith type that describe water waves in bounded two-dimensional domains with slip-wall boundary conditions and variable bottom topography. Such boundary conditions are necessary in situations involving water waves in channels, ports, and generally in basins with solid boundaries. We prove that, given appropriate initial conditions, the corresponding initial-boundary value problems have unique solutions locally in time, which is a fundamental property of deterministic mathematical modeling. Moreover, we demonstrate that the systems under consideration adhere to three basic conservation laws for water waves: mass, vorticity, and energy conservation.
  The theoretical analysis of these specific Boussinesq systems leads to a conservative mixed finite element formulation. Using explicit, relaxation Runge-Kutta methods for the discretization in time, we devise a fully discrete scheme for the numerical solution of initial-boundary value problems with slip-wall conditions, preserving mass, vorticity, and energy. Finally, we present a series of challenging numerical experiments to assess the applicability of the new numerical model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00422v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios Antonopoulos, Dimitrios Mitsotakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Loewner framework for parametric systems: Taming the curse of dimensionality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Loewner framework is an interpolatory framework for the approximation of linear and nonlinear systems. The purpose here is to extend this framework to linear parametric systems with an arbitrary number n of parameters. One main innovation established here is the construction of data-based realizations for any number of parameters. Equally importantly, we show how to alleviate the computational burden, by avoiding the explicit construction of large-scale n-dimensional Loewner matrices of size $N \times N$. This reduces the complexity from $O(N^3)$ to about $O(N^{1.4})$, thus taming the curse of dimensionality and making the solution scalable to very large data sets. To achieve this, a new generalized multivariate rational function realization is defined. Then, we introduce the n-dimensional multivariate Loewner matrices and show that they can be computed by solving a coupled set of Sylvester equations. The null space of these Loewner matrices then allows the construction of the multivariate barycentric transfer function. The principal result of this work is to show how the null space of the n-dimensional Loewner matrix can be computed using a sequence of 1-dimensional Loewner matrices, leading to a drastic computational burden reduction. Finally, we suggest two algorithms (one direct and one iterative) to construct, directly from data, multivariate (or parametric) realizations ensuring (approximate) interpolation. Numerical examples highlight the effectiveness and scalability of the method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00495v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Athanasios C. Antoulas, Ion Victor Gosea, Charles Poussot-Vassal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Order Block Toeplitz Inner-Bordering method for solving the Gelfand-Levitan-Marchenko equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a high precision algorithm for solving the Gelfand-Levitan-Marchenko equation. The algorithm is based on the block version of the Toeplitz Inner-Bordering algorithm of Levinson's type. To approximate integrals, we use the high-precision one-sided and two-sided Gregory quadrature formulas. Also we use the Woodbury formula to construct a computational algorithm. This makes it possible to use the almost Toeplitz structure of the matrices for the fast calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00529v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Medvedev, Irina Vaseva, Mikhail Fedoruk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven approximation of Koopman operators and generators: Convergence rates and error bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Global information about dynamical systems can be extracted by analysing associated infinite-dimensional transfer operators, such as Perron-Frobenius and Koopman operators as well as their infinitesimal generators. In practice, these operators typically need to be approximated from data. Popular approximation methods are extended dynamic mode decomposition (EDMD) and generator extended mode decomposition (gEDMD). We propose a unified framework that leverages Monte Carlo sampling to approximate the operator of interest on a finite-dimensional space spanned by a set of basis functions. Our framework contains EDMD and gEDMD as special cases, but can also be used to approximate more general operators. Our key contributions are proofs of the convergence of the approximating operator and its spectrum under non-restrictive conditions. Moreover, we derive explicit convergence rates and account for the presence of noise in the observations. Whilst all these results are broadly applicable, they also refine previous analyses of EDMD and gEDMD. We verify the analytical results with the aid of several numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00539v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liam Llamazares-Elias, Samir Llamazares-Elias, Jonas Latz, Stefan Klus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Energy Stable Well-balanced Scheme for the Barotropic Euler System with Gravity under the Anelastic Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We design and analyse an energy stable, structure preserving, well-balanced and asymptotic preserving (AP) scheme for the barotropic Euler system with gravity in the anelastic limit. The key to energy stability is the introduction of appropriate velocity shifts in the convective fluxes of mass and momenta. The semi-implicit in time and finite volume in space fully-discrete scheme supports the positivity of density and yields the consistency with the weak solutions of the Euler system upon mesh refinement. The numerical scheme admits the discrete hydrostatic states as solutions and the stability of numerical solutions in terms of the relative energy leads to well-balancing. The AP property of the scheme, i.e. the boundedness of the mesh parameters with respect to the Mach/Froude numbers and the scheme's asymptotic consistency with the anelastic Euler system is rigorously shown on the basis of apriori energy estimates. The numerical scheme is resolved in two steps: by solving a non-linear elliptic problem for the density and a subsequent explicit computation of the velocity. Results from several benchmark case studies are presented to corroborate the proposed claims.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00559v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. R. Arun, Mainak Kar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel central compact finite-difference scheme for third derivatives with high spectral resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a novel category of central compact schemes inspired by existing cell-node and cell-centered compact finite difference schemes, that offer a superior spectral resolution for solving the dispersive wave equation. In our approach, we leverage both the function values at the cell nodes and cell centers to calculate third-order spatial derivatives at the cell nodes. To compute spatial derivatives at the cell centers, we employ a technique that involves half-shifting the indices within the formula initially designed for the cell-nodes. In contrast to the conventional compact interpolation scheme, our proposed method effectively sidesteps the introduction of transfer errors. We employ the Taylor-series expansion-based method to calculate the finite difference coefficients. By conducting systematic Fourier analysis and numerical tests, we note that the methods exhibit exceptional characteristics such as high order, superior resolution, and low dissipation. Computational findings further illustrate the effectiveness of high-order compact schemes, particularly in addressing problems with a third derivative term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00569v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lavanya V Salian, Samala Rathan, Debojyoti Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cantera-Based Python Computer Program for Solving Steam Power Cycles with Superheating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00007v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: One of the main sources of electricity generation is power plants that use water (steam) to rotate turbines, which drive large electric generators. The steam can be generated from renewable or non-renewable energy sources, such as geothermal energy and nuclear fuels. Having an analysis tool for modeling the performance of such steam power plants can greatly help in reaching optimum designs, leading to less fuel consumption, reduced pollution, and cheaper electricity. It is further advantageous if such modeling tool is free to access, does not require many inputs from the user, and gives results in a very short time. These remarks establish a motivation for the current study. This article documents a computer code written in the Python programming language for numerically analysing the main processes in a steam power cycle with superheating. The code utilizes built-in thermodynamic properties for water in the open-source software package "Cantera". A validation case with a benchmarking example in the literature using an independent source of water properties suggests that the developed code is correct. The code can be viewed as an extension to the Python examples for thermodynamic and power generation applications. Cantera can handle both subcritical and supercritical types of superheating. In the subcritical superheating, the steam absolute pressure does not exceed 220.9 bar. In the supercritical superheating, water becomes in a special condition called supercritical fluid, with absolute pressures above 220.9 bar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00007v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.46338/ijetae0323_06</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Emerging Technology and Advanced Engineering. 13(3), 63-73. 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Osama A. Marzouk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Double Maximization Approach for Optimizing the LM Rate of Mismatched Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00545v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An approach is established for maximizing the Lower bound on the Mismatch capacity (hereafter abbreviated as LM rate), a key performance bound in mismatched decoding, by optimizing the channel input probability distribution. Under a fixed channel input probability distribution, the computation of the corresponding LM rate is a convex optimization problem. When optimizing the channel input probability distribution, however, the corresponding optimization problem adopts a max-min formulation, which is generally non-convex and is intractable with standard approaches. To solve this problem, a novel dual form of the LM rate is proposed, thereby transforming the max-min formulation into an equivalent double maximization formulation. This new formulation leads to a maximization problem setup wherein each individual optimization direction is convex. Consequently, an alternating maximization algorithm is established to solve the resultant maximization problem setup. Each step of the algorithm only involves a closed-form iteration, which is efficiently implemented with standard optimization procedures. Numerical experiments show the proposed approach for optimizing the LM rate leads to noticeable rate gains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00545v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingyi Chen, Shitong Wu, Xinwei Li, Huihui Wu, Hao Wu, Wenyi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canonical variables based numerical schemes for hybrid plasma models with kinetic ions and massless electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.10097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.10097v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the canonical variables based numerical schemes of a hybrid model with kinetic ions and mass-less electrons. Two equivalent formulations of the hybrid model are presented with the vector potentials in different gauges and the distribution functions depending on canonical momentum (not velocity), which constitutes a pair of canonical variables with the position variable. Particle-in-cell methods are used for the distribution functions, and the vector potentials are discretized by the finite element methods in the framework of finite element exterior calculus. Splitting methods are used for the time discretizations. It is illustrated that the second formulation is numerically superior and the schemes constructed based on the anti-symmetric bracket proposed have better conservation properties and lower noise, although the filters can be used to improve the schemes of the first formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.10097v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingzhe Li, Florian Holderied, Stefan Possanner, Eric Sonnendr\"ucker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semilinear elliptic eigenvalue problem: Parametric analyticity and the uncertainty quantification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.03159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.03159v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, to the best of our knowledge, we make the first attempt at studying the parametric semilinear elliptic eigenvalue problems with the parametric coefficient and some power-type nonlinearities. The parametric coefficient is assumed to have an affine dependence on the countably many parameters with an appropriate class of sequences of functions. In this paper, we obtain the upper bound estimation for the mixed derivatives of the ground eigenpairs that has the same form obtained recently for the linear eigenvalue problem. The three most essential ingredients for this estimation are the parametric analyticity of the ground eigenpairs, the uniform boundedness of the ground eigenpairs, and the uniform positive differences between ground eigenvalues of linear operators. All these three ingredients need new techniques and a careful investigation of the nonlinear eigenvalue problem that will be presented in this paper. As an application, considering each parameter as a uniformly distributed random variable, we estimate the expectation of the eigenpairs using a randomly shifted quasi-Monte Carlo lattice rule and show the dimension-independent error bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.03159v5</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Byeong-Ho Bahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multistage DPG time-marching scheme for nonlinear problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.00069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.00069v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we employ the construction of the time-marching Discontinuous Petrov-Galerkin (DPG) scheme we developed for linear problems to derive high-order multistage DPG methods for non-linear systems of ordinary differential equations. The methodology extends to abstract evolution equations in Banach spaces, including a class of nonlinear partial differential equations. We present three nested multistage methods: the hybrid Euler method and the two- and three-stage DPG methods. We employ a linearization of the problem as in exponential Rosenbrock methods, so we need to compute exponential actions of the Jacobian that change from time steps. The key point of our construction is that one of the stages can be post-processed from another without an extra exponential step. Therefore, the class of methods we introduce is computationally cheaper than the classical exponential Rosenbrock methods. We provide a full convergence proof to show that the methods are second, third, and fourth-order accurate, respectively. We test the convergence in time of our methods on a 2D + time semi-linear partial differential equation after a semidiscretization in space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.00069v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Judit Mu\~noz-Matute, Leszek Demkowicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Penalty Ensembles for Navier-Stokes with Random Initial Conditions &amp; Forcing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12870v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In many applications, uncertainty in problem data leads to the need for numerous computationally expensive simulations. This report addresses this challenge by developing a penalty-based ensemble algorithm. Building upon Jiang and Layton's work on ensemble algorithms that use a shared coefficient matrix, this report introduces the combination of penalty methods to enhance its capabilities. Penalty methods uncouple velocity and pressure by relaxing the incompressibility condition. Eliminating the pressure results in a system that requires less memory. The reduction in memory allows for larger ensemble sizes, which give more information about the flow and can be used to extend the predictability horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12870v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratic constraint consistency in the projection-free approximation of harmonic maps and bending isometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00381v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We devise a projection-free iterative scheme for the approximation of harmonic maps that provides a second-order accuracy of the constraint violation and is unconditionally energy stable. A corresponding error estimate is valid under a mild but necessary discrete regularity condition. The method is based on the application of a BDF2 scheme and the considered problem serves as a model for partial differential equations with holonomic constraint. The performance of the method is illustrated via the computation of stationary harmonic maps and bending isometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00381v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Akrivis, S\"oren Bartels, Christian Palus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volume-Preserving Transformers for Learning Time Series Data with Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11166v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two of the many trends in neural network research of the past few years have been (i) the learning of dynamical systems, especially with recurrent neural networks such as long short-term memory networks (LSTMs) and (ii) the introduction of transformer neural networks for natural language processing (NLP) tasks. Both of these trends have created enormous amounts of traction, particularly the second one: transformer networks now dominate the field of NLP. Even though some work has been performed on the intersection of these two trends, those efforts was largely limited to using the vanilla transformer directly without adjusting its architecture for the setting of a physical system. In this work we use a transformer-inspired neural network to learn a dynamical system and furthermore (for the first time) imbue it with structure-preserving properties to improve long-term stability. This is shown to be of great advantage when applying the neural network to real world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11166v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedikt Brantner, Guillaume de Romemont, Michael Kraus, Zeyuan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing the diffusion coefficient of overdamped Langevin dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12087v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Overdamped Langevin dynamics are reversible stochastic differential equations which are commonly used to sample probability measures in high-dimensional spaces, such as the ones appearing in computational statistical physics and Bayesian inference. By varying the diffusion coefficient, there are in fact infinitely many overdamped Langevin dynamics which are reversible with respect to the target probability measure at hand. This suggests to optimize the diffusion coefficient in order to increase the convergence rate of the dynamics, as measured by the spectral gap of the generator associated with the stochastic differential equation. We analytically study this problem here, obtaining in particular necessary conditions on the optimal diffusion coefficient. We also derive an explicit expression of the optimal diffusion in some appropriate homogenized limit. Numerical results, both relying on discretizations of the spectral gap problem and Monte Carlo simulations of the stochastic dynamics, demonstrate the increased quality of the sampling arising from an appropriate choice of the diffusion coefficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12087v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tony Leli\`evre, Grigorios A. Pavliotis, Genevi\`eve Robin, R\'egis Santet, Gabriel Stoltz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mathematical model of the visual MacKay effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07338v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the intricate connection between visual perception and the mathematical modelling of neural activity in the primary visual cortex (V1). The focus is on modelling the visual MacKay effect [Mackay, Nature 1957]. While bifurcation theory has been a prominent mathematical approach for addressing issues in neuroscience, especially in describing spontaneous pattern formations in V1 due to parameter changes, it faces challenges in scenarios with localized sensory inputs. This is evident, for instance, in Mackay's psychophysical experiments, where the redundancy of visual stimuli information results in irregular shapes, making bifurcation theory and multi-scale analysis less effective. To address this, we follow a mathematical viewpoint based on the input-output controllability of an Amari-type neural fields model. In this framework, we consider sensory input as a control function, a cortical representation via the retino-cortical map of the visual stimulus that captures its distinct features. This includes highly localized information in the center of MacKay's funnel pattern "MacKay rays". From a control theory point of view, the Amari-type equation's exact controllability property is discussed for linear and nonlinear response functions. For the visual MacKay effect modelling, we adjust the parameter representing intra-neuron connectivity to ensure that cortical activity exponentially stabilizes to the stationary state in the absence of sensory input. Then, we perform quantitative and qualitative studies to demonstrate that they capture all the essential features of the induced after-image reported by MacKay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07338v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyprien Tamekue, Dario Prandi, Yacine Chitour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic Phase Retrieval via Wirtinger Flow: Cartesian Form with Auxiliary Amplitude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10560v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a new gradient method for holography, where a phase-only hologram is parameterized by not only the phase but also amplitude. The key idea of our approach is the formulation of a phase-only hologram using an auxiliary amplitude. We optimize the parameters using the so-called Wirtinger flow algorithm in the Cartesian domain, which is a gradient method defined on the basis of the Wirtinger calculus. At the early stage of optimization, each element of the hologram exists inside a complex circle, and it can take a large gradient while diverging from the origin. This characteristic contributes to accelerating the gradient descent. Meanwhile, at the final stage of optimization, each element evolves along a complex circle, similar to previous state-of-the-art gradient methods. The experimental results demonstrate that our method outperforms previous methods, primarily due to the optimization of the amplitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10560v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ittetsu Uchiyama, Chihiro Tsutake, Keita Takahashi, Toshiaki Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
