<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA</link>
    <description>cs.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 04:00:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sampling recovery on function classes with a structural condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07210v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sampling recovery on some function classes is studied in this paper. Typically, function classes are defined by imposing smoothness conditions. It was understood in nonlinear approximation that structural conditions in the form of control of the number of big coefficients of an expansion of a function with respect to a given system of functions plays an important role. Sampling recovery on smoothness classes is an area of active research, some problems, especially in the case of mixed smoothness classes, are still open. It was discovered recently that universal sampling discretization and nonlinear sparse approximations are useful in the sampling recovery problem. This motivated us to systematically study sampling recovery on function classes with a structural condition. Some results in this direction are already known. In particular, the classes defined by conditions on coefficients with indices from the domains, which are differences of two dyadic cubes are studied in the recent author's papers. In this paper we concentrate on studying function classes defined by conditions on coefficients with indices from the domains, which are differences of two dyadic hyperbolic crosses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07210v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Temlyakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Field Modeling of Fracture for Ferromagnetic Materials through Maxwell's Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07346v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electro-active materials are classified as electrostrictive and piezoelectric materials. They deform under the action of an external electric field. Piezoelectric material, as a special class of active materials, can produce an internal electric field when subjected to mechanical stress or strain. In return, there is the converse piezoelectric response, which expresses the induction of the mechanical deformation in the material when it is subjected to the application of the electric field. This work presents a variational-based computational modeling approach for failure prediction of ferromagnetic materials. In order to solve this problem, a coupling between magnetostriction and mechanics is modeled, then the fracture mechanism in ferromagnetic materials is investigated. Furthermore, the failure mechanics of ferromagnetic materials under the magnetostrictive effects is studied based on a variational phase-field model of fracture. Phase-field fracture is numerically challenging since the energy functional may admit several local minima, imposing the global irreversibility of the fracture field and dependency of regularization parameters related discretization size. Here, the failure behavior of a magnetoelastic solid body is formulated based on the Helmholtz free energy function, in which the strain tensor, the magnetic induction vector, and the crack phase-field are introduced as state variables. This coupled formulation leads to a continuity equation for the magnetic vector potential through well-known Maxwell's equations. Hence, the energetic crack driving force is governed by the coupled magneto-mechanical effects under the magneto-static state. Several numerical results substantiate our developments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07346v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nima Noii, Mehran Ghasabeh, Peter Wriggers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the convergence analysis of one-shot inversion methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When an inverse problem is solved by a gradient-based optimization algorithm, the corresponding forward and adjoint problems, which are introduced to compute the gradient, can be also solved iteratively. The idea of iterating at the same time on the inverse problem unknown and on the forward and adjoint problem solutions yields the concept of one-shot inversion methods. We are especially interested in the case where the inner iterations for the direct and adjoint problems are incomplete, that is, stopped before achieving a high accuracy on their solutions. Here, we focus on general linear inverse problems and generic fixed-point iterations for the associated forward problem. We analyze variants of the so-called multi-step one-shot methods, in particular semi-implicit schemes with a regularization parameter. We establish sufficient conditions on the descent step for convergence, by studying the eigenvalues of the block matrix of the coupled iterations. Several numerical experiments are provided to illustrate the convergence of these methods in comparison with the classical gradient descent, where the forward and adjoint problems are solved exactly by a direct solver instead. We observe that very few inner iterations are enough to guarantee good convergence of the inversion algorithm, even in the presence of noisy data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07526v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcella Bonazzoli (IDEFIX), Houssem Haddar (IDEFIX), Tuan Anh Vu (IDEFIX)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GAN-based iterative motion estimation in HASTE MRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic Resonance Imaging allows high resolution data acquisition with the downside of motion sensitivity due to relatively long acquisition times. Even during the acquisition of a single 2D slice, motion can severely corrupt the image. Retrospective motion correction strategies do not interfere during acquisition time but operate on the motion affected data. Known methods suited to this scenario are compressed sensing (CS), generative adversarial networks (GANs), and explicit motion estimation. In this paper we propose an iterative approach which uses GAN predictions for motion estimation. The motion estimates allow to provide data consistent reconstructions and can improve reconstruction quality and reliability. With this approach, a clinical application of motion estimation is feasible without any further requirements on the acquisition trajectory i.e. no temporal redundancy is needed. We evaluate our proposed supervised network on motion corrupted HASTE acquisitions of brain and abdomen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07576v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathias S. Feinler, Bernadette N. Hahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure-Preserving Numerical Methods for Fokker-Planck Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A common way to numerically solve Fokker-Planck equations is the Chang-Cooper method in space combined with one of the Euler methods in time. However, the explicit Euler method is only conditionally positive, leading to severe restrictions on the time step to ensure positivity. On the other hand, the implicit Euler method is robust but nonlinearly implicit. Instead, we propose to combine the Chang-Cooper method with unconditionally positive Patankar-type time integration methods, since they are unconditionally positive, robust for stiff problems, only linearly implicit, and also higher-order accurate. We describe the combined approach, analyse it, and present a relevant numerical example demonstrating advantages compared to schemes proposed in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07641v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanna Bartel, Joshua Lampert, Hendrik Ranocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Explicit Primitive Conservative Solver for the Euler Equations with Arbitrary Equation of State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a procedure to solve the Euler equations by explicitly updating, in a conservative manner, a generic thermodynamic variable such as temperature, pressure or entropy instead of the total energy. The presented procedure is valid for any equation of state and spatial discretization. When using complex equations of state such as Span-Wagner, choosing the temperature as the generic thermodynamic variable yields great reductions in the computational costs associated to thermodynamic evaluations. Results computed with a state of the art thermodynamic model are presented, and computational times are analyzed. Particular attention is dedicated to the conservation of total energy, the propagation speed of shock waves and jump conditions. The procedure is thoroughly tested using the Span-Wagner equation of state through the CoolProp thermodynamic library and the Van der Waals equation of state, both in the ideal and non-ideal compressible fluid-dynamics regimes, by comparing it to the standard total energy update and analytical solutions where available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07710v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Sirianni, Alberto Guardone, Barbara Re, R\'emi Abgrall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Neural Network Interpolation and Its Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07805v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on tensor neural network, we propose an interpolation method for high dimensional non-tensor-product-type functions. This interpolation scheme is designed by using the tensor neural network based machine learning method. This means that we use a tensor neural network to approximate high dimensional functions which has no tensor product structure. In some sense, the non-tenor-product-type high dimensional function is transformed to the tensor neural network which has tensor product structure. It is well known that the tensor product structure can bring the possibility to design highly accurate and efficient numerical methods for dealing with high dimensional functions. In this paper, we will concentrate on computing the high dimensional integrations and solving high dimensional partial differential equations. The corresponding numerical methods and numerical examples will be provided to validate the proposed tensor neural network interpolation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07805v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongxin Li, Zhongshuo Lin, Yifan Wang, Hehu Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Hyperbolic-cross-space Mapped Jacobi Method on Unbounded Domains with Applications to Solving Multidimensional Spatiotemporal Integrodifferential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we develop a new adaptive hyperbolic-cross-space mapped Jacobi (AHMJ) method for solving multidimensional spatiotemporal integrodifferential equations in unbounded domains. By devising adaptive techniques for sparse mapped Jacobi spectral expansions defined in a hyperbolic cross space, our proposed AHMJ method can efficiently solve various spatiotemporal integrodifferential equations such as the anomalous diffusion model with reduced numbers of basis functions. Our analysis of the AHMJ method gives a uniform upper error bound for solving a class of spatiotemporal integrodifferential equations, leading to effective error control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07844v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunhong Deng, Sihong Shao, Alex Mogilner, Mingtao Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-performance matrix-free unfitted finite element operator evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unfitted finite element methods, like CutFEM, have traditionally been implemented in a matrix-based fashion, where a sparse matrix is assembled and later applied to vectors while solving the resulting linear system. With the goal of increasing performance and enabling algorithms with polynomial spaces of higher degrees, this contribution chooses a more abstract approach by matrix-free evaluation of the operator action on vectors instead. The proposed method loops over cells and locally evaluates the cell, face, and interface integrals, including the contributions from cut cells and the different means of stabilization. The main challenge is the efficient numerical evaluation of terms in the weak form with unstructured quadrature points arising from the unfitted discretization in cells cut by the interface. We present design choices and performance optimizations for tensor-product elements and demonstrate the performance by means of benchmarks and application examples. We demonstrate a speedup of more than one order of magnitude for the operator evaluation of a discontinuous Galerkin discretization with polynomial degree three compared to a sparse matrix-vector product and develop performance models to quantify the performance properties over a wide range of polynomial degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07911v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Bergbauer, Peter Munch, Wolfgang A. Wall, Martin Kronbichler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence, divergence, and inherent oscillations in MFS solutions of two-dimensional Laplace-Neumann problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07914v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The method of fundamental solutions (MFS), also known as the method of auxiliary sources (MAS), is a well-known computational method for the solution of boundary-value problems. The final solution ("MAS solution") is obtained once we have found the amplitudes of $N$ auxiliary "MAS sources." Past studies have demonstrated that it is possible for the MAS solution to converge to the true solution even when the $N$ auxiliary sources diverge and oscillate. The present paper extends the past studies by demonstrating this possibility within the context of Laplace's equation with Neumann boundary conditions. One can thus obtain the correct solution from sources that, when $N$ is large, must be considered unphysical. We carefully explain the underlying reasons for the unphysical results, distinguish from other difficulties that might concurrently arise, and point to significant differences with time-dependent problems that were studied in the past.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07914v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios D. Kolezas, George Fikioris, John A. Roumeliotis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust elastic full-waveform inversion using an alternating direction method of multipliers with reconstructed wavefields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Elastic full-waveform inversion (EFWI) is a process used to estimate subsurface properties by fitting seismic data while satisfying wave propagation physics. The problem is formulated as a least-squares data fitting minimization problem with two sets of constraints: Partial-differential equation (PDE) constraints governing elastic wave propagation and physical model constraints implementing prior information. The alternating direction method of multipliers is used to solve the problem, resulting in an iterative algorithm with well-conditioned subproblems. Although wavefield reconstruction is the most challenging part of the iteration, sparse linear algebra techniques can be used for moderate-sized problems and frequency domain formulations. The Hessian matrix is blocky with diagonal blocks, making model updates fast. Gradient ascent is used to update Lagrange multipliers by summing PDE violations. Various numerical examples are used to investigate algorithmic components, including model parameterizations, physical model constraints, the role of the Hessian matrix in suppressing interparameter cross-talk, computational efficiency with the source sketching method, and the effect of noise and near-surface effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07927v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamal Aghazade, Ali Gholami, Hossein S. Aghamiry, Hamid Reza Siahkoohi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Multigrid Algorithm for Finite Element Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07466v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum linear system algorithms (QLSAs) can provide exponential speedups for the solution of linear systems, but the growth of the condition number for finite element problems can eliminate the exponential speedup. QLSAs are also incapable of using an initial guess of a solution to improve upon it. To circumvent these issues, we present a Quantum Multigrid Algorithm (qMG) for the iterative solution of linear systems by applying the sequence of multigrid operations on a quantum state. Given an initial guess with error e_0, qMG can produce a vector encoding the entire sequence of multigrid iterates with the final iterate having a relative error e'=e/e_0, as a subspace of the final quantum state, with exponential advantage in O( poly log (N/e') ) time using O( poly log (N/e') ) qubits. Although extracting the final iterate from the sequence is efficient, extracting the sequence of iterates from the final quantum state can be inefficient. We provide an analysis of the complexity of the method along with numerical analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07466v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osama Muhammad Raisuddin, Suvranu De</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability in Phase Retrieval: Characterizing Condition Numbers and the Optimal Vector Set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we primarily focus on analyzing the stability property of phase retrieval by examining the bi-Lipschitz property of the map $\Phi_{\boldsymbol{A}}(\boldsymbol{x})=|\boldsymbol{A}\boldsymbol{x}|\in \mathbb{R}_+^m$, where $\boldsymbol{x}\in \mathbb{H}^d$ and $\boldsymbol{A}\in \mathbb{H}^{m\times d}$ is the measurement matrix for $\mathbb{H}\in\{\mathbb{R},\mathbb{C}\}$. We define the condition number $\beta_{\boldsymbol{A}}:=\frac{U_{\boldsymbol{A}}}{L_{\boldsymbol{A}}}$, where $L_{\boldsymbol{A}}$ and $U_{\boldsymbol{A}}$ represent the optimal lower and upper Lipschitz constants, respectively. We establish the first universal lower bound on $\beta_{\boldsymbol{A}}$ by demonstrating that for any ${\boldsymbol{A}}\in\mathbb{H}^{m\times d}$, \begin{equation*} \beta_{\boldsymbol{A}}\geq \beta_0^{\mathbb{H}}:=\begin{cases} \sqrt{\frac{\pi}{\pi-2}}\,\,\approx\,\, 1.659 &amp; \text{if $\mathbb{H}=\mathbb{R}$,}\\ \sqrt{\frac{4}{4-\pi}}\,\,\approx\,\, 2.159 &amp; \text{if $\mathbb{H}=\mathbb{C}$.} \end{cases} \end{equation*} We prove that the condition number of a standard Gaussian matrix in $\mathbb{H}^{m\times d}$ asymptotically matches the lower bound $\beta_0^{\mathbb{H}}$ for both real and complex cases. This result indicates that the constant lower bound $\beta_0^{\mathbb{H}}$ is asymptotically tight, holding true for both the real and complex scenarios. As an application of this result, we utilize it to investigate the performance of quadratic models for phase retrieval. Lastly, we establish that for any odd integer $m\geq 3$, the harmonic frame $\boldsymbol{A}\in \mathbb{R}^{m\times 2}$ possesses the minimum condition number among all $\boldsymbol{A}\in \mathbb{R}^{m\times 2}$. We are confident that these findings carry substantial implications for enhancing our understanding of phase retrieval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07515v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Xia, Zhiqiang Xu, Zili Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximation of Random Evolution Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present an abstract framework to obtain convergence rates for the approximation of random evolution equations corresponding to a random family of forms determined by finite-dimensional noise. The full discretisation error in space, time, and randomness is considered, where polynomial chaos expansion (PCE) is used for the semi-discretisation in randomness. The main result are regularity conditions on the random forms under which convergence of polynomial order in randomness is obtained depending on the smoothness of the coefficients and the Sobolev regularity of the initial value. In space and time, the same convergence rates as in the deterministic setting are achieved. To this end, we derive error estimates for vector-valued PCE as well as a quantified version of the Trotter-Kato theorem for form-induced semigroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07660v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katharina Klioba, Christian Seifert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning-based reduced-order methods for fast transient dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.07737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.07737v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent years, large-scale numerical simulations played an essential role in estimating the effects of explosion events in urban environments, for the purpose of ensuring the security and safety of cities. Such simulations are computationally expensive and, often, the time taken for one single computation is large and does not permit parametric studies. The aim of this work is therefore to facilitate real-time and multi-query calculations by employing a non-intrusive Reduced Order Method (ROM). We propose a deep learning-based (DL) ROM scheme able to deal with fast transient dynamics. In the case of blast waves, the parametrised PDEs are time-dependent and non-linear. For such problems, the Proper Orthogonal Decomposition (POD), which relies on a linear superposition of modes, cannot approximate the solutions efficiently. The piecewise POD-DL scheme developed here is a local ROM based on time-domain partitioning and a first dimensionality reduction obtained through the POD. Autoencoders are used as a second and non-linear dimensionality reduction. The latent space obtained is then reconstructed from the time and parameter space through deep forward neural networks. The proposed scheme is applied to an example consisting of a blast wave propagating in air and impacting on the outside of a building. The efficiency of the deep learning-based ROM in approximating the time-dependent pressure field is shown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.07737v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martina Cracco, Giovanni Stabile, Andrea Lario, Armin Sheidani, Martin Larcher, Folco Casadei, Georgios Valsamos, Gianluigi Rozza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helmholtz FEM solutions are locally quasi-optimal modulo low frequencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.14737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.14737v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For $h$-FEM discretisations of the Helmholtz equation with wavenumber $k$, we obtain $k$-explicit analogues of the classic local FEM error bounds of [Nitsche, Schatz 1974], [Wahlbin 1991], [Demlow, Guzm\'an, Schatz 2011], showing that these bounds hold with constants independent of $k$, provided one works in Sobolev norms weighted with $k$ in the natural way.
  We prove two main results: (i) a bound on the local $H^1$ error by the best approximation error plus the $L^2$ error, both on a slightly larger set, and (ii) the bound in (i) but now with the $L^2$ error replaced by the error in a negative Sobolev norm. The result (i) is valid for shape-regular triangulations, and is the $k$-explicit analogue of the main result of [Demlow, Guzm\'an, Schatz, 2011]. The result (ii) is valid when the mesh is locally quasi-uniform on the scale of the wavelength (i.e., on the scale of $k^{-1}$) and is the $k$-explicit analogue of the results of [Nitsche, Schatz 1974], [Wahlbin 1991].
  Since our Sobolev spaces are weighted with $k$ in the natural way, the result (ii) indicates that the Helmholtz FEM solution is locally quasi-optimal modulo low frequencies (i.e., frequencies $\lesssim k$). Numerical experiments confirm this property, and also highlight interesting propagation phenomena in the Helmholtz FEM error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.14737v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Averseng, Euan A. Spence, Jeffrey Galkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust and conservative dynamical low-rank methods for the Vlasov equation via a novel macro-micro decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dynamical low-rank (DLR) approximation has gained interest in recent years as a viable solution to the curse of dimensionality in the numerical solution of kinetic equations including the Boltzmann and Vlasov equations. These methods include the projector-splitting and Basis-update &amp; Galerkin (BUG) DLR integrators, and have shown promise at greatly improving the computational efficiency of kinetic solutions. However, this often comes at the cost of conservation of charge, current and energy. In this work we show how a novel macro-micro decomposition may be used to separate the distribution function into two components, one of which carries the conserved quantities, and the other of which is orthogonal to them. We apply DLR approximation to the latter, and thereby achieve a clean and extensible approach to a conservative DLR scheme which retains the computational advantages of the base scheme. Moreover, our approach requires no change to the mechanics of the DLR approximation, so it is compatible with both the BUG family of integrators and the projector-splitting integrator which we use here. We describe a first-order integrator which can exactly conserve charge and either current or energy, as well as an integrator which exactly conserves charge and energy and exhibits second-order accuracy on our test problems. To highlight the flexibility of the proposed macro-micro decomposition, we implement a pair of velocity space discretizations, and verify the claimed accuracy and conservation properties on a suite of plasma benchmark problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09425v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Coughlin, Jingwei Hu, Uri Shumlak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuously bounds-preserving discontinuous Galerkin methods for hyperbolic conservation laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03089v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For finite element approximations of transport phenomena, it is often necessary to apply a form of limiting to ensure that the discrete solution remains well-behaved and satisfies physical constraints. However, these limiting procedures are typically performed at discrete nodal locations, which is not sufficient to ensure the robustness of the scheme when the solution must be evaluated at arbitrary locations (e.g., for adaptive mesh refinement, remapping in arbitrary Lagrangian--Eulerian solvers, overset meshes, etc.). In this work, a novel limiting approach for discontinuous Galerkin methods is presented which ensures that the solution is continuously bounds-preserving (i.e., across the entire solution polynomial) for any arbitrary choice of basis, approximation order, and mesh element type. Through a modified formulation for the constraint functionals, the proposed approach requires only the solution of a single spatial scalar minimization problem per element for which a highly efficient numerical optimization procedure is presented. The efficacy of this approach is shown in numerical experiments by enforcing continuous constraints in high-order unstructured discontinuous Galerkin discretizations of hyperbolic conservation laws, ranging from scalar transport with maximum principle preserving constraints to compressible gas dynamics with positivity-preserving constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03089v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tarik Dzanic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of Matrices Satisfying the Reverse Order Law for the Moore-Penrose Pseudoinverse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02843v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a constructive characterization of matrices satisfying the reverse-order law for the Moore--Penrose pseudoinverse. In particular, for a given matrix $A$ we construct another matrix $B$, of arbitrary compatible size and chosen rank, in terms of the right singular vectors of $A$, such that the reverse order law for $AB$ is satisfied. Moreover, we show that any matrix satisfying this law comes from a similar construction. As a consequence, several equivalent conditions to $B^+ A^+$ being a pseudoinverse of $AB$ are given, for example $\mathcal{C}(A^*AB)=\mathcal{C}(BB^*A^*)$ or $B\left(AB\right)^+A$ being an orthogonal projection. In addition, we parameterize all possible SVD decompositions of a fixed matrix and give Greville-like equivalent conditions for $B^+A^+$ being a $\{1,2\}$-,$\{1,2,3\}$- and $\{1,2,4\}$-inverse of $AB$, with a geometric insight in terms of the principal angles between $\mathcal{C}(A^*)$ and $\mathcal{C}(B)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02843v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oskar K\k{e}dzierski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of second-order temporal schemes for modeling flow-solute transport in unsaturated porous media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03603v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, second-order temporal discretizations are analyzed for solving the coupled system of infiltration and solute transport in unsaturated porous media. The Richards equation is used to describe unsaturated flow, while the advection-dispersion equation (ADE) is used for modeling solute transport. The standard finite element discretization in space is utilized and four time-stepping methods are studied. Three of these methods require an iterative resolution to solve the Richards equation in its mixed form. In the remaining method, a novel technique is proposed to linearize the system of equations in time, and the iterative processes are avoided. In this method, a free stabilized parameter is introduced. Numerical tests are conducted to analyze the accuracy and efficiency of methods. The developed linear scheme based on the optimal free parameter is accurate and performs better in terms of efficiency since it offers a considerable gain in computational time compared to the other methods. The reliability and effectiveness of the developed semi-implicit scheme are investigated using numerical experiments for modeling water flow and solute transport in unsaturated soils.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03603v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nour-eddine Toutlini, Abdelaziz Beljadid, Azzeddine Soula\"imani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Counterexample to the L\'evy Flight Foraging Hypothesis in the Narrow Capture Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.13976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.13976v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The L\'evy flight foraging hypothesis asserts that biological organisms have evolved to employ (truncated) L\'evy flight searches due to such strategies being more efficient than those based on Brownian motion. However, we provide here a concrete two-dimensional counterexample in which Brownian search is more efficient. In fact, we show that the efficiency of L\'evy searches worsens the farther the L\'evy flight tail index deviates from the Brownian limit. Our counterexample is based on the framework of the classic narrow capture problem in which a random search is performed for a small target within a confined search domain. Our results are obtained via three avenues: Monte Carlo simulations of the discrete search processes, finite difference solutions and a matched asymptotic analysis of the elliptic (pseudo)-differential equations of the corresponding continuum limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.13976v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. C. Tzou, Leo Tzou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularized methods via cubic model subspace minimization for nonconvex optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.14290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.14290v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Adaptive cubic regularization methods for solving nonconvex problems need the efficient computation of the trial step, involving the minimization of a cubic model. We propose a new approach in which this model is minimized in a low dimensional subspace that, in contrast to classic approaches, is reused for a number of iterations. Whenever the trial step produced by the low-dimensional minimization process is unsatisfactory, we employ a regularized Newton step whose regularization parameter is a by-product of the model minimization over the low-dimensional subspace. We show that the worst-case complexity of classic cubic regularized methods is preserved, despite the possible regularized Newton steps. We focus on the large class of problems for which (sparse) direct linear system solvers are available and provide several experimental results showing the very large gains of our new approach when compared to standard implementations of adaptive cubic regularization methods based on direct linear solvers. Our first choice as projection space for the low-dimensional model minimization is the polynomial Krylov subspace; nonetheless, we also explore the use of rational Krylov subspaces in case where the polynomial ones lead to less competitive numerical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.14290v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefania Bellavia, Davide Palitta, Margherita Porcelli, Valeria Simoncini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tight error bounds for log-determinant cones without constraint qualifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07295v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, without requiring any constraint qualifications, we establish tight error bounds for the log-determinant cone, which is the closure of the hypograph of the perspective function of the log-determinant function. This error bound is obtained using the recently developed framework based on one-step facial residual functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07295v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Lin, Scott B. Lindstrom, Bruno F. Louren\c{c}o, Ting Kei Pong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The turnpike property for high-dimensional interacting agent systems in discrete time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06134v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the interior turnpike phenomenon for discrete-time multi-agent optimal control problems. While for continuous systems the turnpike property has been established, we focus here on first-order discretizations of such systems. It is shown that the resulting time-discrete system inherits the turnpike property with estimates of the same type as in the continuous case. In particular, we prove that the discrete time optimal control problem is strictly dissipative and the cheap control assumption holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06134v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Gugat, Michael Herty, Jiehong Liu, Chiara Segala</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
