<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA</link>
    <description>cs.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 04:00:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Stokes problem with slip boundary conditions using stabilized finite elements combined with Nitsche</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08810v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss how slip conditions for the Stokes equation can be handled using Nitsche method, for a stabilized finite element discretization. Emphasis is made on the interplay between stabilization and Nitsche terms. Well-posedness of the discrete problem and optimal convergence rates, in natural norm for the velocity and the pressure, are established, and illustrated with various numerical experiments. The proposed method fits naturally in the context of a finite element implementation while being accurate, and allows an increased flexibility in the choice of the finite element pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08810v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodolfo Araya, Alfonso Caiazzo, Franz Chouly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving high-dimensional Kolmogorov backward equations with operator-valued functional hierarchical tensor for Markov operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08823v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solving high-dimensional partial differential equations necessitates methods free of exponential scaling in the dimension of the problem. This work introduces a tensor network approach for the Kolmogorov backward equation via approximating directly the Markov operator. We show that the high-dimensional Markov operator can be obtained under a functional hierarchical tensor (FHT) ansatz with a hierarchical sketching algorithm. When the terminal condition admits an FHT ansatz, the proposed operator outputs an FHT ansatz for the PDE solution through an efficient functional tensor network contraction procedure. In addition, the proposed operator-based approach also provides an efficient way to solve the Kolmogorov forward equation when the initial distribution is in an FHT ansatz. We apply the proposed approach successfully to two challenging time-dependent Ginzburg-Landau models with hundreds of variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08823v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xun Tang, Leah Collis, Lexing Ying</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Melt Pool Geometry in Metal Additive Manufacturing Using Goldak's Semi-Ellipsoidal Heat Source: A Data-driven Computational Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08834v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This analytical solution, based on Goldak's Semi-Ellipsoidal Heat Source model, captures the dynamic temperature evolution from a semi-ellipsoidal power density moving heat source within a semi-infinite body. It tackles the convection-diffusion heat transfer equation by integrating an instantaneous point heat source across the volume of the ellipsoidal shape. The model's precision is validated by the excellent match between the predicted transient temperatures and empirical data from bead-on-plate specimens, enhancing its capability to accurately predict in-process temperature profiles in laser-based metal additive manufacturing (AM) operations. Developed in Python, the model offers customized calculations from setup to boundary conditions, adapting to variations in material properties under intense heat gradients. It considers the temperature dependency of thermal material properties and AM-process parameters, accounting for significant temperature gradients and changes in heat transfer mechanisms. The model also includes phase changes of melting or solidification with adjusted heat capacity to accurately reflect these transformations. Additionally, it considers the effects of variable laser power, scanning speed, and timing across each scanning pattern segment, acknowledging the thermal interactions between successive layers and their impact on heat transfer. This comprehensive analytical model is ready for applications including thermal stress analysis, microstructure modeling, and simulation of AM processes, predicting residual stresses and distortions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08834v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Asghari Ilani, Yaser Mike Banad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex variable solution on over-/under-break shallow tunnelling in gravitational geomaterial with reasonable far-field displacement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over-/under-break excavation is a common phenomenon in shallow tunnelling, which is nonetheless not generally considered in existing complex variable solutions. In this paper, a new equilibrium mechanical model on over-/under-break shallow tunnelling in gravitational geomaterial is established by fixing far-field ground surface to form a corresponding mixed boundary problem. With integration of a newly proposed bidirectional composite conformal mapping using Charge Simulation Method, a complex variable solution of infinite complex potential series is subsequently derived using analytic continuation to tranform the mixed boundaries into a homogenerous Riemann-Hilbert problem, which is iteratively solved to obtain the stress and displacement in geomaterial. The infinite complex potential series of the complex variable solution are truncated to obtain numerical results, which is rectified by Lanczos filtering to reduce the oscillation of Gibbs phenomena. The bidirectional conformal mapping is discussed and validated via several numerical cases, and the subsequent complex variable solution is verified by examining the Lanczos filtering and solution convergence, and comparing with corresponding finite element solution and existing analytical solution. Further discussions are made to disclose possible defects of the proposed solution for objectivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08852v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luo-bin Lin, Fu-quan Chen, Jin-ping Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An efficient implementation algorithm for quasi-Monte Carlo approximations of high-dimensional integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we develop and test a fast numerical algorithm, called MDI-LR, for efficient implementation of quasi-Monte Carlo lattice rules for computing $d$-dimensional integrals of a given function. It is based on the idea of converting and improving the underlying lattice rule into a tensor product rule by an affine transformation and adopting the multilevel dimension iteration approach which computes the function evaluations (at the integration points) in the tensor product multi-summation in cluster and iterates along each (transformed) coordinate direction so that a lot of computations can be reused. The proposed algorithm also eliminates the need for storing integration points and computing function values independently at each point. Extensive numerical experiments are presented to gauge the performance of the algorithm MDI-LR and to compare it with standard implementation of quasi-Monte Carlo lattice rules. It is also showed numerically that the algorithm MDI-LR can achieve a computational complexity of order $O(N^2d^3)$ or better, where $N$ represents the number of points in each (transformed) coordinate direction and $d$ standard for the dimension. Thus, the algorithm MDI-LR effectively overcomes the curse of dimensionality and revitalizes QMC lattice rules for high-dimensional integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08867v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huicong Zhong, Xiaobing Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Longtime behaviors of $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama method for stochastic functional differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates longtime behaviors of the $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama method for the stochastic functional differential equation with superlinearly growing coefficients. We focus on the longtime convergence analysis in mean-square sense and weak sense of the $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama method, the convergence of the numerical invariant measure, the existence and convergence of the numerical density function, and the Freidlin-Wentzell large deviation principle of the method. The main contributions are outlined as follows. First, we obtain the longtime mean-square convergence of the $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama method and show that the mean-square convergence rate is $\frac12$. A key step in the proof is to establish the time-independent boundedness of high-order moments of the numerical functional solution. Second, based on the technique of the Malliavin calculus, we present the longtime weak convergence of the $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama method, which implies that the invariant measure of the $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama functional solution converges to the exact one with rate $1.$ Third, by the analysis of the test-functional-independent weak convergence and negative moment estimates of the determinant of the corresponding Malliavin covariance matrix, we derive the existence, convergence, and the logarithmic estimate of the density function of the $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama solution. At last, utilizing the weak convergence method, we obtain the Freidlin-Wentzell large deviation principle for the $\theta$-Euler-Maruyama solution on the infinite time horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08891v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuchu Chen, Tonghe Dang, Jialin Hong, Guoting Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a class of higher-order length preserving and energy decreasing IMEX schemes for the Landau-Lifshitz equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct new higher-order implicit-explicit (IMEX) schemes using the generalized scalar auxiliary variable (GSAV) approach for the Landau-Lifshitz equation. These schemes are linear, length preserving and only require solving one elliptic equation with constant coefficients at each time step. We show that numerical solutions of these schemes are uniformly bounded without any restriction on the time step size, and establish rigorous error estimates in $l^{\infty}(0,T;H^1(\Omega)) \bigcap l^{2}(0,T;H^2(\Omega))$ of orders 1 to 5 in a unified framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08902v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoli Li, Nan Zheng, Jie Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Aspects of Hyperbolic Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09039v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hyperbolic geometry has recently found applications in social networks, machine learning and computational biology. With the increasing popularity, questions about the best representations of hyperbolic spaces arise, as each representation comes with some numerical instability. This paper compares various 2D and 3D hyperbolic geometry representations. To this end, we conduct an extensive simulational scheme based on six tests of numerical precision errors. Our comparisons include the most popular models and less-known mixed and reduced representations. According to our results, polar representation wins, although the halfplane invariant is also very successful. We complete the comparison with a brief discussion of the non-numerical advantages of various representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09039v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dorota Celinska-Kopczynska, Eryk Kopczynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient discretization of the Laplacian on complex geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Highly accurate simulations of problems including second derivatives on complex geometries are of primary interest in academia and industry. Consider for example the Navier-Stokes equations or wave propagation problems of acoustic or elastic waves. Current finite difference discretization methods are accurate and efficient on modern hardware, but they lack flexibility when it comes to complex geometries. In this work I extend the continuous summation-by-parts (SBP) framework to second derivatives and combine it with spectral-type SBP operators on Gauss-Lobatto quadrature points to obtain a highly efficient discretization (accurate with respect to runtime) of the Laplacian on complex domains. The resulting Laplace operator is defined on a grid without duplicated points on the interfaces, thus removing unnecessary degrees of freedom in the scheme, and is proven to satisfy a discrete equivalent to Green's first identity. Semi-discrete stability using the new Laplace operator is proven for the acoustic wave equation in 2D. Furthermore, the method can easily be coupled together with traditional finite difference operators using glue-grid interpolation operators, resulting in a method with great practical potential. Two numerical experiments are done on the acoustic wave equation in 2D. First on a problem with an analytical solution, demonstrating the accuracy and efficiency properties of the method. Finally, a more realistic problem is solved, where a complex region of the domain is discretized using the new method and coupled to the rest of the domain discretized using a traditional finite difference method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09050v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustav Eriksson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic-preserving approximations for stochastic incompressible viscous fluids and SPDEs on group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The long-term dynamics of particles involved in an incompressible flow with a small viscosity ($\epsilon&gt;0$) and slow chemical reactions, is depicted by a class of stochastic reaction-diffusion-advection (RDA) equations with a fast advection term of magnitude $1/\epsilon$. It has been shown in [7] the fast advection asymptotics of stochastic RDA equation in $\mathbb{R}^2$ can be characterized through a stochastic partial differential equation (SPDE) on the graph associated with certain Hamiltonian. To simulate such fast advection asymptotics, we introduce and study an asymptotic-preserving (AP) exponential Euler approximation for the multiscale stochastic RDA equation. There are three key ingredients in proving asymptotic-preserving property of the proposed approximation. First, a strong error estimate, which depends on $1/\epsilon$ linearly, is obtained via a variational argument. Second, we prove the consistency of exponential Euler approximations on the fast advection asymptotics between the original problem and the SPDE on graph. Last, a graph weighted space is introduced to quantify the approximation error for SPDE on graph, which avoids the possible singularity near the vertices. Numerical experiments are carried out to support the theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09168v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianbo Cui, Derui Sheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Methods for Optimal Boundary Control of Advection-Diffusion-Reaction Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper considers the optimal boundary control of chemical systems described by advection-diffusion-reaction (ADR) equations. We use a discontinuous Galerkin finite element method (DG-FEM) for the spatial discretization of the governing partial differential equations, and the optimal control problem is directly discretized using multiple shooting. The temporal discretization and the corresponding sensitivity calculations are achieved by an explicit singly diagonally-implicit Runge Kutta (ESDIRK) method. ADR systems arise in process systems engineering and their operation can potentially be improved by nonlinear model predictive control (NMPC). We demonstrate a numerical approach for the solution to their optimal control problems (OCPs) in a chromatography case study. Preparative liquid chromatography is an important downstream process in biopharmaceutical manufacturing. We show that multi-step elution trajectories for batch processes can be optimized for economic objectives, providing superior performance compared to classical gradient elution trajectories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09209v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcus Johan Schytt, John Bagterp J{\o}rgensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multivariate confluent Vandermonde with G-Arnoldi and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the least-squares fitting framework, the Vandermonde with Arnoldi (V+A) method presented in [Brubeck, Nakatsukasa, and Trefethen, SIAM Review, 63 (2021), pp. 405-415] is an effective approach to compute a polynomial that approximates an underlying univariate function f. Extensions of V+A include its multivariate version and the univariate confluent V+A; the latter enables us to use the information of the derivative of f in obtaining the approximation polynomial. In this paper, we shall extend V+A further to the multivariate confluent V+A. Besides the technical generalization of the univariate confluent V+A, we also introduce a general and application-dependent G-orthogonalization in the Arnoldi process. We shall demonstrate with several applications that, by specifying an application-related G-inner product, the desired approximate multivariate polynomial as well as its certain partial derivatives can be computed accurately from a well-conditioned least-squares problem whose coefficient matrix is orthonormal. The desired multivariate polynomial is represented in a discrete G-orthogonal polynomials basis which admits an explicit recurrence, and therefore, facilitates evaluating function values and certain partial derivatives at new nodes efficiently. We demonstrate its flexibility by applying it to solve the multivariate Hermite least-squares problem and PDEs with various boundary conditions in irregular domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09266v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei-Hong Zhang, Ya-Nan Zhang, Linyi Yang, Yifu Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of a finite element DtN method for scattering resonances of sound hard obstacles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scattering resonances have important applications in many areas of science and engineering. They are the replacement of discrete spectral data for problems on non-compact domains. In this paper, we consider the computation of scattering resonances defined on the exterior to a compact sound hard obstacle. The resonances are the eigenvalues of a holomorphic Fredholm operator function. We truncate the unbounded domain and impose the Dirichlet-to-Neumann (DtN) mapping. The problem is then discretized using the linear Lagrange element. Convergence of the resonances is proved using the abstract approximation theory for holomorphic Fredholm operator functions. The discretization leads to nonlinear algebraic eigenvalue problems, which are solved by the recently developed parallel spectral indicator methods. Numerical examples are presented for validation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09300v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingxia Xi, Bo Gong, Jiguang Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nodal based high order nonlinear stabilization for finite element approximation of Magnetohydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel high-order nodal artificial viscosity approach designed for solving Magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) equations. Unlike conventional methods, our approach eliminates the need for ad hoc parameters. The viscosity is mesh-dependent, yet explicit definition of the mesh size is unnecessary. Our method employs a multimesh strategy: the viscosity coefficient is constructed from a linear polynomial space constructed on the fine mesh, corresponding to the nodal values of the finite element approximation space. The residual of MHD is utilized to introduce high-order viscosity in a localized fashion near shocks and discontinuities. This approach is designed to precisely capture and resolve shocks. Then, high-order Runge-Kutta methods are employed to discretize the temporal domain. Through a comprehensive set of challenging test problems, we validate the robustness and high-order accuracy of our proposed approach for solving MHD equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09311v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuan Anh Dao, Murtazo Nazarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implicit EXP-RBF techniques for modeling unsaturated flow through soils with water uptake by plant roots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modeling unsaturated flow through soils with water uptake by plan root has many applications in agriculture and water resources management. In this study, our aim is to develop efficient numerical techniques for solving the Richards equation with a sink term due to plant root water uptake. The Feddes model is used for water absorption by plant roots, and the van-Genuchten model is employed for capillary pressure. We introduce a numerical approach that combines the localized exponential radial basis function (EXP-RBF) method for space and the second-order backward differentiation formula (BDF2) for temporal discretization. The localized RBF methods eliminate the need for mesh generation and avoid ill-conditioning problems. This approach yields a sparse matrix for the global system, optimizing memory usage and computational time. The proposed implicit EXP-RBF techniques have advantages in terms of accuracy and computational efficiency thanks to the use of BDF2 and the localized RBF method. Modified Picards iteration method for the mixed form of the Richards equation is employed to linearize the system. Various numerical experiments are conducted to validate the proposed numerical model of infiltration with plant root water absorption. The obtained results conclusively demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed numerical model in accurately predicting soil moisture dynamics under water uptake by plant roots. The proposed numerical techniques can be incorporated in the numerical models where unsaturated flows and water uptake by plant roots are involved such as in hydrology, agriculture, and water management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09382v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Boujoudar, Abdelaziz Beljadid, Ahmed Taik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computation and analysis of subdiffusion with variable exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the subdiffusion of variable exponent modeling subdiffusion phenomena with varying memory properties. The main difficulty is that this model could not be analytically solved and the variable-exponent Abel kernel may not be positive definite or monotonic. This work develops a tool called the generalized identity function to convert this model to more feasible formulations for mathematical and numerical analysis, based on which we prove its well-posedness and regularity. In particular, we characterize the singularity of the solutions in terms of the initial value of the exponent. Then the semi-discrete and fully-discrete numerical methods are developed and their error estimates are proved, without any regularity assumption on solutions or requiring specific properties of the variable-exponent Abel kernel. The convergence order is also characterized by the initial value of the exponent. Finally, we investigate an inverse problem of determining the initial value of the exponent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09421v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangcheng Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On maximum residual block Kaczmarz method for solving large consistent linear systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For solving large consistent linear systems by iteration methods, inspired by the maximum residual Kaczmarz method and the randomized block Kaczmarz method, we propose the maximum residual block Kaczmarz method, which is designed to preferentially eliminate the largest block in the residual vector $r_{k}$ at each iteration. At the same time, in order to further improve the convergence rate, we construct the maximum residual average block Kaczmarz method to avoid the calculation of pseudo-inverse in block iteration, which completes the iteration by projecting the iteration vector $x_{k}$ to each row of the constrained subset of $A$ and applying different extrapolation step sizes to average them. We prove the convergence of these two methods and give the upper bounds on their convergence rates, respectively. Numerical experiments validate our theory and show that our proposed methods are superior to some other block Kaczmarz methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09448v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Ning Sun, Mei Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast randomized algorithms for low-rank matrix approximations with applications in global comparative analysis of a class of data sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generalized singular values (GSVs) play an essential role in the comparative analysis. In the real world data for comparative analysis, both data matrices are usually numerically low-rank. This paper proposes a randomized algorithm to first approximately extract bases and then calculate GSVs efficiently. The accuracy of both basis extration and comparative analysis quantities, angular distances, generalized fractions of the eigenexpression, and generalized normalized Shannon entropy, are rigursly analyzed. The proposed algorithm is applied to both synthetic data sets and the genome-scale expression data sets. Comparing to other GSVs algorithms, the proposed algorithm achieves the fastest runtime while preserving sufficient accuracy in comparative analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09459v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiwei Xu, Weijie Shen, Wen Li, Weiguo Gao, Yingzhou Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nehari manifold optimization and its application for finding unstable solutions of semilinear elliptic PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Nehari manifold optimization method (NMOM) is introduced for finding 1-saddles, i.e., saddle points with the Morse index equal to one, of a generic nonlinear functional in Hilbert spaces. Actually, it is based on the variational characterization that 1-saddles of the generic functional are local minimizers of the same functional restricted on the associated Nehari manifold. The framework contains two important ingredients: one is the retraction mapping to make the iteration points always lie on the Nehari manifold; the other is the tangential search direction to decrease the generic functional with suitable step-size search rules. Particularly, the global convergence is rigorously established by virtue of some crucial analysis techniques (including a weak convergence method) overcoming difficulties in the infinite-dimensional setting. In practice, combining with an easy-to-implement Nehari retraction and the negative Riemannian gradient direction, the NMOM is successfully applied to compute the unstable ground-state solutions of a class of typical semilinear elliptic PDEs such as H\'enon equation and the stationary nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation. In particular, the symmetry-breaking phenomenon of the ground states of H\'enon equation is explored numerically in 1D and 2D with interesting numerical findings on the critical value of symmetry-breaking reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09892v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoxing Chen, Wei Liu, Ziqing Xie, Wenfan Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An adaptive hierarchical ensemble Kalman filter with reduced basis models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The use of model order reduction techniques in combination with ensemble-based methods for estimating the state of systems described by nonlinear partial differential equations has been of great interest in recent years in the data assimilation community. Methods such as the multi-fidelity ensemble Kalman filter (MF-EnKF) and the multi-level ensemble Kalman filter (ML-EnKF) are recognized as state-of-the-art techniques. However, in many cases, the construction of low-fidelity models in an offline stage, before solving the data assimilation problem, prevents them from being both accurate and computationally efficient. In our work, we investigate the use of {\it{adaptive}} reduced basis techniques in which the approximation space is modified online based on the information that is extracted from a limited number of full order solutions and that is carried by the past models. This allows to simultaneously ensure good accuracy and low cost for the employed models and thus improve the performance of the multi-fidelity and multi-level methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09907v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco A. B. Silva, Cecilia Pagliantini, Karen Veroy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation-specific explanations through scattered data approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08747v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work introduces the definition of observation-specific explanations to assign a score to each data point proportional to its importance in the definition of the prediction process. Such explanations involve the identification of the most influential observations for the black-box model of interest. The proposed method involves estimating these explanations by constructing a surrogate model through scattered data approximation utilizing the orthogonal matching pursuit algorithm. The proposed approach is validated on both simulated and real-world datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08747v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentina Ghidini, Michael Multerer, Jacopo Quizi, Rohan Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixture of Experts Soften the Curse of Dimensionality in Operator Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09101v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct a mixture of neural operators (MoNOs) between function spaces whose complexity is distributed over a network of expert neural operators (NOs), with each NO satisfying parameter scaling restrictions. Our main result is a \textit{distributed} universal approximation theorem guaranteeing that any Lipschitz non-linear operator between $L^2([0,1]^d)$ spaces can be approximated uniformly over the Sobolev unit ball therein, to any given $\varepsilon&gt;0$ accuracy, by an MoNO while satisfying the constraint that: each expert NO has a depth, width, and rank of $\mathcal{O}(\varepsilon^{-1})$. Naturally, our result implies that the required number of experts must be large, however, each NO is guaranteed to be small enough to be loadable into the active memory of most computers for reasonable accuracies $\varepsilon$. During our analysis, we also obtain new quantitative expression rates for classical NOs approximating uniformly continuous non-linear operators uniformly on compact subsets of $L^2([0,1]^d)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09101v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasis Kratsios, Takashi Furuya, J. Antonio Lara B., Matti Lassas, Maarten de Hoop</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heuristic Solution to Joint Deployment and Beamforming Design for STAR-RIS Aided Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09149v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper tackles the deployment challenges of Simultaneous Transmitting and Reflecting Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface (STAR-RIS) in communication systems. Unlike existing works that use fixed deployment setups or solely optimize the location, this paper emphasizes the joint optimization of the location and orientation of STAR-RIS. This enables searching across all user grouping possibilities and fully boosting the system's performance. We consider a sum rate maximization problem with joint optimization and hybrid beamforming design. An offline heuristic solution is proposed for the problem, developed based on differential evolution and semi-definite programming methods. In particular, a point-point representation is proposed for characterizing and exploiting the user-grouping. A balanced grouping method is designed to achieve a desired user grouping with low complexity. Numerical results demonstrate the substantial performance gains achievable through optimal deployment design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09149v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bai Yan, Qi Zhao, Jin Zhang, J. Andrew Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithm xxx: Faster Randomized SVD with Dynamic Shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09276v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Aiming to provide a faster and convenient truncated SVD algorithm for large sparse matrices from real applications (i.e. for computing a few of largest singular values and the corresponding singular vectors), a dynamically shifted power iteration technique is applied to improve the accuracy of the randomized SVD method. This results in a dynamic shifts based randomized SVD (dashSVD) algorithm, which also collaborates with the skills for handling sparse matrices. An accuracy-control mechanism is included in the dashSVD algorithm to approximately monitor the per vector error bound of computed singular vectors with negligible overhead. Experiments on real-world data validate that the dashSVD algorithm largely improves the accuracy of randomized SVD algorithm or attains same accuracy with fewer passes over the matrix, and provides an efficient accuracy-control mechanism to the randomized SVD computation, while demonstrating the advantages on runtime and parallel efficiency. A bound of the approximation error of the randomized SVD with the shifted power iteration is also proved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09276v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Feng, Wenjian Yu, Yuyang Xie, Jie Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of curved elements for flows over orography with a Discontinuous Galerkin scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a quantitative assessment of the impact of high-order mappings on the simulation of flows over complex orography. Curved boundaries were not used in earlier numerical methods, whereas they are employed nowadays to an increasing extent in combination with high-order methods, such as the Finite Element Method (FEM) and the Spectral Element Method (SEM). We consider here a specific Discontinuous Galerkin (DG) method implemented in the framework of the deal.II library, which natively supports high-order mappings. A number of numerical experiments based on classical benchmarks over idealized orographic profiles demonstrate the positive impact of curved boundaries on the accuracy of the results. These findings are also supported by results of the application of this approach to non-smooth and realistic orographic profiles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09319v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Orlando, Tommaso Benacchio, Luca Bonaventura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum-based gradient descent methods for Lie groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09363v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Polyak's Heavy Ball (PHB; Polyak, 1964), a.k.a. Classical Momentum, and Nesterov's Accelerated Gradient (NAG; Nesterov, 1983) are well know examples of momentum-descent methods for optimization. While the latter outperforms the former, solely generalizations of PHB-like methods to nonlinear spaces have been described in the literature. We propose here a generalization of NAG-like methods for Lie group optimization based on the variational one-to-one correspondence between classical and accelerated momentum methods (Campos et al., 2023). Numerical experiments are shown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09363v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric M. Campos, David Mart\'in de Diego, Jos\'e Torrente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence Analysis of Probability Flow ODE for Score-based Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09730v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Score-based generative models have emerged as a powerful approach for sampling high-dimensional probability distributions. Despite their effectiveness, their theoretical underpinnings remain relatively underdeveloped. In this work, we study the convergence properties of deterministic samplers based on probability flow ODEs from both theoretical and numerical perspectives. Assuming access to $L^2$-accurate estimates of the score function, we prove the total variation between the target and the generated data distributions can be bounded above by $\mathcal{O}(d\sqrt{\delta})$ in the continuous time level, where $d$ denotes the data dimension and $\delta$ represents the $L^2$-score matching error. For practical implementations using a $p$-th order Runge-Kutta integrator with step size $h$, we establish error bounds of $\mathcal{O}(d(\sqrt{\delta} + (dh)^p))$ at the discrete level. Finally, we present numerical studies on problems up to $128$ dimensions to verify our theory, which indicate a better score matching error and dimension dependence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09730v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Zhengyu Huang, Jiaoyang Huang, Zhengjiang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energetic Variational Neural Network Discretizations of Gradient Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.07303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.07303v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a structure-preserving Eulerian algorithm for solving $L^2$-gradient flows and a structure-preserving Lagrangian algorithm for solving generalized diffusions. Both algorithms employ neural networks as tools for spatial discretization. Unlike most existing methods that construct numerical discretizations based on the strong or weak form of the underlying PDE, the proposed schemes are constructed based on the energy-dissipation law directly. This guarantees the monotonic decay of the system's free energy, which avoids unphysical states of solutions and is crucial for the long-term stability of numerical computations. To address challenges arising from nonlinear neural network discretization, we perform temporal discretizations on these variational systems before spatial discretizations. This approach is computationally memory-efficient when implementing neural network-based algorithms. The proposed neural network-based schemes are mesh-free, allowing us to solve gradient flows in high dimensions. Various numerical experiments are presented to demonstrate the accuracy and energy stability of the proposed numerical schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.07303v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqing Hu, Chun Liu, Yiwei Wang, Zhiliang Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-Monte Carlo and discontinuous Galerkin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.07698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.07698v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we consider the development of tailored quasi-Monte Carlo (QMC) cubatures for non-conforming discontinuous Galerkin (DG) approximations of elliptic partial differential equations (PDEs) with random coefficients. We consider both the affine and uniform and the lognormal models for the input random field, and investigate the use of QMC cubatures to approximate the expected value of the PDE response subject to input uncertainty. In particular, we prove that the resulting QMC convergence rate for DG approximations behaves in the same way as if continuous finite elements were chosen. Notably, the parametric regularity bounds for DG, which are developed in this work, are also useful for other methods such as sparse grids. Numerical results underline our analytical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.07698v5</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vesa Kaarnioja, Andreas Rupp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A posteriori error bounds for the block-Lanczos method for matrix function approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.15643v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We extend the error bounds from [SIMAX, Vol. 43, Iss. 2, pp. 787-811 (2022)] for the Lanczos method for matrix function approximation to the block algorithm. Numerical experiments suggest that our bounds are fairly robust to changing block size and have the potential for use as a practical stopping criteria. Further experiments work towards a better understanding of how certain hyperparameters should be chosen in order to maximize the quality of the error bounds, even in the previously studied block-size one case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.15643v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11075-024-01819-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Qichen Xu, Tyler Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double fast algorithm for solving time-space fractional diffusion problems with spectral fractional Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.03493v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents an efficient and concise double fast algorithm to solve high dimensional time-space fractional diffusion problems with spectral fractional Laplacian. We first establish semi-discrete scheme of time-space fractional diffusion equation, which uses linear finite element or fourth-order compact difference method combining with matrix transfer technique to approximate spectral fractional Laplacian. Then we introduce a fast time-stepping L1 scheme for time discretization. The proposed scheme can exactly evaluate fractional power of matrix and perform matrix-vector multiplication at per time level by using discrete sine transform, which doesn't need to resort to any iteration method and can significantly reduce computation cost and memory requirement. Further, we address stability and convergence analyses of full discrete scheme based on fast time-stepping L1 scheme on graded time mesh. Our analysis shows that the choice of graded mesh factor $\omega=(2-\alpha)/\alpha$ shall give an optimal temporal convergence $\mathcal{O}(N^{-(2-\alpha)})$ with $N$ denoting the number of time mesh. Finally, ample numerical examples are delivered to illustrate our theoretical analysis and the efficiency of the suggested scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.03493v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.amc.2024.128715</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yi Yang, Jin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the best convergence rate of lightning plus polynomial approximation for $x^{\alpha}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.16116v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Trefethen and his collaborators in \cite{Herremans2023} built further on a lightning approximation with a low-degree polynomial basis based on introducing a new choice of the tapered exponentially clustering poles. The new scheme achieves the optimal convergence rate for approximation of $x^\alpha$ on $[0,1]$ as by the best rational approximation shown by Stahl in 2003, illustrated through ample delicate numerical experiments. This paper, with the aid of Poisson summation formula, Cauchy's integral theorem and the decay behaviors of Fourier transforms, rigorously shows that the new scheme, utilizing tapered exponentially clustering poles, achieves a root-exponential convergence rate in approximating $x^\alpha$, from which Conjecture 3.1 in \cite{Herremans2023} is confirmed, and the choice of the parameter $\sigma=\frac{2\pi}{\sqrt{\alpha}}$ achieves the fastest convergence rate among all $\sigma&gt;0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.16116v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuhuang Xiang, Shunfeng Yang, Yanghao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence analysis of Lawson's iteration for the polynomial and rational minimax approximations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00778v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Lawson's iteration is a classical and effective method for solving the linear (polynomial) minimax approximation in the complex plane. Extension of Lawson's iteration for the rational minimax approximation with both computationally high efficiency and theoretical guarantee is challenging. A recent work [L.-H. Zhang, L. Yang, W. H. Yang and Y.-N. Zhang, A convex dual programming for the rational minimax approximation and Lawson's iteration, 2023, arXiv:2308.06991v1] reveals that Lawson's iteration can be viewed as a method for solving the dual problem of the original rational minimax approximation, and a new type of Lawson's iteration was proposed. Such a dual problem is guaranteed to obtain the original minimax solution under Ruttan's sufficient condition, and numerically, the proposed Lawson's iteration was observed to converge monotonically with respect to the dual objective function. In this paper, we perform theoretical convergence analysis for Lawson's iteration for both the linear and rational minimax approximations. In particular, we show that (i) for the linear minimax approximation, the near-optimal Lawson exponent $\beta$ in Lawson's iteration is $\beta=1$, and (ii) for the rational minimax approximation, the proposed Lawson's iteration converges monotonically with respect to the dual objective function for any sufficiently small $\beta&gt;0$, and the limit approximant fulfills the complementary slackness: any node associated with positive weight either is an interpolation point or has a constant error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00778v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei-Hong Zhang, Shanheng Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inviscid Burgers as a degenerate elliptic problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08814v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate the feasibility of a scheme to obtain approximate weak solutions to the (inviscid) Burgers equation in conservation and Hamilton-Jacobi form, treated as degenerate elliptic problems. We show different variants recover non-unique weak solutions as appropriate, and also specific constructive approaches to recover the corresponding entropy solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08814v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uditnarayan Kouskiya, Amit Acharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of a Ramshaw-Mesina Iteration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04702v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 1991 Ramshaw and Mesina introduced a clever synthesis of penalty methods and artificial compression methods. Its form makes it an interesting option to replace the pressure update in the Uzawa iteration. The result, for the Stokes problem, is \begin{equation} \left\{ \begin{array} [c]{cc} Step\ 1: &amp; -\triangle u^{n+1}+\nabla p^{n}=f(x),\ {\rm in}\ \Omega,\ u^{n+1}|_{\partial\Omega}=0,\\ Step\ 2: &amp; p^{n+1}-p^{n}+\beta\nabla\cdot(u^{n+1}-u^{n})+\alpha ^{2}\nabla\cdot u^{n+1}=0. \end{array} \right. \end{equation} For saddle point problems, including Stokes, this iteration converges under a condition similar to the one required for Uzawa iteration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04702v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aytekin \c{C}ibik, William Layton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chebyshev and The Fast Fourier Transform Methods for Signal Interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00414v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Approximation theorem is one of the most important aspects of numerical analysis that has evolved over the years with many different approaches. Some of the most popular approximation methods include the Lebesgue approximation theorem, the Weierstrass approximation, and the Fourier approximation theorem. The limitations associated with various approximation methods are too crucial to ignore, and thus, the nature of a specific dataset may require using a specific approximation method for such estimates. In this report, we shall delve into Chebyshev's polynomials interpolation in detail as an alternative approach to reconstructing signals and compare the reconstruction to that of the Fourier polynomials. We will also explore the advantages and limitations of the Chebyshev polynomials and discuss in detail their mathematical formulation and equivalence to the cosine function over a given interval [a, b].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00414v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ishmael N. Amartey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Field Modeling of Fracture for Ferromagnetic Materials through Maxwell's Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07346v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electro-active materials are classified as electrostrictive and piezoelectric materials. They deform under the action of an external electric field. Piezoelectric material, as a special class of active materials, can produce an internal electric field when subjected to mechanical stress or strain. In return, there is the converse piezoelectric response, which expresses the induction of the mechanical deformation in the material when it is subjected to the application of the electric field. This work presents a variational-based computational modeling approach for failure prediction of ferromagnetic materials. In order to solve this problem, a coupling between magnetostriction and mechanics is modeled, then the fracture mechanism in ferromagnetic materials is investigated. Furthermore, the failure mechanics of ferromagnetic materials under the magnetostrictive effects is studied based on a variational phase-field model of fracture. Phase-field fracture is numerically challenging since the energy functional may admit several local minima, imposing the global irreversibility of the fracture field and dependency of regularization parameters related discretization size. Here, the failure behavior of a magnetoelastic solid body is formulated based on the Helmholtz free energy function, in which the strain tensor, the magnetic induction vector, and the crack phase-field are introduced as state variables. This coupled formulation leads to a continuity equation for the magnetic vector potential through well-known Maxwell's equations. Hence, the energetic crack driving force is governed by the coupled magneto-mechanical effects under the magneto-static state. Several numerical results substantiate our developments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07346v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nima Noii, Mehran Ghasabeh, Peter Wriggers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Calder\'on's problem via DeepONets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.08941v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the Dirichlet-to-Neumann operator and the direct and inverse Calder\'on's mappings appearing in the Inverse Problem of recovering a smooth bounded and positive isotropic conductivity of a material filling a smooth bounded domain in space. Using deep learning techniques, we prove that these mappings are rigorously approximated by DeepONets, infinite-dimensional counterparts of standard artificial neural networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.08941v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Castro, Claudio Mu\~noz, Nicol\'as Valenzuela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On posterior consistency of data assimilation with Gaussian process priors: the 2D Navier-Stokes equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.08136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.08136v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a non-linear Bayesian data assimilation model for the periodic two-dimensional Navier-Stokes equations with initial condition modelled by a Gaussian process prior. We show that if the system is updated with sufficiently many discrete noisy measurements of the velocity field, then the posterior distribution eventually concentrates near the ground truth solution of the time evolution equation, and in particular that the initial condition is recovered consistently by the posterior mean vector field. We further show that the convergence rate can in general not be faster than inverse logarithmic in sample size, but describe specific conditions on the initial conditions when faster rates are possible. In the proofs we provide an explicit quantitative estimate for backward uniqueness of solutions of the two-dimensional Navier-Stokes equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.08136v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Nickl, Edriss S. Titi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Pressure-Temperature Residual (CPTR) Preconditioner Performance for Large-Scale Thermal CO2 Injection Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11892v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work studies the performance of a novel preconditioner, designed for thermal reservoir simulation cases and recently introduced in Roy et al. (2020) and Cremon et al. (2020), on large-scale thermal CO2 injection cases. For Carbon Capture and Sequestration (CCS) projects, injecting CO2 under supercritical conditions is typically tens of degrees colder than the reservoir temperature. Thermal effects can have a significant impact on the simulation results, but they also add many challenges for the solvers. More specifically, the usual combination of an iterative linear solver (such as GMRES) and the Constrained Pressure Residual (CPR) physics-based block-preconditioner is known to perform rather poorly or fail to converge when thermal effects play a significant role. The Constrained Pressure-Temperature Residual (CPTR) preconditioner retains the 2x2 block structure (elliptic/hyperbolic) of CPR but includes the temperature in the elliptic subsystem. The elliptic subsystem is now formed by two equations, and is dealt with by the system-solver of BoomerAMG (from the HYPRE library). Then a global smoother, ILU(0), is applied to the full system to handle the local, hyperbolic temperature fronts. We implemented CPTR in the multi-physics solver GEOS and present results on various large-scale thermal CCS simulation cases, including both Cartesian and fully unstructured meshes, up to tens of millions of degrees of freedom. The CPTR preconditioner severely reduces the number of GMRES iterations and the runtime, with cases timing out in 24h with CPR now requiring a few hours with CPTR. We present strong scaling results using hundreds of CPU cores for multiple cases, and show close to linear scaling. CPTR is also virtually insensitive to the thermal Peclet number (which compares advection and diffusion effects) and is suitable to any thermal regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11892v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias A. Cremon, Jacques Franc, Francois P. Hamon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Individualizing Glioma Radiotherapy Planning by Optimization of Data and Physics-Informed Discrete Loss</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05063v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Brain tumor growth is unique to each glioma patient and extends beyond what is visible in imaging scans, infiltrating surrounding brain tissue. Understanding these hidden patient-specific progressions is essential for effective therapies. Current treatment plans for brain tumors, such as radiotherapy, typically involve delineating a uniform margin around the visible tumor on pre-treatment scans to target this invisible tumor growth. This "one size fits all" approach is derived from population studies and often fails to account for the nuances of individual patient conditions. We present the GliODIL framework, which infers the full spatial distribution of tumor cell concentration from available multi-modal imaging, leveraging a Fisher-Kolmogorov type physics model to describe tumor growth. This is achieved through the newly introduced method of Optimizing the Discrete Loss (ODIL), where both data and physics-based constraints are softly assimilated into the solution. Our test dataset comprises 152 glioblastoma patients with pre-treatment imaging and post-treatment follow-ups for tumor recurrence monitoring. By blending data-driven techniques with physics-based constraints, GliODIL enhances recurrence prediction in radiotherapy planning, challenging traditional uniform margins and strict adherence to the Fisher-Kolmogorov partial differential equation (PDE) model, which is adapted for complex cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05063v3</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Balcerak, Jonas Weidner, Petr Karnakov, Ivan Ezhov, Sergey Litvinov, Petros Koumoutsakos, Ray Zirui Zhang, John S. Lowengrub, Bene Wiestler, Bjoern Menze</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
