<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA</link>
    <description>cs.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 04:01:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Framework for the Solution of Tree-Coupled Saddle-Point Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the solution of saddle-point systems with a tree-based block structure, introducing a parallelizable direct method for their solution. As our key contribution, we then propose several structure-exploiting preconditioners to be used during applications of the MINRES and GMRES algorithms and analyze their properties. We adapt several concepts originating in the field of multigrid methods, obtaining a variety of problem-adapted multi-level methods. We analyze the complexity of all algorithms, and derive a number of results on eigenvalues of the preconditioned system and convergence of iterative methods. We validate our theoretical findings through a range of numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23385v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Hansknecht, Bernhard Heinzelreiter, John W. Pearson, Andreas Potschka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An asymptotic-preserving IMEX PN method for the gray model of the radiative transfer equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23650v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An asymptotic-preserving (AP) implicit-explicit PN numerical scheme is proposed for the gray model of the radiative transfer equation, where the first- and second-order numerical schemes are discussed for both the linear and nonlinear models. The AP property of this numerical scheme is proved theoretically and numerically, while the numerical stability of the linear model is verified by Fourier analysis. Several classical benchmark examples are studied to validate the efficiency of this numerical scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23650v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinxue Fu, Juan Cheng, Weiming Li, Tao Xiong, Yanli Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergent analysis of algebraic multigrid method with data-driven parameter learning for non-selfadjoint elliptic problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we apply the practical GADI-HS iteration as a smoother in algebraic multigrid (AMG) method for solving second-order non-selfadjoint elliptic problem. Additionally, we prove the convergence of the derived algorithm and introduce a data-driven parameter learing method called Gaussian process regression (GPR) to predict optimal parameters. Numerical experimental results show that using GPR to predict parameters can save a significant amount of time cost and approach the optimal parameters accurately.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23681v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Zhang, Junyue Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hydrostatic Model for Simulating Moving Bottom-Generated Waves: A Shallow Water Extension with Quadratic Vertical Pressure Profile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate a depth-averaged non-hydrostatic model to solve wave equations with generation by a moving bottom. This model is built upon the shallow water equations, which are widely used in tsunami wave modelling. An extension leads to two additional unknowns to be solved: vertical momentum and non-hydrostatic pressure. We show that a linear vertical velocity assumption turns out to give us a quadratic pressure relation, which is equivalent to Boussinesq-type equations. However, this extension involves a time derivative of an unknown parameter, rendering the solution by a projection method ambiguous. In this study, we derive an alternative form of the elliptic system of equations to avoid such ambiguity. The new set of equations satisfies the desired solubility property, while also consistently representing the non-flat moving topography wave generation. Validations are performed using several test cases based on previous experiments and a high-fidelity simulation. First, we show the efficiency of our model in solving a vertical movement, which represents an undersea earthquake-generated tsunami. Following that, we demonstrate the accuracy of the model for landslide-generated waves. Finally, we compare the performance of our novel set of equations with the linear and simplified quadratic pressure profiles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23707v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kemal Firdaus, J\"orn Behrens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A theoretical analysis of mass scaling techniques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mass scaling is widely used in finite element models of structural dynamics for increasing the critical time step of explicit time integration methods. While the field has been flourishing over the years, it still lacks a strong theoretical basis and mostly relies on numerical experiments as the only means of assessment. This contribution thoroughly reviews existing methods and connects them to established linear algebra results to derive rigorous eigenvalue bounds and condition number estimates. Our results cover some of the most successful mass scaling techniques, unraveling for the first time well-known numerical observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23816v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yannis Voet, Espen Sande, Annalisa Buffa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Primal Staggered Discontinuous Galerkin Method on Polytopal Meshes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel staggered discontinuous Galerkin (SDG) method tailored for solving elliptic equations on polytopal meshes. Our approach utilizes a primal-dual grid framework to ensure local conservation of fluxes, significantly improving stability and accuracy. The method is hybridizable and reduces the degrees of freedom compared to existing approaches. It also bridges connections to other numerical methods on polytopal meshes. Numerical experiments validate the method's optimal convergence rates and computational efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23865v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Chen, X. Huang, E. Park, R. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Derivative-Orthogonal Wavelet Multiscale Method for 1D Elliptic Equations with Rough Diffusion Coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23945v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate 1D elliptic equations $-\nabla\cdot (a\nabla u)=f$ with rough diffusion coefficients $a$ that satisfy $0&lt;a_{\min}\le a\le a_{\max}&lt;\infty$ and $f\in L_2(\Omega)$. To achieve an accurate and robust numerical solution on a coarse mesh of size $H$, we introduce a derivative-orthogonal wavelet-based framework. This approach incorporates both regular and specialized basis functions constructed through a novel technique, defining a basis function space that enables effective approximation. We develop a derivative-orthogonal wavelet multiscale method tailored for this framework, proving that the condition number $\kappa$ of the stiffness matrix satisfies $\kappa\le a_{\max}/a_{\min}$, independent of $H$. For the error analysis, we establish that the energy and $L_2$-norm errors of our method converge at first-order and second-order rates, respectively, for any coarse mesh $H$. Specifically, the energy and $L_2$-norm errors are bounded by $2 a_{\min}^{-1/2} \|f\|_{L_2(\Omega)} H$ and $4 a_{\min}^{-1}\|f\|_{L_2(\Omega)} H^2$. Moreover, the numerical approximated solution also possesses the interpolation property at all grid points. We present a range of challenging test cases with continuous, discontinuous, high-frequency, and high-contrast coefficients $a$ to evaluate errors in $u, u'$ and $a u'$ in both $l_2$ and $l_\infty$ norms. We also provide a numerical example that both coefficient $a$ and source term $f$ contain discontinuous, high-frequency and high-contrast oscillations. Additionally, we compare our method with the standard second-order finite element method to assess error behaviors and condition numbers when the mesh is not fine enough to resolve coefficient oscillations. Numerical results confirm the bounded condition numbers and convergence rates, affirming the effectiveness of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23945v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiwei Feng, Bin Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoupled structure-preserving discretization of incompressible MHD equations with general boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the framework of a mixed finite element method, a structure-preserving formulation for incompressible MHD equations with general boundary conditions is proposed. A leapfrog-type temporal scheme fully decouples the fluid part from the Maxwell part by means of staggered discrete time sequences and, in doing so, partially linearizes the system. Conservation and dissipation properties of the formulation before and after the decoupling are analyzed. We demonstrate optimal spatial and second-order temporal error convergence and conservation and dissipation properties of the proposed method using manufactured solutions, and apply it to the benchmark Orszag-Tang and lid-driven cavity test cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23973v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Zhang, Artur Palha, Andrea Brugnoli, Deepesh Toshniwal, Marc Gerritsma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Power Method for Computing Singular Value Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The singular value decomposition (SVD) allows to put a matrix as a product of three matrices: a matrix with the left singular vectors, a matrix with the positive-valued singular values and a matrix with the right singular vectors. There are two main approaches allowing to get the SVD result: the classical method and the randomized method. The analysis of the classical approach leads to accurate singular values. The randomized approach is especially used for high dimensional matrix and is based on the approximation accuracy without computing necessary all singular values. In this paper, the SVD computation is formalized as an optimization problem and a use of the gradient search algorithm. That results in a power method allowing to get all or the first largest singular values and their associated right vectors. In this iterative search, the accuracy on the singular values and the associated vector matrix depends on the user settings. Two applications of the SVD are the principal component analysis and the autoencoder used in the neural network models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23999v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Doulaye Dembele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-field modeling of ductile fracture across grain boundaries in polycrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24107v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we address damage initiation and micro-crack formation in ductile failure of polycrystalline metals. We show how our recently published thermodynamic framework for ductile phase-field fracture of single crystals can be extended to polycyrstalline structures. A key feature of this framework is that is accounts for size effects by adopting gradient-enhanced (crystal) plasticity. Gradient-enhanced plasticity requires the definition of boundary conditions representing the plastic slip transmission resistance of the boundaries. In this work, we propose a novel type of micro-flexible boundary condition for gradient-plasticity, which couples the slip transmission resistance with the phase-field damage such that the resistance locally changes during the fracturing process. The formulation permits to maintain the effect of grain boundaries as obstacles for plastic slip during plastification, while also accounting for weakening of their resistance during the softening phase. In numerical experiments, the new damage-dependent boundary condition is compared to classical micro-free and micro-hard boundary conditions in polycrystals and it is demonstrated that it indeed produces a response that transitions from micro-hard to micro-free as the material fails. We show that the formulation maintains resistance to slip transmission during hardening, but can generate micro-cracks across grain boundaries during the fracture process. We further show examples of how the model can be used to simulate void coalescence and three-dimensional crack fronts in polycrystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24107v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kim Louisa Auth, Jim Brouzoulis, Magnus Ekh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Two-Level Schwarz Methods: A Parallel Implementation in FROSch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Owing to the ability of nonlinear domain decomposition methods to improve the nonlinear convergence behavior of Newton's method, they have experienced a rise in popularity recently in the context of problems for which Newton's method converges slowly or not at all. This article introduces a novel parallel implementation of a two-level nonlinear Schwarz solver based on the FROSch (Fast and Robust Overlapping Schwarz) solver framework, part of Sandia's Trilinos library. First, an introduction to the key concepts underlying two-level nonlinear Schwarz methods is given, including a brief overview of the coarse space used to build the second level. Next, the parallel implementation is discussed, followed by preliminary parallel results for a scalar nonlinear diffusion problem and a 2D nonlinear plane-stress Neo-Hooke elasticity problem with large deformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24138v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Heinlein, Kyrill Ho, Axel Klawonn, Martin Lanser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain-decomposed image classification algorithms using linear discriminant analysis and convolutional neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23359v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In many modern computer application problems, the classification of image data plays an important role. Among many different supervised machine learning models, convolutional neural networks (CNNs) and linear discriminant analysis (LDA) as well as sophisticated variants thereof are popular techniques. In this work, two different domain decomposed CNN models are experimentally compared for different image classification problems. Both models are loosely inspired by domain decomposition methods and in addition, combined with a transfer learning strategy. The resulting models show improved classification accuracies compared to the corresponding, composed global CNN model without transfer learning and besides, also help to speed up the training process. Moreover, a novel decomposed LDA strategy is proposed which also relies on a localization approach and which is combined with a small neural network model. In comparison with a global LDA applied to the entire input data, the presented decomposed LDA approach shows increased classification accuracies for the considered test problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23359v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel Klawonn, Martin Lanser, Janine Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Lipschitz Operators with respect to Gaussian Measures with Near-Optimal Sample Complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23440v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Operator learning, the approximation of mappings between infinite-dimensional function spaces using ideas from machine learning, has gained increasing research attention in recent years. Approximate operators, learned from data, hold promise to serve as efficient surrogate models for problems in computational science and engineering, complementing traditional numerical methods. However, despite their empirical success, our understanding of the underpinning mathematical theory is in large part still incomplete. In this paper, we study the approximation of Lipschitz operators in expectation with respect to Gaussian measures. We prove higher Gaussian Sobolev regularity of Lipschitz operators and establish lower and upper bounds on the Hermite polynomial approximation error. We further consider the reconstruction of Lipschitz operators from $m$ arbitrary (adaptive) linear samples. A key finding is the tight characterization of the smallest achievable error for all possible (adaptive) sampling and reconstruction maps in terms of $m$. It is shown that Hermite polynomial approximation is an optimal recovery strategy, but we have the following curse of sample complexity: No method to approximate Lipschitz operators based on finitely many samples can achieve algebraic convergence rates in $m$. On the positive side, we prove that a sufficiently fast spectral decay of the covariance operator of the Gaussian measure guarantees convergence rates which are arbitrarily close to any algebraic rate in the large data limit $m \to \infty$. Finally, we focus on the recovery of Lipschitz operators from finitely many point samples. We consider Christoffel sampling and weighted least-squares approximation, and present an algorithm which provably achieves near-optimal sample complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23440v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Adcock, Michael Griebel, Gregor Maier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient-free training of recurrent neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23467v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recurrent neural networks are a successful neural architecture for many time-dependent problems, including time series analysis, forecasting, and modeling of dynamical systems. Training such networks with backpropagation through time is a notoriously difficult problem because their loss gradients tend to explode or vanish. In this contribution, we introduce a computational approach to construct all weights and biases of a recurrent neural network without using gradient-based methods. The approach is based on a combination of random feature networks and Koopman operator theory for dynamical systems. The hidden parameters of a single recurrent block are sampled at random, while the outer weights are constructed using extended dynamic mode decomposition. This approach alleviates all problems with backpropagation commonly related to recurrent networks. The connection to Koopman operator theory also allows us to start using results in this area to analyze recurrent neural networks. In computational experiments on time series, forecasting for chaotic dynamical systems, and control problems, as well as on weather data, we observe that the training time and forecasting accuracy of the recurrent neural networks we construct are improved when compared to commonly used gradient-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23467v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik Lien Bolager, Ana Cukarska, Iryna Burak, Zahra Monfared, Felix Dietrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic wave diffraction by a quadrant of sound-soft scatterers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23647v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by research in metamaterials, we consider the challenging problem of acoustic wave scattering by a doubly periodic quadrant of sound-soft scatterers arranged in a square formation, which we have dubbed the quarter lattice. This leads to a Wiener--Hopf equation in two complex variables with three unknown functions for which we can reduce and solve exactly using a new analytic method. After some suitable truncations, the resulting linear system is inverted using elementary matrix arithmetic and the solution can be numerically computed. This solution is also critically compared to a numerical least squares collocation approach and to our previous method where we decomposed the lattice into semi-infinite rows or columns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23647v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Nethercote, Anastasia Kisil, Raphael Assier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A higher order nonconforming virtual element method for the Cahn-Hilliard equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.11408v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we develop a fully nonconforming virtual element method (VEM) of arbitrary approximation order for the two dimensional Cahn-Hilliard equation. We carry out the error analysis for the semidiscrete (continuous-in-time) scheme and verify the theoretical convergence result via numerical experiments. We present a fully discrete scheme which uses a convex splitting Runge-Kutta method to discretize in the temporal variable alongside the virtual element spatial discretization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.11408v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Dedner, Alice Hodson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient high-resolution refinement in cryo-EM with stochastic gradient descent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electron cryomicroscopy (cryo-EM) is an imaging technique widely used in structural biology to determine the three-dimensional structure of biological molecules from noisy two-dimensional projections with unknown orientations. As the typical pipeline involves processing large amounts of data, efficient algorithms are crucial for fast and reliable results. The stochastic gradient descent (SGD) algorithm has been used to improve the speed of ab initio reconstruction, which results in a first, low-resolution estimation of the volume representing the molecule of interest, but has yet to be applied successfully in the high-resolution regime, where expectation-maximization algorithms achieve state-of-the-art results, at a high computational cost. In this article, we investigate the conditioning of the optimization problem and show that the large condition number prevents the successful application of gradient descent-based methods at high resolution. Our results include a theoretical analysis of the condition number of the optimization problem in a simplified setting where the individual projection directions are known, an algorithm based on computing a diagonal preconditioner using Hutchinson's diagonal estimator, and numerical experiments showing the improvement in the convergence speed when using the estimated preconditioner with SGD. The preconditioned SGD approach can potentially enable a simple and unified approach to ab initio reconstruction and high-resolution refinement with faster convergence speed and higher flexibility, and our results are a promising step in this direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16100v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan Toader, Marcus A. Brubaker, Roy R. Lederman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NumCalc: An open source BEM code for solving acoustic scattering problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00005v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The calculation of the acoustic field in or around objects is an important task in acoustic engineering. To numerically solve this task, the boundary element method (BEM) is a commonly used method especially for infinite domains. The open source tool Mesh2HRTF and its BEM core NumCalc provide users with a collection of free software for acoustic simulations without the need of having an in-depth knowledge into numerical methods. However, we feel that users should have a basic understanding with respect to the methods behind the software they are using. We are convinced that this basic understanding helps in avoiding common mistakes and also helps to understand the requirements to use the software. To provide this background is the first motivation for this paper. A second motivation for this paper is to demonstrate the accuracy of NumCalc when solving benchmark problems. Thus, users can get an idea about the accuracy they can expect when using NumCalc as well as the memory and CPU requirements of NumCalc. A third motivation for this paper is to give users detailed information about some parts of the actual implementation that are usually not mentioned in literature, e.g., the specific version of the fast multipole method and its clustering process or how to use frequency-dependent admittance boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00005v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.enganabound.2024.01.008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eng Anal Bound Elem 161 (2024) 157-178</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang Kreuzer, Katharina Pollack, Fabian Brinkmann, Piotr Majdak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Fourier Diffraction Theorem and Filtered Backpropagation for Tomographic Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01793v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper concerns diffraction-tomographic reconstruction of an object characterized by its scattering potential. We establish a rigorous generalization of the Fourier diffraction theorem in arbitrary dimension, giving a precise relation in the Fourier domain between measurements of the scattered wave and reconstructions of the scattering potential. With this theorem at hand, Fourier coverages for different experimental setups are investigated taking into account parameters such as object orientation, direction of incidence and frequency of illumination. Allowing for simultaneous and discontinuous variation of these parameters, a general filtered backpropagation formula is derived resulting in an explicit approximation of the scattering potential for a large class of experimental setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01793v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Kirisits, Michael Quellmalz, Eric Setterqvist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Interpolation-Based Method for Solving the One-Dimensional Wave Equation on a Domain with a Moving Boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16483v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of solving the one-dimensional wave equation on a domain with moving boundary. In J. Math. Phys. 11, 2679 (1970), Moore introduced an interesting method to do so. As only in rare cases, a closed analytical solution is possible, one must turn to perturbative expansions of Moore's method. We investigate the then made minimal assumption for convergence of the perturbation series, namely that the boundary position should be an analytic function of time. Though, we prove here that the latter requirement is not a sufficient condition for Moore's method to converge. We then introduce a novel numerical approach based on interpolation which also works for fast boundary dynamics. In comparison with other state-of-the-art numerical methods, our method offers greater speed if the wave solution needs to be evaluated at many points in time or space, whilst preserving accuracy. We discuss two variants of our method, either based on a conformal coordinate transformation or on the method of characteristics, together with interpolation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16483v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michiel Lassuyt, Emma Vancayseele, Wouter Deleersnyder, David Dudal, Sebbe Stouten, Koen Van Den Abeele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bound preserving Point-Average-Moment PolynomiAl-interpreted (PAMPA) scheme: one-dimensional case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14292v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a bound-preserving (BP) Point-Average-Moment PolynomiAl-interpreted (PAMPA) scheme by blending third-order and first-order constructions. The originality of the present construction is that it does not need any explicit reconstruction within each element, and therefore the construction is very flexible. The scheme employs a classical blending approach between a first-order BP scheme and a high-order scheme that does not inherently preserve bounds. The proposed BP PAMPA scheme demonstrates effectiveness across a range of problems, from scalar cases to systems such as the Euler equations of gas dynamics. We derive optimal blending parameters for both scalar and system cases, with the latter based on the recent geometric quasi-linearization (GQL) framework of [Wu \&amp; Shu, {\em SIAM Review}, 65 (2023), pp. 1031--1073]. This yields explicit, optimal blending coefficients that ensure positivity and control spurious oscillations in both point values and cell averages. This framework incorporates a convex blending of fluxes and residuals from both high-order and first-order updates, facilitating a rigorous BP property analysis. Sufficient conditions for the BP property are established, ensuring robustness while preserving high-order accuracy. Numerical tests confirm the effectiveness of the BP PAMPA scheme on several challenging problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14292v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'emi Abgrall, Miaosen Jiao, Yongle Liu, Kailiang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Solution of linear drift-diffusion and pure drift equations on one-dimensional graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20931v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose numerical schemes for the approximate solution of problems defined on the edges of a one-dimensional graph. In particular, we consider linear transport and a drift-diffusion equations, and discretize them by extending Finite Volume schemes with upwind flux to domains presenting bifurcation nodes with an arbitrary number of incoming and outgoing edges, and implicit time discretization. We show that the discrete problems admit positive unique solutions, and we test the methods on the intricate geometry of an electrical treeing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20931v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatrice Crippa, Anna Scotti, Andrea Villa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GoRINNs: Godunov-Riemann Informed Neural Networks for Learning Hyperbolic Conservation Laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22193v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present GoRINNs: numerical analysis-informed neural networks for the solution of inverse problems of non-linear systems of conservation laws. GoRINNs are based on high-resolution Godunov schemes for the solution of the Riemann problem in hyperbolic Partial Differential Equations (PDEs). In contrast to other existing machine learning methods that learn the numerical fluxes of conservative Finite Volume methods, GoRINNs learn the physical flux function per se. Due to their structure, GoRINNs provide interpretable, conservative schemes, that learn the solution operator on the basis of approximate Riemann solvers that satisfy the Rankine-Hugoniot condition. The performance of GoRINNs is assessed via four benchmark problems, namely the Burgers', the Shallow Water, the Lighthill-Whitham-Richards and the Payne-Whitham traffic flow models. The solution profiles of these PDEs exhibit shock waves, rarefactions and/or contact discontinuities at finite times. We demonstrate that GoRINNs provide a very high accuracy both in the smooth and discontinuous regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22193v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios G. Patsatzis, Mario di Bernardo, Lucia Russo, Constantinos Siettos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toroidal density-equalizing map for genus-one surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16833v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Density-equalizing map is a shape deformation technique originally developed for cartogram creation and sociological data visualization on planar geographical maps. In recent years, there has been an increasing interest in developing density-equalizing mapping methods for surface and volumetric domains and applying them to various problems in geometry processing and imaging science. However, the existing surface density-equalizing mapping methods are only applicable to surfaces with relatively simple topologies but not surfaces with topological holes. In this work, we develop a novel algorithm for computing density-equalizing maps for toroidal surfaces. In particular, different shape deformation effects can be easily achieved by prescribing different population functions on the torus and performing diffusion-based deformations on a planar domain with periodic boundary conditions. Furthermore, the proposed toroidal density-equalizing mapping method naturally leads to an effective method for computing toroidal parameterizations of genus-one surfaces with controllable shape changes, with the toroidal area-preserving parameterization being a prime example. Experimental results are presented to demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16833v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunyu Yao, Gary P. T. Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplitude Expansion Phase Field Crystal (APFC) Modeling based Efficient Dislocation Simulations using Fourier Pseudospectral Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22720v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Crystalline defects play a critical role in determining the properties of crystalline solids, underscoring the need for accurate computational methods to study them. Lattice deformation in dislocation simulations, which involves changes in atomic positions, can be described either microscopically by specific atomic configurations or macroscopically by continuum elasticity, each with inherent limitations. The complex amplitude expansion of the phase field crystal (APFC) model provides a mesoscopic approach that bridges these scales. In this paper, we introduce a Fourier pseudospectral method for efficiently solving the APFC model in the context of crystalline defect simulations. This study marks the first application of the Fourier pseudospectral method to the APFC model. The method fully exploits the system's periodicity and facilitates the implementation of periodic boundary conditions, thanks to its high accuracy and computational efficiency. Numerical experiments conducted on two-dimensional triangular lattices and three-dimensional body-centered cubic lattices for edge dislocation geometry optimization have produced strain field images that align well with by continuum elasticity predictions. The findings demonstrate the potential of the APFC model to accurately capture the complex strain fields associated with dislocations at the mesoscopic scales, a key step toward modeling more intricate crystalline defect structures and dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22720v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyi Wei, Yangshuai Wang, Kai Jiang, Lei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
