<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA</link>
    <description>cs.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 04:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A mesh-free, derivative-free, matrix-free, and highly parallel localized stochastic method for high-dimensional semilinear parabolic PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02635v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a mesh-free, derivative-free, matrix-free, and highly parallel localized stochastic method for high-dimensional semilinear parabolic PDEs. The efficiency of the proposed method is built upon four essential components: (i) a martingale formulation of the forward backward stochastic differential equation (FBSDE); (ii) a small scale stochastic particle method for local linear regression (LLR); (iii) a decoupling strategy with a matrix-free solver for the weighted least-squares system used to compute $\nabla u$; (iv) a Newton iteration for solving the univariate nonlinear system in $u$. Unlike traditional deterministic methods that rely on global information, this localized computational scheme not only provides explicit pointwise evaluations of $u$ and $\nabla u$ but, more importantly, is naturally suited for parallelization across particles. In addition, the algorithm avoids the need for spatial meshes and global basis functions required by classical deterministic approaches, as well as the derivative-dependent and lengthy training procedures often encountered in machine learning. More importantly, we rigorously analyze the error bound of the proposed scheme, which is fully explicit in both the particle number $M$ and the time step size $\Delta t$. Numerical results conducted for problem dimensions ranging from $d=100$ to $d=10000$ consistently verify the efficiency and accuracy of the proposed method. Remarkably, all computations are carried out efficiently on a standard personal computer, without requiring any specialized hardware. These results confirm that the proposed method is built upon a principled design that not only extends the practical solvability frontier of ultra-high-dimensional PDEs but also maintains rigorous error control and ease of implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02635v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuixin Fang, Changtao Sheng, Bihao Su, Tao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconditionally positivity-preserving explicit order-one strong approximations of financial SDEs with non-Lipschitz coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we are interested in positivity-preserving approximations of stochastic differential equations (SDEs) with non-Lipschitz coefficients, arising from computational finance and possessing positive solutions. By leveraging a Lamperti transformation, we develop a novel, explicit, and unconditionally positivity-preserving numerical scheme for the considered financial SDEs. More precisely, an implicit term $c_{-1}Y_{n+1}^{-1}$ is incorporated in the scheme to guarantee unconditional positivity preservation, and a corrective operator is introduced in the remaining explicit terms to address the challenges posed by non-Lipschitz (possibly singular) coefficients of the transformed SDEs. By finding a unique positive root of a quadratic equation, the proposed scheme can be explicitly solved and is shown to be strongly convergent with order $1$, when used to numerically solve several well-known financial models such as the CIR process, the Heston-3/2 volatility model, the CEV process and the A\"it-Sahalia model. Numerical experiments validate the theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02703v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaojuan Wu, Ruishu Liu, Jiaohao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linearizing a nonlinear eigenvalue problem with quadratic rational eigenvector nonlinearities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonlinear eigenvalue problems with eigenvector nonlinearities (NEPv) are algebraic eigenvalue problems whose matrix depends on the eigenvector. Applications range from computational quantum mechanics to machine learning. Due to its nonlinear behavior, existing methods almost exclusively rely on fixed-point iterations, the global convergence properties of which are only understood in specific cases. Recently, a certain class of NEPv with linear rational eigenvector nonlinearities has been linearized, i.e., the spectrum of the linear eigenvalue problem contains the eigenvalues of the NEPv. This linear problem is solved using structure exploiting algorithms to improve both convergence and reliability. We propose a linearization for a different class of NEPv with quadratic rational nonlinearities, inspired by the discretized Gross-Pitaevskii equation. The eigenvalues of this NEPv form a subset of the spectrum of a linear multiparameter eigenvalue problem which is equivalent to a system of generalized eigenvalue problems expressed in terms of operator determinants. A structure exploiting Arnoldi algorithm is used to filter a large portion of spurious solutions and to accelerate convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02900v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Janssens, Karl Meerbergen, Wim Michiels</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationarity preserving nodal Finite Element methods for multi-dimensional linear hyperbolic balance laws via a Global Flux quadrature formulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider linear, hyperbolic systems of balance laws in several space dimensions. They possess non-trivial steady states, which result from the equilibrium between derivatives of the unknowns in different directions, and the sources. Standard numerical methods fail to account for this equilibrium, and include stabilization that destroys it. This manifests itself in a diffusion of states that are sup- posed to remain stationary. We derive new stabilized high-order Finite Element methods based on a Global Flux quadrature: we reformulate the entire spatial operator as a mixed derivative of a single quantity, referred to as global flux. All spatial derivatives and the sources are thus treated simultaneously, and our methods are stationarity preserving. Additionally, when this formulation is combined with interpolation on Gauss-Lobatto nodes, the new methods are super-convergent at steady state. Formal consistency estimates, and strategies to construct well-prepared initial data are provided. The numerical results confirm the theoretical predictions, and show the tremendous benefits of the new formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02928v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wasilij Barsukow, Mario Ricchiuto, Davide Torlo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-relaxation structure-preserving explicit low-regularity integrators for the nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose and rigorously analyze a novel family of explicit low-regularity exponential integrators for the nonlinear Schr\"odinger (NLS) equation, based on a time-relaxation framework. The methods combine a resonance-based scheme for the twisted variable with a dynamically adjusted relaxation parameter that guarantees exact mass conservation. Unlike existing symmetric or structure-preserving low-regularity integrators, which are typically implicit and computationally expensive, the proposed methods are fully explicit, mass-conserving, and well-suited for solutions with low regularity. Furthermore, the schemes can be naturally extended to a broad class of evolution equations exhibiting the structure of strongly continuous contraction semigroups. Numerical results demonstrate the accuracy, robustness, and excellent long-time behavior of the methods under low-regularity conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02963v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hang Li, Xicui Li, Katharina Schratz, Bin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Market-Based Data Subset Selection -- Principled Aggregation of Multi-Criteria Example Utility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02456v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Selecting a small yet useful subset of training data is hard because signals of example utility (uncertainty, rarity, diversity, etc.) are heterogeneous and typically combined with ad hoc weights. We propose a market-based selector that prices each example via a cost-function prediction market (LMSR), signals act as traders, a single liquidity parameter controls concentration, and topic-wise normalization stabilizes calibration. Token budgets are handled explicitly by a price-per-token rule $\rho=p/\ell^{\gamma}$, with $\gamma$ exposing an interpretable length bias; a lightweight diversity head improves coverage. We quantify coverage via topic cluster coverage and effective sample size. On the theory side, we show that LMSR implements a maximum-entropy aggregation with exponential weighting and a convex objective, yielding transparent knobs for aggregation strength. Empirically, on GSM8K (60k-token budget) the market with diversity achieves parity with strong single-signal baselines while reducing seed variance and incurring $&lt;\!0.1$ GPU-hr selection overhead; on AGNews at kept=5-25\% the market (with light balancing) delivers competitive accuracy with improved balance and stability. The framework unifies multi-signal data curation under fixed compute for prompt-level reasoning and classification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02456v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashish Jha, Valentin Leplat, AH Phan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive randomized pivoting and volume sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02513v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Adaptive randomized pivoting (ARP) is a recently proposed and highly effective algorithm for column subset selection. This paper reinterprets the ARP algorithm by drawing connections to the volume sampling distribution and active learning algorithms for linear regression. As consequences, this paper presents new analysis for the ARP algorithm and faster implementations using rejection sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02513v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan N. Epperly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Even Faster Kernel Matrix Linear Algebra via Density Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02540v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the use of kernel density estimation (KDE) for linear algebraic tasks involving the kernel matrix of a collection of $n$ data points in $\mathbb R^d$. In particular, we improve upon existing algorithms for computing the following up to $(1+\varepsilon)$ relative error: matrix-vector products, matrix-matrix products, the spectral norm, and sum of all entries. The runtimes of our algorithms depend on the dimension $d$, the number of points $n$, and the target error $\varepsilon$. Importantly, the dependence on $n$ in each case is far lower when accessing the kernel matrix through KDE queries as opposed to reading individual entries.
  Our improvements over existing best algorithms (particularly those of Backurs, Indyk, Musco, and Wagner '21) for these tasks reduce the polynomial dependence on $\varepsilon$, and additionally decreases the dependence on $n$ in the case of computing the sum of all entries of the kernel matrix.
  We complement our upper bounds with several lower bounds for related problems, which provide (conditional) quadratic time hardness results and additionally hint at the limits of KDE based approaches for the problems we study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02540v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rikhav Shah, Sandeep Silwal, Haike Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of Extended Lubrication Theories for Stokes Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02595v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Lubrication theory leverages the assumption of a long and thin fluid domain to formulate a linearized approximation to the Navier-Stokes equations. Models in extended lubrication theory consider relaxations of the thin film assumption, leading to the inclusion of higher order terms. However, such models are sensitive to large surface gradients which lead the assumptions of the model to break down. In this paper, we present a formulation of extended lubrication theory, and compare our models with several existing models, along with the numerical solution to the Stokes equations. The error in pressure and velocity is characterized for a variety of fluid domain geometries. Our results indicate that the new solution is suitable for a wide range of geometries. Nonetheless, the magnitude of surface variation and the length scale ratio are both important factors influencing the accuracy of the extended lubrication theory models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02595v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah Dennis, Thomas G. Fai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ohta-Kawasaki Model Reveals Patterns on Multicomponent Vesicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02688v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new mechanochemical modeling framework to explore the shape deformation and pattern formation in multicomponent vesicle membranes. In this framework, the shape of the membrane is described by an elastic bending model, while phase separation of membrane-bound activator proteins is determined by an Ohta-Kawasaki (OK) model. The coupled dynamics consist of an overdamped force-balanced equation for the membrane geometry and an OK-type advection-reaction-diffusion equation on the deformable membrane. We implement efficient spectral methods to simulate these dynamics in both two- and three-dimensions. Numerical experiments show that the model successfully reproduces a wide range of experimentally observed membrane morphologies \cite{baumgart2003imaging}. Taken together, the framework unifies curvature mechanics, microphase separation, and active forcing, providing new insight into membrane-bounded multicomponent vesicle dynamics and a practical platform for studying multicomponent biomembrane morphology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02688v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wangbo Luo, Zhonghua Qiao, Yanxiang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Burgers equation with a twist: A study on rotational-form equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02761v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new three-dimensional (3D) equation is proposed, which is formed like Burgers' equation by starting with the 3D incompressible Navier-Stokes equations (NSE) and eliminating the pressure and the divergence-free constraint, but instead the Bernoulli pressure is eliminated, leaving only the rotational form of the nonlinearity. This results in a globally well-posed 3D equation which has exactly the same energy balance as the 3D NSE. Moreover, we show in simulations that the system seems to exhibit chaotic dynamics. In the viscous case, we prove the global existence, uniqueness, and higher-order regularity of solutions to this equation with no restriction on the initial data other than smoothness. In the inviscid case, local existence holds, but we give an example of a class of solutions with smooth initial data that develop a singularity in finite time in both 2D and 3D. Moreover, a new numerical algorithm is presented in the 2D case, and simulations are included to illustrate the dynamics. In addition, a rotational-form modification for the 2D Kuramoto-Sivashinsky equations (KSE) is proposed, and global well-posedness is also established. We also discuss several related ``rotational form'' equations, and some pedagogical considerations. Global well-posedness for the original 3D NSE and 2D KSE remains a challenging open problem, but it is hoped that by focusing on the rotational term, new insight may be gained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02761v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Larios</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Bed Occupancy Planning in Intensive Care Units Using $M_t/G_t/\infty$ Queueing Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hospitals struggle to make effective long-term capacity planning decisions for intensive care units (ICUs) under uncertainty in future demand. Admission rates fluctuate over time due to temporal factors, and length of stay (LOS) distributions vary with patient heterogeneity, hospital location, case mix, and clinical practices. Common planning approaches rely on steady-state queueing models or heuristic rules that assume fixed parameters, but these methods often fall short in capturing real-world occupancy dynamics. One widely used example is the 85\% occupancy rule, which recommends maintaining average utilization below this level to ensure responsiveness; however, this rule is based on stationary assumptions and may be unreliable when applied to time-varying systems. Our analysis shows that even when long-run utilization targets are met, day-to-day occupancy frequently exceeds 100\% capacity.
  We propose a data-driven framework for estimating ICU bed occupancy using an $M_t/G_t/\infty$ queueing model, which incorporates time-varying arrival rates and empirically estimated LOS distributions. The framework combines statistical decomposition and parametric distribution fitting to capture temporal patterns in ICU admissions and LOS. We apply it to multi-year data from neonatal ICUs (NICUs) in Calgary as a case study. Several capacity planning scenarios are evaluated, including average-based thresholds and surge estimates from Poisson overflow approximations. Results demonstrate the inadequacy of static heuristics in environments with fluctuating demand and highlight the importance of modeling LOS variability when estimating bed needs. Although the case study focuses on NICUs, the methodology generalizes to other ICU settings and provides interpretable, data-informed support for healthcare systems facing rising demand and limited capacity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02852v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Akbari-Moghaddam, Douglas G. Down, Na Li, Catherine Eastwood, Ayman Abou Mehrem, Alexandra Howlett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hardware Accelerator for the Goemans-Williamson Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02863v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The combinatorial problem Max-Cut has become a benchmark in the evaluation of local search heuristics for both quantum and classical optimisers. In contrast to local search, which only provides average-case performance guarantees, the convex semidefinite relaxation of Max-Cut by Goemans and Williamson, provides worst-case guarantees and is therefore suited to both the construction of benchmarks and in applications to performance-critic scenarios.
  We show how extended floating point precision can be incorporated in algebraic subroutines in convex optimisation, namely in indirect matrix inversion methods like Conjugate Gradient, which are used in Interior Point Methods in the case of very large problem sizes. Also, an estimate is provided of the expected acceleration of the time to solution for a hardware architecture that runs natively on extended precision. Specifically, when using indirect matrix inversion methods like Conjugate Gradient, which have lower complexity than direct methods and are therefore used in very large problems, we see that increasing the internal working precision reduces the time to solution by a factor that increases with the system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02863v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. A. Herrera-Mart\'i, E. Guthmuller, J. Fereyre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error analysis of DGTD for linear Maxwell equations with inhomogeneous interface conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01398v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present paper we consider linear and isotropic Maxwell equations with inhomogeneous interface conditions. We discretize the problem with the discontinuous Galerkin method in space and with the leapfrog scheme in time. An analytical setting is provided in which we show wellposedness of the problem, derive stability estimates, and exploit this in the error analysis to prove rigorous error bounds for both the spatial and full discretization. The theoretical findings are confirmed with numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01398v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin D\"orich, Julian D\"orner, Marlis Hochbruck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Analysis of IMEX-RK Methods for ES-BGK Model at Navier-Stokes level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09504v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Implicit-explicit Runge-Kutta (IMEX-RK) time discretization methods are very popular when solving stiff kinetic equations. In [21], an asymptotic analysis shows that a specific class of high-order IMEX-RK schemes can accurately capture the Navier-Stokes limit without needing to resolve the small scales dictated by the Knudsen number. In this work, we extend the asymptotic analysis to general IMEX-RK schemes, known in literature as Type I and Type II. We further suggest some IMEX-RK methods developed in the literature to attain uniform accuracy in the wide range of Knudsen numbers. Several numerical examples are presented to verify the validity of the obtained theoretical results and the effectiveness of the methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09504v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Boscarino, Seung Yeon Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local L2-bounded commuting projections using discrete local problems on Alfeld splits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03601v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct projections onto the classical finite element spaces based on Lagrange, N\'ed\'elec, Raviart-Thomas, and discontinuous elements on shape-regular simplicial meshes. Our projections are defined locally, are bounded in the L2-norm, and commute with the corresponding differential operators. Such projections are a fundamental tool in finite element stability and error analysis. Moreover, to the best of our knowledge, the present construction is the first in the literature where local $L^2$-stability is fully established. The cornerstone of our construction are local weight functions which are piecewise polynomials built using the Alfeld split of local patches from the original simplicial mesh. This way, the L2-stability of the projections is established by invoking discrete Poincar\'e inequalities on these local stars, for which we provide here an original, constructive proof. Another important novelty is that we extend the construction of the projections so as to preserve homogeneous boundary conditions on a subset of the domain boundary. Altogether, the material is presented using the language of vector calculus, and links to the formalism of finite element exterior calculus are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03601v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Ern, Johnny Guzman, Pratyush Potu, Martin Vohralik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal error estimates of the diffuse domain method for parabolic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02226v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the convergence behavior of the diffuse domain method (DDM) for solving a class of second-order parabolic partial differential equations with Neumann boundary condition posed on general irregular domains. The DDM employs a phase-field function to extend the original parabolic problem to a similar but slightly modified problem defined over a larger rectangular domain that contains the target physical domain. Based on the weighted Sobolev spaces, we rigorously establish the convergence of the diffuse domain solution to the original solution as the interface thickness parameter goes to zero, together with the corresponding optimal error estimates under the weighted $L^2$ and $H^1$ norms. Numerical experiments are also presented to validate the theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02226v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenrui Hao, Lili Ju, Yuejin Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elasto-acoustic wave propagation in geophysical media using hybrid high-order methods on general meshes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15771v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hybrid high-order (HHO) methods are numerical methods characterized by several interesting properties such as local conservativity, geometric flexibility and high-order accuracy. Here, HHO schemes are studied for the space semi-discretization of coupled elasto-acoustic waves in the time domain using a first-order formulation. Explicit and singly diagonal implicit Runge--Kutta (ERK &amp; SDIRK) schemes are used for the time discretization. We show that an efficient implementation of explicit (resp. implicit) time schemes calls for a static condensation of the face (resp. cell) unknowns. Crucially, both static condensation procedures only involve block-diagonal matrices. Then, we provide numerical estimates for the CFL stability limit of ERK schemes and present a comparative study on the efficiency of explicit versus implicit schemes. Our findings indicate that implicit time schemes remain competitive in many situations. Finally, simulations in a 2D realistic geophysical configuration are performed, illustrating the geometrical flexibility of the HHO method: both hybrid (triangular and quadrilateral) and nonconforming (with hanging nodes) meshes are easily handled, delivering results of comparable accuracy to a reference spectral element software based on tensorized elements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15771v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romain Mottier, Alexandre Ern, Laurent Guillot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moment-enhanced shallow water equations for non-slip boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14785v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The shallow water equations often assume a constant velocity profile along the vertical axis. However, this assumption does not hold in many practical applications. To better approximate the vertical velocity distribution, models such as the shallow water moment expansion models have been proposed. Nevertheless, under non-slip bottom boundary conditions, both the standard shallow water equation and its moment-enhanced models struggle to accurately capture the vertical velocity profile due to the stiff source terms. In this work, we propose modified shallow water equations and corresponding moment-enhanced models that perform well under both non-slip and slip boundary conditions. The primary difference between the modified and original models lies in the treatment of the source term, which allows our modified moment expansion models to be readily generalized, while maintaining compatibility with our previous analysis on the hyperbolicity of the model. To assess the performance of both the standard and modified moment expansion models, we conduct a comprehensive numerical comparison with the incompressible Navier--Stokes equations -- a comparison that is absent from existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14785v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiping Zhou, Juntao Huang, Andrew J. Christlieb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp numerical approximation of the Hardy constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19422v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the $P_1$ finite element approximation of the best constant in the classical Hardy inequality over bounded domains containing the origin in $\mathbb{R}^N$, for $N \geq 3$.
  Despite the fact that this constant is not attained in the associated Sobolev space $H^1$, our main result establishes an explicit, sharp, and dimension-independent rate of convergence proportional to $1/|\log h|^2$.
  The analysis carefully combines an improved Hardy inequality involving a reminder term with logarithmic weights, approximation estimates for Hardy-type singular radial functions constituting minimizing sequences, properties of piecewise linear and continuous finite elements, and weighted Sobolev space techniques.
  We also consider other closely related spectral problems involving the Laplacian with singular quadratic potentials obtaining sharp convergence rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19422v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liviu I. Ignat, Enrique Zuazua</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An energy-stable parametric finite element method for the Willmore flow in three dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21025v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work develops novel energy-stable parametric finite element methods (ES-PFEM) for the Willmore flow and curvature-dependent geometric gradient flows of surfaces in three dimensions. The key to achieving the energy stability lies in the use of two novel geometric identities: (i) a reformulated variational form of the normal velocity field, and (ii) incorporation of the temporal evolution of the mean curvature into the governing equations. These identities enable the derivation of a new variational formulation. By using the parametric finite element method, an implicit fully discrete scheme is subsequently developed, which maintains the energy dissipative property at the fully discrete level. Based on the ES-PFEM, comprehensive insights into the design of ES-PFEM for general curvature-dependent geometric gradient flows and a new understanding of mesh quality improvement in PFEM are provided. In particular, we develop the first PFEM for the Gauss curvature flow of surfaces. Furthermore, a tangential velocity control methodology is applied to improve the mesh quality and enhance the robustness of the proposed numerical method. Extensive numerical experiments confirm that the proposed method preserves energy dissipation properties and maintain good mesh quality in the surface evolution under the Willmore flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21025v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weizhu Bao, Yifei Li, Dongmin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical modeling and sensitivity analysis of hypoxia-activated drugs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15642v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hypoxia-activated prodrugs offer a promising strategy for targeting oxygen-deficient regions in solid tumors, which are often resistant to conventional therapies. However, modeling their behavior is challenging because of the complex interplay between oxygen availability, drug activation, and cell survival. In this work, we develop a multiscale and mixed-dimensional model that couples spatially resolved drug and oxygen transport with pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics to simulate the cellular response. The model integrates blood flow, oxygen diffusion and consumption, drug delivery, and metabolism. To reduce computational cost, we mitigate the global nonlinearity through a one-way coupling of the multiscale and mixed/dimensional models with a reduced 0D model for the drug metabolism. The global sensitivity analysis is then used to identify key parameters influencing drug activation and therapeutic outcome. This approach enables efficient simulation and supports the design of optimized hypoxia-targeted therapies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15642v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Coclite, Riccardo Montanelli Eccher, Luca Possenti, Piermario Vitullo, Paolo Zunino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transmission Conditions for the Non-Overlapping Schwarz Coupling of Full Order and Operator Inference Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12228v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work investigates transmission conditions for the domain decomposition-based coupling of subdomain-local models using the non-overlapping Schwarz alternating method (NO-SAM). Building on prior efforts involving overlapping SAM (O-SAM), we formulate and assess two NO-SAM variants, based on alternating Dirichlet-Neumann and Robin-Robin transmission conditions. For the subdomain-local models, we consider a mix of full order models (FOMs) and non-intrusive reduced order models (ROMs) constructed via an emerging model reduction technique known as operator inference (OpInf). Of particular novelty is the first application of NO-SAM to couple non-intrusive OpInf ROMs with each other, and with FOMs. Numerical studies on a one-dimensional linear elastic wave propagation benchmark problem demonstrate that transmission condition choice and parameter tuning significantly impact convergence rate, accuracy, and stability. Robin-Robin coupling often yields faster convergence than alternating Dirichlet-Neumann, though improper parameter selection can induce spurious oscillations at subdomain interfaces. For FOM-OpInf and OpInf-OpInf couplings, sufficient modal content in the ROM basis improves accuracy and mitigates instability, in some cases outperforming the coupled FOM-FOM reference solutions in both accuracy and efficiency. These findings highlight NO-SAM's potential for enabling flexible, non-intrusive, and efficient multi-model coupling across independently meshed subdomains, while emphasizing the need for careful interface condition design in higher-dimensional and predictive settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12228v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cameron Rodriguez, Irina Tezaur, Alejandro Mota, Anthony Gruber, Eric Parish, Christopher Wentland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential quantum advantages for practical non-Hermitian eigenproblems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12091v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Non-Hermitian physics has emerged as a rich field of study, with applications ranging from $PT$-symmetry breaking and skin effects to non-Hermitian topological phase transitions. Yet most studies remain restricted to small-scale or classically tractable systems. While quantum computing has shown strong performance in Hermitian eigenproblems, its extension to the non-Hermitian regime remains largely unexplored. Here, we develop a quantum algorithm to address general non-Hermitian eigenvalue problems, specifically targeting eigenvalues near a given line in the complex plane -- thereby generalizing previous results on ground state energy and spectral gap estimation for Hermitian matrices. Our method combines a fuzzy quantum eigenvalue detector with a divide-and-conquer strategy to efficiently isolate relevant eigenvalues. This yields a provable exponential quantum speedup for non-Hermitian eigenproblems. Furthermore, we discuss the broad applications in detecting spontaneous $PT$-symmetry breaking, estimating Liouvillian gaps, and analyzing classical Markov processes. These results highlight the potential of quantum algorithms in tackling challenging problems across quantum physics and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12091v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3n8f-k8pl</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 140601 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Ming Zhang, Yukun Zhang, Wenhao He, Xiao Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wasserstein Bounds for generative diffusion models with Gaussian tail targets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11251v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an estimate of the Wasserstein distance between the data distribution and the generation of score-based generative models. The sampling complexity with respect to dimension is $\mathcal{O}(\sqrt{d})$, with a logarithmic constant. In the analysis, we assume a Gaussian-type tail behavior of the data distribution and an $\epsilon$-accurate approximation of the score. Such a Gaussian tail assumption is general, as it accommodates a practical target - the distribution from early stopping techniques with bounded support.
  The crux of the analysis lies in the global Lipschitz bound of the score, which is shown from the Gaussian tail assumption by a dimension-independent estimate of the heat kernel. Consequently, our complexity bound scales linearly (up to a logarithmic constant) with the square root of the trace of the covariance operator, which relates to the invariant distribution of the forward process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11251v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xixian Wang, Zhongjian Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SUperman: Efficient Permanent Computation on GPUs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16577v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The permanent is a function, defined for a square matrix, with applications in various domains including quantum computing, statistical physics, complexity theory, combinatorics, and graph theory. Its formula is similar to that of the determinant; however, unlike the determinant, its exact computation is #P-complete, i.e., there is no algorithm to compute the permanent in polynomial time unless P=NP. For an $n \times n$ matrix, the fastest algorithm has a time complexity of $O(2^{n-1}n)$. Although supercomputers have been employed for permanent computation before, there is no work and, more importantly, no publicly available software that leverages cutting-edge High-Performance Computing accelerators such as GPUs. In this work, we design, develop, and investigate the performance of SUperman, a complete software suite that can compute matrix permanents on multiple nodes/GPUs on a cluster while handling various matrix types, e.g., real/complex/binary and sparse/dense, etc., with a unique treatment for each type. SUperman run on a single Nvidia A100 GPU is up to $86\times$ faster than a state-of-the-art parallel algorithm on 44 Intel Xeon cores running at 2.10GHz. Leveraging 192 GPUs, SUperman computes the permanent of a $62 \times 62$ matrix in 1.63 days, marking the largest reported permanent computation to date.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16577v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deniz Elbek, Fatih Ta\c{s}yaran, Bora U\c{c}ar, Kamer Kaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global approximations to the error function of real argument for vectorized computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05068v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The error function of real argument can be uniformly approximated to a given accuracy by a single closed-form expression for the whole variable range either in terms of addition, multiplication, division, and square root operations only, or also using the exponential function. The coefficients have been tabulated for up to 128-bit precision. Tests of a computer code implementation using the standard single- and double-precision floating-point arithmetic show good performance and vectorizability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05068v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitri N. Laikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A polytopal discrete de Rham scheme for the exterior calculus Einstein's equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00286v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, based on the $3+1$ decomposition in [24, 33], we present a fully exterior calculus breakdown of spacetime and Einstein's equations. Links to the orthonormal frame approach [38] are drawn to help understand the variables in this context. Two formulations are derived, discretised and tested using the exterior calculus discrete de Rham complex [13], and some discrete quantities are shown to be conserved in one of the cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00286v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6t8n-rlld</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Todd A. Oliynyk, Jia Jia Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence rates for regularized unbalanced optimal transport: the discrete case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07917v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Unbalanced optimal transport (UOT) is a natural extension of optimal transport (OT) allowing comparison between measures of different masses. It arises naturally in machine learning by offering a robustness against outliers. The aim of this work is to provide convergence rates of the regularized transport cost and plans towards their original solution when both measures are weighted sums of Dirac masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07917v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Nenna, Paul Pegon, Louis Tocquec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed-Precision Performance Portability of FFT-Based GPU-Accelerated Algorithms for Block-Triangular Toeplitz Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10202v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The hardware diversity in leadership-class computing facilities, alongside the immense performance boosts from today's GPUs when computing in lower precision, incentivizes scientific HPC workflows to adopt mixed-precision algorithms and performance portability models. We present an on-the-fly framework using hipify for performance portability and apply it to FFTMatvec - an HPC application that computes matrix-vector products with block-triangular Toeplitz matrices. Our approach enables FFTMatvec, initially a CUDA-only application, to run seamlessly on AMD GPUs with excellent performance. Performance optimizations for AMD GPUs are integrated into the open-source rocBLAS library, keeping the application code unchanged. We then present a dynamic mixed-precision framework for FFTMatvec; a Pareto front analysis determines the optimal mixed-precision configuration for a desired error tolerance. Results are shown for AMD Instinct MI250X, MI300X, and the newly launched MI355X GPUs. The performance-portable, mixed-precision FFTMatvec is scaled to 4,096 GPUs on the OLCF Frontier supercomputer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10202v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3731599.3767490</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sreeram Venkat, Kasia Swirydowicz, Noah Wolfe, Omar Ghattas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Algorithm for Representing Positive Semi-Definite Polynomials as Sums of Squares with Rational Coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01568v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel algorithm for constructing a sum-of-squares (SOS) decomposition for positive semi-definite polynomials with rational coefficients. Unlike previous methods that typically yield SOS decompositions with floating-point coefficients, our approach ensures that all coefficients in the decomposition remain rational. This is particularly useful in formal verification and symbolic computation, where exact arithmetic is required. We introduce a stepwise reduction technique that transforms a given polynomial into a sum of ladder-like squares while preserving rationality. Experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of our method compared to existing numerical approaches. This artical is an extension of the following Chinnese paper: HUANG Yong , ZENG Zhenbing , YANG Lu , RAO Yongsheng. An Algorithm to Represent Positive Semi-Definite Polynomials to Sum of Lader-Like Squares of Polynomials with Rational Coefficients (in Chinese). Journal of Systems Science and Mathematical Sciences, 2024, 44(5): 1241-1271 https://doi.org/10.12341/jssms23584CM</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01568v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenbing Zeng, Yong Huang, Lu Yang, Yongsheng Rao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
