<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA</link>
    <description>cs.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 05:03:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An artificial viscosity approach to high order entropy stable discontinuous Galerkin methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entropy stable discontinuous Galerkin (DG) methods improve the robustness of high order DG simulations of nonlinear conservation laws. These methods yield a semi-discrete entropy inequality, and rely on an algebraic flux differencing formulation which involves both summation-by-parts (SBP) discretization matrices and entropy conservative two-point finite volume fluxes. However, explicit expressions for such two-point finite volume fluxes may not be available for all systems, or may be computationally expensive to compute.
  This paper proposes an alternative approach to constructing entropy stable DG methods using an artificial viscosity coefficient based on the local violation of a cell entropy inequality and the local entropy dissipation. The resulting method recovers the same global semi-discrete entropy inequality that is satisfied by entropy stable flux differencing DG methods. The artificial viscosity coefficients are parameter-free and locally computable over each cell, and the resulting artificial viscosity preserves both high order accuracy and a hyperbolic maximum stable time-step size under explicit time-stepping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16529v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient-penalty stabilization of sharp and diffuse interface formulations in unfitted Nitsche finite element methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce an unfitted Nitsche finite element method with a new ghost-penalty stabilization based on local projection of the solution gradient. The proposed ghost-penalty operator is straightforward to implement, ensures algebraic stability, provides an implicit extension of the solution beyond the physical domain, and stabilizes the numerical method for problems dominated by transport phenomena. This paper presents both a sharp interface version of the method and an alternative diffuse interface formulation designed to avoid integration over implicitly defined embedded surfaces. A complete numerical analysis of the sharp interface version is provided. The results of several numerical experiments support the theoretical analysis and illustrate the performance of both variants of the method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16594v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxim Olshanskii, Jan-Phillip B\"acker, Dmitri Kuzmin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A structure-preserving parametric finite element method with optimal energy stability condition for anisotropic surface diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16660v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose and analyze a structure-preserving parametric finite element method (SP-PFEM) for the evolution of closed curves under anisotropic surface diffusion with surface energy density $\hat{\gamma}(\theta)$. Our primary theoretical contribution establishes that the condition $3\hat{\gamma}(\theta)-\hat{\gamma}(\theta-\pi)\geq 0$ is both necessary and sufficient for unconditional energy stability within the framework of local energy estimates. The proposed method introduces a symmetric surface energy matrix $\hat{\boldsymbol{Z}}_k(\theta)$ with a stabilizing function $k(\theta)$, leading to a conservative weak formulation. Its fully discretization via SP-PFEM rigorously preserves the two geometric structures: enclosed area conservation and energy dissipation unconditionally under our energy stability condition. Numerical results are reported to demonstrate the efficiency and accuracy of the proposed method, along with its area conservation and energy dissipation properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16660v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Li, Wenjun Ying, Yulin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier Analysis of Finite Difference Schemes for the Helmholtz Equation: Sharp Estimates and Relative Errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an approach based on Fourier analysis to wavenumber explicit sharp estimation of absolute and relative errors of finite difference methods for the Helmholtz equation. We use the approach to analyze the classical centred scheme for the Helmholtz equation with a general smooth source term and Dirichlet boundary conditions in 1D. For the Fourier interpolants of the discrete solution with homogeneous (or inhomogeneous) Dirichlet conditions, we show rigorously that the worst case attainable convergence order of the absolute error is k2h2 (or k3h2) in the L2-norm and k3h2 (or k4h2) in the H1-semi-norm, and that of the relative error is k3h2 in both L2- and H1-semi-norms. Even though the classical centred scheme is well-known, it is the first time that such sharp estimates of absolute and relative errors are obtained. We show also that the Fourier analysis approach can be used as a convenient visual tool for evaluating finite difference schemes in presence of source terms, which is beyond the scope of dispersion analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16696v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin J. Gander, Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guaranteed upper bounds for iteration errors and modified Kacanov schemes via discrete duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16850v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We apply duality theory to discretized convex minimization problems to obtain computable guaranteed upper bounds for the distance of given discrete functions and the exact discrete minimizer. Furthermore, we show that the discrete duality framework extends convergence results for the Kacanov scheme to a broader class of problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16850v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lars Diening, Johannes Storn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding the nearest $\Omega$-stable pencil with Riemannian optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper considers the problem of finding the nearest $\Omega$-stable pencil to a given square pencil $A+xB \in \mathbb{C}^{n \times n}$, where a pencil is called $\Omega$-stable if it is regular and all of its eigenvalues belong to the closed set $\Omega$. We propose a new method, based on the Schur form of a matrix pair and Riemannian optimization over the manifold $U(n) \times U(n)$, that is, the Cartesian product of the unitary group with itself. While the developed theory holds for any closed set $\Omega$, we focus on two cases that are the most common in applications: Hurwitz stability and Schur stability. For these cases, we develop publicly available efficient implementations. Numerical experiments show that the resulting algorithm outperforms existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16876v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vanni Noferini, Lauri Nyman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybridized Augmented Lagrangian Methods for Contact Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of friction-free contact between two elastic bodies. We develop an augmented Lagrangian method that provides computational convenience by reformulating the contact problem as a nonlinear variational equality. To achieve this, we propose a Nitsche-based method incorporating a hybrid displacement variable defined on an interstitial layer. This approach enables complete decoupling of the contact domains, with interaction occurring exclusively through the interstitial layer. The layer is independently approximated, eliminating the need to handle intersections between unrelated meshes. Additionally, the method supports introducing an independent model on the interface, which we leverage to represent a membrane covering one of the bodies. We present the formulation of the method, establish stability and error estimates, and demonstrate its practical utility through illustrative numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16882v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik Burman, Peter Hansbo, Mats G. Larson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable higher-order nonlinear solvers via higher-order automatic differentiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16895v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper demonstrates new methods and implementations of nonlinear solvers with higher-order of convergence, which is achieved by efficiently computing higher-order derivatives. Instead of computing full derivatives, which could be expensive, we compute directional derivatives with Taylor-mode automatic differentiation. We first implement Householder's method with arbitrary order for one variable, and investigate the trade-off between computational cost and convergence order. We find that the second-order variant, i.e., Halley's method, to be the most valuable, and further generalize Halley's method to systems of nonlinear equations and demonstrate that it can scale efficiently to large-scale problems. We further apply Halley's method on solving large-scale ill-conditioned nonlinear problems, as well as solving nonlinear equations inside stiff ODE solvers, and demonstrate that it could outperform Newton's method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16895v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songchen Tan, Keming Miao, Alan Edelman, Christopher Rackauckas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AT1 fourth-order isogeometric phase-field modeling of brittle fracture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A crucial aspect in phase-field modeling, based on the variational formulation of brittle fracture, is the accurate representation of how the fracture surface energy is dissipated during the fracture process in the energy competition within a minimization problem. In general, the family of AT1 functionals showcases a well-defined elastic limit and narrow transition regions before crack onset, as opposed to AT2 models. On the other hand, high-order functionals provide similar accuracy as low-order ones but allow for larger mesh sizes in their discretization, remarkably reducing the computational cost. In this work, we aim to combine both these advantages and propose a novel AT1 fourth-order phase-field model for brittle fracture within an isogeometric framework, which provides a straightforward discretization of the high-order term in the crack surface density functional. For the introduced AT1 functional, we first prove a {\Gamma}-convergence result (in both the continuum and discretized isogeometric setting) based on a careful study of the optimal transition profile, which ultimately provides the explicit correction factor for the toughness and the exact size of the transition region. Fracture irreversibility is modeled by monotonicity of the damage variable and is conveniently enforced using the Projected Successive Over-Relaxation algorithm. Our numerical results indicate that the proposed fourth-order AT1 model is more accurate than the considered lower-order AT1 and AT2 models; this allows to employ larger mesh sizes, entailing a lower computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16968v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Greco, Eleonora Maggiorelli, Matteo Negri, Alessia Patton, Alessandro Reali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-splitting methods for the cold-plasma model using Finite Element Exterior Calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we propose a high-order structure-preserving discretization of the cold plasma model which describes the propagation of electromagnetic waves in magnetized plasmas. By utilizing B-Splines Finite Elements Exterior Calculus, we derive a space discretization that preserves the underlying Hamiltonian structure of the model, and we study two stable time-splitting geometrical integrators. We approximate an incoming wave boundary condition in such a way that the resulting schemes are compatible with a time-harmonic / transient decomposition of the solution, which allows us to establish their long-time stability. This approach readily applies to curvilinear and complex domains. We perform a numerical study of these schemes which compares their cost and accuracy against a standard Crank-Nicolson time integrator, and we run realistic simulations where the long-term behaviour is assessed using frequency-domain solutions. Our solvers are implemented in the Python library Psydac which makes them memory-efficient, parallel and essentially three-dimensional.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16991v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Moral S\'anchez, Martin Campos Pinto, Yaman G\"u\c{c}l\"u, Omar Maj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Order Boundary Extrapolation Technique for Finite Difference Methods on Complex Domains with Cartesian Meshes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The application of suitable numerical boundary conditions for hyperbolic conservation laws on domains with complex geometry has become a problem with certain difficulty that has been tackled in different ways according to the nature of the numerical methods and mesh type. In this paper we present a technique for the extrapolation of information from the interior of the computational domain to ghost cells designed for structured Cartesian meshes (which, as opposed to non-structured meshes, cannot be adapted to the morphology of the domain boundary). This technique is based on the application of Lagrange interpolation with a filter for the detection of discontinuities that permits a data dependent extrapolation, with higher order at smooth regions and essentially non oscillatory properties near discontinuities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17103v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10915-015-0043-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Baeza, A., Mulet, P. &amp; Zor\'io, D. High Order Boundary Extrapolation Technique for Finite Difference Methods on Complex Domains with Cartesian Meshes. J Sci Comput 66, 761-791 (2016)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Baeza, Pep Mulet, David Zor\'io</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Order Weighted Extrapolation for Boundary Conditions for Finite Difference Methods on Complex Domains with Cartesian Meshes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The design of numerical boundary conditions is a challenging problem that has been tackled in different ways depending on the nature of the problem and the numerical scheme used to solve it. In this paper we present a new weighted extrapolation technique which entails an improvement with respect to the technique that was developed in [1]. This technique is based on the application of a variant of the Lagrange extrapolation through the computation of weights capable of detecting regions with discontinuities. We also present a combination of the above technique with a least squares approach in order to stabilize the scheme in some cases where Lagrange extrapolation can turn the scheme mildly unstable. We show that this combined extrapolation technique can tackle discontinuities more robustly than the procedure introduced in [1].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17106v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10915-016-0188-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Baeza, A., Mulet, P. &amp; Zor\'io, D. High Order Weighted Extrapolation for Boundary Conditions for Finite Difference Methods on Complex Domains with Cartesian Meshes. J Sci Comput 69, 170-200 (2016)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Baeza, Pep Mulet, David Zor\'io</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Approximate Lax-Wendroff-Type Procedure for High Order Accurate Schemes for Hyperbolic Conservation Laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A high order time stepping applied to spatial discretizations provided by the method of lines for hyperbolic conservations laws is presented. This procedure is related to the one proposed in Qiu and Shu (SIAM J Sci Comput 24(6):2185-2198, 2003) for numerically solving hyperbolic conservation laws. Both methods are based on the conversion of time derivatives to spatial derivatives through a Lax-Wendroff-type procedure, also known as Cauchy-Kovalevskaya process. The original approach in Qiu and Shu (2003) uses the exact expressions of the fluxes and their derivatives whereas the new procedure computes suitable finite difference approximations of them ensuring arbitrarily high order accuracy both in space and time as the original technique does, with a much simpler implementation and generically better performance, since only flux evaluations are required and no symbolic computations of flux derivatives are needed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17108v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10915-016-0298-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Zor\'io, D., Baeza, A. &amp; Mulet, P. An Approximate Lax-Wendroff-Type Procedure for High Order Accurate Schemes for Hyperbolic Conservation Laws. J Sci Comput 71, 246-273 (2017)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Zor\'io, Antonio Baeza, Pep Mulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Roughly Forced Nonlinear PDEs via Misspecified Kernel Methods and Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17110v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the use of Gaussian Processes (GPs) or Neural Networks (NNs) to numerically approximate the solutions to nonlinear partial differential equations (PDEs) with rough forcing or source terms, which commonly arise as pathwise solutions to stochastic PDEs. Kernel methods have recently been generalized to solve nonlinear PDEs by approximating their solutions as the maximum a posteriori estimator of GPs that are conditioned to satisfy the PDE at a finite set of collocation points. The convergence and error guarantees of these methods, however, rely on the PDE being defined in a classical sense and its solution possessing sufficient regularity to belong to the associated reproducing kernel Hilbert space. We propose a generalization of these methods to handle roughly forced nonlinear PDEs while preserving convergence guarantees with an oversmoothing GP kernel that is misspecified relative to the true solution's regularity. This is achieved by conditioning a regular GP to satisfy the PDE with a modified source term in a weak sense (when integrated against a finite number of test functions). This is equivalent to replacing the empirical $L^2$-loss on the PDE constraint by an empirical negative-Sobolev norm. We further show that this loss function can be used to extend physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) to stochastic equations, thereby resulting in a new NN-based variant termed Negative Sobolev Norm-PINN (NeS-PINN).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17110v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Darcy, Edoardo Calvello, Ricardo Baptista, Houman Owhadi, Andrew M. Stuart, Xianjin Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Approximation of High-Dimensional Gibbs Distributions Using the Functional Hierarchical Tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The numerical representation of high-dimensional Gibbs distributions is challenging due to the curse of dimensionality manifesting through the intractable normalization constant calculations. This work addresses this challenge by performing a particle-based high-dimensional parametric density estimation subroutine, and the input to the subroutine is Gibbs samples generated by leveraging advanced sampling techniques. Specifically, to generate Gibbs samples, we employ ensemble-based annealed importance sampling, a population-based approach for sampling multimodal distributions. These samples are then processed using functional hierarchical tensor sketching, a tensor-network-based density estimation method for high-dimensional distributions, to obtain the numerical representation of the Gibbs distribution. We successfully apply the proposed approach to complex Ginzburg-Landau models with hundreds of variables. In particular, we show that the approach proposed is successful at addressing the metastability issue under difficult numerical cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17143v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan Sheng, Xun Tang, Haoxuan Chen, Lexing Ying</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Physics-Informed Neural Network with Residuals for Solving Complex Integral Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16370v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present the Residual Integral Solver Network (RISN), a novel neural network architecture designed to solve a wide range of integral and integro-differential equations, including one-dimensional, multi-dimensional, ordinary and partial integro-differential, systems, and fractional types. RISN integrates residual connections with high-accurate numerical methods such as Gaussian quadrature and fractional derivative operational matrices, enabling it to achieve higher accuracy and stability than traditional Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINN). The residual connections help mitigate vanishing gradient issues, allowing RISN to handle deeper networks and more complex kernels, particularly in multi-dimensional problems. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that RISN consistently outperforms PINN, achieving significantly lower Mean Absolute Errors (MAE) across various types of equations. The results highlight RISN's robustness and efficiency in solving challenging integral and integro-differential problems, making it a valuable tool for real-world applications where traditional methods often struggle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16370v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdi Movahedian Moghaddam, Kourosh Parand, Saeed Reza Kheradpisheh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison theorems for the minimum eigenvalue of a random positive-semidefinite matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16578v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper establishes a new comparison principle for the minimum eigenvalue of a sum of independent random positive-semidefinite matrices. The principle states that the minimum eigenvalue of the matrix sum is controlled by the minimum eigenvalue of a Gaussian random matrix that inherits its statistics from the summands. This methodology is powerful because of the vast arsenal of tools for treating Gaussian random matrices. As applications, the paper presents short, conceptual proofs of some old and new results in high-dimensional statistics. It also settles a long-standing open question in computational linear algebra about the injectivity properties of very sparse random matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16578v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joel A. Tropp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic multisymplectic PDEs and their structure-preserving numerical methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct stochastic multisymplectic systems by considering a stochastic extension to the variational formulation of multisymplectic partial differential equations proposed in [Hydon, {\it Proc. R. Soc. A}, 461, 1627--1637, 2005]. The stochastic variational principle implies the existence of stochastic $1$-form and $2$-form conservation laws, as well as conservation laws arising from continuous variational symmetries via a stochastic Noether's theorem. These results are the stochastic analogues of those found in deterministic variational principles. Furthermore, we develop stochastic structure-preserving collocation methods for this class of stochastic multisymplectic systems. These integrators possess a discrete analogue of the stochastic $2$-form conservation law and, in the case of linear systems, also guarantee discrete momentum conservation. The effectiveness of the proposed methods is demonstrated through their application to stochastic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations featuring either stochastic transport or stochastic dispersion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16913v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiao Hu, Linyu Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive multipliers for extrapolation in frequency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17019v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Resolving the details of an object from coarse-scale measurements is a classical problem in applied mathematics. This problem is usually formulated as extrapolating the Fourier transform of the object from a bounded region to the entire space, that is, in terms of performing extrapolation in frequency. This problem is ill-posed unless one assumes that the object has some additional structure. When the object is compactly supported, then it is well-known that its Fourier transform can be extended to the entire space. However, it is also well-known that this problem is severely ill-conditioned.
  In this work, we assume that the object is known to belong to a collection of compactly supported functions and, instead performing extrapolation in frequency to the entire space, we study the problem of extrapolating to a larger bounded set using dilations in frequency and a single Fourier multiplier. This is reminiscent of the refinement equation in multiresolution analysis. Under suitable conditions, we prove the existence of a worst-case optimal multiplier over the entire collection, and we show that all such multipliers share the same canonical structure. When the collection is finite, we show that any worst-case optimal multiplier can be represented in terms of an Hermitian matrix. This allows us to introduce a fixed-point iteration to find the optimal multiplier. This leads us to introduce a family of multipliers, which we call $\Sigma$-multipliers, that can be used to perform extrapolation in frequency. We establish connections between $\Sigma$-multipliers and multiresolution analysis. We conclude with some numerical experiments illustrating the practical consequences of our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17019v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Castelli Lacunza, Carlos A. Sing Long</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of two-timescale gradient descent ascent dynamics: finite-dimensional and mean-field perspectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17122v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The two-timescale gradient descent-ascent (GDA) is a canonical gradient algorithm designed to find Nash equilibria in min-max games. We analyze the two-timescale GDA by investigating the effects of learning rate ratios on convergence behavior in both finite-dimensional and mean-field settings. In particular, for finite-dimensional quadratic min-max games, we obtain long-time convergence in near quasi-static regimes through the hypocoercivity method. For mean-field GDA dynamics, we investigate convergence under a finite-scale ratio using a mixed synchronous-reflection coupling technique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17122v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing An, Jianfeng Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-dimensional approximation spaces of artificial neural networks and applications to partial differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.04326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.04326v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we develop a new machinery to study the capacity of artificial neural networks (ANNs) to approximate high-dimensional functions without suffering from the curse of dimensionality. Specifically, we introduce a concept which we refer to as approximation spaces of artificial neural networks and we present several tools to handle those spaces. Roughly speaking, approximation spaces consist of sequences of functions which can, in a suitable way, be approximated by ANNs without curse of dimensionality in the sense that the number of required ANN parameters to approximate a function of the sequence with an accuracy $\varepsilon &gt; 0$ grows at most polynomially both in the reciprocal $1/\varepsilon$ of the required accuracy and in the dimension $d \in \mathbb{N} = \{1, 2, 3, \ldots \}$ of the function. We show that these approximation spaces are closed under various operations including linear combinations, formations of limits, and infinite compositions. To illustrate the utility of the machinery proposed in this paper, we employ the developed theory to prove that ANNs have the capacity to overcome the curse of dimensionality in the numerical approximation of certain first order transport partial differential equations (PDEs). We even prove that approximation spaces are closed under flows of first order transport PDEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.04326v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierfrancesco Beneventano, Patrick Cheridito, Arnulf Jentzen, Philippe von Wurstemberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using the Newton-Raphson Method with Automatic Differentiation to Numerically Solve Implied Volatility of Stock Option through Binomial Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.09033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.09033v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the paper written by Klibanov et al, it proposes a novel method to calculate implied volatility of a European stock options as a solution to ill-posed inverse problem for the Black-Scholes equation. In addition, it proposes a trading strategy based on the difference between implied volatility of the option and the volatility of the underlying stock. In addition to the Black-Scholes equation, Binomial model is another method used to price European options. And, the implied volatility can be also calculated through this model. In this paper, we apply the Newton-Raphson method together with Automatic Differention to numerically approximate the implied volatility of an arbitrary stock option through this model. We provide an explanation of the mathematical model and methods, the methodology, and the results from our test using the stimulated data from the Geometric Brownian Motion Model and the Binomial Model itself, and the data from the US market data from 2018 to 2021.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.09033v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanchaloem Wunkaew, Yuqing Liu, Kirill V. Golubnichiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable semi-implicit SDC methods for conservation laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19969v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Semi-implicit spectral deferred correction (SDC) methods provide a systematic approach to construct time integration methods of arbitrarily high order for nonlinear evolution equations including conservation laws. They converge towards $A$- or even $L$-stable collocation methods, but are often not sufficiently robust themselves. In this paper, a family of SDC methods inspired by an implicit formulation of the Lax-Wendroff method is developed. Compared to fully implicit approaches, the methods have the advantage that they only require the solution of positive definite or semi-definite linear systems. Numerical evidence suggests that the proposed semi-implicit SDC methods with Radau points are $L$-stable up to order 11 and require very little diffusion for orders 13 and 15. The excellent stability and accuracy of these methods is confirmed by numerical experiments with 1D conservation problems, including the convection-diffusion, Burgers, Euler and Navier-Stokes equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19969v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joerg Stiller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Nonlinear Closures for Moment Equations Based on Orthogonal Polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05894v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present work, an approach to the moment closure problem on the basis of orthogonal polynomials derived from Gram matrices is proposed. Its properties are studied in the context of the moment closure problem arising in gas kinetic theory, for which the proposed approach is proven to have multiple attractive mathematical properties. Numerical studies are carried out for model gas particle distributions and the approach is compared to other moment closure methods, such as Grad's closure and the maximum-entropy method. The proposed ``Gramian'' closure is shown to provide very accurate results for a wide range of distribution functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05894v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eda Yilmaz, Georgii Oblapenko, Manuel Torrilhon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing stable, high-order finite-difference operators on point clouds over complex geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00809v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-order difference operators with the summation-by-parts (SBP) property can be used to build stable discretizations of hyperbolic conservation laws; however, most high-order SBP operators require a conforming, high-order mesh for the domain of interest. To circumvent this requirement, we present an algorithm for building high-order, diagonal-norm, first-derivative SBP operators on point clouds over level-set geometries. The algorithm is not mesh-free, since it uses a Cartesian cut-cell mesh to define the sparsity pattern of the operators and to provide intermediate quadrature rules; however, the mesh is generated automatically and can be discarded once the SBP operators have been constructed. Using this temporary mesh, we construct local, cell-based SBP difference operators that are assembled into global SBP operators. We identify conditions for the existence of a positive-definite diagonal mass matrix, and we compute the diagonal norm by solving a sparse system of linear inequalities using an interior-point algorithm. We also describe an artificial dissipation operator that complements the first-derivative operators when solving hyperbolic problems, although the dissipation is not required for stability. The numerical results confirm the conditions under which a diagonal norm exists and study the distribution of the norm's entries. In addition, the results verify the accuracy and stability of the point-cloud SBP operators using the linear advection equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00809v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Hicken, Ge Yan, Sharanjeet Kaur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jacobi convolution series for Petrov-Galerkin scheme and general fractional calculus of arbitrary order over finite interval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08080v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, general fractional calculus was introduced by Kochubei (2011) and Luchko (2021) as a further generalisation of fractional calculus, where the derivative and integral operator admits arbitrary kernel. Such a formalism will have many applications in physics and engineering, since the kernel is no longer restricted. We first extend the work of Al-Refai and Luchko (2023) on finite interval to arbitrary orders. Followed by, developing an efficient Petrov-Galerkin scheme by introducing Jacobi convolution series as basis functions. A notable property of this basis function, the general fractional derivative of Jacobi convolution series is a shifted Jacobi polynomial. Thus, with a suitable test function it results in diagonal stiffness matrix, hence, the efficiency in implementation. Furthermore, our method is constructed for any arbitrary kernel including that of fractional operator, since, its a special case of general fractional operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08080v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavan Pranjivan Mehta, Gianluigi Rozza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On orthogonality sampling method for Maxwell's equations and its applications to experimental data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11825v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper addresses the inverse scattering problem for Maxwell's equations. We first show that a bianisotropic scatterer can be uniquely determined from multi-static far-field data through the factorization analysis of the far-field operator. Next, we investigate a modified version of the orthogonality sampling method for the numerical reconstruction of the scatterer. Finally, we apply this sampling method to invert unprocessed 3D experimental data obtained from the Fresnel Institute. Numerical examples with synthetic scattering data for bianisotropic targets are also presented to demonstrate the effectiveness of the method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11825v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thu Le, Dinh-Liem Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical proximal Galerkin: a fast $hp$-FEM solver for variational problems with pointwise inequality constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13733v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We leverage the proximal Galerkin algorithm (Keith and Surowiec, Foundations of Computational Mathematics, 2024, DOI: 10.1007/s10208-024-09681-8), a recently introduced mesh-independent algorithm, to obtain a high-order finite element solver for variational problems with pointwise inequality constraints. This is achieved by discretizing the saddle point systems, arising from the latent variable proximal point method, with the hierarchical $p$-finite element basis. This results in discretized sparse Newton systems that admit a simple and effective block preconditioner. The solver can handle both obstacle-type, $u \leq \varphi$, and gradient-type, $|\nabla u| \leq \varphi$, constraints. We apply the resulting algorithm to solve obstacle problems with $hp$-adaptivity, a gradient-type constrained problem, and the thermoforming problem, an example of an obstacle-type quasi-variational inequality. We observe $hp$-robustness in the number of Newton iterations and only mild growth in the number of inner Krylov iterations to solve the Newton systems. Crucially we also provide wall-clock timings that are faster than low-order discretization counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13733v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioannis P. A. Papadopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence theory for two-level hybrid Schwarz preconditioners for high-frequency Helmholtz problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11060v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a novel convergence theory for two-level hybrid Schwarz domain-decomposition (DD) methods for finite-element discretisations of the high-frequency Helmholtz equation. This theory gives sufficient conditions for the preconditioned matrix to be close to the identity, and covers DD subdomains of arbitrary size, and arbitrary absorbing layers/boundary conditions on both the global and local Helmholtz problems. The assumptions on the coarse space are satisfied by the approximation spaces using problem-adapted basis functions that have been recently analysed as coarse spaces for the Helmholtz equation, as well as all spaces that are known to be quasi-optimal via a Schatz-type argument.
  As an example, we apply this theory when the coarse space consists of piecewise polynomials; these are then the first rigorous convergence results about a two-level Schwarz preconditioner applied to the high-frequency Helmholtz equation with a coarse space that does not consist of problem-adapted basis functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11060v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Galkowski, Euan A. Spence</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Type-Based Approaches to Rounding Error Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14598v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This dissertation explores the design and implementation of programming languages that represent rounding error analysis through typing. In the first part of this dissertation, we demonstrate that it is possible to design languages for forward error analysis with NumFuzz, a functional programming language whose type system expresses quantitative bounds on rounding error. This type system combines a sensitivity analysis, enforced through a linear typing discipline, with a novel graded monad to track the accumulation of rounding errors. We establish the soundness of the type system by relating the denotational semantics of the language to both an exact and floating-point operational semantics. To demonstrate the practical utility of NumFuzz as a tool for automated error analysis, we have developed a prototype implementation capable of automatically inferring error bounds. Our implementation produces bounds competitive with existing tools, while often achieving significantly faster analysis times. In the second part of this dissertation, we explore a type-based approach to backward error analysis with Bean, a first-order programming language with a linear type system that can express quantitative bounds on backward error. Bean's type system combines a graded coeffect system with strict linearity to soundly track the flow of backward error through programs. To illustrate Bean's potential as a practical tool for automated backward error analysis, we implement a variety of standard algorithms from numerical linear algebra in Bean, establishing fine-grained backward error bounds via typing in a compositional style. We also develop a prototype implementation of Bean that infers backward error bounds automatically. Our evaluation shows that these inferred bounds match worst-case theoretical relative backward error bounds from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14598v2</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Eileen Kellison</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
