<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NA</link>
    <description>math.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 04:01:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-resolution Isogeometric Analysis -- Efficient adaptivity utilizing the multi-patch structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Isogeometric Analysis (IgA) is a spline based approach to the numerical solution of partial differential equations. There are two major issues that IgA was designed to address. The first issue is the exact representation of domains stemming from Computer Aided Design (CAD) software. In practice, this can be realized only with multi-patch IgA, often in combination with trimming or similar techniques. The second issue is the realization of high-order discretizations (by increasing the spline degree) with numbers of degrees of freedom comparable to low-order methods. High-order methods can deliver their full potential only if the solution to be approximated is sufficiently smooth; otherwise, adaptive methods are required. In the last decades, a zoo of local refinement strategies for splines has been developed. The authors think that many of these approaches are a burden to implement efficiently and impede the utilization of recent advances that rely on tensor-product splines, e.g., concerning matrix assembly and preconditioning. The implementation seems to be particularly cumbersome in the context of multi-patch IgA. Our approach is to moderately increase the number of patches and to utilize different grid sizes on different patches. This allows reusing the existing code bases, recovers the convergence rates of other adaptive approaches and increases the number of degrees of freedom only marginally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08904v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Tyoler, Stefan Takacs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cons-training tensor networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we introduce a novel family of tensor networks, termed constrained matrix product states (MPS), designed to incorporate exactly arbitrary linear constraints into sparse block structures. These tensor networks effectively bridge the gap between U(1) symmetric MPS and traditional, unconstrained MPS. Central to our approach is the concept of a quantum region, an extension of quantum numbers traditionally used in symmetric tensor networks, adapted to capture any linear constraint, including the unconstrained scenario. We further develop canonical forms for these new MPS, which allow for the merging and factorization of tensor blocks according to quantum region fusion rules. Utilizing this canonical form, we apply an unsupervised training strategy to optimize arbitrary cost functions subject to linear constraints. We use this to solve the quadratic knapsack problem and show a superior performance against a leading nonlinear integer programming solver, highlighting the potential of our method in tackling complex constrained combinatorial optimization problems</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09005v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Lopez-Piqueres, Jing Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Krylov subspace methods via the T-product for large Sylvester tensor equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present paper, we introduce new tensor krylov subspace methods for solving large Sylvester tensor equations. The proposed method uses the well-known T-product for tensors and tensor subspaces. We introduce some new tensor products and the related algebraic properties. These new products will enable us to develop third-order the tensor FOM (tFOM), GMRES (tGMRES), tubal Block Arnoldi and the tensor tubal Block Arnoldi method to solve large Sylvester tensor equation. We give some properties related to these method and present some numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09233v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Bouyghf, M. El Guide, A. El Ichi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Coarse-Grained Dynamics on Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a Graph Neural Network (GNN) non-Markovian modeling framework to identify coarse-grained dynamical systems on graphs. Our main idea is to systematically determine the GNN architecture by inspecting how the leading term of the Mori-Zwanzig memory term depends on the coarse-grained interaction coefficients that encode the graph topology. Based on this analysis, we found that the appropriate GNN architecture that will account for $K$-hop dynamical interactions has to employ a Message Passing (MP) mechanism with at least $2K$ steps. We also deduce that the memory length required for an accurate closure model decreases as a function of the interaction strength under the assumption that the interaction strength exhibits a power law that decays as a function of the hop distance. Supporting numerical demonstrations on two examples, a heterogeneous Kuramoto oscillator model and a power system, suggest that the proposed GNN architecture can predict the coarse-grained dynamics under fixed and time-varying graph topologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09324v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin Yu, John Harlim, Daning Huang, Yan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WENO scheme on characteristics for the equilibrium dispersive model of chromatography with generalized Langmuir isotherms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Column chromatography is a laboratory and industrial technique used to separate different substances mixed in a solution. Mathematically, it can be modelled using non-linear partial differential equations whose main ingredients are the adsorption isotherms, which are non-linear functions modelling the affinity between the different substances in the solution and the solid stationary phase filling the column. The goal of this work is twofold. Firstly, we aim to extend the techniques of Donat, Guerrero and Mulet (Appl. Numer. Math. 123 (2018) 22-42) to other adsorption isotherms. In particular, we propose a family of generalized Langmuir-type isotherms and prove that the correspondence between the concentrations of solutes in the liquid phase (the primitive variables) and the conserved variables is well defined and admits a global smooth inverse that can be computed numerically. Secondly, to establish the well-posedness of the mathematical model, we study the eigenstructure of the Jacobian of the mentioned correspondence and use this characteristic information to get oscillation-free sharp interfaces on the numerical approximate solutions. To do so, we determine the structure of the Jacobian matrix of the system and use it to deduce its eigenstructure. We combine the use of characteristic-based numerical fluxes with a second-order implicit-explicit scheme proposed in the cited reference and perform some numerical experiments with T\'oth's adsorption isotherms to demonstrate that the characteristic-based schemes produce accurate numerical solutions with no oscillations, even when steep gradients appear in the solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09328v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.apnum.2024.03.006</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Numerical Mathematics 201 (2024) 247-264</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R. Donat, M. C. Mart\'i, P. Mulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient WENO schemes for nonuniform grids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09367v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A set of arbitrarily high-order WENO schemes for reconstructions on nonuniform grids is presented. These non-linear interpolation methods use simple smoothness indicators with a linear cost with respect to the order, making them easy to implement and computationally efficient. The theoretical analysis to verify the accuracy and the essentially non-oscillatory properties are presented together with some numerical experiments involving algebraic problems in order to validate them. Also, these general schemes are applied for the solution of conservation laws and hyperbolic systems in the context of finite volume methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09367v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. C. Mart\'i, P. Mulet, D. F. Y\'a\~nez, D. Zor\'io</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow updates for domain decomposition of entropic optimal transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Domain decomposition has been shown to be a computationally efficient distributed method for solving large scale entropic optimal transport problems. However, a naive implementation of the algorithm can freeze in the limit of very fine partition cells (i.e.~it asymptotically becomes stationary and does not find the global minimizer), since information can only travel slowly between cells. In practice this can be avoided by a coarse-to-fine multiscale scheme. In this article we introduce flow updates as an alternative approach. Flow updates can be interpreted as a variant of the celebrated algorithm by Angenent, Haker, and Tannenbaum, and can be combined canonically with domain decomposition. We prove convergence to the global minimizer and provide a formal discussion of its continuity limit. We give a numerical comparison with naive and multiscale domain decomposition, and show that the hybrid method does not suffer from freezing in the regime of very many cells. While the multiscale scheme is observed to be faster than the hybrid approach in general, the latter could be a viable alternative in cases where a good initial coupling is available. Our numerical experiments are based on a novel GPU implementation of domain decomposition that we describe in the appendix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09400v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ismael Medina, Bernhard Schmitzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A velocity-based moving mesh Discontinuous Galerkin method for the advection-diffusion equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09408v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In convection-dominated flows, robustness of the spatial discretisation is a key property. While Interior Penalty Galerkin (IPG) methods already proved efficient in the situation of large mesh Peclet numbers, Arbitrary Lagrangian-Eulerian (ALE) methods are able to reduce the convection-dominance by moving the mesh. In this paper, we introduce and analyse a velocity-based moving mesh discontinuous Galerkin method for the solution of the linear advection-diffusion equation. By introducing a smooth parameterized velocity $\tilde{V}$ that separates the flow into a mean flow, also called moving mesh velocity, and a remaining advection field $V-\tilde{V}$, we made a convergence analysis based on the smoothness of the mesh velocity. Furthermore, the reduction of the advection speed improves the stability of an explicit time-stepping and the use of the nonconservative ALE formulation changes the coercivity condition. Finally, by adapting the existing robust error criteria to this moving mesh situation, we derived robust \textit{a posteriori} error criteria that describe the potentially small deviation to the mean flow and include the information of a transition towards $V=\tilde{V}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09408v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ezra Rozier, J\"orn Behrens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the convergence analysis of linear subdivision schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents several new results concerning the analysis of the convergence of binary, univariate, and linear subdivision schemes, all related to the contractivity factor of a convergent scheme. First, we prove that a convergent scheme cannot have a contractivity factor lower than half. Since the lower this factor is, the faster the scheme's convergence, and schemes with contractivity factor $\frac{1}{2}$, such as those generating spline functions, have optimal convergence rates.
  Additionally, we provide further insights and conditions for the convergence of linear schemes and demonstrate their applicability in an improved algorithm for determining the convergence of such subdivision schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09414v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nira Dyn, Nir Sharon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On backward problem for a time-fractional fourth order parabolic equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with the inverse problem of retrieving the initial value of a time-fractional fourth order parabolic equation from source and final time observation. The considered problem is an {\it ill-posed problem.} We obtain regularized approximations for the sought initial value by employing the quasi-boundary value method, its modified version and by Fourier truncation method(FTM). We provide both the apriori and aposteriori parameter choice strategies and derive the error estimates for all these methods under some {\it source conditions} involving some Sobolev smoothness. As an important implication of the obtained rates, we observe that for both the apriori and aposteriori cases, the rates obtained by all these three methods are same for some source sets. Moreover, we observe that in both the apriori and aposteriori cases, the FTM is free from the so-called {\it saturation effect}, whereas both the quasi-boundary value method and its generalizations possesses the saturation effect for both the cases. Further, we observe that the rates obtained by the FTM is always order optimal for all the considered source sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09424v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhankar Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotated reference frames in radiative transport theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rotated reference frames offer fast algorithms for the radiative transport equation (RTE). We review the singular-eigenfunction approach and related numerical methods for the multi-dimensional RTE with rotated reference frames.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09447v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manabu Machida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computation-Aware Kalman Filtering and Smoothing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08971v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kalman filtering and smoothing are the foundational mechanisms for efficient inference in Gauss-Markov models. However, their time and memory complexities scale prohibitively with the size of the state space. This is particularly problematic in spatiotemporal regression problems, where the state dimension scales with the number of spatial observations. Existing approximate frameworks leverage low-rank approximations of the covariance matrix. Since they do not model the error introduced by the computational approximation, their predictive uncertainty estimates can be overly optimistic. In this work, we propose a probabilistic numerical method for inference in high-dimensional Gauss-Markov models which mitigates these scaling issues. Our matrix-free iterative algorithm leverages GPU acceleration and crucially enables a tunable trade-off between computational cost and predictive uncertainty. Finally, we demonstrate the scalability of our method on a large-scale climate dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08971v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marvin Pf\"ortner, Jonathan Wenger, Jon Cockayne, Philipp Hennig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo methods on compact complex manifolds using Bergman kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09203v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a new randomized method for numerical integration on a compact complex manifold with respect to a continuous volume form. Taking for quadrature nodes a suitable determinantal point process, we build an unbiased Monte Carlo estimator of the integral of any Lipschitz function, and show that the estimator satisfies a central limit theorem, with a faster rate than under independent sampling. In particular, seeing a complex manifold of dimension $d$ as a real manifold of dimension $d_{\mathbb{R}}=2d$, the mean squared error for $N$ quadrature nodes decays as $N^{-1-2/d_{\mathbb{R}}}$; this is faster than previous DPP-based quadratures and reaches the optimal worst-case rate investigated by [Bakhvalov 1965] in Euclidean spaces. The determinantal point process we use is characterized by its kernel, which is the Bergman kernel of a holomorphic Hermitian line bundle, and we strongly build upon the work of Berman that led to the central limit theorem in [Berman, 2018].We provide numerical illustrations for the Riemann sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09203v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibaut Lemoine (CRIStAL), R\'emi Bardenet (TAO, CRIStAL)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positional Knowledge is All You Need: Position-induced Transformer (PiT) for Operator Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09285v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Operator learning for Partial Differential Equations (PDEs) is rapidly emerging as a promising approach for surrogate modeling of intricate systems. Transformers with the self-attention mechanism$\unicode{x2013}$a powerful tool originally designed for natural language processing$\unicode{x2013}$have recently been adapted for operator learning. However, they confront challenges, including high computational demands and limited interpretability. This raises a critical question: Is there a more efficient attention mechanism for Transformer-based operator learning? This paper proposes the Position-induced Transformer (PiT), built on an innovative position-attention mechanism, which demonstrates significant advantages over the classical self-attention in operator learning. Position-attention draws inspiration from numerical methods for PDEs. Different from self-attention, position-attention is induced by only the spatial interrelations of sampling positions for input functions of the operators, and does not rely on the input function values themselves, thereby greatly boosting efficiency. PiT exhibits superior performance over current state-of-the-art neural operators in a variety of complex operator learning tasks across diverse PDE benchmarks. Additionally, PiT possesses an enhanced discretization convergence feature, compared to the widely-used Fourier neural operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09285v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junfeng Chen, Kailiang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equations with infinite delay: pseudospectral discretization for numerical stability and bifurcation in an abstract framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13351v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider nonlinear delay differential and renewal equations with infinite delay. We extend the work of Gyllenberg et al, Appl. Math. Comput. (2018) by introducing a unifying abstract framework, and derive a finite-dimensional approximating system via pseudospectral discretization. For renewal equations, we consider a reformulation in the space of absolutely continuous functions via integration. We prove the one-to-one correspondence of equilibria between the original equation and its approximation, and that linearization and discretization commute. Our most important result is the proof of convergence of the characteristic roots of the pseudospectral approximation of the linear(ized) equations when the collocation nodes are chosen as the family of scaled zeros or extrema of Laguerre polynomials. This ensures that the finite-dimensional system correctly reproduces the stability properties of the original linear equation if the dimension of the approximation is large enough. The result is illustrated with several numerical tests, which also demonstrate the effectiveness of the approach for the bifurcation analysis of equilibria of nonlinear equations. The new approach used to prove convergence also provides the exact location of the spectrum of the differentiation matrices for the Laguerre zeros and extrema, adding new insights into properties that are important in the numerical solution of differential equations by pseudospectral methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13351v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Scarabel, Rossana Vermiglio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Local Approximate Ideal Restriction for Advection-Diffusion Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.00229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.00229v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper focuses on developing a reduction-based algebraic multigrid method that is suitable for solving general (non)symmetric linear systems and is naturally robust from pure advection to pure diffusion. Initial motivation comes from a new reduction-based algebraic multigrid (AMG) approach, $\ell$AIR (local approximate ideal restriction), that was developed for solving advection-dominated problems. Though this new solver is very effective in the advection dominated regime, its performance degrades in cases where diffusion becomes dominant. This is consistent with the fact that in general, reduction-based AMG methods tend to suffer from growth in complexity and/or convergence rates as the problem size is increased, especially for diffusion dominated problems in two or three dimensions. Motivated by the success of $\ell$AIR in the advective regime, our aim in this paper is to generalize the AIR framework with the goal of improving the performance of the solver in diffusion dominated regimes. To do so, we propose a novel way to combine mode constraints as used commonly in energy minimization AMG methods with the local approximation of ideal operators used in $\ell$AIR. The resulting constrained $\ell$AIR (C$\ell$AIR) algorithm is able to achieve fast scalable convergence on advective and diffusive problems. In addition, it is able to achieve standard low complexity hierarchies in the diffusive regime through aggressive coarsening, something that has been previously difficult for reduction-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.00229v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1137/23M1583442</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIAM J. SCI. COMPUT. 2024 Vol. 0, No. 0, pp. S96-S122</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ahsan Ali, James Brannick, Karsten Kahl, Oliver A. Krzysik, Jacob B. Schroder, Ben S. Southworth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak approximation for stochastic reaction-diffusion equation near sharp interface limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.08241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.08241v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is known that when the diffuse interface thickness $\epsilon$ vanishes, the sharp interface limit of the stochastic reaction-diffusion equation is formally a stochastic geometric flow. To capture and simulate such geometric flow, it is crucial to develop numerical approximations whose error bounds depends on $\frac 1\epsilon$ polynomially. However, due to loss of spectral estimate of the linearized stochastic reaction-diffusion equation, how to get such error bound of numerical approximation has been an open problem.
  In this paper, we solve this weak error bound problem for stochastic reaction-diffusion equations near sharp interface limit. We first introduce a regularized problem which enjoys the exponential ergodicity. Then we present the regularity analysis of the regularized Kolmogorov and Poisson equations which only depends on $\frac 1{\epsilon}$ polynomially. Furthermore, we establish such weak error bound. This phenomenon could be viewed as a kind of the regularization effect of noise on the numerical approximation of stochastic partial differential equation (SPDE). As a by-product, a central limit theorem of the weak approximation is shown near sharp interface limit. Our method of proof could be extended to a number of other spatial and temporal numerical approximations for semilinear SPDEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.08241v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianbo Cui, Liying Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Volumetric Approach to Monge's Optimal Transport on Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01745v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a volumetric formulation for computing the Optimal Transport problem defined on surfaces in $\mathbb{R}^3$, found in disciplines like optics, computer graphics, and computational methodologies. Instead of directly tackling the original problem on the surface, we define a new Optimal Transport problem on a thin tubular region, $T_{\epsilon}$, adjacent to the surface. This extension offers enhanced flexibility and simplicity for numerical discretization on Cartesian grids. The Optimal Transport mapping and potential function computed on $T_{\epsilon}$ are consistent with the original problem on surfaces. We demonstrate that, with the proposed volumetric approach, it is possible to use simple and straightforward numerical methods to solve Optimal Transport for $\Gamma = \mathbb{S}^2$ and the $2$-torus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01745v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Tsai, Axel G. R. Turnquist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Fractional Fourier Transform (FRFT) scheme using the closed Newton-Cotes rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16379v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper enhances the accuracy of the one-dimensional fractional Fourier transform (FRFT) using the closed Newton Cotes quadrature rules. Given the weights generated by the Composite Newton Cotes rules of order QN, it is shown that a FRFT of a QN-long weighted sequence can be written as two composites of FRFTs. The first composite of FRFTs is made up of a FRFT of a Q-long weighted sequence and a FRFT of a N-long sequence. The second composite is made up of a FRFT of a N-long weighted sequence and a FRFT of a Q-long sequence. The Empirical evidence suggests that the composite FRFTs has commutative property and works both algebraically and numerically. The composite of FRFTs is applied to the problem of inverting Fourier and Laplace transforms. The results show that the composite FRFTs outperforms both the simple non-weighted FRFT and the Newton-Cotes integration method, but the difference is less significant for the integration method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16379v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. H. Nzokem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational methods for abstract linear, non-homogeneous problems without order reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04195v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Starting from an A-stable rational approximation to $\rm{e}^z$ of order $p$, $$r(z)= 1+ z+ \cdots + z^p/ p! + O(z^{p+1}),$$ families of stable methods are proposed to time discretize abstract IVP's of the type $u'(t) = A u(t) + f(t)$. These numerical procedures turn out to be of order $p$, thus overcoming the order reduction phenomenon, and only one evaluation of $f$ per step is required.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04195v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Arranz-Sim\'on, Cesar Palencia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Unstructured Body-of-Revolution Electromagnetic Particle-in-Cell Algorithm with Radial Perfectly Matched Layers and Dual Polarizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07396v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A novel electromagnetic particle-in-cell algorithm has been developed for fully kinetic plasma simulations on unstructured (irregular) meshes in complex body-of-revolution geometries. The algorithm, implemented in the BORPIC++ code, utilizes a set of field scalings and a coordinate mapping, reducing the Maxwell field problem in a cylindrical system to a Cartesian finite element Maxwell solver in the meridian plane. The latter obviates the cylindrical coordinate singularity in the symmetry axis. The choice of an unstructured finite element discretization enhances the geometrical flexibility of the BORPIC++ solver compared to the more traditional finite difference solvers. Symmetries in Maxwell's equations are explored to decompose the problem into two dual polarization states with isomorphic representations that enable code reuse. The particle-in-cell scatter and gather steps preserve charge-conservation at the discrete level. Our previous algorithm (BORPIC+) discretized the E and B field components of TE-phi and TM-phi polarizations on the finite element (primal) mesh. A cylindrical perfectly matched layer is implemented as a boundary condition in the radial direction to simulate open space problems, with periodic boundary conditions in the axial direction. We investigate effects of charged particles moving next to the cylindrical perfectly matched layer. We model azimuthal currents arising from rotational motion of charged rings, which produce TM-phi polarized fields. Several numerical examples are provided to illustrate the first application of the algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07396v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dong-Yeop Na, Fernando L. Teixeira, Yuri A. Omelchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Globally Optimal Solutions to a Class of Fractional Optimization Problems Based on Proximal Gradient Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.11286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.11286v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a category of constrained fractional optimization problems that emerge in various practical applications. The objective function for this category is characterized by the ratio of a numerator and denominator, both being convex, semi-algebraic, Lipschitz continuous, and differentiable with Lipschitz continuous gradients over the constraint sets. The constrained sets associated with these problems are closed, convex, and semi-algebraic. We propose an efficient algorithm that is inspired by the proximal gradient method, and we provide a thorough convergence analysis. Our algorithm offers several benefits compared to existing methods. It requires only a single proximal gradient operation per iteration, thus avoiding the complicated inner-loop concave maximization usually required. Additionally, our method converges to a critical point without the typical need for a nonnegative numerator, and this critical point becomes a globally optimal solution with an appropriate condition. Our approach is adaptable to unbounded constraint sets as well. Therefore, our approach is viable for many more practical models. Numerical experiments show that our method not only reliably reaches ground-truth solutions in some model problems but also outperforms several existing methods in maximizing the Sharpe ratio with real-world financial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.11286v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yizun Lin, Jian-Feng Cai, Zhao-Rong Lai, Cheng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
