<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NA</link>
    <description>math.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 02:30:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A numerical study of a PDE-ODE system with a stochastic dynamical boundary condition: a nonlinear model for sulphation phenomena</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the qualitative behaviour of the solutions of a stochastic boundary value problem on the half-line for a nonlinear system of parabolic reaction-diffusion equations, from a numerical point of view. The model describes the chemical aggression of calcium carbonate stones under the attack of sulphur dioxide. The dynamical boundary condition is given by a Pearson diffusion, which is original in the context of the degradation of cultural heritage. We first discuss a scheme based on the Lamperti transformation for the stochastic differential equation to preserve the boundary and a splitting strategy for the partial differential equation based on recent theoretical results. Positiveness, boundedness, and stability are stated. The impact of boundary noise on the solution and its qualitative behaviour both in the slow and fast regimes is discussed in several numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16307v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Arceci, Daniela Morale, Stefania Ugolini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computation and properties of the Epstein zeta function with high-performance implementation in EpsteinLib</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Epstein zeta function generalizes the Riemann zeta function to oscillatory lattice sums in higher dimensions. Beyond its numerous applications in pure mathematics, it has recently been identified as a key component in simulating exotic quantum materials. This work establishes the Epstein zeta function as a powerful tool in numerical analysis by rigorously investigating its analytical properties and enabling its efficient computation. Specifically, we derive a compact and computationally efficient representation of the Epstein zeta function and thoroughly examine its analytical properties across all arguments. Furthermore, we introduce a superexponentially convergent algorithm, complete with error bounds, for computing the Epstein zeta function in arbitrary dimensions. We also show that the Epstein zeta function can be decomposed into a power law singularity and an analytic function in the first Brillouin zone. This decomposition facilitates the rapid evaluation of integrals involving the Epstein zeta function and allows for efficient precomputations through interpolation techniques. We present the first high-performance implementation of the Epstein zeta function and its regularisation for arbitrary real arguments in EpsteinLib, a C library with Python and Mathematica bindings, and rigorously benchmark its precision and performance against known formulas, achieving full precision across the entire parameter range. Finally, we apply our library to the computation of quantum dispersion relations of three-dimensional spin materials with long-range interactions and Casimir energies in multidimensional geometries, uncovering higher-order corrections to known asymptotic formulas for the arising forces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16317v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas A. Buchheit, Jonathan Busse, Ruben Gutendorf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Stable and Structure-Preserving Algorithms for the Stochastic Galerkin System of 2D Shallow Water Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shallow water equations (SWE) are fundamental nonlinear hyperbolic PDE-based models in fluid dynamics that are essential for studying a wide range of geophysical and engineering phenomena. Therefore, stable and accurate numerical methods for SWE are needed. Although some algorithms are well studied for deterministic SWE, more effort should be devoted to handling the SWE with uncertainty. In this paper, we incorporate uncertainty through a stochastic Galerkin (SG) framework, and building on an existing hyperbolicity-preserving SG formulation for 2D SWE, we construct the corresponding entropy flux pair, and develop structure-preserving, well-balanced, second-order energy conservative and energy stable finite volume schemes for the SG formulation of the two-dimensional shallow water system. We demonstrate the efficacy, applicability, and robustness of these structure-preserving algorithms through several challenging numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16353v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yekaterina Epshteyn, Akil Narayan, Yinqian Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certified Lumped Approximations for the Conduction Dunking Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the dunking problem: a solid body at uniform temperature $T_\text{i}$ is placed in a environment characterized by farfield temperature $T_\infty$ and time-independent spatially uniform heat transfer coefficient; we permit heterogeneous material composition. The problem is described by a heat equation with Robin boundary conditions. The crucial parameter is the Biot number, a nondimensional heat transfer coefficient; we consider the limit of small Biot number.
  We introduce first-order and second-order asymptotic approximations (in Biot number) for the spatial domain average temperature as a function of time; the first-order approximation is the standard `lumped model'. We provide asymptotic error estimates for the first-order and second-order approximations for small Biot number, and also, for the first-order approximation, non-asymptotic bounds valid for all Biot number. We also develop a second-order approximation and associated asymptotic error estimate for the normalized difference in the domain average and boundary average temperatures. Companion numerical solutions of the heat equation confirm the effectiveness of the error estimates for small Biot number.
  The second-order approximation and the first-order and second-order error estimates depend on several functional outputs associated with an elliptic partial differential equation; the latter can be derived from Biot-sensitivity analysis of the heat equation eigenproblem in the limit of small Biot number. Most important is the functional output $\phi$, the only functional output required for the first-order error estimate and also the second-order approximation; $\phi$ admits a simple physical interpretation in terms of conduction length scale. We characterize a class of spatial domains for which the standard lumped-model criterion -- Biot number (based on volume-to-area length scale) small -- is deficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16357v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kento Kaneko (Department of Mechanical Engineering, Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Claude Le Bris (Matherials project-team, \'Ecole des Ponts and Inria), Anthony T. Patera (Department of Mechanical Engineering, Massachusetts Institute of Technology)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transport Quasi-Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16416v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quasi-Monte Carlo (QMC) is a powerful method for evaluating high-dimensional integrals. However, its use is typically limited to distributions where direct sampling is straightforward, such as the uniform distribution on the unit hypercube or the Gaussian distribution. For general target distributions with potentially unnormalized densities, leveraging the low-discrepancy property of QMC to improve accuracy remains challenging. We propose training a transport map to push forward the uniform distribution on the unit hypercube to approximate the target distribution. Inspired by normalizing flows, the transport map is constructed as a composition of simple, invertible transformations. To ensure that RQMC achieves its superior error rate, the transport map must satisfy specific regularity conditions. We introduce a flexible parametrization for the transport map that not only meets these conditions but is also expressive enough to model complex distributions. Our theoretical analysis establishes that the proposed transport QMC estimator achieves faster convergence rates than standard Monte Carlo, under mild and easily verifiable growth conditions on the integrand. Numerical experiments confirm the theoretical results, demonstrating the effectiveness of the proposed method in Bayesian inference tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16416v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sifan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incremental Hierarchical Tucker Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16544v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present two new algorithms for approximating and updating the hierarchical Tucker decomposition of tensor streams. The first algorithm, Batch Hierarchical Tucker - leaf to root (BHT-l2r), proposes an alternative and more efficient way of approximating a batch of similar tensors in hierarchical Tucker format. The second algorithm, Hierarchical Tucker - Rapid Incremental Subspace Expansion (HT-RISE), updates the batch hierarchical Tucker representation of an accumulated tensor as new batches of tensors become available. The HT-RISE algorithm is suitable for the online setting and never requires full storage or reconstruction of all data while providing a solution to the incremental Tucker decomposition problem. We provide theoretical guarantees for both algorithms and demonstrate their effectiveness on physical and cyber-physical data. The proposed BHT-l2r algorithm and the batch hierarchical Tucker format offers up to $6.2\times$ compression and $3.7\times$ reduction in time over the hierarchical Tucker format. The proposed HT-RISE algorithm also offers up to $3.1\times$ compression and $3.2\times$ reduction in time over a state of the art incremental tensor train decomposition algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16544v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Doruk Aksoy, Alex A. Gorodetsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of monostable fronts for a KPP infinite-difference numerical scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the existence of traveling wave solutions for a numerical counterpart of the KPP equation. We obtain the existence of monostable fronts for all super-critical speeds in the regime where the spatial step size is small. The key strategy is to transfer the invertibility of certain linear operators related to the front solutions from the continuous setting to the discrete case we are interested in. We rely on resolvent bounds which are uniform with respect to the step size, a procedure which is also known as spectral convergence. The approach is also able to handle infinite range discretizations with geometrically decaying coefficients that are allowed to have both signs, which prevents the use of the comparison principle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16580v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Gar\'enaux, Hermen Jan Hupkes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance evaluation of mixed-precision Runge-Kutta methods for the solution of partial differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work focuses on the numerical study of a recently published class of Runge-Kutta methods designed for mixed-precision arithmetic. We employ the methods in solving partial differential equations on modern hardware. In particular we investigate what speedups are achievable by the use of mixed precision and the dependence of the methods algorithmic compatibility with the computational hardware. We use state-of-the-art software, utilizing the Ginkgo library, which is designed to incorporate mixed precision arithmetic, and perform numerical tests of 3D problems on both GPU and CPU architectures. We show that significant speedups can be achieved but that performance depends on solver parameters and performance of software kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16638v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivo Dravins, Marcel Koch, Victoria Griehl, Katharina Kormann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unifying Family of Data-Adaptive Partitioning Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Clustering algorithms remain valuable tools for grouping and summarizing the most important aspects of data. Example areas where this is the case include image segmentation, dimension reduction, signals analysis, model order reduction, numerical analysis, and others. As a consequence, many clustering approaches have been developed to satisfy the unique needs of each particular field. In this article, we present a family of data-adaptive partitioning algorithms that unifies several well-known methods (e.g., k-means and k-subspaces). Indexed by a single parameter and employing a common minimization strategy, the algorithms are easy to use and interpret, and scale well to large, high-dimensional problems. In addition, we develop an adaptive mechanism that (a) exhibits skill at automatically uncovering data structures and problem parameters without any expert knowledge and, (b) can be used to augment other existing methods. By demonstrating the performance of our methods on examples from disparate fields including subspace clustering, model order reduction, and matrix approximation, we hope to highlight their versatility and potential for extending the boundaries of existing scientific domains. We believe our family's parametrized structure represents a synergism of algorithms that will foster new developments and directions, not least within the data science community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16713v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guy B. Oldaker IV, Maria Emelianenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A noncoforming virtual element approximation for the Oseen eigenvalue problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we analyze a nonconforming virtual element method to approximate the eigenfunctions and eigenvalues of the two dimensional Oseen eigenvalue problem. The spaces under consideration lead to a divergence-free method which is capable to capture properly the divergence at discrete level and the eigenvalues and eigenfunctions. Under the compact theory for operators we prove convergence and error estimates for the method. By employing the theory of compact operators we recover the double order of convergence of the spectrum. Finally, we present numerical tests to assess the performance of the proposed numerical scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16813v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibyendu Adak, Felipe Lepe, Gonzalo Rivera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Gas-Kinetic Scheme for Maxwell Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a gas-kinetic scheme using discrete velocity space to solve Maxwell equations. The kinetic model recovers Maxwell equations in the zero relaxation time limit. The scheme achieves second-order spatial and temporal accuracy in structured meshes comparable to the finite-difference time-domain (FDTD) method, without requiring staggered grids or leapfrog discretization. Our kinetic scheme is inherently multidimensional due to its use of kinetic beams in multiple directions, allowing larger time steps in multidimensional computations. It demonstrates better stability than FDTD when handling discontinuities and readily extends to unstructured meshes. We validate the method through various test cases including antenna simulation, sphere scattering, and flight vehicle scattering. The results align well with Riemann-solver-based solutions. Finally, we examine charge conservation for Maxwell equations through test cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16845v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhigang Pu, Kun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCMC-Net: Accelerating Markov Chain Monte Carlo with Neural Networks for Inverse Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In many computational problems, using the Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) can be prohibitively time-consuming. We propose MCMC-Net, a simple yet efficient way to accelerate MCMC via neural networks. The key idea of our approach is to substitute the likelihood function of the MCMC method with a neural operator. We extensively evaluate the accuracy and speedup of our method on three different PDE-based inverse problems where likelihood computations are computationally expensive, namely electrical impedance tomography, diffuse optical tomography, and quantitative photoacoustic tomography.
  MCMC-Net performs similar to the classical likelihood counterpart but with a significant, up to twelvefold, speedup. We conjecture that the method can be applied to any problem with a sufficiently expensive likelihood function. We also analyze MCMC-Net in a theoretical setting for the different use cases. We prove a universal approximation theorem-type result to show that the proposed network can approximate the mapping resulting from forward model evaluations to a desired accuracy. Furthermore, we establish convergence of the surrogate posterior to the true posterior under Hellinger distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16883v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudeb Majee, Anuj Abhishek, Thilo Strauss, Taufiquar Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal error bounds on an exponential wave integrator Fourier spectral method for the logarithmic Schr\"odinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a nearly optimal error bound on the exponential wave integrator Fourier spectral (EWI-FS) method for the logarithmic Schr\"odinger equation (LogSE) under the assumption of $H^2$-solution, which is theoretically guaranteed. Subject to a CFL-type time step size restriction $\tau |\ln \tau| \leq h^2/|\ln h|$ for obtaining the stability of the numerical scheme affected by the singularity of the logarithmic nonlinearity, an $L^2$-norm error bound of order $O(\tau |\ln \tau|^2 + h^2 |\ln h|)$ is established, where $\tau$ is the time step size and $h$ is the mesh size. Compared to the error estimates of the LogSE in the literature, our error bound either greatly improves the convergence rate under the same regularity assumptions or significantly weakens the regularity requirement to obtain the same convergence rate. Moreover, our result can be directly applied to the LogSE with low regularity $L^\infty$-potential, which is not allowed in the existing error estimates. Two main ingredients are adopted in the proof: (i) an $H^2$-conditional $L^2$-stability estimate, which is established using the energy method to avoid singularity of the logarithmic nonlinearity, and (ii) mathematical induction with inverse inequalities to control the $H^2$-norm of the numerical solution. Numerical results are reported to confirm our error estimates and demonstrate the necessity of the time step size restriction imposed. We also apply the EWI-FS method to investigate soliton collisions in one dimension and vortex dipole dynamics in two dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16902v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weizhu Bao, Ying Ma, Chushan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traveling-wave solutions and structure-preserving numerical methods for a hyperbolic approximation of the Korteweg-de Vries equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the recently-proposed hyperbolic approximation of the Korteweg-de Vries equation (KdV).
  We show that this approximation, which we call KdVH, possesses a rich variety of
  solutions, including solitary wave solutions that approximate KdV solitons, as well as other
  solitary and periodic solutions that are related to higher-order water wave models,
  and may include singularities.
  We analyze a class of implicit-explicit Runge-Kutta time discretizations for KdVH
  that are asymptotic preserving, energy conserving, and can be applied to other hyperbolized
  systems. We also develop structure-preserving spatial discretizations based on summation-by-parts
  operators in space including finite difference, discontinuous Galerkin, and Fourier methods. We use the
  relaxation approach to make the fully discrete schemes energy-preserving.
  Numerical experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of these discretizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17117v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijit Biswas, David I. Ketcheson, Hendrik Ranocha, Jochen Sch\"utz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subspace correction methods for semicoercive and nearly semicoercive convex optimization with applications to nonlinear PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17318v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present new convergence analyses for subspace correction methods for semicoercive and nearly semicoercive convex optimization problems, generalizing the theory of singular and nearly singular linear problems to the nonlinear domain. Our results demonstrate that the elegant theoretical framework developed for singular and nearly singular linear problems can be extended to semicoercive and nearly semicoercive convex optimization problems. For semicoercive problems, we show that the convergence rate can be estimated in terms of a seminorm stable decomposition over the subspaces and the kernel of the problem, aligning with the theory for singular linear problems. For nearly semicoercive problems, we establish a parameter-independent convergence rate, assuming the kernel of the semicoercive part can be decomposed into a sum of local kernels, which aligns with the theory for nearly singular problems. To demonstrate the applicability of our results, we provide convergence analyses of two-level additive Schwarz methods for solving a nonlinear Neumann boundary value problem and its perturbation within the proposed abstract framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17318v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Young-Ju Lee, Jongho Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Fast Direct Method For Solving Quasi-Toeplitz System of Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The objective of this study is to present a novel, efficient, and fast direct method for solving linear systems of equations whose coefficient matrix is a tridiagonal Quasi-Toeplitz matrix. Such matrices are frequently encountered in the discretization of second-order differential equation problems with Neumann boundary conditions, the discretization of Quasi-Birth-and-Death processes known as QBD matrix equations, and other related applications. The presented method has been demonstrated to produce favorable results in terms of run time for moderately large systems when compared to classical direct methods, such as the LU and PLU methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17326v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahin Hasanbeigi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A second order Langevin sampler preserving positive volume for isothermal isobaric ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17369v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose in this work a second-order Langevin sampler for the isothermal-isobaric ensemble (the NPT ensemble), preserving a positive volume for the simulation box. We first derive the suitable equations of motion for particles to be coupled with the overdamped Langevin equation of volume by sending the artificial mass of the periodic box to zero in the work of Liang et. al. [J. Chem. Phys. 157(14)]. We prove the well-posedness of the new system of equations and show that its invariant measure is the desired ensemble. The new continuous time equations not only justify the previous cell-rescaling methods, but also allow us to choose a suitable friction coefficient so that one has additive noise after a change of variable by taking logarithm of the volume. This observation allows us to propose a second order weak scheme that guarantees the positivity of the volume. Various numerical experiments have been performed to demonstrate the efficacy of our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17369v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Li, Yuzhou Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle Method for the McKean-Vlasov equation with common noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies the numerical simulation of the solution to the McKean-Vlasov equation with common noise. We begin by discretizing the solution in time using the Euler scheme, followed by spatial discretization through the particle method, inspired by the propagation of chaos property. Assuming H{\"o}lder continuity in time, as well as Lipschitz continuity in the state and measure arguments of the coefficient functions, we establish the convergence rate of the Euler scheme and the particle method. These results extend those for the standard McKean-Vlasov equation without common noise. Finally, we present two simulation examples : a modified conditional Ornstein Uhlenbeck process with common noise and an interbank market model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17418v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eophile Le Gall (CEREMADE)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance evaluation of accelerated real and complex multiple-precision sparse matrix-vector multiplication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sparse matrices have recently played a significant and impactful role in scientific computing, including artificial intelligence-related fields. According to historical studies on sparse matrix--vector multiplication (SpMV), Krylov subspace methods are particularly sensitive to the effects of round-off errors when using floating-point arithmetic. By employing multiple-precision linear computation, convergence can be stabilized by reducing these round-off errors. In this paper, we present the performance of our accelerated SpMV using SIMD instructions, demonstrating its effectiveness through various examples, including Krylov subspace methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17510v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomonori Kouya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponentially convergent method for time-fractional evolution equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An exponentially convergent numerical method for solving a differential equation with a right-hand fractional Riemann-Liouville time-derivative and an unbounded operator coefficient in Banach space is proposed and analysed for a homogeneous/inhomogeneous equation of the Hardy-Tichmarsh type.
  We employ a solution representation by the Danford-Cauchy integral on hyperbola that envelopes spectrum of the operator coefficient with a subsequent application of an exponentially convergent quadrature.
  To do that, parameters of the hyperbola are chosen so that the integration function has an analytical extension into a strip around the real axis and then apply the Sinc-quadrature.
  We show the exponential accuracy and illustrate the results by a numerical example confirming the {\it a priori} estimate.
  Existence conditions for the solution of the inhomogeneous equation are established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17521v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Vasylyk, V. L. Makarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speeding up an unsteady flow simulation by adaptive BDDC and Krylov subspace recycling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We deal with accelerating the solution of a sequence of large linear systems solved by an iterative Krylov subspace method. The sequence originates from time-stepping within a simulation of an unsteady incompressible flow. We apply a pressure correction scheme, and we focus on the solution of the Poisson problem for the pressure corrector. Its scalable solution presents the main computational challenge in many applications. The right-hand side of the problem changes in each time step, while the system matrix is constant and symmetric positive definite. The acceleration techniques are studied on a particular problem of flow around a unit sphere. Our baseline approach is based on a parallel solution of each problem in the sequence by nonoverlapping domain decomposition method. The interface problem is solved by the preconditioned conjugate gradient (PCG) method with the three-level BDDC preconditioner. Three techniques for accelerating the solution are gradually added to the baseline approach. First, the stopping criterion for the PCG iterations is studied. Next, deflation is used within the conjugate gradient method with several approaches to Krylov subspace recycling. Finally, we add the adaptive selection of the coarse space within the three-level BDDC method. The paper is rich in experiments with careful measurements of computational times on a parallel supercomputer. The combination of the acceleration techniques eventually leads to saving about one half of the computational time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17543v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Hanek, Jan Pape\v{z}, Jakub \v{S}\'istek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal quadrature for weighted function spaces on multivariate domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider the numerical integration $${\rm Int}_{\mathbb S^d,w}(f)=\int_{\mathbb S^d}f({\bf x})w({\bf x}){\rm d}\sigma({\bf x}) $$ for weighted Sobolev classes $BW_{p,w}^r(\mathbb S^d)$ with a Dunkl weight $w$ and weighted Besov classes $BB_\gamma^\Theta(L_{p,w}(\mathbb S^d))$ with the generalized smoothness index $\Theta $ and a doubling weight $w$ on the unit sphere $\mathbb S^d$ of the Euclidean space $\mathbb R^{d+1}$ in the deterministic and randomized case settings. For $BW_{p,w}^r(\mathbb S^d)$ we obtain the optimal quadrature errors in both settings. For $BB_\gamma^\Theta(L_{p,w}(\mathbb S^d))$ we use the weighted least $\ell_p$ approximation and the standard Monte Carlo algorithm to obtain upper estimates of the quadrature errors which are optimal if $w$ is an $A_\infty$ weight in the deterministic case setting or if $w$ is a product weight in the randomized case setting. Our results show that randomized algorithms can provide a faster convergence rate than that of the deterministic ones when $p&gt;1$.
  Similar results are also established on the unit ball and the standard simplex of $\mathbb R^d$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17546v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiansong Li, Heping Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A $C^0$-continuous nonconforming virtual element method for linear strain gradient elasticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A robust $C^0$-continuous nonconforming virtual element method (VEM) is developed for a boundary value problem arising from strain gradient elasticity in two dimensions, with the family of polygonal meshes satisfying a very general geometric assumption given in Brezzi et al. (2009) and Chen and Huang (2018). The stability condition of the VEMs is derived by establishing Korn-type inequalities and inverse inequalities. Some crucial commutative relations for locking-free analysis as in elastic problems are derived. The sharp and uniform error estimates with respect to both the microscopic parameter and the Lam\'e coefficient are achieved in the lowest-order case, which is also verified by numerical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17631v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianguo Huang, Yue Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of instantaneous pressures in an Eulerian finite element method for moving boundary flow problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper focuses on identifying the cause and proposing a remedy for the problem of spurious pressure oscillations in a sharp-interface immersed boundary finite element method for incompressible flow problems in moving domains. The numerical method belongs to the class of Eulerian unfitted finite element methods. It employs a cutFEM discretization in space and a standard BDF time-stepping scheme, enabled by a discrete extension of the solution from the physical domain into the ambient space using ghost-penalty stabilization. To investigate the origin of spurious temporal pressure oscillations, we revisit a finite element stability analysis for the steady domain case and extend it to derive a stability estimate for the pressure in the $L^\infty(L^2)$-norm that is uniform with respect to discretization parameters. By identifying where the arguments fail in the context of a moving domain, we propose a variant of the method that ensures unconditional stability of the instantaneous pressure. As a result, the modified method eliminates spurious pressure oscillations. We also present extensive numerical studies aimed at illustrating our findings and exploring the effects of fluid viscosity, geometry approximation, mass conservation, discretization and stabilization parameters, and the choice of finite element spaces on the occurrence and magnitude of spurious temporal pressure oscillations. The results of the experiments demonstrate a significant improvement in the robustness and accuracy of the proposed method compared to existing approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17657v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxim Olshanskii, Henry von Wahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast measure modification of orthogonal polynomials via matrices with displacement structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17663v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well known that matrices with low Hessenberg-structured displacement rank enjoy fast algorithms for certain matrix factorizations. We show how $n\times n$ principal finite sections of the Gram matrix for the orthogonal polynomial measure modification problem has such a displacement structure, unlocking a collection of fast algorithms for computing connection coefficients (as the upper-triangular Cholesky factor) between a known orthogonal polynomial family and the modified family. In general, the ${\cal O}(n^3)$ complexity is reduced to ${\cal O}(n^2)$, and if the symmetric Gram matrix has upper and lower bandwidth b, then the ${\cal O}(b^2n)$ complexity for a banded Cholesky factorization is reduced to ${\cal O}(b n)$. In the case of modified Chebyshev polynomials, we show that the Gram matrix is a symmetric Toeplitz-plus-Hankel matrix, and if the modified Chebyshev moments decay algebraically, then a hierarchical off-diagonal low-rank structure is observed in the Gram matrix, enabling a further reduction in the complexity of an approximate Cholesky factorization powered by randomized numerical linear algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17663v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karim Gumerov, Samantha Rigg, Richard Mikael Slevinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the importance of the $\varepsilon$-regularization of the distribution-dependent Mumford-Shah model for hyperspectral image segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17676v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, the distribution-dependent Mumford-Shah model for hyperspectral image segmentation was introduced. It approximates an image based on first and second order statistics using a data term, that is built of a Mahalanobis distance plus a covariance regularization, and the total variation as spatial regularization. Moreover, to achieve feasibility, the appearing matrices are restricted to symmetric positive definite ones with eigenvalues exceeding a certain threshold. This threshold is chosen in advance as a data-independent parameter. In this article, we study theoretical properties of the model. In particular, we prove the existence of minimizers of the functional and show its $\Gamma$-convergence when the threshold regularizing the eigenvalues of the matrices tends to zero. It turns out that in the $\Gamma$-limit we lose the guaranteed existence of minimizers; and we give an example of an image where the $\Gamma$-limit indeed has no minimizer. Finally, we derive a formula for the minimum eigenvalues of the covariance matrices appearing in the functional that hints under which conditions the functional is able to handle the data without regularizing the eigenvalues. The results of this article demonstrate the significance and importance of the eigenvalue regularization to the model and that it cannot be dropped without substantial modifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17676v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-75802-7_10</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jan-Christopher Cohrs, Benjamin Berkels</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient Flow Finite Element Discretisations with Energy-Based $hp$-Adaptivity for the Gross-Pitaevskii Equation with Angular Momentum Rotation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17680v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article deals with the stationary Gross-Pitaevskii non-linear eigenvalue problem in the presence of a rotating magnetic field that is used to model macroscopic quantum effects such as Bose-Einstein condensates (BECs). In this regime, the ground-state wave-function can exhibit an a priori unknown number of quantum vortices at unknown locations, which necessitates the exploitation of adaptive numerical strategies. To this end, we consider the conforming finite element method and introduce a combination of a Sobolev gradient descent that respects the energy-topology of the problem to solve the non-linearity and an $hp$-adaptive strategy that is solely based on energy decay rather than a posteriori error estimators for the refinement process. Numerical results demonstrate that the $hp$-adaptive strategy is highly efficient in terms of accuracy to compute the ground-state wave function and energy for several test problems where we observe exponential convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17680v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Heid, Paul Houston, Benjamin Stamm, Thomas P. Wihler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint denoising and line distortion correction for raster-scanned image series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The problem of noise in a general data acquisition procedure can be resolved more accurately if it is based on a model that describes well the distortions of the data including both spatial and intensity changes. The focus of this article is the modeling of the position distortions during sequential data acquisitions. A guiding example is the data obtained by Scanning Transmission Electron Microscopy (STEM) and High Angular Annular Dark Field (HAADF) data, in particular. The article discusses different models of the position noise and their numerical implementations comparing some computational results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17693v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-75802-7_6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Berkels, Peter Binev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear model reduction with Neural Galerkin schemes on quadratic manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17695v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Leveraging nonlinear parametrizations for model reduction can overcome the Kolmogorov barrier that affects transport-dominated problems. In this work, we build on the reduced dynamics given by Neural Galerkin schemes and propose to parametrize the corresponding reduced solutions on quadratic manifolds. We show that the solutions of the proposed quadratic-manifold Neural Galerkin reduced models are locally unique and minimize the residual norm over time, which promotes stability and accuracy. For linear problems, quadratic-manifold Neural Galerkin reduced models achieve online efficiency in the sense that the costs of predictions scale independently of the state dimension of the underlying full model. For nonlinear problems, we show that Neural Galerkin schemes allow using separate collocation points for evaluating the residual function from the full-model grid points, which can be seen as a form of hyper-reduction. Numerical experiments with advecting waves and densities of charged particles in an electric field show that quadratic-manifold Neural Galerkin reduced models lead to orders of magnitude speedups compared to full models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17695v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Weder, Paul Schwerdtner, Benjamin Peherstorfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear trend of COVID-19 infection time series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00866v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have developed a nonlinear method of time series analysis that allows us to obtain multiple nonlinear trends without harmonics from a given set of numerical data. We propose to apply the method to recognize the ongoing status of COVID-19 infection with an analytical equation for nonlinear trends. We found that there is only a single nonlinear trend, and this result justifies the use of a week-based infection growth rate. In addition, the fit with the obtained analytical equation for the nonlinear trend holds for a duration of more than three months for the Delta variant infection time series. The fitting also visualizes the transition to the Omicron variant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00866v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1587/nolta.14.165</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nolta, Volume 14, Issue 2, Pages 165-174, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fumihiko Ishiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed geometry information regularization for image multiplicative denoising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16445v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper focuses on solving the multiplicative gamma denoising problem via a variation model. Variation-based regularization models have been extensively employed in a variety of inverse problem tasks in image processing. However, sufficient geometric priors and efficient algorithms are still very difficult problems in the model design process. To overcome these issues, in this paper we propose a mixed geometry information model, incorporating area term and curvature term as prior knowledge. In addition to its ability to effectively remove multiplicative noise, our model is able to preserve edges and prevent staircasing effects. Meanwhile, to address the challenges stemming from the nonlinearity and non-convexity inherent in higher-order regularization, we propose the efficient additive operator splitting algorithm (AOS) and scalar auxiliary variable algorithm (SAV). The unconditional stability possessed by these algorithms enables us to use large time step. And the SAV method shows higher computational accuracy in our model. We employ the second order SAV algorithm to further speed up the calculation while maintaining accuracy. We demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of the model and algorithms by a lot of numerical experiments, where the model we proposed has better features texturepreserving properties without generating any false information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16445v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengkun Yang, Zhichang Guo, Jia Li, Fanghui Song, Wenjuan Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kernel Methods for the Approximation of the Eigenfunctions of the Koopman Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16588v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Koopman operator provides a linear framework to study nonlinear dynamical systems. Its spectra offer valuable insights into system dynamics, but the operator can exhibit both discrete and continuous spectra, complicating direct computations. In this paper, we introduce a kernel-based method to construct the principal eigenfunctions of the Koopman operator without explicitly computing the operator itself. These principal eigenfunctions are associated with the equilibrium dynamics, and their eigenvalues match those of the linearization of the nonlinear system at the equilibrium point. We exploit the structure of the principal eigenfunctions by decomposing them into linear and nonlinear components. The linear part corresponds to the left eigenvector of the system's linearization at the equilibrium, while the nonlinear part is obtained by solving a partial differential equation (PDE) using kernel methods. Our approach avoids common issues such as spectral pollution and spurious eigenvalues, which can arise in previous methods. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our algorithm through numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16588v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonghyeon Lee, Boumediene Hamzi, Boya Hou, Houman Owhadi, Gabriele Santin, Umesh Vaidya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KKANs: Kurkova-Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks and Their Learning Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16738v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the Kolmogorov-Arnold representation theorem and Kurkova's principle of using approximate representations, we propose the Kurkova-Kolmogorov-Arnold Network (KKAN), a new two-block architecture that combines robust multi-layer perceptron (MLP) based inner functions with flexible linear combinations of basis functions as outer functions. We first prove that KKAN is a universal approximator, and then we demonstrate its versatility across scientific machine-learning applications, including function regression, physics-informed machine learning (PIML), and operator-learning frameworks. The benchmark results show that KKANs outperform MLPs and the original Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KANs) in function approximation and operator learning tasks and achieve performance comparable to fully optimized MLPs for PIML. To better understand the behavior of the new representation models, we analyze their geometric complexity and learning dynamics using information bottleneck theory, identifying three universal learning stages, fitting, transition, and diffusion, across all types of architectures. We find a strong correlation between geometric complexity and signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), with optimal generalization achieved during the diffusion stage. Additionally, we propose self-scaled residual-based attention weights to maintain high SNR dynamically, ensuring uniform convergence and prolonged learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16738v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Diego Toscano, Li-Lian Wang, George Em Karniadakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient flows on metric graphs with reservoirs: Microscopic derivation and multiscale limits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16775v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study evolution equations on metric graphs with reservoirs, that is graphs where a one-dimensional interval is associated to each edge and, in addition, the vertices are able to store and exchange mass with these intervals. Focusing on the case where the dynamics are driven by an entropy functional defined both on the metric edges and vertices, we provide a rigorous understanding of such systems of coupled ordinary and partial differential equations as (generalized) gradient flows in continuity equation format. Approximating the edges by a sequence of vertices, which yields a fully discrete system, we are able to establish existence of solutions in this formalism. Furthermore, we study several scaling limits using the recently developed framework of EDP convergence with embeddings to rigorously show convergence to gradient flows on reduced metric and combinatorial graphs. Finally, numerical studies confirm our theoretical findings and provide additional insights into the dynamics under rescaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16775v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georg Heinze, Jan-Frederik Pietschmann, Andr\'e Schlichting</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Nonlinear Energy Supply and Demand System Using Physics-Informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17001v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonlinear differential equations and systems play a crucial role in modeling systems where time-dependent factors exhibit nonlinear characteristics. Due to their nonlinear nature, solving such systems often presents significant difficulties and challenges. In this study, we propose a method utilizing Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) to solve the nonlinear energy supply-demand (ESD) system. We design a neural network with four outputs, where each output approximates a function that corresponds to one of the unknown functions in the nonlinear system of differential equations describing the four-dimensional ESD problem. The neural network model is then trained and the parameters are identified, optimized to achieve a more accurate solution. The solutions obtained from the neural network for this problem are equivalent when we compare and evaluate them against the Runge-Kutta numerical method of order 4/5 (RK45). However, the method utilizing neural networks is considered a modern and promising approach, as it effectively exploits the superior computational power of advanced computer systems, especially in solving complex problems. Another advantage is that the neural network model, after being trained, can solve the nonlinear system of differential equations across a continuous domain. In other words, neural networks are not only trained to approximate the solution functions for the nonlinear ESD system but can also represent the complex dynamic relationships between the system's components. However, this approach requires significant time and computational power due to the need for model training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17001v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Van Truong Vo, Samad Noeiaghdam, Denis Sidorov, Aliona Dreglea, Liguo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Convergent ADMM Algorithm for Grain Boundary Energy Minimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17058v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a constrained minimization problem that arise from materials science to determine the dislocation (line defect) structure of grain boundaries. The problems aims to minimize the energy of the grain boundary with dislocation structure subject to the constraint of Frank's formula. In this constrained minimization problem, the objective function, i.e., the grain boundary energy, is nonconvex and separable, and the constraints are linear. To solve this constrained minimization problem, we modify the alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) with an increasing penalty parameter. We provide a convergence analysis of the modified ADMM in this nonconvex minimization problem, with settings not considered by the existing ADMM convergence studies. Specifically, in the linear constraints, the coefficient matrix of each subvariable block is of full column rank. This property makes each subvariable minimization strongly convex if the penalty parameter is large enough, and contributes to the convergence of ADMM without any convex assumption on the entire objective function. We prove that the limit of the sequence from the modified ADMM is primal feasible and is the stationary point of the augmented Lagrangian function. Furthermore, we obtain sufficient conditions to show that the objective function is quasi-convex and thus it has a unique minimum over the given domain. Numerical examples are presented to validate the convergence of the algorithm, and results of the penalty method, the augmented Lagrangian method, and the modified ADMM are compared.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17058v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Wu, Luchan Zhang, Yang Xiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A crack-length control technique for phase field fracture in FFT homogenization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17445v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modeling the propagation of cracks at the microscopic level is fundamental to understand the effect of the microstructure on the fracture process. Nevertheless, microscopic propagation is often unstable and when using phase field fracture poor convergence is found or, in the case of using staggered algorithms, leads to the presence of jumps in the evolution of the cracks. In this work, a novel method is proposed to perform micromechanical simulations with phase field fracture imposing monotonic increases of crack length and allowing the use of monolithic implementations, being able to resolve all the snap-backs during the unstable propagation phases. The method is derived for FFT based solvers in order to exploit its very high numerical performance n micromechanical problems, but an equivalent method is also developed for Finite Elements (FE) showing the equivalence of both implementations. It is shown that the stress-strain curves and the crack paths obtained using the crack control method are superposed in stable propagation regimes to those obtained using strain control with a staggered scheme. J-integral calculations confirm that during the propagation process in the crack control method, the energy release rate remains constant and equal to an effective fracture energy that has been determined as function of the discretization for FFT simulations. Finally, to show the potential of the method, the technique is applied to simulate crack propagation through the microstructure of composites and porous materials providing an estimation of the effective fracture toughness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17445v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Aranda, Javier Segurado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Learning Theory for Neural Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17582v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present statistical convergence results for the learning of (possibly) non-linear mappings in infinite-dimensional spaces. Specifically, given a map $G_0:\mathcal X\to\mathcal Y$ between two separable Hilbert spaces, we analyze the problem of recovering $G_0$ from $n\in\mathbb N$ noisy input-output pairs $(x_i, y_i)_{i=1}^n$ with $y_i = G_0 (x_i)+\varepsilon_i$; here the $x_i\in\mathcal X$ represent randomly drawn 'design' points, and the $\varepsilon_i$ are assumed to be either i.i.d. white noise processes or subgaussian random variables in $\mathcal{Y}$. We provide general convergence results for least-squares-type empirical risk minimizers over compact regression classes $\mathbf G\subseteq L^\infty(X,Y)$, in terms of their approximation properties and metric entropy bounds, which are derived using empirical process techniques. This generalizes classical results from finite-dimensional nonparametric regression to an infinite-dimensional setting. As a concrete application, we study an encoder-decoder based neural operator architecture termed FrameNet. Assuming $G_0$ to be holomorphic, we prove algebraic (in the sample size $n$) convergence rates in this setting, thereby overcoming the curse of dimensionality. To illustrate the wide applicability, as a prototypical example we discuss the learning of the non-linear solution operator to a parametric elliptic partial differential equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17582v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Reinhardt, Sven Wang, Jakob Zech</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An efficient volume-preserving MBO scheme for data clustering and classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17694v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose and study a novel efficient algorithm for clustering and classification tasks based on the famous MBO scheme. On the one hand, inspired by Jacobs et al. [J. Comp. Phys. 2018], we introduce constraints on the size of clusters leading to a linear integer problem. We prove that the solution to this problem is induced by a novel order statistic. This viewpoint allows us to develop exact and highly efficient algorithms to solve such constrained integer problems. On the other hand, we prove an estimate of the computational complexity of our scheme, which is better than any available provable bounds for the state of the art. This rigorous analysis is based on a variational viewpoint that connects this scheme to volume-preserving mean curvature flow in the big data and small time-step limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17694v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabius Kr\"amer, Tim Laux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical study of refined conjectures of the BSD type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17703v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 1987, Mazur and Tate stated conjectures which, in some cases, resemble the classical Birch-Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture and its $p$-adic analog. We study experimentally three conjectures stated by Mazur and Tate using SageMath. Our findings indicate discrepancies in some of the original statements of some of the conjectures presented by Mazur and Tate. However, a slight modification on the statement of these conjectures does appear to hold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17703v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan-Pablo Llerena-C\'ordova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix Decomposition and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2201.00145v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 1954, Alston S. Householder published Principles of Numerical Analysis, one of the first modern treatments on matrix decomposition that favored a (block) LU decomposition-the factorization of a matrix into the product of lower and upper triangular matrices. And now, matrix decomposition has become a core technology in machine learning, largely due to the development of the back propagation algorithm in fitting a neural network. The sole aim of this survey is to give a self-contained introduction to concepts and mathematical tools in numerical linear algebra and matrix analysis in order to seamlessly introduce matrix decomposition techniques and their applications in subsequent sections. However, we clearly realize our inability to cover all the useful and interesting results concerning matrix decomposition and given the paucity of scope to present this discussion, e.g., the separated analysis of the Euclidean space, Hermitian space, Hilbert space, and things in the complex domain. We refer the reader to literature in the field of linear algebra for a more detailed introduction to the related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2201.00145v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of the Kolmogorov-Arnold representation using the Newton-Kaczmarz method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.08194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.08194v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is known that any continuous multivariate function can be represented exactly by a composition functions of a single variable -- the so-called Kolmogorov-Arnold representation. It can be a convenient tool for tasks where it is required to obtain a predictive model that maps some vector input of a black box system into a scalar output. In this case, the representation may not be exact, and it is more correct to refer to such structure as the Kolmogorov-Arnold model (or, as more recently popularised, `network'). Construction of such model based on the recorded input-output data is a challenging task. In the present paper, it is suggested to decompose the underlying functions of the representation into continuous basis functions and parameters. It is then proposed to find the parameters using the Newton-Kaczmarz method for solving systems of non-linear equations. The algorithm is then modified to support parallelisation. The paper demonstrates that such approach is also an excellent tool for data-driven solution of partial differential equations. Numerical examples show that for the considered model, the Newton-Kaczmarz method for parameter estimation is efficient and more robust with respect to the section of the initial guess than the straightforward application of the Gauss-Newton method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.08194v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Poluektov, Andrew Polar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\omega$-Condition Number: Applications to Optimal Preconditioning and Low Rank Generalized Jacobian Updating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13195v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Preconditioning is essential in iterative methods for solving linear systems. It is also the implicit objective in updating approximations of Jacobians in optimization methods, e.g.,in quasi-Newton methods. Motivated by the latter, we study a nonclassic matrix condition number, the $\omega$-condition number, $\omega$ for short. $\omega$ is the ratio of the arithmetic and geometric means of the singular values, rather than largest and smallest. Moreover, unlike the latter classical $\kappa$ condition number, $\omega$ is not invariant under inversion, an important point that allows one to recall that it is the conditioning of the inverse that is important. Our study is in the context of optimal conditioning for: (i) low rank updating of generalized Jacobians arising in the context of nonsmooth Newton methods; and (ii) iterative methods for linear systems; (iia) clustering of eigenvalues; (iib) convergence rates; and (iic) estimating the actual condition of a linear system. We emphasize that the simple functions in $\omega$ allow one to exploit optimality conditions and derive explicit formulae for $\omega$-optimal preconditioners of special structure. Connections to partial Cholesky type sparse preconditioners are made that modify the iterates of Cholesky decomposition by including the entire diagonal at each iteration. Our results confirm the efficacy of using the $\omega$-condition number compared to the classical $\kappa$-condition number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13195v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Woosuk L. Jung, David Torregrosa-Bel\'en, Henry Wolkowicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R3MG: R-tree based agglomeration of polytopal grids with applications to multilevel methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18505v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel approach to perform agglomeration of polygonal and polyhedral grids based on spatial indices. Agglomeration strategies are a key ingredient in polytopal methods for PDEs as they are used to generate (hierarchies of) computational grids from an initial grid. Spatial indices are specialized data structures that significantly accelerate queries involving spatial relationships in arbitrary space dimensions. We show how the construction of the R-tree spatial database of an arbitrary fine grid offers a natural and efficient agglomeration strategy with the following characteristics: i) the process is fully automated, robust, and dimension-independent, ii) it automatically produces a balanced and nested hierarchy of agglomerates, and iii) the shape of the agglomerates is tightly close to the respective axis aligned bounding boxes. Moreover, the R-tree approach provides a full hierarchy of nested agglomerates which permits fast query and allows for efficient geometric multigrid methods to be applied also to those cases where a hierarchy of grids is not present at construction time. We present several examples based on polygonal discontinuous Galerkin methods, confirming the effectiveness of our approach in the context of challenging three-dimensional geometries and the design of geometric multigrid preconditioners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18505v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Feder, Andrea Cangiani, Luca Heltai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Order Reduction of Exponential Runge--Kutta Methods: Non-Commuting Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00470v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonlinear parabolic equations are central to numerous applications in science and engineering, posing significant challenges for analytical solutions and necessitating efficient numerical methods. Exponential integrators have recently gained attention for handling stiff differential equations. This paper explores exponential Runge--Kutta methods for solving such equations, focusing on the simplified form $u^{\prime}(t)+A u(t)=B u(t)$, where $A$ generates an analytic semigroup and $B$ is relatively bounded with respect to $A$. By treating $A$ exactly and $B$ explicitly, we derive error bounds for exponential Runge--Kutta methods up to third order. Our analysis shows that these methods maintain their order under mild regularity conditions on the initial data $u_0$, while also addressing the phenomenon of order reduction in higher-order methods. Through a careful convergence analysis and numerical investigations, this study provides a comprehensive understanding of the applicability and limitations of exponential Runge--Kutta methods in solving linear parabolic equations involving two unbounded and non-commuting operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00470v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trung Hau Hoang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure numerical simulations using fully homomorphic encryption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21824v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Data privacy is a significant concern when using numerical simulations for sensitive information such as medical, financial, or engineering data. This issue becomes especially relevant in untrusted environments like public cloud infrastructures. Fully homomorphic encryption (FHE) offers a promising solution for achieving data privacy by enabling secure computations directly on encrypted data. In this paper, aimed at computational scientists, we explore the viability of FHE-based, privacy-preserving numerical simulations of partial differential equations. We begin with an overview of the CKKS scheme, a widely used FHE method for computations with real numbers. Next, we introduce our Julia-based packages OpenFHE$.$jl and SecureArithmetic$.$jl, which wrap the OpenFHE C++ library and provide a convenient interface for secure arithmetic operations. We then evaluate the accuracy and performance of key FHE operations in OpenFHE as a baseline for more complex numerical algorithms. Following that, we demonstrate the application of FHE to scientific computing by implementing two finite difference schemes for the linear advection equation. Finally, we discuss potential challenges and solutions for extending secure numerical simulations to other models and methods. Our results show that cryptographically secure numerical simulations are possible, but that careful consideration must be given to the computational overhead and the numerical errors introduced by using FHE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21824v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arseniy Kholod, Yuriy Polyakov, Michael Schlottke-Lakemper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-based stabilized finite element approximations of the Poisson--Nernst--Planck equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01358v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present and analyze two stabilized finite element methods for solving numerically the Poisson--Nernst--Planck equations. The stabilization we consider is carried out by using a shock detector and a discrete graph Laplacian operator for the ion equations, whereas the discrete equation for the electric potential need not be stabilized. Discrete solutions stemmed from the first algorithm preserve both maximum and minimum discrete principles. For the second algorithm, its discrete solutions are conceived so that they hold discrete principles and obey an entropy law provided that an acuteness condition is imposed for meshes. Remarkably the latter is found to be unconditionally stable. We validate our methodology through numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01358v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jes\'us Bonilla, Juan Vicente Guti\'errez-Santacreu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel in time partially explicit splitting scheme for high contrast multiscale problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09244v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Solving multiscale diffusion problems is often computationally expensive due to the spatial and temporal discretization challenges arising from high-contrast coefficients. To address this issue, a partially explicit temporal splitting scheme is proposed. By appropriately constructing multiscale spaces, the spatial multiscale property is effectively managed, and it has been demonstrated that the temporal step size is independent of the contrast. To enhance simulation speed, we propose a parallel algorithm for the multiscale flow problem that leverages the partially explicit temporal splitting scheme. The idea is first to evolve the partially explicit system using a coarse time step size, then correct the solution on each coarse time interval with a fine propagator, for which we consider both the sequential solver and all-at-once solver. This procedure is then performed iteratively till convergence. We analyze the stability and convergence of the proposed algorithm. The numerical experiments demonstrate that the proposed algorithm achieves high numerical accuracy for high-contrast problems and converges in a relatively small number of iterations. The number of iterations stays stable as the number of coarse intervals increases, thus significantly improving computational efficiency through parallel processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09244v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yating Wang, Zhengya Yang, Wing Tat Leung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal-rate error estimates and a twice decoupled solver for a backward Euler finite element scheme of the Doyle-Fuller-Newman model of lithium-ion batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15722v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the convergence of a backward Euler finite element discretization applied to a multi-domain and multi-scale elliptic-parabolic system, derived from the Doyle-Fuller-Newman model for lithium-ion batteries. We establish optimal-order error estimates for the solution in the norms $l^2(H^1)$ and $l^2(L^2(H^q_r))$, $q=0,1$. To improve computational efficiency, we propose a novel solver that accelerates the solution process and controls memory usage. Numerical experiments with realistic battery parameters validate the theoretical error rates and demonstrate the significantly superior performance of the proposed solver over existing solvers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15722v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu Xu, Liqun Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Numerical Approximation of the Karhunen-Lo\`{e}ve Expansion for Random Fields with Random Discrete Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00027v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In many applications, random fields reflect uncertain parameters, and often their moments are part of the modeling process and thus well known. However, there are practical situations where this is simply not the case. Therefore, we do not assume that we know moments or expansion terms of the random fields, but only have discretized samples of them. The main contribution of this paper concerns the approximation of the true covariance operator from these finite measurements. We derive explicit error estimates that include the finite-rank approximation error of the covariance operator, the Monte Carlo-type error for sampling in the stochastic domain, and the numerical discretization error in the physical domain. For this purpose, we use modern tapering covariance estimators adapted to high-dimensional applications, where the dimension is introduced by the resolution of the measurement process. This allows us to give sufficient conditions on the three discretization parameters to guarantee that the error is kept below a prescribed accuracy $\varepsilon$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00027v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Griebel, Guanglian Li, Christian Rieger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-Band ECoGNet for ECoG Decoding on Classification Task</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00378v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the application of brain-computer interface (BCI), being able to accurately decode brain signals is a critical task. For the multi-class classification task of brain signal ECoG, how to improve the classification accuracy is one of the current research hotspots. ECoG acquisition uses a high-density electrode array and a high sampling frequency, which makes ECoG data have a certain high similarity and data redundancy in the temporal domain, and also unique spatial pattern in spatial domain. How to effectively extract features is both exciting and challenging. Previous work found that visual-related ECoG can carry visual information via frequency and spatial domain. Based on this finding, we focused on using deep learning to design frequency and spatial feature extraction modules, and proposed a Bi-Band ECoGNet model based on deep learning. The main contributions of this paper are: 1) The Bi-BCWT (Bi-Band Channel-Wise Transform) neural network module is designed to replace the time-consume method MST, this module greatly improves the model calculation and data storage efficiency, and effectively increases the training speed; 2) The Bi-BCWT module can effectively take into account the information both in low-frequency and high-frequency domain, which is more conducive to ECoG multi-classification tasks; 3) ECoG is acquired using 2D electrode array, the newly designed 2D Spatial-Temporal feature encoder can extract the 2D spatial feature better. Experiments have shown that the unique 2D spatial data structure can effectively improve classification accuracy; 3) Compared with previous work, the Bi-Band ECoGNet model is smaller and has higher performance, with an accuracy increase of 1.24%, and the model training speed is increased by 6 times, which is more suitable for BCI applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00378v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changqing Ji, Keisuke Kawasaki, Isao Hasegwa, Takayuki Okatani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Channel Compression Method for Brain Signal Decoding on Classification Task</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02078v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the application of brain-computer interface (BCI), while pursuing accurate decoding of brain signals, we also need consider the computational efficiency of BCI devices. ECoG signals are multi-channel temporal signals which is collected using a high-density electrode array at a high sampling frequency. The data between channels has a high similarity or redundancy in the temporal domain. The redundancy of data not only reduces the computational efficiency of the model, but also overwhelms the extraction of effective features, resulting in a decrease in performance. How to efficiently utilize ECoG multi-channel signals is one of the research topics. Effective channel screening or compression can greatly reduce the model size, thereby improving computational efficiency, this would be a good direction to solve the problem. Based on previous work [1], this paper proposes a very simple channel compression method, which uses a learnable matrix to perform matrix multiplication on the original channels, that is, assigning weights to the channels and then linearly add them up. This effectively reduces the number of final channels. In the experiment, we used the vision-based ECoG multi-classification dataset owned by our laboratory to test the proposed channel selection (compression) method. We found that the new method can compress the original 128-channel ECoG signal to 32 channels (of which subject MonJ is compressed to 8 channels), greatly reducing the size of the model. The demand for GPU memory resources during model training is reduced by about 68.57%, 84.33% for each subject respectively; the model training speed also increased up around 3.82, 4.65 times of the original speed for each subject respectively. More importantly, the performance of the model has improved by about 1.10% compared with our previous work, reached the SOTA level of our unique visual based ECoG dataset</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02078v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changqing Ji, Keisuke Kawasaki, Isao Hasegawa, Takayuki Okatani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical schemes for a fully nonlinear coagulation-fragmentation model coming from wave kinetic theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05402v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article introduces a novel numerical approach, based on Finite Volume Techniques, for studying fully nonlinear coagulation-fragmentation models, where both the coagulation and fragmentation components of the collision operator are nonlinear. The models come from $3-$wave kinetic equations, a pivotal framework in wave turbulence theory. Despite the importance of wave turbulence theory in physics and mechanics, there have been very few numerical schemes for $3-$wave kinetic equations, in which no ad-hoc additional assumptions are imposed on the evolution of the solutions, and the current manuscript provides one of the first of such schemes. To the best of our knowledge, this also is the first numerical scheme capable of accurately capturing the long-term asymptotic behavior of solutions to a fully nonlinear coagulation-fragmentation model that includes both forward and backward energy cascades. The scheme is implemented on some test problems, demonstrating strong alignment with theoretical predictions of energy cascade rates. We further introduce a weighted Finite Volume variant to ensure energy conservation across varying degrees of kernel homogeneity. Convergence and first-order consistency are established through theoretical analysis and verified by experimental convergence orders in test cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05402v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arijit Das, Minh-Binh Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolicity of a semi-Lagrangian formulation of the hydrostatic free-surface Euler system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.15083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.15083v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By a semi-Lagrangian change of coordinates, the hydrostatic Euler equations describing free-surface sheared flows is rewritten as a system of quasilinear equations, where stability conditions can be determined by the analysis of its hyperbolic structure. The system one obtains can be written as a quasi linear system in time and horizontal variables and involves no more vertical derivatives. However, the coefficients in front of the horizontal derivatives include an integral operator acting on the new vertical variable. The spectrum of these operators is studied in detail, in particular it includes a continuous part. Riemann invariants are then determined as conserved quantities along the characteristic curves. Examples of solutions are provided, in particular stationary solutions and solutions blowing-up in finite time. Eventually, we propose an exact multilayer $\mathbb{P}_0$-discretization, which could be used to solve numerically this semi-Lagrangian system, and analyze the eigenvalues of the corresponding discretized operator to investigate the hyperbolic nature of the approximated system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.15083v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6544/ad9b65</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nonlinearity, 38, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bernard Di Martino, Chourouk El Hassanieh, Edwige Godlewski, Julien Guillod, Jacques Sainte-Marie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Unknown Stochastic Dynamical System via Autoencoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10001v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a numerical method to learn an accurate predictive model for an unknown stochastic dynamical system from its trajectory data. The method seeks to approximate the unknown flow map of the underlying system. It employs the idea of autoencoder to identify the unobserved latent random variables. In our approach, we design an encoding function to discover the latent variables, which are modeled as unit Gaussian, and a decoding function to reconstruct the future states of the system. Both the encoder and decoder are expressed as deep neural networks (DNNs). Once the DNNs are trained by the trajectory data, the decoder serves as a predictive model for the unknown stochastic system. Through an extensive set of numerical examples, we demonstrate that the method is able to produce long-term system predictions by using short bursts of trajectory data. It is also applicable to systems driven by non-Gaussian noises.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10001v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1615/JMachLearnModelComput.2024055773</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Machine Learning for Modeling and Computing, 5 (2024), 87-112</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhongshu Xu, Yuan Chen, Qifan Chen, Dongbin Xiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate Contraction of Arbitrary Tensor Networks with a Flexible and Efficient Density Matrix Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09769v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tensor network contractions are widely used in statistical physics, quantum computing, and computer science. We introduce a method to efficiently approximate tensor network contractions using low-rank approximations, where each intermediate tensor generated during the contractions is approximated as a low-rank binary tree tensor network. The proposed algorithm has the flexibility to incorporate a large portion of the environment when performing low-rank approximations, which can lead to high accuracy for a given rank. Here, the environment refers to the remaining set of tensors in the network, and low-rank approximations with larger environments can generally provide higher accuracy. For contracting tensor networks defined on lattices, the proposed algorithm can be viewed as a generalization of the standard boundary-based algorithms. In addition, the algorithm includes a cost-efficient density matrix algorithm for approximating a tensor network with a general graph structure into a tree structure, whose computational cost is asymptotically upper-bounded by that of the standard algorithm that uses canonicalization. Experimental results indicate that the proposed technique outperforms previously proposed approximate tensor network contraction algorithms for multiple problems in terms of both accuracy and efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09769v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linjian Ma, Matthew Fishman, Miles Stoudenmire, Edgar Solomonik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizability of Graph Neural Network Force Fields for Predicting Solid-State Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09931v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine-learned force fields (MLFFs) promise to offer a computationally efficient alternative to ab initio simulations for complex molecular systems. However, ensuring their generalizability beyond training data is crucial for their wide application in studying solid materials. This work investigates the ability of a graph neural network (GNN)-based MLFF, trained on Lennard-Jones Argon, to describe solid-state phenomena not explicitly included during training. We assess the MLFF's performance in predicting phonon density of states (PDOS) for a perfect face-centered cubic (FCC) crystal structure at both zero and finite temperatures. Additionally, we evaluate vacancy migration rates and energy barriers in an imperfect crystal using direct molecular dynamics (MD) simulations and the string method. Notably, vacancy configurations were absent from the training data. Our results demonstrate the MLFF's capability to capture essential solid-state properties with good agreement to reference data, even for unseen configurations. We further discuss data engineering strategies to enhance the generalizability of MLFFs. The proposed set of benchmark tests and workflow for evaluating MLFF performance in describing perfect and imperfect crystals pave the way for reliable application of MLFFs in studying complex solid-state materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09931v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaswat Mohanty, Yifan Wang, Wei Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chebyshev Feature Neural Network for Accurate Function Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19135v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a new Deep Neural Network (DNN) architecture capable of approximating functions up to machine accuracy. Termed Chebyshev Feature Neural Network (CFNN), the new structure employs Chebyshev functions with learnable frequencies as the first hidden layer, followed by the standard fully connected hidden layers. The learnable frequencies of the Chebyshev layer are initialized with exponential distributions to cover a wide range of frequencies. Combined with a multi-stage training strategy, we demonstrate that this CFNN structure can achieve machine accuracy during training. A comprehensive set of numerical examples for dimensions up to $20$ are provided to demonstrate the effectiveness and scalability of the method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19135v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongshu Xu, Yuan Chen, Dongbin Xiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and Robust Hexahedral Mesh Optimization via Augmented Lagrangian, L-BFGS, and Line Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11656v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a new software package, ``HexOpt,'' for improving the quality of all-hexahedral (all-hex) meshes by maximizing the minimum mixed scaled Jacobian-Jacobian energy functional, and projecting the surface points of the all-hex meshes onto the input triangular mesh. The proposed HexOpt method takes as input a surface triangular mesh and a volumetric all-hex mesh. A constrained optimization problem is formulated to improve mesh quality using a novel function that combines Jacobian and scaled Jacobian metrics which are rectified and scaled to quadratic measures, while preserving the surface geometry. This optimization problem is solved using the augmented Lagrangian (AL) method, where the Lagrangian terms enforce the constraint that surface points must remain on the triangular mesh. Specifically, corner points stay exactly at the corner, edge points are confined to the edges, and face points are free to move across the surface. To take the advantage of the Quasi-Newton method while tackling the high-dimensional variable problem, the Limited-Broyden-Fletcher-Goldfarb-Shanno (L-BFGS) algorithm is employed. The step size for each iteration is determined by the Armijo line search. Coupled with smart Laplacian smoothing, HexOpt has demonstrated robustness and efficiency, successfully applying to 3D models and hex meshes generated by different methods without requiring any manual intervention or parameter adjustment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11656v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua Tong, Yongjie Jessica Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Monge problem by Hilbert space embeddings of probability measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03478v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose deep learning methods for classical Monge's optimal mass transportation problems, where where the distribution constraint is treated as penalty terms defined by the maximum mean discrepancy in the theory of Hilbert space embeddings of probability measures. We prove that the transport maps given by the proposed methods converge to optimal transport maps in the problem with $L^2$ cost. Several numerical experiments validate our methods. In particular, we show that our methods are applicable to large-scale Monge problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03478v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takafumi Saito, Yumiharu Nakano</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
