<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NA</link>
    <description>math.NA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the space-time variational formulation for the wave equation with source term in $L^2(Q)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive a variational formulation for the scalar wave equation in the second-order formulation on bounded Lipschitz domains and homogeneous initial conditions. We investigate a variational framework in a bounded space-time cylinder $Q$ with a new solution space and the test space $L^2(Q)$ for source terms in $L^2(Q)$. Using existence and uniqueness results in $H^1(Q)$, we prove that this variational setting fits the inf-sup theory, including an isomorphism as solution operator. Moreover, we show that the new solution space is not a subspace of $H^2(Q)$. This new uniqueness and solvability result is not only crucial for discretizations using space-time methods, including least-squares approaches, but also important for regularity results and the analysis of related space-time boundary integral equations, which form the basis for space-time boundary element methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23807v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Zank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Greedy Rational Approximation for Frequency-Domain Model Reduction of Parametric LTI Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate model reduction of parametric linear time-invariant (LTI) dynamical systems. When posed in the frequency domain, this problem can be formulated as seeking a low-order rational function approximation of a high-order rational function. We propose to use a standard reduced basis method (RBM) to construct this low-order rational function. Algorithmically, this procedure is an iterative greedy approach, where the greedy objective is evaluated through an error estimator that exploits the linearity of the frequency domain representation. The greedy framework is motivated through theoretical results of rational approximability of functions. This framework provides a principled approach to rational compression of high-order rational functions, and provides a computational pathway for model reduction of parametric LTI systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23814v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filip B\v{e}l\'ik, Yanlai Chen, Akil Narayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning methods for inverse problems using connections between proximal operators and Hamilton-Jacobi equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inverse problems are important mathematical problems that seek to recover model parameters from noisy data. Since inverse problems are often ill-posed, they require regularization or incorporation of prior information about the underlying model or unknown variables. Proximal operators, ubiquitous in nonsmooth optimization, are central to this because they provide a flexible and convenient way to encode priors and build efficient iterative algorithms. They have also recently become key to modern machine learning methods, e.g., for plug-and-play methods for learned denoisers and deep neural architectures for learning priors of proximal operators. The latter was developed partly due to recent work characterizing proximal operators of nonconvex priors as subdifferential of convex potentials. In this work, we propose to leverage connections between proximal operators and Hamilton-Jacobi partial differential equations (HJ PDEs) to develop novel deep learning architectures for learning the prior. In contrast to other existing methods, we learn the prior directly without recourse to inverting the prior after training. We present several numerical results that demonstrate the efficiency of the proposed method in high dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23829v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oluwatosin Akande, Gabriel P. Langlois, Akwum Onwunta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal sampling via Schr\"odinger-F\"ollmer samplers with temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generating samples from complex and high-dimensional distributions is ubiquitous in various scientific fields of statistical physics, Bayesian inference, scientific computing and machine learning. Very recently, Huang et al. (IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory, 2025) proposed new Schr\"odinger-F\"ollmer samplers (SFS), based on the Euler discretization of the Schr\"odinger-F\"ollmer diffusion evolving on the unit interval $[0, 1]$. There, a convergence rate of order $\mathcal{O}(\sqrt{h})$ in the $L^2$-Wasserstein distance was obtained for the Euler discretization with a uniform time step-size $h&gt;0$.
  By incorporating a temperature parameter, different samplers are introduced in this paper, based on the Euler discretization of the Schr\"odinger-F\"ollmer process with temperatures. As revealed by numerical experiments, high temperatures are vital, particularly in sampling from multimodal distributions. Further, a novel approach of error analysis is developed for the time discretization and an enhanced convergence rate of order ${ \mathcal{O}(h)}$ is obtained in the $L^2$-Wasserstein distance, under certain smoothness conditions on the drift. This significantly improves the existing order-half convergence in the aforementioned paper. Unlike Langevin samplers, SFS is of gradient-free, works in a unit interval $[0, 1]$ and does not require any ergodicity. Numerical experiments confirm the convergence rate and show that, the SFS substantially outperforms vanilla Langevin samplers, particularly in sampling from multimodal distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23965v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaojie Wang, Xiaoyan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High order numerical discretizations of the Einstein-Euler equations in the Generalized Harmonic formulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24121v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose two new alternative numerical schemes to solve the coupled Einstein-Euler equations in the Generalized Harmonic formulation. The first one is a finite difference (FD) Central Weighted Essentially Non-Oscillatory (CWENO) scheme on a traditional Cartesian mesh, while the second one is an ADER (Arbitrary high order Derivatives) discontinuous Galerkin (DG) scheme on 2D unstructured polygonal meshes. The latter, in particular, represents a preliminary step in view of a full 3D numerical relativity calculation on moving meshes. Both schemes are equipped with a well-balancing (WB) property, which allows to preserve the equilibrium of a priori known stationary solutions exactly at the discrete level. We validate our numerical approaches by successfully reproducing standard vacuum test cases, such as the robust stability, the linearized wave, and the gauge wave tests, as well as achieving long-term stable evolutions of stationary black holes, including Kerr black holes with extreme spin. Concerning the coupling with matter, modeled by the relativistic Euler equations, we perform a classical test of spherical accretion onto a Schwarzschild black hole, as well as an evolution of a perturbed non-rotating neutron star, demonstrating the capability of our schemes to operate also on the full Einstein-Euler system. Altogether, these results provide a solid foundation for addressing more complex and challenging simulations of astrophysical sources through DG schemes on unstructured 3D meshes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24121v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Muzzolon, Michael Dumbser, Olindo Zanotti, Elena Gaburro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure-preserving schemes for nonlinear symmetric hyperbolic and thermodynamically compatible systems of partial differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper aims at developing exactly energy-conservative and structure-preserving finite volume schemes for the discretisation of first-order symmetric-hyperbolic and thermodynamically compatible (SHTC) systems of partial differential equations in continuum physics. Due to their thermodynamic compatibility the class of SHTC systems satisfies an additional conservation law for the total energy and many PDE in this class of equations also satisfy stationary differential constraints (involutions). First, we propose a simple semi-discrete cell-centered HTC finite volume scheme that employs collocated grids and that is compatible with the total energy conservation law, but which does not satisfy the involutions. Second, we develop a fully discrete semi-implicit finite volume scheme that conserves total energy and which can be proven to satisfy also the involution constraints exactly at the discrete level. This method is a vertex-based staggered semi-implicit scheme that preserves the basic vector calculus identities $\nabla \cdot \nabla \times A = 0$ and $\nabla \times \nabla \phi = 0$ for any vector and scalar field, respectively, exactly at the discrete level and which is also exactly totally energy conservative. The main key ingredient of the proposed implicit scheme is the fact that it uses a discrete version of the symmetric-hyperbolic Godunov-form of the governing PDE system. This leads naturally to sequences of symmetric and positive definite linear algebraic systems to be solved inside an iterative fixed-point method used in each time step. We apply our new schemes to three different SHTC systems. In particular, we consider the equations of nonlinear acoustics, the nonlinear Maxwell equations in the absence of charges and a nonlinear version of the Maxwell-GLM system. We also show some numerical results to provide evidence of the stated properties of the proposed schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24127v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessia Lucca, Michael Dumbser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sufficient and Necessary Conditions for Eckart-Young-like Result for Tubal Tensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A valuable feature of the tubal tensor framework is that many familiar constructions from matrix algebra carry over to tensors, including SVD and notions of rank. Most importantly, it has been shown that for a specific family of tubal products, an Eckart-Young type theorem holds, i.e., the best low-rank approximation of a tensor under the Frobenius norm is obtained by truncating its tubal SVD. In this paper, we provide a complete characterization of the family of tubal products that yield an Eckart-Young type result. We demonstrate the practical implications of our theoretical findings by conducting experiments with video data and data-driven dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24405v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uria Mor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast high-order spectral solvers for PDEs on triangulated surfaces with applications to deforming surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24456v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend the classical quadrilateral based hierarchical Poincar\'e-Steklov (HPS) framework to triangulated geometries. Traditionally, the HPS method takes as input an unstructured, high-order quadrilateral mesh and relies on tensor-product spectral discretizations on each element. To overcome this restriction, we introduce two complementary high-order strategies for triangular elements: a reduced quadrilateralization approach which is straightforward to implement, and triangle based spectral element method based on Dubiner polynomials. We show numerically that these extensions preserve the spectral accuracy, efficiency, and fast direct-solver structure of the HPS framework. The method is further extended to time dependent and evolving surfaces, and its performance is demonstrated through numerical experiments on reaction-diffusion systems, and geometry driven surface evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24456v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gentian Zavalani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Convergence of Deep Composite Polynomial Approximation for Cusp-Type Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate deep composite polynomial approximations of continuous but non-differentiable functions with algebraic cusp singularities. The functions in focus consist of finitely many cusp terms of the form $|x-a_j|^{\alpha_j}$ with rational exponents $\alpha_j\in(0,1)$ on a real-analytic background. We propose a constructive approximation scheme that combines a division-free polynomial iteration for fractional powers with an outer layer for the analytic polynomial fitting. Our main result shows that this composite structure achieves exponential convergence in the the number of scalar coefficients in the inner and outer polynomial layers. Specifically, the $L^p([-1,1])$ approximation error, decays exponentially with respect to the parameter budget, in contrast to the algebraic rates obtained by classical single-layer polynomial approximation for cusp-type functions. Numerical experiments for both single and multiple cusp configurations confirm the theoretical rates and demonstrate the parameter efficiency of deep composite polynomial constructions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24523v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kingsley Yeon, Steven B. Damelin, Michael Werman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Newton-Krylov Methods for Computing Steady States of Particle Timesteppers via Optimal Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Timesteppers constitute a powerful tool in modern computational science and engineering. Although they are typically used to advance the system forward in time, they can also be viewed as nonlinear mappings that implicitly encode steady states and stability information. In this work, we present an extension of the matrix-free framework for calculating, via timesteppers, steady states of deterministic systems to stochastic particle simulations, where intrinsic randomness prevents direct steady state extraction. By formulating stochastic timesteppers in the language of optimal transport, we reinterpret them as operators acting on probability measures rather than on individual particle trajectories. This perspective enables the construction of smooth cumulative- and inverse-cumulative-distribution-function ((I)CDF) timesteppers that evolve distributions rather than particles. Combined with matrix-free Newton-Krylov solvers, these smooth timesteppers allow efficient computation of steady-state distributions even under high stochastic noise. We perform an error analysis quantifying how noise affects finite-difference Jacobian action approximations, and demonstrate that convergence can be obtained even in high noise regimes. Finally, we introduce higher-dimensional generalizations based on smooth CDF-related representations of particles and validate their performance on a non-trivial two-dimensional distribution. Together, these developments establish a unified variational framework for computing meaningful steady states of both deterministic and stochastic timesteppers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24567v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannes Vandecasteele, Nicholas Karris, Alexander Cloninger, Ioannis G. Kevrekidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving the inverse Source Problems for wave equation with final time measurements by a data driven approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops a discrete data-driven approach for solving the inverse source problem of the wave equation with final time measurements. Focusing on the $L^2$-Tikhonov regularization method, we analyze its convergence under two different noise models, using noisy discrete spatial observations. By exploiting the spectral decomposition of the forward operator and introducing a noise separation technique into the variational framework, we establish error bounds for the reconstructed solution $u$ and the source term $f$ without requiring classical source conditions. Moreover, an expected convergence rate for the source error is derived in a weaker topology. We also extend the analysis to the fully discrete case with finite element discretization, showing that the overall error depends only on the noise level, regularization parameter, time step size, and spatial mesh size. These estimates provide a basis for selecting the optimal regularization parameter in a data-driven manner, without a priori information. Numerical experiments validate the theoretical results and demonstrate the efficiency of the proposed algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24647v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiling Gu, Wenlong Zhang, Zhidong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary error control for numerical solution of BSDEs by the convolution-FFT method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24714v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We first review the convolution fast-Fourier-transform (CFFT) approach for the numerical solution of backward stochastic differential equations (BSDEs) introduced in (Hyndman and Oyono Ngou, 2017). We then propose a method for improving the boundary errors obtained when valuing options using this approach. We modify the damping and shifting schemes used in the original formulation, which transforms the target function into a bounded periodic function so that Fourier transforms can be applied successfully. Time-dependent shifting reduces boundary error significantly. We present numerical results for our implementation and provide a detailed error analysis showing the improved accuracy and convergence of the modified convolution method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24714v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Gao, Cody Hyndman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A structure-preserving parametric approximation for anisotropic geometric flows via an $\alpha$-surface energy matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a structure-preserving parametric approximation for geometric flows with general anisotropic effects. By introducing a hyperparameter $\alpha$, we construct a unified surface energy matrix $\hat{\boldsymbol{G}}_k^\alpha(\theta)$ that encompasses all existing formulations of surface energy matrices, and apply it to anisotropic curvature flow. We prove that $\alpha=-1$ is the unique choice achieving optimal energy stability under the necessary and sufficient condition $3\hat{\gamma}(\theta)\geq\hat{\gamma}(\theta-\pi)$, while all other $\alpha\neq-1$ require strictly stronger conditions. The framework extends naturally to general anisotropic geometric flows through a unified velocity discretization that ensures energy stability. Numerical experiments validate the theoretical optimality of $\alpha=-1$ and demonstrate the effectiveness and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24875v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weizhu Bao, Yifei Li, Wenjun Ying, Yulin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random compressible Euler flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a finite volume stochastic collocation method for the random Euler system. We rigorously prove the convergence of random finite volume solutions under the assumption that the discrete differential quotients remain bounded in probability. Convergence analysis combines results on the convergence of a deterministic FV method with stochastic compactness arguments due to Skorokhod and Gy\"ongy-Krylov.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24879v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Lukacova-Medvidova, Simon Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A finite element approach for minimizing line and surface energies arising in the study of singularities in liquid crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by a problem originating in the study of defect structures in nematic liquid crystals, we describe and study a numerical algorithm for the resolution of a Plateau-like problem. The energy contains the area of a two-dimensional surface $T$ and the length of its boundary $\partial T$ reduced by a prescribed curve to make our problem non-trivial. We additionally include an obstacle $E$ for $T$ and pose a surface energy on $E$. We present an algorithm based on the Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers that minimizes a discretized version of the energy using finite elements, generalizing existing TV-minimization methods. We study different inclusion shapes demonstrating the rich structure of minimizing configurations and provide physical interpretation of our findings for colloidal particles in nematic liquid crystal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24928v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Stantejsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximating evolution operators of linear delay equations: a general framework for the convergence analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24964v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of discretizing evolution operators of linear delay equations with the aim of approximating their spectra, which is useful in investigating the stability properties of (nonlinear) equations via the principle of linearized stability. We develop a general convergence analysis based on a reformulation of the operators by means of a fixed-point equation, providing a list of hypotheses related to the regularization properties of the equation and the convergence of the chosen approximation techniques on suitable subspaces. This framework unifies the proofs for some methods based on pseudospectral discretization, which we present here in this new form. To exemplify the generality of the framework, we also apply it to a method of weighted residuals found in the literature, which was previously lacking a formal convergence analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24964v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessia and\`o, Giusy Bosco, Dimitri Breda, Davide Liessi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>At the intersection of Numerical Analysis and Spectral Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.25012v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: How do the geometric properties of a domain impact the spectrum of an operator defined on it? How do we compute accurate and reliable approximations of these spectra? The former question is studied in spectral geometry, and the latter is a central concern in numerical analysis. In this short expository survey we revisit the process of eigenvalue approximation, from the perspective of computational spectral geometry. Over the years a multitude of methods -- for discretizing the operator and for the resultant discrete system -- have been developed and analyzed in the field of numerical analysis. High-accuracy and provably convergent discretization approaches can be used to examine the interplay between the spectrum of an operator and the geometric properties of the spatial domain or manifold it is defined on. While computations have been used to guide conjectures in spectral geometry, in recent years approximation-theoretic tools and validated computations are also being used as part of proof strategies in spectral geometry.
  Given a particular spectral feature of interest, should we discretize the original problem, or seek a reformulation? Of the many possible approximation strategies, which should we choose? These choices are inextricably linked to the objective: on the one hand, rapid, specialized methods are often ideal for conjecture formulation (prioritizing efficiency and accuracy), whereas schemes with guaranteed, computable error bounds are needed when computation is incorporated into a proof strategy. We also review instances where the demanding requirements of spectral geometry -- the need for rigorous error control or the robust calculation of higher eigenvalues -- motivate new developments in numerical analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.25012v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilima Nigam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of the generalization error for deep gradient flow methods for PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.25017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.25017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this article is to provide a firm mathematical foundation for the application of deep gradient flow methods (DGFMs) for the solution of (high-dimensional) partial differential equations (PDEs). We decompose the generalization error of DGFMs into an approximation and a training error. We first show that the solution of PDEs that satisfy reasonable and verifiable assumptions can be approximated by neural networks, thus the approximation error tends to zero as the number of neurons tends to infinity. Then, we derive the gradient flow that the training process follows in the ``wide network limit'' and analyze the limit of this flow as the training time tends to infinity. These results combined show that the generalization error of DGFMs tends to zero as the number of neurons and the training time tend to infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.25017v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenguang Liu, Antonis Papapantoleon, Jasper Rou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Galerkin Method and Hierarchical Preconditioning for PDE-constrained Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23804v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop efficient hierarchical preconditioners for optimal control problems governed by partial differential equations with uncertain coefficients. Adopting a discretize-then-optimize framework that integrates finite element discretization, stochastic Galerkin approximation, and advanced time-discretization schemes, the approach addresses the challenge of large-scale, ill-conditioned linear systems arising in uncertainty quantification. By exploiting the sparsity inherent in generalized polynomial chaos expansions, we derive hierarchical preconditioners based on truncated stochastic expansion that strike an effective balance between computational cost and preconditioning quality. Numerical experiments demonstrate that the proposed preconditioners significantly accelerate the convergence of iterative solvers compared to existing methods, providing robust and efficient solvers for both steady-state and time-dependent optimal control applications under uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23804v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhendong Li, Akwum Onwunta, Bed\v{r}ich Soused\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Flow-Limit of Reflect-Reflect-Relax: Existence, Stability, and Discrete-Time Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23843v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the Reflect-Reflect-Relax (RRR) algorithm in its small-step (flow-limit) regime. In the smooth transversal setting, we show that the transverse dynamics form a hyperbolic sink, yielding exponential decay of a natural gap measure. Under uniform geometric assumptions, we construct a tubular neighborhood of the feasible manifold on which the squared gap defines a strict Lyapunov function, excluding recurrent dynamics and chaotic behavior within this basin.
  In the discrete setting, the induced flow is piecewise constant on W-domains and supports Filippov sliding along convergent boundaries, leading to finite-time capture into a solution domain. We prove that small-step RRR is a forward-Euler discretization of this flow, so that solution times measured in rescaled units converge to a finite limit while iteration counts diverge, explaining the emergence of iteration-optimal relaxation parameters. Finally, we introduce a heuristic mesoscopic framework based on percolation and renormalization group to organize performance deterioration near the Douglas-Rachford limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23843v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manish Krishan Lal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$L^p$ Estimates for Numerical Approximation of Hamilton-Jacobi Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24051v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish $L^p$ error estimates for monotone numerical schemes approximating Hamilton-Jacobi equations on the $d$-dimensional torus. Using the adjoint method, we first prove a $L^1$ error bound of order one for finite-difference and semi-Lagrangian schemes under standard convexity assumptions on the Hamiltonian. By interpolation, we also obtain $L^p$ estimates for every finite $p&gt;1$. Our analysis covers a broad class of schemes, improves several existing results, and provides a unified framework for discrete error estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24051v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Basti, Fabio Camilli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite element analysis of very large bone models based on micro-CT scans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-resolution voxel-based micro-finite element ($\mu$FE) models derived from $\mu$CT imaging enable detailed investigation of bone mechanics but remain computationally challenging at anatomically relevant scales. This study presents a comprehensive $\mu$FE framework for large-scale biomechanical analysis of an intact New Zealand White (NZW) rabbit femur, integrating advanced segmentation, scalable finite element solvers, and experimental validation using predominantly open-source libraries. Bone geometries were segmented from $\mu$CT data using the MIA clustering algorithm and converted into voxel-based $\mu$FE meshes, which were solved using the open-source MFEM library with algorithms designed for large-scale linear elasticity systems.
  The numerical solutions were verified by comparing with a commercial finite element solver, and by evaluating the performance of full assembly and element-by-element formulations within MFEM. Models containing over $8\times10^{8}$ DOFs were solved using moderate HPC resources, demonstrating the feasibility of anatomically realistic $\mu$FE simulations at this scale. Resolution effects were investigated by comparing models with voxel sizes of 20, 40, and 80 $\mu$m, revealing that 40 $\mu$m preserves boundary displacement and principal strain distributions with minimal bias while significantly reducing computational cost. Sensitivity analyses further showed that segmentation parameters influence the global mechanical response.
  Finally, $\mu$FE predictions were coupled with Digital Image Correlation measurements on an NZW rabbit femur under compression to calibrate effective bone material properties at the micron scale. The results demonstrate that large-scale, experimentally informed $\mu$FE modeling can be achieved using open-source tools, providing a robust foundation for preclinical assessment of bone mechanics and treatment-related risks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24401v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shani Martinez-Weissberg, Will Pazner, Zohar Yosibash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soliton profiles: Classical Numerical Schemes vs. Neural Network - Based Solvers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comparative study of classical numerical solvers, such as Petviashvili's method or finite difference with Newton iterations, and neural network-based methods for computing ground states or profiles of solitary-wave solutions to the one-dimensional dispersive PDEs that include the nonlinear Schr\"odinger, the nonlinear Klein-Gordon and the generalized KdV equations. We confirm that classical approaches retain high-order accuracy and strong computational efficiency for single-instance problems in the one-dimensional setting. Physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) are also able to reproduce qualitative solutions but are generally less accurate and less efficient in low dimensions than classical solvers due to expensive training and slow convergence. We also investigate the operator-learning methods, which, although computationally intensive during training, can be reused across many parameter instances, providing rapid inference after pretraining, making them attractive for applications involving repeated simulations or real-time predictions. For single-instance computations, however, the accuracy of operator-learning methods remains lower than that of classical methods or PINNs, in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24634v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chandler Haight, Svetlana Roudenko, Zhongming Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified spatiotemporal formulation with physics-preserving structure for time-dependent convection-diffusion problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24650v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a unified four-dimensional (4D) spatiotemporal formulation for time-dependent convection-diffusion problems that preserves underlying physical structures. By treating time as an additional space-like coordinate, the evolution problem is reformulated as a stationary convection-diffusion equation on a 4D space-time domain. Using exterior calculus, we extend this framework to the full family of convection-diffusion problems posed on $H(\textbf{grad})$, $H(\textbf{curl})$, and $H(\text{div})$. The resulting formulation is based on a 4D Hodge-Laplacian operator with a spatiotemporal diffusion tensor and convection field, augmented by a small temporal perturbation to ensure nondegeneracy. This formulation naturally incorporates fundamental physical constraints, including divergence-free and curl-free conditions. We further introduce an exponentially-fitted 4D spatiotemporal flux operator that symmetrizes the convection-diffusion operator and enables a well-posed variational formulation. Finally, we prove that the temporally-perturbed formulation converges to the original time-dependent convection-diffusion model as the perturbation parameter tends to zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24650v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James H. Adler, Xiaozhe Hu, Seulip Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basic Inequalities for First-Order Optimization with Applications to Statistical Risk Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24999v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce \textit{basic inequalities} for first-order iterative optimization algorithms, forming a simple and versatile framework that connects implicit and explicit regularization. While related inequalities appear in the literature, we isolate and highlight a specific form and develop it as a well-rounded tool for statistical analysis. Let $f$ denote the objective function to be optimized. Given a first-order iterative algorithm initialized at $\theta_0$ with current iterate $\theta_T$, the basic inequality upper bounds $f(\theta_T)-f(z)$ for any reference point $z$ in terms of the accumulated step sizes and the distances between $\theta_0$, $\theta_T$, and $z$. The bound translates the number of iterations into an effective regularization coefficient in the loss function. We demonstrate this framework through analyses of training dynamics and prediction risk bounds. In addition to revisiting and refining known results on gradient descent, we provide new results for mirror descent with Bregman divergence projection, for generalized linear models trained by gradient descent and exponentiated gradient descent, and for randomized predictors. We illustrate and supplement these theoretical findings with experiments on generalized linear models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24999v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seunghoon Paik, Kangjie Zhou, Matus Telgarsky, Ryan J. Tibshirani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An analysis on stochastic Lanczos quadrature with asymmetric quadrature nodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.00847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.00847v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The stochastic Lanczos quadrature method has garnered significant attention recently. Upon examination of the error analyses given by Ubaru, Chen and Saad and Cortinovis and Kressner, certain notable inconsistencies arise. It turns out that the former's results are valid for cases with symmetric quadrature nodes and may not be adequate for many practical cases such as estimating log determinant of matrices. This paper analyzes probabilistic error bound of the stochastic Lanczos quadrature method for cases with asymmetric quadrature nodes. Besides, an optimized error allocation technique is employed to minimize the overall number of matrix vector multiplications required by the stochastic Lanczos quadrature method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.00847v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhao Li, Zongyuan Han, Yixuan Huang, Shengxin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Gas-Kinetic Scheme for Maxwell Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16845v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Gas-Kinetic Scheme (GKS), widely used in computational fluid dynamics for simulating hypersonic and other complicated flow phenomena, is extended in this work to electromagnetic problems by solving Maxwell's equations. In contrast to the classical GKS formulation, the proposed scheme employs a discrete rather than a continuous velocity space. By evaluating a time-accurate numerical flux at cell interfaces, the proposed scheme attains second-order accuracy within a single step. Its kinetic formulation provides an inherently multidimensional framework, while the finite-volume formulation ensures straightforward extension to unstructured meshes. Through the incorporation of a collision process, the scheme exhibits lower numerical dissipation than classical flux-vector splitting (FVS) methods. Furthermore, the kinetic decomposition enables direct implementation of non-reflecting boundary conditions. The proposed scheme is validated against several benchmark problems and compared with established methods, including the Finite-Difference Time-Domain (FDTD) method and FVS. A lattice Boltzmann method (LBM) implementation is also included for comparative analysis. Finally, the technique is applied to simulate electromagnetic wave propagation in a realistic aircraft configuration, demonstrating its ability to model complex geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16845v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhigang Pu, Wenpei Long, Kun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Numerical Solutions for Hamilton-Jacobi PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20833v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hamilton-Jacobi partial differential equations (HJ PDEs) play a central role in many applications such as economics, physics, and engineering. These equations describe the evolution of a value function which encodes valuable information about the system, such as action, cost, or level sets of a dynamic process. Their importance lies in their ability to model diverse phenomena, ranging from the propagation of fronts in computational physics to optimal decision-making in control systems. This paper provides a review of some recent advances in numerical methods to address challenges such as high-dimensionality, nonlinearity, and computational efficiency. By examining these developments, this paper sheds light on important techniques and emerging directions in the numerical solution of HJ PDEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20833v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tingwei Meng, Siting Liu, Samy Wu Fung, Stanley Osher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Field Equations with random data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16343v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study neural field equations, which are prototypical models of large-scale cortical activity, subject to random data. We view this spatially-extended, nonlocal evolution equation as a Cauchy problem on abstract Banach spaces, with randomness in the synaptic kernel, firing rate function, external stimuli, and initial conditions. We determine conditions on the random data that guarantee existence, uniqueness, and measurability of the solution in an appropriate Banach space, and examine the regularity of the solution in relation to the regularity of the inputs. We present results for linear and nonlinear neural fields, and for the two most common functional setups in the numerical analysis of this problem. In addition to the continuous problem, we analyse in abstract form neural fields that have been spatially discretised, setting the foundations for analysing uncertainty quantification (UQ) schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16343v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Avitabile, Francesca Cavallini, Svetlana Dubinkina, Gabriel J. Lord</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Geometric Multigrid Preconditioner for Discontinuous Galerkin Shifted Boundary Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12899v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a geometric multigrid preconditioner for the Shifted Boundary Method (SBM) designed to solve PDEs on complex geometries. While SBM simplifies mesh generation by using a non-conforming background grid, it often results in non-symmetric and potentially ill-conditioned linear systems that are challenging to solve efficiently. Standard multigrid methods with pointwise smoothers prove ineffective for such systems due to the localized perturbations introduced by the shifted boundary conditions. To address this challenge, we introduce a Discontinuous Galerkin (DG) formulation for SBM that enables the design of a cell-wise multiplicative smoother within an $hp$-multigrid framework. The element-local nature of DG methods naturally facilitates cell-wise correction, which can effectively handle the local complexities arising from the boundary treatment. Numerical results for the Poisson equation demonstrate favorable performance with mesh refinement for linear ($p=1$) and quadratic ($p=2$) elements in both 2D and 3D, with iteration counts showing mild growth. However, challenges emerge for cubic ($p=3$) elements, particularly in 3D, where the current smoother shows reduced effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12899v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Wichrowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical feedback control with operator learning for the Vlasov-Poisson system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23063v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To meet the demands of instantaneous control of instabilities over long time horizons in plasma fusion, we design a dynamic feedback control strategy for the Vlasov-Poisson system by constructing an operator that maps state perturbations to an external control field. In the first part of the paper, we propose learning such an operator using a neural network. Inspired by optimal control theory for linearized dynamics, we introduce a low-rank neural operator architecture and train it via adjoint state method. The resulting controller is effective at suppressing instabilities well beyond the training time horizon. To generalize control across varying initial data, we further introduce a novel cancellation-based control strategy that removes the destabilizing component of the electric field. This approach naturally defines an operator without requiring any training, ensures perturbation decay over infinite time, and demonstrates strong robustness under noisy feedback. Numerical experiments confirm the effectiveness of the method in both one- and multidimensional settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23063v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingcheng Lu, Li Wang, Jeff Calder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Accelerated Algebraic Multigrid Methods for Polytopal Discretizations of Second-Order Differential Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01442v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Algebraic Multigrid (AMG) methods are state-of-the-art algebraic solvers for partial differential equations. Still, their efficiency depends heavily on the choice of suitable parameters and/or ingredients. Paradigmatic examples include the so-called strong threshold parameter $\theta$, which controls the algebraic coarse-grid hierarchy, as well as the smoother, i.e., the relaxation methods used on the fine grid to damp out high-frequency errors. In AMG, since the coarse grids are constructed algebraically (without geometric intuition), the smoother's performance is even more critical. For the linear systems stemming from polytopal discretizations, such as Polytopal Discontinuous Galerkin (PolyDG) and Virtual Element Methods (VEM), AMG sensitivity to such choices is even more critical due to the significant variability of the underlying meshes, which results in algebraic systems with different sparsity patterns. We propose a novel deep learning approach that automatically tunes the strong threshold parameter, as well as the smoother choice in AMG solvers, for linear systems of equations arising from polytopal discretizations, thereby maximizing AMG performance. We interpret the sparse matrix resulting from polytopal discretization as a grayscale image, and by applying pooling, our neural network extracts compact features that preserve the necessary information at a low computational cost. We test various differential problems in both two- and three-dimensional settings, with heterogeneous coefficients and polygonal/polyhedral meshes, and demonstrate that the proposed approach generalizes well. In practice, we demonstrate that we can reduce AMG solver time by up to $27\%$ with minimal changes to existing PolyDG and VEM codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01442v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paola F. Antonietti, Matteo Caldana, Lorenzo Gentile, Marco Verani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smoother-type a posteriori error estimates for finite element methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07677v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work develops user-friendly a posteriori error estimates of finite element methods, based on smoothers of linear iterative solvers. The proposed method employs simple smoothers, such as Jacobi or Gauss--Seidel iteration, on an auxiliary finer mesh to process the finite element residual for a posteriori error control. The implementation has linear complexity and requires only a coarse-to-fine prolongation operator. For symmetric problems, we prove the reliability and efficiency of smoother-type error estimators under a saturation assumption. Numerical experiments for various PDEs demonstrate that the proposed smoother-type error estimators outperform residual-type estimators in accuracy and exhibit robustness with respect to parameters and polynomial degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07677v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuwen Li, Han Shui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimization-based embedded boundary methods as polynomial corrections: a stability study of discontinuous Galerkin for hyperbolic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05278v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work establishes a novel, unified theoretical framework for a class of high order embedded boundary methods, revealing that the Reconstruction for Off-site Data (ROD) treatment shares a fundamental structure with the recently developed shifted boundary polynomial correction [Ciallella, M., et al. (2023)]. By proving that the ROD minimization problem admits an equivalent direct polynomial correction formulation, we unlock two major advances. First, we derive a significant algorithmic simplification, replacing the solution of the minimization problem with a straightforward polynomial evaluation, thereby enhancing computational efficiency. Second, and most critically, this reformulation enables the first stability result for the ROD method when applied to the linear advection equation with discontinuous Galerkin discretization. Our analysis, supported by a comprehensive eigenspectrum study for polynomial degrees up to six, characterizes the stability region of the new ROD formulation. The theoretical findings, which demonstrate the stability constraints, are validated through targeted numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05278v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mirco Ciallella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomized Algorithms for Low-Rank Matrix and Tensor Decompositions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05286v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper surveys randomized algorithms in numerical linear algebra for low-rank decompositions of matrices and tensors. The survey begins with a review of classical matrix algorithms that can be accelerated by randomized dimensionality reduction, such as the singular value decomposition (SVD) or interpolative (ID) and CUR decompositions. Recent advances in randomized dimensionality reduction are discussed, including new methods of fast matrix sketching and sampling techniques, which are incorporated into classical matrix algorithms for fast low-rank matrix approximations. The extension of randomized matrix algorithms to tensors is then explored for several low-rank tensor decompositions in the CP and Tucker formats, including the higher-order SVD, ID, and CUR decomposition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05286v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katherine J. Pearce, Per-Gunnar Martinsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A strong two-stage explicit/implicit approach combined with mixed finite element methods for a three-dimensional nonlinear radiation-conduction model in anisotropic media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06456v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper develops a strong computational approach to simulate a three-dimensional nonlinear radiation-conduction model in optically thick media, subject to suitable initial and boundary conditions. The space derivatives are approximated by the mixed finite element method ($\mathcal{P}_{p}/\mathcal{P}_{p-1}$), while the interpolation technique is employed in two stages to approximate the time derivative. The proposed strategy is so-called, a strong two-stage explicit/implicit computational technique combined with mixed finite element method. Specifically, the new algorithm should be observed as a predictor-corrector numerical scheme. Additionally, it efficiently treats the time derivative term and provides a necessary requirement on time step for stability. Under this time step limitation, the stability is deeply analyzed whereas the convergence order is numerically computed in the $L^{2}$-norm. The theoretical results suggest that the developed approach is stable and temporal second-order accurate. Some numerical experiments are performed to confirm the theory, to establish that the constructed method is spatial fourth-order convergent and to demonstrate the practical applicability and computational efficiency of the numerical scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06456v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Ngondiep</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super-Resolution of Elliptic PDE Solutions Using Least Squares Support Vector Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09967v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A hybrid computational approach that integrates the finite element method (FEM) with least squares support vector regression (LSSVR) is introduced to solve partial differential equations. The method combines FEM's ability to provide the nodal solutions and LSSVR with higher-order Legendre polynomial kernels to deliver a closed-form analytical solution for interpolation between the nodes. The hybrid approach implements element-wise enhancement (super-resolution) of a given numerical solution, resulting in high resolution accuracy, while maintaining consistency with FEM nodal values at element boundaries. It can adapt any low-order FEM code to obtain high-order resolution by leveraging localized kernel refinement and parallel computation without additional implementation overhead. Therefore, effective inference/post-processing of the obtained super-resolved solution is possible. Evaluation results show that the hybrid FEM-LSSVR approach can achieve significantly higher accuracy compared to the base FEM solution. Comparable accuracy is a achieved when comparing the hybrid solution with a standalone FEM result with the same polynomial basis function order. The convergence studies were conducted for four elliptic boundary value problems to demonstrate the method's ability, accuracy, and reliability. Finally, the algorithm can be directly used as a plug-and-play method for super-resolving low-order numerical solvers and for super-resolution of expensive/under-resolved experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09967v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Babaei, Peter Rucz, Manfred Kaltenbacher, Stefan Schoder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A homogeneous geometry of low-rank tensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13594v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider sets of fixed CP, multilinear, and TT rank tensors, and derive conditions for when (the smooth parts of) these sets are smooth homogeneous manifolds. For CP and TT ranks, the conditions are essentially that the rank is sufficiently low. These homogeneous structures are then used to derive Riemannian metrics whose geodesics are both complete and efficient to compute.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13594v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Jacobsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Precision General Alternating-Direction Implicit Method for Solving Large Sparse Linear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21164v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we introduce a three-precision formulation of the General Alternating-Direction Implicit method (GADI) designed to accelerate the solution of large-scale sparse linear systems $Ax=b$. GADI is a framework that can represent many existing Alternating-Direction Implicit (ADI) methods. These methods are a class of linear solvers based on a splitting of $A$ such that the solution of the original linear system can be decomposed into the successive computation of easy-to-solve structured subsystems. Our proposed mixed precision scheme for GADI solves these subsystems in low precision to reduce the overall execution time while computing the residual and solution update in high precision to enable the solution to converge to high accuracy. We develop a rounding error analysis of mixed precision GADI that establishes the rates of convergence of the forward and backward errors to certain limiting accuracies. Our analysis also highlights the conditions on the splitting matrices under which mixed precision GADI is guaranteed to converge for a given set of precisions. We then discuss a systematic and robust strategy for selecting the GADI regularization parameter $\alpha$, whose adjustment is critical for performance. Specifically, our proposed strategy makes use of a Gaussian Process Regression (GPR) model trained on a dataset of low-dimensional problems to initialize $\alpha$. Finally, we proceed to a performance analysis of mixed precision GADI on an NVIDIA A100 GPU to validate our approach. Using low precision (Bfloat16 or FP32) to solve the subsystems, we obtain speedups of $2.6\times$, $1.7\times$, and $3.1\times$ over a full double precision GADI implementation on large-scale 2D, 3D convection-diffusion and complex reaction-diffusion problems (up to $1.3\times 10^{8}$ unknowns), respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21164v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jifeng Ge, Bastien Vieubl\'e, Juan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Modelling of L\'evy Area for High Order SDE Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.02452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.02452v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is well understood that, when numerically simulating SDEs with general noise, achieving a strong convergence rate better than $O(\sqrt{h})$ (where h is the step size) requires the use of certain iterated integrals of Brownian motion, commonly referred to as its "L\'evy areas". However, these stochastic integrals are difficult to simulate due to their non-Gaussian nature and for a $d$-dimensional Brownian motion with $d &gt; 2$, no fast almost-exact sampling algorithm is known.
  In this paper, we propose L\'evyGAN, a deep-learning-based model for generating approximate samples of L\'evy area conditional on a Brownian increment. Due to our "Bridge-flipping" operation, the output samples match all joint and conditional odd moments exactly. Our generator employs a tailored GNN-inspired architecture, which enforces the correct dependency structure between the output distribution and the conditioning variable. Furthermore, we incorporate a mathematically principled characteristic-function based discriminator. Lastly, we introduce a novel training mechanism termed "Chen-training", which circumvents the need for expensive-to-generate training data-sets. This new training procedure is underpinned by our two main theoretical results.
  For 4-dimensional Brownian motion, we show that L\'evyGAN exhibits state-of-the-art performance across several metrics which measure both the joint and marginal distributions. We conclude with a numerical experiment on the log-Heston model, a popular SDE in mathematical finance, demonstrating that high-quality synthetic L\'evy area can lead to high order weak convergence and variance reduction when using multilevel Monte Carlo (MLMC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.02452v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1137/23M161077X</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIAM Journal on Mathematics of Data Science, vol. 7, no. 4, pp. 1541-1567, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andra\v{z} Jelin\v{c}i\v{c}, Jiajie Tao, William F. Turner, Thomas Cass, James Foster, Hao Ni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mathematical model for a universal digital quantum computer with an application to the Grover-Rudolph algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13388v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we develop a novel mathematical framework for universal digital quantum computation using algebraic probability theory. We rigorously define quantum circuits as finite sequences of elementary quantum gates and establish their role in implementing unitary transformations. A key result demonstrates that every unitary matrix in \(\mathrm{U}(N)\) can be expressed as a product of elementary quantum gates, leading to the concept of a universal dictionary for quantum computation. We apply this framework to the construction of quantum circuits that encode probability distributions, focusing on the Grover-Rudolph algorithm. By leveraging controlled quantum gates and rotation matrices, we design a quantum circuit that approximates a given probability density function. Numerical simulations, conducted using Qiskit, confirm the theoretical predictions and validate the effectiveness of our approach. These results provide a rigorous foundation for quantum circuit synthesis within an algebraic probability framework and offer new insights into the encoding of probability distributions in quantum algorithms. Potential applications include quantum machine learning, circuit optimization, and experimental implementations on real quantum hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13388v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Falc\'o, Daniela Falc\'o--Pomares, Hermann G. Matthies</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical artificial data for operator learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06752v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine learning has emerged as a transformative tool for solving differential equations (DEs), yet prevailing methodologies remain constrained by dual limitations: data-driven methods demand costly labeled datasets while model-driven techniques face efficiency-accuracy trade-offs. We present the Mathematical Artificial Data (MAD) framework, a new paradigm that integrates physical laws with data-driven learning to facilitate large-scale operator discovery. By exploiting DEs' intrinsic mathematical structure to generate physics-embedded analytical solutions and associated synthetic data, MAD fundamentally eliminates dependence on experimental or simulated training data. This enables computationally efficient operator learning across multi-parameter systems while maintaining mathematical rigor. Through numerical demonstrations spanning 2D parametric problems where both the boundary values and source term are functions, we showcase MAD's generalizability and superior efficiency/accuracy across various DE scenarios. This physics-embedded-data-driven framework and its capacity to handle complex parameter spaces gives it the potential to become a universal paradigm for physics-informed machine intelligence in scientific computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06752v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng Wu, Benzhuo Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lipschitz-Guided Design of Interpolation Schedules in Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01629v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the design of interpolation schedules in the stochastic interpolants framework for flow and diffusion-based generative models. We show that while all scalar interpolation schedules achieve identical statistical efficiency under Kullback-Leibler divergence in path space after optimal diffusion coefficient tuning, their numerical efficiency can differ substantially. This motivates focusing on numerical properties of the resulting drift fields rather than purely statistical criteria for schedule design. We propose averaged squared Lipschitzness minimization as a principled criterion for numerical optimization, providing an alternative to kinetic energy minimization used in optimal transport approaches. A transfer formula is derived that enables conversion between different schedules at inference time without retraining neural networks. For Gaussian distributions, the optimized schedules achieve exponential improvements in Lipschitz constants over standard linear schedules, while for Gaussian mixtures, they reduce mode collapse in few-step sampling. We also validate our approach on high-dimensional invariant distributions from stochastic Allen-Cahn equations and Navier-Stokes equations, demonstrating robust performance improvements across resolutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01629v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Chen, Eric Vanden-Eijnden, Jiawei Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A space-time extension of a conservative two-fluid cut-cell method for moving diffusion problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23358v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a space-time extension of a conservative Cartesian cut-cell finite-volume method for two-phase diffusion problems with prescribed interface motion. The formulation follows a two-fluid approach: one scalar field is solved in each phase with discontinuous material properties, coupled by sharp interface conditions enforcing flux continuity and jump laws. To handle moving boundaries on a fixed Cartesian grid, the discrete balance is written over phase-restricted space-time control volumes, whose geometric moments (swept volumes and apertures) are used as weights in the finite-volume operators. This construction naturally accounts for the creation and destruction of cut cells (fresh/dead-cell events) and yields strict discrete conservation. The resulting scheme retains the algebraic structure of the static cut-cell formulation while incorporating motion through local geometric weights and interface coupling operators. A series of verification and validation tests in two and three dimensions demonstrate super-linear accuracy in space, robust behavior under repeated topology changes and conservation across strong coefficient jumps and moving interfaces. The proposed space-time cut-cell framework provides a conservative building block for multiphase transport in evolving geometries and a foundation for future free-boundary extensions such as Stefan-type phase change.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23358v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Libat, Can Sel\c{c}uk, Eric Ch\'enier, Vincent Le Chenadec</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
