<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Anosov magnetic flows on surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the quotient bundle introduced by Wojtkowski, we give necessary and sufficient conditions for a magnetic flow on a closed, oriented surface to be Anosov.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18735v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Marshall Reber, Yumin Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wild attractors for Fibonacci maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Existence of wild attractors -- attractors whose basin has a positive Lebesgue measure but is not a residual set -- has been one of central themes in one-dimensional dynamics. It has been demonstrated by H. Bruin et al. that Fibonacci maps with a sufficiently flat critical point admit a wild attractor. We propose a constructive trichotomy that describes possible scenarios for the Lebesgue measure of the Fibonacci attractor based on a computable criterion. We use this criterion, together with a computer-assisted proof of existence of a Fibonacci renormalization $2$-cycle for non-integer critical degrees, to demonstrate that Fibonacci maps do not have a wild attractor when the degree of the critical point is $d=3.8$ (and, conjecturally, for $2&lt; d \le 3.8$), and do admit it when $d=5.1$ (and, conjecturally, for $d \ge 5.1$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19019v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Gaidashev, Artem Dudko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Third Order Dynamical System for Mixed Variational Inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce and study a class of resolvent dynamical systems to investigate some inertial proximal methods for solving mixed variational inequalities. These proposed methods along with their discretizations and derived rates of convergences require only the monotonicity for mixed variational inequalities under some mild conditions. We establish the global asymptotically and exponentially stability of the solution of the resolvent dynamical system for monotone operators. Ideas and techniques of this paper may be extended for other classes of variational inequalities and equilibrium problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19345v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oday Hazaimah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Weighted-Median Model of Opinion Dynamics on Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17552v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Social interactions influence people's opinions. In some situations, these interactions result in a consensus opinion; in others, they result in opinion fragmentation and the formation of different opinion groups in the form of "echo chambers". Consider a social network of individuals, who hold continuous-valued scalar opinions and change their opinions when they interact with each other. In such an opinion model, it is common for an opinion-update rule to depend on the mean opinion of interacting individuals. However, we consider an alternative update rule - which may be more realistic in some situations - that instead depends on a weighted median opinion of interacting individuals. Through numerical simulations of our opinion model, we investigate how the limit opinion distribution depends on network structure. For configuration-model networks, we also derive a mean-field approximation for the asymptotic dynamics of the opinion distribution when there are infinitely many individuals in a network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17552v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lasse Mohr, Poul G. Hjorth, Mason A. Porter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform Stability of Dynamic SICA HIV Transmission Models on Time Scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18596v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a SICA model for HIV transmission on time scales. We prove permanence of solutions and we derive sufficient conditions for the existence and uniform asymptotic stability of a unique positive almost periodic solution of the system in terms of a Lyapunov function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18596v1</guid>
      <category>math.GM</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahra Belarbi, Benaoumeur Bayour, Delfim F. M. Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A finiteness condition for complex continued fraction algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18689v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A continued fraction algorithm allows to represent numbers in a way that is particularly valuable if one wants to approximate irrational numbers by rationals. Some of these algorithms are simple in the sense that the possible representations can be characterized in an easy way. For instance, for the classical continued fraction algorithm each infinite string of positive integer digits (called partial quotients in this setting) can occur. For complex continued fraction algorithms this does not hold. However, for some algorithms an easy condition, the so-called finite range condition, characterizes the possible "digit strings". We show that this condition holds for complex $\boldsymbol{\alpha}$-Hurwitz algorithms with parameters $\boldsymbol{\alpha}\in\mathbb{Q}^2$. Our proofs are elementary, and our result opens new perspectives for the exploration of these algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18689v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlene Kalle, Fanni M. S\'elley, J\"org M. Thuswaldner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promoting Prelaminations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by problems in the study of Anosov and pseudo-Anosov flows on 3-manifolds, we characterize when a pair $(L^+, L^-)$ of subsets of transverse laminations of the circle can be completed to a pair of transverse foliations of the plane or, separately, realized as the endpoints of such a bifoliation of the plane. (We allow also singular bifoliations with simple prongs, such as arise in pseudo-Anosov flows). This program is carried out at a level of generality applicable to bifoliations coming from pseudo-Anosov flows with and without perfect fits, as well as many other examples, and is natural with respect to group actions preserving these structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18917v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Barthelm\'e, Christian Bonatti, Kathryn Mann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schur Stability of Matrix Segment via Bialternate Product</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18973v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, the problem of robust Schur stability of $n\times n$ dimensional matrix segments by using the bialternate product of matrices is considered. It is shown that the problem can be reduced to the existence of negative eigenvalues of two of three specially constructed matrices and the existence of eigenvalues belonging to the interval $[1,\infty)$ of the third matrix. A necessary and sufficient condition is given for the convex combinations of two stable matrices with rank one difference to be robust Schur stable. It is shown that the robust stability of the convex hull of a finite number of matrices whose two-by-two differences are of rank $1$ is equivalent to the robust stability of the segments formed by these matrices. Examples of applying the obtained results are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18973v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serife Yilmaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits of definable families and dilations in nilmanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a unipotent group and $\mathcal F=\{F_t:t\in (0,\infty)\}$ a family of subsets of $G$, with $\mathcal F$ definable in an o-minimal expansion of the real field. Given a lattice $\Gamma\subseteq G$, we study the possible Hausdorff limits of $\pi(\mathcal F)$ in $G/\Gamma$ as $t$ tends to $\infty$ (here $\pi:G\to G/\Gamma$ is the canonical projection). Towards a solution, we associate to $\mathcal F$ finitely many real algebraic subgroups $L\subseteq G$, and, uniformly in $\Gamma$, determine if the only Hausdorff limit at $\infty$ is $G/\Gamma$, depending on whether $L^\Gamma=G$ or not. The special case of polynomial dilations of a definable set is treated in details.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19160v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya'acov Peterzil, Sergei Starchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Borel-Cantelli, zero-one laws and inhomogeneous Duffin-Schaeffer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19198v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The most versatile version of the classical divergence Borel-Cantelli lemma shows that for any divergent sequence of events $E_n$ in a probability space satisfying a quasi-independence condition, its corresponding limsup set $E_\infty$ has positive probability. In particular, it provides a lower bound on the probability of $E_\infty$. In this paper we establish a new version of this classical result which guarantees, under an additional mild assumption, that the probability of $E_\infty$ is not just positive but is one. Unlike existing optimal results, it is applicable within the setting of arbitrary probability spaces. We then go onto to consider a range of applications in number theory and dynamical systems. These include new results on the inhomogeneous Duffin-Schaeffer conjecture. In particular, we establish alternatives to the classical (homogeneous) zero-one laws of Cassels and Gallagher and use them to resolve the so-called weak Duffin-Schaeffer conjecture for an arbitrary rational inhomogeneous shift. As a bi-product, we establish the Duffin-Schaeffer conjecture with congruence relations. The applications to dynamical systems include new characterisations of Borel-Cantelli sequences and new dynamical Borel-Cantelli lemmas, as well as characterising Khintchine-type sequences for shrinking targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19198v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Beresnevich, Manuel Hauke, Sanju Velani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical exponents and dimension for generalised limit sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19252v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There is a beautiful and well-studied relationship between the Poincare exponent and the fractal dimensions of the limit set of a Kleinian group. Motivated by this, given an arbitrary discrete subset of the unit ball we define a critical exponent and investigate how it relates to the fractal dimensions of the associated generalised limit set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19252v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyi Feng, Jonathan M. Fraser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into the Structured Coordination Game with Neutral Options through Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19273v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Coordination games have been of interest to game theorists, economists, and ecologists for many years to study such problems as the emergence of local conventions and the evolution of cooperative behavior. Approaches for understanding the coordination game with discrete structure have been limited in scope, often relying on symmetric reduction of the state space, or other constraints which limit the power of the model to give insight into desired applications. In this paper, we introduce a new way of thinking about equilibria of the structured coordination game with neutral strategies by means of graph partitioning. We begin with a few elementary game theoretical results and then catalogue all the Nash equilibria of the coordination game with neutral options for graphs with seven or fewer vertices. We extend our observations through the use of simulation on larger Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi random graphs to form the basis for proposing some conjectures about the general relationships among edge density, cluster number, and consensus stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19273v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John S. McAlister, Nina H. Fefferman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform exponential mixing for congruence covers of convex cocompact hyperbolic manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.00825</link>
      <description>arXiv:1903.00825v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be a Zariski dense convex cocompact subgroup contained in an arithmetic lattice of $\operatorname{SO}(n, 1)^{\circ}$. We prove uniform exponential mixing of the geodesic flow for congruence covers of the hyperbolic manifold $\Gamma \backslash \mathbb{H}^n$ avoiding finitely many prime ideals. This extends the work of Oh-Winter who proved the result for the $n = 2$ case. Following their approach, we use Dolgopyat's method for the proof of exponential mixing of the geodesic flow. We do this uniformly over congruence covers by establishing uniform spectral bounds for the congruence transfer operators associated to the geodesic flow. This requires another key ingredient which is the expander machinery due to Bourgain-Gamburd-Sarnak extended by Golsefidy-Varj\'{u}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1903.00825v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pratyush Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential mixing of frame flows for convex cocompact hyperbolic manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.14551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2004.14551v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to establish exponential mixing of frame flows for convex cocompact hyperbolic manifolds of arbitrary dimension with respect to the Bowen-Margulis-Sullivan measure. Some immediate applications include an asymptotic formula for matrix coefficients with an exponential error term as well as the exponential equidistribution of holonomy of closed geodesics. The main technical result is a spectral bound on transfer operators twisted by holonomy, which we obtain by building on Dolgopyat's method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2004.14551v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1112/s0010437x21007600</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Compositio Mathematica, 157(12):2585-2634, 2021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pratyush Sarkar, Dale Winter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Regions of Attraction in Unknown Dynamical Systems via Zubov-Koopman Lifting: Regularities and Convergence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15119v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The estimation for the region of attraction (ROA) of an asymptotically stable equilibrium point is crucial in the analysis of nonlinear systems. There has been a recent surge of interest in estimating the solution to Zubov's equation, whose non-trivial sub-level sets form the exact ROA. In this paper, we propose a lifting approach to map observable data into an infinite-dimensional function space, which generates a flow governed by the proposed `Zubov-Koopman' operators. By learning a Zubov-Koopman operator over a fixed time interval, we can indirectly approximate the solution to Zubov's equation through iterative application of the learned operator on certain functions. We also demonstrate that a transformation of such an approximator can be readily utilized as a near-maximal Lyapunov function. We approach our goal through a comprehensive investigation of the regularities of Zubov-Koopman operators and their associated quantities. Based on these findings, we present an algorithm for learning Zubov-Koopman operators that exhibit strong convergence to the true operator. We show that this approach reduces the amount of required data and can yield desirable estimation results, as demonstrated through numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15119v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Meng, Ruikun Zhou, Jun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits of Rauzy graphs of languages with subexponential complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To a subshift over a finite alphabet, one can naturally associate an infinite family of finite graphs, called its Rauzy graphs. We show that for a subshift of subexponential complexity the Rauzy graphs converge to the line $\mathbf{Z}$ in the sense of Benjamini-Schramm convergence if and only if its complexity function $p(n)$ is unbounded and satisfies $\lim_n\frac{p(n+1)}{p(n)} = 1$. We then apply this criterion to many examples of well-studied dynamical systems. If the subshift is moreover uniquely ergodic then we show that the limit of labelled Rauzy graphs if it exists can be identified with the unique invariant measure. In addition we consider an example of a non uniquely ergodic system recently studied by Cassaigne and Kabor\'e and identify a continuum of invariant measures with subsequential limits of labelled Rauzy graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15877v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul-Henry Leemann, Tatiana Nagnibeda, Alexandra Skripchenko, Georgii Veprev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Results on Dynamics of Bungee set of Composite Entire Functions in the Eremenko-Lyubich Class</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11217v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we have discussed the dynamics of composite entire functions in terms of relationship between bungee set, repelling periodic points (to be denoted by $RP$) and rationally indifferent fixed point set. We have established relation between the dynamics of composite function and the functions taken for composition. We showed that the union of their Bungee sets contains Bungee set of the composite function. We also showed that $RP$ set of composite functions contains the $ RP$ set of functions used for the composition. We have mostly dealt with the permutable functions of class $\mathcal{B}$. These results hold true when we have a composite function in which one function is a periodic translation of another.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11217v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dinesh Kumar, Soumyajeet Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improvement of system identification of stochastic systems via Koopman generator and locally weighted expectation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15357v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The estimation of equations from data is of interest in physics. One of the famous methods is the sparse identification of nonlinear dynamics (SINDy), which utilizes sparse estimation techniques to estimate equations from data. Recently, a method based on the Koopman operator has been developed; the generator extended dynamic mode decomposition (gEDMD) estimates a time evolution generator of dynamical and stochastic systems. However, a naive application of the gEDMD algorithm cannot work well for stochastic differential equations because of the noise effects in the data. Hence, the estimation based on conditional expectation values, in which we approximate the first and second derivatives on each coordinate, is practical. A naive approach is the usage of locally weighted expectations. We show that the naive locally weighted expectation is insufficient because of the nonlinear behavior of the underlying system. For improvement, we apply the clustering method in two ways; one is to reduce the effective number of data, and the other is to capture local information more accurately. We demonstrate the improvement of the proposed method for the double-well potential system with state-dependent noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15357v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Tahara, Kakutaro Fukushi, Shunta Takahashi, Kayo Kinjo, Jun Ohkubo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From incommensurate bilayer heterostructures to Allen-Cahn: An exact thermodynamic limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.18186v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a complete and rigorous derivation of the mechanical energy for twisted 2D bilayer heterostructures without any approximation beyond the existence of an empirical many-body site energy. Our results apply to both the continuous and discontinuous continuum limit. Approximating the intralayer Cauchy-Born energy by linear elasticity theory and assuming an interlayer coupling via pair potentials, our model reduces to a modified Allen-Cahn functional. We rigorously control the error, and, in the case of sufficiently smooth lattice displacements, provide a rate of convergence for twist angles satisfying a Diophantine condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.18186v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Hott, Alexander B. Watson, Mitchell Luskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating True Beliefs in Opinion Dynamics with Social Pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17171v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Social networks often exert social pressure, causing individuals to adapt their expressed opinions to conform to their peers. An agent in such systems can be modeled as having a (true and unchanging) inherent belief while broadcasting a declared opinion at each time step based on her inherent belief and the past declared opinions of her neighbors. An important question in this setting is parameter estimation: how to disentangle the effects of social pressure to estimate inherent beliefs from declared opinions. This is useful for forecasting when agents' declared opinions are influenced by social pressure while real-world behavior only depends on their inherent beliefs. To address this, Jadbabaie et al. formulated the Interacting P\'olya Urn model of opinion dynamics under social pressure and studied it on complete-graph social networks using an aggregate estimator, and found that their estimator converges to the inherent beliefs unless majority pressure pushes the network to consensus.
  In this work, we studythis model on arbitrary networks, providing an estimator which converges to the inherent beliefs even in consensus situations. Finally, we bound the convergence rate of our estimator in both consensus and non-consensus scenarios; to get the bound for consensus scenarios (which converge slower than non-consensus) we additionally found how quickly the system converges to consensus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17171v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Tang, Aviv Adler, Amir Ajorlou, Ali Jadbabaie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian identification of nonseparable Hamiltonians with multiplicative noise using deep learning and reduced-order modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12476v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a structure-preserving Bayesian approach for learning nonseparable Hamiltonian systems using stochastic dynamic models allowing for statistically-dependent, vector-valued additive and multiplicative measurement noise. The approach is comprised of three main facets. First, we derive a Gaussian filter for a statistically-dependent, vector-valued, additive and multiplicative noise model that is needed to evaluate the likelihood within the Bayesian posterior. Second, we develop a novel algorithm for cost-effective application of Bayesian system identification to high-dimensional systems. Third, we demonstrate how structure-preserving methods can be incorporated into the proposed framework, using nonseparable Hamiltonians as an illustrative system class. We assess the method's performance based on the forecasting accuracy of a model estimated from-single trajectory data. We compare the Bayesian method to a state-of-the-art machine learning method on a canonical nonseparable Hamiltonian model and a chaotic double pendulum model with small, noisy training datasets. The results show that using the Bayesian posterior as a training objective can yield upwards of 724 times improvement in Hamiltonian mean squared error using training data with up to 10% multiplicative noise compared to a standard training objective. Lastly, we demonstrate the utility of the novel algorithm for parameter estimation of a 64-dimensional model of the spatially-discretized nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with data corrupted by up to 20% multiplicative noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12476v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Galioto, Harsh Sharma, Boris Kramer, Alex Arkady Gorodetsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Periodic orbits of non-degenerate lacunary contact forms on prequantization bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08462v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A non-degenerate contact form is lacunary if the indexes of every contractible periodic Reeb orbit have the same parity. To the best of our knowledge, every contact form with finitely many periodic orbits known so far is non-degenerate and lacunary. We show that every non-degenerate lacunary contact form on a suitable prequantization of a closed symplectic manifold $B$ has precisely $r_B$ contractible closed orbits, where $r_B=\dim \mathrm{H}_*(B;{\mathbb Q})$. Examples of such prequantizations include the standard contact sphere and the unit cosphere bundle of a compact rank one symmetric space (CROSS). We also consider some prequantizations of orbifolds, like lens spaces and the unit cosphere bundle of lens spaces, and obtain multiplicity results for these prequantizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08462v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Abreu, Leonardo Macarini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
