<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-explosion solutions for a class of stochastic physical diffusion oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we are interested in problems that are related to the physical phenomena of diffusion. We will focus on the theoretical aspect of the study, such as existence, uniqueness and non-explosive solutions. We will weaken the conditions imposed on the coefficients of the stochastic differential equations (SDE) that model some diffusion phenomena of mechanics. The work will be based on a general non-explosion criterion and we will obtain sufficient conditions so that the solution for a certain class of diffusions does not explode. We will construct Lyapunov functions that ensure the non-explosion of the solutions. Two important oscillators, namely the Duffing and the Van Der Pol oscillators, belong to this class. The Euler-Maruyama method is applied to these two oscillators to give us a simulation solution for them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19099v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amrane Houas, Fateh Merahi, Mustafa Moumni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifications and bifurcations of tangent points and their loops of planar piecewise-smooth systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19450v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tangent points, especial dynamics existing only in piecewise-smooth systems, usually have dynamical properties like equilibria of smooth systems. Loops connecting tangent points own partly properties of limit cycles and homoclinic loops of smooth systems. In this paper we give classifications for tangent points by tangency degree and for loops connecting them by configuration, and investigate their bifurcations. The classic method is to construct functional parameters for the case of low tangency degree but, is no longer valid for the case of general tangency degree, which leads to complicated interlacement of sliding and crossing motions on the switching manifold. We provide an explicit unfolding for tangent points of general tangency degree and their loops, in which explicit functional functions are constructed to replace functional parameters. We mainly obtain relations between original tangency degree and numbers of bifurcating tangent points, bifurcating tangent orbits and bifurcating loops for this unfolding. Some of these relations are generalizations to general tangency degree and others are new for previous publications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19450v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhihao Fang, Xingwu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bifurcations and explicit unfoldings of grazing loops connecting one high multiplicity tangent point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19455v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For piecewise-smooth differential systems, in this paper we focus on crossing limit cycles and sliding loops bifurcating from a grazing loop connecting one high multiplicity tangent point. For the low multiplicity cases considered in previous publications, the method is to define and analyze return maps following the classic idea of Poincar\'e. However, high multiplicity leads to that either domains or properties of return maps are unclear under perturbations. To overcome these difficulties, we unfold grazing loops by functional parameters and functional functions, and analyze this unfolding along some specific parameter curve. Relationships between multiplicity and the numbers of crossing limit cycles and sliding loops are given, and our results not only generalize the results obtained in [J. Differential Equations 255(2013), 4403-4436; 269(2020), 11396-11434], but also are new for some specific grazing loops.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19455v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhihao Fang, Xingwu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Billiard Partitions, Fibonacci Sequences, SIP Classes, and Quivers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19078v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starting from billiard partitions which arose recently in the description of periodic trajectories of ellipsoidal billiards in $d$-dimensional Euclidean space, we introduce a new type of separable integer partition classes, called type B. We study the numbers of basis partitions with $d$ parts and relate them to the Fibonacci sequence and its natural generalizations. Remarkably, the generating series of basis partitions can be related to the quiver generating series of symmetric quivers corresponding to the framed unknot via knots-quivers correspondence, and to the count of Schr\"oder paths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19078v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Dragovi\'c, Marko Sto\v{s}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Rational Recursion for Holonomic Sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19136v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It was recently conjectured that every component of a discrete rational dynamical system is a solution to an algebraic difference equation that is linear in its highest-shift term (a quasi-linear equation). Holonomic sequences are trivially seen as solutions to such dynamical systems. We prove that the conjecture holds for holonomic sequences and propose two algorithms for converting holonomic recurrence equations into such quasi-linear equations. The two algorithms differ in their efficiency and the minimality of orders in their outputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19136v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bertrand Teguia Tabuguia, James Worrell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning of continuous and discrete variational ODEs with convergence guarantee and uncertainty quantification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19626v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The article introduces a method to learn dynamical systems that are governed by Euler--Lagrange equations from data. The method is based on Gaussian process regression and identifies continuous or discrete Lagrangians and is, therefore, structure preserving by design. A rigorous proof of convergence as the distance between observation data points converges to zero is provided. Next to convergence guarantees, the method allows for quantification of model uncertainty, which can provide a basis of adaptive sampling techniques. We provide efficient uncertainty quantification of any observable that is linear in the Lagrangian, including of Hamiltonian functions (energy) and symplectic structures, which is of interest in the context of system identification. The article overcomes major practical and theoretical difficulties related to the ill-posedness of the identification task of (discrete) Lagrangians through a careful design of geometric regularisation strategies and through an exploit of a relation to convex minimisation problems in reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19626v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Offen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intraspecific and monotone enzyme catalysis with oscillatory substrate and inhibitor supplies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06984v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Enzyme catalysis in reactors for industrial applications usually require an external intervention of the species involved in the chemical reactions. We analyze the most elementary open enzyme catalysis with competitive inhibition where a time-dependent inflow of substrate and inhibitor supplies is modeled by almost periodic functions. We prove global stability of an almost periodic solution for the non-autonomous dynamical system arising from the mass-law action. This predicts a well behaved situation in which the reactor oscillates with global stability. This is a first case study in the path toward broader global stability results regarding intraspecific and monotone open reaction networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06984v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Homero G. D\'iaz-Mar\'in, Jos\'e L. S\'anchez-Ponce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unique stationary boundary property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18140v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a locally compact group and $\mu$ an admissible probability measure on $G$. Let $(B,\nu)$ be the universal topological Poisson $\mu$-boundary of $(G,\mu)$ and $\Pi_s(G)$ the universal minimal strongly proximal $G$-flow. In this note we present an alternative proof to a recent result of Hartman and Kalantar. We show that the following conditions are equivalent: (i) the measure $\nu$ is the unique $\mu$-stationary measure on $B$, (ii) $(B,G) \cong (\Pi_s(G),G)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18140v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eli Glasner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network transformation-based analysis of biochemical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.12586v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A dynamical system obtains a wide variety of kinetic realizations, which is advantageous for the analysis of biochemical systems. A reaction network, derived from a dynamical system, may or may not possess some properties needed for a thorough analysis. We improve and extend the work of M. Johnston \cite{JOHN2014} and Hong et al. \cite{HONG2023} on network translations to network transformations, where the network is modified while preserving the dynamical system. These transformations can shrink, extend, or retain the stoichiometric subspace. Here, we show that positive dependent network can be translated to a weakly reversible network. Using the kinetic realizations of (1) calcium signaling in the olfactory system and (2) metabolic insulin signaling, we demonstrate the benefits of transformed systems with positive deficiency for analyzing biochemical systems. Furthermore, we present an algorithm for a network transformation of a weakly reversible non-complex factorizable kinetic (NFK) system to a weakly reversible complex factorizable kinetic (CFK) system, thereby enhancing the Subspace Coincidence Theorem for NFK systems of Nazareno et al. \cite{NAZA2019}. Finally, using the transformed kinetic realization of monolignol biosynthesis in \textit{Populus xylem}, we study the structural and kinetic properties of transformed systems,including the invariance of concordance and variation of injectivity and mono-/multi-stationarity under network transformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.12586v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Antonio Talabis, Eduardo Mendoza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Globalization of partial inverse semigroupoid actions on sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.08693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.08693v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that every partial action of an inverse semigroupoid on a set admits a universal globalization. Moreover, we show that our construction gives a reflector from the category of partial actions on the full subcategory of global actions. Finally, we investigate if the mediating function given by the universal property of our construction is injective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.08693v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paulinho Demeneghi, Felipe Augusto Tasca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal measure rigidity and ergodicity of horospherical foliations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13727v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a higher rank extension of rigidity theorems of Sullivan, Tukia, Yue, and Kim-Oh for representations of rank one discrete subgroups of divergence type, in terms of the push-forwards of conformal measures via boundary maps. We consider a certain class of higher rank discrete subgroups, which we call hypertransverse subgroups. It includes all rank one discrete subgroups, Anosov subgroups, relatively Anosov subgroups, and their subgroups.
  Our proof of the rigidity theorem generalizes the idea of Kim-Oh to self-joinings of higher rank hypertransverse subgroups, overcoming the lack of CAT(-1) geometry on symmetric spaces. In contrast to the work of Sullivan, Tukia, and Yue, our argument is closely related to the study of horospherical foliations. We also show the ergodicity of horospherical foliations with respect to Burger-Roblin measures. This generalizes the classical work of Hedlund, Burger, and Roblin in rank one and of Lee-Oh for Borel Ansov subgroups in higher rank.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13727v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongryul M. Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
