<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 05:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cocycles in Lie Groups, Cochains and Regularity Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18757v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: After the fundamental work of Livschitz in [1; 2], various research directions emerged, among which the following stand out: (i) the study of cocycles with values in groups and semigroups beyond R, as well as the investigation of corresponding regularity results; (ii) the analysis of how a certain degree of regularity of the cocycle can confer corresponding regularity to the solution of the cohomological equation; and (iii) the study of higher-dimensional cohomology naturally associated with the action of groups other than Z or R. The aim of this article is to present, as self-contained as possible, a review of the natural generalizations of the notions of cocycles and cochains, as well as their corresponding results, in the study of cohomological equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18757v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ros\'ario D. Laureano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditional symmetries and conditional constants of motion for dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18802v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conditional symmetries were introduced by Levi and Winternitz in their 1989 seminal paper to deal with nonlinear PDEs. Here we discuss their application in the framework of ODEs, and more specifically Dynamical Systems; it turns out they are closely related to two established -- albeit maybe less widely known -- concepts, i.e. orbital symmetries and configurational invariants. The paper is devoted to studying the interplay of these notions, and their application in the study of Dynamical Systems, with special attention to invariant manifolds of these.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18802v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Gaeta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local high-degree polynomial integrals of geodesic flows and the generalized hodograph method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18920v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study Riemannian metrics on 2-surfaces with integrable geodesic flows such that an additional first integral is high-degree polynomial in momenta. This problem reduces to searching for solutions to certain quasi-linear systems of PDEs which turn out to be semi-Hamiltonian. We construct plenty of local explicit and implicit integrable examples with polynomial first integrals of degrees 3, 4, 5. Our construction is essentially based on applying the generalized hodograph method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18920v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Agapov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharkovskii theorem for infinite dimensional dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present adaptation of the relatively simple topological argument to show the existence of many periodic orbits in a system of Delay Differential Equations. Namely, we prove a Sharkovskii-type theorem: if the system has a periodic orbit of basic period $m$, then it must have all periodic orbits of periods $n \triangleright m$, for $n$ preceding $m$ in Sharkovskii ordering. The assumptions of the theorem can be verified with computer assistance. Moreover, the theory is general in a way that it can be applied to any dynamical system in infinite dimensions, provided the system is close to a one-dimensional map in a certain sense.
  As an exemplary application we show that the R\"ossler system perturbed by a delayed term retains periodic orbits of all natural periods for fixed values of parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19190v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Gierzkiewicz, Robert Szczelina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dold coefficients of quasi-unipotent homeomorphisms of orientable surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sequence of Dold coefficients $(a_n(f))_n$ of a self-map $f\colon X \to X$ forms a dual sequence to the sequence of Lefschetz numbers $(L(f^n))_n$ of iterations of $f$ under the M\"obius inversion formula. The set ${\mathcal AP}(f) = \{ n \,\colon\, a_n(f) \neq 0 \}$ is called the set of algebraic periods of $f$. Both the set of algebraic periods and sequence of Dold coefficients play an important role in dynamical system and periodic point theory.
  In this work we provide a description of surface homeomorphisms with bounded $(L(f^n))_n$ (quasi-unipotent maps) in terms of Dold coefficients. We also discuss the problem of minimization of the genus of a surface for which one can realize a given set of natural numbers as the set of algebraic periods. Finally, we compute and list all possible Dold coefficients and algebraic periods for a given orientable surface with small genus and give some geometrical applications of the obtained results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19313v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grzegorz Graff, Wac{\l}aw Marzantowicz, {\L}ukasz Patryk Michalak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fractional Poisson process and other limit point processes for rare events in infinite ergodic theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the process of suitably normalized successive return times to rare events in the setting of infinite-measure preserving dynamical systems. Specifically, we consider small neighborhoods of points whose measure tends to zero. We obtain two types of results. First, we conduct a detailed study of a class of interval maps with a neutral fixed point and we fully characterize the limit processes for all points, highlighting a trichotomy and the emergence of the fractional (possibly compound) Poisson process. This is the first time that these processes have been explicitly identified in this context. Second, we prove an abstract result that offers an explanation for the emergence of the fractional Poisson process, as the unique fixed point of a functional equation, drawing a parallel with the well-established behavior of the Poisson process in finite-measure preserving dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19337v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Bansard-Tresse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant Distributions of Partially Hyperbolic Systems: Fractal Graphs, Excessive Regularity, and Rigidity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19665v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel approach linking fractal geometry to partially hyperbolic dynamics, revealing several new phenomena related to regularity jumps and rigidity. One key result demonstrates a sharp phase transition for partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms $f \in \mathrm{Diff}^\infty_{\mathrm{vol}}(\mathbb{T}^3)$ with a contracting center direction: $f$ is $C^\infty$-rigid if and only if both $E^s$ and $E^c$ exhibit H\"older exponents exceeding the expected threshold. Specifically, we prove:
  If the H\"older exponent of $E^s$ exceeds the expected value, then $E^s$ is $C^{1+}$ and $E^u \oplus E^s$ is jointly integrable.
  If the H\"older exponent of $E^c$ exceeds the expected value, then $W^c$ forms a $C^{1+}$ foliation.
  If $E^s$ (or $E^c$) does not exhibit excessive H\"older regularity, it must have a fractal graph.
  These and related results originate from a general non-fractal invariance principle: for a skew product $F$ over a partially hyperbolic system $f$, if $F$ expands fibers more weakly than $f$ along $W^u_f$ in the base, then for any $F$-invariant section, if $\Phi$ has no a fractal graph, then it is smooth along $W^u_f$ and holonomy-invariant.
  Motivated by these findings, we propose a new conjecture on the stable fractal or stable smooth behavior of invariant distributions in typical partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19665v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Disheng Xu, Jiesong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic asymptotic dimension growth for group actions and groupoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19712v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of dynamic asymptotic dimension growth for actions of discrete groups on compact spaces, and more generally for locally compact \'etale groupoids with compact unit space. Using the work of Bartels, L\"uck, and Reich to bridge our notion for group actions with asymptotic dimension growth for groups, thus providing many concrete examples for our notion. Moreover, we show that the asymptotic dimension growth for a discrete metric space of bounded geometry is equivalent to the dynamic asymptotic dimension growth for its associated coarse groupoid, hence deducing that the coarse groupoid with subexponential dynamic asymptotic dimension growth is amenable. More generally, every $\sigma$-compact locally compact Hausdorff \'etale groupoid with compact unit space having dynamic asymptotic dimension growth at most $x^{\alpha}$ $(0&lt;\alpha&lt;1)$ is amenable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19712v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hang Wang, Yanru Wang, Jianguo Zhang, Dapeng Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of topography and combustion functions on fire front propagation in an advection-diffusion-reaction model for wildfires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02837v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given the recent increase in wildfires, developing a better understanding of their dynamics is crucial. For this purpose, the advection-diffusion-reaction model has been widely used to study wildfire dynamics. In this study, we introduce the previously unconsidered influence of topography through an additional advective term. Furthermore, we propose a linear term for the combustion function, comparing it with the commonly used Arrhenius law to offer a simpler model for further analysis. Our findings on the model's dynamics are supported by numerical simulations showing the differences of model extensions and approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02837v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Nieding, Cordula Reisch, Dirk Langemann, Adri\'an Navas-Montilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Operators for Predictor Feedback Control of Nonlinear Delay Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Predictor feedback designs are critical for delay-compensating controllers in nonlinear systems. However, these designs are limited in practical applications as predictors cannot be directly implemented, but require numerical approximation schemes. These numerical schemes, typically combining finite difference and successive approximations, become computationally prohibitive when the dynamics of the system are expensive to compute. To alleviate this issue, we propose approximating the predictor mapping via a neural operator. In particular, we introduce a new perspective on predictor designs by recasting the predictor formulation as an operator learning problem. We then prove the existence of an arbitrarily accurate neural operator approximation of the predictor operator. Under the approximated-predictor, we achieve semiglobal practical stability of the closed-loop nonlinear system. The estimate is semiglobal in a unique sense - namely, one can increase the set of initial states as large as desired but this will naturally increase the difficulty of training a neural operator approximation which appears practically in the stability estimate. Furthermore, we emphasize that our result holds not just for neural operators, but any black-box predictor satisfying a universal approximation error bound. From a computational perspective, the advantage of the neural operator approach is clear as it requires training once, offline and then is deployed with very little computational cost in the feedback controller. We conduct experiments controlling a 5-link robotic manipulator with different state-of-the-art neural operator architectures demonstrating speedups on the magnitude of $10^2$ compared to traditional predictor approximation schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18964v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke Bhan, Peijia Qin, Miroslav Krstic, Yuanyuan Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractal Conditional Correlation Dimension Infers Complex Causal Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19284v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Determining causal inference has become popular in physical and engineering applications. While the problem has immense challenges, it provides a way to model the complex networks by observing the time series. In this paper, we present the optimal conditional correlation dimensional geometric information flow principle ($oGeoC$) that can reveal direct and indirect causal relations in a network through geometric interpretations. We introduce two algorithms that utilize the $oGeoC$ principle to discover the direct links and then remove indirect links. The algorithms are evaluated using coupled logistic networks. The results indicate that when the number of observations is sufficient, the proposed algorithms are highly accurate in identifying direct causal links and have a low false positive rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19284v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\"Ozge Canl{\i} Usta, Erik M. Bollt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LD-EnSF: Synergizing Latent Dynamics with Ensemble Score Filters for Fast Data Assimilation with Sparse Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19305v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Data assimilation techniques are crucial for correcting the trajectory when modeling complex physical systems. A recently developed data assimilation method, Latent Ensemble Score Filter (Latent-EnSF), has shown great promise in addressing the key limitation of EnSF for highly sparse observations in high-dimensional and nonlinear data assimilation problems. It performs data assimilation in a latent space for encoded states and observations in every assimilation step, and requires costly full dynamics to be evolved in the original space. In this paper, we introduce Latent Dynamics EnSF (LD-EnSF), a novel methodology that completely avoids the full dynamics evolution and significantly accelerates the data assimilation process, which is especially valuable for complex dynamical problems that require fast data assimilation in real time. To accomplish this, we introduce a novel variant of Latent Dynamics Networks (LDNets) to effectively capture and preserve the system's dynamics within a very low-dimensional latent space. Additionally, we propose a new method for encoding sparse observations into the latent space using Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) networks, which leverage not only the current step's observations, as in Latent-EnSF, but also all previous steps, thereby improving the accuracy and robustness of the observation encoding. We demonstrate the robustness, accuracy, and efficiency of the proposed method for two challenging dynamical systems with highly sparse (in both space and time) and noisy observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19305v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengpeng Xiao, Phillip Si, Peng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalization of the Painlev\'e Property and Existence and Uniqueness in Fractional Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19411v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, the Painlev\'e property to fractional differential equations (FDEs) are extended and the existence and uniqueness theorems for both linear and nonlinear FDEs are established. The results contribute to the research of integrability and solvability in the context of fractional calculus, which has significant implications in various fields such as physics, engineering, and applied sciences. By bridging the gap between pure mathematical theory and practical applications, this work provides a foundational understanding that can be utilized in modeling phenomena exhibiting memory and hereditary properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19411v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Fiedorowicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lyapunov based dynamic controller designs for reach-and-avoid problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19607v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Safe obstacle avoidance and target set stabilization for nonlinear systems using reactive feedback control is under consideration. Based only on local information and by considering virtual dynamics, a safe path is generated online. The control law for the virtual dynamics is combined with a feedback controller for the dynamics of interest, where Lyapunov arguments and forward invariance are used to ensure that the state of the system remains in a vicinity of the path. To allow for discrete decisions in the avoidance controller design, the closed-loop dynamics are formulated using the hybrid systems framework. The results are illustrated by a numerical example for unicycle dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19607v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Lanza, Philipp Braun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the degenerate Arnold conjecture on $\mathbb T^{2m}\times \mathbb C\mathbb P^n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19636v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the 1960s Arnold conjectured that a Hamiltonian diffeomorphism of a closed connected symplectic manifold $(M,\omega)$ should have at least as many contractible fixed points as a smooth function on $M$ has critical points. Such a conjecture can be seen as a natural generalization of Poincar\'e's last geometric theorem and is one of the most famous (and still nowadays open in its full generality) problems in symplectic geometry. In this paper, we build on a recent approach of the authors and Izydorek to the Arnold conjecture on $\mathbb C\mathbb P^n$ to show that the (degenerate) Arnold conjecture holds for Hamiltonian diffeomorphisms $\phi$ of $\mathbb T^{2m}\times \mathbb C\mathbb P^n$, $m,n\geq 1$, which are $C^0$-close to the identity in the $\mathbb C \mathbb P^n$-direction, namely that any such $\phi$ has at least $\text{CL}(\mathbb T^{2m}\times \mathbb C\mathbb P^n)+1= 2m+n+1$ contractible fixed points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19636v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Asselle, M. Starostka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The modulating function method for state estimation and feedback of infinite-dimensional systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19771v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate state feedback and observation for infinite-dimensional linear systems, including a variety of partial differential equations with boundary control and observation. We extend the modulating function approach to infinite-dimensional systems. This approach, simply put, involves reconstructing part of the state by convolving with null controls of the adjoint system. We show how this method aids in state reconstruction, and we also examine distributional solutions of the adjoint system, showing their ability to handle unbounded feedback operators. This enables us to use feedback from spatial point evaluations in partial differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19771v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Folke Friedrich, Johann Reger, Timo Reis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite volume ends of quotient graphs and homogeneous spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19776v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the space of infinite volume ends of a locally compact second countable (lcsc) space that admits a Radon measure. In certain cases, this coincides with the classical space of ends.
  Consider a discrete subgroup $\Gamma$ of a unimodular lcsc group $G$ that is not coamenable. Assume that $G$ has property (T) and the associated homogeneous space $G/\Gamma$ is equipped with the Haar measure. We demonstrate that if $G$ is path connected, then $G/\Gamma$ has exactly one infinite volume end. In a related vein, if $G$ acts transitively on a locally finite connected graph $X$ with compact open vertex stabilizers and the action of the subgroup $\Gamma$ is free, we show that $X/\Gamma$ has exactly one end. We also obtain identical results for certain discrete subgroups $\Gamma$ of nonamenable product groups $G$.
  These results can be applied to understand ends of Schreier graphs and infinite volume ends of quotients of symmetric spaces of noncompact type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19776v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konrad Wr\'obel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperdimensional Computing Provides a Programming Paradigm for Oscillatory Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11783v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The increasing difficulty in continued development of digital electronic logic has led to a renewed interest in alternative approaches. Oscillatory computing is one such approach that leverages alternative physical systems and computation strategies, but it lacks high-level paradigms for system design and programming. We address this gap by describing a model based on hyperdimensional computing that serves as an "instruction set" to integrate oscillatory networks into algorithms for real-valued computing. The expressiveness and compositionality of these instructions allow oscillatory systems to implement both common tasks and novel functions, providing a clear computational role for many emerging hardware devices. We detail the computational primitives of this system, prove how they can be executed via oscillatory systems, quantify the performance of these operations, and apply them to execute multiple tasks including compression, factorization, and classification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11783v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wilkie Olin-Ammentorp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On extended model of Josephson junction, linear systems with polynomial solutions, determinantal surfaces and Painlev\'e III equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11236v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a 3-parameter family of linear special double confluent Heun equations introduced and studied by V.M.Buchstaber and S.I.Tertychnyi, which is an equivalent presentation of a model of Josephson junction in superconductivity. Buchstaber and Tertychnyi have shown that the set of those complex parameters for which the Heun equation has a polynomial solution is a union of explicit planar algebraic curves: the spectral curves indexed by $\ell\in\mathbb N$. In his paper with I.V.Netay, the author has shown that each spectral curve is irreducible in Heun equation parameters (consists of two irreducible components in parameters of Josephson junction model). Netay discovered numerically and conjectured a genus formula for spectral curves. He reduced it to the conjecture stating that each of them is regular in $\mathbb C^2$ with a coordinate axis deleted. Here we prove Netay's regularity and genus conjectures. For the proof we study a 4-parameter extension of a family of linear systems equivalent to the Heun equations. They yield an equivalent presentation of the extension of model of Josephson junction introduced by the author in his paper with Yu.P.Bibilo. We describe the so-called determinantal surfaces consisting of linear systems with polynomial solutions as explicit algebraic surfaces indexed by $\ell\in\mathbb N$. The spectral curves are their intersections with the hyperplane of the initial Heun equation family. We prove that each determinantal surface is regular outside appropriate hyperplane and consists of two rational irreducible components. The proofs use Stokes phenomena theory, holomorphic vector bundle technique, foliation of determinantal surfaces by isomonodromic families of linear systems governed by Painlev\'e 3 equation and transversality of the latter foliation to the initial model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11236v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Glutsyuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noisy Fixed Points: Stability of the Invariant Distribution of the Random Logistic Map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13116v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The full family of discrete logistic maps has been widely studied both as a canonical example of the period-doubling route to chaos, and as a model of natural processes. In this paper we present a study of the stochastic process described by iterations of the logistic map with a random parameter. In addition to bringing together previously known results, we present a proof that the unique invariant measure of the process in the chaotic regime is asymptotically stable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13116v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kimberly Ayers, Ami Radunskaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the topological synchronisation of unimodal maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07661v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note we complete the analysis carried on in \cite{CGSV} about the topological synchronisation of unimodal maps of the interval coupled in a master-slave configuration, by answering to the questions raised in that paper. Namely, we compute the weak limits of the invariant measure of the coupled system as the coupling strength $k\in\left( 0,1\right) $ tends to $0$ and to $1$ and discuss the uniqueness of the invariant measure of its random dynamical system counterpart, proving that the convergence of the associated Markov chain to its unique stationary measure is geometric.
  [CGSV] Caby Th., Gianfelice M., Saussol B., Vaienti S. "Topological synchronisation or a simple attractor?" Nonlinearity Vol. 36, no. 7, pp. 3603-3621 (2023).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07661v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Gianfelice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The moduli space of multi-scale differentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.13492</link>
      <description>arXiv:1910.13492v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a compactification of the moduli spaces of abelian differentials on Riemann surfaces with prescribed zeroes and poles. This compactification, called the moduli space of multi-scale differentials, is a complex orbifold with normal crossing boundary. Locally, our compactification can be described as the normalization of an explicit blowup of the incidence variety compactification, which was defined in [BCGGM18] as the closure of the stratum of abelian differentials in the closure of the Hodge bundle. We also define families of projectivized multi-scale differentials, which gives a proper Deligne-Mumford stack, and our compactification is the orbifold corresponding to it. Moreover, we perform a real oriented blowup of the unprojectivized moduli space of multi-scale differentials such that the $\mathrm{GL}_2(\mathbb R)$-action in the interior of the moduli space extends continuously to the boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1910.13492v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matt Bainbridge, Dawei Chen, Quentin Gendron, Samuel Grushevsky, Martin M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving-Horizon Estimators for Hyperbolic and Parabolic PDEs in 1-D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02516v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Observers for PDEs are themselves PDEs. Therefore, producing real time estimates with such observers is computationally burdensome. For both finite-dimensional and ODE systems, moving-horizon estimators (MHE) are operators whose output is the state estimate, while their inputs are the initial state estimate at the beginning of the horizon as well as the measured output and input signals over the moving time horizon. In this paper we introduce MHEs for PDEs which remove the need for a numerical solution of an observer PDE in real time. We accomplish this using the PDE backstepping method which, for certain classes of both hyperbolic and parabolic PDEs, produces moving-horizon state estimates explicitly. Precisely, to explicitly produce the state estimates, we employ a backstepping transformation of a hard-to-solve observer PDE into a target observer PDE, which is explicitly solvable. The MHEs we propose are not new observer designs but simply the explicit MHE realizations, over a moving horizon of arbitrary length, of the existing backstepping observers. Our PDE MHEs lack the optimality of the MHEs that arose as duals of MPC, but they are given explicitly, even for PDEs. In the paper we provide explicit formulae for MHEs for both hyperbolic and parabolic PDEs, as well as simulation results that illustrate theoretically guaranteed convergence of the MHEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02516v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke Bhan, Yuanyuan Shi, Iasson Karafyllis, Miroslav Krstic, James B. Rawlings</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive control of reaction-diffusion PDEs via neural operator-approximated gain kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01745v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural operator approximations of the gain kernels in PDE backstepping has emerged as a viable method for implementing controllers in real time. With such an approach, one approximates the gain kernel, which maps the plant coefficient into the solution of a PDE, with a neural operator. It is in adaptive control that the benefit of the neural operator is realized, as the kernel PDE solution needs to be computed online, for every updated estimate of the plant coefficient. We extend the neural operator methodology from adaptive control of a hyperbolic PDE to adaptive control of a benchmark parabolic PDE (a reaction-diffusion equation with a spatially-varying and unknown reaction coefficient). We prove global stability and asymptotic regulation of the plant state for a Lyapunov design of parameter adaptation. The key technical challenge of the result is handling the 2D nature of the gain kernels and proving that the target system with two distinct sources of perturbation terms, due to the parameter estimation error and due to the neural approximation error, is Lyapunov stable. To verify our theoretical result, we present simulations achieving calculation speedups up to 45x relative to the traditional finite difference solvers for every timestep in the simulation trajectory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01745v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke Bhan, Yuanyuan Shi, Miroslav Krstic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parsimonious Dynamic Mode Decomposition: A Robust and Automated Approach for Optimally Sparse Mode Selection in Complex Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16656v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces the Parsimonious Dynamic Mode Decomposition (parsDMD), a novel algorithm designed to automatically select an optimally sparse subset of dynamic modes for both spatiotemporal and purely temporal data. By incorporating time-delay embedding and leveraging Orthogonal Matching Pursuit (OMP), parsDMD ensures robustness against noise and effectively handles complex, nonlinear dynamics. The algorithm is validated on a diverse range of datasets, including standing wave signals, identifying hidden dynamics, fluid dynamics simulations (flow past a cylinder and transonic buffet), and atmospheric sea-surface temperature (SST) data. ParsDMD addresses a significant limitation of the traditional sparsity-promoting DMD (spDMD), which requires manual tuning of sparsity parameters through a rigorous trial-and-error process to balance between single-mode and all-mode solutions. In contrast, parsDMD autonomously determines the optimally sparse subset of modes without user intervention, while maintaining minimal computational complexity. Comparative analyses demonstrate that parsDMD consistently outperforms spDMD by providing more accurate mode identification and effective reconstruction in noisy environments. These advantages render parsDMD an effective tool for real-time diagnostics, forecasting, and reduced-order model construction across various disciplines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16656v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Das, Pier Marzocca, Oleg Levinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypergraphs and homogeneous Lotka-Volterra systems with linear Darboux polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18264v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We associate homogeneous $n$-component Lotka-Volterra systems which admit $k$ additional linear Darboux polynomials, with admissible hypergraphs of order $n$ and size $k$. We study the equivalence relation on admissible hypergraphs induced by linear transformations of the associated LV-systems, for $n\leq 5$. We present a new 13-parameter 5-component superintegrable Lotka-Volterra system, i.e. one that is not equivalent to a so-called tree-system. We conjecture that tree-systems associated with nonisomorphic trees are not equivalent, which we verified for $n&lt;9$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18264v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter H. van der Kamp</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
