<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 04:00:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Garbage disposal game on finite graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17511v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The garbage disposal game involves a finite set of individuals, each of whom updates their garbage by either receiving from or dumping onto others. We examine the case where only social neighbors, whose garbage levels differ by a given threshold, can offload an equal proportion of their garbage onto others. Remarkably, in the absence of this threshold, the garbage amounts of all individuals converge to the initial average on any connected social graph that is not a star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17511v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsin-Lun Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-formally integrable centers admitting an algebraic inverse integrating factor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17694v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Westudy the existence of a class of inverse integrating factor for a family of non formally integrable systems, in general, whose lowest-degree quasi-homogeneous
  term is a Hamiltonian vector field. Once the existence of an inverse integrat ing factor is established, we characterize the systems having a center. Among others, we characterize the centers of the systems whose lowest-degree quasiho mogeneous term is (-y3,x3)T with an algebraic inverse integrating factor.
  Keywords: Nonlinear differential systems, Inverse integrating factor, Integrability problem, Degenerate center problem</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17694v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3934/dcds.2018041</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. Algaba, N. Fuentes, C. Garcia, M. Reyes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital normal forms for a class of three-dimensional systems with an application to Hopf-zero bifurcation analysis of Fitzhugh-Nagumo system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a class of three-dimensional systems having an equilibrium point at the origin, whose principal part is of the form (-Dy h(x, y), Dx h(x,y), f(x,y))^T . This principal part, which has zero divergence and does not depend on the third variable z, is the coupling of a planar Hamiltonian vector field Xh(x,y)=(-Dy h(x, y), Dx h(x,y))^T with a one-dimensional system. We analyze the quasi-homogeneous orbital normal forms for this kind of systems, by introducing a new splitting for quasi-homogeneous three-dimensional vector fields. The obtained results are applied to the nondegenerate Hopf-zero singularity that falls into this kind of systems. Beyond the Hopf-zero normal form, a parametric normal form is obtained, and the analytic expressions for the normal form coefficients are provided. Finally, the results are applied to a case of the three-dimensional Fitzhugh-Nagumo system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18079v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A Algaba, N Fuentes, E Gamero, C Garc\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Using Active Learning Methods for Human-Seat Interactions To Generate Realistic Occupant Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17163v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the context of developing new vehicle concepts, especially autonomous vehicles with novel seating arrangements and occupant activities, predicting occupant motion can be a tool for ensuring safety and comfort. In this study, a data-driven surrogate contact model integrated into an optimal control framework to predict human occupant behavior during driving maneuvers is presented. High-fidelity finite element simulations are utilized to generate a dataset of interaction forces and moments for various human body configurations and velocities. To automate the generation of training data, an active learning approach is introduced, which iteratively queries the high-fidelity finite element simulation for an additional dataset. The feasibility and effectiveness of the proposed method are demonstrated through a case study of a head interaction with an automotive headrest, showing promising results in accurately replicating contact forces and moments while reducing manual effort.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17163v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Fahse, Monika Harant, Marius Obentheuer, Joachim Linn, J\"org Fehr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Kermack--McKendrick type epidemic model with double threshold phenomenon (and a possible application to Covid-19)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17278v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The suggestion by K.L. Cooke (1967) that infected individuals become infective if they are exposed often enough for a natural disease resistance to be overcome is built into a Kermack-McKendrick type epidemic model with infectivity age. Both the case that the resistance may be the same for all hosts and the case that it is distributed among the host population are considered. In addition to the familiar threshold behavior of the final size of the epidemic with respect to a basic reproductive number, an Allee effect is generated with respect to the final cumulative force of infection exerted by the initial infectives. This offers a deterministic explanation of why geographic areas that appear to be epidemiologically similar have epidemic outbreaks of quite different severity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17278v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joan Ponce, Horst R. Thieme</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Koopman-driven grip force prediction through EMG sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17340v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Loss of hand function due to conditions like stroke or multiple sclerosis significantly impacts daily activities. Robotic rehabilitation provides tools to restore hand function, while novel methods based on surface electromyography (sEMG) enable the adaptation of the device's force output according to the user's condition, thereby improving rehabilitation outcomes. This study aims to achieve accurate force estimations during medium wrap grasps using a single sEMG sensor pair, thereby addressing the challenge of escalating sensor requirements for precise predictions. We conducted sEMG measurements on 13 subjects at two forearm positions, validating results with a hand dynamometer. We established flexible signal-processing steps, yielding high peak cross-correlations between the processed sEMG signal (representing meaningful muscle activity) and grip force. Influential parameters were subsequently identified through sensitivity analysis. Leveraging a novel data-driven Koopman operator theory-based approach and problem-specific data lifting techniques, we devised a methodology for the estimation and short-term prediction of grip force from processed sEMG signals. A weighted mean absolute percentage error (wMAPE) of approx. 5.5% was achieved for the estimated grip force, whereas predictions with a 0.5-second prediction horizon resulted in a wMAPE of approx. 17.9%. The methodology proved robust regarding precise electrode positioning, as the effect of sensing position on error metrics was non-significant. The algorithm executes exceptionally fast, processing, estimating, and predicting a 0.5-second sEMG signal batch in just approx. 30 ms, facilitating real-time implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17340v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomislav Bazina, Ervin Kamenar, Maria Fonoberova, Igor Mezi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the number of quadratic polynomials with a given portrait</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a number field. Given a quadratic polynomial $f_c(z) = z^2 + c \in F[z]$, we can construct a directed graph $Preper(f_c, F)$ (also called a portrait), whose vertices are $F$-rational preperiodic points for $f_c$, with an edge $\alpha \to \beta$ if and only if $f_c(\alpha) = \beta$. Poonen and Faber classified the portraits that occur for infinitely many $c$'s.
  Given a portrait $P$, we prove an asymptotic formula for counting the number of $c \in F$'s by height, such that $Preper(f_c, F) \cong P$. We also prove an asymptotic formula for the analogous counting problem, where $Preper(f_c, K) \cong P$ for some quadratic extension $K/F$. These results are conditioned on Morton-Silverman conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18074v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ho Chung Siu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A $C^r$-connecting lemma for Lorenz attractors and its application on the space of ergodic measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.08193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2006.08193v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For every $r\in\mathbb{N}_{\geq 2}\cup\{\infty\}$, we prove a $C^r$-connecting lemma for Lorenz attractors. To be precise, for a Lorenz attractor of a $3$-dimensional $C^r$ ($r\geq 2$) vector field, a heteroclinic orbit associated to the singularity and a critical element can be created through arbitrarily small $C^r$-perturbations. As an application, we show that for $C^r$-dense geometric Lorenz attractors, the Dirac measure of the singularity is isolated inside the space of ergodic measures and thus the ergodic measure space is not connected; while for $C^r$-generic geometric Lorenz attractors, the space of ergodic measures is path connected with dense periodic measures. In particular, the generic part proves a conjecture proposed by C. Bonatti in $C^r$-topology for Lorenz attractors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2006.08193v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Shi, Xueting Tian, Xiaodong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A version of Hilbert's 16th Problem for 3D polynomial vector fields: Counting isolated invariant tori</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.12006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.12006v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hilbert's 16th Problem, about the maximum number of limit cycles of planar polynomial vector fields of a given degree $m$, has been one of the most important driving forces for new developments in the qualitative theory of vector fields. Increasing the dimension, one cannot expect the existence of a finite upper bound for the number of limit cycles of, for instance, $3$D polynomial vector fields of a given degree $m$. Here, as an extension of such a problem in the $3$D space, we investigate the number of isolated invariant tori in $3$D polynomial vector fields. In this context, given a natural number $m$, we denote by $N(m)$ the upper bound for the number of isolated invariant tori of $3$D polynomial vector fields of degree $m$. Based on a recently developed averaging method for detecting invariant tori, our first main result provides a mechanism for constructing $3$D differential vector fields with a number $H$ of normally hyperbolic invariant tori from a given planar differential vector field with $H$ hyperbolic limit cycles. The strength of our mechanism in studying the number $N(m)$ lies in the fact that the constructed $3$D differential vector field is polynomial provided that the given planar differential vector field is polynomial. Accordingly, our second main result establishes a lower bound for $N(m)$ in terms of lower bounds for the number of hyperbolic limit cycles of planar polynomial vector fields of degree $[m/2]-1$. Based on this last result, we apply a methodology due to Christopher &amp; Lloyd to show that $N(m)$ grows as fast as $m^3/128$. Finally, the above-mentioned problem is also formulated for higher dimensional polynomial vector fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.12006v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Douglas D. Novaes, Pedro C. C. R. Pereira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Exact Linearization of Minimally Underactuated Configuration Flat Lagrangian Systems in Generalized State Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05023v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we examine the exact linearization of configuration flat Lagrangian control systems in generalized state representation with p degrees of freedom and p-1 control inputs by quasi-static feedback of its generalized state. We formally introduce generalized Lagrangian control systems, which are obtained when configuration variables are considered as inputs instead of forces. This work presents all possible lengths of integrator chains achieved by an exact linearization with a quasi-static feedback law of the generalized state that allows for rest-to-rest transitions. We show that such feedback laws can be systematically derived without using Brunovsk\'y states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05023v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georg Hartl, Conrad Gst\"ottner, Bernd Kolar, Markus Sch\"oberl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a variant of Hilbert's 16th problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04281v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the number of limit cycles that a planar polynomial vector field can have as a function of its number $m$ of monomials. We prove that the number of limit cycles increases at least quadratically with $m$ and we provide good lower bounds for $m\leqslant10$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04281v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armengol Gasull, Paulo Santana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time and State Dependent Neural Delay Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.14545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.14545v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Discontinuities and delayed terms are encountered in the governing equations of a large class of problems ranging from physics and engineering to medicine and economics. These systems cannot be properly modelled and simulated with standard Ordinary Differential Equations (ODE), or data-driven approximations such as Neural Ordinary Differential Equations (NODE). To circumvent this issue, latent variables are typically introduced to solve the dynamics of the system in a higher dimensional space and obtain the solution as a projection to the original space. However, this solution lacks physical interpretability. In contrast, Delay Differential Equations (DDEs), and their data-driven approximated counterparts, naturally appear as good candidates to characterize such systems. In this work we revisit the recently proposed Neural DDE by introducing Neural State-Dependent DDE (SDDDE), a general and flexible framework that can model multiple and state- and time-dependent delays. We show that our method is competitive and outperforms other continuous-class models on a wide variety of delayed dynamical systems. Code is available at the repository \href{https://github.com/thibmonsel/Time-and-State-Dependent-Neural-Delay-Differential-Equations}{here}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.14545v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibault Monsel (DATAFLOT, TAU), Onofrio Semeraro (DATAFLOT), Lionel Mathelin (DATAFLOT), Guillaume Charpiat (TAU)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
