<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bifurcations and invariant sets for a family of replicator maps from evolutionary games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16379v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of a family of replicator maps, depending on two parameters. Such studies are motivated by the analysis of the dynamics of evolutionary games under selections. From the dynamics viewpoint, we prove the existence of hyperbolic chaos for the considered map. Moreover, we also give a partial solution of an open problem formulated in \cite{Misiurewicz1}: to describe all the one-dimensional maps with all the periodic orbits having the same mean value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16379v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Kryzhevich, Yiwei Zhang, Magdalena Chmara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On elementary integrability of rational vector fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider two aspects related to the Prelle-Singer theorem on elementary integrability of rational vector fields over $\mathbb C$. First, we present an alternative proof of this theorem which uses techniques developed in a recent paper. Second, elementary integrable vector fields which are not Darboux integrable may be considered exceptional. Building on this observation from earlier work, we characterize the possible algebraic extension fields underlying the exceptional cases, and provide a construction of exceptional vector fields, in dimension two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16550v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin Christopher, Sebastian Walcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kernel Methods for the Approximation of the Eigenfunctions of the Koopman Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Koopman operator provides a linear framework to study nonlinear dynamical systems. Its spectra offer valuable insights into system dynamics, but the operator can exhibit both discrete and continuous spectra, complicating direct computations. In this paper, we introduce a kernel-based method to construct the principal eigenfunctions of the Koopman operator without explicitly computing the operator itself. These principal eigenfunctions are associated with the equilibrium dynamics, and their eigenvalues match those of the linearization of the nonlinear system at the equilibrium point. We exploit the structure of the principal eigenfunctions by decomposing them into linear and nonlinear components. The linear part corresponds to the left eigenvector of the system's linearization at the equilibrium, while the nonlinear part is obtained by solving a partial differential equation (PDE) using kernel methods. Our approach avoids common issues such as spectral pollution and spurious eigenvalues, which can arise in previous methods. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our algorithm through numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16588v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonghyeon Lee, Boumediene Hamzi, Boya Hou, Houman Owhadi, Gabriele Santin, Umesh Vaidya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability analysis of the nonlinear pendulums under stochastic perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a nonlinear pendulum whose suspension point undergoes stochastic vibrations in its plane of motion. Stochastic vibrations are constructed by stochastic differential equations with random periodic solutions. Averaging over these stochastic vibrations can be simplified with ergodicity. We give a complete description of the bifurcations of phase portraits of the averaged Hamiltonian system. The bifurcation curves of the stochastic perturbed Hamiltonian system are shown numerically. Estimations between the averaged system and the exact system are calculated. The correspondence of the averaged system to the exact system is explained through the Poincar\'e return map. Studying the averaged Hamiltonian system provided important information for the exact stochastic perturbed Hamiltonian system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16639v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Luo, Kaicheng Sheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Behaviors of the Gradient Flows for In-Context Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the system of differential equations for the gradient flow characterizing the training process of linear in-context learning in full generality. Next, we explore the geometric structure of the gradient flows in two instances, including identifying its invariants, optimum, and saddle points. This understanding allows us to quantify the behavior of the two gradient flows under the full generality of parameters and data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16683v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songtao Lu, Yingdong Lu, Tomasz Nowicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power Law Behavior of Center-Like Decaying Oscillation : Exponent through Perturbation Theory and Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16695v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In dynamical systems theory, there is a lack of a straightforward rule to distinguish exact center solutions from decaying center-like solutions, as both require the damping force function to be zero [1, 2]. By adopting a multi-scale perturbative method, we have demonstrated a general rule for the decaying center-like power law behavior, characterized by an exponent of 1/3 . The investigation began with a physical question about the higher-order nonlinearity in a damping force function, which exhibits birhythmic and trirhythmic behavior under a transition to a decaying center-type solution. Using numerical optimization algorithms, we identified the power law exponent for decaying center-type behavior across various rhythmic conditions. For all scenarios, we consistently observed a decaying power law with an exponent of 1/3 .Our study aims to elucidate their dynamical differences, contributing to theoretical insights and practical applications where distinguishing between different types of center-like behaviour is crucial. This key result would be beneficial for studying the multi-rhythmic nature of biological and engineering systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16695v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandip Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimension of self-conformal measures associated to an exponentially separated analytic IFS on $\mathbb{R}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend Hochman's work on exponentially separated self-similar measures on $\mathbb{R}$ to the real analytic setting. More precisely, let $\Phi=\left\{ \varphi_{i}\right\} _{i\in\Lambda}$ be an iterated function system on $I:=[0,1]$ consisting of real analytic contractions, let $p=(p_{i})_{i\in\Lambda}$ be a positive probability vector, and let $\mu$ be the associated self-conformal measure. Suppose that the maps in $\Phi$ do not have a common fixed point, $0&lt;\left|\varphi_{i}'(x)\right|&lt;1$ for $i\in\Lambda$ and $x\in I$, and $\Phi$ is exponentially separated. Under these assumptions, we prove that $\dim\mu=\min\left\{ 1,H(p)/\chi\right\} $, where $H(p)$ is the entropy of $p$ and $\chi$ is the Lyapunov exponent. We also deduce an analogous result for the dimension of self-conformal sets.
  The main novelty of our work lies in an argument that reduces convolutions of $\mu$ with measures on the (infinite-dimensional) space of real analytic maps to convolutions with measures on vector spaces of polynomials of bounded degree. The reason for this reduction is that, for the latter convolutions, we can establish an entropy increase result, which plays a crucial role in the proof. We believe that our proof strategy has the potential to extend other significant recent results in the dimension theory of stationary fractal measures to the real analytic setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16753v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Rapaport</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiflows strongly focusing monotone with respect to high-rank cones: II. Pseudo-ordered principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a semiflow strongly focusing monotone with respect to a cone of rank k on a Banach space. We prove that the omega-limit set of a pseudo-ordered semiorbit is ordered, which is called as pseudo-ordered principle. Based on this principle, we obtain the solid Poincar\{'}e-Bendixson theorem with the rank k=2, that is, the omega-limit set of a pseudo-ordered semiorbit is either a nontrivial periodic orbit or a set consisting of equilibria with their potential connected orbits. The generic solid dynamics theorem with a general rank k and the generic solid Poincar\{'}e-Bendixson theorem with the rank k=2 are also obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17071v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lirui Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oscillating Turing patterns, chaos and strange attractors in a reaction-diffusion system augmented with self- and cross-diffusion terms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article we introduce an original model in order to study the emergence of chaos in a reaction diffusion system in the presence of self- and cross-diffusion terms. A Fourier Spectral Method is derived to approximate equilibria and orbits of the latter. Special attention is paid to accuracy, a necessary condition when one wants to catch periodic orbits and to perform their linear stability analysis via Floquet multipliers. Bifurcations with respect to a single control parameter are studied in four different regimes of diffusion: linear diffusion, self-diffusion for each of the two species, and cross-diffusion. Key observations are made: development of original Turing patterns, Hopf bifurcations leading to oscillating patterns and period doubling cascades leading to chaos. Eventually, original strange attractors are reported in phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17076v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Aymard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability and synchronisation in modelling an oscillatory stochastic reaction network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In many applied settings, the chemical Langevin equation and linear noise approximation are used in the simulation and data analysis of stochastic reaction networks. With the goal of exploring the sensitivities of reaction network paths to their initial conditions, we subject these modelling techniques to the analysis of random dynamical systems and stochastic flows of diffeomorphisms respectively. After introducing this perspective to stochastic reaction networks in general, we turn our attention to the Brusselator: a two dimensional stochastic reaction network whose paths, when noise is neglected, exhibits a Hopf bifurcation. Studying both Lyapunov exponents, as well as their finite time counterparts, provides two new insights. Firstly, the Brusselator, when modelled by the chemical Langevin equation, exhibits a global synchronisation property of paths of similar noise realisations; secondly, contrary to statistical accuracy in the distributions of concentrations of reactants, the linear noise approximation can fail to capture the finite time dynamical properties of paths of the chemical Langevin equation. In doing so, we explore the notions of dynamical bifurcation and quasi-ergodicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17093v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frederick Truman-Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Buff forms and invariant curves of near-parabolic maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a general framework to study the local dynamics of near-parabolic maps using the meromorphic $1$-form introduced by X.~Buff. As a sample application of this setup, we prove the following tameness result on invariant curves of near-parabolic maps: Let $g(z)=\lambda z+O(z^2)$ have a non-degenerate parabolic fixed point at $0$ with multiplier $\lambda$ a primitive $q$th root of unity, and let $\gamma: \, ]-\infty,0] \to {\mathbb D}(0,r)$ be a $g^{\circ q}$-invariant curve landing at $0$ in the sense that $g^{\circ q}(\gamma(t))=\gamma(t+1)$ and $\lim_{t \to -\infty} \gamma(t)=0$. Take a sequence $g_n(z)=\lambda_n z+O(z^2)$ with $|\lambda_n|\neq 1$ such that $g_n \to g$ uniformly on ${\mathbb D}(0,r)$ and suppose each $g_n$ admits a $g_n^{\circ q}$-invariant curve $\gamma_n: \, ]-\infty,0] \to {\mathbb C}$ such that $\gamma_n \to \gamma$ uniformly on the fundamental segment $[-1,0]$. If $\lambda_n^q \to 1$ non-tangentially, then $\gamma_n$ lands at a repelling periodic point near $0$, and $\gamma_n \to \gamma$ uniformly on $]-\infty,0]$. In the special case of polynomial maps, this proves Hausdorff continuity of external rays of a given periodic angle when the associated multipliers approach a root of unity non-tangentially.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17125v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carsten Lunde Petersen, Saeed Zakeri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete spectrum of probability measures for locally compact group actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study discrete spectrum of probability measures for non-autonomous systems and locally compact amenable group actions. It turns out that a probability measure has discrete spectrum if and only if it has bounded measure-max-mean-complexity. And as an application, an invariant measure of a locally compact amenable group action has discrete spectrum if and only if it has bounded mean-complexity along Folner sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17409v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongrui Hu, Xiao Ma, Leiye Xu, Xiaomin Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine Anosov representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this survey article we discuss about possible generalizations of Anosov representations in the affine setting and their consequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17422v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost sure convergence of cover times for $\psi$-mixing systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a topologically transitive system on the unit interval, one can investigate the \emph{cover time}, \ie time for an orbit to reach certain level of resolution in the repeller. We introduce a new notion of dimension, namely the \emph{stretched Minkowski dimension}, and show that under mixing conditions, the asymptotics of typical cover times are determined by Minkowski dimensions when they are finite, or by stretched Minkowski dimensions otherwise. For application, we show that for countably full-branched affine maps, results using the usual Minkowski dimensions fail to produce a finite log limit of cover times whilst the stretched version gives an finite limit. In addition, cover times of irrational rotations are explicitly calculated as counterexamples, due to the absence of mixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17425v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyuan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traveling Waves in Bistable Reaction-Diffusion Cellular Automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17441v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe various types of traveling fronts of bistable reaction-diffusion cellular automata. These dynamical systems with discrete time, space, and state spaces can be seen as fully discrete versions of widely studied bistable reaction-diffusion equations. We show that moving traveling waves for high diffusion parameters are restricted to slow speeds and their profiles are interestingly not unique. Pinned waves always exist for weak diffusion as in the case of lattice equations but do not complement parametric region of moving traveling waves. The remaining parameter domain is dominated by waves which are unique to cellular automaton settings. These higher-order traveling waves move and periodically change profile at the same time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17441v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel \v{S}pale, Petr Stehl\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational principle for packing topological pressure of nonautonomous dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the relationship between various topological pressures and the corresponding measure-theoretic pressures for nonautonomous dynamical systems based on the Carath\'eodory-Pesin structure. We prove a pressure distribution principle for Pesin topological pressure and a Billingsley type theorem for packing topological pressure. We then obtain a variational principle for packing topological pressure, which reveals a variational relation between the packing pressure and measure-theoretic upper local pressure. We further examine the applicability of our findings to a typical nonautonomous dynamical system, wherein the sequence of continuous selfmaps preserves the same Borel probability measures. In addition, we derive an upper bound for the packing topological pressure on the set of generic points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17634v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang-Bing Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the finiteness issue of four-body balanced configurations in the plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the number of $\mathbf{S}$-balanced configurations of four bodies in the plane is finite, provided that the symmetric matrix $\mathbf{S}$ is close to a numerical matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17639v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Wang, Lei Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small-amplitude periodic traveling waves in dimer Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17733v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the existence of small-amplitude periodic traveling waves in dimer Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou (FPUT) lattices without assumptions of physical symmetry. Such lattices are infinite, one-dimensional chains of coupled particles in which the particle masses and/or the potentials of the coupling springs can alternate. Previously, periodic traveling waves were constructed in a variety of limiting regimes for the symmetric mass and spring dimers, in which only one kind of material data alternates. The new results discussed here remove the symmetry assumptions by exploiting the gradient structure and translation invariance of the traveling wave problem. Together, these features eliminate certain solvability conditions that symmetry would otherwise manage and facilitate a bifurcation argument involving a two-dimensional kernel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17733v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy E. Faver, Hermen Jan Hupkes, J. Douglas Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric coupling of non-chaotic Rulkov neurons: fractal attractors, quasi-multistability, and final state sensitivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16189v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Although neuron models have been well-studied for their rich dynamics and biological properties, limited research has been done on the complex geometries that emerge from the basins of attraction and basin boundaries of multistable neuron systems. In this paper, we investigate the geometrical properties of the strange attractors, four-dimensional basins, and fractal basin boundaries of an asymmetrically electrically coupled system of two identical non-chaotic Rulkov neurons. We discover a quasi-multistability in the system emerging from the existence of a chaotic spiking-bursting pseudo-attractor, and we classify and quantify the system's basins of attraction, which are found to have complex fractal geometries. Using the method of uncertainty exponents, we also find that the system exhibits extreme final state sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16189v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brandon B. Le</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Varying Parameters in Dynamical Systems: A Modular Framework Using Switch Detection, Optimization, and Sparse Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16198v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The estimation of static parameters in dynamical systems and control theory has been extensively studied, with significant progress made in estimating varying parameters in specific system types. Suppose, in the general case, we have data from a system with parameters that depend on an independent variable such as time or space. Further, suppose the system's model structure is known, but our aim is to identify functions describing parameter-varying elements as they change with respect to time or another variable. Focusing initially on the subclass of problems where parameters are discretely switching piecewise constant functions, we develop an algorithmic framework for detecting discrete parameter switches and fitting a piecewise constant model to data using optimization-based parameter estimation. Our modular framework allows for customization of switch detection, numerical integration, and optimization sub-steps to suit user requirements. Binary segmentation is used for switch detection, with Nelder-Mead and Powell methods employed for optimization. To address broader problems, we extend our framework using dictionary-based sparse regression with trigonometric and polynomial functions to obtain continuously varying parameter functions. Finally, we assess the framework's robustness to measurement noise. We demonstrate its capabilities across several examples, including time-varying promoter-gene expression, a genetic toggle switch, a parameter-switching manifold, the heat equation with a time-varying diffusion coefficient, and the advection-diffusion equation with a continuously varying parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16198v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jamiree Harrison, Enoch Yeung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Young diagrams, deformed Calogero-Moser systems and Cayley graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16259v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let ${\mathtt{k}}$ be an algebraically closed field of characteristic zero and $n, m$ coprime positive integers. Let ${\stackrel{{\rm o}}{{\mathfrak{g}}}}$ be the Lie superalgebra ${\mathfrak{gl}}(n|m)$ with root system $\Delta$. Using $\Delta$, Sergeev and Veselov, \cite{SV2} introduced an action of the Weyl groupoid ${\mathcal{W}}$, in connection with their study of the the Grothendieck group of finite dimensinonal graded $\mathfrak{g}$-modules. We denote the subgroupoid of ${\mathcal{W}}$ with morphisms corresponding to isotropic roots by $\mathfrak T_{iso}$.
  Later, \cite{SV101} the same authors defined an action of ${\mathcal{W}}$ on $X={\mathtt{k}}^{n|m}$ such that the invariant algebra ${\mathcal{O}}(X)^{\mathcal{W}}$ is isomorphic to the algebra of quantum integrals for the deformed Calogero-Moser system introduced in \cite{SV1}. This completely integrable system depends on a non-zero parameter $\kappa$. When $\kappa=-m/n$ we study a certain infinite $\mathfrak T_{iso}$-orbit {\bf O} for this action. %which appears in \cite{SV101} Equation (14). The Cayley graph for this orbit is isomorphic to the Cayley graphs for two other actions of $\mathfrak T_{iso}$ which were studied in \cite{M23}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16259v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian M. Musson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The geometry of totally geodesic subvarieties of moduli spaces of Riemann surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a semi-simplicity result for the boundary, in the corresponding Deligne-Mumford compactification, of totally geodesic subvarieties of moduli spaces of Riemann surfaces. Phrased at the level of Teichm\"uller space, this semi-simplicity theorem gives that each component of the boundary is a product of simple factors, each of which behaves metrically like a diagonal embedding. We use this to show that the associated totally geodesic submanifolds of Teichm\"uller space and orbifold fundamental groups are hierarchically hyperbolic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16330v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Arana-Herrera, Alex Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the spectral flow theorem of Robbin-Salamon for finite intervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16332v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article we consider operators of the form $\partial_s\xi+A(s)\xi$ where $s$ lies in an interval $[-T,T]$ and $s\mapsto A(s)$ is continuous. Without boundary conditions these operators are not Fredholm. However, using interpolation theory one can define suitable boundary conditions for these operators so that they become Fredholm. We show that in this case the Fredholm index is given by the spectral flow of the operator path $A$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16332v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Urs Frauenfelder, Joa Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative energy functionals of passive linear time-varying systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16347v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The concept of dissipativity plays a crucial role in the analysis of control systems. Dissipative energy functionals, also known as Hamiltonians, storage functions, or Lyapunov functions, depending on the setting, are extremely valuable to analyze and control the behavior of dynamical systems, but in general circumstances they are very difficult to compute, and not fully understood. In this paper we consider passive linear time-varying (LTV) systems, under very mild regularity assumptions, and their associated storage functions, as a necessary step to analyze general nonlinear systems. We demonstrate that every passive LTV system must have at least one time-varying positive semidefinite quadratic storage function, greatly reducing our search scope. Now focusing on quadratic storage functions, we analyze in detail their necessary regularity, which is lesser than continuous. Moreover, we prove that the rank of quadratic storage functions is nonincreasing in time, allowing us to introduce a novel null space decomposition, under much weaker assumptions than the one needed for general matrix functions. Additionally, we show a necessary kernel condition for the quadratic storage function, allowing us to reduce our search scope even further.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16347v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Morandin, Dorothea Hinsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central limit theorem for periodic solutions of stochastic differential equations driven by Levy noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16437v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Through certain appropriate constructions, we establish periodic solutions in distribution for some stochastic differential equations with infinite-dimensional Levy noise. Additionally, we obtain the corresponding periodic measures and periodic transition semigroup. Under suitable conditions, we also achieve a certain contractivity in the space of probability measures. By constructing an appropriate invariant measure, we standardize the observation functions. Utilizing the classical martingale approximation approach, we establish the law of large numbers and the central limit theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16437v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinying Deng, Yong Li, Xue Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Multifractal Behavior of the Human Genome T2T-CHM13v2.0: Graphical Representations and Cytogenetics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16705v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we applied the Chaos Game Representation (CGR) to the complete human genomic sequence T2T-CHM13v2.0, analyzing the entire chromosome assembly and each chromosome separately, including mitochondrial DNA. Multifractal spectra were determined using two types of box-counting coverage, revealing slight variations across most chromosomes. While the geometric support remained consistent, distinct distributions were observed for each chromosome. Chromosomes 9 and Y exhibited the greatest differences in singularity (H\"older exponent), with minor variations in their fractal support. The CGR distributions generally demonstrated an approximate separation between coding and non-coding sections, as well as CpG or GpC islands. A base-by-base analysis of the fractal support of the CGR uncovered characteristic structural bands in chromosome sequences, which align with patterns identified in cytogenetic studies. Using the complete assembly as a reference, we compared two alternative representations: the Binary Genomic Representation (RGB) and the Markov Chain (MC) representation. Both methods tended toward the same fractal support but displayed differing distributions based on the assigned length parameter. Multifractal analysis highlighted quantitative differences between these representations: RGB aligned more closely with high-frequency components, while MC showed better correspondence with low frequencies. The optimal fit was achieved using MC for twelve-base chains, yielding an average percentage error of 2% relative to the full genomic assembly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16705v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.OT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuli\'an A. Alvarez-Ballesteros, Mario A. Quiroz-Juarez, Jos\'e L. Del-Rio-Correa, Adrian M. Escobar-Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The farthest point map on the 4-cube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16862v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the farthest point mapping on (the boundary of) the 4-cube with respect to the intrinsic metric, and its dynamics as a multivalued mapping. It is a piecewise rational map. It is more complicated than the one on the 3-cube, but it is shown that the limit set of the farthest point map on the 4-cube is the union of the diagonals of eight (3-cube) facets, like the farthest point map on the 3-cube whose limit set is the union of the six (square) facets. This is in contrast to the doubly covered simplices and (the boundary of) the regular 4-simplex, where the limit set is a finite set. If the source point is in the interior of a facet, its limit set is also in the facet.
  The farthest point mapping is closely related to the star unfolding and source unfolding. We give a loose definition of star unfolding of the surface of a 4-dimensional polytope.
  We also study the intrinsic radius and diameter of the 4-cube. It is expected that the intrinsic radius/diameter ratio of an n-cube is monotonically decreasing in dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16862v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshikazu Yamagishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization for random operators on $\mathbb{Z}^d$ with the long-range hopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate random operators on $\mathbb{Z}^d$ with H\"older continuously distributed potentials and the long-range hopping. The hopping amplitude decays with the inter-particle distance $\|\bm x\|$ as $e^{-\log^{\rho}(\|\bm x\|+1)}$ with $\rho&gt;1,\bm x\in\Z^d$. By employing the multi-scale analysis (MSA) technique, we prove that for large disorder, the random operators have pure point spectrum with localized eigenfunctions whose decay rate is the same as the hopping term. This gives a partial answer to a conjecture of Yeung and Oono [{\it Europhys. Lett.} 4(9), (1987): 1061-1065].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17262v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunfeng Shi, Li Wen, Dongfeng Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lipschitz Continuity Results for Minimax Solutions of Path-Dependent Hamilton--Jacobi Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17388v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a Cauchy problem for a (first-order) path-dependent Hamilton--Jacobi equation with coinvariant derivatives and a right-end boundary condition. Such problems arise naturally in the study of properties of the value functional in (deterministic) optimal control problems and differential games for time-delay systems. We prove that, under certain assumptions on the Hamiltonian and the boundary functional, a minimax (generalized) solution of the Cauchy problem satisfies Lipschitz conditions both in time and functional variables. In the latter case, Lipschitz conditions are formulated with respect to the uniform norm and some special norm of the space of continuous functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17388v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail I. Gomoyunov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous carrying capacities and global extinction in metapopulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17461v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we consider a simple two patch reaction diffusion model with strong Allee effect, sufficiently distinct carrying capacities, similar reaction strengths, and strong diffusion. In the homogeneous case, i.e., in in the case of equal or similar capacities and reaction strengths, it is well known that the number of stationary solutions ranges from three (strong diffusion) to nine (weak diffusion). We provide sufficient conditions which includes the diffusion strength and reaction parameters that ensure that the extinction point is the unique and globally asymptotically stable equilibrium in the case of heterogeneous capacities. For the sake of robustness we consider several bistable reaction functions, compare our analytical result with numerical simulations, and conclude the paper with a short discussion on global extinction literature (which has provided mostly numerical results so far), as well as other related phenomena, e.g., fragmentation, the perfect mixing paradox, and the natural form the reaction diffusion patch models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17461v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Hesoun, Petr Stehl\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A reaction network approach to modeling carbon dioxide removal systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17568v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper focuses on what we call Reaction Network Cardon Dioxide Removal (RNDCR) framework to analyze several proposed negative emissions technologies (NETs) so as to determine when present-day Earth carbon cycle system would exhibit multistationarity (steady-state multiplicity) or possibly monostationarity, that will in effect lower the rising earth temperature. Using mathematical modeling based on the techniques of chemical reaction network theory (CRNT), we propose an RNDCR system consisting of the Anderies subnetwork, fossil fuel emission reaction, the carbon capture subnetwork and the carbon storage subnetwork. The RNCDR framework analysis was done in the cases of two NETs: Bioenergy with Carbon Capture and Storage and Afforestation/Reforestation. It was found out that these two methods of carbon dioxide removal are almost similar with respect to their network properties and their capacities to exhibit multistationarity and absolute concentration robustness in certain species.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17568v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noel Fortun, Piolo Gaspar, Editha Jose, Angelyn Lao, Eduardo Mendoza, Luis Razon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The generic geometry of steady state varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17798v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We answer several fundamental geometric questions about reaction networks with power-law kinetics, on topics such as generic finiteness of steady states, robustness, and nondegenerate multistationarity. In particular, we give an ideal-theoretic characterization of generic absolute concentration robustness, as well as conditions under which a network that admits multiple steady states also has the capacity for nondegenerate multistationarity. The key tools underlying our results come from the theory of vertically parametrized systems, and include a linear algebra condition that characterizes when the steady state system has positive nondegenerate zeros.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17798v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisenda Feliu, Oskar Henriksson, Beatriz Pascual-Escudero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Plaque Expansivity Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1311.6890</link>
      <description>arXiv:1311.6890v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is one of the main properties of uniformly hyperbolic dynamics that points of two distinct trajectories cannot be uniformly close one to another. This characteristics of hyperbolic dynamics is called expansivity. Hirsch, Pugh and Shub, 1977, formulated the so-called Plaque Expansivity Conjecture, assuming that two invariant sequences of leaves of central manifolds, corresponding to a partially hyperbolic diffeomorphism, cannot be locally close. There are many important statements in the theory of partial hyperbolicity that can be proved provided Plaque Expansivity Conjecture holds true. Here we are proving this conjecture in its general form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1311.6890v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Kryzhevich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Mixing Via Additive Combinatorics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.00527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.00527v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the geodesic flow on a geometrically finite locally symmetric space of negative curvature is exponentially mixing with respect to the Bowen-Margulis-Sullivan measure. The approach is based on constructing a suitable anisotropic Banach space on which the infinitesimal generator of the flow admits an essential spectral gap. A key step in the proof involves estimating certain oscillatory integrals against the Patterson-Sullivan measure. For this purpose, we prove a general result of independent interest asserting that the Fourier transform of measures on $\mathbb{R}^d$ that do not concentrate near proper affine hyperplanes enjoy polynomial decay outside of a sparse set of frequencies. As an intermediate step, we show that the $L^q$-dimension ($1&lt;q\leq \infty$) of iterated self-convolutions of such measures tend towards that of the ambient space. Our analysis also yields that the Laplace transform of the correlation function of smooth observables extends meromorphically to the entire complex plane in the convex cocompact case and to a strip of explicit size beyond the imaginary axis in the case the manifold admits cusps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.00527v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osama Khalil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An embedding theorem for multidimensional subshifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05650v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Krieger's embedding theorem provides necessary and sufficient conditions for an arbitrary subshift to embed in a given topologically mixing $\mathbb{Z}$-subshift of finite type. For some $\mathbb{Z}^d$-subshifts of finite type, Lightwood characterized the \emph{aperiodic} subsystems. In the current paper we prove a new embedding theorem for a class of subshifts of finite type over any countable abelian group. Our main theorem provides necessary and sufficient conditions for an arbitrary subshift $X$ to embed inside a given subshift of finite type $Y$ that satisfies a certain condition. For the particular case of $\mathbb{Z}$-subshifts, our new theorem coincides with Krieger's theorem. In particular, our result gives the first complete characterization of the subsystems of the multidimensional full shift $Y= A^{\mathbb{Z}^d}$. The natural condition on the target subshift $Y$, introduced explicitly for the first time in the current paper, is called the map extension property. It was introduced implicitly by Mike Boyle in the early 1980's for $\mathbb{Z}$-subshifts, and is closely related to the notion of an absolute retract, introduced by Borsuk in the 1930's. A $\mathbb{Z}$-subshift has the map extension property if and only if it is a topologically mixing subshift of finite type. Over abelian groups, a subshift has the map extension property if and only if it is a contractible SFT as shown in work of Poirier and Salo. We also establish a new theorem regarding lower entropy factors of multidimensional subshifts, that extends Boyle's lower entropy factor theorem from the one-dimensional case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05650v5</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Meyerovitch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equidistribution of graphs of holomorphic correspondences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13838v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a compact Riemann surface. Let $f$ be a holomorphic self-correspondence of $X$ with dynamical degrees $d_1$ and $d_2$. Assume that $d_1\neq d_2$ or $f$ is non-weakly modular. We show that the graphs of the iterates $f^n$ of $f$ are equidistributed exponentially fast with respect to a positive closed current in $X\times X$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13838v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhan Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed spectral approximation of Koopman operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05663v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Koopman operators and transfer operators represent nonlinear dynamics in state space through its induced action on linear spaces of observables and measures, respectively. This framework enables the use of linear operator theory for supervised and unsupervised learning of nonlinear dynamical systems, and has received considerable interest in recent years. Here, we propose a data-driven technique for spectral approximation of Koopman operators of continuous-time, measure-preserving ergodic systems that is asymptotically consistent and makes direct use of known equations of motion (physics). Our approach is based on a bounded transformation of the Koopman generator (an operator implementing directional derivatives of observables along the dynamical flow), followed by smoothing by a Markov semigroup of kernel integral operators. This results in a skew-adjoint, compact operator whose eigendecomposition is expressible as a variational generalized eigenvalue problem. We develop Galerkin methods to solve this eigenvalue problem and study their asymptotic consistency in the large-data limit. A key aspect of these methods is that they are physics-informed, in the sense of making direct use of dynamical vector field information through automatic differentiation of kernel functions. Solutions of the eigenvalue problem reconstruct evolution operators that preserve unitarity of the underlying Koopman group while spectrally converging to it in a suitable limit. In addition, the computed eigenfunctions have representatives in a reproducing kernel Hilbert space, enabling out-of-sample evaluation of learned dynamical features. Numerical experiments performed with this method on integrable and chaotic low-dimensional systems demonstrate its efficacy in extracting dynamically coherent observables under complex dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05663v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claire Valva, Dimitrios Giannakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting random bifurcations via rigorous enclosures of large deviations rate functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12556v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main goal of this work is to provide a description of transitions from uniform to non-uniform snychronization in diffusions based on large deviation estimates for finite time Lyapunov exponents. These can be characterized in terms of moment Lyapunov exponents which are principal eigenvalues of the generator of the tilted (Feynman-Kac) semigroup. Using a computer assisted proof, we demonstrate how to determine these eigenvalues and investigate the rate function which is the Legendre-Fenichel transform of the moment Lyapunov function. We apply our results to two case studies: the pitchfork bifurcation and a two-dimensional toy model, also considering the transition to a positive asymptotic Lyapunov exponent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12556v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandra Blessing, Alex Blumenthal, Maxime Breden, Maximilian Engel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar polynomial vector fields in real and complex time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05043v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present paper, the simplest scalar ODE case is studied for polynomials $$ \dot{w}=f(w)=(w-e_0)\cdot\ldots\cdot(w-e_{d-1}) $$ of degree $d$ with $d$ simple complex zeros. The explicit solution by separation of variables and explicit integration is an almost trivial matter.
  In a classical spirit, indeed, we describe the complex Riemann surface $\mathcal{R}$ of the global nontrivial solution $(t,w(t))$ in complex time, as an unbranched cover of the punctured Riemann sphere. The flow property, however, fails at $w=\infty$. The global consequences depend on the period map of the residues $2\pi\mathrm{i}/f'(e_j)$ of $1/f$ at the punctures, in detail. We therefore show that polynomials $f$ exist for arbitrarily prescribed residues with zero sum. This result is not covered by standard interpolation theory.
  Motivated by the PDE case, we also classify the planar real-time phase portraits of the above ODE.
  Poincar\'e compactification of $w$ regularizes $w=\infty$ by $2(d-1)$ equilibria, alternatingly stable and unstable within the invariant circle boundary at infinity. In structurally stable cases, we classify all compactified phase portraits, up to orientation preserving orbit equivalence and time reversal. Combinatorially, their connection graphs are equivalent to certain unrooted, unlabeled, undirected planar trees of $d$ vertices or, dually, to certain chord diagrams with $d-1$ nonintersecting chords. We sketch a proof that all planar trees are actually realized by Poincar\'e compactifications.
  Not least, we offer a 1,000 Euro reward for the discovery, or refutation, of complex entire homoclinic orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05043v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernold Fiedler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Avatars of Margulis invariants and proper actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.03777</link>
      <description>arXiv:1812.03777v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we provide a necessary and sufficient criterion for proper actions on $\mathbb{H}^{n,n-1}$ in terms of certain special Anosov representations in $\mathsf{SO}(n,n)$. Moreover, we show that affine Anosov representations of any word hyperbolic group in $\mathsf{SO}(n,n-1)\ltimes\mathbb{R}^{2n-1}$ are infinitesimal versions of such special Anosov representations. Finally, using the above two results we interpret Margulis spacetimes as infinitesimal versions of quotient manifolds of $\mathbb{H}^{n,n-1}$.
  In the appendix, we give a description of the appropriate cross-ratios in our setting and their infinitesimal versions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1812.03777v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Periodic points of rational functions over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.13281v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For $q$ a prime power and $\phi$ a rational function with coefficients in $\mathbb{F}_q$, let $p(q,\phi)$ be the proportion of $\mathbb{P}^1(\mathbb{F}_q)$ that is periodic with respect to $\phi$. And if $d$ is a positive integer, let $Q_d$ be the set of prime powers coprime to $d!$ and let $\mathcal{P}(d,q)$ be the expected value of $p(q,\phi)$ as $\phi$ ranges over rational functions with coefficients in $\mathbb{F}_q$ of degree $d$. We prove that if $d$ is a positive integer no less than $2$, then $\mathcal{P}(d,q)$ tends to 0 as $q$ increases in $Q_d$. This theorem generalizes our previous work, which held only for quadratic polynomials, and only in fixed characteristic. To deduce this result, we prove a uniformity theorem on specializations of dynamical systems of rational functions with coefficients in certain finitely-generated algebras over residually finite Dedekind domains. This specialization theorem generalizes our previous work, which held only for algebras of dimension one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.13281v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Derek Garton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bender--Knuth Billiards in Coxeter Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17360v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $(W,S)$ be a Coxeter system, and write $S=\{s_i:i\in I\}$, where $I$ is a finite index set. Fix a nonempty convex subset $\mathscr{L}$ of $W$. If $W$ is of type $A$, then $\mathscr{L}$ is the set of linear extensions of a poset, and there are important Bender--Knuth involutions $\mathrm{BK}_i\colon\mathscr{L}\to\mathscr{L}$ indexed by elements of $I$. For arbitrary $W$ and for each $i\in I$, we introduce an operator $\tau_i\colon W\to W$ (depending on $\mathscr{L}$) that we call a noninvertible Bender--Knuth toggle; this operator restricts to an involution on $\mathscr{L}$ that coincides with $\mathrm{BK}_i$ in type $A$. Given a Coxeter element $c=s_{i_n}\cdots s_{i_1}$, we consider the operator $\mathrm{Pro}_c=\tau_{i_n}\cdots\tau_{i_1}$. We say $W$ is futuristic if for every nonempty finite convex set $\mathscr{L}$, every Coxeter element $c$, and every $u\in W$, there exists an integer $K\geq 0$ such that $\mathrm{Pro}_c^K(u)\in\mathscr{L}$. We prove that finite Coxeter groups, right-angled Coxeter groups, rank-3 Coxeter groups, affine Coxeter groups of types $\widetilde A$ and $\widetilde C$, and Coxeter groups whose Coxeter graphs are complete are all futuristic. When $W$ is finite, we actually prove that if $s_{i_N}\cdots s_{i_1}$ is a reduced expression for the long element of $W$, then $\tau_{i_N}\cdots\tau_{i_1}(W)=\mathscr{L}$; this allows us to determine the smallest integer $\mathrm{M}(c)$ such that $\mathrm{Pro}_c^{{\mathrm{M}}(c)}(W)=\mathscr{L}$ for all $\mathscr{L}$. We also exhibit infinitely many non-futuristic Coxeter groups, including all irreducible affine Coxeter groups that are not of type $\widetilde A$, $\widetilde C$, or $\widetilde G_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17360v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grant Barkley, Colin Defant, Eliot Hodges, Noah Kravitz, Mitchell Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Webs Generated by Products of convex and homogeneous Foliations on $\mathbb{P}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09602v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates flat webs on the projective plane. We present two methods for constructing such webs: the first involves taking the product of finitely many convex reduced foliations and invariant lines, while the second consists of taking the product of finitely many convex homogeneous foliations and invariant lines. In both cases, we demonstrate that the dual web is flat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09602v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carla Pracias, Maycol Falla Luza</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
