<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On dense orbits in the space of subequivalence relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We first explain how to endow the space of subequivalence relations of any non-singular countable equivalence relation with a Polish topology, extending the framework of Kechris' recent monograph on subequivalence relations of probability measure-preserving (p.m.p.) countable equivalence relations. We then restrict to p.m.p. equivalence relations and discuss dense orbits therein for the natural action of the full group and of the automorphism group of the relation. Our main result is a characterization of the subequivalence relations having a dense orbit in the space of subequivalence relations of the ergodic hyperfinite p.m.p. equivalence relation. We also show that in this setup, all full groups orbits are meager. We finally provide a few Borel complexity calculations of natural subsets in spaces of subequivalence relations using a natural metric we call the uniform metric. This answers some questions from an earlier version of Kechris' monograph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01806v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fran\c{c}ois Le Ma\^itre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full-dimensional KAM torus with frequency-preserving in infinite-dimensional Hamiltonian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present two infinite-dimensional KAM theorems with frequency-preserving for a nonresonant frequency of Diophantine type or even weaker. To be more precise, under a nondegenerate condition for an infinite-dimensional Hamiltonian system, we prove the persistence of a full-dimensional KAM torus with the specified frequency independent of any spectral asymptotics, by advantage of the generating function method. This appears to be the first Kolmogorov type result in the infinite-dimensional context. As a direct application, we provide a positive answer to Bourgain's conjecture: full-dimensional invariant tori for 1D nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equations do exist.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01864v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhicheng Tong, Yong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long time behavior of a degenerate stochastic system modeling the response of a population face to environmental impacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01898v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the asymptotics of a two-dimensional stochastic differential system with a degenerate diffusion matrix. This system describes the dynamics of a population where individuals contribute to the degradation of their environment through two different behaviors. We exploit the almost one-dimensional form of the dynamical system to compute explicitly the Freidlin-Wentzell action functional. That allows to give conditions under which the small noise regime of the invariant measureis concentrated around the equilibrium of the dynamical system having the smallest diffusion coefficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01898v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Collet (CPHT), Claire Ecoti\`ere (CMAP,MERGE), Sylvie M\'el\'eard (CMAP,MERGE)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The bifurcation measure is exponentially mixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01939v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove general mixing theorems for sequences of meromorphic maps on compact K\"ahler manifolds. We deduce that the bifurcation measure is exponentially mixing for a family of rational maps of $\mathbb{P}^q(\mathbb{C})$ endowed with suitably many marked points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01939v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry de Thelin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking and forecasting oscillatory data streams using Koopman autoencoders and Kalman filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data-driven modelling techniques provide a method for deriving models of dynamical systems directly from complicated data streams. However, tracking and forecasting such data streams poses a significant challenge to most methods, as they assume the underlying process and model does not change over time. In this paper, we apply one such data-driven method, the Koopman autoencoder (KAE), to high-dimensional oscillatory data to generate a low-dimensional latent space and model, where the system's dynamics appear linear. This allows one to accurately track and forecast systems where the underlying model may change over time. States and the model in the reduced order latent space can then be efficiently updated as new data becomes available, using data assimilation techniques such as the ensemble Kalman filter (EnKF), in a technique we call the KAE EnKF. We demonstrate that this approach is able to effectively track and forecast time-varying, nonlinear dynamical systems in synthetic examples. We then apply the KAE EnKF to a video of a physical pendulum, and achieve a significant improvement over current state-of-the-art methods. By generating effective latent space reconstructions, we find that we are able to construct accurate short-term forecasts and efficient adaptations to externally forced changes to the pendulum's frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02166v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen A Falconer, David J. B. Lloyd, Naratip Santitissadeekorn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a question of Kwakkel and Markovic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02176v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A question of F. Kwakkel and V. Markovic on existence of C^1-diffeomorphisms of closed surfaces that permute a dense collection of domains with bounded geometry is answered in the negative. In fact, it is proved that for closed surfaces of genus at least one such diffeomorphisms do not exist regardless of whether they have positive or zero topological entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02176v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Merenkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-monodromy and the Mandelbrot set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the discontinuity of codings for the Julia set of a quadratic map. To each parameter ray, we associate a natural coding for Julia sets on the ray. Given a hyperbolic component $H$ of the Mandelbrot set, we consider the codings along the two parameter rays landing on the root point of $H$. Our main result describes the discontinuity of these two coding in terms of the kneading sequences of the hyperbolic components which are conspicuous to $H$. This result can be interpreted as a solution to the degenerated case of Lipa's conjecture on the monodromy problem of the horseshoe locus for the complex H\'enon family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02204v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutaka Ishii, Thomas Richards</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital perturbation coupling of primary oblateness and solar radiation pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01669v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solar radiation pressure can have a substantial long-term effect on the orbits of high area-to-mass ratio spacecraft, such as solar sails. We present a study of the coupling between radiation pressure and the gravitational perturbation due to polar flattening. Removing the short-period terms via perturbation theory yields a time-dependent two-degree-of-freedom Hamiltonian, depending on one physical and one dynamical parameter. While the reduced model is non-integrable in general, assuming coplanar orbits (i.e., both Spacecraft and Sun on the equator) results in an integrable invariant manifold. We discuss the qualitative features of the coplanar dynamics, and find three regions of the parameters space characterized by different regimes of the reduced flow. For each regime, we identify the fixed points and their character. The fixed points represent frozen orbits, configurations for which the long-term perturbations cancel out to the order of the theory. They are advantageous from the point of view of station keeping, allowing the orbit to be maintained with minimal propellant consumption. We complement existing studies of the coplanar dynamics with a more rigorous treatment, deriving the generating function of the canonical transformation that underpins the use of averaged equations. Furthermore, we obtain an analytical expression for the bifurcation lines that separate the regions with different qualitative flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01669v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Lara, Elena Fantino, Roberto Flores</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of the attractor for nonautonomous reaction-diffusion equations with discontinuous nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01894v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the asymptotic behavior of the solutions of a nonautonomous differential inclusion modeling a reaction-diffusion equation with a discontinuous nonlinearity. We obtain first several properties concerning the uniqueness and regularity of non-negative solutions. Then we study the structure of the pullback attractor in the positive cone, showing that it consists of the zero solution, the unique positive nonautonomous equilibrium and the heteroclinic connections between them, which can be expressed in terms of the solutions of an associated linear problem. Finally, we analyze the relationship of the pullback attractor with the uniform, the cocycle and the skew product semiflow attractors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01894v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jde.2020.11.036</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Differential Equations, 2021, V.275, 270-308</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Valero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Context Flows for Learning Generalizable Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02154v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neural Ordinary Differential Equations typically struggle to generalize to new dynamical behaviors created by parameter changes in the underlying system, even when the dynamics are close to previously seen behaviors. The issue gets worse when the changing parameters are unobserved, i.e., their value or influence is not directly measurable when collecting data. We introduce Neural Context Flow (NCF), a framework that encodes said unobserved parameters in a latent context vector as input to a vector field. NCFs leverage differentiability of the vector field with respect to the parameters, along with first-order Taylor expansion to allow any context vector to influence trajectories from other parameters. We validate our method and compare it to established Multi-Task and Meta-Learning alternatives, showing competitive performance in mean squared error for in-domain and out-of-distribution evaluation on the Lotka-Volterra, Glycolytic Oscillator, and Gray-Scott problems. This study holds practical implications for foundational models in science and related areas that benefit from conditional neural ODEs. Our code is openly available at https://github.com/ddrous/ncflow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02154v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roussel Desmond Nzoyem, David A. W. Barton, Tom Deakin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Lyapunov-based feedback stabilization of bipedal locomotion based on reference spreading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02184v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a hybrid formulation of the linear inverted pendulum model for bipedal locomotion, where the foot switches are triggered based on the center of mass position, removing the need for pre-defined footstep timings. Using a concept similar to reference spreading, we define nontrivial tracking error coordinates induced by our hybrid model. These coordinates enjoy desirable linear flow dynamics and rather elegant jump dynamics perturbed by a suitable extended class ${\mathcal K}_\infty$ function of the position error. We stabilize this hybrid error dynamics using a saturated feedback controller, selecting its gains by solving a convex optimization problem. We prove local asymptotic stability of the tracking error and provide a certified estimate of the basin of attraction, comparing it with a numerical estimate obtained from the integration of the closed-loop dynamics. Simulations on a full-body model of a real robot show the practical applicability of the proposed framework and its advantages with respect to a standard model predictive control formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02184v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Bertollo, Gianni Lunardi, Andrea Del Prete, Luca Zaccarian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moment matching based reduced closed-loop design to achieve asymptotic performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02253v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, the moment matching techniques are adopted to obtain reduced-order closed-loop systems with reduced-order controllers that maintain the closed-loop stability and guarantee desired asymptotic performance, after revealing the relationship between the Internal Model Principle used in control design and the time-domain moment matching problem. As a result, the design of a low order controller can be done starting from considering the achieving of asymptotic performance as a moment matching problem, resulting in a reduced order closed-loop system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02253v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tudor C. Ionescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$Out(F_n)$-invariant probability measures on the space of $n$-generated marked groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.03659v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal G_n$ denote the space of $n$-generated marked groups. We prove that, for every $n\ge 2$, there exist $2^{\aleph_0}$ non-atomic, $Out(F_n)$-invariant, mixing probability measures on $\mathcal G_n$. On the other hand, there are non-empty closed subsets of $\mathcal G_n$ that admit no $Out(F_n)$-invariant probability measure. Acylindrical hyperbolicity of the group $Aut(F_n)$ plays a crucial role in the proof of both results. We also discuss model theoretic implications of the existence of $Out(F_n)$-invariant, ergodic probability measures on $\mathcal G_n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.03659v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Osin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded-Confidence Models of Opinion Dynamics with Adaptive Confidence Bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.07563v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: People's opinions change with time as they interact with each other. In a bounded-confidence model (BCM) of opinion dynamics, individuals (which are represented by the nodes of a network) have continuous-valued opinions and are influenced by neighboring nodes whose opinions are sufficiently similar to theirs (i.e., are within a confidence bound). In this paper, we formulate and analyze discrete-time BCMs with heterogeneous and adaptive confidence bounds. We introduce two new models: (1) a BCM with synchronous opinion updates that generalizes the Hegselmann--Krause (HK) model and (2) a BCM with asynchronous opinion updates that generalizes the Deffuant--Weisbuch (DW) model. We analytically and numerically explore our adaptive BCMs' limiting behaviors, including the confidence-bound dynamics, the formation of clusters of nodes with similar opinions, and the time evolution of an "effective graph", which is a time-dependent subgraph of a network with edges between nodes that {are currently receptive to each other.} For a variety of networks and a wide range of values of the parameters that control the increase and decrease of confidence bounds, we demonstrate numerically that our adaptive BCMs result in fewer major opinion clusters and longer convergence times than the baseline (i.e., nonadaptive) BCMs. We also show that our adaptive BCMs can have adjacent nodes that converge to the same opinion but are not {receptive to each other.} This qualitative behavior does not occur in the associated baseline BCMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.07563v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grace J. Li, Jiajie Luo, Mason A. Porter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nature of the Volcano Transition in the Fully Disordered Kuramoto Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.09079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.09079v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Randomly coupled phase oscillators may synchronize into disordered patterns of collective motion. We analyze this transition in a large, fully connected Kuramoto model with symmetric but otherwise independent random interactions. Using the dynamical cavity method we reduce the dynamics to a stochastic single-oscillator problem with self-consistent correlation and response functions that we study analytically and numerically. We clarify the nature of the volcano transition and elucidate its relation to the existence of an oscillator glass phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.09079v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.187201</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 187201, Published 30 April 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Axel Pr\"user, Sebastian Rosmej, Andreas Engel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does $\mathcal P(\omega) / \mathrm{fin}$ know its right hand from its left?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04358v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\sigma$ denote the shift automorphism on $\mathcal{P}(\omega) / \mathrm{fin}$, defined by setting $\sigma([A]) = [A+1]$ for all $A \subseteq \omega$. We show that the Continuum Hypothesis implies the shift automorphism $\sigma$ and its inverse $\sigma^{-1}$ are conjugate in the automorphism group of $\mathcal{P}(\omega) / \mathrm{fin}$.
  Due to work of van Douwen and Shelah, it has been known since the 1980's that it is consistent with $\mathsf{ZFC}$ that $\sigma$ and $\sigma^{-1}$ are not conjugate. Our result shows that the question of whether $\sigma$ and $\sigma^{-1}$ are conjugate is independent of $\mathsf{ZFC}$.
  As a corollary to the main theorem, we deduce that the structures $\langle \mathcal{P}(\omega) / \mathrm{fin},\sigma \rangle$ and $\langle \mathcal{P}(\omega) / \mathrm{fin},\sigma^{-1} \rangle$ are elementarily equivalent in the language of algebraic dynamical systems (Boolean algebras together with an automorphism). This corollary does not depend on the Continuum Hypothesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04358v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Brian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Growth in products of matrices: fastest, average, and generic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00610v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The problems that we consider in this paper are as follows. Let A and B be 2x2 matrices (over reals). Let w(A, B) be a word of length n. After evaluating w(A, B) as a product of matrices, we get a 2x2 matrix, call it W. What is the largest (by the absolute value) possible entry of W, over all w(A, B) of length n, as a function of n? What is the expected absolute value of the largest (by the absolute value) entry in a random product of n matrices, where each matrix is A or B with probability 0.5? What is the Lyapunov exponent for a random matrix product like that? We give partial answer to the first of these questions and an essentially complete answer to the second question. For the third question (the most difficult of the three), we offer a very simple method to produce an upper bound on the Lyapunov exponent in the case where all entries of the matrices A and B are nonnegative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00610v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Shpilrain</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
