<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 04:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Pseudo-Anosov Maps and Hubbard Trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14996v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this project, we develop a new connection between the dynamics of quadratic polynomials on the complex plane and the dynamics of homeomorphisms of surfaces. In particular, given a quadratic polynomial, we investigate whether one can construct an extension of it which is a generalized pseudo-Anosov homeomorphism. Generalized pseudo-Anosov means it preserves a pair of foliations with infinitely many singularities that accumulate on finitely many points. We determine for which quadratic polynomials such an extension exists. The construction is related to the dynamics on the Hubbard tree, which is a forward invariant subset of the filled Julia set containing the critical orbit. We define a type of Hubbard trees, which we call crossing-free, and show that these are precisely the Hubbard trees for which one can construct a generalized pseudo-Anosov map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14996v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariam Al-Hawaj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A finiteness result for common zeros of iterates of rational maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Answering a question asked by Hsia and Tucker in their paper on the finiteness of greatest common divisors of iterates of polynomials, we prove that if $f, g \in \mathbb{C}(X)$ are compositionally independent rational functions and $c \in \mathbb{C}(X)$, then there are at most finitely many $\lambda\in\mathbb{C}$ with the property that there is an $n$ such that $f^n(\lambda) = g^n(\lambda) = c(\lambda)$, except for a few families of $f, g \in Aut(\mathbb{P}^1_\mathbb{C})$ which gives counterexamples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15104v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chatchai Noytaptim, Xiao Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Packing topological pressure for amenable group actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15212v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we first prove the variational principle for amenable packing topological pressure. Then we obtain an inequality concerning amenable packing pressure for factor maps. Finally, we show that the equality about packing topological pressure of the set of generic points when the system satisfies the almost specification property, or $\mu$ is ergodic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15212v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqing Ding, Ercai Chen, Xiaoyao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonance in isochronous systems with decaying oscillatory perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-autonomous perturbations of isochronous systems in the plane are considered. It is assumed that the intensity of perturbations decays with time, and the frequency is asymptotically constant with the limiting value satisfying a resonance condition. We discuss the emergence of attracting resonant solutions with an asymptotically constant amplitude. By combining the averaging technique and the Lyapunov function method, we show that this behaviour can occur in the phase locking and phase drifting regimes. The conditions that guarantee the existence and stability of such resonant dynamics are described.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15238v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oskar A. Sultanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability Analysis of Biochemical Reaction Networks Linearly Conjugated to complex balanced Systems with Time Delays Added</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linear conjugacy offers a new perspective to broaden the scope of stable biochemical reaction networks to the systems linearly conjugated to the well-established complex balanced mass action systems ($\ell$cCBMASs). This paper addresses the challenge posed by time delay, which can disrupt the linear conjugacy relationship and complicate stability analysis for delayed versions of $\ell$cCBMASs (D$\ell$cCBMAS). Firstly, we develop Lyapunov functionals tailored to some D$\ell$cCBMASs by using the persisted parameter relationships under time delays. Subsequently, we redivide the phase space as several invariant sets of trajectories and further investigate the existence and uniqueness of equilibriums in each newly defined invariant set. This enables us to determine the local asymptotic stability of some D$\ell$cCBMASs within an updated framework. Furthermore, illustrative examples are provided to demonstrate the practical implications of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15472v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyu Zhang, Shibo He, Chuanhou Gao, Denis Dochain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability Analysis of a Diffusive SVIR Epidemic Model with Distributed Delay, Imperfect Vaccine and General Incidence Rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this chapter, we consider a reaction-diffusion SVIR infection model with dis-tributed delay and nonlinear incidence rate. The wellposedness of the proposed model is proved. By means of Lyapunov functionals, we show that the disease-free equilibrium state is globally asymptotically stable when the basic reproduction number is less or equal than one, and that the disease endemic equilibrium is globally asymptotically stable when the basic reproduction number is greater than one. Numerical simulations are provided to illustrate the obtained theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15478v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achraf Zinihi, Mostafa Tahiri, Moulay Rchid Sidi Ammi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Analysis of a Cocaine-Heroin Epidemiological Model with Spatial Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article conducts an in-depth investigation of a new spatio-temporal model for the cocaine-heroin epidemiological model with vital dynamics, incorporating the Laplacian operator. The study rigorously establishes the existence, uniqueness, non-negativity, and boundedness of solutions for the proposed model. In addition, the local stability of both a drug-free equilibrium and a drug-addiction equilibrium are analyzed by studying the corresponding characteristic equations. The research provides conclusive evidence that when the basic reproductive number $\mathcal{R}_0$ exceeds 1, the drug-addiction equilibrium is globally asymptotically stable. Conversely, using comparative arguments, it is shown that if $\mathcal{R}_0$ is less than 1, the drug-free equilibrium is globally asymptotically stable. Furthermore, the article includes a series of numerical simulations to visually convey and support the analytical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15532v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achraf Zinihi, Moulay Rchid Sidi Ammi, Matthias Ehrhardt, Ahmed Bachir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formulating human risk response in epidemic models: exogenous vs endogenous approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15535v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent pandemic emphasized the need to consider the role of human behavior in shaping epidemic dynamics. In particular, it is necessary to extend beyond the classical epidemiological structures to fully capture the interplay between the spread of disease and how people respond. Here, we focus on the challenge of incorporating change in human behavior in the form of "risk response" into compartmental epidemiological models, where humans adapt their actions in response to their perceived risk of becoming infected. The review examines over 40 compartmental models, categorizing them into two fundamentally distinct classes: exogenous and endogenous approaches to modeling risk response. While in exogenous approaches, human behavior is often included using different fixed parameter values for certain time periods, endogenous approaches seek for a mechanism internal to the model to explain changes in human behavior as a function of the state of disease. We further discuss two different formulations within endogenous models as implicit versus explicit representation of information diffusion. This comprehensive analysis provides modelers with guidance in selecting an appropriate framework for epidemic modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15535v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leah LeJeune, Navid Ghaffarzadegan, Lauren Childs, Omar Saucedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Far-from-equilibrium travelling pulses in sloped semi-arid environments driven by autotoxicity effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, an extension of the 1D Klausmeier model that accounts for the toxicity compounds is considered and the occurrence of travelling stripes is investigated. Numerical simulations are firstly conducted to capture the qualitative behaviours of the pulse-type solutions and, then, geometric singular perturbation theory is used to prove the existence of such travelling pulses by constructing the corresponding homoclinic orbits in the associated 4-dimensional system. A scaling analysis on the investigated model is performed to identify the asymptotic scaling regime in which travelling pulses can be constructed. Biological observations are extracted from the analytical results and the role of autotoxicity in travelling patterns is emphasized. Finally, the analytically constructed solutions are compared with the numerical ones, leading to a good agreement that confirms the validity of the conducted analysis. Numerical investigations are also carried out in order to gain additional information on vegetation dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15602v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Grif\`o, Annalisa Iuorio, Frits Veerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grand orbit relations in wandering domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the fundamental distinctions in McMullen and Sullivan's description of the Teichm\"uller space of a complex dynamical system is between discrete and indiscrete grand orbit relations. We investigate these on the Fatou set of transcendental entire maps and provide criteria to distinguish between the two types. Furthermore, we show that discrete and indiscrete grand orbit relations may coexist non-trivially in a wandering domain, a phenomenon which does not occur for any other type of Fatou component. One of the tools used is a novel quasiconformal surgery technique of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15667v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasiliki Evdoridou, N\'uria Fagella, Lukas Geyer, Leticia Pardo-Sim\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reservoir Computing with Generalized Readout based on Generalized Synchronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14885v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reservoir computing is a machine learning framework that exploits nonlinear dynamics, exhibiting significant computational capabilities. One of the defining characteristics of reservoir computing is its low cost and straightforward training algorithm, i.e. only the readout, given by a linear combination of reservoir variables, is trained. Inspired by recent mathematical studies based on dynamical system theory, in particular generalized synchronization, we propose a novel reservoir computing framework with generalized readout, including a nonlinear combination of reservoir variables. The first crucial advantage of using the generalized readout is its mathematical basis for improving information processing capabilities. Secondly, it is still within a linear learning framework, which preserves the original strength of reservoir computing. In summary, the generalized readout is naturally derived from mathematical theory and allows the extraction of useful basis functions from reservoir dynamics without sacrificing simplicity. In a numerical study, we find that introducing the generalized readout leads to a significant improvement in accuracy and an unexpected enhancement in robustness for the short- and long-term prediction of Lorenz chaos, with a particular focus on how to harness low-dimensional reservoir dynamics. A novel way and its advantages for physical implementations of reservoir computing with generalized readout are briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14885v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akane Ookubo, Masanobu Inubushi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the dynamics of the Hepatitis B virus via a variable-order discrete system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14887v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the dynamics of the hepatitis B virus by integrating variable-order calculus and discrete analysis. Specifically, we utilize the Caputo variable-order difference operator in this study. To establish the existence and uniqueness results of the model, we employ a fixed-point technique. Furthermore, we prove that the model exhibits bounded and positive solutions. Additionally, we explore the local stability of the proposed model by determining the basic reproduction number. Finally, we present several numerical simulations to illustrate the richness of our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14887v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.chaos.2024.114987</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chaos Solitons Fractals 184 (2024), Art. 114987, 8pp</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Meriem Boukhobza, Amar Debbouche, Lingeshwaran Shangerganesh, Delfim F. M. Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical behavior of Predator-Prey with Allee Effect on Both Populations and Disease in Predator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the current study, we took into account a model of nonlinear ``predator-prey'' interactions including the ``Allee effect'' on both populations and disease in the predator population. The population as a whole is split into three: the prey population, susceptible predator, and diseased predator. The ``Takagi-Sugeno (T-S) impulsive control model'' and the Fuzzy impulsive control model have been used to test the stability of the three-dimensional ``Lotka-Volterra predator-prey system'' model. Following the model's formulation, the global-stability and the fuzzy solution are examined using numerical simulations and graphical displays, together with the necessary consultation, to help comprehend the effectiveness of our suggested model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15448v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khushbu Singh, K. Kaladhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taut foliations and contact pairs in dimension three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15635v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new construction of codimension-one foliations from pairs of contact structures in dimension three. This constitutes a converse result to a celebrated theorem of Eliashberg and Thurston on approximations of foliations by contact structures. Under suitable hypotheses on the initial contact pairs, the foliations we construct are taut, allowing us to characterize taut foliations entirely in terms of contact geometry. This viewpoint reveals some surprising flexible phenomena for taut foliations, and provides new insight into the $L$-space conjecture.
  The first part of the proof builds upon the work on Colin and Firmo on positive contact pairs. The second part involves a wide generalization of a technical result of Burago and Ivanov on the construction of branching foliations tangent to continuous plane fields, and might be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15635v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Massoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well Posed Origin Anywhere Consistent Systems in Celestial Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15639v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Certain measurements in celestial mechanics necessitate having the origin O of a Cartesian coordinate system (CCS) coincide with a point mass. For the two and three body problems we show mathematical inadequacies in Newton's celestial mechanics equations (NCME) when the origin of a coordinate system coincides with a point mass. A certain system of equations of relative differences implied by NCME is free of these inadequacies and is invariant with respect to any CCS translation. A new constant of motion is derived for the relative system. It shows that the universe of relative differences of the $N$-body problem is ``restless''.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15639v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry Gingold, Jocelyn Quaintance</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On physical measures of multi-singular hyperbolic vector fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03910v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bonatti and da Luz have introduced the class of \emph{multi-singular hyperbolic} vector fields to characterize systems whose periodic orbits and singularities do not bifurcate under perturbation (called star vector fields).
  In this paper, we study the Sina\"{\i}-Ruelle-Bowen measures for multi-singular hyperbolic vector fields: in a $C^1$ open and $C^1$ dense subset of multi-singular hyperbolic vector fields, each {$C^\infty$} one admits \emph{finitely} many physical measures whose basins cover a \emph{full} Lebesgue measure subset of the manifold. Similar results are also obtained for $C^1$ generic multi-singular hyperbolic vector fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03910v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sylvain Crovisier, Xiaodong Wang, Dawei Yang, Jinhua Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics and topology of the Hat family of tilings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.05639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.05639v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recently discovered Hat tiling admits a 4-dimensional family of shape deformations, including the 1-parameter family already known to yield alternate monotiles. The continuous hulls resulting from these tilings are all topologically conjugate dynamical systems, and hence have the same dynamics and topology. We construct and analyze a self-similar element of this family called the CAP tiling, and we use it to derive properties of the entire family. The CAP tiling has pure-point dynamical spectrum, which we compute explicitly, and comes from a natural cut-and-project scheme with 2-dimensional Euclidean internal space. All other members of the Hat family, in particular the original version constructed from 30-60-90 right triangles, are obtained via small modifications of the projection from this cut-and-project scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.05639v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Baake, Franz G\"ahler, Lorenzo Sadun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irrational rotations and 2-filling rays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00097v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a skew product transformation associated to an irrational rotation of the circle [0,1]/~. This skew product keeps track of the number of times an orbit of the rotation lands in the two complementary intervals of {0,1/2} in the circle. We show that under certain conditions on the continued fraction expansion of the irrational number defining the rotation, the skew product transformation has certain dense orbits. This is in spite of the presence of numerous non-dense orbits. We use this to construct laminations on infinite type surfaces with exotic properties. In particular, we show that for every infinite type surface with an isolated planar end, there is an infinite clique of 2-filling rays based at that end. These 2-filling rays are relevant to Bavard--Walker's loop graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00097v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lvzhou Chen, Alexander J. Rasmussen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic representation of the gradient of a killed diffusion semigroup: The half-space case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07096v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a probabilistic representation of the derivative of the semigroup associated to a multidimensional killed diffusion process defined on the half-space. The semigroup derivative is expressed as a functional of a process that is normally reflected when it hits the hyperplane. The representation of the derivative also involves a matrix-valued process which replaces the Jacobian of the underlying process that appears in the traditional pathwise derivative of a classical diffusion. The components of this matrix-valued process become zero except for those on the first row every time the reflected process touches the boundary. The results in this paper extend those in recent work of the authors, where the one-dimensional case was studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07096v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Crisan, Arturo Kohatsu-Higa</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
