<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 05:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fractal analysis of canard cycles and slow-fast Hopf points in piecewise smooth Li\'{e}nard equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The main goal of this paper is to give a complete fractal analysis of piecewise smooth (PWS) slow-fast Li\'{e}nard equations. For the analysis, we use the notion of Minkowski dimension of one-dimensional orbits generated by slow relation functions. More precisely, we find all possible values for the Minkowski dimension near PWS slow-fast Hopf points and near bounded balanced crossing canard cycles. We study fractal properties of the unbounded canard cycles using PWS classical Li\'{e}nard equations. We also show how the trivial Minkowski dimension implies the non-existence of limit cycles of crossing type close to Hopf points. This is not true for crossing limit cycles produced by bounded balanced canard cycles, i.e. we find a system undergoing a saddle-node bifurcation of crossing limit cycles and a system without limit cycles (in both cases, the Minkowski dimension is trivial). We also connect the Minkowski dimension with upper bounds for the number of limit cycles produced by bounded canard cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09713v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renato Huzak (Hasselt University), Ansfried Janssens (Hasselt University), Otavio Henrique Perez (Universidade de S\~ao Paulo), Goran Radunovi\'c (University of Zagreb)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Fiber Contraction Mapping Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a generalized non-stationary version of the fiber contraction mapping theorem. It was originally used in [HirschPugh70] to prove that the stable foliation of a $C^2$ Anosov diffeomorphism of a surface is $C^1$. Our generalized principle is used in [Luna24], where an analogous regularity result for stable foliations of non-stationary systems is proved. The result is stated in a general setting so that it may be used in future dynamical results in the random and non-stationary settings, especially for graph transform arguments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09767v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandro Luna, Weiran Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two Results for the Omega Limit Sets of Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper provides two results for the omega limit sets of a dynamical system. We show that omega limit sets can be estimated by using functions that satisfy different (and in many cases less demanding) assumptions than the usual assumptions in Lyapunov theorems and LaSalle's theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10014v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iasson Karafyllis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonstandard analysis of asymptotic points of expansive systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we apply techniques from nonstandard analysis to study expansive dynamical systems. Among other results, we provide a necessary and sufficient condition for an expansive homeomorphism on a compact metric space to admit doubly-asymptotic points in terms of the decay of expansivity constants of the powers of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10201v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alfonso Artigue, Luis Ferrari, Jorge Groisman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical sparse regression on quadratic manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09746v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Approximating field variables and data vectors from sparse samples is a key challenge in computational science. Widely used methods such as gappy proper orthogonal decomposition and empirical interpolation rely on linear approximation spaces, limiting their effectiveness for data representing transport-dominated and wave-like dynamics. To address this limitation, we introduce quadratic manifold sparse regression, which trains quadratic manifolds with a sparse greedy method and computes approximations on the manifold through novel nonlinear projections of sparse samples. The nonlinear approximations obtained with quadratic manifold sparse regression achieve orders of magnitude higher accuracies than linear methods on data describing transport-dominated dynamics in numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09746v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Schwerdtner, Serkan Gugercin, Benjamin Peherstorfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale Dynamical Indices Reveal Scale-Dependent Atmospheric Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10069v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Geophysical systems are inherently complex and span multiple spatial and temporal scales, making their dynamics challenging to understand and predict. This challenge is especially pronounced for extreme events, which are primarily governed by their instantaneous properties rather than their average characteristics. Advances in dynamical systems theory, including the development of local dynamical indices such as local dimension and inverse persistence, have provided powerful tools for studying these short-lasting phenomena. However, existing applications of such indices often rely on predefined fixed spatial domains and scales, with limited discussion on the influence of spatial scales on the results. In this work, we present a novel spatially multiscale methodology that applies a sliding window method to compute dynamical indices, enabling the exploration of scale-dependent properties. Applying this framework to high-impact European summertime heatwaves, we reconcile previously different perspectives, thereby underscoring the importance of spatial scales in such analyses. Furthermore, we emphasize that our novel methodology has broad applicability to other atmospheric phenomena, as well as to other geophysical and spatio-temporal systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10069v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyu Dong, Gabriele Messori, Davide Faranda, Adriano Gualandi, Valerio Lucarini, Gianmarco Mengaldo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birkhoff sums as distributions I: Regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.04806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.04806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study Birkhoff sums as distributions. We obtain regularity results on such distributions for various dynamical systems with hyperbolicity, as hyperbolic linear maps on the torus and piecewise expanding maps on the interval. We also give some applications, as the study of advection in discrete dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.04806v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clodoaldo Grotta-Ragazzo, Daniel Smania</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The pruning front conjecture, folding patterns and classification of H\'enon maps in the presence of strange attractors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.12568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.12568v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the topological dynamics of H\'enon maps. For a parameter set generalizing the Benedicks-Carleson parameters (the Wang-Young parameter set) we obtain the following:
  The pruning front conjecture (due to Cvitanovi\'c);
  A kneading theory (realizing a conjecture by Benedicks and Carleson);
  A classification: two H\'enon maps are conjugate on their strange attractors if and only if their sets of kneading sequences coincide, if and only if their folding patterns coincide.
  The folding pattern is a single sequence of 0s and 1s, which allows to distinguish two nonconjugate H\'enon attractors in finitely many steps. The classification result relies on further development of the authors' recent inverse limit description of H\'enon attractors in terms of densely branching trees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.12568v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan P. Boro\'nski, Sonja \v{S}timac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reading multiplicity in unfoldings from epsilon-neighborhoods of orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.07914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.07914v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider generic 1-parameter unfoldings of parabolic vector fields. It is known that the box dimension of orbits of their time-one maps is discontinuous at the bifurcation value. Here, we expand asymptotically the Lebesgue measure of the epsilon-neighborhoods of orbits of the time-one maps in a Chebyshev scale, uniformly with respect to the bifurcation parameter. We use the so-called Ecalle-Roussarie-type compensators. We read from the expansion the number of hyperbolic points born in the unfolding of the parabolic point (i.e. the codimension of the bifurcation).
  We consider generic analytic 1-parameter unfoldings of saddle-node germs of analytic vector fields on the real line, their time-one maps and the Lebesgue measure of $\varepsilon$-neighborhoods of the orbits of these time-one maps.The box dimension of an orbit gives the asymptotics of the principal term of this Lebesgue measure and it is known that it is discontinuous at bifurcation parameters. In order to recover continuous dependence of the asymptotics on the parameter, here we expand asymptotically the Lebesgue measure of $\varepsilon$-neighborhoods of orbits of time-one maps in a Chebyshev system, uniformly with respect to the bifurcation parameter. We use \'Ecalle-Roussarie-type compensators. We show how the number of fixed points of the time-one map born in the universal analytic unfolding of the parabolic point corresponds to the number of terms vanishing in this uniform expansion of the Lebesgue measure of $\varepsilon$-neighborhoods of orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.07914v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renato Huzak, Pavao Marde\v{s}i\'c, Maja Resman, Vesna \v{Z}upanovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cycling Signatures: Identifying Cycling Motions in Time Series using Algebraic Topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04734v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recurrence is a fundamental characteristic of dynamical systems with complicated behavior. Understanding the inner structure of recurrence is challenging, especially if the system has many degrees of freedom and is subject to noise. We develop algebraic topological notions for identifying and classifying elementary recurrent motions -- called cycling -- and the transitions between those. Statistics on these cycling motions can be computed from sampled trajectories (time series data), providing coarse global information on the structure of the recurrent behavior. We demonstrate this through three examples; in particular, we identify and analyze six cycling motions in a four dimensional system with a hyperchaotic attractor. We see this as a promising approach to reveal coarse-grained dynamical information on high-dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04734v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Bauer, David Hien, Oliver Junge, Konstantin Mischaikow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular dynamics for discrete weak K.A.M. solutions of exact twist maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01141v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For any exact twist map $f$ and any cohomology class $c\in\mathbb{R}$, let $u_c$ be any associated discrete weak K.A.M. solution, and we introduce an inherent Lipschitz dynamics $\Sigma_+$ given by the discrete forward Lax-Oleinik semigroup. We investigate several properties of $\Sigma_+$ and show that the non-differentiable points of $u_c$ are globally propagated and forward invariant by $\Sigma_+$. In particular, such propagating dynamics possesses the same rotation number $\alpha'(c)$ as the associated Aubry-Mather set at cohomology class $c$. As applications, we provide via $\Sigma_+$ {a discrete analogue of Bernard's regularization theorem \cite{Ber07} and} a detailed exposition of Arnaud's observation \cite{Arnaud_2011}. Furthermore, we construct and analyze the corresponding dynamics on the full pseudo-graphs of discrete weak K.A.M. solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01141v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianxing Du, Xifeng Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimum Reduced-Order Models via Causal Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00271v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Constructing sparse, effective reduced-order models (ROMs) for high-dimensional dynamical data is an active area of research in applied sciences. In this work, we study an efficient approach to identifying such sparse ROMs using an information-theoretic indicator called causation entropy. Given a feature library of possible building block terms for the sought ROMs, the causation entropy ranks the importance of each term to the dynamics conveyed by the training data before a parameter estimation procedure is performed. It thus allows for an efficient construction of a hierarchy of ROMs with varying degrees of sparsity to effectively handle different tasks. This article examines the ability of the causation entropy to identify skillful sparse ROMs when a relatively high-dimensional ROM is required to emulate the dynamics conveyed by the training dataset. We demonstrate that a Gaussian approximation of the causation entropy still performs exceptionally well even in presence of highly non-Gaussian statistics. Such approximations provide an efficient way to access the otherwise hard to compute causation entropies when the selected feature library contains a large number of candidate functions. Besides recovering long-term statistics, we also demonstrate good performance of the obtained ROMs in recovering unobserved dynamics via data assimilation with partial observations, a test that has not been done before for causation-based ROMs of partial differential equations. The paradigmatic Kuramoto-Sivashinsky equation placed in a chaotic regime with highly skewed, multimodal statistics is utilized for these purposes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00271v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan Chen, Honghu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passivity Tools for Hybrid Learning Rules in Large Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02083v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent work has pioneered the use of system-theoretic passivity to study equilibrium stability for the dynamics of noncooperative strategic interactions in large populations of learning agents. In this and related works, the stability analysis leverages knowledge that certain ``canonical'' classes of learning rules used to model the agents' strategic behaviors satisfy a passivity condition known as $\delta$-passivity. In this paper, we consider that agents exhibit learning behaviors that do not align with a canonical class. Specifically, we focus on characterizing $\delta$-passivity for hybrid learning rules that combine elements from canonical classes. Our analysis also introduces and uses a more general version of $\delta$-passivity, which, for the first time, can handle discontinuous learning rules, including those showing best-response behaviors. We state and prove theorems establishing $\delta$-passivity for two broad convex cones of hybrid learning rules. These cones can merge into a larger one preserving $\delta$-passivity in scenarios limited to two strategies. In our proofs, we establish intermediate facts that are significant on their own and could potentially be used to further generalize our work. We illustrate the applicability of our results through numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02083v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jair Certorio, Kevin Chang, Nuno C. Martins, Pierluigi Nuzzo, Yasser Shoukry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Markovian Reduced Models to Unravel Transitions in Non-equilibrium Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work proposes a general framework for capturing noise-driven transitions in spatially extended non-equilibrium systems and explains the emergence of coherent patterns beyond the instability onset. The framework relies on stochastic parameterizations to reduce the original equations' complexity while capturing the key effects of unresolved scales. It works for both Gaussian and Levy-type noise. Our parameterizations offer two key advantages. First, they approximate stochastic invariant manifolds when the latter exist. Second, even when such manifolds break down, our formulas can be adapted by a simple optimization of its constitutive parameters. This allows us to handle scenarios with weak time-scale separation where the system has undergone multiple transitions, resulting in large-amplitude solutions not captured by invariant manifold or other time-scale separation methods. The optimized stochastic parameterizations capture how small-scale noise impacts larger scales through the system's nonlinear interactions. This effect is achieved by the very fabric of our parameterizations incorporating non-Markovian coefficients into the reduced equation. Such coefficients account for the noise's past influence using a finite memory length, selected for optimal performance. The specific "memory" function, which determines how this past influence is weighted, depends on the noise's strength and how it interacts with the system's nonlinearities. Remarkably, training our theory-guided reduced models on a single noise path effectively learns the optimal memory length for out-of-sample predictions, including rare events. This success stems from our "hybrid" approach, which combines analytical understanding with data-driven learning. This combination avoids a key limitation of purely data-driven methods: their struggle to generalize to unseen scenarios, also known as the "extrapolation problem."</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13428v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micka\"el D. Chekroun, Honghu Liu, James C. McWilliams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant Polydiagonal Subspaces of Matrices and Constraint Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10904v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a polydiagonal subspace of the Euclidean space, certain components of the vectors are equal (synchrony) or opposite (anti-synchrony). Polydiagonal subspaces invariant under a matrix have many applications in graph theory and dynamical systems, especially coupled cell networks. We describe invariant polydiagonal subspaces in terms of coloring vectors. This approach gives an easy formulation of a constraint satisfaction problem for finding invariant polydiagonal subspaces. Solving the resulting problem with existing state-of-the-art constraint solvers greatly outperforms the currently known algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10904v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John M. Neuberger, N\'andor Sieben, James W. Swift</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disturbance-Robust Backup Control Barrier Functions: Safety Under Uncertain Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07700v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Obtaining a controlled invariant set is crucial for safety-critical control with control barrier functions (CBFs) but is non-trivial for complex nonlinear systems and constraints. Backup control barrier functions allow such sets to be constructed online in a computationally tractable manner by examining the evolution (or flow) of the system under a known backup control law. However, for systems with unmodeled disturbances, this flow cannot be directly computed, making the current methods inadequate for assuring safety in these scenarios. To address this gap, we leverage bounds on the nominal and disturbed flow to compute a forward invariant set online by ensuring safety of an expanding norm ball tube centered around the nominal system evolution. We prove that this set results in robust control constraints which guarantee safety of the disturbed system via our Disturbance-Robust Backup Control Barrier Function (DR-bCBF) solution. The efficacy of the proposed framework is demonstrated in simulation, applied to a double integrator problem and a rigid body spacecraft rotation problem with rate constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07700v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LCSYS.2024.3514998</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David E. J. van Wijk, Samuel Coogan, Tamas G. Molnar, Manoranjan Majji, Kerianne L. Hobbs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-dimensional cellular automata with a unique active transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03601v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A one-dimensional cellular automaton $\tau : A^\mathbb{Z} \to A^\mathbb{Z}$ is a transformation of the full shift defined via a finite neighborhood $S \subset \mathbb{Z}$ and a local function $\mu : A^S \to A$. We study the family of cellular automata whose finite neighborhood $S$ is an interval containing $0$, and there exists a pattern $p \in A^S$ satisfying that $\mu(z) = z(0)$ if and only if $z \neq p$; this means that these cellular automata have a unique \emph{active transition}. Despite its simplicity, this family presents interesting and subtle problems, as the behavior of the cellular automaton completely depends on the structure of $p$. We show that every cellular automaton $\tau$ with a unique active transition $p \in A^S$ is either idempotent or strictly almost equicontinuous, and we completely characterize each one of these situations in terms of $p$. In essence, the idempotence of $\tau$ depends on the existence of a certain subpattern of $p$ with a translational symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03601v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alonso Castillo-Ramirez, Maria G. Maga\~na-Chavez, Luguis de los Santos Ba\~nos</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
