<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Seminorm estimates and joint ergodicity for pairwise independent Hardy sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a robust structure theory for multiple ergodic averages of commuting transformations along Hardy sequences of polynomial growth. We then apply it to derive a number of novel results on joint ergodicity, recurrence and convergence. Specifically, we construct a suitable generalization of Host-Kra and box seminorms that quantitatively controls the aforementioned averages subject to necessary nondegeneracy conditions on the Hardy sequences. Combining this with a variant of the seminorm smoothing argument, we obtain Host-Kra seminorm estimates for averages along all pairwise independent Hardy sequences. In conjunction with joint ergodicity criteria and classical equidistribution results, these estimates yield a number of novel joint ergodicity results that reach far beyond the state of the art. In particular, we prove joint ergodicity for (a) pairwise independent Hardy sequences and weakly mixing transformations, (b) strongly independent Hardy sequences and ergodic transformations, (c) irrationally strongly independent Hardy sequences and totally ergodic transformations. We also positively resolve the joint ergodicity classification problem for all pairwise independent Hardy sequences, of which the aforementioned three families are special cases. Lastly, we use these joint ergodicity results to provide new recurrence results for multidimensional patterns along strongly independent Hardy sequences.
  While building on recent technical advances (e.g. PET coefficient tracking schemes and joint ergodicity criteria), our work introduces a number of technical developments of its own, including the theory of generalized box seminorms, an ergodic version of the quantitative concatenation argument, improved simultaneous Taylor approximations for Hardy sequences, and a generalization of the seminorm smoothing argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15130v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebasti\'an Donoso, Andreas Koutsogiannis, Borys Kuca, Wenbo Sun, Konstantinos Tsinas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The discrete charm of iterated function systems. A computer scientist's perspective on approximation of IFS invariant sets and measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15139v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study invariant sets and measures generated by iterated function systems defined on countable discrete spaces that are uniform grids of a finite dimension. The discrete spaces of this type can be considered as models of spaces in which actual numerical computation takes place. In this context, we investigate the possibility of the application of the random iteration algorithm to approximate these discrete IFS invariant sets and measures. The problems concerning a discretization of hyperbolic IFSs are considered as special cases of this more general setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15139v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomasz Martyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning the Rolling Penny Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider learning the dynamics of a typical nonholonomic system -- the rolling penny. A nonholonomic system is a system subject to nonholonomic constraints. Unlike holonomic constraints, a nonholonomic constraint does not define a submanifold on the configuration space. Therefore, the inverse problem of finding the constraints has to involve the tangent space. This paper discuss how to learn the dynamics, as well as the constraints for such a system given the data set of discrete trajectories on the tangent bundle $TQ$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15201v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baiyue Wang, Anthony Bloch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the limit cycles of a quartic model for evolutionary stable strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15354v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies the number of centers and limit cycles of the family of planar quartic polynomial vector fields that has the invariant algebraic curve $(4x^2-1)(4y^2-1)=0.$ The main interest for this type of vector fields comes from their appearance in some mathematical models in Game Theory composed by two players. In particular, we find examples with five nested limit cycles surrounding the same singularity, as well as examples with four limit cycles formed by two disjoint nests, each one of them with two limit cycles. We also prove a Berlinski\u \i's type result for this family of vector fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15354v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armengol Gasull, Luiz F. S. Gouveia, Paulo Santana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log H\"older continuity of the rotation number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider one-parameter families of smooth circle cocycles over an ergodic transformation in the base, and show that their rotation numbers must be log-H\"older regular with respect to the parameter. As an immediate application, we get a dynamical proof of 1D version of the Craig-Simon theorem that establishes that the integrated density of states of an ergodic Schr\"odinger operator must be log-H\"older.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15462v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Gorodetski, Victor Kleptsyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinearity, Fractals, Fourier decay -- Harmonic analysis of equilibrium states for hyperbolic dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is my (reviewed) PhD manuscript. It contains 6 Chapters, which contains mostly already published work, except for Chapter 5 which is new. Chapter 1 introduce basic notions on fractal geometry: the Fourier dimension, the thermodynamical formalism and additive combinatorics. Chapter 2 is a generalized version of arXiv:2211.08088. Chapter 3 is a slightly upgraded version of arXiv:2112.00701. Chapter 4 is a generalized version of arXiv:2301.10623. Chapter 5 and Chapter 4 together contains the first proof of the positivity of the Fourier dimension for basic sets of nonlinear, area-preserving, smooth Axiom A diffeomorphisms on surfaces. This is possible by adapting some ideas that can be found in Tsujii-Zhang's work arXiv:2006.04293. Some future work still needs to be done to prove that the nonlinearity conditions are generic in this setting: this should become a proper research article in the future. Chapter 6 is a slighty upgraded version of arXiv:2307.10755.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15476v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ga\'etan Leclerc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transitivity of real Anosov diffeomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15740v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the transitivity of real Anosov diffeomorphisms, which are Anosov diffeomorphisms where stable and unstable spaces decompose into a continuous sum of invariant one-dimensional sub-spaces with uniform contraction/expansion over the ambient manifold. We analyze how the stable/unstable holonomies of Anosov diffeomorphisms behave on Artigue's self-similar hyperbolic metric and prove that if a stable/unstable curve has a well-defined length in a self-similar hyperbolic metric, then it has a globally defined holonomy. We exhibit a self-similar hyperbolic metric with well-defined length of curves for each real Anosov diffeomorphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15740v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernardo Carvalho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral theoretic characterisation of Markov chain convergence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we characterise the statistics of Markov chains by constructing an associated sequence of periodic differential operators. Studying the density of states of these operators reveals the absolutely continuous invariant measure of the Markov chain. This approach also leads to a direct proof of convergence to the invariant measure, along with explicit convergence rates. We show how our method can be applied to a class of related Markov chains including the logistic map, the tent map and Chebyshev maps of arbitrary order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15829v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bryn Davies, Yu Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of asymptotic systems in Cohen-Grossberg neural network models with unbounded delays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the convergence of asymptotic systems in non-autonomous Cohen--Grossberg neural network models, which include both infinite discrete time-varying and distributed delays. We derive stability results under conditions where the non-delay terms asymptotically dominate the delay terms. Several examples and a numerical simulation are provided to illustrate the significance and novelty of the main result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15867v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Elmwafy, Jos\'e J. Oliveira, C\'esar M. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State Estimation Using Sparse DEIM and Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Discrete Empirical Interpolation Method (DEIM) estimates a function from its pointwise incomplete observations. In particular, this method can be used to estimate the state of a dynamical system from observational data gathered by sensors. However, when the number of observations are limited, DEIM returns large estimation errors. Sparse DEIM (S-DEIM) was recently developed to address this problem by introducing a kernel vector which previous DEIM-based methods had ignored. Unfortunately, estimating the optimal kernel vector in S-DEIM is a difficult task. Here, we introduce a data-driven method to estimate this kernel vector from sparse observational time series using recurrent neural networks. Using numerical examples, we demonstrate that this machine learning approach together with S-DEIM leads to nearly optimal state estimations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15982v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Farazmand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood-Free Inference and Hierarchical Data Assimilation for Geological Carbon Storage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15302v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Data assimilation will be essential for the management and expansion of geological carbon storage operations. In traditional data assimilation approaches a fixed set of geological hyperparameters, such as mean and standard deviation of log-permeability, is often assumed. Such hyperparameters, however, may be highly uncertain in practical CO2 storage applications. In this study, we develop a hierarchical data assimilation framework for carbon storage that treats hyperparameters as uncertain variables characterized by hyperprior distributions. To deal with the computationally intractable likelihood function in hyperparameter estimation, we apply a likelihood-free (or simulation-based) inference algorithm, specifically sequential Monte Carlo-based approximate Bayesian computation (SMC-ABC), to draw independent posterior samples of hyperparameters given dynamic monitoring-well data. In the second step we use an ensemble smoother with multiple data assimilation (ESMDA) procedure to provide posterior realizations of grid-block permeability. To reduce computational costs, a 3D recurrent R-U-Net deep-learning surrogate model is applied for forward function evaluations. The accuracy of the surrogate model is established through comparisons to high-fidelity simulation results. A rejection sampling (RS) procedure for data assimilation is applied to provide reference posterior results. Detailed data assimilation results from SMC-ABC-ESMDA are compared to those from the reference RS method. These include marginal posterior distributions of hyperparameters, pairwise posterior samples, and history matching results for pressure and saturation at the monitoring location. Close agreement is achieved with 'converged' RS results, for two synthetic true models, in all quantities considered. Importantly, the SMC-ABC-ESMDA procedure provides speedup of 1-2 orders of magnitude relative to RS for the two cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15302v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenchao Teng, Louis J. Durlofsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding how higher-order network interactions shape complex contagion dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Complex contagion models that involve contagion along higher-order structures, such as simplicial complexes and hypergraphs, yield new classes of mean-field models. Interestingly, the differential equations arising from many such models often exhibit a similar form, resulting in qualitatively comparable global bifurcation patterns. Motivated by this observation, we investigate a generalized mean-field-type model that provides a unified framework for analysing a range of different models. In particular, we derive analytical conditions for the emergence of different bifurcation regimes exhibited by three models of increasing complexity -- ranging from three- and four-body interactions to two connected populations with both pairwise and three-body interactions. For the first two cases, we give a complete characterisation of all possible outcomes, along with the corresponding conditions on network and epidemic parameters. In the third case, we demonstrate that multistability is possible despite only three-body interactions. Our results reveal that single population models with three-body interactions can only exhibit simple transcritical transitions or bistability, whereas with four-body interactions multistability with two distinct endemic steady states is possible. Surprisingly, the two-population model exhibits multistability via symmetry breaking despite three-body interactions only. Our work sheds light on the relationship between equation structure and model behaviour and makes the first step towards elucidating mechanisms by which different system behaviours arise, and how network and dynamic properties facilitate or hinder outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15330v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Istv\'an Z. Kiss, Christian Bick, P\'eter L. Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Topological Dirac Synchronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15338v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Synchronization is a fundamental dynamical state of interacting oscillators, observed in natural biological rhythms and in the brain. Global synchronization which occurs when non-linear or chaotic oscillators placed on the nodes of a network display the same dynamics as received great attention in network theory. Here we propose and investigate Global Topological Dirac Synchronization on higher-order networks such as cell and simplicial complexes. This is a state where oscillators associated to simplices and cells of arbitrary dimension, coupled by the Topological Dirac operator, operate at unison. By combining algebraic topology with non-linear dynamics and machine learning, we derive the topological conditions under which this state exists and the dynamical conditions under which it is stable. We provide evidence of 1-dimensional simplicial complexes (networks) and 2-dimensional simplicial and cell complexes where Global Topological Dirac Synchronization can be observed. Our results point out that Global Topological Dirac Synchronization is a possible dynamical state of simplicial and cell complexes that occur only in some specific network topologies and geometries, the latter ones being determined by the weights of the higher-order networks</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15338v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timoteo Carletti, Lorenzo Giambagli, Riccardo Muolo, Ginestra Bianconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long time behavior of semi-Markov modulated perpetuity and some related processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Examples of stochastic processes whose state space representations involve functions of an integral type structure $$I_{t}^{(a,b)}:=\int_{0}^{t}b(Y_{s})e^{-\int_{s}^{t}a(Y_{r})dr}ds, \quad t\ge 0$$ are studied under an ergodic semi-Markovian environment described by an $S$ valued jump type process $Y:=(Y_{s}:s\in\mathbb{R}^{+})$ that is ergodic with a limiting distribution $\pi\in\mathcal{P}(S)$. Under different assumptions on signs of $E_{\pi}a(\cdot):=\sum_{j\in S}\pi_{j}a(j)$ and tail properties of the sojourn times of $Y$ we obtain different long time limit results for $I^{(a,b)}_{}:=(I^{(a,b)}_{t}:t\ge 0).$ In all cases mixture type of laws emerge which are naturally represented through an affine stochastic recurrence equation (SRE) $X\stackrel{d}{=}AX+B,\,\, X\perp\!\!\!\perp (A, B)$. Examples include explicit long-time representations of pitchfork bifurcation, and regime-switching diffusions under semi-Markov modulated environments, etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15824v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Pal Majumder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equidistribution of iterations of holomorphic correspondences and Hutchinson invariant sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.13959v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we analyze a certain family of holomorphic correspondences on $\hat{\mathbb C}\times\hat{\mathbb C}$ and prove their equidistribution properties. In particular, for any correspondence in this family we prove that the naturally associated multivalued map $F$ is such that for any $a\in \mathbb C$, we have that $(F^n)_*(\delta_a)$ converges to a probability measure $\mu_F$ for which $F_*(\mu_F)=\mu_F d$ where $d$ is the degree of $F$. This result is used to show that the minimal Hutchinson invariant set in degree $n$ of a large class of operators and for sufficiently large $n$ exists and is the support of the aforementioned measure. We prove that under a minor additional assumption, this set is a Cantor set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.13959v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1090/ecgd/394</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Conform. Geom. Dyn. 28 (2024), 97-114</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nils Hemmingsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Koopman Learning with Episodic Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Koopman operator theory has found significant success in learning models of complex, real-world dynamical systems, enabling prediction and control. The greater interpretability and lower computational costs of these models, compared to traditional machine learning methodologies, make Koopman learning an especially appealing approach. Despite this, little work has been performed on endowing Koopman learning with the ability to leverage its own failures. To address this, we equip Koopman methods - developed for predicting non-autonomous time-series - with an episodic memory mechanism, enabling global recall of (or attention to) periods in time where similar dynamics previously occurred. We find that a basic implementation of Koopman learning with episodic memory leads to significant improvements in prediction on synthetic and real-world data. Our framework has considerable potential for expansion, allowing for future advances, and opens exciting new directions for Koopman learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12615v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William T. Redman, Dean Huang, Maria Fonoberova, Igor Mezi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Destruction and Persistence of Lagrangian Torus in Hamiltonian Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01695v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For an integrable Hamiltonian systems with $d$ degrees of freedom ($d\geq 2$), we consider quantitatively the existence and non-existence of the flow-invariant Lagrangian torus with given frequency under the perturbation beyond the scope of the classical KAM method in the $C^r$ topology. As applications, the non-existence result gives a partial answer to an open problem on non-existence of invariant circles by Mather from 1988. The existence result sheds a light on another open problem on the existence of invariant circles with lower regularity by Mather from 1998.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01695v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slow entropy and variational dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11137v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define variational properties for dynamical systems with subexponential complexity, and study these properties in certain specific examples. By computing the value of slow entropy directly, we show that some subshifts are not variational, while a class of interval exchange transformations are variational.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11137v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minhua Cheng, Carlos Ospina, Kurt Vinhage, Yibo Zhai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poisson stability of solutions for stochastic evolution equations driven by fractional Brownian motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04313v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the problem of Poisson stability of solutions for stochastic semi-linear evolution equation driven by fractional Brownian motion \mathrm{d} X(t)= \left( AX(t) + f(t, X(t)) \right) \mathrm{d}t + g\left(t, X(t)\right)\mathrm{d}B^H_{Q}(t), where A is an exponentially stable linear operator acting on a separable Hilbert space \mathbb{H}, coefficients f and g are Poisson stable in time, and B^H_Q (t) is a Q-cylindrical fBm with Hurst index H. First, we establish the existence and uniqueness of the solution for this equation. Then, we prove that under the condition where the functions f and g are sufficiently "small", the equation admits a solution that exhibits the same character of recurrence as f and g. The discussion is further extended to the asymptotic stability of these Poisson stable solutions. Finally, we include an example to validate our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04313v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinze Zhang, Li Yong, Xue Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic dynamics on amenable groups and van der Corput sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We answer a question of Bergelson and Lesigne by showing that the notion of van der Corput set does not depend on the F\o lner sequence used to define it. This result has been discovered independently by Sa\'ul Rodr\'iguez Mart\'in. Both ours and Rodr\'iguez's proofs proceed by first establishing a converse to the Furstenberg Correspondence Principle for amenable groups.
  This involves studying the distributions of Reiter sequences over congruent sequences of tilings of the group.
  Lastly, we show that many of the equivalent characterizations of van der Corput sets in $\mathbb{N}$ that do not involve F\o lner sequences remain equivalent for arbitrary countably infinite groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00806v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sohail Farhangi, Robin Tucker-Drob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient pseudometrics for data-driven comparisons of nonlinear dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18681v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Computationally efficient solutions for pseudometrics quantifying deviation from topological conjugacy between dynamical systems are presented. Deviation from conjugacy is quantified in a Pareto optimal sense that accounts for spectral properties of Koopman operators as well as trajectory geometry. Theoretical justification is provided for computing such pseudometrics in Koopman eigenfunction space rather than observable space. Furthermore, it is shown deriving the pseudometrics from unitary transformations is necessary to recover a value of zero if two systems are topologically conjugate. Therefore the pseudometrics for quantifying deviation from conjugacy are based on analytical solutions for unitary transformations in Koopman eigenfunction space. Finally, geometric considerations for the deviation from conjugac Pareto optimality problem are used to develop scalar pseudometrics that account for all possible solutions given just two Pareto points based. The approach is demonstrated on two example problems; the first being a simple benchmarking problems and the second an engineering example comparing the dynamics of morphological computation of biological nonlinear muscle actuators to simplified `man-made' or bio-inspired approaches. The benefits of considering operator based and trajectory geometry based dissimilarity measures in a unified and consistent formalism were demonstrated. Overall, the deviation from conjugacy pseudometrics provide practical advantages in terms of efficiency and scalability, while maintaining theoretical consistency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18681v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bryan Glaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>URP, comparison, mean dimension, and sharp shift embeddability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01757v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a free action $G \curvearrowright X$ of an amenable group on a compact metrizable space, we study the Uniform Rokhlin Property (URP) and the conjunction of Uniform Rokhlin Property and comparison (URPC). We give several equivalent formulations of the latter and show that it passes to extensions. We introduce technical conditions called property FCSB and property FCSB in measure, both of which reduce to the marker property if $G$ is abelian. Our first main result is that for any amenable group $G$ property FCSB in measure is equivalent to URP, and for a large class of amenable groups property FCSB is equivalent to URPC. In the latter case, it follows that if the action is moreover minimal then the C$^*$-crossed product $C(X) \rtimes G$ has stable rank one, satisfies the Toms-Winter conjecture, and is classifiable if $\mathrm{mdim}(G \curvearrowright X) = 0$.
  Our second main result is that if a system $G \curvearrowright X$ has URPC and $\mathrm{mdim}(G \curvearrowright X) &lt; M/2$, then it is embeddable into the $M$-cubical shift $\left([0, 1]^M\right)^G$. Combined with the first main result, we recover the Gutman-Qiao-Tsukamoto sharp shift embeddability theorem as a special case. Notably, the proof avoids the use of either Euclidean geometry or signal analysis and directly extends the theorem to all abelian groups.
  Finally, we show that if $G$ is a nonamenable group that contains a free subgroup on two generators and $G \curvearrowright X$ is a topologically amenable action, then it is embeddable into $[0, 1]^G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01757v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petr Naryshkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphism Groups of Commuting Polynomial Maps of the Affine Plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10598v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{L}$ be a finite-dimensional semisimple Lie algebra of rank $N$ over an algebraically closed field of characteristic $0$. Associated to $\mathcal{L}$ is a family of polynomial folding maps $$\textsf{F}_{n}:\mathbb{A}^N\to\mathbb{A}^N\quad\text{for}\quad n\ge1$$ having the property that $\textsf{F}_{n}$ has topological degree $n^N$ and $$\textsf{F}_{m}\circ\textsf{F}_{n}=\textsf{F}_{n}\circ\textsf{F}_{m}\quad\text{for all}\quad m,n\ge1.$$ We derive formulas for the leading terms of the folding maps on $\mathbb{A}^2$ associated to the Lie algebras $\mathcal{A}_2$, $\mathcal{B}_2$, and $\mathcal{G}_2$, and we use these formulas to compute the affine automorphism group of each folding map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10598v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jospeh H. Silverman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Koopman representations for positive definite functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.19386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.19386v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that for any locally compact second countable group $G$ and any continuous positive definite function $\phi:G\rightarrow\mathbb{C}$, there exists an ergodic measure preserving system $(X,\mathscr{B},\mu,\{T_g\}_{g \in G})$ and a function $f \in L^2(X,\mu)$ for which $\phi(g) = \langle T_gf,f\rangle$. We also show that if $G$ is a countably infinite abelian group, then there exists a (not necessarily ergodic) measure preserving system $(X,\mathscr{B},\mu,\{T_g\}_{g \in G})$ and a function $f \in L^2(X,\mu)$ with $|f| = \phi(0)$ and $\phi(g) = \langle T_gf,f\rangle$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.19386v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sohail Farhangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shocks and instability in Brownian last-passage percolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07866v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For stochastic Hamilton-Jacobi (SHJ) equations, instability points are the space-time locations where two eternal solutions with the same asymptotic velocity differ. Another crucial structure in such equations is shocks, which are the space-time locations where the velocity field is discontinuous. In this work, we provide a detailed analysis of the structure and relationships between shocks, instability, and competition interfaces in the Brownian last-passage percolation model, which serves as a prototype of a semi-discrete inviscid stochastic HJ equation in one space dimension. Among our findings, we show that the shock trees of the two unstable eternal solutions differ within the instability region and align outside of it. Furthermore, we demonstrate that one can reconstruct a skeleton of the instability region from these two shock trees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07866v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Firas Rassoul-Agha, Mikhail Sweeney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volumes, Lorenz-like templates, and braids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04391v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we find a more straightforward problem that is equivalent to one of the major challenges in knot theory: the classification of links in the 3-sphere. More precisely, we provide a simpler braid description for all links in the 3-sphere in terms of generalised T-links. With this, we translate the problem of classifying links in the 3-sphere into a problem of counting the number of generalised T-links that represent the same link. Generalised T-links are a natural generalisation of twisted torus links and Lorenz links, two families of links that have been extensively studied by many people. Moreover, we generalise the bunch algorithm to construct links embedded in universal Lorenz-like templates and provide an upper volume bound that is quadratic in the trip number. We use the upper bound obtained from the generalised bunch algorithm for generalised T-links to establish an upper bound for the sum of the volumes of the hyperbolic pieces of all closed, orientable, connected 3-manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04391v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thiago de Paiva, Connie On Yu Hui, Jos\'e Andr\'es Rodr\'iguez Migueles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-informed modeling of the formation, persistence, and evolution of social norms and conventions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06663v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Social norms and conventions are commonly accepted and adopted behaviors and practices within a social group that guide interactions -- e.g., how to spell a word or how to greet people -- and are central to a group's culture and identity. Understanding the key mechanisms that govern the formation, persistence, and evolution of social norms and conventions in social communities is a problem of paramount importance for a broad range of real-world applications, spanning from preparedness for future emergencies to promotion of sustainable practices. In the past decades, mathematical modeling has emerged as a powerful tool to reproduce and study the complex dynamics of norm and convention change, gaining insights into their mechanisms, and ultimately deriving tools to predict their evolution. The first goal of this chapter is to introduce some of the main mathematical approaches for modeling social norms and conventions, including population models and agent-based models relying on the theories of dynamical systems, evolutionary dynamics, and game theory. The second goal of the chapter is to illustrate how quantitative observations and empirical data can be incorporated into these mathematical models in a systematic manner, establishing a data-based approach to mathematical modeling of formation, persistence, and evolution of social norms and conventions. Finally, current challenges and future opportunities in this growing field of research are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06663v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengbin Ye, Lorenzo Zino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurable splittings and the measured group theoretic structure of wreath products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11754v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be a countable group that admits an essential measurable splitting (for instance, any group measure equivalent to a free product of nontrivial groups).
  We show: (1) for any two nontrivial countable groups $A$ and $B$ that are measure equivalent, the wreath product groups $A\wr\Gamma$ and $B\wr\Gamma$ are measure equivalent (in fact, orbit equivalent) -- this is interesting even in the case when the groups $A$ and $B$ are finite; and (2) the groups $A\wr \Gamma$ and $(A\times\mathbf{Z})\wr\Gamma$ are measure equivalent (in fact, orbit equivalent) for every nontrivial countable group $A$.
  On the other hand, we show that certain wreath product actions are not even stably orbit equivalent if $\Gamma$ is instead assumed to be a sofic icc group that is Bernoulli superrigid, and $A$ and $B$ have different cardinalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11754v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin Tucker-Drob, Konrad Wr\'obel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
