<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 02:53:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Group-Convolutional Extended Dynamic Mode Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores the integration of symmetries into the Koopman-operator framework for the analysis and efficient learning of equivariant dynamical systems using a group-convolutional approach. Approximating the Koopman operator by finite-dimensional surrogates, e.g., via extended dynamic mode decomposition (EDMD), is challenging for high-dimensional systems due to computational constraints. To tackle this problem with a particular focus on EDMD, we demonstrate -- under suitable equivarance assumptions on the system and the observables -- that the optimal EDMD matrix is equivariant. That is, its action on states can be described by group convolutions and the generalized Fourier transform. We show that this structural property has many advantages for equivariant systems, in particular, that it allows for data-efficient learning, fast predictions and fast eigenfunction approximations. We conduct numerical experiments on the Kuramoto--Sivashinsky equation, a nonlinear and chaotic partial differential equation, providing evidence of the effectiveness of this approach, and highlighting its potential for broader applications in dynamical systems analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00905v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans Harder, Sebastian Peitz, Feliks N\"uske, Friedrich M. Philipp, Manuel Schaller, Karl Worthmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolvent-Type Data-Driven Learning of Generators for Unknown Continuous-Time Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A semigroup characterization, or equivalently, a characterization by the generator, is a classical technique used to describe continuous-time nonlinear dynamical systems. In the realm of data-driven learning for an unknown nonlinear system, one must estimate the generator of the semigroup of the system's transfer operators (also known as the semigroup of Koopman operators) based on discrete-time observations and verify convergence to the true generator in an appropriate sense. As the generator encodes essential transient transitional information of the system, challenges arise for some existing methods that rely on accurately estimating the time derivatives of the state with constraints on the observation rate. Recent literature develops a technique that avoids the use of time derivatives by employing the logarithm of a Koopman operator. However, the validity of this method has been demonstrated only within a restrictive function space and requires knowledge of the operator's spectral properties. In this paper, we propose a resolvent-type method for learning the system generator to relax the requirements on the observation frequency and overcome the constraints of taking operator logarithms. We also provide numerical examples to demonstrate its effectiveness in applications of system identification and constructing Lyapunov functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00923v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Meng, Ruikun Zhou, Melkior Ornik, Jun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the dynamics of non-autonomous systems in a~neighborhood of a~homoclinic trajectory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article is devoted to the study of a $2$-dimensional piecewise smooth (but possibly) discontinuous dynamical system, subject to a non-autonomous perturbation; we assume that the unperturbed system admits a homoclinic trajectory $\vec{\gamma}(t)$. Our aim is to analyze the dynamics in a neighborhood of $\vec{\gamma}(t)$ as the perturbation is turned on, by defining a Poincar\'e map and evaluating fly time and space displacement of trajectories performing a loop close to $\vec{\gamma}(t)$.
  Besides their intrinsic mathematical interest, these results can be thought of as a first step in the analysis of several interesting problems, such as the stability of a homoclinic trajectory of a non-autonomous ODE and a possible extension of Melnikov chaos to a discontinuous setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01181v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Calamai, Matteo Franca, Michal Pospisil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interval maps mimicking circle rotations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the dynamics of maps of the real line whose behavior on an invariant interval is close to a rational rotation on the circle. We concentrate on a specific two-parameter family, describing the dynamics arising from models in game theory, mathematical biology and machine learning. If one parameter is a rational number, $k/n$, with $k,n$ coprime, and the second one is large enough, we prove that there is a periodic orbit of period $n$. It behaves like an orbit of the circle rotation by an angle $2\pi k/n$ and attracts trajectories of Lebesgue almost all starting points. We also discover numerically other interesting phenomena. While we do not give rigorous proofs for them, we provide convincing explanations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01495v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Bielawski, Thiparat Chotibut, Fryderyk Falniowski, Micha{\l} Misiurewicz, Georgios Piliouras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The equivalence of asymptotic average shadowing and vague specification properties and its consequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the equivalence between the asymptotic average shadowing and the vague specification properties and we use this equivalence to answer a question posed by Downarowicz and Weiss [Ergod. Th. \&amp; Dynam. Sys. 44 (9) (2024), 2565-2580]. Additionally, we prove that the asymptotic average shadowing property is equivalent to the average shadowing property if the phase space is complete with respect to the dynamical Besicovitch pseudometric. We use the latter result to prove that proximal and minimal shift spaces from [Minimal and proximal examples of $\bar{d}$-stable and $\bar{d}$-approachable shift spaces, Ergod. Th. \&amp; Dynam. Sys., (2024) First View] possess the asymptotic average shadowing property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01556v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melih Emin Can, Alexandre Trilles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LES-SINDy: Laplace-Enhanced Sparse Identification of Nonlinear Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sparse Identification of Nonlinear Dynamical Systems (SINDy) is a powerful tool for the data-driven discovery of governing equations. However, it encounters challenges when modeling complex dynamical systems involving high-order derivatives or discontinuities, particularly in the presence of noise. These limitations restrict its applicability across various fields in applied mathematics and physics. To mitigate these, we propose Laplace-Enhanced SparSe Identification of Nonlinear Dynamical Systems (LES-SINDy). By transforming time-series measurements from the time domain to the Laplace domain using the Laplace transform and integration by parts, LES-SINDy enables more accurate approximations of derivatives and discontinuous terms. It also effectively handles unbounded growth functions and accumulated numerical errors in the Laplace domain, thereby overcoming challenges in the identification process. The model evaluation process selects the most accurate and parsimonious dynamical systems from multiple candidates. Experimental results across diverse ordinary and partial differential equations show that LES-SINDy achieves superior robustness, accuracy, and parsimony compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01719v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyang Zheng, Guang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectra and joint dynamics of Poisson suspensions over rank-one automorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02024v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For every natural $n&gt;1$, there is an operator $T$ of dynamical origin such that its tensor power $T^{\otimes n}$ has singular spectrum, and $T^{\otimes (n+1)}$ has absolutely continuous one. For a set $D$ of positive measure there are mixing zero entropy automorphisms $S,T$ such that $S^nD\cap T^nD=\varnothing$ for all $n&gt;0$. The following answers, in particular, Frantzikinakis-Host's question. If $ p(n+1)- p(n), \ \ q(n+1)- q(n)\ \to\ +\infty$, then there is a divergent sequence $ \sum_{n=1}^{N} \mu(S^{ p(n)}C\cap T^{ q(n)}C)/N$ for some set $C$ and automorphisms $S,T$ of simple singular spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02024v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valery V. Ryzhikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Length averages for codimension one foliations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study geometrical and dynamical properties of codimension one foliations, by exploring a relation between length averages and ball averages of certain group actions. We introduce a new mechanism, which relies on the group structure itself, to obtain irregular behavior of ball averages for certain non-amenable group actions. Several geometric realization results show that any such groups can appear connected with the topology of leaves which are connected sums of plugs with a special geometry, namely nearly equidistant boundary components. This is used to produce the first examples of codimension one $\mathcal C^\infty$ regular foliations on a compact Riemannian manifold $M$ for which the length average of some continuous function does not exist on a non-empty open subset of $M$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02106v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masayuki Asaoka, Yushi Nakano, Paulo Varandas, Tomoo Yokoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nekhoroshev theory and discrete averaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper contains a proof of the Nekhoroshev theorem for quasi-integrable symplectic maps. In contrast to the classical methods, our proof is based on the discrete averaging method and does not rely on transformations to normal forms. At the centre of our arguments lies the theorem on embedding of a near-the-identity symplectic map into an autonomous Hamiltonian flow with exponentially small error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02190v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Gelfreich, A. Vieiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Global Analysis of Experimental Dynamics through Low-Dimensional Linear Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00989v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dynamical systems theory has long provided a foundation for understanding evolving phenomena across scientific domains. Yet, the application of this theory to complex real-world systems remains challenging due to issues in mathematical modeling, nonlinearity, and high dimensionality. In this work, we introduce a data-driven computational framework to derive low-dimensional linear models for nonlinear dynamical systems directly from raw experimental data. This framework enables global stability analysis through interpretable linear models that capture the underlying system structure. Our approach employs time-delay embedding, physics-informed deep autoencoders, and annealing-based regularization to identify novel low-dimensional coordinate representations, unlocking insights across a variety of simulated and previously unstudied experimental dynamical systems. These new coordinate representations enable accurate long-horizon predictions and automatic identification of intricate invariant sets while providing empirical stability guarantees. Our method offers a promising pathway to analyze complex dynamical behaviors across fields such as physics, climate science, and engineering, with broad implications for understanding nonlinear systems in the real world.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00989v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel A. Moore, Brian P. Mann, Boyuan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Dynamics of McKean-Vlasov SDEs via Stochastic Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01364v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the rich dynamics of general one-dimensional McKean-Vlasov stochastic differential equations based on the preservation of stochastic order. The existing work is limited to the case of additive noises, while our framework allows multiplicative noises. When the equation has multiple invariant measures, we show basins of attraction of certain invariant measures contain unbounded open sets in the 2-Wasserstein space, which is vacant in previous research even for additive noises. Also, our main results target on total orderedness and finiteness of invariant measures, global convergence to order interval enclosed by two order-related invariant measures, alternating arrangement of invariant measures in terms of stability (locally attracting) and instability (connecting orbits). Our theorems cover a wide range of classical granular media equations, such as symmetric, flat-bottom and asymmetric double-well confinement potentials with quadratic interaction, multi-well landscapes, and double-well landscapes with perturbations. Specific values for the parameter ranges, explicit descriptions of attracting sets and phase diagrams are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01364v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baoyou Qu, Jinxiang Yao, Yanpeng Zhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qualitative analysis of HAART effects on HIV and SARS-CoV-2 coinfection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01374v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: HIV is known for causing the destruction of the immune system by affecting different types of cells, while SARS-CoV-2 is an extremely contagious virus that leads to the development of COVID-19. In this study, we propose a mathematical model to investigate the interaction between HIV and SARS-CoV-2 under highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART). We determine the conditions for the endemic equilibria of both viruses, showing that transcritical bifurcations occur when the basic reproduction numbers of HIV and SARS-CoV-2 pass through 1. We set the condition for the stability of the disease-free equilibrium point of the model with coinfection as a function of the basic reproduction number $\mathcal{R}_0$. Through numerical simulations, we conclude that HAART, used to control HIV, also reduces the proliferation of SARS-CoV-2-infected cells in coinfected hosts. These findings provide important insights into the epidemiological dynamics of HIV and SARS-CoV-2 coinfection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01374v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao P. S. Maur\'icio de Carvalho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Mexican hat dance: clustering in Ricker-potential particle systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01770v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dynamics and spontaneous organization of coupled particles is a classic problem in modeling and applied mathematics. Here we examine the behavior of particles coupled by the Ricker potential, exhibiting finite local repulsion transitioning to distal attraction, leading to an energy-minimizing ``preferred distance''. When compressed by a background potential well of varying severity, these particles exhibit intricate self-organization into ``stacks" with varying sizes and positions. We examine bifurcations of these high-dimensional arrangements, yielding tantalizing glimpses into a rich dynamical zoo of behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01770v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Sabin-Miller, Daniel M. Abrams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new approach to data assimilation initialization problems with sparse data using multiple cost functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article develops a novel data assimilation methodology, addressing challenges that are common in real-world settings, such as severe sparsity of observations, lack of reliable models, and non-stationarity of the system dynamics. These challenges often cause identifiability issues and can confound model parameter initialization, both of which can lead to estimated models with unrealistic qualitative dynamics and induce deeper parameter estimation errors. The proposed methodology's objective function is constructed as a sum of components, each serving a different purpose: enforcing point-wise and distribution-wise agreement between data and model output, enforcing agreement of variables and parameters with a model provided, and penalizing unrealistic rapid parameter changes, unless they are due to external drivers or interventions. This methodology was motivated by, developed and evaluated in the context of estimating blood glucose levels in different medical settings. Both simulated and real data are used to evaluate the methodology from different perspectives, such as its ability to estimate unmeasured variables, its ability to reproduce the correct qualitative blood glucose dynamics, how it manages known non-stationarity, and how it performs when given a range of dense and severely sparse data. The results show that a multicomponent cost function can balance the minimization of point-wise errors with global properties, robustly preserving correct qualitative dynamics and managing data sparsity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01786v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David J. Abers, George Hripcsak, Lena Mamykina, Melike Sirlanci, Esteban G. Tabak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backstepping Design for Incremental Input-to-State Stabilization of Unknown Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01872v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Incremental stability of dynamical systems ensures the convergence of trajectories from different initial conditions towards each other rather than a fixed trajectory or equilibrium point. Here, we introduce and characterize a novel class of incremental Lyapunov functions, an incremental stability notion known as Incremental Input-to-State practical Stability ({\delta}-ISpS). Using Gaussian Process, we learn the unknown dynamics of a class of control systems. We then present a backstepping control design scheme that provides state-feedback controllers that render the partially unknown control system {\delta}-ISpS. To show the effectiveness of the proposed controller, we implement it in two case studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01872v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Smith Sundarsingh, Bhabani Shankar Dey, Pushpak Jagtap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Periodic colorings and orientations in infinite graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01951v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the existence of periodic colorings and orientations in locally finite graphs. A coloring or orientation of a graph $G$ is periodic if the resulting colored or oriented graph is quasi-transitive, meaning that $V(G)$ has finitely many orbits under the action of the group of automorphisms of $G$ preserving the coloring or the orientation. When such a periodic coloring or orientation of $G$ exists, $G$ itself must be quasi-transitive and it is natural to investigate when quasi-transitive graphs have such periodic colorings or orientations. We provide examples of Cayley graphs with no periodic orientation or non-trivial coloring, and examples of quasi-transitive graphs of treewidth 2 without periodic orientation or proper coloring. On the other hand we show that every quasi-transitive graph $G$ of bounded pathwidth has a periodic proper coloring with $\chi(G)$ colors and a periodic orientation. We relate these problems with techniques and questions from symbolic dynamics and distributed computing and conclude with a number of open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01951v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tara Abrishami, Louis Esperet, Ugo Giocanti, Matthias Hamann, Paul Knappe, R\"ognvaldur G. M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approaches to critical point theory via sequential and parametrized topological complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01980v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Lusternik-Schnirelmann category of a space was introduced to obtain a lower bound on the number of critical points of a $C^1$-function on a given manifold. Related to Lusternik-Schnirelmann category and motivated by topological robotics, the topological complexity (TC) of a space is a numerical homotopy invariant whose topological properties are an active field of research. The notions of sequential and parametrized topological complexity extend the ideas of topological complexity. While the definition of TC is closely related to Lusternik-Schnirelmann category, the connections of sequential and parametrized TC to critical point theory have not been fully explored yet. In this article we apply methods from Lusternik-Schnirelmann theory to establish various lower bounds on numbers of critical points of functions in terms of sequential and parametrized TCs. We carry out several consequences and applications of these bounds, among them a computation of the parametrized TC of the unit tangent bundles of $(4m-1)$-spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01980v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Mescher, Maximilian Stegemeyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite ergodic components for upper probabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02030v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Under the notion of ergodicity of upper probability in the sense of Feng and Zhao (2021) that any invariant set either has capacity $0$ or its complement has capacity 0, we introduce the definition of finite ergodic components (FEC). We prove an invariant upper probability has FEC if and only if it is in the regime that any invariant set has either capacity $0$ or capacity $1$, proposed by Cerreia-Vioglio, Maccheroni, and Marinacci (2016). Furthermore, this is also equivalent to that the eigenvalue $1$ of the Koopman operator is of finite multiplicity, while in the ergodic upper probability regime, as in the classical ergodic probability case, the eigenvalue $1$ of the Koopman operator is simple.
  Additionally, we obtain the equivalence of the law of large numbers with multiple values, the asymptotic independence and the FEC. Furthermore, we apply these to obtain the corresponding results for non-invariant probabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02030v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunrong Feng, Wen Huang, Chunlin Liu, Huaizhong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of critically fixed anti-Thurston maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.10788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2006.10788v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a complete combinatorial classification of critically fixed anti-Thurston maps, i.e., orientation-reversing branched covers of the 2-sphere that fix every critical point. The first step in the proof, and an interesting result in its own right, is a combinatorial classification of critically fixed anti-rational maps as "Schottky maps" associated to certain plane graphs. Both of these classification results heavily rely on an orientation-reversing version of Thurstons's theory, including the canonical decomposition of anti-Thurston maps, which we develop in this paper. Lastly, we give some applications to the global curve attractor and twisting problems, as well as to anti-rational maps with symmetries and to critically fixed anti-polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2006.10788v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Geyer, Mikhail Hlushchanka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birational Kleinian groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.09350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.09350v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we study birational Kleinian groups, i.e.\ groups of birational transformations of complex projective varieties acting in a free, properly discontinuous and cocompact way on an open set of the variety with respect to the usual topology. We obtain a classification in dimension two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.09350v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengyuan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contributions to the Theory of Asymptotically Sectional Hyperbolic Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.12038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.12038v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we make several contributions to the theory of asymptotically sectional-hyperbolic (ASH) flows. First, we prove that every star ASH attractor for a $C^2$ vector field is, in fact, sectional-hyperbolic (SH). Second, we establish that all ASH attractors exhibit the property of entropy flexibility. Additionally, we show that any ASH attractor for three-dimensional vector fields is entropy-expansive and admits periodic orbits. Finally, we provide a lower bound for the growth rate of periodic orbits in an ASH attractor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.12038v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Arbieto, Miguel Pineda, Elias Rego, Kendry J. Vivas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Winding of geodesic rays chosen by a harmonic measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.15232v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove limit theorems for the homological winding of geodesic rays distributed via a harmonic measure on a Gromov hyperbolic space. We obtain applications to the inverse problem for the harmonic measure, and winding statistics for Patterson-Sullivan measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.15232v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timoth\'ee B\'enard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy cascade for the Klein-Gordon lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.07146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.07146v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study analytically the dynamics of a $d$-dimensional Klein-Gordon lattice with periodic boundary conditions, for $d \leq 3$. We consider initial data supported on one low-frequency Fourier mode. We show that, in the continuous approximation, the resonant normal form of the system is given by a small-dispersion nonlinear Schr\"odinger (NLS) equation. By exploiting a result about the growth of Sobolev norms for solutions of small-dispersion NLS, we are able to describe an energy cascade phenomenon for the Klein-Gordon lattice, where part of the energy is transferred to modes associated to higher frequencies. Such phenomenon holds within the time-scale for which we can ensure the validity of the continuous approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.07146v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Pasquali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noninvasive Adaptive Control of a Class of Nonlinear Systems With Unknown Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09806v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Control-based continuation (CBC) is a general and systematic method to explore the dynamic response of a physical system and perform bifurcation analysis directly during experimental tests. Although CBC has been successfully demonstrated on a wide range of systems, rigorous and general approaches to designing a noninvasive controller underpinning the methodology are still lacking. In this paper, a noninvasive adaptive control strategy for a wide class of nonlinear systems with unknown parameters is proposed. We prove that the proposed adaptive control methodology is such that the states of the dynamical system track a reference signal in a noninvasive manner if and only if the reference is a response of the uncontrolled system to an excitation force. Compared to the existing literature, the proposed method does not require any a priori knowledge of some system parameters, does not require a persistent excitation, and is not restricted to linearly-stable systems, facilitating the application of CBC to a much larger class of systems than before. Rigorous mathematical analyses are provided, and the proposed control method is numerically demonstrated on a range of single- and multi-degree-of-freedom nonlinear systems, including a Duffing oscillator with multiple static equilibria. It is especifically shown that the unstable periodic orbits of the uncontrolled systems can be stabilized and reached, noninvasively, in controlled conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09806v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamed Rezaee, Ludovic Renson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry of PCF parameters in spaces of quadratic polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05274v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study algebraic relations among postcritically finite (PCF) parameters in the family $f_c(z) = z^2 + c$. Ghioca, Krieger, Nguyen and Ye proved that an algebraic curve in $\mathbb{C}^2$ contains infinitely many PCF pairs $(c_1, c_2)$ if and only if the curve is special (i.e., the curve is a vertical or horizontal line through a PCF parameter, or the curve is the diagonal). Here we extend this result to subvarieties of $\mathbb{C}^n$ for any $n\geq 2$. Consequently, we obtain uniform bounds on the number of PCF pairs on non-special curves in $\mathbb{C}^2$ and the number of PCF parameters in real algebraic curves in $\mathbb{C}$, depending only on the degree of the curve. We also compute the optimal bound for the general curve of degree $d$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05274v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura DeMarco, Niki Myrto Mavraki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Example of Pathological Foliations in Skew-Product Diffeomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18495v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inspired by examples of Katok and Milnor \cite{Milnor1997}, we construct simple examples of skew-product volume preserving diffeomorphism where the center foliation is pathological in the sense that, there is a full measure set whose intersection with any center leaf contains at most one point. Comparing with other examples in literature, our mechanism for producing such pathological foliation is simple and elementary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18495v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhihong Xia, Peizheng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded geometry for PCF-special subvarieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17343v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For each integer $d\geq 2$, let $M_d$ denote the moduli space of maps $f: \mathbb{P}^1\to \mathbb{P}^1$ of degree $d$. We study the geometric configurations of subsets of postcritically finite (or PCF) maps in $M_d$. A complex-algebraic subvariety $Y \subset M_d$ is said to be PCF-special if it contains a Zariski-dense set of PCF maps. Here we prove that there are only finitely many positive-dimensional irreducible PCF-special subvarieties in $M_d$ with degree $\leq D$. In addition, there exist constants $N = N(D,d)$ and $B = B(D,d)$ so that for any complex algebraic subvariety $X \subset M_d$ of degree $\leq D$, the Zariski closure $\overline{X\cap\mathrm{PCF}}~$ has at most $N$ irreducible components, each with degree $\leq B$. We also prove generalizations of these results for points with small critical height in $M_d(\bar{\mathbb{Q}})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17343v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura DeMarco, Niki Myrto Mavraki, Hexi Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bohr recurrence and density of non-lacunary semigroups of $\mathbb{N}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01353v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A subset $R$ of integers is a set of Bohr recurrence if every rotation on $\mathbb{T}^d$ returns arbitrarily close to zero under some non-zero multiple of $R$. We show that the set $\{k!\, 2^m3^n\colon k,m,n\in \mathbb{N}\}$ is a set of Bohr recurrence. This is a particular case of a more general statement about images of such sets under any integer polynomial with zero constant term. We also show that if $P$ is a real polynomial with at least one non-constant irrational coefficient, then the set $\{P(2^m3^n)\colon m,n\in \mathbb{N}\}$ is dense in $\mathbb{T}$, thus providing a joint generalization of two well-known results, one of Furstenberg and one of Weyl.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01353v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikos Frantzikinakis, Bernard Host, Bryna Kra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic entropy for harmonic measures on singular holomorphic foliations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09793v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathscr{F}=(M,\mathscr{L},E)$ be a Brody-hyperbolic singular holomorphic foliation on a compact complex manifold $M$. Suppose that $\mathscr{F}$ has isolated singularities and that its Poincar\'e metric is complete. This is the case for a very large class of singularities, namely, non-degenerate and saddle-nodes in dimension $2$. Let $\mu$ be an ergodic harmonic measure on $\mathscr{F}$. We show that the upper and lower local hyperbolic entropies of $\mu$ are leafwise constant almost everywhere. Moreover, we show that the entropy of $\mu$ is at least $2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09793v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fran\c{c}ois Bacher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Mathematical Epidemiology and Chemical Reaction Network Theory via Synergies Between Them</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00488v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Our paper reviews some key concepts in chemical reaction network theory and mathematical epidemiology, and examines their intersection, with three goals. The first is to make the case that mathematical epidemiology (ME), and also related sciences like population dynamics, virology, ecology, etc., could benefit by adopting the universal language of essentially non-negative kinetic systems as developed by chemical reaction network (CRN) researchers. In this direction, our investigation of the relations between CRN and ME lead us to propose for the first time a definition of ME models, stated in Open Problem 1. Our second goal is to inform researchers outside ME of the convenient next generation matrix (NGM) approach for studying the stability of boundary points, which do not seem suficiently well known. Last but not least, we want to help students and researchers who know nothing about either ME or CRN to learn them quickly, by offering them a Mathematica package "BootCamp", located at https://github.com/adhalanay/epidemiology_crns, including illustrating notebooks (and certain sections below will contain associated suggested notebooks; however, readers with experience may safely skip the bootcamp). We hope that the files indicated in the titles of various sections will be helpful, though of course improvement is always possible, and we ask the help of the readers for that.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00488v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/e26110936</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Florin Avram, Rim Adenane, Mircea Neagu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endomorphisms of quasi-projective varieties -- towards Zariski dense orbit and Kawaguchi-Silverman conjectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.05339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.05339v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a quasi-projective variety and $f\colon X\to X$ a finite surjective endomorphism. We consider Zariski Dense Orbit Conjecture (ZDO), and Adelic Zariski Dense Orbit Conjecture (AZO). We consider also Kawaguchi-Silverman Conjecture (KSC) asserting that the (first) dynamical degree $d_1(f)$ of $f$ equals the arithmetic degree $\alpha_f(P)$ at a point $P$ having Zariski dense $f$-forward orbit. Assuming $X$ is a smooth affine surface, such that the log Kodaira dimension $\bar{\kappa}(X)$ is non-negative (resp. the \'etale fundamental group $\pi_1^{\text{\'et}}(X)$ is infinite), we confirm AZO, (hence) ZDO, and KSC (when $\operatorname{deg}(f)\geq 2$) (resp. AZO and hence ZDO). We also prove ZDO (resp. AZO and hence ZDO) for every surjective endomorphism on any projective variety with ''larger'' first dynamical degree (resp. every dominant endomorphism of any semiabelian variety).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.05339v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia Jia, Takahiro Shibata, Junyi Xie, De-Qi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Neural Network Identification for Low-Speed Ship Maneuvering Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.06120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.06120v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Several studies on ship maneuvering models have been conducted using captive model tests or computational fluid dynamics (CFD) and physical models, such as the maneuvering modeling group (MMG) model. A new system identification method for generating a low-speed maneuvering model using recurrent neural networks (RNNs) and free running model tests is proposed in this study. We especially focus on a low-speed maneuver such as the final phase in berthing to achieve automatic berthing control. Accurate dynamic modeling with minimum modeling error is highly desired to establish a model-based control system. We propose a new loss function that reduces the effect of the noise included in the training data. Besides, we revealed the following facts - an RNN that ignores the memory before a certain time improved the prediction accuracy compared with the "standard" RNN, and the random maneuver test was effective in obtaining an accurate berthing maneuver model. In addition, several low-speed free running model tests were performed for the scale model of the M.V. Esso Osaka. As a result, this paper showed that the proposed method using a neural network model could accurately represent low-speed maneuvering motions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.06120v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00773-021-00867-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kouki Wakita, Atsuo Maki, Umeda Naoya, Yoshiki Miyauchi, Tohga Shimoji, Dimas M. Rachman, Youhei Akimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretation of generalized Langevin equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.03781v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many real-world systems exhibit ``noisy'' evolution in time; interpreting their finitely-sampled behavior as arising from continuous-time processes (in the It\^o or Stratonovich sense) has led to significant success in modeling and analysis in a wide variety of fields. Yet such interpretation hinges on a fundamental linear separation of randomness from determinism in the underlying dynamics. Here we propose some theoretical systems which resist easy and self-consistent interpretation into this well-defined class of equations, requiring an expansion of the interpretive framework. We argue that a wider class of stochastic differential equations, where evolution depends nonlinearly on a random or effectively-random quantity, may be consistently interpreted and in fact exhibit finite-time stochastic behavior in line with an equivalent It\^o process, at which point many existing numerical and analytical techniques may be used. We put forward a method for this conversion, and demonstrate its use on both a toy system and on a system of direct physical relevance: the velocity of a meso-scale particle suspended in a turbulent fluid. This work enables the theoretical and numerical examination of a wide class of mathematical models which might otherwise be oversimplified due to a lack of appropriate tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.03781v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Sabin-Miller, Daniel M. Abrams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anosov contact metrics, Dirichlet optimization and entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15397v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The first main result of this paper classifies contact 3-manifolds admitting critical metrics, i.e. adapted metrics which are the critical points (of the Dirichlet energy functional. This gives a complete answer to a question raised by Chern-Hamilton in 1984. Secondly, we show that in the case of Anosov contact metrics, the optimization of such energy functional is closely related to Reeb dynamics and can be described in terms of its entropy. We also study the consequences in the curvature realization problem for such contact metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15397v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surena Hozoori</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
