<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 04:00:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Formulations of Furstenberg's $\times 2 \times 3$ conjecture in complex analysis and operator algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Furstenberg's $\times 2 \times 3$ conjecture has remained a central open problem in ergodic theory for over $50$ years, and it serves as the basic test case for a broad class of rigidity phenomena which are believed to hold in number-theoretic dynamics. More recently, two related statements have appeared in the literature: a question about periodic approximation raised by Levit and Vigdorovich in the context of approximate group theory and a periodic equidistribution conjecture formulated by Lindenstrauss. The purpose of this article is to provide equivalent formulations for these three statements in a complex-analytic setting and an operator-algebraic setting, giving nine conjectures grouped into three triples. The complex-analytic conjectures involve so-called Carath\'{e}odory functions on the unit disk that satisfy a certain functional identity, and we find that Furstenberg's conjecture is equivalent to the assertion that every such function is a convex combination of rational functions. The operator-algebraic conjectures involve tracial states on the full group $C^\ast$-algebra of a certain semidirect product, which is related to Baumslag-Solitar groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22701v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Burton, Jane Panangaden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shrinking targets versus recurrence: the quantitative theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22993v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $X = [0,1]$, and let $T:X\to X$ be an expanding piecewise linear map sending each interval of linearity to $[0,1]$. For $\psi:\mathbb N\to\mathbb R_{\geq 0}$, $x\in X$, and $N\in\mathbb N$ we consider the recurrence counting function \[ R(x,N;T,\psi) := \#\{1\leq n\leq N: d(T^n x, x) &lt; \psi(n)\}. \] We show that for any $\varepsilon &gt; 0$ we have \[ R(x,N;T,\psi) = \Psi(N)+O\left(\Psi^{1/2}(N) \ (\log\Psi(N))^{3/2+\varepsilon}\right) \] for $\mu$-almost all $x\in X$ and for all $N\in\mathbb N$, where $\Psi(N):= 2 \sum_{n=1}^N \psi(n)$. We also prove a generalization of this result to higher dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22993v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Levesley, Bing Li, David Simmons, Sanju Velani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic absolutely continuous invariant measures for C^r one-dimensional maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23021v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For r &gt; 1, we show, using the Ledrappier-Young entropy characterization of SRB measures for non-invertible maps, that if a C^r map f of the interval or the circle has its Lyapunov exponent greater than 1/r log ||f ' || $\infty$ on a set E of positive Lebesgue measure, then it admits hyperbolic ergodic invariant measures that are absolutely continuous with respect to the Lebesgue measure. We also show that the basins of these measures cover E Lebesgue-almost everywhere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23021v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Delplanque (LPSM, SU)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symplectic bipotentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23122v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a previous paper, we proposed a symplectic version of Brezis-Ekeland-Nayroles principle based on the concepts of Hamiltonian inclusions and symplectic polar functions. We applied it to the standard plasticity. The object of this work is to extend the previous formalism to non associated plasticity. For this aim, we generalize the concept of bipotential to dynamical systems. The keystone idea is to define a symplectic bipotential. We present a method to build it from a bipotential. Next, we generalize the symplectic Brezis-Ekeland-Nayroles principle to non associated dissipative laws. We apply it to the non associated plasticity and to the unilateral contact law with Coulomb's dry friction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23122v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Harakeh, Michael Ban, G\'ery de Saxc\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Which Meyer sets are regular model sets? A characterization via almost periodicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22536v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 2012, Meyer introduced the notions of generalized almost periodic measure and almost periodic pattern and proved that regular model sets in Euclidean space are almost periodic patterns. Here, we prove the converse in a slightly more general setting. Specifically, we show that a Meyer set in any $\sigma$-compact locally compact abelian group is a regular model set if and only if it is an almost periodic pattern.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22536v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Lenz, Christoph Richard, Nicolae Strungaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust chaos in $\mathbb{R}^n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22563v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We treat $n$-dimensional piecewise-linear continuous maps with two pieces, each of which has exactly one unstable direction, and identify an explicit set of sufficient conditions for the existence of a chaotic attractor. The conditions correspond to an open set within the space of all such maps, allow all $n \ge 2$, and allow all possible values for the unstable eigenvalues in the limit that all stable eigenvalues tend to zero. To prove an attractor exists we use the stable manifold of a fixed point to construct a trapping region; to prove the attractor is chaotic we use the unstable directions to construct an invariant expanding cone for the derivatives of the pieces of the map. We also show the chaotic attractor is persistent under nonlinear perturbations, thus when such an attractor is created locally in a border-collision bifurcation of a general piecewise-smooth system, it persists and is chaotic for an interval of parameter values beyond the bifurcation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22563v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Ghosh, David J. W. Simpson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate Solutions to Optimal Control Problems via a Flexible Mesh and Integrated Residual Transcription</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23037v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose joining a flexible mesh design with an integrated residual transcription in order to improve the accuracy of numerical solutions to optimal control problems. This approach is particularly useful when state or input trajectories are non-smooth, but it may also be beneficial when dynamics constraints are stiff. Additionally, we implement an initial phase that will ensure a feasible solution is found and can be implemented immediately in real-time controllers. Subsequent iterations with warm-starting will improve the solution until optimality is achieved. Optimizing over the mesh node locations allows for discontinuities to be captured exactly, while integrated residuals account for the approximation error in-between the nodal points. First, we numerically show the improved convergence order for the flexible mesh. We then present the feasibility-driven approach to solve control problems and show how flexible meshing and integrated residual methods can be used in practice. The presented numerical examples demonstrate for the first time the numerical implementation of a flexible mesh for an integrated residual transcription. The results show that our proposed method can be more than two times more accurate than conventional fixed mesh collocation for the same computational time and more than three times more accurate for the same problem size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23037v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucian Nita, Eric C. Kerrigan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness of hyperbolic Busemann functions in the Newtonian N-body problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For the N-body problem we prove that any two hyperbolic rays having the same limit shape define the same Busemann function. We localize a region of differentiability for these functions, of which we know that they are viscosity solutions of the stationary Hamilton-Jacobi equation. As a first corollary, we deduce that every hyperbolic motion of the $N$-body problem must become, after some time, a calibrating curve for the Busemann function associated to its limit shape. This implies that every hyperbolic motionof the $N$-body problem is eventually a minimizer, that is, it must contain a geodesic ray of the Jacobi-Maupertuis metric. Since the viscosity solutions of the Hamilton-Jacobi equation are almost everywhere differentiable, we also deduce the generic uniqueness of geodesic rays with a given limit shape without collisions. That is to say, if the limit shape is given, then for almost every initial configuration the geodesic ray is unique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23164v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ezequiel Maderna, Andrea Venturelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performative Control for Linear Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23251v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the framework of performative control, where the policy chosen by the controller affects the underlying dynamics of the control system. This results in a sequence of policy-dependent system state data with policy-dependent temporal correlations. Following the recent literature on performative prediction [21], we introduce the concept of a performatively stable control (PSC) solution. We first propose a sufficient condition for the performative control problem to admit a unique PSC solution with a problem-specific structure of distributional sensitivity propagation and aggregation. We further analyze the impacts of system stability on the existence of the PSC solution. Specifically, for almost surely strongly stable policy-dependent dynamics, the PSC solution exists if the sum of the distributional sensitivities is small enough. However, for almost surely unstable policy-dependent dynamics, the existence of the PSC solution will necessitate a temporally backward decaying of the distributional sensitivities. We finally provide a repeated stochastic gradient descent scheme that converges to the PSC solution and analyze its non-asymptotic convergence rate. Numerical results validate our theoretical analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23251v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songfu Cai, Fei Han, Xuanyu Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eremenko's conjecture, wandering Lakes of Wada, and maverick points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.10256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.10256v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a general technique for realising full closed subsets of the complex plane as wandering sets of entire functions. Using this construction, we solve a number of open problems.
  (1) We construct a counterexample to Eremenko's conjecture, a central problem in transcendental dynamics that asks whether every connected component of the set of escaping points of a transcendental entire function is unbounded.
  (2) We prove that there is a transcendental entire function for which infinitely many Fatou components share the same boundary. This resolves the long-standing problem whether "Lakes of Wada continua" can arise in complex dynamics, and answers the analogue of a question of Fatou from 1920 concerning Fatou components of rational functions.
  (3) We answer a question of Rippon concerning the existence of non-escaping points on the boundary of a bounded escaping wandering domain, that is, a wandering Fatou component contained in the escaping set. In fact we show that the set of such points can have positive Lebesgue measure.
  (4) We give the first example of an entire function having a simply connected Fatou component whose closure has a disconnected complement, answering a question of Boc Thaler.
  In view of (3), we introduce the concept of "maverick points": points on the boundary of a wandering domain whose accumulation behaviour differs from that of internal points. We prove that the set of such points has harmonic measure zero, but that it can nonetheless be rather large. For example, it may have positive planar Lebesgue measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.10256v5</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Mart\'i-Pete, Lasse Rempe, James Waterman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-uniformly hyperbolic endomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.08295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.08295v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show the existence of large $\mathcal C^1$ open sets of area preserving endomorphisms of the two-torus which have no dominated splitting and are non-uniformly hyperbolic, meaning that Lebesgue almost every point has a positive and a negative Lyapunov exponent. The integrated Lyapunov exponents vary continuously with the dynamics in the $\mathcal C^1$ topology and can be taken as far away from zero as desired. Explicit real analytic examples are obtained by deforming linear endomorphisms, including expanding ones. The technique works in nearly every homotopy class and the examples are stably ergodic (in fact Bernoulli), provided that the linear map has no eigenvalue of modulus one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.08295v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Andersson, Pablo D. Carrasco, Radu Saghin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A minimal model for multigroup adaptive SIS epidemics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17639v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a generalization of the adaptive N-Intertwined Mean-Field Approximation (aNIMFA) model studied in \emph{Achterberg and Sensi} \cite{achterbergsensi2022adaptive} to a heterogeneous network of communities. In particular, the multigroup aNIMFA model describes the impact of both local and global disease awareness on the spread of a disease in a network. We obtain results on existence and stability of the equilibria of the system, in terms of the basic reproduction number~$R_0$. Under light constraints, we show that the basic reproduction number~$R_0$ is equivalent to the basic reproduction number of the NIMFA model on static networks. Based on numerical simulations, we demonstrate that with just two communities periodic behaviour can occur, which contrasts the case with only a single community, in which periodicity was ruled out analytically. We also find that breaking connections between communities is more fruitful compared to breaking connections within communities to reduce the disease outbreak on dense networks, but both strategies are viable to networks with fewer links. Finally, we emphasise that our method of modelling adaptivity is not limited to SIS models, but has huge potential to be applied in other compartmental models in epidemiology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17639v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimo A. Achterberg, Mattia Sensi, Sara Sottile</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to split a tera-polynomial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06083v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article presents a new algorithm to compute all the roots of two families of polynomials that are of interest for the Mandelbrot set $\mathcal{M}$ : the roots of those polynomials are respectively the parameters $c\in\mathcal{M}$ associated with periodic critical dynamics for $f_c(z)=z^2+c$ (hyperbolic centers) or with pre-periodic dynamics (Misiurewicz-Thurston parameters). The algorithm is based on the computation of discrete level lines that provide excellent starting points for the Newton method. In practice, we observe that these polynomials can be split in linear time of the degree. This article is paired with a code library [Mandel] that implements this algorithm. Using this library and about 723 000 core-hours on the HPC center Rom\'eo (Reims), we have successfully found all hyperbolic centers of period $\leq 41$ and all Misiurewicz-Thurston parameters whose period and pre-period sum to $\leq 35$. Concretely, this task involves splitting a tera-polynomial, i.e. a polynomial of degree $\sim10^{12}$, which is orders of magnitude ahead of the previous state of the art. It also involves dealing with the certifiability of our numerical results, which is an issue that we address in detail, both mathematically and along the production chain. The certified database is available to the scientific community. For the smaller periods that can be represented using only hardware arithmetic (floating points FP80), the implementation of our algorithm can split the corresponding polynomials of degree $\sim10^{9}$ in less than one day-core. We complement these benchmarks with a statistical analysis of the separation of the roots, which confirms that no other polynomial in these families can be split without using higher precision arithmetic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06083v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francois Vigneron, Nicolae Mihalache</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensions of $\mathcal{KL}$ and Lyapunov Functions for Discrete-time Dynamical System Peaks Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04896v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend two classes of functions classically involved in asymptotic stability analyses for studying a maximization problem on the reachable values of a discrete-time dynamical system. This maximization problem is called a peaks computation problem. The problem is to find a couple composed of an initial state and a time which maximizes a given function over states. The paper focuses on the time component of the optimal solution which is an integer as the time is discrete. We develop a method to provide an upper bound of this integer from a formula which requires a pair of a strictly increasing and continuous function on [0,1] and a scalar in (0,1). A first result proves that the formula provides, in theory, the optimal integer. However, in practice, the computation cannot be so precise. Then, we develop two alternative methods. The first is based on discontinuous and non strictly increasing/decreasing $\mathcal{KL}$-like functions named $\klgen$ functions. We prove that the existence of a $mathcal{KL}_{\rm gen}$ upper bound is equivalent to the existence of a pair of a strictly increasing and continuous function on [0,1] and a scalar in (0,1). The construction of the strictly increasing continuous function from a $mathcal{KL}_{\rm gen}$ function needs an extension of the famous Sontag's lemma. Finally, we construct a new type of Lyapunov functions, called Opt-Lyapunov functions, well designed for our peaks computation problem. Opt-Lyapunov functions are well designed as we establish an equivalence theorem between the existence of an Opt-Lyapunov function and of a pair of a strictly increasing and continuous function on $[0,1]$ and a scalar in (0,1). The construction of a Opt-Lyapunov function from a pair of a strictly increasing and continuous function on [0,1] and a convergent geometric sequence is insipred by the Yoshizawa construction of Lyapunov functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04896v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Assal\'e Adj\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
