<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Equilibrium Stability for Open Zooming Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that for a wide family of open zooming systems and zooming potentials we have equilibrium stability, i.e., the equilibrium states depend continuously on the dynamics and the potential. We consider the open zooming systems with special holes and quite general contractions and zooming potentials with locally H\"older induced potential, which include the H\"older ones. We also prove stability for skew-products with the base being a zooming system like above.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08693v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael A. Bilbao, Eduardo Santana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-compactness and statistical properties for discontinuous systems semi-conjugated to piecewise convex maps with countable branches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08751v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish the quasi-compactness of the transfer operator associated with skew product systems that are semi-conjugate to piecewise convex maps with a countably infinite number of branches. These non-invertible skew products admit discontinuities, with the critical set confined to a countable collection of fibers. Furthermore, we demonstrate that such systems possess an invariant measure whose disintegration along the fibers exhibits bounded variation, a concept introduced and developed in this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08751v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Lucena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential mixing for Hamiltonian shear flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09123v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the advection equation on $\mathbb{T}^2$ with a real analytic and time-periodic velocity field that alternates between two Hamiltonian shears. Randomness is injected by alternating the vector field randomly in time between just two distinct shears. We prove that, under general conditions, these models have a positive top Lyapunov exponent and exhibit exponential mixing. This framework is then applied to the Pierrehumbert model with randomized time and to a model analogous to the Chirikov standard map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09123v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weili Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pace in Concert with Phase: Rate-induced Phase-tipping in Birhythmic Oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study rate-induced phase-tipping (RP-tipping) between two stable limit cycles of a birhythmic oscillator. We say that such an oscillator RP-tips when a time variation of an input parameter preserves the bistability of the limit cycles but induces transitions from one stable limit cycle to the other, causing abrupt changes in the amplitude and frequency of the oscillations. Crucially, these transitions occur when: the rate of change of the input is in a certain interval bounded by critical rate(s), and the system is in certain phases of the cycle.
  We focus on two illustrative examples: the birhythmic van der Pol oscillator and the birhythmic Decroly-Goldbeter glycolysis model, each subjected to monotone and non-monotone shifts in their input parameters. We explain RP-tipping in terms of properties of the autonomous frozen system, including the phase of a cycle and partial basin instability along the parameter path traced by the changing input. We show that RP-tipping can occur as an irreversible one-way transition or as a series of transitions between the stable limit cycles. Finally, we present RP-tipping diagrams showing combinations of the rate and magnitude of parameter shifts and the phase of the oscillation that give rise to this genuine non-autonomous instability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09190v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravi Kumar K, Hassan Alkhayuon, Sebastian Wieczorek, Partha Sharathi Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal response for stochastic differential equations by local kernel perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a random dynamical system on $\mathbb{R}^d$, whose dynamics is defined by a stochastic differential equation. The annealed transfer operator associated with such systems is a kernel operator. Given a set of feasible infinitesimal perturbations $P$ to this kernel, with support in a certain compact set, and a specified observable function $\phi: \mathbb{R}^d \to \mathbb{R}$, we study which infinitesimal perturbation in $P$ produces the greatest change in expectation of $\phi$. We establish conditions under which the optimal perturbation uniquely exists and present a numerical method to approximate the optimal infinitesimal kernel perturbation. Finally, we numerically illustrate our findings with concrete examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09300v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianmarco del Sarto, Stefano Galatolo, Sakshi Jain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unilateral vibration transmission in mechanical systems with bilinear coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Unilateral transmission refers to the scenario in which the waves transmitted through a system remain in pure tension or pure compression. This transmission phenomenon may occur in systems that exhibit different effective elasticity in compression and tension; i.e. bilinear elasticity. We present a computational investigation of unilateral transmission in the steady-state response of harmonically driven mechanical systems with bilinear coupling. Starting with two bilinearly coupled oscillators, we find that breaking the mirror symmetry of the system, in either elastic or inertial properties, facilitates unilateral transmission by allowing it to occur near a primary resonance. This asymmetry also enables nonreciprocal transmission to occur. We then investigate the nonreciprocal dynamics of the system, including linear stability analysis, with a focus on unilateral transmission. We also extend our discussion to a bilinear periodic structure, for which we investigate the influence of the number of units and energy dissipation on unilateral transmission. We report on the existence of stable nonreciprocal unilateral transmission near primary and internal resonances of the system, as well as other nonreciprocal features such as period-doubled and quasiperiodic response characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08726v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Kogani, Behrooz Yousefzadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phototactic Bioconvection in a Rotating Isotropic Porous Medium: Linear Stability Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09078v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the linear stability of phototactic bioconvection in a rotating porous medium under collimated light, incorporating the effects of critical intensity, Darcy number, and Taylor number. Using a mathematical model and the MATLAB Bvp4c solver, the critical Rayleigh number and wavenumber for instability onset are identified. The results reveal that higher Darcy numbers enhance instability, increasing the wavelength of bioconvection patterns, while rotation exerts a stabilizing effect by limiting vertical motion and confining fluid dynamics to the horizontal plane. Additionally, an increase in critical intensity amplifies instability. Furthermore, the study explores the transition between oscillatory and stationary solutions, highlighting the role of rotational dynamics in altering instability modes. These findings provide novel insights into the interplay of phototaxis, rotation, and porous media, advancing the understanding of bioconvective systems with potential applications in environmental engineering, biophysics, and geophysical fluid dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09078v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandeep Kumar, Suneet Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anosov deformations of Barbot representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09107v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct for each conformal structure on a closed orientable surface of genus at least 2 a proper slice in the character variety of representations of the associated surface group into SL(3,R) that belongs to the Barbot component and show that the corresponding representations are Borel Anosov. We describe a fibered geometric structure in the space of full flags associated with these representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09107v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Bronstein, Colin Davalo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Design with Dynamic Mode Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09490v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a computationally efficient method for the automation of inverse design in science and engineering. Based on simple least-square regression, the underlying dynamic mode decomposition algorithm can be used to construct a low-rank subspace spanning multiple experiments in parameter space. The proposed inverse design dynamic mode composition (ID-DMD) algorithm leverages the computed low-dimensional subspace to enable fast digital design and optimization on laptop-level computing, including the potential to prescribe the dynamics themselves. Moreover, the method is robust to noise, physically interpretable, and can provide uncertainty quantification metrics. The architecture can also efficiently scale to large-scale design problems using randomized algorithms in the ID-DMD. The simplicity of the method and its implementation are highly attractive in practice, and the ID-DMD has been demonstrated to be an order of magnitude more accurate than competing methods while simultaneously being 3-5 orders faster on challenging engineering design problems ranging from structural vibrations to fluid dynamics. Due to its speed, robustness, interpretability, and ease-of-use, ID-DMD in comparison with other leading machine learning methods represents a significant advancement in data-driven methods for inverse design and optimization, promising a paradigm shift in how to approach inverse design in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09490v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunpeng Zhu, Liangliang Cheng, Anping Jing, Hanyu Huo, Ziqiang Lang, Bo Zhang, J. Nathan Kutz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Erd\H{o}s's integer dilation approximation problem and GCD graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09539v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{A}\subset\mathbb{R}_{\geqslant1}$ be a countable set such that $\limsup_{x\to\infty}\frac{1}{\log x}\sum_{\alpha\in\mathcal{A}\cap[1,x]}\frac{1}{\alpha}&gt;0$. We prove that, for every $\varepsilon&gt;0$, there exist infinitely many pairs $(\alpha, \beta)\in \mathcal{A}^2$ such that $\alpha\neq \beta$ and $|n\alpha-\beta| &lt;\varepsilon$ for some positive integer $n$. This resolves a problem of Erd\H{o}s from 1948. A critical role in the proof is played by the machinery of GCD graphs, which were introduced by the first author and by James Maynard in their work on the Duffin--Schaeffer conjecture in Diophantine approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09539v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitris Koukoulopoulos, Youness Lamzouri, Jared Duker Lichtman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Eigenfunctions of the Transfer Operator for the Dyson model in a field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09588v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The recent works \cite{EFMV2024} and \cite{JOP2023} have studied the spectral properties of the Dyson model in the absence of an external field. This paper is a continuation of \cite{EFMV2024} and aims to bridge the gap in the literature by investigating the Dyson model in a field.\\ In this paper, we prove that, for high temperatures or strong magnetic fields, there exists a non-negative, integrable (with respect to the unique half-line Gibbs measure) eigenfunction of the transfer operator for the Dyson model if $\alpha\in(\frac 3 2,2]$. However, unlike in the zero-magnetic-field case, this eigenfunction is not continuous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09588v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mirmukhsin Makhmudov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathcal{S}$-adic characterization of minimal dendric shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.00333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.00333v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dendric shifts are defined by combinatorial restrictions of the extensions of the words in their languages. This family generalizes well-known families of shifts such as Sturmian shifts, Arnoux-Rauzy shifts and codings of interval exchange transformations. It is known that any minimal dendric shift has a primitive $\mathcal{S}$-adic representation where the morphisms in $\mathcal{S}$ are positive tame automorphisms of the free group generated by the alphabet. In this paper we give an $\mathcal{S}$-adic characterization of this family by means of two finite graphs. As an application, we are able to decide whether a shift space generated by a uniformly recurrent morphic word is (eventually) dendric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.00333v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>France Gheeraert, Julien Leroy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pointwise convergence of some continuous-time polynomial ergodic averages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16780v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the pointwise convergence of centain continuous-time polynomial ergodic averages. Our approach is based on the topological models of measurable flows. One of the main results of this paper is as follows: Let $a\in \mathbb{R}$, $Q\in \mathbb{R}[t]$ with $\text{deg}\ Q\ge 2$. Let $(X,\mathcal{X},\mu, (T^{t})_{t\in \mathbb{R}})$ and $(X,\mathcal{X},\mu, (S^{t})_{t\in \mathbb{R}})$ be two measurable flows. Then for any $f_1, f_2, g\in L^{\infty}(\mu)$, the limit \begin{equation*} \lim\limits_{M\to\infty}\frac{1}{M}\int_{0}^{M}f_1(T^{t}x)f_2(T^{at}x)g(S^{Q(t)}x)dt \end{equation*} exists for $\mu$-a.e. $x\in X$. In particular, we are able to build a pointwise ergodic theorem involving geodesic flow and horocycle flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16780v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Huang, Song Shao, Rongzhong Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy bounds for Glass networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04435v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose that chaotic Glass networks (a class of piecewise-linear Ordinary Differential Equations) are good candidates for the design of true random number generators. A Glass network design has the advantage of involving only standard Boolean logic gates. Furthermore, an already chaotic (deterministic) system combined with random ``jitter'' due to thermal noise can be used to generate random bit sequences in a more robust way than noisy limit-cycle oscillators. Since the goal is to generate bit sequences with as large a positive entropy as possible, it is desirable to have a theoretical method to assess the irregularity of a large class of networks. We develop a procedure here to calculate good upper bounds on the entropy of a Glass network, by means of symbolic representations of the continuous dynamics. Our method improves on a result by Farcot (2006), and allows in principle for an arbitrary level of precision by refinements of the estimate, and we show that in the limiting case, these estimates converge to the true entropy of the symbolic system corresponding to the continuous dynamics. As a check on the method, we demonstrate for an example network that our upper bound after only a few refinement steps is very close to the entropy estimated from a long numerical simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04435v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin W. Wild, Roderick Edwards</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring localization in nonlinear oscillator systems through network-based predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05497v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Localized vibrations, arising from nonlinearities or symmetry breaking, pose a challenge in engineering, as the resulting high-amplitude vibrations may result in component failure due to fatigue. During operation, the emergence of localization is difficult to predict, partly because of changing parameters over the life cycle of a system. This work proposes a novel, network-based approach to detect an imminent localized vibration. Synthetic measurement data is used to generate a functional network, which captures the dynamic interplay of the machine parts, complementary to their geometric coupling. Analysis of these functional networks reveals an impending localized vibration and its location. The method is demonstrated using a model system for a bladed disk, a ring composed of coupled nonlinear Duffing oscillators. Results indicate that the proposed method is robust against small parameter uncertainties, added measurement noise, and the length of the measurement data samples. The source code for this work is available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05497v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlotte Geier (Hamburg University of Technology), Norbert Hoffmann (Hamburg University of Technology, Imperial College London),  .</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bifurcation for families of Ahlfors island maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04180v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We extend Ma\~n\'e-Sad-Sullivan and Lyubich's equivalent characterization of stability to the setting of Ahlfors island maps, which include notably all meromorphic maps. As a consequence we also obtain the density of $J$-stability for finite type maps in the sense of Epstein.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04180v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Astorg, Anna Miriam Benini, Nuria Fagella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimension of diagonal self-affine measures with exponentially separated projections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17378v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $ \mu $ be a self-affine measure associated with a diagonal affine iterated function system (IFS) $ \Phi = \{ (x_{1}, \ldots, x_{d}) \mapsto ( r_{i, 1}x_{1} + t_{i,1}, \ldots, r_{i,d}x_{d} + t_{i,d}) \}_{i\in\Lambda} $ on $ \mathbb{R}^{d} $ and a probability vector $ p = (p_{i})_{i\in\Lambda}$. For $ 1 \leq j \leq d $, denote the $ j $-th the Lyapunov exponent by $ \chi_{j} := \sum_{i\in\Lambda} - p_{i} \log | r_{i,j} |$, and define the IFS induced by $ \Phi $ on the $j$-th coordinate as $ \Phi_{j} := \{ x \mapsto r_{i,j}x + t_{i,j}\}_{i\in\Lambda}$. We prove that if $ \chi_{j_{1}} \neq \chi_{j_{2}} $ for $ 1 \leq j_{1} &lt; j_{2} \leq d $, and $ \Phi_{j}$ is exponentially separated for $ 1 \leq j \leq d $, then the dimension of $ \mu $ is the minimum of $ d $ and its Lyapunov dimension. This confirms a conjecture of Rapaport by removing the additional assumption that the linear parts of the maps in $ \Phi $ are contained in a 1-dimensional subgroup. One of the main ingredients of the proof involves disintegrating $ \mu $ into random measures with convolution structure. In the course of the proof, we establish new results on dimension and entropy increase for these random measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17378v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhou Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global linearization without hyperbolicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07708v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a proof of an extension of the Hartman-Grobman theorem to nonhyperbolic but asymptotically stable equilibria of vector fields. Moreover, the linearizing topological conjugacy is (i) defined on the entire basin of attraction if the vector field is complete, and (ii) a $C^{k\geq 1}$ diffeomorphism on the complement of the equilibrium if the vector field is $C^k$ and the underlying space is not $5$-dimensional. We also show that the $C^k$ statement in the $5$-dimensional case is equivalent to the $4$-dimensional smooth Poincar\'{e} conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07708v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew D. Kvalheim, Eduardo D. Sontag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness and global attractor for wave equation with nonlinear damping and super-cubic nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06208v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study investigates a semilinear wave equation characterized by nonlinear damping $g(u_t) $ and nonlinearity $f(u)$. First, the well-posedness of weak solutions across broader exponent ranges for $g$ and $f$ is established, by utilizing a priori space-time estimates. Moreover, the existence of a global attractor in the phase space $H^1_0(\Omega)\times L^2(\Omega)$ is obtained. Furthermore, it is proved that this global attractor is regular, implying that it is a bounded subset of $(H^2(\Omega)\cap H^1_0(\Omega))\times H^1_0(\Omega)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06208v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cuncai Liu, Fengjuan Meng, Xiaoying Han, Chang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal Models in Biology and Life Sciences: Sources, Developments, and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14651v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nonlocality is important in realistic mathematical models of physical and biological systems when local models fail to capture the essential dynamics and interactions that occur over a range of distances. This review illustrates different nonlocal mathematical models applied to biology and life sciences. The major focus has been given to sources, developments, and applications of such models. Among other things, a systematic discussion has been provided for the conditions of pattern formations in biological systems of population dynamics. Special attention has also been given to nonlocal interactions on networks, network coupling and integration, including brain dynamics models that provide an important tool to understand neurodegenerative diseases better. In addition, we have discussed nonlocal modelling approaches for cancer stem cells and tumor cells that are widely applied in the cell migration processes, growth, and avascular tumors in any organ. Furthermore, the discussed nonlocal continuum models can go sufficiently smaller scales, including nanotechnology, where classical local models often fail to capture the complexities of nanoscale interactions, applied to build biosensors to sense biomaterial and its concentration. Piezoelectric and other smart materials are among them, and these devices are becoming increasingly important in the digital and physical world that is intrinsically interconnected with biological systems. Additionally, we have reviewed a nonlocal theory of peridynamics, which deals with continuous and discrete media and applies to model the relationship between fracture and healing in cortical bone, tissue growth and shrinkage, and other areas increasingly important in biomedical and bioengineering applications. Finally, we provided a comprehensive summary of emerging trends and highlighted future directions in this rapidly expanding field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14651v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swadesh Pal, Roderick Melnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit theorems for a strongly irreducible product of independent random matrices under optimal moment assumptions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05751v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\nu$ be a probability distribution over the semi-group of square matrices of size $d\ge2$. We assume that $\nu$ is proximal, strongly irreducible and that $\nu^{*n}\{0\}=0$ for all $n$. We consider the sequence $\overline\gamma_n:=\gamma_0\cdots\gamma_{n-1}$ for $(\gamma_k)_{k}$ independent of distribution law $\nu$. Let $s_1\ge s_2\ge\dots s_d$ be the singular values given by the Cartan projection. We show that $(\log\frac{s_1}{s_2}(\overline{\gamma}_n))_{n}$, escapes to infinity linearly and satisfies exponential large deviations inequalities below its escape rate. This is an extension the simplicity of the top Lyapunov exponent result, proven by Guivarc'h and Raugi under a first moment assumption. We also show that the image of a generic line by $\overline{\gamma}_n$ as well as its eigenspace of maximal eigenvalue both converge to the same random line $l^\infty$ at an exponential speed.
  If we moreover assume that $\nu$ is supported on the group of invertible matrices and that the push-forward distribution $N_*\nu$ is $\mathrm{L}^p$ for $N:g\mapsto\log\|g\|\|g^{-1}\|$ and for some $p&gt;0$, then we show that $-\log d(l^\infty,H)$ is uniformly $\mathrm{L}^p$ for all proper subspace $H\subset\mathbb{R}^d$. For $p=1$, we moreover show that the rescaled logarithm of each coefficient of $\overline{\gamma}_n$ almost surely converges to the top Lyapunov exponent. This is an extension of results by Benoist and Quint which were themselves improvements of historic results by Guivarc'h, Lepage and Raugi, first proven under exponential moment assumptions.
  To prove these results, we do not rely on the existence of the stationary measure nor on the existence of the Lyapunov exponent. Instead we describe an effective way to group the i.i.d. factors into i.i.d. random words that are aligned in the Cartan decomposition. We moreover have an explicit control over the moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05751v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel P\'eneau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rhythmic sharing: A bio-inspired paradigm for zero-shot adaptation and learning in neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08644v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The brain can rapidly adapt to new contexts and learn from limited data, a coveted characteristic that artificial intelligence algorithms have struggled to mimic. Inspired by oscillatory rhythms of the mechanical structures of neural cells, we developed a learning paradigm that is based on oscillations in link strengths and associates learning with the coordination of these oscillations. We find that this paradigm yields rapid adaptation and learning in artificial neural networks. Link oscillations can rapidly change coordination, endowing the network with the ability to sense subtle context changes in an unsupervised manner. In other words, the network generates the missing contextual tokens required to perform as a generalist AI architecture capable of predicting dynamics in multiple contexts. Oscillations also allow the network to extrapolate dynamics to never-seen-before contexts. These capabilities make our learning paradigm a powerful starting point for novel models of learning and cognition. Furthermore, learning through link coordination is agnostic to the specifics of the neural network architecture, hence our study opens the door for introducing rapid adaptation and learning capabilities into leading AI models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08644v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoony Kang, Wolfgang Losert</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
