<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the cyclicity of persistent hyperbolic polycycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we consider families of smooth vector fields having a persistent polycycle with $n$ hyperbolic saddles. We derive the asymptotic expansion of the return map associated to the polycycle, determining explicitly its leading terms. As a consequence, explicit conditions on the leading terms allow us to determine the cyclicity of such polycycles. We then apply our results to study the cyclicity of a polycycle of a model with applications in Game Theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07225v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Queiroz Arakaki, Paulo Santana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fans, phans and pans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07267v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A fan is an arcwise-connected continuum, which is hereditarily unicoherent and has exactly one ramification point. Many of the known examples of fans were constructed as 1-dimensional continua that are unions of arcs which intersect in exactly one point. Borsuk proved in 1954 that each fan is a 1-dimensional continuum which is the union of arcs intersecting in exactly one point. But it is not yet known if this property is equivalent to being a fan. In this paper, we show that under two additional assumptions, every such union of arcs is a fan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07267v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iztok Bani\v{c}, Goran Erceg, Ivan Jeli\'c, Judy Kennedy, Van Nall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monotonicity of the Liouville entropy along the Ricci flow on surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using geometric and microlocal methods, we show that the Liouville entropy of the geodesic flow of a closed surface of non-constant negative curvature is strictly increasing along the normalized Ricci flow. This affirmatively answers a question of Manning from 2004. More generally, we obtain an explicit formula for the derivative of the Liouville entropy along arbitrary area-preserving conformal perturbations in this setting. In addition, we show the mean root curvature, a purely geometric quantity which is a lower bound for the Liouville entropy, is also strictly increasing along the normalized Ricci flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07290v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karen Butt, Alena Erchenko, Tristan Humbert, Daniel Mitsutani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Koopman Meets Hamilton and Jacobi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07346v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a connection between the spectral theory of the Koopman operator and the solution of the Hamilton Jacobi (HJ) equation. The HJ equation occupies a central place in systems theory, and its solution is of interest in various control problems, including optimal control, robust control, and input-output analysis. A Hamiltonian dynamical system can be associated with the HJ equation and the solution of the HJ equation can be extracted from the Hamiltonian system in the form of Lagrangian submanifold. One of the main contributions of this paper is to show that the Lagrangian submanifolds can be obtained using the spectral analysis of the Koopman operator. We present two different procedures for the approximation of the HJ solution. We utilize the spectral properties of the Koopman operator associated with the uncontrolled dynamical system and Hamiltonian systems to approximate the HJ solution. We present a convex optimization-based computational framework with convergence analysis for approximating the Koopman eigenfunctions and the Lagrangian submanifolds. Our solution approach to the HJ equation using Koopman theory provides for a natural extension of results from linear systems to nonlinear systems. We demonstrate the application of this work for solving the optimal control problem. Finally, we present simulation results to validate the paper's main findings and compare them against linear quadratic regulator and Taylor series based approximation controllers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07346v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Umesh Vaidya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the variety of solutions of 1-dimensional nonlinear eigenvalue problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07548v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Second order nonlinear eigenvalue problems are considered for which the spectrum is an interval. The boundary conditions are of Robin and Dirichlet type. The shape and the number of solutions are discussed by means of a phase plane analysis. A new type of asymmetric solutions are discovered. Some numerical illustrations are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07548v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catherine Bandle, Simon Stingelin, Alfred Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Period-Doubling Cascades Invariants: Braided Routes To Chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By a classical result of Kathleen Alligood and James Yorke we know that as we isotopically deform a map $f:ABCD\to\mathbb{R}^2$ to a Smale horseshoe map we should often expect the dynamical complexity to increase via a period--doubling route to chaos. Inspired by this fact and by how braids force the existence of complex dynamics, in this paper we introduce three topological invariants that describe the topology of period--doubling routes to chaos. As an application, we use our methods to ascribe symbolic dynamics to perturbations of the Shilnikov homoclinic scenario and to study the dynamics of the Henon map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07572v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eran Igra, Valerii Sopin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper semi-continuity of metric entropy for $\mathcal{C}^{1,\alpha}$ diffeomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that for $\mathcal{C}^{1,\alpha}$ diffeomorphisms on a compact manifold $M$ with ${\rm dim} M\leq 3$, if an invariant measure $\mu$ is a continuity point of the sum of positive Lyapunov exponents, then $\mu$ is an upper semi-continuity point of the entropy map. This gives several consequences, such as the upper-semi continuity of dimensions of measures for surface diffeomorphisms. Furthermore, we know the continuity of dimensions for measures of maximal entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07746v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiyi Luo, Dawei Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Variants of Shadowing of Free Semigroup Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that for finitely generated free semigroup actions the average shadowing property, the weak asymptotic average shadowing property, the mean ergodic shadowing property, the almost asymptotic average shadowing property, the asymptotic average shadowing property and the $M_{\alpha}$-shadowing property for every $\alpha\in (0,1)$, are equivalent. This gives an affirmative answer to an open question asked in Question 10.3 [M. Kulczycki, D. Kwietniak, P. Oprocha, On almost specification and average shadowing properties, Fundamenta Mathematicae, 224 (2014)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07799v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pramod Kumar Das, Priyabrata Bag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase diagram for intermittent maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the phase diagram for potentials in the space of H\"older continuous functions of a given exponent and for the dynamical system generated by a Pomeau--Manneville, or intermittent, map. There is always a phase where the unique Gibbs state exhibits intermittent behavior. It is the only phase for a specific range of values of the H\"older exponent. For the remaining values of the H\"older exponent, a second phase with stationary behavior emerges. In this case, a co-dimension 1 submanifold separates the intermittent and stationary phases. It coincides with the set of potentials at which the pressure function fails to be real-analytic. We also describe the relationship between the phase transition locus, (persistent) phase transitions in temperature, and ground states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07864v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Coronel, Juan Rivera-Letelier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equidistribution in 2-Nilpotent Polish Groups and triple restricted sumsets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to establish a Ratner-type equidistribution theorem for orbits on homogeneous spaces associated with \(2\)-nilpotent locally compact Polish groups under the action of a countable discrete abelian group. We apply this result to establish the existence of triple restricted sumsets in subsets of positive density in arbitrary countable discrete abelian groups, subject to a necessary finiteness condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07865v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Ackelsberg, Asgar Jamneshan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing Universal Causal Deep Learning Models: The Case of Infinite-Dimensional Dynamical Systems from Stochastic Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.13300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.13300v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Several non-linear operators in stochastic analysis, such as solution maps to stochastic differential equations, depend on a temporal structure which is not leveraged by contemporary neural operators designed to approximate general maps between Banach space. This paper therefore proposes an operator learning solution to this open problem by introducing a deep learning model-design framework that takes suitable infinite-dimensional linear metric spaces, e.g. Banach spaces, as inputs and returns a universal \textit{sequential} deep learning model adapted to these linear geometries specialized for the approximation of operators encoding a temporal structure. We call these models \textit{Causal Neural Operators}. Our main result states that the models produced by our framework can uniformly approximate on compact sets and across arbitrarily finite-time horizons H\"older or smooth trace class operators, which causally map sequences between given linear metric spaces. Our analysis uncovers new quantitative relationships on the latent state-space dimension of Causal Neural Operators, which even have new implications for (classical) finite-dimensional Recurrent Neural Networks. In addition, our guarantees for recurrent neural networks are tighter than the available results inherited from feedforward neural networks when approximating dynamical systems between finite-dimensional spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.13300v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Galimberti, Anastasis Kratsios, Giulia Livieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new construction of counterexamples to the bounded orbit conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17243v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The bounded orbit conjecture says that every homeomorphism on the plane with each of its orbits being bounded must have a fixed point. Brouwer's translation theorem asserts that the conjecture is true for orientation preserving homeomorphisms, but Boyles' counterexample shows that it is false for the orientation reversing case. In this paper, we give a more comprehensible construction of counterexamples to the conjecture. Roughly speaking, we construct an orientation reversing homeomorphisms $f$ on the square $J^2=[-1, 1]^2$ with $\omega(x, f)=\{(-1. 1), (1, 1)\}$ and $\alpha(x, f)=\{(-1. -1), (1, -1)\}$ for each $x\in (-1, 1)^2$. Then by a semi-conjugacy defined by pushing an appropriate part of $\partial J^2$ into $(-1, 1)^2$, $f$ induces a homeomorphism on the plane, which is a counterexample.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17243v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiehua Mai, Enhui Shi, Kesong Yan, Fanping Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensions of orthogonal projections of typical self-affine sets and measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04000v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $T_1,\ldots, T_m$ be a family of $d\times d$ invertible real matrices with $\|T_i\|&lt;1/2$ for $1\leq i\leq m$. For ${\bf a}=(a_1,\ldots, a_m)\in {\Bbb R}^{md}$, let $\pi^{\bf a}\colon \Sigma=\{1,\ldots, m\}^{\Bbb N}\to {\Bbb R}^d$ denote the coding map associated with the affine IFS $\{T_ix+a_i\}_{i=1}^m$, and let $K^{\bf a}$ denote the attractor of this IFS. Let $W$ be a linear subspace of ${\Bbb R}^d$ and $P_W$ the orthogonal projection onto $W$. We show that for $\mathcal L^{md}$-a.e.~${\bf a}\in {\Bbb R}^{md}$, the Hausdorff and box-counting dimensions of $P_W(K^{\bf a})$ coincide and are determined by the zero point of a certain pressure function associated with $T_1,\ldots, T_m$ and $W$. Moreover, for every ergodic $\sigma$-invariant measure $\mu$ on $\Sigma$ and for $\mathcal L^{md}$-a.e.~${\bf a}\in {\Bbb R}^{md}$, the local dimensions of $(P_W\pi^{\bf a})_*\mu$ exist almost everywhere, here $(P_W\pi^{\bf a})_*\mu$ stands for the push-forward of $\mu$ by $P_W\pi^{\bf a}$. However, as illustrated by examples, $(P_W\pi^{\bf a})_*\mu$ may not be exact dimensional for $\mathcal L^{md}$-a.e.~${\bf a}\in {\Bbb R}^{md}$. Nevertheless, when $\mu$ is a Bernoulli product measure, or more generally, a supermultiplicative ergodic $\sigma$-invariant measure, $(P_W\pi^{\bf a})_*\mu$ is exact dimensional for $\mathcal L^{md}$-a.e.~${\bf a}\in {\Bbb R}^{md}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04000v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>De-Jun Feng, Yu-Hao Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry and Local Recovery of Global Minima of Two-layer Neural Networks at Overparameterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.00508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.00508v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Under mild assumptions, we investigate the geometry of the loss landscape for two-layer neural networks in the vicinity of global minima. Utilizing novel techniques, we demonstrate: (i) how global minima with zero generalization error become geometrically separated from other global minima as the sample size grows; and (ii) the local convergence properties and rate of gradient flow dynamics. Our results indicate that two-layer neural networks can be locally recovered in the regime of overparameterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.00508v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leyang Zhang, Yaoyu Zhang, Tao Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-periodic response solutions of nonlinear plate models with nonlocal energy damping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02628v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Response solutions are quasi-periodic ones with the same frequency as the forcing term. The present work is devoted to constructing response solutions for $d$-dimensional nonlinear plate models with nonlocal energy
  damping, which are closely related to damping phenomena in flight structures.
  For such models, the main characteristic is that the dissipation rate depends on the energy strength. By considering a small parameter $\epsilon$ in the domain excluding the origin and imposing a small quasi-periodic forcing with a Diophantine frequency vector, we demonstrate the persistence of the corresponding response solution. We provide an alternative approach to the contraction mapping principle (cf. [7, 33]) through a combination of reduction together with the Nash--Moser iteration technique. The reason behind this approach lies in the derivative losses caused by the nonlocal nonlinearity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02628v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bochao Chen, Yixian Gao, Zhaosheng Feng, Huiying Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform property $\Gamma$ and the small boundary property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09808v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that, for a free action $\alpha \colon G \curvearrowright X$ of a countably infinite discrete amenable group on a compact metric space, the small boundary property is implied by uniform property $\Gamma$ of the Cartan subalgebra $(C(X) \subseteq C(X) \rtimes_\alpha G)$. The reverse implication has been demonstrated by Kerr and Szab\'o for free actions, from which we obtain that these two conditions are equivalent. We moreover show that, if $\alpha$ is also minimal, then almost finiteness of $\alpha$ is implied by tracial $\mathcal{Z}$-stability of the subalgebra $(C(X) \subseteq C(X) \rtimes_\alpha G)$. The reverse implication is due to Kerr, resulting in the equivalence of these two properties as well. As an application, we prove that if $\alpha \colon G \curvearrowright X$ and $\beta \colon H \curvearrowright Y$ are free actions and $\alpha$ has the small boundary property, then $\alpha \times \beta \colon G \times H \curvearrowright X \times Y$ has the small boundary property. An analogous permanence property is obtained for almost finiteness in case $\alpha$ and $\beta$ are free minimal actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09808v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigoris Kopsacheilis, Hung-Chang Liao, Aaron Tikuisis, Andrea Vaccaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lipschitz-free spaces and dual representations of group actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15208v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study selected topics about induced actions of topological groups $G$ on Lipschitz-free spaces $\mathcal{F}(M)$ coming from isometric actions on pointed metric spaces $M$. In particular, induced dynamical $G$-systems (under weak-star topology and the dual actions) on the dual $\mathrm{Lip_0} (M)=\mathcal{F}(M)^*$ and on the bidual $\mathcal{F}(M)^{**}$. Two such natural examples are the so-called metric compactification of isometric $G$-spaces for a pointed metric space and the Gromov $G$-compactification of a bounded metric $G$-space. One of the results asserts that for every bounded stable metric $G$-space $(M,d,\mathbf{0})$ the corresponding metric $G$-compactification $\widehat{M}$ is a weakly almost periodic $G$-flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15208v4</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Megrelishvili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Velocities in the Toda Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11407v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the Toda lattice $(\boldsymbol{p}(t); \boldsymbol{q}(t))$ at thermal equilibrium, meaning that its variables $(p_i)$ and $(e^{q_i-q_{i+1}})$ are independent Gaussian and Gamma random variables, respectively. This model can be thought of a dense collection of many ``quasiparticles'' that act as solitons. We establish a law of large numbers for the trajectory of these quasiparticles, showing that they travel with approximately constant velocities, which are explicit. Our proof is based on a direct analysis of the asymptotic scattering relation, an equation (proven in previous work of the author) that approximately governs the dynamics of quasiparticles locations. This makes use of a regularization argument that essentially linearizes this relation, together with concentration estimates for the Toda lattice's (random) Lax matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11407v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amol Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
