<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 02:40:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Stable components for gradient-like diffeomorphisms of torus inducing matrix $\begin{pmatrix} -1 &amp; -1\cr 1&amp; 0\end{pmatrix}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19643v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An isotopy between two diffeomorphisms means the existence of an arc connecting them in the space of diffeomorphisms. Among such arcs there are so-called stable arcs, which do not qualitatively change under small perturbations. In the present paper we consider a set of gradient-like diffeomorphisms f of 2-torus whose induced isomorphism given by a matrix $\begin{pmatrix} -1 &amp; -1\cr 1&amp; 0\end{pmatrix}$. We prove that the set of such diffeomorphisms is decomposed into four stable components. Moreover, we establish that two diffeomorphisms under consideration are stably connected if and only if they have the same number of fixed sinks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19643v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Baranov, O. Pochinka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A classification of pseudo-Anosov homeomorphisms I: the geometric type is a complete conjugacy invariant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Every pseudo-Anosov homeomorphism $f$ admits infinitely many Markov partitions. A \textit{geometric Markov partition} is a Markov partition $\mathcal{R}$ in which each rectangle is equipped with a vertical orientation. To each pair $(f, \mathcal{R})$, consisting of a pseudo-Anosov homeomorphism $f$ and a geometric Markov partition $\mathcal{R}$, there is a naturally associated combinatorial object called its \textit{geometric type} $\mathbf{T}(f, \mathcal{R})$. We prove, using symbolic dynamics, that two pseudo-Anosov homeomorphisms are topologically conjugate via an orientation-preserving homeomorphism if and only if they admit geometric Markov partitions with the same geometric type. This result lays the groundwork for the algorithmic classification we will develop in subsequent work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19774v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Inti Cruz Diaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canonical order spectra in topological dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a compact topological dynamical system $(X,f)$, we associate to every pair $(x,y)$ a canonical order-theoretic invariant: its emergent order spectrum $\Omega(x,y)$. We first prove that one can always build families of nested $\varepsilon_n$-chains ($\varepsilon_n \to 0$) whose linear orders are eventually compatible under inclusion. $\Omega(x,y)$ is then defined as the set of countable linear order-types obtained as direct limits of order-compatible nested $\varepsilon_n$-chains (empty if and only if $x$ is not in chain relation with $y$). The order spectrum is independent of the compatible metric and of the vanishing sequence, and invariant under topological conjugacy. Moreover, it reveals tight connections with the underlying dynamics and discriminates recurrence phenomena that are indiscernible via Conley's decomposition or Auslander's prolongational hierarchy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19777v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Ciavattini, A. Della Corte, C. Lucamarini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primitive Geometric Markov Partitions for pseudo-Anosov Homeomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $f$ be a pseudo-Anosov homeomorphism on a closed, oriented surface. We give an effective construction of Markov partitions for $f$ based on a simple combinatorial criterion deciding when an immersed graph bounds a Markov partition. This yields an explicit algorithm: from a point $z$ at the intersection of stable and unstable separatrices of a singularity of $f$, and a sufficiently large integer $n$, it produces a partition $\mathcal{R}(f,z,n)$.
  Applying the algorithm to the first intersection points of $f$ we produces the set of primitive Markov partitions. We prove the existence of an integer $n(f)$, the compatibility order of $f$, depending only on the conjugacy class of $f$, such that $\mathcal{R}(f,z,n)$ exists for all $n\ge n(f)$ and all first intersection points $z$. Each geometric Markov partition $\mathcal{R}$ has an associated geometric type $T(f,\mathcal{R})$, extending the incidence matrix; it result the geometric type is constant along orbits of primitive partitions, and for $n\ge n(f)$ the set $\mathcal{T}(f,n)$ of primitive geometric types is finite.
  By \cite{IntiThesis}, this family is canonical: two maps are topologically conjugate by an orientation-preserving homeomorphism iff they share the compatibility order and the primitive geometric types for some $n\ge n(f)$. The types in $\mathcal{T}(f,n(f))$ are minimal and are the canonical Markov partitions of $f$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19792v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Inti Cruz Diaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian systems and monotone twist mappings for braids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1986, Moser showed that for a given area-preserving map, there exists a Hamiltonian system that realizes it on the Poincar\'e section. Using his technique, we show that for any braid, there exists a Hamiltonian system whose orbits realize the given braid. In particular, when the braid is pseudo-Anosov, so is the Poincar\'e map of the corresponding Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19927v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuika Kajihara, Mitsuru Shibayama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Structure of Chaotic Attractors in FitzHugh-Rinzel model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chaotic bursting behaviors have been observed by many authors in neural dynamics mainly in the transition between different kinds of bursting behavior. As a well-known three-dimensional ODEs model with various bursting solutions, the FitzHugh-Rinzel model has been considered in this paper. The structure of the strange attractor that appears in chaotic transitions of this model was investigated by introducing a stochastic approach to uncover the transition mechanism. To portray this idea the attractor of the dynamical system can be partitioned into some regions and a discrete evolution that is inspired by the flow between them is sketched. A suitable Markov chain has been associated with the strange attractor based on partition selected by the recognizable regions of the attractor. Then the entropy rate of the Markov chain and the topological entropy of dynamical systems are compared to decide if the associated Markov chain should be modified or not. Furthermore, the differences between entropies guide us to uncover some changes in the shape of the attractor including some new regions which play important roles in the chaotic behavior of our system. It can be also ensured with the help of Lempel-Ziv quantity that the estimated entropy rate is reliable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19944v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammadreza Razvan, Sheida Shahidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology of 4-manifolds that admit non-singular flows with saddle orbits of the same index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies regular topological flows $f^t$ defined on closed {topological} manifolds $M^n$. The chain recurrent set of such a flow consists of a finite number of topologically hyperbolic fixed points and periodic orbits. Like their smooth analogs -- Morse-Smale flows -- regular flows possess a continuous Morse-Bott function that decreases outside the chain recurrent set and is constant on the chain components of the flow. This circumstance leads to a close connection between such flows and the topology of the carrying manifold. In particular, the ambient manifold for non-singular flows (regular flows without fixed points), by the Poincare-Hopf formula, has a zero Euler characteristic. The latter property is a criterion for a manifold $M^n$ to admit a non-singular flow in all dimensions except dimension $n=3$. Thus, in higher dimensions, any odd-dimensional manifold admits a non-singular flow, and the list of even-dimensional manifolds is quite broad; at the very least, it includes all manifolds of the form $M^{n-1}\times\mathbb S^1$, where $M^{n-1}$ is any closed $(n-1)$-manifold.
  A surprising result of the present paper is the proof of the fact that in dimension 4, all this variety of carrying spaces can only be achieved if the flow has saddle orbits of different Morse indices. Specifically, for dimensional reasons, the Morse index of a saddle orbit of a non-singular flow $f^t: M^4 \to M^4$ can only take two values, 1 or 2. We prove that non-singular 4-flows with saddle orbits of the same Morse index exist only on skew or direct products of the 3-sphere and the circle, i.e., $M^4\cong\mathbb S^3\tilde\times\,\mathbb S^1$ or $M^4\cong\mathbb S^3\times\mathbb S^1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19968v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Galkin, O. Pochinka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Efficient Nonlinear Microscopic Dynamical Model for Autonomous and Electric Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20054v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article proposes a nonlinear microscopic dynamical model for autonomous electric vehicles (A-EVs) that considers battery energy efficiency in the car-following dynamics. The model builds upon the Optimal Velocity Model (OVM), with the control term based on the battery dynamics to enable thermally optimal and energy-efficient driving. We rigorously prove that the proposed model achieves lower energy consumption compared to the Optimal Velocity Follow-the-Leader (OVFL) model. Through numerical simulations, we validate the analytical results on the energy efficiency. We additionally investigate the stability properties of the proposed model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20054v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuneil Yeo, Jaewoong Lee, Scott Moura, Maria Laura Delle Monache</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A billiard table close to an ellipse is deformationally spectrally rigid among dihedrally symmetric domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we show that any dihedrally symmetric deformation with constant length spectrum of a domain close to an ellipse is obtained by translating and rotating the initial domain. A domain is said to be dihedrally symmetric if it is axis-symmetric and centrally symmetric. In this result, the topology set on domains' boundaries is a finitely smooth Whitney topology depending on the ellipse we are considering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20062v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corentin Fierobe, Vadim Kaloshin, Alfonso Sorrentino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure-Preserving Coupling and Decoupling of Port-Hamiltonian Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The port-Hamiltonian framework is a structure-preserving modeling approach that preserves key physical properties such as energy conservation and dissipation. When subsystems are modeled as port-Hamiltonian systems (pHS) with linearly related inputs and outputs, their interconnection remains port-Hamiltonian. This paper introduces a systematic method for transforming coupled port Hamiltonian ordinary differential equations systems (pHODE) into a single monolithic formulation, and for decomposing a monolithic system into weakly coupled subsystems. The monolithic representation ensures stability and structural integrity, whereas the decoupled form enables efficient distributed simulation via operator splitting or dynamic iteration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20150v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Ehrhardt, Michael G\"unther, Daniel \v{S}ev\v{c}ovi\v{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the convergence of boundary points for hyperbolic inner functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20502v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a hyperbolic inner function \( f\colon \mathbb{D}\to\mathbb{D} \) with Denjoy--Wolff point \( p\in\partial\mathbb{D} \), it is well known that almost every point \( \xi\in \partial\mathbb{D} \) converges to \( p \) under iteration of the radial extension \( f^*\colon\partial\mathbb{D}\to\partial\mathbb{D} \). We provide explicit bounds for the rate of this convergence in terms of the angular derivative, holding almost surely. Our results also cover the case where the Denjoy--Wolff point is a singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20502v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Jov\'e, Mateo Menc\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying seizure generation mechanisms: A critical transitions framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding how the brain switches from normal activity to an epileptic seizure is essential for improving seizure therapy, yet the underlying mechanisms remain largely unknown. In particular, seizure onset can be described as a critical transition (CT), but there is no consensus on whether (i) bifurcation-induced, (ii) noise-induced, or (iii) bifurcation/noise-induced CTs are responsible. To clarify this, we develop a versatile CT-classification framework that can be applied to seizures in both animals and humans. First, we identify a canonical mathematical model which displays CTs that closely resemble voltage recordings of real seizures and can be of the three types mentioned above. We then identify distinctive properties of each CT-type in the model's output and use them to train a machine learning CT-type classifier. Finally, we apply the model-trained classifier to voltage recordings from epileptic rodents. We find that the largest proportion of analysed seizures are classified as noise-induced CTs. This challenges the conventional view that seizures are predominantly bifurcation-induced and could inform new therapeutic strategies for seizures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20522v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Flynn, Cian McCafferty, Klaus Lehnertz, Fran\c{c}ois David, Vincenzo Crunelli, William P. Marnane, Sebastian Wieczorek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backward Julia sets for a class of p-adic H\'enon like maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20535v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we study the backward filled Julia sets of a class of $p$-adic polynomial maps $f:\mathbb{Q}_p^2\longrightarrow \mathbb{Q}_p^2$ defined by $f(x,y)=(xy+c,x)$, where $c\in\mathbb{Q}_p$ is a $p$-adic number. In particular, if $|c|\leq 1$, then we proved that the backward filled Julia set of $f$ is a bounded subset in $\mathbb{Z}_p^2$. On the other hand, if $|c|&gt; 1$, then we prove that the backward filled Julia set of $f$ is an unbounded set and has infinity Haar measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20535v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'efferson L. R. Bastos, Danilo Caprio, Oyran Raizzaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogeneous potentials, Lagrange's identity and Poisson geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19903v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Lagrange identity expresses the second derivative of the moment of inertia of a system of material points through kinetic energy and homogeneous potential energy, from which follows the Jacobi well-known result on the instability of a system of gravitating bodies. In this work, it is proven that if a Hamiltonian system satisfies the Lagrange identity, then it possesses additional tensor invariants that are not expressed through the basic invariants existing for all Hamiltonian systems. A new class of Hamiltonian systems with inhomogeneous potentials is considered, which also possess similar additional tensor invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19903v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Tsiganov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-projective K3 surfaces with real or Salem multiplication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19970v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We determine the Hodge endomorphism algebras of non-projective complex K3 surfaces (and more generally, hyperk\"ahler manifolds). We show that they are either totally real fields or number fields generated by Salem numbers. This is unlike the projective case, where the endomorphism fields are either totally real or CM. We also develop precise existence criteria and explore the relations to number theory and dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19970v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eva Bayer-Fluckiger, Bert van Geemen, Matthias Sch\"utt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded Fatou components of cosine functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20010v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We constructed Yoccoz puzzle for cosine functions $f(z)=ae^z+be^{-z}$ with bounded post-critical set, and proved that a Fatou component is a Jordan domains if it is bounded and is not eventually a Siegal disk. We proved that $f$ is renormalizable if a critical value escapes to $\infty$. Finally, we obtained the local connectivity of $J(f)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20010v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiyuan Qiu, Lingrui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable rank one in nonnuclear crossed products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We initiate an investigation into the local structure of simple nonnuclear C$^*$-crossed products by showing that stable rank one is generic within two natural classes of minimal actions of free groups on the Cantor set. The arguments also apply to some other free product groups. Our approach is inspired by Li and Niu's stable rank one theorem in the amenable setting and also yields a streamlined argument in that case, along with a generalization to product actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20132v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jamie Bell, Shirly Geffen, David Kerr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinearly preconditioned gradient flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20370v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a continuous-time dynamical system which arises as the limit of a broad class of nonlinearly preconditioned gradient methods. Under mild assumptions, we establish existence of global solutions and derive Lyapunov-based convergence guarantees. For convex costs, we prove a sublinear decay in a geometry induced by some reference function, and under a generalized gradient-dominance condition we obtain exponential convergence. We further uncover a duality connection with mirror descent, and use it to establish that the flow of interest solves an infinite-horizon optimal-control problem of which the value function is the Bregman divergence generated by the cost. These results clarify the structure and optimization behavior of nonlinearly preconditioned gradient flows and connect them to known continuous-time models in non-Euclidean optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20370v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Oikonomidis, Alexander Bodard, Jan Quan, Panagiotis Patrinos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonuniform-Grid Markov Chain Approximation of Continuous Processes with Time-Linear Moments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20416v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a method to approximate continuous-time, continuous-state stochastic processes by a discrete-time Markov chain defined on a nonuniform grid. Our method provides exact moment matching for processes whose first and second moments are linear functions of time. In particular, we show that, under certain conditions, the transition probabilities of a Markov chain can be chosen so that its first two moments match prescribed linear functions of time. These conditions depend on the grid points of the Markov chain and the coefficients of the linear mean and variance functions. Our proof relies on two recurrence relations for the expectation and variance across time. This approach enables simulation-based numerical analysis of continuous processes while preserving their key characteristics. We illustrate its efficacy by approximating continuous processes describing heat diffusion and geometric Brownian motion (GBM). For heat diffusion, we show that the heat profile at a set of points can be investigated by embedding those points inside the nonuniform grid of our Markov chain. For GBM, numerical simulations demonstrate that our approach, combined with suitable nonuniform grids, yields accurate approximations, with consistently small empirical Wasserstein-1 distances at long time horizons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20416v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Do Hyun Kim, Ahmet Cetinkaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Presymplectic and Symmetry Reduced Formulation of the Maxwell Vlasov System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20538v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a unified geometric formulation of the Maxwell-Vlasov system using the infinite-dimensional Skinner-Rusk (SR) formalism. In this framework, particles and fields are treated simultaneously within a single presymplectic manifold, and the Gotay-Nester-Hinds algorithm recovers the full Maxwell-Vlasov equations as the compatibility conditions of a single variational system. The hierarchy of constraints -- including Vlasov advection, Gauss and Faraday laws, and the electromagnetic gauge structure -- arises naturally from the presymplectic geometry of the SR formalism.
  Reduction by the diffeomorphism group of phase space produces a reduced presymplectic manifold whose dynamics reproduces both the Euler-Poincare formulation for the Vlasov sector and the Marsden-Weinstein/Morrison-Greene Lie-Poisson Hamiltonian structure. We further extend the construction to equilibria that partially break the relabeling symmetry, obtaining a translated SR system that yields an effective symplectic linearization, clarifies the appearance of Goldstone-type neutral modes, and provides a geometric foundation for the energy-Casimir method.
  Finally, we incorporate external antenna fields into this setting by introducing affine Hamiltonian controls and establishing a theory of controlled symmetry breaking within the reduced SR framework. This leads to controlled Lie-Poisson equations for plasma-antenna coupling and a geometric mechanism for stabilization through Casimir shaping and symmetry-selective forcing. The resulting picture provides a single presymplectic structure that unifies Lagrangian, Hamiltonian, gauge, reduction, and control-theoretic aspects of the Maxwell-Vlasov system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20538v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Colombo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuity of fractal dimensions in conservative generic Markov and Lagrange dynamical spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.07819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.07819v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\varphi_0$ be a smooth conservative diffeomorphism of a compact surface $S$ and let $\Lambda_0$ be a transitive horseshoe of $\varphi_0$. Given a smooth real function $f$ defined in $S$ and a small smooth conservative perturbation $\varphi$ of $\varphi_0$, let $L_{\varphi, f}$ and $M_{\varphi, f}$ be respectively the Lagrange and Markov spectra associated to the hyperbolic continuation $\Lambda(\varphi)$ of the horseshoe $\Lambda_0$ and $f$. We show that for generic choices of $\varphi$ and $f$, the Hausdorff dimension of the sets $L_{\varphi, f}\cap (-\infty, t)$ and $M_{\varphi, f}\cap (-\infty, t)$ are equal and determine a continuous function as $t\in \mathbb{R}$ varies; generalizing then the Cerqueira-Matheus-Moreira theorem to horseshoes with arbitrary Hausdorff dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.07819v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davi Lima, Carlos Gustavo Moreira, Christian Camilo Silva Villamil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High entropy measures on the space of lattices with escape of mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16840v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For any diagonal element $a$ with two eigenvalues, we construct a sequence of $a$-invariant probability measures on the space of unimodular lattices with high entropy but converging to the zero measure. This extends the result of Kadyrov [Ergodic Theory Dynam. Systems, 32(1) (2012)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16840v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taehyeong Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Return Times Theorem, Auto-Correlation and Sequences with an Empty Fourier-Bohr Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07453v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper explores the proof by J. Bourgain, H. Furstenberg, Y. Katznelson and D.S. Ornstein of their return times theorem [2] and lights a corner in it regarding the role of auto-correlation. As for pointwise convergence, this was already observed in [5], and here we exploit the opportunity to write down the proof. This yields a more intrinsic characterization of the sequences satisfying the pointwise theorem. Then we proceed and obtain a characterization linked to auto-correlation also to sequences satisfying the mean theorem - by that theorem those were already known to be exactly the sequences with an empty Fourier-Bohr spectrum. Some further investigation is done and examples are provided regarding generic sequences satisfying the pointwise theorem for which the measure on the circle that the auto-correlation function represents (by Fourier transform) is not atomless, and also regarding the existence of sequences that satisfy the mean theorem but not the pointwise one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07453v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matan Tal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the dimension of pullback attractors in recurrent neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11357v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recurrent neural networks trained via the reservoir computing paradigm have demonstrated remarkable success in learning and reconstructing attractors from chaotic systems, often replicating quantities such as Lyapunov exponents and fractal dimensions. It has recently been conjectured that this is because the reservoir computer embeds the dynamics of the chaotic system in its state space before learning. This conjecture has been established for reservoir computers with linear activation functions and remains open for more general reservoir systems. In this work, we employ a non-autonomous dynamical systems approach to establish an upper bound for the box-counting dimension of the pullback attractor, a subset of the reservoir state space that is approximated during training and prediction phases. We prove that the box-counting dimension of the pullback attractor is bounded above by the box-counting dimension of the space of input sequences with respect to the product topology. In particular, for input sequences originating from an Nin-dimensional smooth dynamical system or their generic continuously differentiable observations, the box-counting dimension of the pullback attractor is bounded above by Nin. The results obtained here highlight the fact that, while a reservoir computer may possess a very high-dimensional state space, it exhibits effective low-dimensional dynamics. Our findings also partly explain why reservoir computers are successful in tasks such as attractor reconstruction and the computation of dynamic invariants like Lyapunov exponents and fractal dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11357v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammed Fadera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piecewise Recursive Sequences with Adaptive Thresholds : Boundary Convergence and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19605v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study discrete-time dynamical systems that switch between different evolution rules based on thresholds that themselves adapt over time. Specifically, we analyze the coupled recursion $a_{n+1} = f(a_n)$ if $a_n \leq c_n$ and $a_{n+1} = g(a_n)$ if $a_n &gt; c_n$, where the threshold evolves according to $c_{n+1} = h(a_n, c_n)$. By transforming the system into triangular coordinates, we map the problem to a piecewise-smooth system with a fixed switching boundary. We derive explicit local stability criteria based on the lower-triangular structure of the associated Jacobians and establish a ``common-limit constraint'': we prove that any convergent orbit that switches regimes infinitely often must converge to a limit where the state and threshold coincide. To demonstrate the framework's utility, we develop an asset-pricing model where investor sentiment follows a ``trailing-stop'' rule. We characterize the parameter regions for market stability versus bubble formation and numerically extend the analysis to coupled markets, illustrating how adaptive thresholds can facilitate the propagation of instability and contagion across financial networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19605v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Slimane Alaoui Soulimani Valenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical tests of formulae for volume enclosed by flux surfaces of integrable magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01957v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Numerical tests of volume formulae are presented to compute efficiently the volume enclosed between flux surfaces for integrable 3D vector fields with various degrees of symmetry. In the process, a new case is proposed and tested.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01957v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/math13233772</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Martinez-del-Rio, Robert S. MacKay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Systems Models for Market Evolution: A Mechanistic Alternative to Autoregressive Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06778v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel approach to modeling market dynamics using ordinary differential equations that explicitly incorporates product competitiveness and consumer behavior. Our framework treats market segments as interacting populations in a dynamical system analogous to predator-prey models, where competitive advantages drive market share transitions through mechanistic modeling of market flows including new product adoption, refresh cycles, and obsolescence dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06778v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aparna Komarla, Max Hill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-time consensus in a compromise process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01024v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A compromise process describes the evolution of opinions through binary interactions. Opinions are real numbers, and at each step, two randomly selected agents reach a compromise by averaging their pre-interaction opinions. We prove that if the number $N$ of agents is a power of two, then consensus emerges after a finite number of compromise events with probability one; otherwise, consensus cannot be reached in a finite number of steps, provided the initial opinions are in a general position. The number of steps required to reach consensus is random for $N=2^k$ with $k\geq 2$. We prove that the smallest number of steps is $k\cdot 2^{k-1}$ when the initial opinions are in a general position. For $N=4$, we determine the distribution of the number of steps. In particular, we show that it has a purely exponential tail and compute all cumulants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01024v3</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. L. Krapivsky, A. Yu. Plakhov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
