<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ergodicity Of Partially Hyperbolic Endomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05620v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that for volume preserving, partially hyperbolic, center bunched endomorphisms with constant Jacobian, essential accessibility implies ergodicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05620v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andy Hammerlindl, Audrey Tyler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of sequences with minimal maximal pattern complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2002, Kamae and Zamboni introduced maximal pattern complexity and determined that any aperiodic sequence must have maximal pattern complexity at least $2k$. In 2006, Kamae and Rao examined the maximal pattern complexity of sequences over larger alphabets and showed that sequences which have maximal pattern complexity less than $\ell k$, for $\ell$ the size of the alphabet, must have some periodic structure. In this paper, we investigate the structure of sequences of low maximal pattern complexity over $\ell$ letters where $\liminf\limits\limits_{k \to \infty} p_{\alpha}^*(k) - 3k = -\infty$. In addition, we show that the minimal maximal pattern complexity of an aperiodic sequence which uses all $\ell$ letters is $p_{\alpha}^*(k) = 2k + \ell -2$, and give an exact structure for aperiodic sequences with this maximal pattern complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05627v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Casey Schlortt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonance properties and chaotic dynamics of a three-dimensional discrete logistic ecological system within the neighborhoods of bifurcation points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we delve into the dynamical properties of a class of three-dimensional logistic ecological models. By using the complete discriminant theory of polynomials, we first give a topological classification for each fixed point and investigate the stability of corresponding system near the fixed points. Then employing the bifurcation and normal form theory, we discuss all possible codimension-1 bifurcations near the fixed points, i.e., transcritical, flip, and Neimark-Sacker bifurcations, and further prove that the system can undergo codimension-2 bifurcations, specifically 1:2, 1:3, 1:4 strong resonances and weak resonance Arnold tongues. Additionally, chaotic behaviors in the sense of Marotto are rigorously analyzed. Numerical simulations are conducted to validate the theoretical findings and illustrate the complex dynamical phenomena identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05737v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujiang Chen, Lin Li, Lingling Liu, Zhiheng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of complex spectra and eigenfunctions of transfer and Koopman operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Complex spectra of transfer and Koopman operators describe rotational motion in dynamical systems. A particularly relevant situation in applications is where the rotation speed depends on the position in the phase space. We consider a canonical model of such dynamics in the presence of small noise, and provide precise characterisations of the eigenspectrum and eigenfunctions of the corresponding transfer operators. Further, we study the limiting behaviour of the eigenspectrum and eigenfunctions in the zero-noise limit, including their quadratic and linear response. Our results clarify the structure of transfer and Koopman operator eigenspectra, and provide new interpretations for applications. Our theorems on support localisation of the eigenfunctions yield simple algorithms to detect the existence and phase-space location of approximately cyclic motion with distinct periods. Our response results demonstrate that information on the cycle periods and their locations determined by the operator eigendata is largely insensitive to the noise level. We believe the mechanisms creating the eigendata apply more broadly and enhance our understanding of approximate cycle detection in dynamical systems with operator methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05770v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matheus M Castro, Gary Froyland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Globalizing manifold-based reduced models for equations and data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the very few mathematically rigorous nonlinear model reduction methods is the restriction of a dynamical system to a low-dimensional, sufficiently smooth, attracting invariant manifold. Such manifolds are usually found using local polynomial approximations and, hence, are limited by the unknown domains of convergence of their Taylor expansions. To address this limitation, we extend local expansions for invariant manifolds via Pad\'e approximants, which re-express the Taylor expansions as rational functions for broader utility. This approach significantly expands the range of applicability of manifold-reduced models, enabling reduced modeling of global phenomena, such as large-scale oscillations and chaotic attractors of finite element models. We illustrate the power of globalized manifold-based model reduction on several equation-driven and data-driven examples from solid mechanics and fluid mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05876v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B\'alint Kasz\'as, George Haller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local rigidity of group actions of isometries on compact Riemannian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we consider perturbations of isometries on a compact Riemannian manifold $M$. We investigate the smooth (resp. analytic) rigidity phenomenon of groups of these isometries. As a particular case, we prove that if a finite family of smooth (resp. analytic) small enough perturbations is simultaneously conjugate to the family of isometries via a finitely smooth diffeomorphism, then it is simultaneously smoothly (resp. analytically) conjugate to it whenever the family of isometries satisfies a Diophantine condition. Our results generalize the rigidity theorems of Arnold, Herman, Yoccoz, Moser, etc. about circle diffeomorphisms which are small perturbations of rotations as well as Fisher-Margulis's theorem on group actions satisfying Kazhdan's property (T).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05884v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurent Stolovitch, Zhiyan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Siegel-Radon transforms of transverse dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend Helgason's classical definition of a generalized Radon transform, defined for a pair of homogeneous spaces of an lcsc group $G$, to a broader setting in which one of the spaces is replaced by a possibly non-homogeneous dynamical system over $G$ together with a suitable cross section. This general framework encompasses many examples studied in the literature, including Siegel (or $\Theta$-) transforms and Marklof-Str\"ombergsson transforms in the geometry of numbers, Siegel-sVeech transforms for translation surfaces, and Zak transforms in time-frequency analysis.
  Our main applications concern dynamical systems $(X, \mu)$ in which the cross section is induced from a separated cross section. We establish criteria for the boundedness, integrability, and square-integrability of the associated Siegel-Radon transforms, and show how these transforms can be used to embed induced $G$-representations into $L^p(X, \mu)$ for appropriate values of $p$. These results apply in particular to hulls of approximate lattices and certain "thinnings" thereof, including arbitrary positive density subsets in the amenable case.
  In the special case of cut-and-project sets, we derive explicit formulas for the dual transforms, and in the special case of the Heisenberg group we provide isometric embedding of Schr\"odinger representations into the $L^2$-space of the hulls of positive density subsets of approximate lattices in the Heisenberg group by means of aperiodic Zak transforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05980v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Bj\"orklund, Tobias Hartnick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Dynamical Systems with the Spectral Exterior Calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06061v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a data-driven framework for learning dynamical systems on compact Riemannian manifolds based on the spectral exterior calculus (SEC). This approach represents vector fields as linear combinations of frame elements constructed using the eigenfunctions of the Laplacian on smooth functions, along with their gradients. Such reconstructed vector fields generate dynamical flows that consistently approximate the true system, while being compatible with the nonlinear geometry of the manifold. The data-driven implementation of this framework utilizes embedded data points and tangent vectors as training data, along with a graph-theoretic approximation of the Laplacian. In this paper, we prove the convergence of the SEC-based reconstruction in the limit of large data. Moreover, we illustrate the approach numerically with applications to dynamical systems on the unit circle and the 2-torus. In these examples, the reconstructed vector fields compare well with the true vector fields, in terms of both pointwise estimates and generation of orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06061v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suddhasattwa Das, Dimitrios Giannakis, Yanbing Gu, Joanna Slawinska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond $0$ and $\infty$: A solution to the Barge Entropy Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.11133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2105.11133v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the entropy conjecture of M. Barge from 1989: for every $r\in [0,\infty]$ there exists a pseudo-arc homeomorphism $h$, whose topological entropy is $r$. Until now all pseudo-arc homeomorphisms with known entropy have had entropy $0$ or $\infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2105.11133v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan P. Boro\'nski, Jernej \v{C}in\v{c}, Piotr Oprocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-classification for flows on two-tori</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18847v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the classification of real-analytic vector fields on the two-torus up to orbital topological equivalence does not admit a complete numerical invariant that is a Borel function. Moreover, smooth vector fields that are difficult to classify appear in generic smooth 7-parameter families. In dimension 2, this improves the recent result of Gorodetski and Foreman (arXiv:2206.09322) for non-classifiability of smooth diffeomorphisms up to continuous conjugacy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18847v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nataliya Goncharuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two billiard domains whose billiard maps are Lazutkin conjugates are the same</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19550v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper demonstrates that two billiards whose billiard maps share the same expression in Lazutkin coordinates are isometric. Moreover, two conjugate billiard maps must be conjugated via a diffeomorphism that is tangent to a Lazutkin-type change of coordinates up to order 1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19550v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corentin Fierobe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong universality, recurrence, and analytic P-ideals in dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01131v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a dynamical system $(X,T)$ and a family $\mathsf{I}\subseteq \mathcal{P}(\omega)$ of "small" sets of nonnegative integers, a point $x \in X$ is said to be $\mathsf{I}$-strong universal if for each $y \in X$ there exists a subsequence $(T^nx: n \in A)$ of its orbit which is convergent to $y$ and, in addition, the set of indexes $A$ is "not small," that is, $A\notin \mathsf{I}$. An analoguous definition is given for $\mathsf{I}$-strong recurrence. In this work, we provide several structural properties and relationships between $\mathsf{I}$-strong universality, $\mathsf{I}$-strong recurrence, and the corresponding ordinary notions of $\mathsf{I}$-universality and $\mathsf{I}$-recurrence.
  As applications, we provide sufficient conditions which ensure the equivalence between the above notions and the property that each nonempty open set contains some cluster point of some orbit. In addition, we show that if $T$ is a homomorphism on a Fr\'{e}chet space $X$ and there exists a dense set of vectors with null orbit, then for each $y \in X$ the set of all vectors $x \in X$ such that $\lim_{n \in A}T^nx=y$ for some $A\subseteq \omega$ with nonzero upper asymptotic density is either empty or comeager.
  In the special case of linear dynamical systems on Banach spaces with a dense set of uniformly recurrent vectors, we obtain that $T$ is upper frequently hypercyclic if and only if there exists a hypercyclic vector $x \in X$ for which $\lim_{n \in A}T^nx=0$ for some $A\subseteq \omega$ with nonzero upper asymptotic density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01131v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Leonetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform property $\Gamma$ and the small boundary property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09808v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that, for a free action $\alpha \colon G \curvearrowright X$ of a countably infinite discrete amenable group on a compact metric space, the small boundary property is implied by uniform property $\Gamma$ of the Cartan subalgebra $(C(X) \subseteq C(X) \rtimes_\alpha G)$. The reverse implication has been demonstrated by Kerr and Szab\'o for free actions, from which we obtain that these two conditions are equivalent. We moreover show that, if $\alpha$ is also minimal, then almost finiteness of $\alpha$ is implied by tracial $\mathcal{Z}$-stability of the subalgebra $(C(X) \subseteq C(X) \rtimes_\alpha G)$. The reverse implication is due to Kerr, resulting in the equivalence of these two properties as well. As an application, we prove that if $\alpha \colon G \curvearrowright X$ and $\beta \colon H \curvearrowright Y$ are free actions and $\alpha$ has the small boundary property, then $\alpha \times \beta \colon G \times H \curvearrowright X \times Y$ has the small boundary property. An analogous permanence property is obtained for almost finiteness in case $\alpha$ and $\beta$ are free minimal actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09808v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigoris Kopsacheilis, Hung-Chang Liao, Aaron Tikuisis, Andrea Vaccaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
