<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS</link>
    <description>math.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 05:01:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Tail Decay for Stationary Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show on complete metric spaces a polynomial tail decay for stationary measures of contracting on average generating measures. Our result applies for example to self-similar or self-affine measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00086v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Kittle, Constantin Kogler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite Time Hyperbolic Coordinates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define finite-time hyperbolic coordinates, describe their geometry, and prove various results on both their convergence as the time scale increases, and on their variation in the state space. Hyperbolic coordinates reframe the classical paradigm of hyperbolicity: rather than define a hyperbolic dynamical system in terms of a splitting of the tangent space into stable and unstable subspaces, we define hyperbolicity in terms of the co-eccentricity of the map. The co-eccentricity describes the distortion of unit circles in the tangent space under the differential of the map. Finite-time hyperbolic coordinates have been used to demonstrate the existence of SRB measures for the Henon map; our eventual goal is to both elucidate these techniques and to extend them to a broad class of nonuniformly and singular hyperbolic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00291v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Luzzatto, Dominic Veconi, Khadim War</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensibility and denseness of periodic semigroup actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study periodic points and finitely supported invariant measures for continuous semigroup actions. Introducing suitable notions of periodicity in both topological and measure-theoretical contexts, we analyze the space of invariant Borel probability measures associated with these actions. For embeddable semigroups, we establish a direct relationship between the extensibility of invariant measures to the free group on the semigroup and the denseness of finitely supported invariant measures. Applying this framework to shift actions on the full shift, we prove that finitely supported invariant measures are dense for every left amenable semigroup that is residually a finite group and for every finite-rank free semigroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00312v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raimundo Brice\~no, \'Alvaro Bustos-Gajardo, Miguel Donoso-Echenique</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling car-following dynamics with stochastic input-state-output port-Hamiltonian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00370v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this contribution, we introduce a general class of car-following models with an input-state-output port-Hamiltonian structure. We derive stability conditions and long-term behavior of the finite system with periodic boundaries and quadratic interaction potential by spectral analysis and using asymptotic properties of multivariate Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes. The uncontrolled dynamics exhibit instability and random collective behavior under stochastic perturbations. By implementing an open-loop speed control, the system stabilizes and weakly converges to Gaussian limit distributions. The convergence is unconditional for constant speed control. However, a stability condition arises for the closed-loop system where the speed control acts as a dynamic feedback depending on the distance ahead. The results are illustrated by numerical simulations. Interestingly, only the closed-loop system is able to reproduce, at least transiently, realistic stop-and-go behavior that can be resolved using the Hamiltonian component of the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00370v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Ackermann, Matthias Ehrhardt, Thomas Kruse, Antoine Tordeux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dense uniform Li-Yorke chaos for linear operators on a Banach space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper focuses on the dense uniform Li-Yorke chaos for linear operators on a Banach space. Some sufficient conditions and equivalent conditions are established under which the dynamical system is densely uniformly Li-Yorke chaotic. It is shown that there are plenty of densely uniformly Li-Yorke chaotic operators. For unilateral backward weighted shifts and bilateral backward weighted shifts on $\ell^p$, it is shown that Li-Yorke chaos is equivalent to dense uniform Li-Yorke chaos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00424v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinsheng Wang, Jian Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms and topological invariants for dynamic systems. II. Discrete Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct algorithms and topological invariants that allow us to distinguish the topological type of a surface, as well as functions and vector fields for their topological equivalence. In the first part (arXiv:2501.15657), we discused basic concepts of diferential topology. In the second part we discus the main discrete topological structures used in the topological theory of dynamic systems: simplicial complexes, regular SW-complexes, Euler characteristic and homology groops, Morse-Smale complexes and handle decomposition of manifolds, Poincare rotation index of vector field, discrete Morse function and vector fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00506v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandr Prishlyak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite codimension stability of invariant surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00898v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Following recent work of T.~Alazard and C.~Shao on applications of para-differential calculus to smooth conjugacy and stability problems for Hamiltonian systems, we prove finite codimension stability of invariant surfaces (in finite differentiability classes) of flat geodesic flows on translation surfaces. The result is also based on work of the author on the cohomological equation for translation flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00898v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Forni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity and Toeplitz systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00917v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to study measure-theoretical rigidity and partial rigidity for classes of Cantor dynamical systems including Toeplitz systems and enumeration systems. We use Bratteli diagrams to control invariant measures that are produced in our constructions. This leads to systems with desired properties. Among other things, we show that there exist Toeplitz systems with zero entropy which are not partially measure-theoretically rigid with respect to any of its invariant measures. We investigate enumeration systems defined by a linear recursion, prove that all such systems are partially rigid and present an example of an enumeration system which is not measure-theoretically rigid. We construct a minimal $\mathcal{S}$-adic Toeplitz subshift which has countably infinitely many ergodic invariant probability measures which are rigid for the same rigidity sequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00917v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henk Bruin, Olena Karpel, Piotr Oprocha, Silvia Radinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equilibrium Moment Analysis of It\^o SDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stochastic differential equations have proved to be a valuable governing framework for many real-world systems which exhibit ``noise'' or randomness in their evolution. One quality of interest in such systems is the shape of their equilibrium probability distribution, if such a thing exists. In some cases a straightforward integral equation may yield this steady-state distribution, but in other cases the equilibrium distribution exists and yet that integral equation diverges. Here we establish a new equilibrium-analysis technique based on the logic of finite-timestep simulation which allows us to glean information about the equilibrium regardless -- in particular, a relationship between the raw moments of the equilibrium distribution. We utilize this technique to extract information about one such equilibrium resistant to direct definition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00918v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Sabin-Miller, Daniel M. Abrams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded-Confidence Models of Multi-Dimensional Opinions with Topic-Weighted Discordance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00284v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: People's opinions on a wide range of topics often evolve over time through their interactions with others. Models of opinion dynamics primarily focus on one-dimensional opinions which represent opinions on one topic. However, opinions on various topics are rarely isolated; instead, they can be interdependent and exhibit correlations. In a bounded-confidence model (BCM) of opinion dynamics, agents influence each other's opinions only if their opinions are sufficiently similar. We extend classical agent-based BCMs -- namely, the Hegeselmann--Krause BCM, which has synchronous interactions, and the Deffuant--Weisbuch BCM, which has asynchronous interactions -- to a multidimensional setting, in which the opinions are multidimensional vectors representing opinions of different topics and opinions on different topics are interdependent. To measure opinion differences between agents, we introduce topic-weighted discordance functions that account for opinion differences in all topics. We use the regions of receptiveness to characterize the steady-state opinion clusters and provide an analytical approach to compute these regions. In addition, we numerically simulate our models on various networks with initial opinions drawn from a variety of distributions. When initial opinions are correlated across different topics, our topic-weighted BCMs yield significantly different results in both transient and steady states compared to baseline models, where the dynamics of each opinion topic are independent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00284v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grace Jingying Li, Jiajie Luo, Weiqi Chu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects and biological consequences of the predator-mediated apparent competition I: ODE models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to investigating the effects and biological consequences of the predator-mediated apparent competition based on a two prey species (one is native and the other is invasive) and one predator model with Holling type I and II functional response functions. Through the analytical results and case studies alongside numerical simulations, we find that the initial mass of the invasive prey species, capture rates of prey species, and the predator's mortality rate are all important factors determining the success/failure of invasions and the species coexistence/extinction. The global dynamics can be completely classified for the Holling type I functional response function, but can only be partially determined for the Holling type II functional response function. For the Holling type I response function, we find that whether the invasive prey species can successfully invade to promote the predator-mediated apparent competition is entirely determined by the capture rates of prey species. If the Holling type II response function is applied, then the dynamics are more complicated. First, if two prey species have the same ecological characteristics, then the initial mass of the invasive prey species is the key factor determining the success/failure of the invasion and hence the effect of the predator-mediated apparent competition. Whereas if two prey species have different ecological characteristics, say different capture rates, then the success of the invasion no longer depends on the initial mass of the invasive prey species, but on the capture rates. In all cases, if the invasion succeeds, then the predator-mediated apparent competition's effectiveness essentially depends on the predator's mortality rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00410v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Lou, Weirun Tao, Zhi-An Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binned Spectral Power Loss for Improved Prediction of Chaotic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Forecasting multiscale chaotic dynamical systems with deep learning remains a formidable challenge due to the spectral bias of neural networks, which hinders the accurate representation of fine-scale structures in long-term predictions. This issue is exacerbated when models are deployed autoregressively, leading to compounding errors and instability. In this work, we introduce a novel approach to mitigate the spectral bias which we call the Binned Spectral Power (BSP) Loss. The BSP loss is a frequency-domain loss function that adaptively weighs errors in predicting both larger and smaller scales of the dataset. Unlike traditional losses that focus on pointwise misfits, our BSP loss explicitly penalizes deviations in the energy distribution across different scales, promoting stable and physically consistent predictions. We demonstrate that the BSP loss mitigates the well-known problem of spectral bias in deep learning. We further validate our approach for the data-driven high-dimensional time-series forecasting of a range of benchmark chaotic systems which are typically intractable due to spectral bias. Our results demonstrate that the BSP loss significantly improves the stability and spectral accuracy of neural forecasting models without requiring architectural modifications. By directly targeting spectral consistency, our approach paves the way for more robust deep learning models for long-term forecasting of chaotic dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00472v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibyajyoti Chakraborty, Arvind T. Mohan, Romit Maulik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological flow data analysis for transient flow patterns: a graph-based approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00664v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a time-series analysis method for transient two-dimensional flow patterns based on Topological Flow Data Analysis (TFDA), a new approach to topological data analysis. TFDA identifies local topological flow structures from an instantaneous streamline pattern and describes their global connections as a unique planar tree and its string representation. With TFDA, the evolution of two-dimensional flow patterns is reduced to a discrete dynamical system represented as a transition graph between topologically equivalent streamline patterns. We apply this method to study the lid-driven cavity flow at Reynolds numbers ranging from $Re=14000$ to $Re=16000$, a benchmark problem in fluid dynamics data analysis. Our approach reveals the transition from periodic to chaotic flow at a critical Reynolds number when the reduced dynamical system is modelled as a Markov process on the transition graph. Additionally, we perform an observational causal inference to analyse changes in local flow patterns at the cavity corners and discuss differences with a standard interventional sensitivity analysis. This work demonstrates the potential of TFDA-based time-series analysis for uncovering complex dynamical behaviours in fluid flow data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00664v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Sakajo, Takeshi Matsumoto, Shizuo Kaji, Tomoo Yokoyama, Tomoki Uda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nearly geodesic surfaces are filling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01134v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A surface $S$ in a manifold $M$ is filling if $M-S$ consists of contractible components. We prove for any closed hyperbolic $3$-manifold $M$, there exists an $\epsilon_0&gt;0$ such that every homotopy class of $(1+\epsilon)$-quasi-Fuchsian surfaces with $0&lt;\epsilon \leq \epsilon_0$ is filling. As a corollary, the set of embedded surfaces in $M$ satisfies a dichotomy: it consists of at most finitely many totally geodesic surfaces and surfaces with a quasi-Fuchsian constant lower bound $1+\epsilon_0$. Each of these nearly geodesic surfaces separates any pair of distinct points at the boundary of infinity of the universal cover. Crucial tools include the rigidity results of Mozes-Shah, Ratner, and Shah. This work is inspired by a question of Wu and Xue whether random geodesics on random hyperbolic surfaces are filling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01134v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaolong Hans Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pathwise mild solutions for superlinear stochastic evolution equations and their attractors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01209v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate stochastic parabolic evolution equations with time-dependent random generators and locally Lipschitz continuous drift terms. Using pathwise mild solutions, we construct an infinite-dimensional stationary Ornstein-Uhlenbeck type process, which is shown to be tempered in suitable function spaces. This property, together with a bootstrapping argument based on the regularizing effect of parabolic evolution families, is then applied to prove the global well-posedness and the existence of a random attractor for reaction-diffusion equations with random non-autonomous generators and nonlinearities satisfying certain growth and dissipativity assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01209v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandra Blessing, Tim Seitz, Stefanie Sonner, Bao Quoc Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intraseasonal atmospheric variability under climate trends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01279v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Low-order climate models can play an important role in understanding low-frequency variability in the atmospheric circulation and how forcing consistent with anthropogenic climate change may affect this variability. Here, we study a conceptual model of the mid-latitudes' atmospheric circulation from the perspective of nonautonomous dynamical systems. First, a bifurcation analysis is carried out under time-independent forcing in order to identify different types of behavior in the autonomous model's parameter space. Next, we focus on the study of the nonautonomous system in which the cross-latitudinal heat flux varies seasonally, according to insolation changes. The forward attractor of the seasonally forced model is compared with the attractor of the autonomous one. The seasonal forcing results in a clear change of the attractor's shape. The summer attractor loses its periodicity, and hence predictability, when the forcing is seasonal, while the winter attractor favors energy transport through one of the model's two wave components. Climate change forcing produces several remarkable effects. Thus, the analysis of the model's snapshot attractor under climate trends suggests that the jet speed does not always follow the sign of the change in equator-to-pole thermal contrast, while the change in the energy transported by the eddies does. Chaotic behavior can be completely suppressed in favor of a regular periodic one and vice-versa. Circulation patterns can change, suddenly disappear, and rebuild. The model's snapshot attractor proves to be a robust tool to study its changes in internal variability due to climate trends, both positive and negative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01279v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernardo Maraldi, Henk Dijkstra, Michael Ghil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training in reverse: How iteration order influences convergence and stability in deep learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01557v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite exceptional achievements, training neural networks remains computationally expensive and is often plagued by instabilities that can degrade convergence. While learning rate schedules can help mitigate these issues, finding optimal schedules is time-consuming and resource-intensive. This work explores theoretical issues concerning training stability in the constant-learning-rate (i.e., without schedule) and small-batch-size regime. Surprisingly, we show that the order of gradient updates affects stability and convergence in gradient-based optimizers. We illustrate this new line of thinking using backward-SGD, which processes batch gradient updates like SGD but in reverse order. Our theoretical analysis shows that in contractive regions (e.g., around minima) backward-SGD converges to a point while the standard forward-SGD generally only converges to a distribution. This leads to improved stability and convergence which we demonstrate experimentally. While full backward-SGD is computationally intensive in practice, it highlights opportunities to exploit reverse training dynamics (or more generally alternate iteration orders) to improve training. To our knowledge, this represents a new and unexplored avenue in deep learning optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01557v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benoit Dherin, Benny Avelin, Anders Karlsson, Hanna Mazzawi, Javier Gonzalvo, Michael Munn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Edge Geometry of Regular Polygons -- Part 1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.06800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.06800v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There are multiple mappings that can be used to generate what we call the 'edge geometry' of a regular N-gon, but they are all based on piecewise isometries acting on the extended edges of N to form a 'singularity' set W. This singularity set is also known as the 'web' because it is connected and consists of rays or line segments, with possible accumulation points in the limit. We will use three such maps here, all of which appear to share the same local geometry of W. These mappings are the outer-billiards map Tau, the 'digital-filter' map of Chou and Lin and a 'dual-center' map of Arek Goetz. In (arXiv:1206.5223) we show that these maps are equivalent to a 'shear and rotation' in a toral space and the complex plane respectively, and in the main paper [H5] 'First Families of Regular Polygons and their Mutations' (arXiv:1612.09295) we show that the Tau-web W can also be reduced to a shear and rotation. This equivalence of maps supports the premise that this web geometry is inherent in the N-gon. In terms of Edge Geometry there appears to be just 8 classes of regular N-gons which make up an '8-Fold Way'. Since the topology of W is very complex, we hope to make some progress by studying the region local to N. The edges of every regular N-gon are part of a Tau-invariant region that should include at least 1/4 of the First Family S[k] tiles of N, so the edge geometry overlaps the global web. In Appendix II to [H5] we formulated what may be sufficient conditions for invariance of these regions local to N, based on 'edge-sharing' of adjacent tiles. In this paper we extend this conjecture and provide algebraic criteria with many examples. In the appendix we give examples of 'projections' of orbits based on the work of R.Schwartz in [S2].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.06800v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. H. Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A group from a map and orbit equivalence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.00637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.00637v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In two papers published in 1979, R. Bowen and C. Series defined a dynamical system from a Fuchsian group, acting on the hyperbolic plane $\mathbb{H}^2$. The dynamics is given by a map on $S^1$ which is, in particular, an expanding piecewise homeomorphism of the circle. In this paper we consider a reverse question: which dynamical conditions for an expanding piecewise homeomorphism of $S^1$ are sufficient for the map to be a ``Bowen-Series-type" map (see below) for some group $G$ and which groups can occur? We give a partial answer to these questions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.00637v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\^ome Los, Natalia A. Viana Bedoya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Cobb-Douglas Production Function and the Old Bowley's Law</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.02609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.02609v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bowley's law, also referred to as the law of the constant wage share, was a noteworthy empirical finding in economics, suggesting that a nation's wage share tended to remain stable over time, as observed through most of the 20th century. The wage share represents the proportion of a country's economic output that is distributed to employees as compensation for their labor, usually in the form of wages. The term ''Bowley's law'' was coined in 1964 by Paul Samuelson, the first American laureate of the Nobel memorial prize in economic sciences. He attributed this principle to Sir Arthur Bowley, an English economist, mathematician, and statistician. In this paper, we introduce a mathematical model derived from data for the American economy, originally employed by Cobb and Douglas in 1928 to validate the renowned Cobb-Douglas production function. We utilize symmetry methods, particularly those developed by Peter Olver, to elucidate the validity of Bowley's law within our model's framework. By employing these advanced mathematical techniques, our objective is to elucidate the factors contributing to the stability of the wage share over time. We demonstrate that the validity of both Bowley's law and the Cobb-Douglas production function arises from the robust growth of an economy, characterized by expansion in capital, labor, and production, which can be approximated by an exponential function. Through our analysis, we aim to offer valuable insights into the underlying mechanisms that support Bowley's law and its implications for comprehending income distribution patterns in economies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.02609v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3842/SIGMA.2024.045</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIGMA 20 (2024), 045, 20 pages</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Roman G. Smirnov, Kunpeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surfaces and other Peano Continua with no Generic Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08667v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The space of chains on a compact connected space encodes all the different ways of continuously growing out of a point until exhausting the space. A chain is \emph{generic} if its orbit under the action of the underlying homeomorphism group is comeager. In this paper we show that a large family of topological spaces do not have a generic chain: in addition to all manifolds of dimension at least 3, for which the result was already known, our theorem covers all compact surfaces except for the sphere and the real projective plane - for which the question remains open - as well as all other homogeneous Peano continua, circle excluded. If the spaces are moreover strongly locally homogeneous, which is the case for any closed manifold and the Menger curve, we prove that chains cannot be classified up to homeomorphism by countable structures, and that the underlying homeomorphism groups have non-metrizable universal minimal flows, with all orbits meager, in contrast to the case of 1-dimensional manifolds. The proof of the main result is of combinatorial nature, and it relies on the creation of a dictionary between open sets of chains on one side, and walks on finite connected graphs on the other.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08667v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Basso, Alessandro Codenotti, Andrea Vaccaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifractal Analysis of F-exponents for Finitely Irreducible Conformal Graph Directed Markov Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09348v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\Phi = \{\phi_e\}_{e\in E}$ be a finitely irreducible conformal graph directed Markov system (CGDMS) with symbolic representation $E_A^{\infty}$ and limit set $J$. Under a mild condition on the system, we give a multifractal analysis of level sets of Birkhoff averages with respect to Hausdorff dimension for a large family of functions. We then apply these results to a few examples in the case of both $E$ finite and $E$ countably infinite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09348v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Dalaklis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adversarial ergodic optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14981v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we introduce an ergodic optimization problem inspired by information theory, which can be presented informally as follows: given a factor map $\pi : (X, T) \to (Y, S)$ of topological dynamical systems, and a continuous function $f \in C(X)$, what can be said about the extrema $$\sup_{y \in Y} \inf_{x \in \pi^{-1} \{y\}} \lim_{k \to \infty} \frac{1}{k} \sum_{j = 0}^{k - 1} f \left( T^j x \right) ? $$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14981v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aperiodic Flows on Finite Semigroups: Foundations and First Examples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06668v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The theory of flows was used as a crucial tool in the recent proof by Margolis, Rhodes and Schilling that Krohn-Rhodes complexity is decidable. In this paper we begin a systematic study of aperiodic flows. We give the foundations of the theory of flows and give a unified approach to the Presentation Lemma and its relations to flows and the Slice Theorem. We completely describe semigroups having a flow over the trivial semigroup and connect this to classical results in inverse semigroup theory. We reinterpret Tilson's Theorem on the complexity of small monoids in terms of flows. We conclude with examples of semigroups built from the character table of Abelian Groups that have an aperiodic flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06668v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stuart Margolis, John Rhodes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patterns of Non-Stationary Solutions to Symmetric Systems of Second-Order Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18263v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish the existence of non-stationary solutions to a symmetric system of second-order autonomous differential equations. Our technique is based on the equivariant degree theory and involves a novel characterization of orbit types of maximal kind in the Burnside Ring product of a finite number of basic degrees for the group $O(2) \times \Gamma \times \mathbb Z_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18263v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziad Ghanem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derived from expanding endomorphism on $\mathbb{T}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09342v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Assume that $f$ is a $C^r(r\geq 2)$ specially absolutely partially hyperbolic endomorphism on the 2-torus which is homotopic to an expanding linear endomorphism $A$ with irrational eigenvalues $|\lambda^u_A|&gt;|\lambda^c_A|&gt;1$. If $f$ is area expanding, then the topological semi-conjugacy $h$ between $f$ and $A$ is the topological conjugacy, and $h$ is $C^1$ along the center foliation. Furthermore, if $f$ is area expanding and the center bundle is $C^1$, then the conjugacy is $C^{\max\{r-3,1\}+\alpha}$, in particular, if $r=\omega$, the conjugacy is $C^{\omega}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09342v5</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daohua Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic asymptotic dimension growth for group actions and groupoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19712v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of dynamic asymptotic dimension growth for actions of discrete groups on compact spaces, and more generally for locally compact \'etale groupoids. Using the work of Bartels, L\"uck, and Reich, we bridge asymptotic dimension growth for countable discrete groups with our notion for their group actions, thereby providing numerous concrete examples. Moreover, we demonstrate that the asymptotic dimension growth for a discrete metric space of bounded geometry is equivalent to the dynamic asymptotic dimension growth for its associated coarse groupoid. Consequently, we deduce that the coarse groupoid with subexponential dynamic asymptotic dimension growth is amenable. More generally, we show that every $\sigma$-compact locally compact Hausdorff \'etale groupoid with compact unit space having dynamic asymptotic dimension growth at most $x^{\alpha}$ $(0&lt;\alpha&lt;1)$ is amenable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19712v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hang Wang, Yanru Wang, Jianguo Zhang, Dapeng Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurrence of integral zeros for ergodic flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05326v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let a flow $T_t$ preserve an ergodic probability measure $\mu$, $\int f\,d\mu=0$, and $\mu(A)&gt;0$. Then for almost all $x\in A$, for which $f(x)\neq 0$, there is a sequence ${t_k}\to \infty$ such that $T_{t_k}x\in A$ and $\int_0^{t_k} f(T_sx)ds=0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05326v5</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valery V. Ryzhikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved estimates of statistical properties in some non-uniformly hyperbolic dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16102v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Building upon previous works by Young, Chernov-Zhang and Bruin-Melbourne-Terhesiu, we present a general scheme to improve bounds on the statistical properties (in particular, decay of correlations, and rates in the almost sure invariant principle) for a class of non-uniformly hyperbolic dynamical systems. Specifically, for systems with polynomial, yet summable mixing rates, our method removes logarithmic factors of earlier arguments, resulting in essentially optimal bounds. Applications include Wojtkowski's system of two falling balls, dispersing billiards with flat points and Bunimovich's flower-shaped billiard tables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16102v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P\'eter B\'alint, \'Abel Kom\'alovics</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State-dependent Delay Differential Equations on $H^1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.04730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.04730v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classically, solution theories for state-dependent delay equations are developed in spaces of continuous or continuously differentiable functions. The former can be technically challenging to apply in as much as suitably Lipschitz continuous extensions of mappings onto the space of continuous functions are required; whereas the latter approach leads to restrictions on the class of initial pre-histories. Here, we establish a solution theory for state-dependent delay equations for arbitrary Lipschitz continuous pre-histories and suitably Lipschitz continuous right-hand sides on the Sobolev space $H^1$. The provided solution theory is independent of previous ones and is based on the contraction mapping principle on exponentially weighted spaces. In particular, initial pre-histories are not required to belong to solution manifolds and the generality of the approach permits the consideration of a large class of functional differential equations even for which the continuity of the right-hand side has constraints on the derivative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.04730v4</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jde.2024.08.009</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Differential Equations, Volume 410, 25 November 2024, Pages 737-771</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Johanna Frohberg, Marcus Waurick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear-Quadratic Mean Field Games in Hilbert spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14935v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper represents the first attempt to develop a theory for linear-quadratic mean field games in possibly infinite dimensional Hilbert spaces. As a starting point, we study the case, considered in most finite dimensional contributions on the topic, where the dependence on the distribution enters just in the objective functional through the mean. This feature allows, similarly to the finite dimensional case, to reduce the usual mean field game system to a Riccati equation and a forward-backward coupled system of abstract evolution equations. Such system is completely new in infinite dimension and no results have been proved on it so far. We show existence and uniqueness of solutions for such system, applying a delicate approximation procedure. We apply the results to a production output planning problem with delay in the control variable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14935v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salvatore Federico, Fausto Gozzi, Daria Ghilli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prescribed exponential stabilization of scalar neutral differential equations: Application to neural control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13730v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a control-oriented delay-based modeling approach for the exponential stabilization of a scalar neutral functional differential equation, which is then applied to the local exponential stabilization of a one-layer neural network of Hopfield type with delayed feedback. The proposed approach utilizes a recently developed partial pole placement method for linear functional differential equations, leveraging the coexistence of real spectral values to explicitly prescribe the exponential decay of the closed-loop solution. While a delayed proportional (P) feedback control may achieve stabilization, it requires higher gains and only allows for a shorter maximum delay compared to the proportional-derivative (PD) feedback control presented in this work. The framework provides a practical illustration of the stabilization strategy, improving upon previous literature results that characterize the solution's exponential decay for simple real spectral values. This approach enhances neural stability in cases where the inherent dynamics are stable and offers a method to achieve local exponential stabilization with a prescribed decay rate when the inherent dynamics are unstable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13730v4</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyprien Tamekue, Islam Boussaada, Karim Trabelsi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized replicator dynamics based on mean-field pairwise comparison dynamic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20751v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The pairwise comparison dynamic is a forward ordinary differential equation in a Banach space whose solution is a time-dependent probability measure to maximize utility based on a nonlinear and nonlocal protocol. It contains a wide class of evolutionary game models, such as replicator dynamics and its generalization. We present an inverse control approach to obtain a replicator-type pairwise comparison dynamic from the large discount limit of a mean field game (MFG) as a coupled forward-backward system. This methodology provides a new interpretation of replicator-type dynamics as a myopic perception limit of the dynamic programming. The cost function in the MFG is explicitly obtained to derive the generalized replicator dynamics. We present a finite difference method to compute these models such that the conservation and nonnegativity of the probability density and bounds of the value function can be numerically satisfied. We conduct a computational convergence study of a large discount limit, focusing on potential games and an energy management problem under several conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20751v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidekazu Yoshioka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing Social Contagions with Opinion Dependent Infectivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10373v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The spread of disinformation (maliciously spread false information) in online social networks has become an important problem in today's society. Disinformation's spread is facilitated by the fact that individuals often accept false information based on cognitive biases which predispose them to believe information that they have heard repeatedly or that aligns with their beliefs. Moreover, disinformation often spreads in direct competition with a corresponding true information. To model these phenomena, we develop a model for two competing beliefs spreading on a social network, where individuals have an internal opinion that models their cognitive biases and modulates their likelihood of adopting one of the competing beliefs. By numerical simulations of an agent-based model and a mean-field description of the dynamics, we study how the long-term dynamics of the spreading process depends on the initial conditions for the number of spreaders and the initial opinion of the population. We find that the addition of cognitive biases enriches the transient dynamics of the spreading process, facilitating behavior such as the revival of a dying belief and the overturning of an initially widespread opinion. Finally, we study how external recruitment of spreaders can lead to the eventual dominance of one of the two beliefs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10373v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corbit R. Sampson, Juan G. Restrepo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Koopman-layered Model with Universal Property Based on Toeplitz Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02199v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose deep Koopman-layered models with learnable parameters in the form of Toeplitz matrices for analyzing the transition of the dynamics of time-series data. The proposed model has both theoretical solidness and flexibility. By virtue of the universal property of Toeplitz matrices and the reproducing property underlying the model, we can show its universality and generalization property. In addition, the flexibility of the proposed model enables the model to fit time-series data coming from nonautonomous dynamical systems. When training the model, we apply Krylov subspace methods for efficient computations. In this sense, the proposed model establishes a new connection between Koopman operators and numerical linear algebraic methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02199v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuka Hashimoto, Tomoharu Iwata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasicrystals in pattern formation, Part I: Local existence and basic properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19967v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a general mechanism for the existence of quasicrystals in spatially extended systems (partial differential equations with Euclidean symmetry). We argue that the existence of quasicrystals with higher order rotational symmetry, icosahedral symmetry, etc, is a natural and universal consequence of spontaneous symmetry breaking, bypassing technical issues such as Diophantine properties and hard implicit function theorems. The diffraction diagrams associated with these quasicrystal solutions are not Delone sets, so strictly speaking they do not conform to the definition of a ``mathematical quasicrystal''. But they do appear to capture very well the features of the diffraction diagrams of quasicrystals observed in nature. For the Swift-Hohenberg equation, we obtain more detailed information, including that the $\ell^2$ norm of the diffraction diagram grows like the square root of the bifurcation parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19967v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Melbourne, Jens Rademacher, Bob Rink, Sergey Zelik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Operator Theory for the Collatz Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08084v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Collatz map (or the $3n{+}1$-map) $f$ is defined on positive integers by setting $f(n)$ equal to $3n+1$ when $n$ is odd and $n/2$ when $n$ is even. The Collatz conjecture states that starting from any positive integer $n$, some iterate of $f$ takes value $1$. In this study, we discuss formulations of the Collatz conjecture by $C^{*}$-algebras in the following three ways: (1) single operator, (2) two operators, and (3) Cuntz algebra. For the $C^{*}$-algebra generated by each of these, we consider the condition that it has no non-trivial reducing subspaces. For (1), we prove that the condition implies the Collatz conjecture. In the cases (2) and (3), we prove that the condition is equivalent to the Collatz conjecture. For similar maps, we introduce equivalence relations by them and generalize connections between the Collatz conjecture and irreducibility of associated $C^{*}$-algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08084v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takehiko Mori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A lower bound on end-periodic stretch factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17389v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given an end-periodic homeomorphism $f: S \to S$ we give a lower bound on the Handel--Miller stretch factor of $f$ in terms of the capacity of $f$, which is a measure of topological complexity for an end-periodic homeomorphism. We also show that this bound is asymptotically sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17389v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marissa Loving, Chenxi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
