<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM</link>
    <description>cs.MM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 02:43:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Can Large Language Models Grasp Event Signals? Exploring Pure Zero-Shot Event-based Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in event-based zero-shot object recognition have demonstrated promising results. However, these methods heavily depend on extensive training and are inherently constrained by the characteristics of CLIP. To the best of our knowledge, this research is the first study to explore the understanding capabilities of large language models (LLMs) for event-based visual content. We demonstrate that LLMs can achieve event-based object recognition without additional training or fine-tuning in conjunction with CLIP, effectively enabling pure zero-shot event-based recognition. Particularly, we evaluate the ability of GPT-4o / 4turbo and two other open-source LLMs to directly recognize event-based visual content. Extensive experiments are conducted across three benchmark datasets, systematically assessing the recognition accuracy of these models. The results show that LLMs, especially when enhanced with well-designed prompts, significantly improve event-based zero-shot recognition performance. Notably, GPT-4o outperforms the compared models and exceeds the recognition accuracy of state-of-the-art event-based zero-shot methods on N-ImageNet by five orders of magnitude. The implementation of this paper is available at \url{https://github.com/ChrisYu-Zz/Pure-event-based-recognition-based-LLM}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09628v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongyou Yu, Qiang Qu, Xiaoming Chen, Chen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DriveMM: All-in-One Large Multimodal Model for Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07689v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) have demonstrated exceptional comprehension and interpretation capabilities in Autonomous Driving (AD) by incorporating large language models. Despite the advancements, current data-driven AD approaches tend to concentrate on a single dataset and specific tasks, neglecting their overall capabilities and ability to generalize. To bridge these gaps, we propose DriveMM, a general large multimodal model designed to process diverse data inputs, such as images and multi-view videos, while performing a broad spectrum of AD tasks, including perception, prediction, and planning. Initially, the model undergoes curriculum pre-training to process varied visual signals and perform basic visual comprehension and perception tasks. Subsequently, we augment and standardize various AD-related datasets to fine-tune the model, resulting in an all-in-one LMM for autonomous driving. To assess the general capabilities and generalization ability, we conduct evaluations on six public benchmarks and undertake zero-shot transfer on an unseen dataset, where DriveMM achieves state-of-the-art performance across all tasks. We hope DriveMM as a promising solution for future end-to-end autonomous driving applications in the real world. Project page with code: https://github.com/zhijian11/DriveMM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07689v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhijian Huang, Chengjian Feng, Feng Yan, Baihui Xiao, Zequn Jie, Yujie Zhong, Xiaodan Liang, Lin Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Latency Scalable Streaming for Event-Based Vision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07889v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, we have witnessed the rise of novel ``event-based'' camera sensors for high-speed, low-power video capture. Rather than recording discrete image frames, these sensors output asynchronous ``event'' tuples with microsecond precision, only when the brightness change of a given pixel exceeds a certain threshold. Although these sensors have enabled compelling new computer vision applications, these applications often require expensive, power-hungry GPU systems, rendering them incompatible for deployment on the low-power devices for which event cameras are optimized. Whereas receiver-driven rate adaptation is a crucial feature of modern video streaming solutions, this topic is underexplored in the realm of event-based vision systems. On a real-world event camera dataset, we first demonstrate that a state-of-the-art object detection application is resilient to dramatic data loss, and that this loss may be weighted towards the end of each temporal window. We then propose a scalable streaming method for event-based data based on Media Over QUIC, prioritizing object detection performance and low latency. The application server can receive complementary event data across several streams simultaneously, and drop streams as needed to maintain a certain latency. With a latency target of 5 ms for end-to-end transmission across a small network, we observe an average reduction in detection mAP as low as 0.36. With a more relaxed latency target of 50 ms, we observe an average mAP reduction as low as 0.19.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07889v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Hamara, Benjamin Kilpatrick, Alex Baratta, Brendon Kofink, Andrew C. Freeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frechet Music Distance: A Metric For Generative Symbolic Music Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07948v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce the Frechet Music Distance (FMD), a novel evaluation metric for generative symbolic music models, inspired by the Frechet Inception Distance (FID) in computer vision and Frechet Audio Distance (FAD) in generative audio. FMD calculates the distance between distributions of reference and generated symbolic music embeddings, capturing abstract musical features. We validate FMD across several datasets and models. Results indicate that FMD effectively differentiates model quality, providing a domain-specific metric for evaluating symbolic music generation, and establishing a reproducible standard for future research in symbolic music modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07948v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Retkowski, Jakub St\k{e}pniak, Mateusz Modrzejewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeRF-NQA: No-Reference Quality Assessment for Scenes Generated by NeRF and Neural View Synthesis Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08029v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neural View Synthesis (NVS) has demonstrated efficacy in generating high-fidelity dense viewpoint videos using a image set with sparse views. However, existing quality assessment methods like PSNR, SSIM, and LPIPS are not tailored for the scenes with dense viewpoints synthesized by NVS and NeRF variants, thus, they often fall short in capturing the perceptual quality, including spatial and angular aspects of NVS-synthesized scenes. Furthermore, the lack of dense ground truth views makes the full reference quality assessment on NVS-synthesized scenes challenging. For instance, datasets such as LLFF provide only sparse images, insufficient for complete full-reference assessments. To address the issues above, we propose NeRF-NQA, the first no-reference quality assessment method for densely-observed scenes synthesized from the NVS and NeRF variants. NeRF-NQA employs a joint quality assessment strategy, integrating both viewwise and pointwise approaches, to evaluate the quality of NVS-generated scenes. The viewwise approach assesses the spatial quality of each individual synthesized view and the overall inter-views consistency, while the pointwise approach focuses on the angular qualities of scene surface points and their compound inter-point quality. Extensive evaluations are conducted to compare NeRF-NQA with 23 mainstream visual quality assessment methods (from fields of image, video, and light-field assessment). The results demonstrate NeRF-NQA outperforms the existing assessment methods significantly and it shows substantial superiority on assessing NVS-synthesized scenes without references. An implementation of this paper are available at https://github.com/VincentQQu/NeRF-NQA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08029v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TVCG.2024.3372037</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 30, no. 5, pp. 2129-2139, May 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Qu, Hanxue Liang, Xiaoming Chen, Yuk Ying Chung, Yiran Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LatentSpeech: Latent Diffusion for Text-To-Speech Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Diffusion-based Generative AI gains significant attention for its superior performance over other generative techniques like Generative Adversarial Networks and Variational Autoencoders. While it has achieved notable advancements in fields such as computer vision and natural language processing, their application in speech generation remains under-explored. Mainstream Text-to-Speech systems primarily map outputs to Mel-Spectrograms in the spectral space, leading to high computational loads due to the sparsity of MelSpecs. To address these limitations, we propose LatentSpeech, a novel TTS generation approach utilizing latent diffusion models. By using latent embeddings as the intermediate representation, LatentSpeech reduces the target dimension to 5% of what is required for MelSpecs, simplifying the processing for the TTS encoder and vocoder and enabling efficient high-quality speech generation. This study marks the first integration of latent diffusion models in TTS, enhancing the accuracy and naturalness of generated speech. Experimental results on benchmark datasets demonstrate that LatentSpeech achieves a 25% improvement in Word Error Rate and a 24% improvement in Mel Cepstral Distortion compared to existing models, with further improvements rising to 49.5% and 26%, respectively, with additional training data. These findings highlight the potential of LatentSpeech to advance the state-of-the-art in TTS technology</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08117v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haowei Lou, Helen Paik, Pari Delir Haghighi, Wen Hu, Lina Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Hybrid Propagator for Temporal Misalignment in Audio-Visual Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08161v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Audio-visual video segmentation (AVVS) aims to generate pixel-level maps of sound-producing objects that accurately align with the corresponding audio. However, existing methods often face temporal misalignment, where audio cues and segmentation results are not temporally coordinated. Audio provides two critical pieces of information: i) target object-level details and ii) the timing of when objects start and stop producing sounds. Current methods focus more on object-level information but neglect the boundaries of audio semantic changes, leading to temporal misalignment. To address this issue, we propose a Collaborative Hybrid Propagator Framework~(Co-Prop). This framework includes two main steps: Preliminary Audio Boundary Anchoring and Frame-by-Frame Audio-Insert Propagation. To Anchor the audio boundary, we employ retrieval-assist prompts with Qwen large language models to identify control points of audio semantic changes. These control points split the audio into semantically consistent audio portions. After obtaining the control point lists, we propose the Audio Insertion Propagator to process each audio portion using a frame-by-frame audio insertion propagation and matching approach. We curated a compact dataset comprising diverse source conversion cases and devised a metric to assess alignment rates. Compared to traditional simultaneous processing methods, our approach reduces memory requirements and facilitates frame alignment. Experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach across three datasets and two backbones. Furthermore, our method can be integrated with existing AVVS approaches, offering plug-and-play functionality to enhance their performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08161v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kexin Li, Zongxin Yang, Yi Yang, Jun Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TextRefiner: Internal Visual Feature as Efficient Refiner for Vision-Language Models Prompt Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08176v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite the efficiency of prompt learning in transferring vision-language models (VLMs) to downstream tasks, existing methods mainly learn the prompts in a coarse-grained manner where the learned prompt vectors are shared across all categories. Consequently, the tailored prompts often fail to discern class-specific visual concepts, thereby hindering the transferred performance for classes that share similar or complex visual attributes. Recent advances mitigate this challenge by leveraging external knowledge from Large Language Models (LLMs) to furnish class descriptions, yet incurring notable inference costs. In this paper, we introduce TextRefiner, a plug-and-play method to refine the text prompts of existing methods by leveraging the internal knowledge of VLMs. Particularly, TextRefiner builds a novel local cache module to encapsulate fine-grained visual concepts derivedfrom local tokens within the image branch. By aggregating and aligning the cached visual descriptions with the original output of the text branch, TextRefiner can efficiently refine and enrich the learned prompts from existing methods without relying on any external expertise. For example, it improves the performance of CoOp from 71.66 % to 76.94 % on 11 benchmarks, surpassing CoCoOp which introduces instance-wise features for text prompts. Equipped with TextRefiner, PromptKD achieves state-of-the-art performance and is efficient in inference. Our code is relesed at https://github.com/xjjxmu/TextRefiner</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08176v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingjing Xie, Yuxin Zhang, Jun Peng, Zhaohong Huang, Liujuan Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAFIRE: Segment Any Forged Image Region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08197v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Most techniques approach the problem of image forgery localization as a binary segmentation task, training neural networks to label original areas as 0 and forged areas as 1. In contrast, we tackle this issue from a more fundamental perspective by partitioning images according to their originating sources. To this end, we propose Segment Any Forged Image Region (SAFIRE), which solves forgery localization using point prompting. Each point on an image is used to segment the source region containing itself. This allows us to partition images into multiple source regions, a capability achieved for the first time. Additionally, rather than memorizing certain forgery traces, SAFIRE naturally focuses on uniform characteristics within each source region. This approach leads to more stable and effective learning, achieving superior performance in both the new task and the traditional binary forgery localization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08197v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Myung-Joon Kwon, Wonjun Lee, Seung-Hun Nam, Minji Son, Changick Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MoMuSE: Momentum Multi-modal Target Speaker Extraction for Real-time Scenarios with Impaired Visual Cues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08247v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Audio-visual Target Speaker Extraction (AV-TSE) aims to isolate the speech of a specific target speaker from an audio mixture using time-synchronized visual cues. In real-world scenarios, visual cues are not always available due to various impairments, which undermines the stability of AV-TSE. Despite this challenge, humans can maintain attentional momentum over time, even when the target speaker is not visible. In this paper, we introduce the Momentum Multi-modal target Speaker Extraction (MoMuSE), which retains a speaker identity momentum in memory, enabling the model to continuously track the target speaker. Designed for real-time inference, MoMuSE extracts the current speech window with guidance from both visual cues and dynamically updated speaker momentum. Experimental results demonstrate that MoMuSE exhibits significant improvement, particularly in scenarios with severe impairment of visual cues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08247v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junjie Li, Ke Zhang, Shuai Wang, Kong Aik Lee, Haizhou Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Model For Voice and Accent Conversion In Speech and Singing using Self-Supervised Learning and Feature Extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08312v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a new voice conversion model capable of transforming both speaking and singing voices. It addresses key challenges in current systems, such as conveying emotions, managing pronunciation and accent changes, and reproducing non-verbal sounds. One of the model's standout features is its ability to perform accent conversion on hybrid voice samples that encompass both speech and singing, allowing it to change the speaker's accent while preserving the original content and prosody. The proposed model uses an encoder-decoder architecture: the encoder is based on HuBERT to process the speech's acoustic and linguistic content, while the HiFi-GAN decoder audio matches the target speaker's voice. The model incorporates fundamental frequency (f0) features and singer embeddings to enhance performance while ensuring the pitch &amp; tone accuracy and vocal identity are preserved during transformation. This approach improves how naturally and flexibly voice style can be transformed, showing strong potential for applications in voice dubbing, content creation, and technologies like Text-to-Speech (TTS) and Interactive Voice Response (IVR) systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08312v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sowmya Cheripally</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>POINTS1.5: Building a Vision-Language Model towards Real World Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Vision-language models have made significant strides recently, demonstrating superior performance across a range of tasks, e.g. optical character recognition and complex diagram analysis. Building on this trend, we introduce a new vision-language model, POINTS1.5, designed to excel in various real-world applications. POINTS1.5 is an enhancement of POINTS1.0 and incorporates several key innovations: i) We replace the original CLIP vision encoder, which had a fixed image resolution, with a NaViT-style vision encoder that supports native dynamic high resolution. This allows POINTS1.5 to process images of any resolution without needing to split them into tiles. ii) We add bilingual support to POINTS1.5, significantly enhancing its capability in Chinese. Due to the scarcity of open-source Chinese datasets for vision-language models, we collect numerous images from the Internet and annotate them using a combination of manual and automatic methods. iii) We propose a set of rigorous filtering methods for visual instruction tuning datasets. We comprehensively evaluate all these filtering methods, and choose the most effective ones to obtain the final visual instruction tuning set. Thanks to these innovations, POINTS1.5 significantly outperforms POINTS1.0 and demonstrates strong performance across a range of real-world applications. Notably, POINTS1.5-7B is trained on fewer than 4 billion tokens and ranks first on the OpenCompass leaderboard among models with fewer than 10 billion parameters</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08443v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Liu, Le Tian, Xiao Zhou, Xinyu Gao, Kavio Yu, Yang Yu, Jie Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Dual-Module Denoising Approach with Curriculum Learning for Enhancing Multimodal Aspect-Based Sentiment Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08489v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multimodal Aspect-Based Sentiment Analysis (MABSA) combines text and images to perform sentiment analysis but often struggles with irrelevant or misleading visual information. Existing methodologies typically address either sentence-image denoising or aspect-image denoising but fail to comprehensively tackle both types of noise. To address these limitations, we propose DualDe, a novel approach comprising two distinct components: the Hybrid Curriculum Denoising Module (HCD) and the Aspect-Enhance Denoising Module (AED). The HCD module enhances sentence-image denoising by incorporating a flexible curriculum learning strategy that prioritizes training on clean data. Concurrently, the AED module mitigates aspect-image noise through an aspect-guided attention mechanism that filters out noisy visual regions which unrelated to the specific aspects of interest. Our approach demonstrates effectiveness in addressing both sentence-image and aspect-image noise, as evidenced by experimental evaluations on benchmark datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08489v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Van Doan, Dat Tran Nguyen, Cam-Van Thi Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PointTalk: Audio-Driven Dynamic Lip Point Cloud for 3D Gaussian-based Talking Head Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08504v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Talking head synthesis with arbitrary speech audio is a crucial challenge in the field of digital humans. Recently, methods based on radiance fields have received increasing attention due to their ability to synthesize high-fidelity and identity-consistent talking heads from just a few minutes of training video. However, due to the limited scale of the training data, these methods often exhibit poor performance in audio-lip synchronization and visual quality. In this paper, we propose a novel 3D Gaussian-based method called PointTalk, which constructs a static 3D Gaussian field of the head and deforms it in sync with the audio. It also incorporates an audio-driven dynamic lip point cloud as a critical component of the conditional information, thereby facilitating the effective synthesis of talking heads. Specifically, the initial step involves generating the corresponding lip point cloud from the audio signal and capturing its topological structure. The design of the dynamic difference encoder aims to capture the subtle nuances inherent in dynamic lip movements more effectively. Furthermore, we integrate the audio-point enhancement module, which not only ensures the synchronization of the audio signal with the corresponding lip point cloud within the feature space, but also facilitates a deeper understanding of the interrelations among cross-modal conditional features. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method achieves superior high-fidelity and audio-lip synchronization in talking head synthesis compared to previous methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08504v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Xie, Tao Feng, Xin Zhang, Xiangyang Luo, Zixuan Guo, Weijiang Yu, Heng Chang, Fei Ma, Fei Richard Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mel-Refine: A Plug-and-Play Approach to Refine Mel-Spectrogram in Audio Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08577v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Text-to-audio (TTA) model is capable of generating diverse audio from textual prompts. However, most mainstream TTA models, which predominantly rely on Mel-spectrograms, still face challenges in producing audio with rich content. The intricate details and texture required in Mel-spectrograms for such audio often surpass the models' capacity, leading to outputs that are blurred or lack coherence. In this paper, we begin by investigating the critical role of U-Net in Mel-spectrogram generation. Our analysis shows that in U-Net structure, high-frequency components in skip-connections and the backbone influence texture and detail, while low-frequency components in the backbone are critical for the diffusion denoising process. We further propose ``Mel-Refine'', a plug-and-play approach that enhances Mel-spectrogram texture and detail by adjusting different component weights during inference. Our method requires no additional training or fine-tuning and is fully compatible with any diffusion-based TTA architecture. Experimental results show that our approach boosts performance metrics of the latest TTA model Tango2 by 25\%, demonstrating its effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08577v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongming Guo, Ruibo Fu, Yizhong Geng, Shuai Liu, Shuchen Shi, Tao Wang, Chunyu Qiang, Chenxing Li, Ya Li, Zhengqi Wen, Yukun Liu, Xuefei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHORDONOMICON: A Dataset of 666,000 Songs and their Chord Progressions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22046v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Chord progressions encapsulate important information about music, pertaining to its structure and conveyed emotions. They serve as the backbone of musical composition, and in many cases, they are the sole information required for a musician to play along and follow the music. Despite their importance, chord progressions as a data domain remain underexplored. There is a lack of large-scale datasets suitable for deep learning applications, and limited research exploring chord progressions as an input modality. In this work, we present Chordonomicon, a dataset of over 666,000 songs and their chord progressions, annotated with structural parts, genre, and release date - created by scraping various sources of user-generated progressions and associated metadata. We demonstrate the practical utility of the Chordonomicon dataset for classification and generation tasks, and discuss its potential to provide valuable insights to the research community. Chord progressions are unique in their ability to be represented in multiple formats (e.g. text, graph) and the wealth of information chords convey in given contexts, such as their harmonic function . These characteristics make the Chordonomicon an ideal testbed for exploring advanced machine learning techniques, including transformers, graph machine learning, and hybrid systems that combine knowledge representation and machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22046v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spyridon Kantarelis, Konstantinos Thomas, Vassilis Lyberatos, Edmund Dervakos, Giorgos Stamou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LinVT: Empower Your Image-level Large Language Model to Understand Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05185v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have been widely used in various tasks, motivating us to develop an LLM-based assistant for videos. Instead of training from scratch, we propose a module to transform arbitrary well-trained image-based LLMs into video-LLMs (after being trained on video data). To better adapt image-LLMs for processing videos, we introduce two design principles: linear transformation to preserve the original visual-language alignment and representative information condensation from redundant video content. Guided by these principles, we propose a plug-and-play Linear Video Tokenizer(LinVT), which enables existing image-LLMs to understand videos. We benchmark LinVT with six recent visual LLMs: Aquila, Blip-3, InternVL2, Mipha, Molmo and Qwen2-VL, showcasing the high compatibility of LinVT. LinVT-based LLMs achieve state-of-the-art performance across various video benchmarks, illustrating the effectiveness of LinVT in multi-modal video understanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05185v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lishuai Gao, Yujie Zhong, Yingsen Zeng, Haoxian Tan, Dengjie Li, Zheng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving Speaker Information in Direct Speech-to-Speech Translation with Non-Autoregressive Generation and Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07316v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Speech-to-Speech Translation (S2ST) refers to the conversion of speech in one language into semantically equivalent speech in another language, facilitating communication between speakers of different languages. Speech-to-Discrete Unit Translation (S2UT), a mainstream approach for end-to-end S2ST, addresses challenges such as error propagation across modules and slow inference speed often encountered in traditional cascade systems. However, as discrete units primarily capture content information, conventional S2UT methods fail to retain speaker-specific characteristics from the source. Our previous work, SC-S2UT, introduced a speaker adapter and a unit-to-mel structure, enabling the preservation of speaker information and non-autoregressive speech generation. Building on this foundation, this study proposes a self-supervised pretraining method to enrich the information extracted by both the speaker adapter and the unit-to-mel structure. Additionally, we investigate different feature fusion strategies to further improve the integration of speaker and content features. Experiments conducted on the CVSS-T dataset for ES-EN and FR-EN tasks demonstrate that our proposed method achieves a BLEU score improvement of 1.14 compared to SC-S2UT, along with significant enhancements in MOS and speaker similarity. Furthermore, our approach achieves translation quality comparable to traditional S2UT, with only a minimal increase of 0.04s per utterance in inference time, while maintaining high speaker similarity. These results validate the effectiveness of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07316v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Zhou, Akinori Ito, Takashi Nose</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
