<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM</link>
    <description>cs.MM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 04:00:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Taming Data and Transformers for Audio Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19388v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generating ambient sounds and effects is a challenging problem due to data scarcity and often insufficient caption quality, making it difficult to employ large-scale generative models for the task. In this work, we tackle the problem by introducing two new models. First, we propose AutoCap, a high-quality and efficient automatic audio captioning model. We show that by leveraging metadata available with the audio modality, we can substantially improve the quality of captions. AutoCap reaches CIDEr score of 83.2, marking a 3.2% improvement from the best available captioning model at four times faster inference speed. We then use AutoCap to caption clips from existing datasets, obtaining 761,000 audio clips with high-quality captions, forming the largest available audio-text dataset. Second, we propose GenAu, a scalable transformer-based audio generation architecture that we scale up to 1.25B parameters and train with our new dataset. When compared to state-of-the-art audio generators, GenAu obtains significant improvements of 15.7% in FAD score, 22.7% in IS, and 13.5% in CLAP score, indicating significantly improved quality of generated audio compared to previous works. This shows that the quality of data is often as important as its quantity. Besides, since AutoCap is fully automatic, new audio samples can be added to the training dataset, unlocking the training of even larger generative models for audio synthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19388v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moayed Haji-Ali, Willi Menapace, Aliaksandr Siarohin, Guha Balakrishnan, Sergey Tulyakov, Vicente Ordonez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Alleviating Text-to-Image Retrieval Hallucination for CLIP in Zero-shot Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18400v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pretrained cross-modal models, for instance, the most representative CLIP, have recently led to a boom in using pre-trained models for cross-modal zero-shot tasks, considering the generalization properties. However, we analytically discover that CLIP suffers from the text-to-image retrieval hallucination, adversely limiting its capabilities under zero-shot learning: CLIP would select the image with the highest score when asked to figure out which image perfectly matches one given query text among several candidate images even though CLIP knows contents in the image. Accordingly, we propose a Balanced Score with Auxiliary Prompts (BSAP) to mitigate the CLIP's text-to-image retrieval hallucination under zero-shot learning. Specifically, we first design auxiliary prompts to provide multiple reference outcomes for every single image retrieval, then the outcomes derived from each retrieved image in conjunction with the target text are normalized to obtain the final similarity, which alleviates hallucinations in the model. Additionally, we can merge CLIP's original results and BSAP to obtain a more robust hybrid outcome (BSAP-H). Extensive experiments on two typical zero-shot learning tasks, i.e., Referring Expression Comprehension (REC) and Referring Image Segmentation (RIS), are conducted to demonstrate the effectiveness of our BSAP. Specifically, when evaluated on the validation dataset of RefCOCO in REC, BSAP increases CLIP's performance by 20.6%. Further, we validate that our strategy could be applied in other types of pretrained cross-modal models, such as ALBEF and BLIP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18400v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanyao Wang, Yibing Zhan, Liu Liu, Liang Ding, Yan Yang, Jun Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
