<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM</link>
    <description>cs.MM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 04:01:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AllTheDocks road safety dataset: A cyclist's perspective and experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active travel is an essential component in intelligent transportation systems. Cycling, as a form of active travel, shares the road space with motorised traffic which often affects the cyclists' safety and comfort and therefore peoples' propensity to uptake cycling instead of driving. This paper presents a unique dataset, collected by cyclists across London, that includes video footage, accelerometer, GPS, and gyroscope data. The dataset is then labelled by an independent group of London cyclists to rank the safety level of each frame and to identify objects in the cyclist's field of vision that might affect their experience. Furthermore, in this dataset, the quality of the road is measured by the international roughness index of the surface, which indicates the comfort of cycling on the road. The dataset will be made available for open access in the hope of motivating more research in this area to underpin the requirements for cyclists' safety and comfort and encourage more people to replace vehicle travel with cycling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10528v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chia-Yen Chiang, Ruikang Zhong, Jennifer Ding, Joseph Wood, Stephen Bee, Mona Jaber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrieval Augmented Verification : Unveiling Disinformation with Structured Representations for Zero-Shot Real-Time Evidence-guided Fact-Checking of Multi-modal Social media posts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10702v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Social Media posts, where real images are unscrupulously reused along with provocative text to promote a particular idea, have been one of the major sources of disinformation. By design, these claims are without editorial oversight and accessible to a vast population who otherwise may not have access to multiple information sources. This implies the need to fact-check these posts and clearly explain which parts of the posts are fake. In the supervised learning setup, this is often reduced to a binary classification problem, neglecting all intermediate stages. Further, these claims often involve recent events on which systems trained on historical data are prone to fail. In this work, we propose a zero-shot approach by retrieving real-time web-scraped evidence from multiple news websites and matching them with the claim text and image using pretrained language vision systems. We propose a graph structured representation, which a) allows us to gather evidence automatically and b) helps generate interpretable results by explicitly pointing out which parts of the claim can not be verified. Our zero-shot method, with improved interpretability, generates competitive results against the state-of-the-art methods</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10702v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arka Ujjal Dey, Artemis Llabr\'es, Ernest Valveny, Dimosthenis Karatzas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ANCHOR: LLM-driven News Subject Conditioning for Text-to-Image Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10141v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Text-to-Image (T2I) Synthesis has made tremendous strides in enhancing synthesized image quality, but current datasets evaluate model performance only on descriptive, instruction-based prompts. Real-world news image captions take a more pragmatic approach, providing high-level situational and Named-Entity (NE) information and limited physical object descriptions, making them abstractive. To evaluate the ability of T2I models to capture intended subjects from news captions, we introduce the Abstractive News Captions with High-level cOntext Representation (ANCHOR) dataset, containing 70K+ samples sourced from 5 different news media organizations. With Large Language Models (LLM) achieving success in language and commonsense reasoning tasks, we explore the ability of different LLMs to identify and understand key subjects from abstractive captions. Our proposed method Subject-Aware Finetuning (SAFE), selects and enhances the representation of key subjects in synthesized images by leveraging LLM-generated subject weights. It also adapts to the domain distribution of news images and captions through custom Domain Fine-tuning, outperforming current T2I baselines on ANCHOR. By launching the ANCHOR dataset, we hope to motivate research in furthering the Natural Language Understanding (NLU) capabilities of T2I models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10141v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aashish Anantha Ramakrishnan, Sharon X. Huang, Dongwon Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AniFrame: A Programming Language for 2D Drawing and Frame-Based Animation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10250v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Creative coding is an experimentation-heavy activity that requires translating high-level visual ideas into code. However, most languages and libraries for creative coding may not be adequately intuitive for beginners. In this paper, we present AniFrame, a domain-specific language for drawing and animation. Designed for novice programmers, it (i) features animation-specific data types, operations, and built-in functions to simplify the creation and animation of composite objects, (ii) allows for fine-grained control over animation sequences through explicit specification of the target object and the start and end frames, (iii) reduces the learning curve through a Python-like syntax, type inferencing, and a minimal set of control structures and keywords that map closely to their semantic intent, and (iv) promotes computational expressivity through support for common mathematical operations, built-in trigonometric functions, and user-defined recursion. Our usability test demonstrates AniFrame's potential to enhance readability and writability for multiple creative coding use cases. AniFrame is open-source, and its implementation and reference are available at https://github.com/memgonzales/aniframe-language.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10250v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Edward M. Gonzales, Hans Oswald A. Ibrahim, Elyssia Barrie H. Ong, Ryan Austin Fernandez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Data Deluge to Data Curation: A Filtering-WoRA Paradigm for Efficient Text-based Person Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In text-based person search endeavors, data generation has emerged as a prevailing practice, addressing concerns over privacy preservation and the arduous task of manual annotation. Although the number of synthesized data can be infinite in theory, the scientific conundrum persists that how much generated data optimally fuels subsequent model training. We observe that only a subset of the data in these constructed datasets plays a decisive role. Therefore, we introduce a new Filtering-WoRA paradigm, which contains a filtering algorithm to identify this crucial data subset and WoRA (Weighted Low-Rank Adaptation) learning strategy for light fine-tuning. The filtering algorithm is based on the cross-modality relevance to remove the lots of coarse matching synthesis pairs. As the number of data decreases, we do not need to fine-tune the entire model. Therefore, we propose a WoRA learning strategy to efficiently update a minimal portion of model parameters. WoRA streamlines the learning process, enabling heightened efficiency in extracting knowledge from fewer, yet potent, data instances. Extensive experimentation validates the efficacy of pretraining, where our model achieves advanced and efficient retrieval performance on challenging real-world benchmarks. Notably, on the CUHK-PEDES dataset, we have achieved a competitive mAP of 67.02% while reducing model training time by 19.82%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10292v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jintao Sun, Zhedong Zheng, Gangyi Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Referring Flexible Image Restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In reality, images often exhibit multiple degradations, such as rain and fog at night (triple degradations). However, in many cases, individuals may not want to remove all degradations, for instance, a blurry lens revealing a beautiful snowy landscape (double degradations). In such scenarios, people may only desire to deblur. These situations and requirements shed light on a new challenge in image restoration, where a model must perceive and remove specific degradation types specified by human commands in images with multiple degradations. We term this task Referring Flexible Image Restoration (RFIR). To address this, we first construct a large-scale synthetic dataset called RFIR, comprising 153,423 samples with the degraded image, text prompt for specific degradation removal and restored image. RFIR consists of five basic degradation types: blur, rain, haze, low light and snow while six main sub-categories are included for varying degrees of degradation removal. To tackle the challenge, we propose a novel transformer-based multi-task model named TransRFIR, which simultaneously perceives degradation types in the degraded image and removes specific degradation upon text prompt. TransRFIR is based on two devised attention modules, Multi-Head Agent Self-Attention (MHASA) and Multi-Head Agent Cross Attention (MHACA), where MHASA and MHACA introduce the agent token and reach the linear complexity, achieving lower computation cost than vanilla self-attention and cross-attention and obtaining competitive performances. Our TransRFIR achieves state-of-the-art performances compared with other counterparts and is proven as an effective architecture for image restoration. We release our project at https://github.com/GuanRunwei/FIR-CP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10342v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runwei Guan, Rongsheng Hu, Zhuhao Zhou, Tianlang Xue, Ka Lok Man, Jeremy Smith, Eng Gee Lim, Weiping Ding, Yutao Yue</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
