<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM</link>
    <description>cs.MM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 02:37:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AutoMV: An Automatic Multi-Agent System for Music Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Music-to-Video (M2V) generation for full-length songs faces significant challenges. Existing methods produce short, disjointed clips, failing to align visuals with musical structure, beats, or lyrics, and lack temporal consistency. We propose AutoMV, a multi-agent system that generates full music videos (MVs) directly from a song. AutoMV first applies music processing tools to extract musical attributes, such as structure, vocal tracks, and time-aligned lyrics, and constructs these features as contextual inputs for following agents. The screenwriter Agent and director Agent then use this information to design short script, define character profiles in a shared external bank, and specify camera instructions. Subsequently, these agents call the image generator for keyframes and different video generators for "story" or "singer" scenes. A Verifier Agent evaluates their output, enabling multi-agent collaboration to produce a coherent longform MV. To evaluate M2V generation, we further propose a benchmark with four high-level categories (Music Content, Technical, Post-production, Art) and twelve ine-grained criteria. This benchmark was applied to compare commercial products, AutoMV, and human-directed MVs with expert human raters: AutoMV outperforms current baselines significantly across all four categories, narrowing the gap to professional MVs. Finally, we investigate using large multimodal models as automatic MV judges; while promising, they still lag behind human expert, highlighting room for future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12196v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxuan Tang, Xinping Lei, Chaoran Zhu, Shiyun Chen, Ruibin Yuan, Yizhi Li, Changjae Oh, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Emmanouil Benetos, Yang Liu, Jiaheng Liu, Yinghao Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JointAVBench: A Benchmark for Joint Audio-Visual Reasoning Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding videos inherently requires reasoning over both visual and auditory information. To properly evaluate Omni-Large Language Models (Omni-LLMs), which are capable of processing multi-modal information including vision and audio, an effective benchmark must comprehensively cover three key aspects: (1) multi-modal dependency (i.e., questions that cannot be answered using vision or audio alone), (2) diverse audio information types (e.g., speech, sound events), and (3) varying scene spans. However, existing datasets fall short in one or more of these dimensions, limiting strict and comprehensive evaluation. To address this gap, we introduce JointAVBench, a novel benchmark with strict audio-video correlation, spanning five cognitive dimensions, four audio information types (speech, sound events, music, vocal traits), and three scene spans (single-, cross-, and full-scene). Given the high cost of manual annotation, we propose an automated pipeline that leverages state-of-the-art vision-LLMs, audio-LLMs, and general-purpose LLMs to synthesize questions and answers that strictly require joint audio-visual understanding. We evaluate leading vision-only, audio-only, and Omni-LLMs on our dataset. Results show that even the best-performing Omni-LLM achieves an average accuracy of only 62.6\%, outperforming uni-modal baselines but revealing substantial room for improvement, especially in cross-scene reasoning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12772v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianghan Chao, Jianzhang Gao, Wenhui Tan, Yuchong Sun, Ruihua Song, Liyun Ru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Semantic and Temporal Alignment for Interactive Video Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The growing volume of video data and the introduction of complex retrieval challenges, such as the Temporal Retrieval and Alignment of Key Events (TRAKE) task at the Ho Chi Minh City AI Challenge 2025, expose critical limitations in existing systems. Many methodologies lack scalable, holistic architectures and rely on "frozen" embedding models that fail on out-of-knowledge (OOK) or real-world queries. This paper introduces the comprehensive video retrieval framework developed by team AIO\_Owlgorithms to address these gaps. Our system features an architecture integrating TransNetV2 for scene segmentation, BEiT-3 for visual embeddings in Milvus, and Gemini OCR for metadata in Elasticsearch. We propose two components: (1) \textbf{QUEST} (Query Understanding and External Search for Out-of-Knowledge Tasks), a two-branch framework that leverages a Large Language Model (LLM) for query rewriting and an external image search pathway to resolve OOK queries; and (2) \textbf{DANTE} (Dynamic Alignment of Narrative Temporal Events), a dynamic programming algorithm that efficiently solves the temporally-incoherent TRAKE task. These contributions form a robust and intelligent system that significantly advances the state-of-the-art in handling complex, real-world video search queries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13169v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanh-Danh Luu, Le-Vu Nguyen Dinh, Duc-Thien Tran, Duy-Bao Bui, Nam-Tien Le, Tinh-Anh Nguyen Nhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CreativeVR: Diffusion-Prior-Guided Approach for Structure and Motion Restoration in Generative and Real Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12060v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern text-to-video (T2V) diffusion models can synthesize visually compelling clips, yet they remain brittle at fine-scale structure: even state-of-the-art generators often produce distorted faces and hands, warped backgrounds, and temporally inconsistent motion. Such severe structural artifacts also appear in very low-quality real-world videos. Classical video restoration and super-resolution (VR/VSR) methods, in contrast, are tuned for synthetic degradations such as blur and downsampling and tend to stabilize these artifacts rather than repair them, while diffusion-prior restorers are usually trained on photometric noise and offer little control over the trade-off between perceptual quality and fidelity.
  We introduce CreativeVR, a diffusion-prior-guided video restoration framework for AI-generated (AIGC) and real videos with severe structural and temporal artifacts. Our deep-adapter-based method exposes a single precision knob that controls how strongly the model follows the input, smoothly trading off between precise restoration on standard degradations and stronger structure- and motion-corrective behavior on challenging content. Our key novelty is a temporally coherent degradation module used during training, which applies carefully designed transformations that produce realistic structural failures.
  To evaluate AIGC-artifact restoration, we propose the AIGC54 benchmark with FIQA, semantic and perceptual metrics, and multi-aspect scoring. CreativeVR achieves state-of-the-art results on videos with severe artifacts and performs competitively on standard video restoration benchmarks, while running at practical throughput (about 13 FPS at 720p on a single 80-GB A100). Project page: https://daveishan.github.io/creativevr-webpage/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12060v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tejas Panambur, Ishan Rajendrakumar Dave, Chongjian Ge, Ersin Yumer, Xue Bai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-Rex: Real-Time Streaming Video LLM Acceleration via Dynamic KV Cache Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12284v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Streaming video large language models (LLMs) are increasingly used for real-time multimodal tasks such as video captioning, question answering, conversational agents, and augmented reality. However, these models face fundamental memory and computational challenges because their key-value (KV) caches grow substantially with continuous streaming video input. This process requires an iterative prefill stage, which is a unique feature of streaming video LLMs. Due to its iterative prefill stage, it suffers from significant limitations, including extensive computation, substantial data transfer, and degradation in accuracy. Crucially, this issue is exacerbated for edge deployment, which is the primary target for these models.
  In this work, we propose V-Rex, the first software-hardware co-designed accelerator that comprehensively addresses both algorithmic and hardware bottlenecks in streaming video LLM inference. At its core, V-Rex introduces ReSV, a training-free dynamic KV cache retrieval algorithm. ReSV exploits temporal and spatial similarity-based token clustering to reduce excessive KV cache memory across video frames. To fully realize these algorithmic benefits, V-Rex offers a compact, low-latency hardware accelerator with a dynamic KV cache retrieval engine (DRE), featuring bit-level and early-exit based computing units. V-Rex achieves unprecedented real-time of 3.9-8.3 FPS and energy-efficient streaming video LLM inference on edge deployment with negligible accuracy loss. While DRE only accounts for 2.2% power and 2.0% area, the system delivers 1.9-19.7x speedup and 3.1-18.5x energy efficiency improvements over AGX Orin GPU. This work is the first to comprehensively tackle KV cache retrieval across algorithms and hardware, enabling real-time streaming video LLM inference on resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12284v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghyuk Kim, Sejeong Yang, Wonjin Shin, Joo-Young Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personalized QoE Prediction: A Demographic-Augmented Machine Learning Framework for 5G Video Streaming Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12736v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quality of Experience (QoE) prediction is a critical component of modern multimedia systems, particularly for adaptive video streaming in 5G networks. Accurate QoE estimation enables intelligent resource management and supports user centric service delivery. Existing QoE prediction approaches primarily rely on limited datasets and assume uniform user perception, which restricts their applicability in heterogeneous real world environments.
  This paper proposes a demographic aware machine learning framework for personalized QoE prediction. We introduce a behaviorally realistic demographic based data augmentation strategy that expands a small QoE dataset six fold by modeling varying user sensitivities to streaming impairments such as rebuffering, bitrate variation, and quality degradation. Using the augmented dataset, we evaluate a comprehensive set of classical machine learning models alongside advanced deep learning architectures, including an attention-based MLP and TabNet.
  Experimental results demonstrate significant improvements in prediction accuracy across RMSE, MAE, and R metrics compared to baseline models. Among all evaluated approaches, TabNet achieves the strongest performance, benefiting from its inherent feature selection and attention mechanisms. The results confirm that demographic-aware augmentation substantially enhances QoE prediction robustness and provides a scalable direction for personalized QoE-aware intelligence in 5G video streaming networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12736v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Syeda Zunaira Ahmed, Hejab Tahira Beg, Maryam Khalid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schrodinger Audio-Visual Editor: Object-Level Audiovisual Removal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12875v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Joint editing of audio and visual content is crucial for precise and controllable content creation. This new task poses challenges due to the limitations of paired audio-visual data before and after targeted edits, and the heterogeneity across modalities. To address the data and modeling challenges in joint audio-visual editing, we introduce SAVEBench, a paired audiovisual dataset with text and mask conditions to enable object-grounded source-to-target learning. With SAVEBench, we train the Schrodinger Audio-Visual Editor (SAVE), an end-to-end flow-matching model that edits audio and video in parallel while keeping them aligned throughout processing. SAVE incorporates a Schrodinger Bridge that learns a direct transport from source to target audiovisual mixtures. Our evaluation demonstrates that the proposed SAVE model is able to remove the target objects in audio and visual content while preserving the remaining content, with stronger temporal synchronization and audiovisual semantic correspondence compared with pairwise combinations of an audio editor and a video editor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12875v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weihan Xu, Kan Jen Cheng, Koichi Saito, Muhammad Jehanzeb Mirza, Tingle Li, Yisi Liu, Alexander H. Liu, Liming Wang, Masato Ishii, Takashi Shibuya, Yuki Mitsufuji, Gopala Anumanchipalli, Paul Pu Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Unified Co-Speech Gesture Generation via Hierarchical Implicit Periodicity Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generating 3D-based body movements from speech shows great potential in extensive downstream applications, while it still suffers challenges in imitating realistic human movements. Predominant research efforts focus on end-to-end generation schemes to generate co-speech gestures, spanning GANs, VQ-VAE, and recent diffusion models. As an ill-posed problem, in this paper, we argue that these prevailing learning schemes fail to model crucial inter- and intra-correlations across different motion units, i.e. head, body, and hands, thus leading to unnatural movements and poor coordination. To delve into these intrinsic correlations, we propose a unified Hierarchical Implicit Periodicity (HIP) learning approach for audio-inspired 3D gesture generation. Different from predominant research, our approach models this multi-modal implicit relationship by two explicit technique insights: i) To disentangle the complicated gesture movements, we first explore the gesture motion phase manifolds with periodic autoencoders to imitate human natures from realistic distributions while incorporating non-period ones from current latent states for instance-level diversities. ii) To model the hierarchical relationship of face motions, body gestures, and hand movements, driving the animation with cascaded guidance during learning. We exhibit our proposed approach on 3D avatars and extensive experiments show our method outperforms the state-of-the-art co-speech gesture generation methods by both quantitative and qualitative evaluations. Code and models will be publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13131v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Guo, Yifan Zhao, Jia Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angle-Optimized Partial Disentanglement for Multimodal Emotion Recognition in Conversation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22447v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multimodal Emotion Recognition in Conversation (MERC) aims to enhance emotion understanding by integrating complementary cues from text, audio, and visual modalities. Existing MERC approaches predominantly focus on cross-modal shared features, often overlooking modality-specific features that capture subtle yet critical emotional cues such as micro-expressions, prosodic variations, and sarcasm. Although related work in multimodal emotion recognition (MER) has explored disentangling shared and modality-specific features, these methods typically employ rigid orthogonal constraints to achieve full disentanglement, which neglects the inherent complementarity between feature types and may limit recognition performance. To address these challenges, we propose Angle-Optimized Feature Learning (AO-FL), a framework tailored for MERC that achieves partial disentanglement of shared and specific features within each modality through adaptive angular optimization. Specifically, AO-FL aligns shared features across modalities to ensure semantic consistency, and within each modality it adaptively models the angular relationship between its shared and modality-specific features to preserve both distinctiveness and complementarity. An orthogonal projection refinement further removes redundancy in specific features and enriches shared features with contextual information, yielding more discriminative multimodal representations. Extensive experiments confirm the effectiveness of AO-FL for MERC, demonstrating superior performance over state-of-the-art approaches. Moreover, AO-FL can be seamlessly integrated with various unimodal feature extractors and extended to other multimodal fusion tasks, such as MER, thereby highlighting its strong generalization beyond MERC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22447v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyi Che, Wenbo Wang, Yuanbo Hou, Mingjie Xie, Qijun Zhao, Jian Guan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LookAhead Tuning: Safer Language Models via Partial Answer Previews</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19041v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fine-tuning enables large language models (LLMs) to adapt to specific domains, but often compromises their previously established safety alignment. To mitigate the degradation of model safety during fine-tuning, we introduce LookAhead Tuning, a lightweight and effective data-driven approach that preserves safety during fine-tuning. The method introduces two simple strategies that modify training data by previewing partial answer prefixes, thereby minimizing perturbations to the model's initial token distributions and maintaining its built-in safety mechanisms. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that LookAhead Tuning effectively maintains model safety without sacrificing robust performance on downstream tasks. Our findings position LookAhead Tuning as a reliable and efficient solution for the safe and effective adaptation of LLMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19041v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kangwei Liu, Mengru Wang, Yujie Luo, Lin Yuan, Mengshu Sun, Lei Liang, Zhiqiang Zhang, Jun Zhou, Bryan Hooi, Shumin Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory-Centric Embodied Question Answering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13948v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Embodied Question Answering (EQA) requires agents to autonomously explore and comprehend the environment to answer context-dependent questions. Typically, an EQA framework consists of four components: a planner, a memory module, a stopping module, and an answering module. However, the memory module is utilized inefficiently in existing methods, as the information it stores is leveraged solely for the answering module. Such a design may result in redundant or inadequate exploration, leading to a suboptimal success rate. To solve this problem, we propose MemoryEQA, an EQA framework centered on memory, which establishes mechanisms for memory storage, update, and retrieval, allowing memory information to contribute throughout the entire exploration process. Specifically, we convert the observation into structured textual representations, which are stored in a vector library following a fixed structure. At each exploration step, we utilize a viewpoint comparison strategy to determine whether the memory requires updating. Before executing each module, we employ an entropy-based adaptive retrieval strategy to obtain the minimal yet sufficient memory information that satisfies the requirements of different modules. The retrieved module-specific information is then integrated with the current observation as input to the corresponding module. To evaluate EQA models' memory capabilities, we constructed the benchmark based on HM3D called MT-HM3D, comprising 1,587 question-answer pairs involving multiple targets across various regions, which requires agents to maintain memory of exploration-acquired target information. Experimental results on HM-EQA, MT-HM3D, and OpenEQA demonstrate the effectiveness of our framework, where a 9.9% performance gain on MT-HM3D compared to baseline models further underscores the memory capability's pivotal role in solving complex tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13948v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingliang Zhai, Zhi Gao, Yuwei Wu, Yunde Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GMFVAD: Using Grained Multi-modal Feature to Improve Video Anomaly Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20268v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Video anomaly detection (VAD) is a challenging task that detects anomalous frames in continuous surveillance videos. Most previous work utilizes the spatio-temporal correlation of visual features to distinguish whether there are abnormalities in video snippets. Recently, some works attempt to introduce multi-modal information, like text feature, to enhance the results of video anomaly detection. However, these works merely incorporate text features into video snippets in a coarse manner, overlooking the significant amount of redundant information that may exist within the video snippets. Therefore, we propose to leverage the diversity among multi-modal information to further refine the extracted features, reducing the redundancy in visual features, and we propose Grained Multi-modal Feature for Video Anomaly Detection (GMFVAD). Specifically, we generate more grained multi-modal feature based on the video snippet, which summarizes the main content, and text features based on the captions of original video will be introduced to further enhance the visual features of highlighted portions. Experiments show that the proposed GMFVAD achieves state-of-the-art performance on four mainly datasets. Ablation experiments also validate that the improvement of GMFVAD is due to the reduction of redundant information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20268v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-981-95-4109-6_29</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Guangyu Dai, Dong Chen, Siliang Tang, Yueting Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HUD: Hierarchical Uncertainty-Aware Disambiguation Network for Composed Video Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02792v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Composed Video Retrieval (CVR) is a challenging video retrieval task that utilizes multi-modal queries, consisting of a reference video and modification text, to retrieve the desired target video. The core of this task lies in understanding the multi-modal composed query and achieving accurate composed feature learning. Within multi-modal queries, the video modality typically carries richer semantic content compared to the textual modality. However, previous works have largely overlooked the disparity in information density between these two modalities. This limitation can lead to two critical issues: 1) modification subject referring ambiguity and 2) limited detailed semantic focus, both of which degrade the performance of CVR models. To address the aforementioned issues, we propose a novel CVR framework, namely the Hierarchical Uncertainty-aware Disambiguation network (HUD). HUD is the first framework that leverages the disparity in information density between video and text to enhance multi-modal query understanding. It comprises three key components: (a) Holistic Pronoun Disambiguation, (b) Atomistic Uncertainty Modeling, and (c) Holistic-to-Atomistic Alignment. By exploiting overlapping semantics through holistic cross-modal interaction and fine-grained semantic alignment via atomistic-level cross-modal interaction, HUD enables effective object disambiguation and enhances the focus on detailed semantics, thereby achieving precise composed feature learning. Moreover, our proposed HUD is also applicable to the Composed Image Retrieval (CIR) task and achieves state-of-the-art performance across three benchmark datasets for both CVR and CIR tasks. The codes are available on https://zivchen-ty.github.io/HUD.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02792v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiwei Chen, Yupeng Hu, Zixu Li, Zhiheng Fu, Haokun Wen, Weili Guan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
