<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM</link>
    <description>cs.MM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Universally Unfiltered and Unseen:Input-Agnostic Multimodal Jailbreaks against Text-to-Image Model Safeguards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05658v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Various (text) prompt filters and (image) safety checkers have been implemented to mitigate the misuse of Text-to-Image (T2I) models in creating Not-Safe-For-Work (NSFW) content.In order to expose potential security vulnerabilities of such safeguards, multimodal jailbreaks have been studied.However, existing jailbreaks are limited to prompt-specific and image-specific perturbations, which suffer from poor scalability and time-consuming optimization.To address these limitations, we propose Universally Unfiltered and Unseen (U3)-Attack, a multimodal jailbreak attack method against T2I safeguards.Specifically, U3-Attack optimizes an adversarial patch on the image background to universally bypass safety checkers and optimizes a safe paraphrase set from a sensitive word to universally bypass prompt filters while eliminating redundant computations.Extensive experimental results demonstrate the superiority of our U3-Attack on both open-source and commercial T2I models.For example, on the commercial Runway-inpainting model with both prompt filter and safety checker, our U3-Attack achieves $~4\times$ higher success rates than the state-of-the-art multimodal jailbreak attack, MMA-Diffusion.Content Warning: This paper includes examples of NSFW content.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05658v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Song Yan, Hui Wei, Jinlong Fei, Guoliang Yang, Zhengyu Zhao, Zheng Wamg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Item Graph Enhancement for Multimodal Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06154v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multimodal recommendation systems have attracted increasing attention for their improved performance by leveraging items' multimodal information. Prior methods often build modality-specific item-item semantic graphs from raw modality features and use them as supplementary structures alongside the user-item interaction graph to enhance user preference learning. However, these semantic graphs suffer from semantic deficiencies, including (1) insufficient modeling of collaborative signals among items and (2) structural distortions introduced by noise in raw modality features, ultimately compromising performance. To address these issues, we first extract collaborative signals from the interaction graph and infuse them into each modality-specific item semantic graph to enhance semantic modeling. Then, we design a modulus-based personalized embedding perturbation mechanism that injects perturbations with modulus-guided personalized intensity into embeddings to generate contrastive views. This enables the model to learn noise-robust representations through contrastive learning, thereby reducing the effect of structural noise in semantic graphs. Besides, we propose a dual representation alignment mechanism that first aligns multiple semantic representations via a designed Anchor-based InfoNCE loss using behavior representations as anchors, and then aligns behavior representations with the fused semantics by standard InfoNCE, to ensure representation consistency. Extensive experiments on four benchmark datasets validate the effectiveness of our framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06154v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxiong Zhang, Xin Zhou, Zhiwei Zeng, Dusit Niyato, Zhiqi Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Copyright Infringement on Short Video Platforms: Novel Datasets and an Audio Restoration Deep Learning Pipeline</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21772v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Short video platforms like YouTube Shorts and TikTok face significant copyright compliance challenges, as infringers frequently embed arbitrary background music (BGM) to obscure original soundtracks (OST) and evade content originality detection. To tackle this issue, we propose a novel pipeline that integrates Music Source Separation (MSS) and cross-modal video-music retrieval (CMVMR). Our approach effectively separates arbitrary BGM from the original OST, enabling the restoration of authentic video audio tracks. To support this work, we introduce two domain-specific datasets: OASD-20K for audio separation and OSVAR-160 for pipeline evaluation. OASD-20K contains 20,000 audio clips featuring mixed BGM and OST pairs, while OSVAR-160 is a unique benchmark dataset comprising 1,121 video and mixed-audio pairs, specifically designed for short video restoration tasks. Experimental results demonstrate that our pipeline not only removes arbitrary BGM with high accuracy but also restores OSTs, ensuring content integrity. This approach provides an ethical and scalable solution to copyright challenges in user-generated content on short video platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21772v3</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minwoo Oh, Minsu Park, Eunil Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Multimodal Large Language Models Understand Spatial Relations?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19015v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Spatial relation reasoning is a crucial task for multimodal large language models (MLLMs) to understand the objective world. However, current benchmarks have issues like relying on bounding boxes, ignoring perspective substitutions, or allowing questions to be answered using only the model's prior knowledge without image understanding. To address these issues, we introduce SpatialMQA, a human-annotated spatial relation reasoning benchmark based on COCO2017, which enables MLLMs to focus more on understanding images in the objective world. To ensure data quality, we design a well-tailored annotation procedure, resulting in SpatialMQA consisting of 5,392 samples. Based on this benchmark, a series of closed- and open-source MLLMs are implemented and the results indicate that the current state-of-the-art MLLM achieves only 48.14% accuracy, far below the human-level accuracy of 98.40%. Extensive experimental analyses are also conducted, suggesting the future research directions. The benchmark and codes are available at https://github.com/ziyan-xiaoyu/SpatialMQA.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19015v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.18653/v1/2025.acl-long.31</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>In Proceedings of the 63rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers), pages 620-632, 2025, Vienna, Austria</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jingping Liu, Ziyan Liu, Zhedong Cen, Yan Zhou, Yinan Zou, Weiyan Zhang, Haiyun Jiang, Tong Ruan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
