<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM</link>
    <description>cs.MM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 01:28:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Fusion with Semi-Supervised Learning Minimizes Annotation Quantity for Modeling Videoconference Conversation Experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13971v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Group conversations over videoconferencing are a complex social behavior. However, the subjective moments of negative experience, where the conversation loses fluidity or enjoyment remain understudied. These moments are infrequent in naturalistic data, and thus training a supervised learning (SL) model requires costly manual data annotation. We applied semi-supervised learning (SSL) to leverage targeted labeled and unlabeled clips for training multimodal (audio, facial, text) deep features to predict non-fluid or unenjoyable moments in holdout videoconference sessions. The modality-fused co-training SSL achieved an ROC-AUC of 0.9 and an F1 score of 0.6, outperforming SL models by up to 4% with the same amount of labeled data. Remarkably, the best SSL model with just 8% labeled data matched 96% of the SL model's full-data performance. This shows an annotation-efficient framework for modeling videoconference experience.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13971v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Chang, Chenkai Hu, Ji Qi, Zhuojian Wei, Kexin Zhang, Viswadruth Akkaraju, David Poeppel, Dustin Freeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fretting-Transformer: Encoder-Decoder Model for MIDI to Tablature Transcription</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14223v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Music transcription plays a pivotal role in Music Information Retrieval (MIR), particularly for stringed instruments like the guitar, where symbolic music notations such as MIDI lack crucial playability information. This contribution introduces the Fretting-Transformer, an encoderdecoder model that utilizes a T5 transformer architecture to automate the transcription of MIDI sequences into guitar tablature. By framing the task as a symbolic translation problem, the model addresses key challenges, including string-fret ambiguity and physical playability. The proposed system leverages diverse datasets, including DadaGP, GuitarToday, and Leduc, with novel data pre-processing and tokenization strategies. We have developed metrics for tablature accuracy and playability to quantitatively evaluate the performance. The experimental results demonstrate that the Fretting-Transformer surpasses baseline methods like A* and commercial applications like Guitar Pro. The integration of context-sensitive processing and tuning/capo conditioning further enhances the model's performance, laying a robust foundation for future developments in automated guitar transcription.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14223v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Hamberger, Sebastian Murgul, Jochen Schmidt, Michael Heizmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manipulated Regions Localization For Partially Deepfake Audio: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14396v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the development of audio deepfake techniques, attacks with partially deepfake audio are beginning to rise. Compared to fully deepfake, it is much harder to be identified by the detector due to the partially cryptic manipulation, resulting in higher security risks. Although some studies have been launched, there is no comprehensive review to systematically introduce the current situations and development trends for addressing this issue. Thus, in this survey, we are the first to outline a systematic introduction for partially deepfake audio manipulated region localization tasks, including the fundamentals, branches of existing methods, current limitations and potential trends, providing a revealing insight into this scope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14396v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayi He, Jiangyan Yi, Jianhua Tao, Siding Zeng, Hao Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>M3SD: Multi-modal, Multi-scenario and Multi-language Speaker Diarization Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the field of speaker diarization, the development of technology is constrained by two problems: insufficient data resources and poor generalization ability of deep learning models. To address these two problems, firstly, we propose an automated method for constructing speaker diarization datasets, which generates more accurate pseudo-labels for massive data through the combination of audio and video. Relying on this method, we have released Multi-modal, Multi-scenario and Multi-language Speaker Diarization (M3SD) datasets. This dataset is derived from real network videos and is highly diverse. In addition, we further propose a scenario-related model fine-tuning strategy. Based on the general model pre-trained using the above dataset, we combine the specific data of the target scenario (e.g., meetings) and achieve targeted optimization by using Adapter and LoRA joint fine-tuning, thus achieving the model's domain adaptation. Our dataset and code have been open-sourced at https://huggingface.co/spaces/OldDragon/m3sd.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14427v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilong Wu, Hang Chen, Jun Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeRF-QA: Neural Radiance Fields Quality Assessment Database</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This short paper proposes a new database - NeRF-QA - containing 48 videos synthesized with seven NeRF based methods, along with their perceived quality scores, resulting from subjective assessment tests; for the videos selection, both real and synthetic, 360 degrees scenes were considered. This database will allow to evaluate the suitability, to NeRF based synthesized views, of existing objective quality metrics and also the development of new quality metrics, specific for this case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03176v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Martin, Ant\'onio Rodrigues, Jo\~ao Ascenso, Maria Paula Queluz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GS-QA: Comprehensive Quality Assessment Benchmark for Gaussian Splatting View Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gaussian Splatting (GS) offers a promising alternative to Neural Radiance Fields (NeRF) for real-time 3D scene rendering. Using a set of 3D Gaussians to represent complex geometry and appearance, GS achieves faster rendering times and reduced memory consumption compared to the neural network approach used in NeRF. However, quality assessment of GS-generated static content is not yet explored in-depth. This paper describes a subjective quality assessment study that aims to evaluate synthesized videos obtained with several static GS state-of-the-art methods. The methods were applied to diverse visual scenes, covering both 360-degree and forward-facing (FF) camera trajectories. Moreover, the performance of 18 objective quality metrics was analyzed using the scores resulting from the subjective study, providing insights into their strengths, limitations, and alignment with human perception. All videos and scores are made available providing a comprehensive database that can be used as benchmark on GS view synthesis and objective quality metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13196v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Martin, Ant\'onio Rodrigues, Jo\~ao Ascenso, Maria Paula Queluz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immersive Fantasy Based on Digital Nostalgia: Environmental Narratives for the Korean Millennials and Gen Z</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10013v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study introduces the media artwork Dear Passenger, Please Wear a Mask, designed to offer a layered exploration of single-use mask waste, which escalated during the COVID-19 pandemic. The piece reframes underappreciated ecological concerns by interweaving digital nostalgia and airline travel recollections of Millennials and Gen Z with a unique fantasy narrative. Via a point-and-click game and an immersive exhibition, participants traverse both virtual and real domains, facing ethical and environmental dilemmas. While it fosters empathy and potential action, resource use and post-experience engagement challenges persist.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10013v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yerin Doh, Joonhyung Bae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tile Classification Based Viewport Prediction with Multi-modal Fusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14704v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Viewport prediction is a crucial aspect of tile-based 360 video streaming system. However, existing trajectory based methods lack of robustness, also oversimplify the process of information construction and fusion between different modality inputs, leading to the error accumulation problem. In this paper, we propose a tile classification based viewport prediction method with Multi-modal Fusion Transformer, namely MFTR. Specifically, MFTR utilizes transformer-based networks to extract the long-range dependencies within each modality, then mine intra- and inter-modality relations to capture the combined impact of user historical inputs and video contents on future viewport selection. In addition, MFTR categorizes future tiles into two categories: user interested or not, and selects future viewport as the region that contains most user interested tiles. Comparing with predicting head trajectories, choosing future viewport based on tile's binary classification results exhibits better robustness and interpretability. To evaluate our proposed MFTR, we conduct extensive experiments on two widely used PVS-HM and Xu-Gaze dataset. MFTR shows superior performance over state-of-the-art methods in terms of average prediction accuracy and overlap ratio, also presents competitive computation efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14704v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3581783.3613809</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zhihao Zhang, Yiwei Chen, Weizhan Zhang, Caixia Yan, Qinghua Zheng, Qi Wang, Wangdu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllable Dance Generation with Style-Guided Motion Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07871v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dance plays an important role as an artistic form and expression in human culture, yet the creation of dance remains a challenging task. Most dance generation methods primarily rely solely on music, seldom taking into consideration intrinsic attributes such as music style or genre. In this work, we introduce Flexible Dance Generation with Style Description Prompts (DGSDP), a diffusion-based framework suitable for diversified tasks of dance generation by fully leveraging the semantics of music style. The core component of this framework is Music-Conditioned Style-Aware Diffusion (MCSAD), which comprises a Transformer-based network and a music Style Modulation module. The MCSAD seemly integrates music conditions and style description prompts into the dance generation framework, ensuring that generated dances are consistent with the music content and style. To facilitate flexible dance generation and accommodate different tasks, a spatial-temporal masking strategy is effectively applied in the backward diffusion process. The proposed framework successfully generates realistic dance sequences that are accurately aligned with music for a variety of tasks such as long-term generation, dance in-betweening, dance inpainting, and etc. We hope that this work has the potential to inspire dance generation and creation, with promising applications in entertainment, art, and education. Code is available on Github: https://github.com/mucunzhuzhu/DGSDP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07871v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongsong Wang, Ying Zhu, Yang Zhang, Junbo Wang, Xin Geng, Liang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Baseline with Single-encoder for Referring Image Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15521v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Referring image segmentation (RIS) requires dense vision-language interactions between visual pixels and textual words to segment objects based on a given description. However, commonly adapted dual-encoders in RIS, e.g., Swin transformer and BERT (uni-modal encoders) or CLIP (a multi-modal dual-encoder), lack dense multi-modal interactions during pre-training, leading to a gap with a pixel-level RIS task. To bridge this gap, existing RIS methods often rely on multi-modal fusion modules that interact two encoders, but this approach leads to high computational costs. In this paper, we present a novel RIS method with a single-encoder, i.e., BEiT-3, maximizing the potential of shared self-attention across all framework components. This enables seamless interactions of two modalities from input to final prediction, producing granularly aligned multi-modal features. Furthermore, we propose lightweight yet effective decoder modules, a Shared FPN and a Shared Mask Decoder, which contribute to the high efficiency of our model. Our simple baseline with a single encoder achieves outstanding performances on the RIS benchmark datasets while maintaining computational efficiency, compared to the most recent SoTA methods based on dual-encoders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15521v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seonghoon Yu, Ilchae Jung, Byeongju Han, Taeoh Kim, Yunho Kim, Dongyoon Wee, Jeany Son</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge Bridger: Towards Training-free Missing Modality Completion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19834v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Previous successful approaches to missing modality completion rely on carefully designed fusion techniques and extensive pre-training on complete data, which can limit their generalizability in out-of-domain (OOD) scenarios. In this study, we pose a new challenge: can we develop a missing modality completion model that is both resource-efficient and robust to OOD generalization? To address this, we present a training-free framework for missing modality completion that leverages large multimodal models (LMMs). Our approach, termed the "Knowledge Bridger", is modality-agnostic and integrates generation and ranking of missing modalities. By defining domain-specific priors, our method automatically extracts structured information from available modalities to construct knowledge graphs. These extracted graphs connect the missing modality generation and ranking modules through the LMM, resulting in high-quality imputations of missing modalities. Experimental results across both general and medical domains show that our approach consistently outperforms competing methods, including in OOD generalization. Additionally, our knowledge-driven generation and ranking techniques demonstrate superiority over variants that directly employ LMMs for generation and ranking, offering insights that may be valuable for applications in other domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19834v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanzhou Ke, Shengfeng He, Xiao Li Wang, Bo Wang, Guoqing Chao, Yuanyang Zhang, Yi Xie, HeXing Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ArrayDPS: Unsupervised Blind Speech Separation with a Diffusion Prior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05657v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Blind Speech Separation (BSS) aims to separate multiple speech sources from audio mixtures recorded by a microphone array. The problem is challenging because it is a blind inverse problem, i.e., the microphone array geometry, the room impulse response (RIR), and the speech sources, are all unknown. We propose ArrayDPS to solve the BSS problem in an unsupervised, array-agnostic, and generative manner. The core idea builds on diffusion posterior sampling (DPS), but unlike DPS where the likelihood is tractable, ArrayDPS must approximate the likelihood by formulating a separate optimization problem. The solution to the optimization approximates room acoustics and the relative transfer functions between microphones. These approximations, along with the diffusion priors, iterate through the ArrayDPS sampling process and ultimately yield separated voice sources. We only need a simple single-speaker speech diffusion model as a prior along with the mixtures recorded at the microphones; no microphone array information is necessary. Evaluation results show that ArrayDPS outperforms all baseline unsupervised methods while being comparable to supervised methods in terms of SDR. Audio demos are provided at: https://arraydps.github.io/ArrayDPSDemo/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05657v3</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongweiyang Xu, Xulin Fan, Zhong-Qiu Wang, Xilin Jiang, Romit Roy Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EEG2TEXT-CN: An Exploratory Study of Open-Vocabulary Chinese Text-EEG Alignment via Large Language Model and Contrastive Learning on ChineseEEG</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00854v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose EEG2TEXT-CN, which, to the best of our knowledge, represents one of the earliest open-vocabulary EEG-to-text generation frameworks tailored for Chinese. Built on a biologically grounded EEG encoder (NICE-EEG) and a compact pretrained language model (MiniLM), our architecture aligns multichannel brain signals with natural language representations via masked pretraining and contrastive learning. Using a subset of the ChineseEEG dataset, where each sentence contains approximately ten Chinese characters aligned with 128-channel EEG recorded at 256 Hz, we segment EEG into per-character embeddings and predict full sentences in a zero-shot setting. The decoder is trained with teacher forcing and padding masks to accommodate variable-length sequences. Evaluation on over 1,500 training-validation sentences and 300 held-out test samples shows promising lexical alignment, with a best BLEU-1 score of 6.38\%. While syntactic fluency remains a challenge, our findings demonstrate the feasibility of non-phonetic, cross-modal language decoding from EEG. This work opens a new direction in multilingual brain-to-text research and lays the foundation for future cognitive-language interfaces in Chinese.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00854v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacky Tai-Yu Lu, Jung Chiang, Chi-Sheng Chen, Anna Nai-Yun Tung, Hsiang Wei Hu, Yuan Chiao Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HKD4VLM: A Progressive Hybrid Knowledge Distillation Framework for Robust Multimodal Hallucination and Factuality Detection in VLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13038v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Driven by the rapid progress in vision-language models (VLMs), the responsible behavior of large-scale multimodal models has become a prominent research area, particularly focusing on hallucination detection and factuality checking. In this paper, we present the solution for the two tracks of Responsible AI challenge. Inspirations from the general domain demonstrate that a smaller distilled VLM can often outperform a larger VLM that is directly tuned on downstream tasks, while achieving higher efficiency. We thus jointly tackle two tasks from the perspective of knowledge distillation and propose a progressive hybrid knowledge distillation framework termed HKD4VLM. Specifically, the overall framework can be decomposed into Pyramid-like Progressive Online Distillation and Ternary-Coupled Refinement Distillation, hierarchically moving from coarse-grained knowledge alignment to fine-grained refinement. Besides, we further introduce the mapping shift-enhanced inference and diverse augmentation strategies to enhance model performance and robustness. Extensive experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of our HKD4VLM. Ablation studies provide insights into the critical design choices driving performance gains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13038v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Zhang, Xuecheng Wu, Danlei Huang, Siyu Yan, Chong Peng, Xuezhi Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
