<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM</link>
    <description>cs.MM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AGAV-Rater: Adapting Large Multimodal Model for AI-Generated Audio-Visual Quality Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many video-to-audio (VTA) methods have been proposed for dubbing silent AI-generated videos. An efficient quality assessment method for AI-generated audio-visual content (AGAV) is crucial for ensuring audio-visual quality. Existing audio-visual quality assessment methods struggle with unique distortions in AGAVs, such as unrealistic and inconsistent elements. To address this, we introduce AGAVQA, the first large-scale AGAV quality assessment dataset, comprising 3,382 AGAVs from 16 VTA methods. AGAVQA includes two subsets: AGAVQA-MOS, which provides multi-dimensional scores for audio quality, content consistency, and overall quality, and AGAVQA-Pair, designed for optimal AGAV pair selection. We further propose AGAV-Rater, a LMM-based model that can score AGAVs, as well as audio and music generated from text, across multiple dimensions, and selects the best AGAV generated by VTA methods to present to the user. AGAV-Rater achieves state-of-the-art performance on AGAVQA, Text-to-Audio, and Text-to-Music datasets. Subjective tests also confirm that AGAV-Rater enhances VTA performance and user experience. The project page is available at https://agav-rater.github.io.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18314v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuqin Cao, Xiongkuo Min, Yixuan Gao, Wei Sun, Guangtao Zhai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Audiovisual Speech Processing via MUTUD: Multimodal Training and Unimodal Deployment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18157v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Building reliable speech systems often requires combining multiple modalities, like audio and visual cues. While such multimodal solutions frequently lead to improvements in performance and may even be critical in certain cases, they come with several constraints such as increased sensory requirements, computational cost, and modality synchronization, to mention a few. These challenges constrain the direct uses of these multimodal solutions in real-world applications. In this work, we develop approaches where the learning happens with all available modalities but the deployment or inference is done with just one or reduced modalities. To do so, we propose a Multimodal Training and Unimodal Deployment (MUTUD) framework which includes a Temporally Aligned Modality feature Estimation (TAME) module that can estimate information from missing modality using modalities present during inference. This innovative approach facilitates the integration of information across different modalities, enhancing the overall inference process by leveraging the strengths of each modality to compensate for the absence of certain modalities during inference. We apply MUTUD to various audiovisual speech tasks and show that it can reduce the performance gap between the multimodal and corresponding unimodal models to a considerable extent. MUTUD can achieve this while reducing the model size and compute compared to multimodal models, in some cases by almost 80%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18157v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joanna Hong, Sanjeel Parekh, Honglie Chen, Jacob Donley, Ke Tan, Buye Xu, Anurag Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inkspire: Supporting Design Exploration with Generative AI through Analogical Sketching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18588v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With recent advancements in the capabilities of Text-to-Image (T2I) AI models, product designers have begun experimenting with them in their work. However, T2I models struggle to interpret abstract language and the current user experience of T2I tools can induce design fixation rather than a more iterative, exploratory process. To address these challenges, we developed Inkspire, a sketch-driven tool that supports designers in prototyping product design concepts with analogical inspirations and a complete sketch-to-design-to-sketch feedback loop. To inform the design of Inkspire, we conducted an exchange session with designers and distilled design goals for improving T2I interactions. In a within-subjects study comparing Inkspire to ControlNet, we found that Inkspire supported designers with more inspiration and exploration of design ideas, and improved aspects of the co-creative process by allowing designers to effectively grasp the current state of the AI to guide it towards novel design intentions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18588v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3706598.3713397</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Chuan-En Lin, Hyeonsu B. Kang, Nikolas Martelaro, Aniket Kittur, Yan-Ying Chen, Matthew K. Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamArtist++: Controllable One-Shot Text-to-Image Generation via Positive-Negative Adapter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.11337v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: State-of-the-arts text-to-image generation models such as Imagen and Stable Diffusion Model have succeed remarkable progresses in synthesizing high-quality, feature-rich images with high resolution guided by human text prompts. Since certain characteristics of image content \emph{e.g.}, very specific object entities or styles, are very hard to be accurately described by text, some example-based image generation approaches have been proposed, \emph{i.e.} generating new concepts based on absorbing the salient features of a few input references. Despite of acknowledged successes, these methods have struggled on accurately capturing the reference examples' characteristics while keeping diverse and high-quality image generation, particularly in the one-shot scenario (\emph{i.e.} given only one reference). To tackle this problem, we propose a simple yet effective framework, namely DreamArtist, which adopts a novel positive-negative prompt-tuning learning strategy on the pre-trained diffusion model, and it has shown to well handle the trade-off between the accurate controllability and fidelity of image generation with only one reference example. Specifically, our proposed framework incorporates both positive and negative embeddings or adapters and optimizes them in a joint manner. The positive part aggressively captures the salient characteristics of the reference image to drive diversified generation and the negative part rectifies inadequacies from the positive part. We have conducted extensive experiments and evaluated the proposed method from image similarity (fidelity) and diversity, generation controllability, and style cloning. And our DreamArtist has achieved a superior generation performance over existing methods. Besides, our additional evaluation on extended tasks, including concept compositions and prompt-guided image editing, demonstrates its effectiveness for more applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.11337v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyi Dong, Pengxu Wei, Liang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EmoDubber: Towards High Quality and Emotion Controllable Movie Dubbing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08988v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a piece of text, a video clip, and a reference audio, the movie dubbing task aims to generate speech that aligns with the video while cloning the desired voice. The existing methods have two primary deficiencies: (1) They struggle to simultaneously hold audio-visual sync and achieve clear pronunciation; (2) They lack the capacity to express user-defined emotions. To address these problems, we propose EmoDubber, an emotion-controllable dubbing architecture that allows users to specify emotion type and emotional intensity while satisfying high-quality lip sync and pronunciation. Specifically, we first design Lip-related Prosody Aligning (LPA), which focuses on learning the inherent consistency between lip motion and prosody variation by duration level contrastive learning to incorporate reasonable alignment. Then, we design Pronunciation Enhancing (PE) strategy to fuse the video-level phoneme sequences by efficient conformer to improve speech intelligibility. Next, the speaker identity adapting module aims to decode acoustics prior and inject the speaker style embedding. After that, the proposed Flow-based User Emotion Controlling (FUEC) is used to synthesize waveform by flow matching prediction network conditioned on acoustics prior. In this process, the FUEC determines the gradient direction and guidance scale based on the user's emotion instructions by the positive and negative guidance mechanism, which focuses on amplifying the desired emotion while suppressing others. Extensive experimental results on three benchmark datasets demonstrate favorable performance compared to several state-of-the-art methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08988v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaoxiang Cong, Jiadong Pan, Liang Li, Yuankai Qi, Yuxin Peng, Anton van den Hengel, Jian Yang, Qingming Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
