<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.OT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.OT</link>
    <description>q-bio.OT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.OT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 04:05:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Study on the presence and density of three types of Brachyuran crabs in Shatt Al-Basra Canal, Basrah, Iraq</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The environment of the Shatt Al-Basra Canal suffers from many pollutants like is a sewage channel for all areas of Basra Governorate, in addition, the riverbanks are a dumping ground for butchery waste, dirt, construction waste, and spoiled medicines thrown into the river and its banks, leading to a lack of biodiversity in the region and the low density of existing organisms. The river banks are characterized by their dryness at low tide due to the high temperature, so they are not suitable for the life of many organisms except the eurythermal and euryhaline organisms.
  Samples of crabs were collected monthly from September 2023 to June 2024 by using a quadrate with a 1 m length end drilled to a depth of 15 cm, the air temperature at the time of sample collection ranged from 8 to 38{\deg}C, While the BOD ranged between 3.5 to 7.3 mg/L, As for TOC, it ranged from 0.25 to 0.54. The highest density recorded for the species Nasima dotilliformis was in December and reached 6ind/m2 , as the highest density of the species Leptochryseus kuwaitensis was 4ind/m2 in February, and the highest density of the species Ilyoplax stevensi was in December and January, reaching 4ind/m2. The species N. dotilloformis was characterized by its appearance throughout the study period, while the other two species were absent for many months, while the the species L. kuwaitensis was characterized by a lower appearance and lower density.
  Temperature had the greatest impact on the presence and density of the crab community and was the greatest controller of the rest of the other factors and a basic factor in the dryness of the riverbank soil. The statistical analysis results also showed a significant inverse correlation between temperature and biological oxygen demand (BOD) and a non-significant direct correlation between temperature and total organic carbon (TOC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04233v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anfas N. Okash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metabolic allometric scaling of multicellular organisms as a product of evolutionary development and optimization of food chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.00098</link>
      <description>arXiv:1612.00098v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Production of energy is a foundation of life. Metabolic rate of organisms (amount of energy produced per unit time) generally increases slower than organisms' mass, which has important implications for life organization. This phenomenon, when considered across different taxa, is called interspecific allometric scaling. Its origin has puzzled scientists for many decades, and still is considered unknown. In this paper we posit that natural selection, as determined by evolutionary pressures, leads to distribution of resources, and accordingly energy, within a food chain, which is optimal from the perspective of stability of the food chain, when each species has sufficient amount of resources for continuous reproduction, but not too much to jeopardize existence of other species. Metabolic allometric scaling is then a quantitative representation of this optimal distribution. Taking locomotion and the primary mechanism for distribution of energy, we developed a biomechanical model to find energy expenditures, considering limb length, skeleton mass and speed. Using the interspecific allometric exponents for these three measures and substituting into the locomotion-derived model for energy expenditure, we calculated allometric exponents for mammals, reptiles, fish and birds, and compared these values with allometric exponents derived from experimental observations. The calculated allometric exponents were nearly identical to experimentally observed exponents for mammals, and very close for fish, reptiles and the basal metabolic rate of birds. The main result of the study is that the metabolic allometric scaling is a function of a mechanism of optimal energy distribution between the species of a food chain. This optimized sharing of common resources provides stability of a food chain for a given habitat and is guided by evolutionary pressures and natural selection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1612.00098v5</guid>
      <category>q-bio.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S1793048024500061</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Biophysical Reviews and Letters, Vol. 19, No. 2, 67-119 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuri K. Shestopaloff</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
