<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.OT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.OT</link>
    <description>q-bio.OT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.OT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 02:44:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Toward AI-Ready Medical Imaging Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Medical imaging data plays a vital role in disease diagnosis, monitoring, and clinical research discovery. Biomedical data managers and clinical researchers must navigate a complex landscape of medical imaging infrastructure, input/output tools and data reliability workflow configurations taking months to operationalize.
  While standard formats exist for medical imaging data, standard operating procedures (SOPs) for data management are lacking. These data management SOPs are key for developing Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR) data, a prerequisite for AI-ready datasets.
  The National Institutes of Health (NIH) Bridge to Artificial Intelligence (Bridge2AI) Standards Working Group members and domain-expert stakeholders from the Bridge2AI Grand Challenges teams developed data management SOPs for the Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine (DICOM) format.
  We describe novel SOPs applying to both static and cutting edge video imaging modalities. We emphasize steps required for centralized data aggregation, validation, and de-identification, including a review of new defacing methods for facial DICOM scans, anticipating adversarial AI/ML data re-identification methods. Data management vignettes based on Bridge2AI datasets include example parameters for efficient capture of a wide modality spectrum, including datasets from new ophthalmology retinal scans DICOM modalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03541v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milen Nikolov, Edilberto Amorim, J Harry Caufield, Nayoon Gim, Nomi L Harris, Jared Houghtaling, Xiang Li, Danielle Morrison, Ana\"is Rameau, Jamie Shaffer, Hari Trivedi, Monica C Munoz-Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
