<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 02:30:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Compatible anti-pre-Lie algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16273v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the notion of compatible anti-pre-Lie algebras and study relationship between them and the related structures such as anti-$\mathcal{O}$-operators, commutative $2$-cocycles on compatible Lie algebras. Moreover, we give the classification of $2$-dimensional compatible anti-pre-Lie algebras from the classification of anti-pre-Lie algebras of the same dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16273v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zafar Normatov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Homogeneous Derivations of Graded Rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a novel concept in graded rings called generalized homogeneous derivations, which serve as a natural generalization of the homogeneous derivations introduced by Kanunnikov. We provide an example demonstrating that the class of homogeneous derivations is strictly contained within the class of generalized homogeneous derivations. Furthermore, we extend several significant results, originally established for prime rings, to the context of gr-prime rings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17187v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yassine Ait Mohamed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triangular Decomposition of Third Order Hermitian Tensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define lower triangular tensors, and show that all diagonal entries of such a tensor are eigenvalues of that tensor. We then define lower triangular sub-symmetric tensors, and show that the number of independent entries of a lower triangular sub-symmetric tensor is the same as that of a symmetric tensor of the same order and dimension. We further introduce third order Hermitian tensors, third order positive semi-definite Hermitian tensors, and third order positive semi-definite symmetric tensors. Third order completely positive tensors are positive semi-definite symmetric tensors. Then we show that a third order positive semi-definite Hermitian tensor is triangularly decomposable. This generalizes the classical result of Cholesky decomposition in matrix analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17368v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liqun Qi, Chunfeng Cui, Ziyan Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A characterization of varieties of algebras of proper central exponent equal to two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a field of characteristic zero and let $ \mathcal V$ be a variety of associative $F$-algebras. In \cite{regev2016} Regev introduced a numerical sequence measuring the growth of the proper central polynomials of a generating algebra of $ \mathcal V$. Such sequence $c_n^\delta(\mathcal V), \, n \ge 1,$ is called the sequence of proper central polynomials of $ \mathcal V$ and in \cite{GZ2018}, \cite{GZ2019} the authors computed its exponential growth. This is an invariant of the variety. They also showed that $c_n^\delta(\mathcal V)$ either grows exponentially or is polynomially bounded. The purpose of this paper is to characterize the varieties of associative algebras whose exponential growth of $c_n^\delta(\mathcal V)$ is greater than two. As a consequence, we find a characterization of the varieties whose corresponding exponential growth is equal to two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17689v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. S. Benanti, A. Valenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unimodular bilinear lattices, automorphism groups, vanishing cycles, monodromy groups, distinguished bases, braid group actions and moduli spaces from upper triangular matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16570v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This monograph starts with an upper triangular matrix with integer entries and 1's on the diagonal. It develops from this a spectrum of structures, which appear in different contexts, in algebraic geometry, representation theory and the theory of irregular meromorphic connections. It provides general tools to study these structures, and it studies sytematically the cases of rank 2 and 3. The rank 3 cases lead already to a rich variety of phenomena and give an idea of the general landscape. The first structure associated to the matrix is a Z-lattice with unimodular bilinear form (called Seifert form) and a triangular basis. It leads immediately to an even and an odd intersection form, reflections and transvections, an even and an odd monodromy group, even and odd vanishing cycles. Braid group actions lead to braid group orbits of distinguished bases and of upper triangular matrices. Finally, complex manifolds, which consist of correctly glued Stokes regions, are associated to these braid group orbits. The last chapter is a report on the case of isolated hypersurface singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16570v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claus Hertling, Khadija Larabi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular vectors, characters, and composition series for the N=1 BMS superalgebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17000v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the structure of Verma modules over the N=1 BMS superalgebra. We provide a detailed classification of singular vectors, establish necessary and sufficient conditions for the existence of subsingular vectors, uncover the structure of maximal submodules, present the composition series of Verma modules, and derive character formulas for irreducible highest weight modules. As a byproduct, we also explicitly determine all singular vectors, subsingular vectors, and the composition series of Verma modules over the algebra W(2,2).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17000v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Jiang, Dong Liu, Yufeng Pei, Kaiming Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cancellations for dispersive PDEs with random initial data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17051v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we provide a combinatorial formalism for dealing with the cancellations that have appeared recently in the context of dispersive PDEs with random initial data. The main idea is to transform iterated integrals encoded by decorated trees into words via an arborification map. This provides a formalism alternative to the one of molecules introduced by Deng and Hani (2023). It allows us to compute the cancellations coming from Wave turbulence and the proof of the invariance of the Gibbs measure under the dynamics of the three-dimensional cubic wave equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17051v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yvain Bruned, Leonardo Tolomeo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformations and homotopy theory of Nijenhuis associative algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17253v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper is the first in a series of works devoted to an operadic study of Nijenhuis structures, focusing on Nijenhuis associative algebras. We introduce the concept of homotopy Nijenhuis associative algebras and demonstrate that the differential graded (=dg) operad $\NjAoperad_{\infty}$ governing these structures serves as the minimal model of the operad $\NjAoperad$ for Nijenhuis associative algebras. Additionally, we determine the Koszul dual homotopy cooperad of $\NjAoperad$. We construct an $L_\infty$-algebra that controls the simultaneous deformations of associative products and Nijenhuis operators. The Maurer-Cartan elements of this $L_\infty$-algebra correspond bijectively to Nijenhuis associative algebra structures. From this, we derive a cochain complex (deformation complex) and an associated cohomology theory of Nijenhuis associative algebras. Finally, we explore the connection between homotopy relative Rota-Baxter associative algebras of weight $0$ and homotopy Nijenhuis associative algebras. A sequel to this work will extend the study to Nijenhuis Lie algebras, with applications to Nijenhuis geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17253v1</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Song, Kai Wang, Yuanyuan Zhang, Guodong Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Width bounds and Steinhaus property for unit groups of continuous rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17480v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove an algebraic decomposition theorem for the unit group $\mathrm{GL}(R)$ of an arbitrary non-discrete irreducible, continuous ring $R$ (in von Neumann's sense), which entails that every element of $\mathrm{GL}(R)$ is both a product of $7$ commutators and a product of $16$ involutions. Combining this with further insights into the geometry of involutions, we deduce that $\mathrm{GL}(R)$ has the so-called Steinhaus property with respect to the natural rank topology, thus every homomorphism from $\mathrm{GL}(R)$ to a separable topological group is necessarily continuous. Due to earlier work, this has further dynamical ramifications: for instance, for every action of $\mathrm{GL}(R)$ by homeomorphisms on a non-void metrizable compact space, every element of $\mathrm{GL}(R)$ admits a fixed point in the latter. In particular, our results answer two questions by Carderi and Thom, even in generalized form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17480v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josefin Bernard, Friedrich Martin Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beck modules and alternative algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07962v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We set out the general theory of ``Beck modules'' in a variety of algebras and describe them as modules over suitable ``universal enveloping'' unital associative algebras. We develop a theory of ``noncommutative partial differentiation'' to pass from the equations of the variety to relations in a universal enveloping algebra. We pay particular attention to the case of alternative algebras, defined by a restricted associative law, and determine the Poincar\'e polynomial of the universal enveloping algebra in the homogeneous case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07962v4</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nishant Dhankhar, Haynes Miller, Ali Tahboub, Victor Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak Hopf algebra structures on hybrid numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02313v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb{K}$ be the set of hybrid numbers. This paper is to look for all the weak Hopf structures on $\mathbb{K}$. Once $\mathbb{K}$ is endowed with a structure of a weak Hopf algebra, we shall compute the source algebra and target algebra of $\mathbb{K}$. Also, we shall discuss the integrals in such weak Hopf algebra $\mathbb{K}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02313v4</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tang Jiangang, Chen Quanguo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost classical skew bracoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10268v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate two sub-classes of skew bracoids, the first consists of those we term almost a brace, meaning the multiplicative group decomposes as a certain semi-direct product, and then those that are almost classical, which additionally specifies the relationship between the multiplicative group and the additive. Skew bracoids with these properties have applications in Hopf-Galois theory, in particular for questions concerning the Hopf-Galois correspondence, and can also yield solutions to the set-theoretic Yang-Baxter equation. We use this skew bracoid perspective to give a new construction building on the induced Hopf-Galois structures of Crespo, Rio and Vela, recover a result of Greither and Pareigis on the Hopf-Galois correspondence, and examine the solutions that arise from skew bracoids, in particular where more than one solution may be drawn from a single skew bracoid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10268v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabel Martin-Lyons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Averaging groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11600v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rota-Baxter operators on groups were studied quite recently. Motivated mainly by the fact that weight zero Rota-Baxter operators and averaging operators are Koszul dual to each other, we propose the concepts of averaging group and averaging Hopf algebra, and study relationships among them and the existing averaging Lie algebras. We also show that an averaging group induces a disemigroup and a rack, respectively. As the free object is one of the most significant objects in a category, we also construct explicitly the free averaging group on a set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11600v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huhu Zhang, Xing Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum group deformations and quantum $ R $-(co)matrices vs. Quantum Duality Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15096v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we describe the effect on quantum groups -- namely, both QUEA's and QFSHA's -- of deformations by twist and by 2-cocycles, showing how such deformations affect the semiclassical limit. As a second, more important task, we discuss how these deformation procedures can be "stretched" to a new extent, via a formal variation of the original recipes, using "polar twists" and "polar 2-cocycles". These recipes seemingly should make no sense at all, yet we prove that they actually work, thus providing well-defined, more general deformation procedures. Later on, we explain the underlying reason that motivates such a result in light of the "Quantum Duality Principle", through which every "polar twist/2-cocycle" for a given quantum group can be seen as a standard twist/2-cocycle for another quantum group, associated to the original one via the appropriate Drinfeld functor. As a third task, we consider standard constructions involving $R$-(co)matrices in the general theory of Hopf algebras. First we adapt them to quantum groups, then we show that they extend to the case of "polar $R$-(co)matrices", and finally we discuss how these constructions interact with the Quantum Duality Principle. As a byproduct, this yields new special symmetries (isomorphisms) for the underlying pair of dual Poisson (formal) groups that one gets by specialization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15096v3</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gast\'on Andr\'es Garc\'ia, Fabio Gavarini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
