<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>D\'eterminant d'une matrice carr\'ee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03998v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We are interested in matrices of minors of order p of a invertible matrix. Special cases are studied when this matrix is in SL(n) or SO(n)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03998v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisabeth Remm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Dextral Symmetric Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define the notion of dextral symmetric algebras (not necessarily associative), motivated by the idea of symmetric rings. We derive a complete classification of dextral symmetric algebras of Leavitt path algebras, and right Leibniz algebras up to dimension $4$. We also obtain that a finite-dimensional dextral symmetric right Leibniz algebra is solvable if and only if it satisfies a weaker notion of nilpotency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04013v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimpy M. Dutta, Shanborlang Bynnud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A classification of nilpotent compatible Lie algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04036v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Working over an arbitrary field of characteristic different from $2$, we extend the Skjelbred-Sund method to compatible Lie algebras and give a full classification of nilpotent compatible Lie algebras up to dimension $4$. In case the base field is cubically closed, we find that there are three isomorphism classes and a one-parameter family in dimension $3$, and $10$ isomorphism classes, $7$ one-parameter families and two $2$-parameter families in dimension $4$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04036v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Ladra, Bernardo Leite da Cunha, Samuel A. Lopes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twists of twisted generalized Weyl algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study graded twisted tensor products and graded twists of twisted generalized Weyl algebras (TGWAs). We show that the class of TGWAs is closed under these operations assuming mild hypotheses. We generalize a result on cocycle equivalence amongst multiparameter quantized Weyl algebras to the setting of TGWAs. As another application we prove that certain TGWAs of type $A_2$ are noetherian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04172v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Gaddis, Daniele Rosso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Root graded groups revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03558v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A group $G$ is called root graded if it has a family of subgroups $G_\alpha$ indexed by roots from a root system $\Phi$ satisfying natural conditions similar to Chevalley groups over commutative unital rings. For any such group there is a corresponding algebraic structure (commutative unital ring, associative unital ring, etc.) encoding the commutator relations between $G_\alpha$. We give a complete description of varieties of such structures for irreducible root systems of rank $\geq 3$ excluding $\mathsf H_3$ and $\mathsf H_4$. Moreover, we provide a construction of root graded groups for all algebraic structures from these varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03558v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Egor Voronetsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyclically ordered quivers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03604v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A cyclically ordered quiver is a quiver endowed with an additional structure of a cyclic ordering of its vertices. This structure, which naturally arises in many important applications, gives rise to new powerful mutation invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03604v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Fomin, Scott Neville</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graded contractions of g2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05308v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graded contractions of the fine $\mathbb{Z}_2^3$-grading on the complex exceptional Lie algebra $\mathfrak{g}_2$ are classified up to equivalence and up to strongly equivalence. In particular, a large family of 14-dimensional Lie algebras arise, most of them solvable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05308v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristina Draper, Juana Sanchez Ortega, Thomas Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dedekind Superrings and Related Concepts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03822v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the concept of Dedekind superrings, investigate its properties, and compare them to those of the classical Dedekind rings. We also define invertible supermodules, fractional superideals, the Picard group of a superring, and the ideal class group of a superring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03822v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Rizzo, Joel Torres Del Valle, Alexander Torres-Gomez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rota--Baxter operators and skew left brace structures over Heisenberg Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rota--Baxter operators over groups have been recently defined in \cite{LHY2021}, and they share a close connection with skew braces, as demonstrated in \cite{VV2022}. In this paper, we classify all Rota--Baxter operators of weight 1 over the Heisenberg Lie algebra of dimension 3 by directly solving the operators defining equations. Using the fact that the exponential map from the Heisenberg Lie algebra to the Heisenberg Group is bijective, we induces these operators to the Heisenberg Group. Finally, we enumerate all skew left brace structures over the Heisenberg Group induced by these Rota--Baxter operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15428v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nishant Rathee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Varieties of MV-monoids and positive MV-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08471v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: MV-monoids are algebras $\langle A,\vee,\wedge, \oplus,\odot, 0,1\rangle$ where $\langle A, \vee, \wedge, 0, 1\rangle$ is a bounded distributive lattice, both $\langle A, \oplus, 0 \rangle$ and $\langle A, \odot, 1\rangle$ are commutative monoids, and some further connecting axioms are satisfied. Every MV-algebra in the signature $\{\oplus,\neg,0\}$ is term equivalent to an algebra that has an MV-monoid as a reduct, by defining, as standard, $1:= \neg 0$, $x \odot y := \neg(\neg x \oplus\neg y)$, $x \vee y := (x \odot \neg y) \oplus y$ and $x \wedge y := \neg(\neg x \vee \neg y)$. Particular examples of MV-monoids are positive MV-algebras, i.e. the $\{\vee, \wedge, \oplus, \odot, 0, 1\}$-subreducts of MV-algebras. Positive MV-algebras form a peculiar quasivariety in the sense that, albeit having a logical motivation (being the quasivariety of subreducts of MV-algebras), it is not the equivalent quasivariety semantics of any logic. In this paper, we study the lattices of subvarieties of MV-monoids and of positive MV-algebras. In particular, we characterize and axiomatize all almost minimal varieties of MV-monoids, we characterize the finite subdirectly irreducible positive MV-algebras, and we characterize and axiomatize all varieties of positive MV-algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08471v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Abbadini, Paolo Aglian\`o, Stefano Fioravanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Position: Categorical Deep Learning is an Algebraic Theory of All Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15332v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present our position on the elusive quest for a general-purpose framework for specifying and studying deep learning architectures. Our opinion is that the key attempts made so far lack a coherent bridge between specifying constraints which models must satisfy and specifying their implementations. Focusing on building a such a bridge, we propose to apply category theory -- precisely, the universal algebra of monads valued in a 2-category of parametric maps -- as a single theory elegantly subsuming both of these flavours of neural network design. To defend our position, we show how this theory recovers constraints induced by geometric deep learning, as well as implementations of many architectures drawn from the diverse landscape of neural networks, such as RNNs. We also illustrate how the theory naturally encodes many standard constructs in computer science and automata theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15332v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Gavranovi\'c, Paul Lessard, Andrew Dudzik, Tamara von Glehn, Jo\~ao G. M. Ara\'ujo, Petar Veli\v{c}kovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
