<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 03:59:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Almost classical skew bracoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate two sub-classes of skew bracoids, the first consists of those we term almost a brace, meaning the multiplicative group decomposes as a certain semi-direct product, and then those that are almost classical, which additionally specifies the relationship between the multiplicative group and the additive. Skew bracoids with these properties have applications in Hopf-Galois theory, in particular for questions concerning the Hopf-Galois correspondence, and can also yield solutions to the set-theoretic Yang-Baxter equation. We use this skew bracoid perspective to give a new construction building on the induced Hopf-Galois structures of Crespo, Rio and Vela, recover a result of Greither and Pareigis on the Hopf-Galois correspondence, and examine the solutions that arise from skew bracoids, in particular where more than one solution may be drawn from a single skew bracoid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10268v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabel Martin-Lyons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Codes in algebras of direct products of groups and associated quantum codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09695v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we obtain the Wedderburn-Artin decomposition of a semisimple group algebra associated to a direct product of finite groups. We also provide formulae for the number of all possible group codes, and their dimensions, that can be constructed in a group algebra. As particular cases, we present the complete algebraic description of the group algebra of any direct product of groups whose direct factors are cyclic, dihedral, or generalised quaternion groups. Finally, in the specific case of semisimple dihedral group algebras, we give a method to build quantum error-correcting codes, based on the CSS construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09695v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Sales, Xaro Soler-Escriv\`a, V\'ictor Sotomayor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>M\"obius function for modules and thin representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05656v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies the M\"obius function and related questions about the finiteness of the poset of submodules of semisimple and general modules. We show how to calculate the M\"obius function for semisimple modules based on endomorphism rings of simple submodules. We discuss the M\"obius function for representations of bounded path algebras in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05656v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Krasula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endomorphism rings of simple modules and block decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A left and right noetherian semiperfect ring R is known to be indecomposable if and only if its factor by the second power of Jacobson radical is. This characterisation is used to study simple R-modules in terms of their Ext groups. It is shown that if R is indecomposable, all its simple modules are either finite or have the same infinite cardinality and their endomorphism rings have the same characteristics. The results are further strengthened in the case when R is quasi-Frobenius.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13582v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Krasula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the asymptotic behaviour of the graded-star-codimension sequence of upper triangular matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00087v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the algebra of upper triangular matrices endowed with a group grading and a homogeneous involution over an infinite field. We compute the asymptotic behaviour of its (graded) star-codimension sequence. It turns out that the asymptotic growth of the sequence is independent of the grading and the involution under consideration, depending solely on the size of the matrix algebra. This independence of the group grading also applies to the graded codimension sequence of the associative algebra of upper triangular matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00087v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.46298/cm.14050</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Mathematics 33 (2025), no. 1</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Diogo Diniz, Felipe Yukihide Yasumura</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
