<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 01:50:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Moves for Bergman algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define Bergman presentations and Bergman algebras associated to Bergman presentations. These algebras embrace various generalisations of Leavitt path algebras. A Bergman presentation can be visualised by a Bergman graph, which is a finite bicoloured hypergraph satisfying two conditions. We define several moves for Bergman graphs and prove that they preserve the isomorphism class (respectively the Morita equivalence class) of the corresponding Bergman algebra. One recovers the well-known results, that in the context of finite directed graphs the shift move, outsplitting, insplitting, source elimination and collapsing preserve the isomorphism class (respectively the Morita equivalence class) of the corresponding Leavitt path algebra. Moreover, we mention some connections between Tietze transformations and the moves for Bergman graphs defined in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00208v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raimund Preusser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superalgebras with Homogeneous structures of Lie type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend the concept of Lie superalgebras to a more generalized framework called Super-Lie superalgebras. In addition, they seem to be exploring various supergeneralizations of other algebraic structures, such as Super-associative, left (right) Super-Leibniz, and Super-left(right)-symmetric superalgebras, then we give some examples and related fundamental results. The notion of Rota-Baxter operators with any parity on the Super-Lie superalgebras is given. Moreover, we study a representations of Super-Lie superalgebras and its associate dual representations. The notion of derivations of Super-Lie superalgebras is introduced thus we show that the converse of a bijective derivation defines a Rota-Baxter operator. Finally, we give a generalization of the Super-Lie superalgebras and some other structures in the ternary case which we supported this with some examples and interesting results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00618v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sami Mabrouk, Othmen Ncib</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-involutive solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation of multipermutation level 2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study non-degenerate set-theoretic solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation of multipermutation level 2 which are not 2-reductive. We describe an effective way of constructing such solutions using square-free 2-reductive solutions and two bijections. We present an algorithm how to obtain all such finite solutions, up to isomorphism. Using this algorithm, we enumerate all solutions of multipermutation level 2 up to size 6.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00755v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Hora, Premysl Jedlicka, Agata Pilitowska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero product and zero Jordan product determined Munn algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\mathfrak{M}(\mathbb{D}, m, n, P)$ be the ring of all $m \times n$ matrices over a division ring $\mathbb{D}$, with the product given by $A \bullet B=A P B$, where $P$ is a fixed $n \times m$ matrix over $\mathbb{D}$. When $2\leq m, n &lt;\infty$ and $\operatorname{rank} P \geq 2$, we demonstrate that every element in $\mathcal{A}=\mathfrak{M}(\mathbb{D}, m, n, P)$ is a sum of finite products of pairs of commutators. We also estimate the minimal number $N$ such that $\mathcal{A}= \sum^N [\mathcal{A}, \mathcal{A}][\mathcal{A}, \mathcal{A}]$. Furthermore, if $\operatorname{char}\mathbb{D}\neq 2$, we prove that $\mathfrak{M}(\mathbb{D}, m, n, P)$ is additively spanned by Jordan products of idempotents. For a field $\mathbb{F}$ with $\operatorname{char}\mathbb{F}\neq 2, 3$, we show that the Munn algebra $\mathfrak{M}(\mathbb{F}, m, n, P)$ is zero product determined and zero Jordan product determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00892v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Yu, Kaijia Luo, Jiankui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A straightforward construction of $\Bbb Z$-graded Lie algebras of full-fledged nonlocal symmetries via recursion operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00622v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the reduced quasi-classical self-dual Yang-Mills equation (rYME) and two recently found (Jahnov\'{a} and Voj\v{c}\'{a}k, 2024) invertible recursion operators $\mathcal{R}^q$ and $\mathcal{R}^m$ for its full-fledged (in a given differential covering) nonlocal symmetries. We introduce a $\mathbb{Z}$-grading on the Lie algebra $\mathrm{sym}_{\mathcal{L}}^{\tau^W} (\mathcal E)$ of all nonlocal Laurent polynomial symmetries of the rYME and prove that both the operators $\mathcal{R}^q$ and $\mathcal{R}^m$ are $\mathbb{Z}$-graded automorphisms of the underlying vector space on the set $\mathrm{sym}_{\mathcal{L}}^{\tau^W} (\mathcal E)$. This inter alia implies that all its vector subspaces formed by all homogeneous elements of a given fixed degree (i.e. a weight in the context below) are mutually isomorphic, and thus each of them can be uniquely reconstructed from the vector space of all homogeneous symmetries of the zero degree. To the best of our knowledge, such a result is unparalleled in the current body of literature. The obtained results are used for the construction of a Lie subalgebra $V$ of $\mathrm{sym}_{\mathcal{L}}^{\tau^W} (\mathcal E)$ which contains all known to us nonlocal Laurent polynomial symmetries of the rYME. The Lie algebra $V$ is subsequently described as the linear span of the orbits of a set of selected zero-weight symmetries - we refer to them as to the seed generators of $V$. Further, we study the hierarchies of symmetries related to the seed generators under the action of the group of recursion operators generated by $\mathcal{R}^q$ and $\mathcal{R}^m$. Finally, the linear dependence/independence of the (sub)set of generators of $V$ is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00622v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jirina Jahnova, Petr Vojcak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inner isotopes associated with automorphisms of commutative associative algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16284v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The principal observation of the present paper is that an inner isotopy (i.e. a principal isotopy defined by an algebra endomorphism) is a very helpful instrument in constructing and studying interesting classes of nonassociative algebras. By using methods developed in the paper, we define a new class of commutative nonassociative algebras obtained by inner isotopy from commutative associative polynomial algebras. There is a natural bijection between isomorphism classes of our algebras and integer partitions of the algebra dimensions. Among the interesting features of the nonassociative algebras constructed are that these algebras are generic, some of examples are axial and metrized algebras. We completely describe both the set of algebra idempotents and their spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16284v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir G. Tkachev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagonals of solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15652v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the diagonal mappings in non-involutive set-theoretic solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation. We show that, for non-degenerate solutions, they are commuting bijections. This gives the positive answer to the question: ``Is every non-degenerate solution bijective?'' of Ced\'{o}, Jespers and Verwimp. Additionally, we show that for a subclass of solutions called k-permutational, only one-sided non-degeneracy suffices to prove that one of the diagonal mappings is invertible. We also present an equational characterization of multipermutation solutions and extend results of Rump and Gateva-Ivanova about decomposability to non-involutive case. In particular, we show that each, not necessarily involutive, square-free multipermutation solution of finite level and arbitrary cardinality, is always decomposable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15652v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Premysl Jedlicka, Agata Pilitowska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The face numbers of homology spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03322</link>
      <description>arXiv:1706.03322v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $g$-theorem is a momentous result in combinatorics that gives a complete numerical characterization of the face numbers of simplicial convex polytopes. The $g$-conjecture asserts that the same numerical conditions given in the $g$-theorem also characterizes the face numbers of all simplicial spheres, or even more generally, all simplicial homology spheres.
  In this paper, we prove the $g$-conjecture for simplicial $\mathbb{R}$-homology spheres. A key idea in our proof is a new algebra structure for polytopal complexes. Given a polytopal $d$-complex $\Delta$, we use ideas from rigidity theory to construct a graded Artinian $\mathbb{R}$-algebra $\Psi(\Delta,\nu)$ of stresses on a PL realization $\nu$ of $\Delta$ in $\mathbb{R}^d$, where overlapping realized $d$-faces are allowed. In particular, we prove that if $\Delta$ is a simplicial $\mathbb{R}$-homology sphere, then for generic PL realizations $\nu$, the stress algebra $\Psi(\Delta,\nu)$ is Gorenstein and has the weak Lefschetz property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1706.03322v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Fong Ernest Chong, Tiong Seng Tay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing the noncommutative inner rank by means of operator-valued free probability theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.03667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.03667v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We address the noncommutative version of the Edmonds' problem, which asks to determine the inner rank of a matrix in noncommuting variables. We provide an algorithm for the calculation of this inner rank by relating the problem with the distribution of a basic object in free probability theory, namely operator-valued semicircular elements. We have to solve a matrix-valued quadratic equation, for which we provide precise analytical and numerical control on the fixed point algorithm for solving the equation. Numerical examples show the efficiency of the algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.03667v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Hoffmann, Tobias Mai, Roland Speicher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Durdevic approach to quantum principal bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07944v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit and extend the Durdevic theory of complete calculi on quantum principal bundles. In this setting one naturally obtains a graded Hopf-Galois extension of the higher order calculus and an intrinsic decomposition of degree 1-forms into horizontal and vertical forms. This proposal is appealing, since it is consistently equipped with a canonical braiding and exactness of the Atiyah sequence is guaranteed. Moreover, we provide examples of complete calculi, including the noncommutative 2-torus, the quantum Hopf fibration and differential calculi on crossed product algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07944v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Del Donno, Emanuele Latini, Thomas Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
