<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 04:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomologies of Reynolds Lie-Yamaguti algebras of any weight and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12859v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The purpose of the present paper is to investigate cohomologies of Reynolds Lie-Yamaguti algebras of any weight and provide some applications. First, we introduce the notion of Reynolds Lie-Yamaguti algebras and give some new examples. Moreover, cohomologies of Reynolds operators and Reynolds Lie-Yamaguti algebras with coefficients in a suitable representation are established. Finally, formal deformations and abelian extensions of Reynolds Lie-Yamaguti algebras are characterized in terms of lower degree cohomology groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12859v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Teng, Shuangjian Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isomorphisms between lattices of hyperinvariant subspaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given two nilpotent endomorphisms, we determine when their lattices of hyperinvariant subspaces are isomorphic. The study of the lattice of hyperinvariant subspaces can be reduced to the nilpotent case when the endomorphism has a Jordan-Chevalley decomposition; for example, it occurs if the underlying field is the field of complex numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12861v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Mingueza, M. Eul\`alia Montoro, Alicia Roca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skew-supersymmetric solution of the super Malcev Yang-Baxter equation and Pre-Malcev superalgebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12866v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The purpose of this paper is to introduce the notion of pre-Malcev superalgebras as the algebraic structure behind the super $\mathcal{O}$-operators on Malcev superalgebras. Moreover, the relations among Malcev superalgebras, pre-Malcev superalgebras and pre-alternative superalgebras are established. Then, we study the operator forms of the classical Yang-Baxter equation (CYBE) in Malcev superalgebras and give their relationship with super $\mathcal{O}$-operators. There are close relationships between the CYBE in Malcev superalgebras and pre-Malcev superalgebras which can be interpreted through the super $\mathcal{O}$-operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12866v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fattoum Harrathi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted differential ($q$-tri)dendriform algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we first introduce a weighted derivation on algebras over an operad $\cal P$, and prove that for the free $\cal P$-algebra, its weighted derivation is determined by the restriction on the generators. As applications, we propose the concept of weighted differential ($q$-tri)dendriform algebras and study some basic properties of them. Then Novikov-(tri)dendriform algebras are initiated, which can be induced from differential ($q$-tri) dendriform of weight zero. Finally, the corresponding free objects are constructed, in both the commutative and noncommutative contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12871v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanyuan Zhang, Huhu Zhang, Tingzeng Wu, Xing Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the third cohomology of the Lie algebra of vector fields on weighted densities on R</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let Vect($\mathbb{R}$) be the Lie algebra of smooth vector fields on $\mathbb{R}$ and $\mathbb{F}_{\lambda}$ be the space of $\lambda$-densities on $\mathbb{R}$.
  Vect($\mathbb{R}$) acts on $\mathbb{F}_{\lambda}$ by Lie derivative. In this paper, we compute the third differential cohomology of the Lie algebra Vect($\mathbb{R}$) with coeffcients in the space $\mathbb{F}_{\lambda}.$ Explicit cocycles spanning these cohomology spaces are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12872v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wajd Afsi, Salem Omri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphisms of free metabelian Lie algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that every automorphism of a free metabelian Lie algebra $M_n$ of rank $n\geq 4$ over an arbitrary field $K$ is almost tame, that is, it is a product of so-called Chein automorphisms (or one-row transformations). Moreover, we show that the group of all automorphisms $\mathrm{Aut}(M_n)$ of $M_n$ of rank $n\geq 4$ over a field $K$ of characteristic $\neq 3$ is generated by all linear automorphisms, as well as one quadratic and one cubic automorphism. The same result holds for fields of any characteristic if $n\geq 5$.
  We also show that all Chein automorphisms of lower degree $\geq 4$ and all exponential automorphisms of lower degree $\geq 5$ are tame, which contradicts the results of \cite{BN,OE}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12884v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ualbai Umirbaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The conductor ideals of maximal subrings in non-commutative rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12890v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $R$ be a maximal subring of a ring $T$, and $(R:T)$, $(R:T)_l$ and $(R:T)_r$ denote the greatest ideal, left ideal and right ideal of $T$ which are contained in $R$, respectively. It is shown that $(R:T)_l$ and $(R:T)_r$ are prime ideals of $R$ and $|Min_R((R:T))|\leq 2$. We prove that if $T_R$ has a maximal submodule, then $(R:T)_l$ is a right primitive ideal of $R$. We investigate that when $(R:T)_r$ is a completely prime (right) ideal of $R$ or $T$. If $R$ is integrally closed in $T$, then $(R:T)_l$ and $(R:T)_r$ are prime one-sided ideals of $T$. We observe that if $(R:T)_lT=T$, then $T$ is a finitely generated left $R$-module and $(R:T)_l$ is a finitely generated right $R$-module. We prove that $Char(R/(R:T)_l)=Char(R/(R:T)_r)$, and if $Char(T)$ is neither zero or a prime number, then $(R:T)\neq 0$. If $|Min(R)|\geq 3$, then $(R:T)$ and $(R:T)_l(R:T)_r$ are nonzero ideals. Finally we study the Noetherian and the Artinian properties between $R$ and $T$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12890v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alborz Azarang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical ideals theory of maximal subrings in non-commutative rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $R$ be a maximal subring of a ring $T$. In this paper we study relation between some important ideals in the ring extension $R\subseteq T$. In fact, we would like to find some relation between $Nil_*(R)$ and $Nil_*(T)$, $Nil^*(R)$ and $Nil^*(T)$, $J(R)$ and $J(T)$, $Soc({}_RR)$ and $Soc({}_RT)$, and finally $Z({}_RR)$ and $Z({}_RT)$; especially, in certain cases, for example when $T$ is a reduced ring, $R$ (or $T$) is a left Artinian ring, or $R$ is a certain maximal subring of $T$. We show that either $Soc({}_RR)=Soc({}_RT)$ or $(R:T)_r$ (the greatest right ideal of $T$ which is contained in $R$) is a left primitive ideal of $R$. We prove that if $T$ is a reduced ring, then either $Z({}_RT)=0$ or $Z({}_RT)$ is a minimal ideal of $T$, $T=R\oplus Z({}_RT)$, and $(R:T)=(R:T)_l=(R:T)_r=ann_R(Z({}_RT))$. If $T=R\oplus I$, where $I$ is an ideal of $T$, then we completely determine relation between Jacobson radicals, lower nilradicals, upper nilradicals, socle and singular ideals of $R$ and $T$. Finally, we study the relation between previous ideals of $R$ and $T$ when either $R$ or $T$ is a left Artinian ring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12891v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alborz Azarang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Dimensional Mathematics: A Foundation For STP/STA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12920v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When investigating the set of matrices and vectors with mixed dimensions (MVMD), which are posed by cross-dimensional operators: semi-tensor product (STP) and semi-tensor addition (STA), the existing mathematical tools seem not very efficient. A new mathematical structure, called the mix-dimensional mathematics (MDM), is proposed. The MDM considered in this paper consists of three parts: hyper algebra, hyper geometry, and hyper Lie group/Lie algebra. Hyper algebra proposes some new algebraic structures such as hyper group, hyper ring, and hyper module over MVMDs. They have sets of classical groups, rings, and modules as their components and cross-dimensional connections among their components. Their basic properties are investigated. Hyper geometry starts from mixed dimensional Euclidian space, and hyper vector space. Then the hyper topological vector space, hyper inner product space, and hyper manifold are constructed. They have a joined cross-dimensional geometric structure. Finally, hyper metric space, topological hyper group and hyper Lie algebra are built gradually, and finally, their corresponding hyper Lie group is introduced. All these concepts are built over MVMDs, and to reach our purpose in addition to using existing STPs and STAs, a couple of most general STP and STA are introduced. Some existing structures/results about STPs/STAs have also been resumed and integrated into this MDM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12920v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daizhan Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rings of almost everywhere defined functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13063v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the following representation theorem: A partially ordered commutative ring $R$ is a subring of a ring of almost everywhere defined continuous real-valued functions on a compact Hausdorff space $X$ if and only if $R$ is archimedean and localizable. Here we assume that the positive cone of $R$ is closed under multiplication and stable under multiplication with squares, but we also show that one of these assumptions implies the other. An almost everywhere defined function on $X$ is one that is defined on a dense open subset of $X$. These functions can be added and multiplied pointwise so that the result is again almost everywhere defined. A partially ordered commutative ring $R$ is archimedean if the underlying additive partially ordered abelian group is archimedean, and $R$ is localizable essentially if its order is compatible with the construction of a localization with sufficiently large, positive denominators. As application we obtain several more specific representation theorems: representations by continuous real-valued functions on some topological space if $R$ is $\sigma$-bounded, and representation of lattice-ordered commutative rings ($f$-rings), of partially ordered fields, and of commutative operator algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13063v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Sch\"otz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formal deformations and extensions of `twisted' Lie algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between derivations and algebraic structures has been a subject of significant interest and exploration. Inspired by Yau's twist and the Leibniz rule, we investigate the formal deformation of twisted Lie algebras by invertible derivations, herein referred to as "InvDer Lie". We define representations of InvDer Lie, elucidate cohomology structures of order 1 and 2, and identify infinitesimals as 2-cocycles. Furthermore, we explore central extensions of InvDer Lie, revealing their intricate relationship with cohomology theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13422v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Basdouri, E. Peyghan, M. A. Sadraoui, R. Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endomorphism rings of simple modules and block decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13582v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A left and right noetherian semiperfect ring R is known to be indecomposable if and only if its factor by the second power of Jacobson radical is. This characterisation is used to study simple R-modules in terms of their Ext groups. It is shown that if R is indecomposable, all its simple modules are either finite or have the same infinite cardinality and their endomorphism rings have the same characteristics. The results are further strengthened in the case when R is quasi-Frobenius.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13582v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Krasula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The triangulant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the triangulant of two matrices, and relate it to the existence of orthogonal eigenvectors. We also use it for a new characterization of mutually unbiased bases. Generalizing the notion, we introduce higher order triangulants of two matrices, and relate them to the existence of nontrivially intersecting invariant subspaces of complementary dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13421v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tam\'as Bencze, P\'eter E. Frenkel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can the quadratrix truly square the circle?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14032v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quadratrix received its name from the circle quadrature, squaring the circle, but it only solves it if completed by taking a limit, as pointed out already in antiquity. We ask if it can square the circle without limits and restrict its use accordingly, to converting ratios of angles and segments into each other. The problem is then translated into algebra by analogy to straightedge and compass constructions, and leads to an open question in transcendental number theory. In particular, Lindemann's impossibility result no longer suffices, and the answer depends on whether $\pi$ belongs to the analog of Ritt's exponential-logarithmic field with an algebraic base. We then derive that it does not from the well-known Schanuel conjecture. Thus, the quadratrix so restricted cannot square the circle after all.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14032v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Cruz, Sergiy Koshkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logical reduction of relations: from relational databases to Peirce's reduction thesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14094v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study logical reduction (factorization) of relations into relations of lower arity by Boolean or relative products that come from applying conjunctions and existential quantifiers to predicates, i.e. by primitive positive formulas of predicate calculus. Our algebraic framework unifies natural joins and data dependencies of database theory and relational algebra of clone theory with the bond algebra of C.S. Peirce. We also offer new constructions of reductions, systematically study irreducible relations and reductions to them, and introduce a new characteristic of relations, ternarity, that measures their `complexity of relating' and allows to refine reduction results. In particular, we refine Peirce's controversial reduction thesis, and show that reducibility behavior is dramatically different on finite and infinite domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14094v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/jigpal/jzad010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Logic Journal of the IGPL, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergiy Koshkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed multiquadratic splitting fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14339v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study mixed multiquadratic field extensions as splitting fields for central simple algebras of exponent $2$ in characteristic $2$. As an application, we provide examples of nonexcellent mixed biquadratic field extensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14339v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatma Kader Bing\"ol, Adam Chapman, Ahmed Laghribi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normal forms for ordinary differential operators, I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14414v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we develop the generalised Schur theory offered in the recent paper by the second author in dimension one case, and apply it to obtain two applications in different directions of algebra/algebraic geometry.
  The first application is a new explicit parametrisation of torsion free rank one sheaves on projective irreducible curves with vanishing cohomology groups.
  The second application is a commutativity criterion for operators in the Weyl algebra or, more generally, in the ring of ordinary differential operators, which we prove in the case when operators have a normal form with the restriction top line (for details see Introduction).
  Both applications are obtained with the help of normal forms. Namely, considering the ring of ordinary differential operators $D_1=K[[x]][\partial ]$ as a subring of a certain complete non-commutative ring $\hat{D}_1^{sym}$, the normal forms of differential operators mentioned here are obtained after conjugation by some invertible operator ("Schur operator"), calculated using one of the operators in a ring. Normal forms of commuting operators are polynomials with constant coefficients in the differentiation, integration and shift operators, which have a finite order in each variable, and can be effectively calculated for any given commuting operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14414v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Guo, A. B. Zheglov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to a system of Yang-Baxter matrix equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.13149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.13149v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, a system of Yang-Baxter-type matrix equations is studied, $XAX=BXB$, $XBX=AXA$, which "generalizes" the matrix Yang-Baxter equation and exhibits a broken symmetry. We investigate the solutions of this system from various geometric and topological points of view. We analyze the existence of doubly stochastic solutions and intertwining solutions to the system and describe the conditions for their existence. Furthermore, we characterize the case when $A$ and $B$ are idempotent orthogonal complements. i.e., $A^2 =A, B^2= B, AB = BA =0$. We also completely characterize the set of solutions for $n=2$ using commutative algebraic techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.13149v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himadri Mukherjee, Askar Ali M, Bogdan D. Djordjevic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolutions as directed colimits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07197v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A general principle suggests that "anything flat is a directed colimit of countably presentable flats". In this paper, we consider resolutions and coresolutions of modules over a countably coherent ring $R$ (e.g., any coherent ring or any countably Noetherian ring). We show that any $R$-module of flat dimension $n$ is a directed colimit of countably presentable $R$-modules of flat dimension at most $n$, and any flatly coresolved $R$-module is a directed colimit of countably presentable flatly coresolved $R$-modules. If $R$ is a countably coherent ring with a dualizing complex, then any F-totally acyclic complex of flat $R$-modules is a directed colimit of F-totally acyclic complexes of countably presentable flat $R$-modules. The proofs are applications of an even more general category-theoretic principle going back to an unpublished 1977 preprint of Ulmer. Our proof of the assertion that every Gorenstein-flat module over a countably coherent ring is a directed colimit of countably presentable Gorenstein-flat modules uses a different technique, based on results of Saroch and Stovicek. We also discuss totally acyclic complexes of injectives and Gorenstein-injective modules, obtaining various cardinality estimates for the accessibility rank under various assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07197v4</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid Positselski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Key varieties for prime $\mathbb{Q}$-Fano threefolds defined by Jordan algebras of cubic forms. Part I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14991v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The first aim of this paper is to construct a $13$-dimensional affine variety $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ related with $\mathbb{P}^{2}\times\mathbb{P}^{2}$-fibration. It is well-known that the affine cone of the Segre embedded $\mathbb{P}^{2}\times\mathbb{P}^{2}$ is defined as the null loci of the so called $\sharp$-mapping of a 9-dimensional nondegenerate quadratic Jordan algebra $J$ of a cubic form. Inspired with this fact, we construct $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ in the same way coordinatizing $J$ with 8 parameters. We derive such a coordinatization of $J$ using fixed three complementary primitive idempotents and the associated Peirce decomposition of $J$.
  The second aim of this paper is to construct complex prime $\mathbb{Q}$-Fano $3$-folds of anti-canonical codimension 4 as weighted complete intersections of appropriate weighted projectivizations of $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ or its subvarieties (possibly allowing some coordinates with weight $0$). The affine variety $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ and such weighted projectivizations of $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ are called key varieties for prime $\mathbb{Q}$-Fano 3-folds. We show that a prime $\mathbb{Q}$-Fano 3-fold of genus $3$ with three $\frac{1}{2}(1,1,1)$-singularities belonging to the class of No.5.4 as in [Tak1] is constructed from one weighted projectivization of $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ such that all the coordinates have positive weights. Conversely, we also show that any such a prime $\mathbb{Q}$-Fano 3-fold is obtained in this way. Moreover, relating $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ with the $C_{2}$-cluster variety constructed by Coughlan and Ducat [CD1], we show that weighted projectivizations of $\mathscr{H}_{\mathbb{A}}^{13}$ or its subvarieties are key varieties for prime $\mathbb{Q}$-Fano 3-folds belonging to 108 classes in the online database [GRDB].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14991v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiromichi Takagi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry of Kupershmidt's operators and non-commutative probability theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02670v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have developed a comprehensive framework to calculate the envelope of particular deformations of PostLie algebras. We have applied this framework to operator-valued non-commutative probability by introducing new transforms that enable the computation of conditionally free and conditionally monotone multiplicative convolutions of operator-valued non-commutative distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02670v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Gilliers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative projective partial resolutions and quiver varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00709v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma\in \mathrm{SL}_2(\mathbb{C})$ be a finite subgroup. We introduce a class of projective noncommutative surfaces $\mathbb{P}^2_I$, indexed by a set of irreducible $\Gamma$-representations. Extending the action of $\Gamma$ from $\mathbb{C}^2$ to $\mathbb{P}^2$, we show that these surfaces generalise both $[\mathbb{P}^2/\Gamma]$ and $\mathbb{P}^2/\Gamma$. We prove that isomorphism classes of framed torsion-free sheaves on any $\mathbb{P}^2_I$ carry a canonical bijection to the closed points of appropriate Nakajima quiver varieties. In particular, we provide geometric interpretations for a class of Nakajima quiver varieties using noncommutative geometry. Our results partially generalise several previous results on such quiver varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00709v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S{\o}ren Gammelgaard, \'Ad\'am Gyenge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shifted twisted Yangians and Slodowy slices in classical Lie algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05492v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce the shifted twisted Yangian of type {\sf AI}, following the work of Lu--Wang--Zhang, and we study their semiclassical limits, a class of Poisson algebras. We demonstrate that they coincide with the Dirac reductions of the semiclassical shifted Yangian for $\gl_n$. We deduce that these shifted twisted Yangians admit truncations which are isomorphic to Slodowy slices for many non-rectangular nilpotent elements in types {\sf B}, {\sf C}, {\sf D}. As a direct consequence we obtain parabolic presentations of the semiclassical shifted twisted Yangian, analogous to those introduced by Brundan--Kleshchev for the Yangian of type {\sf A}. Finally we give Poisson presentations of Slodowy slices for all even nilpotent elements in types {\sf B}, {\sf C}, {\sf D}, generalising the recent work of the second author.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05492v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Tappeiner, Lewis Topley</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
