<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 01:30:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Rings with $\Delta$-quasipolarity Property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study provides a comprehensive investigation into the structure and properties of a novel class of rings known as $\Delta$-quasipolar rings, in which for every $a\in R$ there exisxt $p^2=p \in comm^2(a)$ such that $a+p \in \Delta(R)$. Here, $\Delta(R)$ is the largest Jacobson radical subring of $R$ which is closed with respect to multiplication by units of $R$. We have developed a general and comprehensive theoretical framework for $\Delta$-quasipolar rings. Within this framework, we have described the fundamental mathematical properties of these rings and examined their behavior under various classical algebraic structures, such as matrix rings and polynomial rings. Furthermore, we have investigated how this class of rings is related to other well-known ring types in mathematics, such as strongly $\Delta$-clean rings, uniquely clean rings, $J$-quasipolar rings and others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13885v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tugce Pekacar Calci, Serhat Emirhan Soycan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Groupoids of finitely aligned higher-rank graphs via filters and graph morphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Path and boundary-path groupoids of finitely aligned higher-rank graphs are often constructed using either filters or graph morphisms. We generalise the graph morphism approach to finitely aligned P-graphs where (Q, P) is a weakly quasi-lattice ordered group, and we show the filter approach and the graph morphism approach yield isomorphic path and boundary-path groupoids. To do this, we define conjugacy of partial semigroup actions such that conjugate actions have isomorphic semidirect product groupoids. Combining our results with others in the literature, we survey many isomorphic presentations of path and boundary-path groupoids at different levels of generality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13929v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lisa Orloff Clark, Malcolm Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-pre-Poisson bialgebras and relative Rota-Baxter operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we first introduce the notion of an anti-pre-Poisson bialgebra, which is shown to be equivalent to both quadratic anti-pre-Poisson algebras and matched pairs of Poisson algebras. The study of coboundary anti-pre-Poisson bialgebras leads to the anti-pre-Poisson Yang-Baxter equation (APP-YBE). Skew-symmetric solutions of this equation give rise to coboundary anti-pre-Poisson bialgebras. Furthermore, we investigate how solutions without skew-symmetry can also induce such bialgebras, prompting the introduction of quasi-triangular and factorizable anti-pre-Poisson bialgebras. In particular, solutions of the APP-YBE whose symmetric parts are invariant induce a quasi-triangular anti-pre-Poisson bialgebra. Such solutions are also interpreted as relative Rota-Baxter operators with weights. Finally, we establish a one-to-one correspondence between quadratic Rota-Baxter anti-pre-Poisson algebras and factorizable anti-pre-Poisson bialgebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13963v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qinxiu Sun, Min Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skew braces and Rota-Baxter operators on semi-direct products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13959v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper examines the connections between (relative) Rota-Baxter groups, skew left braces, and enlargements of these structures on naturally associated semi-direct products. For any skew left brace, we introduce a new skew left brace, called the square, on the natural semi-direct product of its additive and multiplicative groups. Further, the square construction turns out to be distinct from the previously known double construction arising as a special case of matched pairs of skew braces. This provides a method to construct a new bijective, non-degenerate solution to the Yang-Baxter equation from an existing solution arising from a skew left brace. We show that the square construction is functorial and integrates naturally into both the cohomological and extension-theoretic frameworks for (relative) Rota-Baxter groups and skew left braces. Furthermore, we provide a sufficient condition under which two isoclinic skew left braces yield isoclinic squares.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13959v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pragya Belwal, Mahender Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards the classification of DGAs with polynomial homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14015v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the classification of $\mathbb{Z}$-DGAs with polynomial homology $\mathbb{F}_p[x]$ with $\lvert x \rvert &gt;0$, motivated by computations in algebraic $K$-theory. This classification problem was left open in work of Dwyer, Greenlees, and Iyengar. We prove that there are infinitely many such DGAs for even $\lvert x \rvert$ and that for $\lvert x \rvert \geq 2p-2$ any such DGA is formal as a ring spectrum. Through this, we obtain examples of triangulated categories with infinitely many DG-enhancements and a classification of prime DG-division rings.
  Combining our results with earlier work of the second author and Tamme, we obtain new (relative) algebraic $K$-theory computations for rings such as the mixed characteristic coordinate axes $\mathbb{Z}[x]/px$ and the group ring $\mathbb{Z}[C_{p^n}]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14015v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haldun \"Ozg\"ur Bay{\i}nd{\i}r, Markus Land</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Telescope conjecture for quiver representations over artinian rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14179v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{D}(RC)$ be the derived category of representations of a small category $C$ over a commutative noetherian ring $R$. We study the homotopically smashing t-structures on this category. Specifying our discussion to the stalk categories $\Gamma_{\mathfrak{p}}\mathcal{D}(RQ)$ for a finite quiver $Q$ and a prime ideal $\mathfrak{p}$ of $R$, we prove the telescope conjecture for the derived category of representations of finite quivers over artinian rings. More generally, we prove the same result also outside of the noetherian context, for representations of finite quivers over commutative perfect rings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14179v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Hrbek, Enrico Sabatini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-associative structures in extended geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14215v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a generalisation of vector fields on a vector space, where the vector space is generalised to a highest-weight module over a Kac-Moody algebra. The generalised vector field is an element in a non-associative superalgebra defined by the module and the Kac-Moody algebra. Also the Lie derivative of a vector field parameterised by another is generalised and expressed in a simple way in terms of this superalgebra. It reproduces the generalised Lie derivative in the general framework of extended geometry, which in special cases reduces to the one in exceptional field theory, unifying diffeomorphisms with gauge transformations in supergravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14215v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Cederwall, Jakob Palmkvist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal operations over permutation groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22060v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We classify the possible types of minimal operations above an arbitrary permutation group. Above the trivial group, a theorem of Rosenberg yields that there are five types of minimal operations. We show that above any non-trivial permutation group there are at most four such types. Indeed, except above Boolean groups acting freely on a set, there are only three. In particular, this is the case for oligomorphic permutation groups, for which we improve a result of Bodirsky and Chen by showing one of the types in their classification does not exist. Building on these results, we answer three questions of Bodirsky that were previously open.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22060v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Marimon, Michael Pinsker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Description of the structure of DG--algebras via characters on a groupoid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21784v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a description of graded derivations in group algebras. Using this result for arbitrary graduation of the group algebra, we describe all possible structures of DG algebras. The corresponding examples are given. The description is given in terms of characters on a groupoid analogous to the groupoid of inner action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21784v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andronick Arutyunov, Oleg Muravev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-triangular, factorizable anti-dendriform bialgebras and relative Rota-Baxter operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01650v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a notion of quasi-triangular anti-dendriform bialgebras, which can be induced by the solutions of the AD-YBE whose symmetric parts are invariant. A factorizable anti-dendriform bialgebra leads to a factorization of the underlying anti-dendriform algebra. Moreover, relative Rota-Baxter operators with weights are introduced to characterize the solutions of the AD-YBE whose symmetric parts are invariant. Finally, we interpret factorizable anti-dendriform bialgebras in terms of quadratic Rota-Baxter anti-dendriform algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01650v4</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qinxiu Sun, Min Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8-dimensional 2-step nilpotent Lie algebras over algebraically closed fields of characteristic 0</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14907v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a self contained, elementary, and geometrically-flavored classification of 8-dimensional 2-step nilpotent Lie algebras over algebraically closed fields of characteristic 0, using the algebro-geometric arguments from Bazzoni-Mu\~noz and elementary linear algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14907v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Bazzoni, Juan Rojo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Deligne-Simpson Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11998v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given k similarity classes of invertible matrices, the Deligne-Simpson problem asks to determine whether or not one can find matrices in these classes whose product is the identity and with no common invariant subspace. The author conjectured an answer in terms of an associated root system, and proved one implication in joint work with Shaw. In this paper we prove the other implication, thus confirming the conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11998v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Crawley-Boevey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dualizing complexes over $\mathbb{Z}$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13073v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the notions of dualizing complexes and balanced dualizing complexes over $\mathbb{Z}$-algebras. We prove that a noetherian connected $\mathbb{Z}$-algebra $A$ admits a balanced dualizing complex if and only if $A$ satisfies Artin-Zhang's $\chi$-condition, has finite local cohomology dimension, and possesses symmetric derived torsion as a bigraded $A$-$A$-bimodule. As an application of our study of dualizing complexes, we show that any smooth noncommutative projective scheme associated to a $\mathbb{Z}$-algebra with a balanced dualizing complex admits a Serre functor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13073v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Mizuno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A geometric construction of $U(\mathfrak{n})$ for affine Kac-Moody algebras of type $\tilde{\mathsf{C}}_{n}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.06260v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the work of Geiss, Leclerc and Schr\"oer [Represent. Theory 20, (2016)] we realize the enveloping algebra of the positive part of an affine Kac-Moody Lie algebra of Dynkin type $\tilde{\mathsf{C}}_n$ as a generalized composition algebra of constructible functions on the varieties of locally free representations of the corresponding 1-Iwanaga-Gorenstein algebra $H=H_{\mathbb{C}}(C,D,\Omega)$ with minimal symmetrizer $D$ and arbitrary orientation $\Omega$. To this end, we exploit in several ways the fact that in this situation $H$ is a string algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.06260v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jpaa.2025.108069</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Pure Appl. Algebra 229 (2025), no. 10, Paper No. 108069</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Castillo G\'omez, Christof Geiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying integral Grothendieck rings up to rank 5 and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07023v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we define a Grothendieck ring as a fusion ring categorifiable into a fusion category over the complex field. An integral fusion ring is called Drinfeld if all its formal codegrees are integers dividing the global Frobenius--Perron dimension. Every integral Grothendieck ring is necessarily Drinfeld.
  Using the fact that the formal codegrees of integral Drinfeld rings form an Egyptian fraction summing to 1, we derive a finite list of possible global FPdims for small ranks. Applying Normaliz, we classify all fusion rings with these candidate FPdims, retaining only those admitting a Drinfeld structure. To exclude Drinfeld rings that are not Grothendieck rings, we analyze induction matrices to the Drinfeld center, classified via our new Normaliz feature. Further exclusions and constructions involve group-theoretical fusion categories and Schur multipliers.
  Our main result is a complete classification of integral Grothendieck rings up to rank 5, extended to rank 7 in odd-dimensional and noncommutative cases using Frobenius--Schur indicators and Galois theory. Moreover, we show that any noncommutative, odd-dimensional, integral Grothendieck ring of rank at most 22 is pointed of rank 21.
  We also classify all integral 1-Frobenius Drinfeld rings of rank 6, identify the first known non-Isaacs integral fusion category (which turns out to be group-theoretical), classify integral noncommutative Drinfeld rings of rank 8, and integral 1-Frobenius MNSD Drinfeld rings of rank 9. Finally, we determine the smallest-rank exotic simple integral fusion rings: rank 4 in general, rank 6 in the Drinfeld case, and rank 7 in the 1-Frobenius Drinfeld case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07023v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max A. Alekseyev, Winfried Bruns, Jingcheng Dong, Sebastien Palcoux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Negation Of Singer's Conjecture For The Sixth Algebraic Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09455v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathscr A$ be the Steenrod algebra over the field of characteristic two, $\mathbb F_2.$ Denote by $GL(q)$ the general linear group of rank $q$ over $\mathbb F_2.$ The algebraic transfer, introduced by W. Singer [Math. Z. 202 (1989), 493-523], is a rather effective tool for unraveling the intricate structure of the (mod-2) cohomology of the Steenrod algebra, ${\rm Ext}_{\mathscr A}^{q,*}(\mathbb F_2, \mathbb F_2).$ The Kameko homomorphism is one of the useful tools to study the dimension of the domain of the Singer transfer. Singer conjectured that the algebraic transfer is always a monomorphism, but this remains open for all homology degrees $q\geq 5.$ In this paper, by constructing a novel algorithm implemented in the computer algebra system OSCAR for computing $GL(q)$-invariants of the kernel of the Kameko homomorphism, we disprove Singer's conjecture for bidegree $(6,6+36).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09455v4</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dang Vo Phuc</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
