<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 04:01:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of three-dimensional Nijenhuis Leibniz algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There are thirteen types of three-dimensional Leibniz algebras over the real field $\mathbb{R}$ based on the classification given by S. Ayupov, B. Omirov and I. Rakhimov in [Leibniz algebras: structure and classification. CRC Press, Boca Raton, FL, 2020]. In this paper, we investigate all the Nijenhuis operators on these thirteen types of three-dimensional Leibniz algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12692v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianshui Ma, Chan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fist order joint differential projective invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13051v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a complete algebraic description of the field of first-order joint projective invariants for configurations of \( n \) points in the plane, under the natural diagonal action of the projective group \( PGL(3,\mathbb{R}) \). For \( n &gt; 1 \), we construct an explicit minimal generating set for the field of absolute invariants and prove its algebraic independence. We further determine the structure of the full field of invariants as a simple algebraic extension of field of absolute invariants, generated by a single primitive relative invariant of weight~$-1$, for which we provide a closed-form expression valid for all \( n &gt; 1 \).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13051v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid Bedratyuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poisson triple systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13212v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce Poisson triple systems, which are vector spaces with 3 trilinear operations satisfying 9 polynomial identities of degree 5. We show that every Poisson triple system has a universal enveloping Poisson algebra. Finally, we briefly discuss operadic aspects of Poisson triple systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13212v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1080/03081087.2022.2053039</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Linear and Multilinear Algebra, Volume 71, 2023 - Issue 7, pages 1145-1157</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Murray Bremner, Hader Elgendy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arrow reductions for the finitistic dimension conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12978v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present new techniques for removing arrows of bound quiver algebras, reducing thus the Finitistic Dimension Conjecture $\mathsf{(FDC)}$ for a given algebra to a smaller one. Unlike the classic arrow removal operation of Green-Psaroudakis-Solberg, our methods allow for removing arrows even when they occur in every generating set for the defining admissible ideal of the algebra. Our first main result establishes an equivalence for the finiteness of the finitistic (and global) dimensions of a ring $\Lambda$ and its quotient $\Lambda/K$, under specific homological and structural conditions on the ideal $K$, in the broader context of left artinian rings. The application of this result to bound quiver algebras suggests the notion of removability for sets of arrows, and we prove that successive arrow removals of this sort lead to a uniquely defined arrow reduced version of the algebra. Towards the opposite direction, we characterize generalized arrow removal algebras via removable multiplicative bimodules, and introduce trivial one-arrow extensions as a novel combinatorial construction for adding arrows while preserving the finiteness of the finitistic (and global) dimensions. All these new techniques are illustrated through various concrete bound quiver algebras, for which confirming the $\mathsf{(FDC)}$ had previously seemed intractable to the best of our knowledge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12978v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Odysseas Giatagantzidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On differential smoothness of certain Artin-Schelter regular algebras of dimension 5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10853v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article investigates the differential smoothness of various five-dimensional Artin-Schelter regular algebras. By analyzing the relationship between the number of generators and the Gelfand-Kirillov dimension, we provide structural obstructions to differential smoothness in specific algebraic families. In particular, we prove that certain two- and four-generator AS-regular algebras of global dimension five fail to admit a differential calculus, while a five-generator graded Clifford algebra provides a contrasting positive example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10853v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es Rubiano</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
