<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 02:15:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomology of Restricted Twisted Heisenberg Lie Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over an algebraically closed ffeld F of characteristic p&gt;0, the restricted twisted Heisenberg Lie algebras are studied. We use the Hochschild-Serre spectral sequence relative to its Heisenberg ideal to compute the trivial cohomology. The ordinary 1- and 2-cohomology spaces are used to compute the restricted 1- and 2-cohomology spaces and describe the restricted 1-dimensional central extensions, including explicit formulas for the Lie brackets and [p]-operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05879v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial maps with constants on split octonion algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06221v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\mathbf{O}(\mathbb{F})$ be the split octonion algebra over an algebraically closed field $\mathbb{F}$. For positive integers $k_1, k_2\geq 2$, we study surjectivity of the map $A_1(x^{k_1}) + A_2(y^{k_2}) \in \mathbf{O}(\mathbb{F})\langle x, y\rangle$ on $\mathbf{O}(\mathbb{F})$. For this, we use the orbit representatives of the ${G}_2(\mathbb{F})$-action on $\mathbf{O}(\mathbb{F}) \times \mathbf{O}(\mathbb{F}) $ for the tuple $(A_1, A_2)$, and characterize the ones which give a surjective map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06221v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikat Panja, Prachi Saini, Anupam Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Transposed) Poisson algebra structures on null-filiform associative algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate classifications of all (transposed) Poisson algebras of the associated associative null-filiform algebra</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06295v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jobir Adashev, Xursanoy Berdalova, Feruza Toshtemirova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite fields whose members are the sum of a potent and a 4-potent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We classify those finite fields $\mathbb{F}_q$, for $q$ a power of some fixed prime number, whose members are the sum of an $n$-potent element with $n&gt;1$ and a 4-potent element. It is shown that there are precisely ten non-trivial pairs $(q,n)$ for which this is the case.
  This continues a recent publication by Cohen-Danchev et al. in Turk. J. Math. (2024) in which the tripotent version was examined in-depth as well as it extends recent results of this branch established by Abyzov-Tapkin in Sib. Math. J. (2024).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06600v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen D. Cohen, Peter V. Danchev, Tom\'as Oliveira e Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of uniformly bounded simple Lie conformal algebras with upper bound one</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06694v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that uniformly bounded simple Lie conformal algebra must be finitely generated. Furthermore, we give a completely classification of simple uniformly bounded Lie conformal algebras with upper bound one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06694v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maosen Xu, Huangjie Yu, Lipeng Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morita Equivalence of Subrings with Applications to Inverse Semigroup Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a technique to show the Morita equivalence of certain subrings of a ring with local units. We then apply this technique to develop conditions that are sufficient to show the Morita equivalence of subalgebras induced by partial subactions on generalized Boolean algebras and, subsequently, strongly $E^{\ast}$-unitary inverse subsemigroups. As an application, we prove that the Leavitt path algebra of a graph is Morita equivalent to the Leavitt path algebra of certain subgraphs and use this to calculate the Morita equivalence class of some Leavitt path algebras. Finally, as the main application, we prove a desingularization result for labelled Leavitt path algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06715v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mu$-elements: An extension of essential elements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06739v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce and study $\mu$-elements, that generalize a lattice-theoretic abstraction (namely, essential elements) of essential ideals of rings, essential submodules of modules, and dense subsets of topological spaces. Exploring several examples, we show that $\mu$-elements are indeed a genuine extension of essential elements. We study preservation of $\mu$-elements under contractions and extensions of quantale homomorphisms. We introduce $\mu$-complements and $\mu$-closedness and study their properties. We determine $\mu$-elements for several distinguished quantales, including ideals of $\mathbb{Z}_n$ and open subsets of topological spaces. Finally, we provide a complete characterization of $\mu$-elements in modular quantales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06739v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Caviglia, Amartya Goswami, Luca Mesiti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regular evolution algebras are closed under subalgebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The main goal of this note is to show that subalgebras of regular evolution algebras are themselves evolution algebras. This allows us to assume, without loss of generality, that every subalgebra in the regular setting has a basis consisting of vectors with disjoint supports. Finally, we use this result to characterise the existence of codimension-one subalgebras in regular evolution algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07187v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Ladra, Andr\'es P\'erez-Rodr\'iguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quelques r\'esultats sur les anneaux de Lie qui n ' ont pas de chaine infinie de centralisateurs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06230v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In line with known results on groups, we give some characterizations of radicals in Lie rings with minimal condition on centralizers. In particular, we prove the existence of the nilpotent radical and we deduce a form of Engel theorem if the characteristic is zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06230v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Zamour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the category of Hopf braces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06280v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hopf braces are the quantum analogues of skew braces and, as such, their cocommutative counterparts provide solutions to the quantum Yang-Baxter equation. We investigate various properties of categories related to Hopf braces. In particular, we prove that the category of Hopf braces is accessible while the category of cocommutative Hopf braces is even locally presentable. We also show that functors forgetting multiple antipodes and/or multiplications down to coalgebras are monadic. Colimits in the category of cocommutative Hopf braces are described explicitly and a free cocommutative Hopf brace on an arbitrary cocommutative Hopf algebra is constructed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06280v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana Agore, Alexandru Chirvasitu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F-invariant and E-invariant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06605v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: $F$-invariant for a pair of good elements (e.g. cluster monomials) in cluster algebras is introduced by the author in a previous work. A key feature of $F$-invariant is that it is a coordinate-free invariant, that is, it is mutation invariant under the initial seed mutations. $E$-invariant for a pair of decorated representations of quivers with potentials is introduced by Derksen, Weyman and Zelevinsky, which is also a coordinate-free invariant. The strategies used to show the mutation-invariance of $F$-invariant and $E$-invariant are totally different.
  In this paper, we give a new proof of the mutation-invariance of $F$-invariant following the strategy used by Derksen, Weyman and Zelevinsky. As a result, we prove that $F$-invariant coincides with $E$-invariant on cluster monomials. We also give a proof of Reading's conjecture, which says that the non-compatible cluster variables in cluster algebras can be separated by the sign-coherence of $g$-vectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06605v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peigen Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representability for distributive quasi relation algebras via generalised ordinal sums</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06657v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the work of Galatos (2004) on generalised ordinal sums of residuated lattices. We show that the generalised ordinal sum of an odd quasi relation algebra (qRA) satisfying certain conditions and an arbitrary qRA is again a qRA. In a recent paper by Craig and Robinson (2024), the notion of representability for distributive quasi relation algebras (DqRAs) was developed. For certain pairs of representable DqRAs, we prove that their generalised ordinal sum is again representable. An important consequence of this result is that finite Sugihara chains are finitely representable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06657v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Craig, Claudette Robinson, Wilmari Morton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximal rigid modules over a gentle algebra and applications to higher Auslander-Reiten theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06819v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct a bijective correspondence between the set of rigid modules over a gentle algebra and the set of admissible arc systems on the associated coordinated-marked surface. In particular, a maximal rigid module aligns with an equivalence class of admissible $5$-partial triangulations, which is an (admissible) set of simple arcs dissecting the surface into $s$-gons with $3\leqslant s\leqslant 5$. Furthermore, the rank of the maximal rigid module is equal to the rank of the algebra plus the number of internal $4$-gons and $5$-gons in the associated $5$-partial triangulation.
  Subsequently, these results facilitate an exploration of the higher Auslander-Reiten theory for gentle algebras with global dimension $n$. The $\tau_m$-closures of injective modules are realized as admissible $(m+2)$-partial triangulations, where $\tau_m$ are higher Auslander-Reiten translations with $2\leqslant m \leqslant n$. Finally, we provide a complete classification of gentle algebras that are $\tau_n$-finite or $n$-complete introduced by Iyama [I11].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06819v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decompositions into a direct sum of projective and stable submodules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07271v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A module $M$ is said to be stable if it has no nonzero projective direct summand. For a ring $ R $, we study the conditions under which every $R$-module $M$ within a specific class can be decomposed into a direct sum of a projective module and a stable module, focusing on identifying the types of rings and the class of $R$-modules where this property holds. Some well-known classes of rings over which every finitely presented module can be decomposed into a direct sum of a projective submodule and a stable submodule are semiperfect rings or semilocal rings or rings satisfying some finiteness conditions like having finite uniform dimension or hollow dimension or being Noetherian or Artinian. By using the Auslander-Bridger transpose of modules, we prove that every finitely presented right $R$-module over a left semihereditary ring $R$ has such a decomposition; note that the semihereditary condition is on the opposite side. Our main focus in this article is to give examples where such a decomposition fails. We give some ring examples over which there exists an infinitely generated or finitely generated or cyclic module or finitely presented module or cyclically presented module where such a decomposition fails. Our main example is a cyclically presented module $M$ over a commutative ring such that~$M$ has no such decomposition and $M$ is not projectively equivalent to a stable module.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07271v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gulizar Gunay, Engin Mermut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the complexity of solving equations over the symmetric group $S_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07285v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The complexity of solving equations over finite groups has been an active area of research over the last two decades, starting with Goldmann and Russell, \emph{The complexity of solving equations over finite groups} from 1999. One important case of a group with unknown complexity is the symmetric group $S_4.$ In 2023, Idziak, Kawa{\l}ek, and Krzaczkowski published $\exp(\Omega(\log^2 n))$ lower bounds for the satisfiability and equivalence problems over $S_4$ under the Exponential Time Hypothesis. In the present note, we prove that the satisfiability problem $\textsc{PolSat}(S_4)$ can be reduced to the equivalence problem $\textsc{PolEqv}(S_4)$ and thus, the two problems have the same complexity. We provide several equivalent formulations of the problem. In particular, we prove that $\textsc{PolEqv}(S_4)$ is equivalent to the circuit equivalence problem for $\operatorname{CC}[2,3,2]$-circuits, which were introduced by Idziak, Kawe{\l}ek and Krzaczkowski. Under their strong exponential size hypothesis, such circuits cannot compute $\operatorname{AND}_n$ in size $\exp(o(\sqrt{n})).$ Our results provide an upper bound on the complexity of $\textsc{PolEqv}(S_4)$ that is based on the minimal size of $\operatorname{AND}_n$ over $\operatorname{CC}[2,3,2]$-circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07285v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erhard Aichinger, Simon Gr\"unbacher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E(n)-coactions on semisimple Clifford algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07301v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article we prove that $E(n)$-coactions over a finite-dimensional algebra $A$ are classified by tuples $(\varphi, d_1, ... , d_n)$ consisting of an involution $\varphi$ and a family $(d_i)_{i=1,...,n}$ of $\varphi$-derivations satisfying appropriate conditions. Tuples of maps can be replaced by tuples of suitable elements $(c, u_1, . . . , u_n)$, whenever $A$ is a semisimple Clifford algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07301v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Renda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categorical equivalences for Hopf trusses and their modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.06520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.06520v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce the notion of generalized invertible 1-cocycle in a strict braided monoidal category C, and we prove that the category of Hopf trusses is equivalent to the category of generalized invertible 1-cocycles. On the other hand, we also introduce the notions of module for a Hopf truss and for a generalized invertible 1-cocycle. We prove some functorial results involving these categories of modules and we show that the category of modules associated to a generalized invertible 1-cocycle is equivalent to a category of modules associated to a suitable Hopf truss. Finally, assuming that in C we have equalizers, we introduce the notion of Hopf-module in the Hopf truss setting and we obtain the Fundamental Theorem of Hopf modules associated to a Hopf truss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.06520v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ram\'on Gonz\'alez Rodr\'iguez, Ana Bel\'en Rodr\'iguez Raposo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous direct sum decompositions of several multivariate polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01205v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the problem of simultaneous direct sum decomposition of a set of multivariate polynomials. To this end, we extend Harrison's center theory for a single homogeneous polynomial to this broader setting. It is shown that the center of a set of polynomials is a special Jordan algebra, and simultaneous direct sum decompositions of the given polynomials are in bijection with complete sets of orthogonal idempotents of their center algebra. Several examples are provided to illustrate the performance of this method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01205v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lishan Fang, Hua-Lin Huang, Lili Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial invariants for two-dimensional algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05337v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We classify all two-dimensional simple algebras over an algebraically closed field. For each two-dimensional algebra $\mathcal{A}$ with an infinite group of automorphisms we describe a minimal (with respect to inclusion) generating set for the algebra of invariants of the $m$-tuples of $\mathcal{A}$ in characteristic zero case. As a consequence, we show that in characteristic zero case Artin-Procesi-Iltyakov Equality holds for all two-dimensional simple algebras with an infinite group of automorphisms. We also consider nondegenerate invariant bilinear forms over two-dimensional algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05337v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mar\'ia Alejandra Alvarez, Artem Lopatin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A lifting approach to ParaTuck-2 tensor decompositions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.00922v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ParaTuck-2 decomposition (PT2D) of third-order tensor is a two-layer generalization of the well-known canonical polyadic decomposition (CPD).While being more flexible than the CPD, the PT2D also possesses similar uniqueness properties.In this paper, we show than under the best known uniqueness conditions, the exact PT2D can be computed by an algebraic algorithm (i.e., can the PT2D problems can be reduced to computing nullspaces and eigenvalues of certain matrices).We do so by lifting the slices of the tensor to higher-dimensional space, which also allows for refining the existing uniqueness conditions.The algorithms are developed for general PT2D and its symmetric version (DEDICOM), which leads to an algebraic algorithm for another generalization of the CPD, the PARAFAC2 decomposition.Our methods are also applicable in the approximation scenario, as shown by the numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.00922v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin Usevich (CRAN)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categorifications of Non-Integer Quivers: Type $I_2(2n)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.06988v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use weighted unfoldings of quivers to provide a categorification of mutations of quivers of types $I_2(2n)$, thus extending the construction of categorifications of mutations of quivers to all finite types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.06988v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Drew Damien Duffield, Pavel Tumarkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The set-theoretic Yang-Baxter equation, Kimura semigroups and functional graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.06700v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that the category of solutions of the set-theoretic Yang-Baxter equation of Frobenius-Separability (FS) type is equivalent to the category of pointed Kimura semigroups. As applications, all involutive, idempotent, nondegenerate, surjective, finite order, unitary or indecomposable solutions of FS type are classified. For instance, if $|X| = n$, then the number of isomorphism classes of all such solutions on $X$ that are (a) left non-degenerate, (b) bijective, (c) unitary or (d) indecomposable and left-nondegenerate is: (a) the Davis number $d(n)$, (b) $\sum_{m|n} \, p(m)$, where $p(m)$ is the Euler partition number, (c) $\tau(n) + \sum_{d|n}\left\lfloor \frac d2\right\rfloor$, where $\tau(n)$ is the number of divisors of $n$, or (d) the Harary number $\mathfrak{c} (n)$. The automorphism groups of such solutions can also be recovered as automorphism groups $\mathrm{Aut}(f)$ of sets $X$ equipped with a single endo-function $f:X\to X$. We describe all groups of the form $\mathrm{Aut}(f)$ as iterations of direct and (possibly infinite) wreath products of cyclic or full symmetric groups, characterize the abelian ones as products of cyclic groups, and produce examples of symmetry groups of FS solutions not of the form $\mathrm{Aut}(f)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.06700v3</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. L. Agore, A. Chirvasitu, G. Militaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representable distributive quasi relation algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11719v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a definition of representability for distributive quasi relation algebras (DqRAs). These algebras are a generalisation of relation algebras and were first described by Galatos and Jipsen (2013). Our definition uses a construction that starts with a poset. The algebra is concretely constructed as the lattice of upsets of a partially ordered equivalence relation. The key to defining the three negation-like unary operations is to impose certain symmetry requirements on the partial order. Our definition of representable distributive quasi relation algebras is easily seen to be a generalisation of the definition of representable relations algebras by Jonsson and Tarski (1948). We give examples of representable DqRAs and give a necessary condition for an algebra to be finitely representable. We leave open the questions of whether every DqRA is representable, and also whether the class of representable DqRAs forms a variety. Moreover, our definition provides many other opportunities for investigations in the spirit of those carried out for representable relation algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11719v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Craig, Claudette Robinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclidean domains with no multiplicative norms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05573v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a Euclidean domain with no multiplicative Euclidean norm to a compatibly well-ordered monoid, and hence with no multiplicative Euclidean norm to $\mathbb{R}$ (under its usual order).
  A key step in the proof is showing that the UFD property is preserved when adjoining a free factorization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05573v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caleb J. Dastrup, Pace P. Nielsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frobenius subalgebra lattices in tensor categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19876v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper explores Frobenius subalgebra posets within abelian monoidal categories and shows that they form lattices under certain conditions, including all semisimple tensor categories. Furthermore, it extends Watatani's theorem on the finiteness of intermediate subfactors, proving that these lattices are finite under weak positivity constraints, encompassing all semisimple tensor categories as well. The primary tools employed in this paper are semisimplification and a concept of formal angle. Additionally, we have broadened several intermediate results, such as the exchange relation theorem and Landau's theorem, to apply to abelian monoidal categories. Key applications of our findings include a stronger version of the Ino-Watatani result: we show that the finiteness of intermediate C*-algebras holds in a finite-index unital irreducible inclusion of C*-algebras without requiring the simple assumption. Moreover, for a finite-dimensional semisimple Hopf algebra H, we demonstrate that H* contains a finite number of Frobenius subalgebra objects in Rep(H). Finally, we explore a range of applications, including abstract spin chains, vertex operator algebras, and speculations on quantum arithmetic involving the generalization of Ore's theorem, Euler's totient and sigma functions, and RH.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19876v3</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mainak Ghosh, Sebastien Palcoux</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
