<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry of dyadic polygons I: the structure of dyadic triangles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05467v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dyadic rationals are rationals whose denominator is a power of 2. A dyadic n-dimensional convex set is defined as the intersection with n-dimensional dyadic space of an n-dimensional real convex set. Such a dyadic convex set is said to be a dyadic n-dimensional polytope if the real convex set is a polytope whose vertices lie in the dyadic space. Dyadic convex sets are described as subalgebras of reducts of faithful affine spaces over the ring of dyadic numbers, or equivalently as commutative, entropic and idempotent groupoids (binars or magmas) under the binary operation of arithmetic mean. This paper investigates the structure of dyadic polygons (two-dimensional polytopes), in particular dyadic triangles, following some earlier results. A new classification of dyadic triangles is provided. In addition, dyadic triangles with a pointed vertex are characterized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05467v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Mu\'cka, A. Romanowska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commutators on Generalized Block-Triangular Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The characterization of commutators in associative algebras is a classical problem in ring theory. In this paper, we address this problem for the natural class of generalized block-triangular algebras. To this end, we introduce a new invariant: the multitrace of an arbitrary element in an associative unital algebra, and prove that in a generalized block-triangular algebra, an element is a commutator if and only if its multitrace vanishes. As a consequence, we show that the set of commutators is closed under addition in these algebras. Our main result extends the classical Albert-Muckenhoupt-Shoda theorem for full matrix algebras to the broader setting of generalized block-triangular algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05820v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Souza Fagundes, Thiago Castilho de Mello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of small binary bibraces via bilinear maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We classify small binary bibraces, using the correspondence with alternating algebras over the field F2, up to dimension eight, also determining their isomorphism classes. These finite-dimensional algebras, defined by an alternating bilinear multiplication and nilpotency of class two, can be represented by subspaces of skew-symmetric matrices, with classification corresponding to GL(m, F_2)-orbits under congruence. Our approach combines theoretical invariants, such as rank sequences and the identification of primitive algebras, with computational methods implemented in Magma. These results also count the number of possible alternative operations that can be used in differential cryptanalysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05848v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Civino, Valerio Fedele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exposure Orders in Free Group Algebras: Minimal Schreier Transversals, Free Bases, and Gr\"obner Bases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05906v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Consider the free group algebra $K\left[F\right]$, where $F$ is a free group and $K$ a field. A well-order $\prec$ on $F$ is called an exposure order if words are greater than their proper prefixes. We show that every one-sided ideal $I$ in $K\left[F\right]$ admits a Schreier transversal, a basis, and a Gr\"obner basis -- each minimal in a natural sense with respect to $\prec$. When $I$ is finitely generated and $\prec$ is computable, we provide an algorithm for computing these minimal structures from a finite generating set. This extends the foundational works of Lewin and Rosenmann, which relied on the shortlex order, to both a broader class of orders on $F$ and to infinitely generated ideals, while retaining algorithmic capabilities for such orders in case $I$ is finitely generated.
  General exposure orders lack a form of compatibility with products which we call suffix-invariance, that shortlex enjoys, and which prior Gr\"obner basis constructions in $K\left[F\right]$ relied on. In its absence, reductions may strictly increase the support of elements, requiring nontrivial conceptual adaptations to definitions and algorithms. These adaptations clarify the notion of minimality underlying prior constructions and demonstrate that algorithmic Gr\"obner theory in $K\left[F\right]$ does not fundamentally require suffix-invariance, although its presence -- as in shortlex -- results in a simpler theory.
  Our framework further illuminates the flexibility of exposure orders: with a suitable choice of $\prec$, any Schreier transversal for $I$ can be realized as minimal, and any basis for $I$ arising from the constructions of Lewin or Rosenmann can likewise be realized as its minimal basis, unifying both approaches under a single framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05906v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matan Seidel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Spectral Theorem for Zeon Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.09321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2201.09321v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, spectral properties of matrices with (complex) zeon entries are investigated. It is shown that when $A$ is an $m\times m$ self-adjoint matrix whose characteristic polynomial $\chi_A(u)$ has $m$ ``spectrally simple'' zeros $\lambda_1, \ldots, \lambda_m$ in the zeon algebra ${\mathbb{C}\mathfrak{Z}}$, there exist $m$ linearly independent normalized zeon eigenvectors $v_1, \ldots, v_m$ such that $A=\bigoplus_{j=1}^m \lambda_j\pi_j$, where $\pi_j=v_j{v_j}^\dag$ is a rank-one projection onto the zeon submodule ${\rm span}\{v_j\}$ for $j=1, \ldots, m$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2201.09321v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Stacey Staples</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Remarks on Gorenstein Projective Precovers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10727v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The existence of the Gorenstein projective precovers over arbitrary rings is an open question. In this paper, we make use of three diferent techniques addressing intrinsic and homological properties of several classes of relative Gorenstein projective $R$-modules, among them including the Gorenstein projectives and Ding projectives, with the purpose of giving some situations where Gorenstein projective precovers exists. Within the development of such techniques we obtaint a family of hereditary and complete cotorsion pairs and hereditary Hovey triples that comes from relative Gorenstein projective $R$-modules. We also study a class of Gorenstein projective $R$-modules relative to the Auslander class $\mathcal{A}_C(R)$ of a semidualizing $(R,S)$-bimodule $_R C _S$, where we make use of a property of "reduction".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10727v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V\'ictor Becerril</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Description of the structure of DG--algebras via characters on a groupoid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21784v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a description of graded derivations in group algebras. Using this result for arbitrary graduation of the group algebra, we describe all possible structures of DG algebras. The corresponding examples are given. The description is given in terms of characters on a groupoid analogous to the groupoid of inner action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21784v4</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andronick Arutyunov, Oleg Muravev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torsion modules and differential operators in infinitely many variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07739v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper grew out of the author's work on arXiv:2504.18460. Differential operators in the sense of Grothendieck acting between modules over a commutative ring can be interpreted as torsion elements in the bimodule of all operators with respect to the diagonal ideal in the tensor square of the ring. Various notions of torsion modules for an infinitely generated ideal in a commutative ring lead to various notions of differential operators. We discuss differential operators of transfinite orders and differential operators having no global order at all, but only local orders with respect to specific elements of the ring. Many examples are presented. In particular, we prove that every ordinal can be realized as the order of a differential operator acting on the algebra of polynomials in infinitely many variables over a field. We also discuss extension of differential operators to localizations of rings and modules, and to colocalizations of modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07739v4</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid Positselski</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
