<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA</link>
    <description>math.RA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 03:05:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Gorenstein homological invariants and monoidal model categories of Hopf algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $H$ be a Hopf algebra over a field $k$ with a bijective antipode. It is proved that the Gorenstein global dimension of $H$ coincides with the Gorenstein projective dimension of the trivial left (or right) $H$-module $k$. Then, $H$ is finite dimensional if and only if the Gorenstein projective dimension of $k$ is trivial. Although monoidal Morita-Takeuchi equivalence of Hopf algebras does not preserve the global dimension, we demonstrate that it does preserve the Gorenstein global dimension and the Artin-Schelter Gorenstein property; this supports Brown-Goodearl's question of whether every noetherian (affine) Hopf algebra is AS Gorenstein. Finally, for $H$ and an $H$-Galois object $B$, we show the categories of modules $_H\mathcal{M}$ and $_B\mathcal{M}_B^H$ are monoidal model categories regarding Gorenstein projective model structure, provided that the Gorenstein global dimension of $H$ is finite. The corresponding stable categories are tensor triangulated categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20249v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Ren, Ruipeng Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trivial extensions of monomial algebras are symmetric fractional Brauer configuration algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02537v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By providing equivalent definitions of fractional Brauer configuration algebras in certain special cases, we associate to each monomial algebra some combinatorial data called a fractional Brauer configuration, from which we construct a corresponding fractional Brauer configuration algebra. We show that this algebra is isomorphic to the trivial extension of the given monomial algebra. Furthermore, we establish a one-to-one correspondence between the isomorphism classes of monomial algebras and the equivalence classes of pairs consisting of a symmetric fractional Brauer configuration algebra of type S with a free fractional-degree function and an admissible cut on it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02537v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuming Liu, Bohan Xing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A universal group-theoretic characterisation of $p$-typical Witt vectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12680v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For a prime $p$ and a commutative ring $R$ with unity, let $W(R)$ denote the group of $p$-typical Witt vectors. The group $W(R)$ is endowed with a Verschiebung operator $V: W(R)\to W(R)$ and a Teichm\"{u}ller map $\langle \ \rangle: R\rightarrow W(R)$. One of the properties satisfied by $V, \langle \ \rangle$ is that the map $R \to W(R)$ given by $x\mapsto V\langle x^p \rangle - p\langle x \rangle$ is an additive map. In this paper we show that for $p\neq 2$, this property essentially characterises the functor $W$. Unlike other characterisations, this is a group-theoretic characterisation, in the sense that it does not use the ring structure of $W(R)$. Most constructions of the group of $p$-typical Witt vectors of non-commutative rings do not have a ring structure, and hence the above characterisation is more suitable for generalisation to the non-commutative setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12680v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jalgebra.2025.03.021</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Algebra (2025), vol. 677, pp. 1-12</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Supriya Pisolkar, Biswanath Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torsion modules and differential operators in infinitely many variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07739v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper grew out of the author's work on arXiv:2504.18460. Differential operators in the sense of Grothendieck acting between modules over a commutative ring can be interpreted as torsion elements in the bimodule of all operators with respect to the diagonal ideal in the tensor square of the ring. Various notions of torsion modules for an infinitely generated ideal in a commutative ring lead to various notions of differential operators. We discuss differential operators of transfinite orders and differential operators having no global order at all, but only local orders with respect to specific elements of the ring. Many examples are presented. In particular, we prove that every ordinal can be realized as the order of a differential operator acting on the algebra of polynomials in infinitely many variables over a field. We also discuss extension of differential operators to localizations of rings and modules, and to colocalizations of modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07739v5</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid Positselski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determining unit groups and $\mathrm{K}_1$ of finite rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00266v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the computational problem of determining the unit group of a finite ring, by which we mean the computation of a finite presentation together with an algorithm to express units as words in the generators. We show that the problem is equivalent to the number theoretic problems of factoring integers and solving discrete logarithms in finite fields. A similar equivalence is shown for the problem of determining the abelianization of the unit group or the first $K$-group of finite rings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00266v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jalgebra.2026.01.019</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Algebra 693 (2026) 510-530</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tommy Hofmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure and Symmetry of Sally Type Semigroup Rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18136v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Consider a numerical semigroup minimally generated by a subset of the interval $[e,2e-1]$ with multiplicity $e$ and width $e-1$. Such numerical semigroups are called Sally type semigroups. We show that the defining ideals of these semigroup rings, when the embedding dimension is $e-2$, generically have the structure of the sum of two determinantal ideals. More generally, Sally type numerical semigroups with multiplicity $e$ and embedding dimension $d=e-k$ are obtained by introducing $k$ gaps in the interval $[e,2e-1]$. It is known that for $k =2$, there is precisely one such semigroup that is Gorenstein, and it happens when one deletes consecutive integers. Let $S^e_k(j)$ denote the Sally type numerical semigroup of multiplcity $e$, embedding dimension $e-k$ obtained by deleting the $k$ consecutive integers $j, j+1, \ldots, j+k-1$.We prove that for any $1\le k &lt; e/2$, the semigroup $S^e_k(j)$ is Gorenstein if and only if $j=k$. We construct an explicit minimal free resolution of the semigroup ring of $S^e_k(k)$ and compute the Betti numbers. In general, we characterize when $S^e_k(j)$ are symmetric and construct minimal resolutions for these Gorenstein semigroup rings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18136v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srishti Singh, Hema Srinivasan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
