<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM</link>
    <description>cs.DM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 05:10:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Approximately covering vertices by order-$5$ or longer paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11225v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies $MPC^{5+}_v$, which is to cover as many vertices as possible in a given graph $G=(V,E)$ by vertex-disjoint $5^+$-paths (i.e., paths each with at least five vertices). $MPC^{5+}_v$ is NP-hard and admits an existing local-search-based approximation algorithm which achieves a ratio of $\frac {19}7\approx 2.714$ and runs in $O(|V|^6)$ time. In this paper, we present a new approximation algorithm for $MPC^{5+}_v$ which achieves a ratio of $2.511$ and runs in $O(|V|^{2.5} |E|^2)$ time. Unlike the previous algorithm, the new algorithm is based on maximum matching, maximum path-cycle cover, and recursion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11225v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyang Gong, Zhi-Zhong Chen, Guohui Lin, Lusheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting simplicial pairs in hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11806v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present two ways to measure the simplicial nature of a hypergraph: the simplicial ratio and the simplicial matrix. We show that the simplicial ratio captures the frequency, as well as the rarity, of simplicial interactions in a hypergraph while the simplicial matrix provides more fine-grained details. We then compute the simplicial ratio, as well as the simplicial matrix, for 10 real-world hypergraphs and, from the data collected, hypothesize that simplicial interactions are more and more deliberate as edge size increases. We then present a new Chung-Lu model that includes a parameter controlling (in expectation) the frequency of simplicial interactions. We use this new model, as well as the real-world hypergraphs, to show that multiple stochastic processes exhibit different behaviour when performed on simplicial hypergraphs vs. non-simplicial hypergraphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11806v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Barrett, Pawe{\l} Pra{\l}at, Aaron Smith, Fran\c{c}ois Th\'eberge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Half-space separation in monophonic convexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17564v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study half-space separation in the convexity of chordless paths of a graph, i.e., monophonic convexity. In this problem, one is given a graph and two (disjoint) subsets of vertices and asks whether these two sets can be separated by complementary convex sets, called half-spaces. While it is known this problem is $\mathbf{NP}$-complete for geodesic convexity -- the convexity of shortest paths -- we show that it can be solved in polynomial time for monophonic convexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17564v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Elaroussi, Lhouari Nourine, Simon Vilmin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully graphic degree sequences and P-stable degree sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12013v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The notion of $P$-stability of an infinite set of degree sequences plays influential role in approximating the permanents, rapidly sampling the realizations of graphic degree sequences, or even studying and improving network privacy. While there exist several known sufficient conditions for $P$-stability, we don't know any useful necessary condition for it. We also do not have good insight of possible structure of $P$-stable degree sequence families.
  At first we will show that every known infinite $P$-stable degree sequence set, described by inequalities of the parameters $n, c_1, c_2, \Sigma$ (the sequence length, the maximum and minimum degrees and the sum of the degrees) is ,,fully graphic" meaning that every degree sequence from the region with an even degree sum, is graphic. Furthermore, if $\Sigma$ does not occur in the determining inequality, then the notions of $P$-stability and full graphicality will be proved equivalent. In turns, this equality provides a strengthening of the well-known theorem of Jerrum, McKay and Sinclair about $P$-stability, describing the maximal $P$-stable sequence set by $n, c_1, c_2$. Furthermore we conjecture that similar equivalences occur in cases if $\Sigma$ also part of the defining inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12013v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P\'eter L. Erd\H{o}s, Istv\'an Mikl\'os, Lajos Soukup</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
