<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM</link>
    <description>cs.DM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 04:04:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>GMSNP and Finite Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given an (infinite) relational structure $\mathbb S$, we say that a finite structure $\mathbb C$ is a minimal finite factor of $\mathbb S$ if for every finite structure $\mathbb A$ there is a homomorphism $\mathbb S\to \mathbb A$ if and only if there is a homomorphism $\mathbb{C} \to \mathbb{A}$. In this brief note we prove that if CSP($\mathbb S$) is in GMSNP, then $\mathbb S$ has a minimal finite factor $\mathbb C$, and moreover, CSP($\mathbb C$) reduces in polynomial time to CSP($\mathbb S$). We discuss two nice applications of this result. First, we see that if a finite promise constraint satisfaction problem PCSP($\mathbb A,\mathbb B$) has a tractable GMSNP sandwich, then it has a tractable finite sandwich. We also show that if $\mathbb G$ is a non-bipartite (possibly infinite) graph with finite chromatic number, and CSP($\mathbb G$) is in GMSNP, then CSP($\mathbb G$) in NP-complete, partially answering a question recently asked by Bodirsky and Guzm\'an-Pro.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13529v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santiago Guzm\'an-Pro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Algorithm for the Assignment Game Beyond Additive Valuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13620v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The assignment game, introduced by Shapley and Shubik (1971), is a classic model for two-sided matching markets between buyers and sellers. In the original assignment game, it is assumed that payments lead to transferable utility and that buyers have unit-demand valuations for the items being sold. Two important and mostly independent lines of work have studied more general settings with imperfectly transferable utility and gross substitutes valuations. Multiple efficient algorithms have been proposed for computing a competitive equilibrium, the standard solution concept in assignment games, in these two settings. Our main result is an efficient algorithm for computing competitive equilibria in a setting with both imperfectly transferable utility and gross substitutes valuations. Our algorithm combines augmenting path techniques from maximum matching and algorithms for matroid intersection. We also show that, in a mild generalization of our model, computing a competitive equilibrium is NP-hard.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13620v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Balkanski, Christopher En, Yuri Faenza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomized Greedy Online Edge Coloring Succeeds for Dense and Randomly-Ordered Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13000v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Vizing's theorem states that any graph of maximum degree $\Delta$ can be properly edge colored with at most $\Delta+1$ colors. In the online setting, it has been a matter of interest to find an algorithm that can properly edge color any graph on $n$ vertices with maximum degree $\Delta = \omega(\log n)$ using at most $(1+o(1))\Delta$ colors. Here we study the na\"{i}ve random greedy algorithm, which simply chooses a legal color uniformly at random for each edge upon arrival. We show that this algorithm can $(1+\epsilon)\Delta$-color the graph for arbitrary $\epsilon$ in two contexts: first, if the edges arrive in a uniformly random order, and second, if the edges arrive in an adversarial order but the graph is sufficiently dense, i.e., $n = O(\Delta)$. Prior to this work, the random greedy algorithm was only known to succeed in trees.
  Our second result is applicable even when the adversary is adaptive, and therefore implies the existence of a deterministic edge coloring algorithm which $(1+\epsilon)\Delta$ edge colors a dense graph. Prior to this, the best known deterministic algorithm for this problem was the simple greedy algorithm which utilized $2\Delta-1$ colors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13000v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditi Dudeja, Rashmika Goswami, Michael Saks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Networks: from Multipartite Entanglement to Hypergraph Immersion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13452v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multipartite entanglement, a higher-order interaction unique to quantum information, offers various advantages over bipartite entanglement in quantum network (QN) applications. Establishing multipartite entanglement across remote parties in QN requires entanglement routing, which irreversibly transforms the QN topology at the cost of existing entanglement links. Here, we address the question of whether a QN can be topologically transformed into another via entanglement routing. Our key result is an exact mapping from multipartite entanglement routing to Nash-Williams's graph immersion problem, extended to hypergraphs. This generalized hypergraph immersion problem introduces a partial order between QN topologies, permitting certain topological transformations while precluding others, offering discerning insights into the design and manipulation of higher-order network topologies in QNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13452v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Tian, Yuefei Liu, Xiangyi Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-Correcting Graph Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13867v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we define, study, and construct {\em Error-Correcting Graph Codes}. An error-correcting graph code of distance $\delta$ is a family $C$ of graphs, on a common vertex set of size $n$, such that if we start with any graph in $C$, we would have to modify the neighborhoods of at least $\delta n$ vertices in order to reach some other graph in $C$.
  This is a natural graph generalization of the standard Hamming distance error-correcting codes for binary strings. We show:
  1. Combinatorial results determining the optimal rate vs distance tradeoff nonconstructively.
  2. A connection to rank-metric codes, enabling some simple and some involved constructions achieving certain positive rates and distances.
  3. Graph code analogues of Reed-Solomon codes and code concatenation, leading to positive distance codes for all rates and positive rate codes for all distances.
  4. Graph code analogues of dual-BCH codes, yielding large codes with distance $\delta = 1-o(1)$. This gives an explicit "graph code of Ramsey graphs".
  Several recent works, starting with the paper of Alon, Gujgiczer, K\"orner, Milojevi\'c, and Simonyi, have studied more general graph codes; where the symmetric difference between any two graphs in the code is required to have a desired property. Error-correcting graph codes are a particularly interesting instantiation of this concept.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13867v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swastik Kopparty, Aditya Potukuchi, Harry Sha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signed combinatorial interpretations in algebraic combinatorics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13902v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the existence of signed combinatorial interpretations for several large families of structure constants. These families include standard bases of symmetric and quasisymmetric polynomials, as well as various bases in Schubert theory. The results are stated in the language of computational complexity, while the proofs are based on the effective M\"obius inversion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13902v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Pak, Colleen Robichaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multicoloured Hardcore Model: Fast Mixing and Queueing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the hardcore model to a multicoloured version: a subset of vertices of a graph are coloured such that no vertex is adjacent to one of the same colour; uncoloured vertices do not constrain neighbours. This mathematically models multi-channel resource sharing, such as fibreoptic routing.
  We analyse certain simple Glauber-type dynamics on such configurations, and find conditions which ensure fast mixing. These dynamics model a queueing system: customers queue for service at vertices, who only serve customers whilst they are coloured in the underlying configuration; uncoloured vertices sit idle. The mixing estimates are applied to control queue lengths in equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14376v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam Olesker-Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logic-based analogical proportions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14402v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The author has recently introduced an abstract algebraic framework of analogical proportions within the general setting of universal algebra. The purpose of this paper is to lift that framework from universal algebra to the strictly more expressive setting of full first-order logic. We show that the so-obtained logic-based framework preserves all desired properties and we prove novel results in that extended setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14402v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Anti\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Matching and Contention Resolution for Edge Arrivals with Vanishing Probabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14506v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the performance of sequential contention resolution and matching algorithms on random graphs with vanishing edge probabilities. When the edges of the graph are processed in an adversarially-chosen order, we derive a new OCRS that is $0.382$-selectable, attaining the "independence benchmark" from the literature under the vanishing edge probabilities assumption. Complementary to this positive result, we show that no OCRS can be more than $0.390$-selectable, significantly improving upon the upper bound of $0.428$ from the literature. We also derive negative results that are specialized to bipartite graphs or subfamilies of OCRS's. Meanwhile, when the edges of the graph are processed in a uniformly random order, we show that the simple greedy contention resolution scheme which accepts all active and feasible edges is $1/2$-selectable. This result is tight due to a known upper bound. Finally, when the algorithm can choose the processing order, we show that a slight tweak to the random order -- give each vertex a random priority and process edges in lexicographic order -- results in a strictly better contention resolution scheme that is $1-\ln(2-1/e)\approx0.510$-selectable. Our positive results also apply to online matching on $1$-uniform random graphs with vanishing (non-identical) edge probabilities, extending and unifying some results from the random graphs literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14506v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>In EC 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Will Ma, Calum MacRury, Pranav Nuti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rank of sparse random matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.05757</link>
      <description>arXiv:1906.05757v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We determine the rank of a random matrix over an arbitrary field with prescribed numbers of non-zero entries in each row and column. As an application we obtain a formula for the rate of low-density parity check codes. This formula vindicates a conjecture of Lelarge (2013). The proofs are based on coupling arguments and a novel random perturbation, applicable to any matrix, that diminishes the number of short linear relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1906.05757v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amin Coja-Oghlan, Alperen A. Erg\"ur, Pu Gao, Samuel Hetterich, Maurice Rolvien</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving systems of equations on antichains for the computation of the ninth Dedekind Number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20904v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study systems of equations on antichains, together with a way to count the number of solutions. We start with two simple examples, generalise and show more applications. One of the results was used in the recent computation of D(9), the others have potential to speed up existing techniques in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20904v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick De Causmaecker, Lennart Van Hirtum</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
