<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM</link>
    <description>cs.DM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Delivery with a Faulty Drone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce and study a new cooperative delivery problem inspired by drone-assisted package delivery. We consider a scenario where a drone, en route to deliver a package to a destination (a point on the plane), unexpectedly loses communication with its central command station. The command station cannot know whether the drone's system has wholly malfunctioned or merely experienced a communications failure. Consequently, a second, helper drone must be deployed to retrieve the package to ensure successful delivery. The central question of this study is to find the optimal trajectory for this second drone. We demonstrate that the optimal solution relies heavily on the relative spatial positioning of the command station, the destination point, and the last known location of the disconnected drone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17711v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jared Coleman, Danny Krizanc, Evangelos Kranakis, Oscar Morales-Ponce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing Roberts' characterization of unit interval graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For any natural number $d$, a graph $G$ is a (disjoint) $d$-interval graph if it is the intersection graph of (disjoint) $d$-intervals, the union of $d$ (disjoint) intervals on the real line. Two important subclasses of $d$-interval graphs are unit and balanced $d$-interval graphs (where every interval has unit length or all the intervals associated to a same vertex have the same length, respectively). A celebrated result by Roberts gives a simple characterization of unit interval graphs being exactly claw-free interval graphs. Here, we study the generalization of this characterization for $d$-interval graphs. In particular, we prove that for any $d \geq 2$, if $G$ is a $K_{1,2d+1}$-free interval graph, then $G$ is a unit $d$-interval graph. However, somehow surprisingly, under the same assumptions, $G$ is not always a \emph{disjoint} unit $d$-interval graph. This implies that the class of disjoint unit $d$-interval graphs is strictly included in the class of unit $d$-interval graphs. Finally, we study the relationships between the classes obtained under disjoint and non-disjoint $d$-intervals in the balanced case and show that the classes of disjoint balanced 2-intervals and balanced 2-intervals coincide, but this is no longer true for $d&gt;2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17872v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Virginia Ard\'evol Mart\'inez, Romeo Rizzi, Abdallah Saffidine, Florian Sikora, St\'ephane Vialette</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reducing Dominating Sets in Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A dominating set of a graph $G=(V,E)$ is a subset of vertices $S\subseteq V$ such that every vertex $v\in V\setminus S$ has at least one neighbor in set $S$. The corresponding optimization problem is known to be NP-hard. The best known polynomial time approximation algorithm for the problem separates the solution process in two stages applying first a fast greedy algorithm to obtain an initial dominating set, and then it uses an iterative procedure to reduce (purify) this dominating set. The purification stage turned out to be practically efficient. Here we further strengthen the purification stage presenting four new purification algorithms. All four purification procedures outperform the earlier purification procedure. The algorithms were tested for over 1300 benchmark problem instances. Compared to the known upper bounds, the obtained solutions were about 7 times better. Remarkably, for the 500 benchmark instances for which the optimum is known, the optimal solutions were obtained for 46.33\% of the tested instances, whereas the average error for the remaining instances was about 1.01.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18028v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ernesto Parra Inza, Jos\'e Mar\'ia Sigarreta Almira, Nodari Vakhania</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Search Trees and the Intermezzo Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18645v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The last in-tree recognition problem asks whether a given spanning tree can be derived by connecting each vertex with its rightmost left neighbor of some search ordering. In this study, we demonstrate that the last-in-tree recognition problem for Generic Search is $\mathsf{NP}$-complete. We utilize this finding to strengthen a complexity result from order theory. Given partial order $\pi$ and a set of triples, the $\mathsf{NP}$-complete intermezzo problem asks for a linear extension of $\pi$ where each first element of a triple is not between the other two. We show that this problem remains $\mathsf{NP}$-complete even when the Hasse diagram of the partial order forms a tree of bounded height. In contrast, we give an $\mathsf{XP}$ algorithm for the problem when parameterized by the width of the partial order. Furthermore, we show that $\unicode{x2013}$ under the assumption of the Exponential Time Hypothesis $\unicode{x2013}$ the running time of this algorithm is asymptotically optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18645v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Beisegel, Ekkehard K\"ohler, Fabienne Ratajczak, Robert Scheffler, Martin Strehler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On classes of bounded tree rank, their interpretations, and efficient sparsification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graph classes of bounded tree rank were introduced recently in the context of the model checking problem for first-order logic of graphs. These graph classes are a common generalization of graph classes of bounded degree and bounded treedepth, and they are a special case of graph classes of bounded expansion. We introduce a notion of decomposition for these classes and show that these decompositions can be efficiently computed. Also, a natural extension of our decomposition leads to a new characterization and decomposition for graph classes of bounded expansion (and an efficient algorithm computing this decomposition).
  We then focus on interpretations of graph classes of bounded tree rank. We give a characterization of graph classes interpretable in graph classes of tree rank $2$. Importantly, our characterization leads to an efficient sparsification procedure: For any graph class $C$ interpretable in a efficiently bounded graph class of tree rank at most $2$, there is a polynomial time algorithm that to any $G \in C$ computes a (sparse) graph $H$ from a fixed graph class of tree rank at most $2$ such that $G = I(H)$ for a fixed interpretation $I$. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first efficient "interpretation reversal" result that generalizes the result of Gajarsk\'y et al. [LICS 2016], who showed an analogous result for graph classes interpretable in classes of graphs of bounded degree.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18904v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Gajarsk\'y, Rose McCarty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability for binary scalar products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17933v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bohn, Faenza, Fiorini, Fisikopoulos, Macchia, and Pashkovich (2015) conjectured that 2-level polytopes cannot simultaneously have many vertices and many facets, namely, that the maximum of the product of the number of vertices and facets is attained on the cube and cross-polytope. This was proved in a recent work by Kupavskii and Weltge. In this paper, we resolve a strong version of the conjecture by Bohn et al., and find the maximum possible product of the number of vertices and the number of facets in a 2-level polytope that is not affinely isomorphic to the cube or the cross-polytope. To do this, we get a sharp stability result of Kupavskii and Weltge's upper bound on $\left|\mathcal A\right|\cdot\left|\mathcal B\right|$ for $\mathcal A,\mathcal B \subseteq \mathbb R^d$ with a property that $\forall a \in \mathcal A, b \in \mathcal B$ the scalar product $\langle a, b\rangle \in\{0,1\}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17933v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey Kupavskii, Dmitry Tsarev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Spatial Hash Chemistry as a Minimalistic Open-Ended Evolutionary System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18027v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There is an increasing level of interest in open-endedness in the recent literature of Artificial Life and Artificial Intelligence. We previously proposed the cardinality leap of possibility spaces as a promising mechanism to facilitate open-endedness in artificial evolutionary systems, and demonstrated its effectiveness using Hash Chemistry, an artificial chemistry model that used a hash function as a universal fitness evaluator. However, the spatial nature of Hash Chemistry came with extensive computational costs involved in its simulation, and the particle density limit imposed to prevent explosion of computational costs prevented unbounded growth in complexity of higher-order entities. To address these limitations, here we propose a simpler non-spatial variant of Hash Chemistry in which spatial proximity of particles are represented explicitly in the form of multisets. This model modification achieved a significant reduction of computational costs in simulating the model. Results of numerical simulations showed much more significant unbounded growth in both maximal and average sizes of replicating higher-order entities than the original model, demonstrating the effectiveness of this non-spatial model as a minimalistic example of open-ended evolutionary systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18027v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Sayama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endhered patterns in matchings and RNA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18802v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An endhered (end-adhered) pattern is a subset of arcs in matchings, such that the corresponding starting points are consecutive and the same holds for the ending points. Such patterns are in one-to-one correspondence with the permutations. We focus on the occurrence frequency of such patterns in matchings and real-world RNA structures with pseudoknots. We present combinatorial results related to the distribution and asymptotic behavior of the pattern 21, which corresponds to two consecutive stacked bonds frequently encountered in RNA, and the pattern 12, representing the archetypal minimal pseudoknot. We show that in matchings these two patterns are equidistributed, which is quite different from what we can find in real-world RNAs. We also examine the distribution of endhered patterns of size 3, showing how the patterns change under the transformation called endhered twist. Finally, we compute the distributions of endhered patterns of size 2 and 3 in real-world secondary RNA structures with pseudoknots and discuss possible outcomes of our study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18802v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'elia Biane, Sergey Kirgizov, Greg Hampikian, Khaydar Nurligareev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the parameterized complexity of computing tree-partitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.11832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.11832v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the parameterized complexity of computing the tree-partition-width, a graph parameter equivalent to treewidth on graphs of bounded maximum degree. On one hand, we can obtain approximations of the tree-partition-width efficiently: we show that there is an algorithm that, given an $n$-vertex graph $G$ and an integer $k$, constructs a tree-partition of width $O(k^7)$ for $G$ or reports that $G$ has tree-partition-width more than $k$, in time $k^{O(1)}n^2$. We can improve slightly on the approximation factor by sacrificing the dependence on $k$, or on $n$. On the other hand, we show the problem of computing tree-partition-width exactly is XALP-complete, which implies that it is $W[t]$-hard for all $t$. We deduce XALP-completeness of the problem of computing the domino treewidth. Next, we adapt some known results on the parameter tree-partition-width and the topological minor relation, and use them to compare tree-partition-width to tree-cut width. Finally, for the related parameter weighted tree-partition-width, we give a similar approximation algorithm (with ratio now $O(k^{15})$) and show XALP-completeness for the special case where vertices and edges have weight 1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.11832v4</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans L. Bodlaender, Carla Groenland, Hugo Jacob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bhargava greedoid as a Gaussian elimination greedoid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.05535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2001.05535v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Inspired by Manjul Bhargava's theory of generalized factorials, Fedor Petrov and the author have defined the "Bhargava greedoid" -- a greedoid (a matroid-like set system on a finite set) assigned to any "ultra triple" (a somewhat extended variant of a finite ultrametric space). Here we show that the Bhargava greedoid of a finite ultra triple is always a "Gaussian elimination greedoid" over any sufficiently large (e.g., infinite) field; this is a greedoid analogue of a representable matroid. We find necessary and sufficient conditions on the size of the field to ensure this.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2001.05535v5</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darij Grinberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the minimum number of arcs in $4$-dicritical oriented graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.10784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.10784v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The dichromatic number $\vec{\chi}(D)$ of a digraph $D$ is the minimum number of colours needed to colour the vertices of a digraph such that each colour class induces an acyclic subdigraph. A digraph $D$ is $k$-dicritical if $\vec{\chi}(D) = k$ and each proper subdigraph $H$ of $D$ satisfies $\vec{\chi}(H) &lt; k$.
  For integers $k$ and $n$, we define $d_k(n)$ (respectively $o_k(n)$) as the minimum number of arcs possible in a $k$-dicritical digraph (respectively oriented graph). Kostochka and Stiebitz have shown that $d_4(n) \geq \frac{10}{3}n -\frac{4}{3}$. They also conjectured that there is a constant $c$ such that $o_k(n) \geq cd_k(n)$ for $k\geq 3$ and $n$ large enough. This conjecture is known to be true for $k=3$ (Aboulker et al.).
  In this work, we prove that every $4$-dicritical oriented graph on $n$ vertices has at least $(\frac{10}{3}+\frac{1}{51})n-1$ arcs, showing the conjecture for $k=4$. We also characterise exactly the $k$-dicritical digraphs on $n$ vertices with exactly $\frac{10}{3}n -\frac{4}{3}$ arcs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.10784v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fr\'ed\'eric Havet, Lucas Picasarri-Arrieta, Cl\'ement Rambaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting Moments of Autocorrelation Demerit Factors of Binary Sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.14566v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An aperiodic binary sequence of length $\ell$ is a doubly infinite sequence $f=\ldots,f_{-1},f_0,f_1,\ldots$ with $f_j \in \{-1,1\}$ when $0 \leq j &lt; \ell$ and and $f_j=0$ otherwise. Various problems in engineering and natural science demand binary sequences that do not resemble translates of themselves. The autocorrelation of $f$ at shift $s$ is the dot product of $f$ with the sequence obtained by translating $f$ by $s$ places. The demerit factor of $f$ is the sum of the squares of the autocorrelations at all nonzero shifts for the sequence obtained by normalizing $f$ to unit Euclidean norm. Low demerit factor therefore indicates low self-similarity under translation. We endow the $2^\ell$ binary sequences of length $\ell$ with uniform probability measure and consider the distribution of their demerit factors. Earlier works used combinatorial techniques to find exact formulas for the mean, variance, skewness, and kurtosis of the distribution as a function of $\ell$. These revealed that for $\ell \geq 4$, the $p$th central moment of this distribution is strictly positive for every $p \geq 2$. This article shows that every $p$th central moment is a quasi-polynomial function of $\ell$ with rational coefficients divided by $\ell^{2 p}$. It also shows that, in the limit as $\ell$ tends to infinity, the $p$th standardized moment is the same as that of the standard normal distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.14566v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. Katz, Miriam E. Ramirez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumeration Kernels of Polynomial Size for Cuts of Bounded Degree</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.01286v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Enumeration kernelization was first proposed by Creignou et al. [TOCS 2017] and was later refined by Golovach et al. [JCSS 2022] into two different variants: fully-polynomial enumeration kernelization and polynomial-delay enumeration kernelization. In this paper, we consider the DEGREE-d-CUT problem from the perspective of (polynomial-delay) enumeration kenrelization. Given an undirected graph G = (V, E), a cut F = (A, B) is a degree-d-cut of G if every $u \in A$ has at most d neighbors in B and every $v \in B$ has at most d neighbors in A. Checking the existence of a degree-d-cut in a graph is a well-known NP-hard problem and is well-studied in parameterized complexity [Algorithmica 2021, IWOCA 2021]. This problem also generalizes a well-studied problem MATCHING CUT (set d = 1) that has been a central problem in the literature of polynomial-delay enumeration kernelization. In this paper, we study three different enumeration variants of this problem, ENUM DEGREE-d-CUT, ENUM MIN-DEGREE-d-CUT and ENUM MAX-DEGREE-d-CUT that intends to enumerate all the d-cuts, all the minimal d-cuts and all the maximal degree-d-cuts respectively. We consider various structural parameters of the input and for every fixed $d \geq 1$, we provide polynomial-delay enumeration kernelizations of polynomial size for ENUM DEGREE-d-CUT and ENUM MAX-DEGREE-d-CUT and fully-polynomial enumeration kernels of polynomial size for ENUM MIN-DEGREE-d-CUT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.01286v5</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diptapriyo Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimum number of arcs in $k$-critical digraphs with order at most $2k-1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03584v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The dichromatic number $\vec{\chi}(D)$ of a digraph $D$ is the least integer $k$ for which $D$ has a coloring with $k$ colors such that there is no monochromatic directed cycle in $D$. The digraphs considered here are finite and may have antiparallel arcs, but no parallel arcs. A digraph $D$ is called $k$-critical if each proper subdigraph $D'$ of $D$ satisfies $\vec{\chi}(D')&lt;\vec{\chi}(D)=k$. For integers $k$ and $n$, let $\overrightarrow{\mathrm{ext}}(k,n)$ denote the minimum number of arcs possible in a $k$-critical digraph of order $n$. It is easy to show that $\overrightarrow{\mathrm{ext}}(2,n)=n$ for all $n\geq 2$, and $\overrightarrow{\mathrm{ext}}(3,n)\geq 2n$ for all possible $n$, where equality holds if and only if $n$ is odd and $n\geq 3$. As a main result we prove that if $n, k$ and $p$ are integers with $n=k+p$ and $2\leq p \leq k-1$, then $\overrightarrow{\mathrm{ext}}(k,n)=2({\binom{n}{2}} - (p^2+1))$, and we give an exact characterisation of $k$-critical digraphs for which equality holds. This generalizes a result about critical graphs obtained in 1963 by Tibor Gallai.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03584v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Picasarri-Arrieta, Michael Stiebitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summing the sum of digits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16806v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit and generalize inequalities for the summatory function of the sum of digits in a given integer base. We prove that several known results can be deduced from a theorem in a 2023 paper by Mohanty, Greenbury, Sarkany, Narayanan, Dingle, Ahnert, and Louis, whose primary scope is the maximum mutational robustness in genotype-phenotype maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16806v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Paul Allouche, Manon Stipulanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
