<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM</link>
    <description>cs.DM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 04:02:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Reflexive Composition of Elementary State Machines, with an Application to the Reversal of Cellular Automata Rule 90</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the dynamics of a one-dimensional lattice of state machines on two states and two symbols sequentially updated via a process of "reflexive composition." The space of 256 machines exhibits a variety of behavior, including substitution, reversible "billiard ball" dynamics, and fractal nesting. We show that one machine generates the Sierpinski Triangle and, for a subset of boundary conditions, is isomorphic to cellular automata Rule 90 in Wolfram's naming scheme. More surprisingly, two other machines follow trajectories that map to Rule 90 in reverse. Whereas previous techniques have been developed to uncover preimages of Rule 90, this is the first study to produce such inverse dynamics naturally from the formalism itself. We argue that the system's symmetric treatment of state and message underlies its expressive power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07186v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Salzberg, Hiroki Sayama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniCO: Towards a Unified Model for Combinatorial Optimization Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Combinatorial Optimization (CO) encompasses a wide range of problems that arise in many real-world scenarios. While significant progress has been made in developing learning-based methods for specialized CO problems, a unified model with a single architecture and parameter set for diverse CO problems remains elusive. Such a model would offer substantial advantages in terms of efficiency and convenience. In this paper, we introduce UniCO, a unified model for solving various CO problems. Inspired by the success of next-token prediction, we frame each problem-solving process as a Markov Decision Process (MDP), tokenize the corresponding sequential trajectory data, and train the model using a transformer backbone. To reduce token length in the trajectory data, we propose a CO-prefix design that aggregates static problem features. To address the heterogeneity of state and action tokens within the MDP, we employ a two-stage self-supervised learning approach. In this approach, a dynamic prediction model is first trained and then serves as a pre-trained model for subsequent policy generation. Experiments across 10 CO problems showcase the versatility of UniCO, emphasizing its ability to generalize to new, unseen problems with minimal fine-tuning, achieving even few-shot or zero-shot performance. Our framework offers a valuable complement to existing neural CO methods that focus on optimizing performance for individual problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06290v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zefang Zong, Xiaochen Wei, Guozhen Zhang, Chen Gao, Huandong Wang, Yong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Finding Randomly Planted Cliques in Arbitrary Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06725v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a planted clique model introduced by Feige where a complete graph of size $c\cdot n$ is planted uniformly at random in an arbitrary $n$-vertex graph. We give a simple deterministic algorithm that, in almost linear time, recovers a clique of size $(c/3)^{O(1/c)} \cdot n$ as long as the original graph has maximum degree at most $(1-p)n$ for some fixed $p&gt;0$. The proof hinges on showing that the degrees of the final graph are correlated with the planted clique, in a way similar to (but more intricate than) the classical $G(n,\frac{1}{2})+K_{\sqrt{n}}$ planted clique model. Our algorithm suggests a separation from the worst-case model, where, assuming the Unique Games Conjecture, no polynomial algorithm can find cliques of size $\Omega(n)$ for every fixed $c&gt;0$, even if the input graph has maximum degree $(1-p)n$. Our techniques extend beyond the planted clique model. For example, when the planted graph is a balanced biclique, we recover a balanced biclique of size larger than the best guarantees known for the worst case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06725v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Agrimonti, Marco Bressan, Tommaso d'Orsi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Spin Elimination in Ising Hamiltonians and Energy-Based Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07163v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an exact spin-elimination technique that reduces the dimensionality of both quadratic and k-local Ising Hamiltonians while preserving their original ground-state configurations. By systematically replacing each removed spin with an effective interaction among its neighbors, our method lowers the total spin count without invoking approximations or iterative recalculations. This capability is especially beneficial for hardware-constrained platforms, classical or quantum, that can directly implement multi-body interactions but have limited qubit or spin resources. We demonstrate three key advances enabled by this technique. First, we handle larger instances of benchmark problems such as Max-Cut on cubic graphs without exceeding a 2-local interaction limit. Second, we reduce qubit requirements in QAOA-based integer factorization on near-term quantum devices, thus extending the feasible range of integers to be factorized. Third, we improve memory capacity in Hopfield associative memories and enhance memory retrieval by suppressing spurious attractors, enhancing retrieval performance. Our spin-elimination procedure trades local spin complexity for higher-order couplings or higher node degrees in a single pass, opening new avenues for scaling up combinatorial optimization and energy-based machine learning on near-term hardware. Finally, these results underscore that the next-generation physical spin machines will likely capitalize on k-local spin Hamiltonians to offer an alternative to classical computations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07163v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalia G. Berloff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Sparse Matrix Coloring and Bicoloring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07308v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sparse matrix coloring and bicoloring are fundamental building blocks of sparse automatic differentiation. Bicoloring is particularly advantageous for rectangular Jacobian matrices with at least one dense row and column. Indeed, in such cases, unidirectional row or column coloring demands a number of colors equal to the number of rows or columns. We introduce a new strategy for bicoloring that encompasses both direct and substitution-based decompression approaches. Our method reformulates the two variants of bicoloring as star and acyclic colorings of an augmented symmetric matrix. We extend the concept of neutral colors, previously exclusive to bicoloring, to symmetric colorings, and we propose a post-processing routine that neutralizes colors to further reduce the overall color count. We also present the Julia package SparseMatrixColorings, which includes these new bicoloring algorithms alongside all standard coloring methods for sparse derivative matrix computation. Compared to ColPack, the Julia package also offers enhanced implementations for star and acyclic coloring, vertex ordering, as well as decompression.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07308v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Montoison, Guillaume Dalle, Assefaw Gebremedhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Lifting of Discrete Logarithms Modulo Prime Powers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07434v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a deterministic algorithm that, given a prime $p$ and a solution $x \in \mathbb Z$ to the discrete logarithm problem $a^x \equiv b \pmod p$ with $p\nmid a$, efficiently lifts it to a solution modulo $p^k$, i.e., $a^x \equiv b \pmod {p^k}$, for any fixed $k \geq 1$.
  The algorithm performs $k(\lceil \log_2 p\rceil +2)+O(\log p)$ multiplications modulo $p^k$ in the worst case, improving upon prior lifting methods by at least a factor of 8.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07434v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Viglietta, Yasuyuki Kachi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On core of categorical product of (di)graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The core of a graph is the smallest graph (in terms of number of vertices) to which it is homomorphically equivalent.
  The question of the possible order of the core of the tensor product (also known as categorical, Heidetnemi or direct product) of two graphs captures some well known problems. For instance, the recent counterexample to the Hedetniemi conjecture for 5-chromatic graphs is equivalent to saying that there are cores of order at least 5 whose product has a core of order 4.
  In this work, motivated by a question from Leonid Libkin in the area of graph databases, we first present methods of building cores whose categorical product is also a core. Extending on this we present sufficient conditions for a set of cores to have a product which is also a core. Presenting an example of such a family of digraphs, we construct a family of $\binom{2n}{n}$ digraphs, where the number of vertices of each is between $n^2+5n+2$ and $3n^2+3n+2$ and the product is a core. We then present a method of transforming the example into a family of graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07463v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Naserasr, Cyril Pujol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isomorphisms of unit distance graphs of layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07799v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For any $\varepsilon\in (0,+\infty)$, consider the metric spaces $\mathbb{R} \times [0,\varepsilon]$ in the Euclidean plane named layers or strips. B. Baslaugh in 1998 found the minimal width $\varepsilon \in (0,1)$ of a layer such that its unit distance graph contains a cycle of a given odd length $k$. The first of the main results of this paper is the fact that the unit distance graphs of two layers $\mathbb{R} \times [0,\varepsilon_1], \mathbb{R} \times [0,\varepsilon_2]$ are non-isomorphic for any different values $\varepsilon_1,\varepsilon_2 \in (0,+\infty)$. We also get a multidimensional analogue of this theorem. For given $n,m \in \mathbb{N}, p \in (1,+\infty), \varepsilon \in (0,+\infty)$, we say that the metric space on $\mathbb{R}^n \times [0,\varepsilon]^m$ with the metric space distance generated by $l_p$-norm in $\mathbb{R}^{n+m}$ is a layer $L(n,m,p,\varepsilon)$. We show that the unit distance graphs of multi-layers $L(n,m,p,\varepsilon_1), L(n,m,p,\varepsilon_2)$ are non-isomorphic for $\varepsilon_1 \neq \varepsilon_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07799v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Igorevich Bikeev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic analysis and efficient random sampling of directed ordered acyclic graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.14710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.14710v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) are directed graphs in which there is no path from a vertex to itself. DAGs are an omnipresent data structure in computer science and the problem of counting the DAGs of given number of vertices and to sample them uniformly at random has been solved respectively in the 70's and the 00's. In this paper, we propose to explore a new variation of this model where DAGs are endowed with an independent ordering of the out-edges of each vertex, thus allowing to model a wide range of existing data structures. We provide efficient algorithms for sampling objects of this new class, both with or without control on the number of edges, and obtain an asymptotic equivalent of their number. We also show the applicability of our method by providing an effective algorithm for the random generation of classical labelled DAGs with a prescribed number of vertices and edges, based on a similar approach. This is the first known algorithm for sampling labelled DAGs with full control on the number of edges, and it meets a need in terms of applications, that had already been acknowledged in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.14710v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin P\'epin, Alfredo Viola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triangle processes on graphs with given degree sequence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.08499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.08499v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The switch chain is a well-studied Markov chain which generates random graphs with a given degree sequence and has uniform stationary distribution. Motivated by the high number of triangles seen in some real-world networks, we study a variant of the switch chain which is more likely to produce graphs with higher numbers of triangles. Specifically, we apply a Metropolis scheme designed to have the following stationary distribution: graph $G$ has probability proportional to $\lambda^{\min\{t(G),\nu\}}$, where $t(G)$ is the number of triangles in $G$ and $\nu$ is a cut-off value introduced to moderate the impact of graphs with a very high number of triangles. We assume that the ``activity'' $\lambda$ satisfies $\lambda\geq 1$, and call the resulting chain the modified Metropolis switch chain. We prove that the modified Metropolis switch chain is rapidly mixing whenever the (standard) switch chain is rapidly mixing, provided that the activity and maximum degree are not too large.
  The triangle switch (or ``$\triangle$-switch'') chain is a restriction of the switch chain which only performs switches that change the set of triangles in the graph. We prove that the $\triangle$-switch chain is irreducible for any degree sequence with minimum degree at least 3, and prove a rapid mixing result for the modified Metropolis $\triangle$-switch chain.
  Finally, we investigate the distribution of triangles in random graphs with given degrees, under both the uniform distribution and the distribution in which graph $G$ has probability proportional to $\lambda^{t(G)}$. Our analysis implies that the imposition of the cut-off $\nu$ does not significantly impact the behaviour of these modified Metropolis chains over polynomially many steps</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.08499v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin Cooper, Martin Dyer, Catherine Greenhill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planar cycle-extendable graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15416v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For most problems pertaining to perfect matchings, one may restrict attention to matching covered graphs - that is, connected nontrivial graphs with the property that each edge belongs to some perfect matching. There is extensive literature on these graphs that are also known as 1-extendable graphs (since each edge extends to a perfect matching) including an ear decomposition theorem due to Lov\'asz and Plummer.
  A cycle $C$ of a graph $G$ is conformal if $G-V(C)$ has a perfect matching; such cycles play an important role in the study of perfect matchings, especially when investigating the Pfaffian orientation problem. A matching covered graph $G$ is cycle-extendable if - for each even cycle $C$ - the cycle $C$ is conformal, or equivalently, each perfect matching of $C$ extends to a perfect matching of $G$, or equivalently, $C$ is the symmetric difference of two perfect matchings of $G$, or equivalently, $C$ extends to an ear decomposition of $G$. In the literature, these are also known as cycle-nice or as 1-cycle resonant graphs.
  Zhang, Wang, Yuan, Ng and Cheng, 2022, provided a characterization of claw-free cycle-extendable graphs. Guo and Zhang, 2004, and independently Zhang and Li, 2012, provided characterizations of bipartite planar cycle-extendable graphs. In this paper, we establish a characterization of all planar cycle-extendable graphs - in terms of $K_2$ and four infinite families.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15416v5</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Y Dalwadi, Kapil R Shenvi Pause, Ajit A Diwan, Nishad Kothari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic aspects of semistability of quiver representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06493v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the semistability of quiver representations from an algorithmic perspective. We present efficient algorithms for several fundamental computational problems on the semistability of quiver representations: deciding the semistability and $\sigma$-semistability, finding the maximizers of King's criterion, and computing the Harder--Narasimhan filtration. We also investigate a class of polyhedral cones defined by the linear system in King's criterion, which we refer to as King cones. For rank-one representations, we demonstrate that these King cones can be encoded by submodular flow polytopes, enabling us to decide the $\sigma$-semistability in strongly polynomial time. Our approach employs submodularity in quiver representations, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06493v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuni Iwamasa, Taihei Oki, Tasuku Soma</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
