<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM</link>
    <description>cs.DM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Instability of all Backoff Protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21315v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we prove Aldous's conjecture from 1987 that there is no backoff protocol that is stable for any positive arrival rate. The setting is a communication channel for coordinating requests for a shared resource. Each user who wants to access the resource makes a request by sending a message to the channel. The users don't have any way to communicate with each other, except by sending messages to the channel. The operation of the channel proceeds in discrete time steps. If exactly one message is sent to the channel during a time step then this message succeeds (and leaves the system). If multiple messages are sent during a time step then these messages collide. Each of the users that sent these messages therefore waits a random amount of time before re-sending. A backoff protocol is a randomised algorithm for determining how long to wait -- the waiting time is a function of how many collisions a message has had. Specifically, a backoff protocol is described by a send sequence $\overline{p} = (p_0,p_1,p_2,\ldots)$. If a message has had $k$ collisions before a time step then, with probability $p_k$, it sends during that time step, whereas with probability $1-p_k$ it is silent (waiting for later). The most famous backoff protocol is binary exponential backoff, where $p_k = 2^{-k}$. Under Kelly's model, in which the number of new messages that arrive in the system at each time step is given by a Poisson random variable with mean $\lambda$, Aldous proved that binary exponential backoff is unstable for any positive $\lambda$. He conjectured that the same is true for any backoff protocol. We prove this conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21315v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leslie Ann Goldberg, John Lapinskas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2-dimensional unit vector flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study $2$-dimensional unit vector flows on graphs, that is, nowhere-zero flows that assign to each oriented edge a unit vector in $\mathbb R^{3}$. We give a new geometric characterization of $\mathbb S^{2}$-flows on cubic graphs. We also prove that the class of cubic graphs admitting an $\mathbb S^{2}$-flow is closed under a natural composition operation, which yields further constructions; in particular, blowing up a vertex into a triangle preserves the existence of an $\mathbb S^{2}$-flow. Our second contribution is algebraic: we extend the rank-based approach of [SIAM J. Discrete Math., 29 (2015), pp.~2166--2178] from $\mathbb S^{1}$-flows to $\mathbb S^{2}$-flows. More precisely, we show that if an $\mathbb S^{2}$-flow $\varphi$ satisfies $\operatorname{rank}(S_{\mathbb{Q}}(\varphi))\le 2$ and $S_{\mathbb{Q}}(\varphi)$ is odd-coordinate-free, then the graph admits a nowhere-zero $4$-flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21526v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hussein Houdrouge, Bobby Miraftab, Pat Morin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DRESS and the WL Hierarchy: Climbing One Deletion at a Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21557v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Cai--F\"urer--Immerman (CFI) construction provides the canonical family of hard instances for the Weisfeiler--Leman (WL) hierarchy: distinguishing the two non-isomorphic CFI graphs over a base graph $G$ requires $k$-WL where $k$ meets or exceeds the treewidth of $G$. In this paper, we introduce $\Delta^\ell$-DRESS, which applies $\ell$ levels of iterated node deletion to the DRESS continuous structural refinement framework. $\Delta^\ell$-DRESS runs Original-DRESS on all $\binom{n}{\ell}$ subgraphs obtained by removing $\ell$ nodes, and compares the resulting histograms. We show empirically on the canonical CFI benchmark family that Original-DRESS ($\Delta^0$) already distinguishes $\text{CFI}(K_3)$ (requiring 2-WL), and that each additional deletion level extends the range by one WL level: $\Delta^1$ reaches 3-WL, $\Delta^2$ reaches 4-WL, and $\Delta^3$ reaches 5-WL, distinguishing CFI pairs over $K_n$ for $n = 3, \ldots, 6$. Crucially, $\Delta^3$ fails on $\text{CFI}(K_7)$ (requiring 6-WL), confirming a sharp boundary at $(\ell+2)$-WL. The computational cost is $\mathcal{O}\bigl(\binom{n}{\ell} \cdot I \cdot m \cdot d_{\max}\bigr)$ -- polynomial in $n$ for fixed $\ell$. These results establish $\Delta^\ell$-DRESS as a practical framework for systematically climbing the WL hierarchy on the canonical CFI benchmark family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21557v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduar Castrillo Velilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steiner Forest for $H$-Subgraph-Free Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21859v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Our main result is a full classification, for every connected graph $H$, of the computational complexity of Steiner Forest on $H$-subgraph-free graphs. To obtain this dichotomy, we establish the following new algorithmic, hardness, and combinatorial results:
  Algorithms: We identify two new classes of graph-theoretical structures that make it possible to solve Steiner Forest in polynomial time. Roughly speaking, our algorithms handle the following cases: (1) a set $X$ of vertices of bounded size that are pairwise connected by subgraphs of treewidth $2$ or bounded size, possibly together with an independent set of arbitrary size that is connected to $X$ in an arbitrary way; (2) a set $X$ of vertices of arbitrary size that are pairwise connected in a cyclic manner by subgraphs of treewidth $2$ or bounded size.
  Hardness results: We show that Steiner Forest remains NP-complete for graphs with 2-deletion set number $3$. (The $c$-deletion set number is the size of a smallest cutset $S$ such that every component of $G-S$ has at most $c$ vertices.)
  Combinatorial results: To establish the dichotomy, we perform a delicate graph-theoretic analysis showing that if $H$ is a path or a subdivided claw, then excluding $H$ as a subgraph either yields one of the two algorithmically favourable structures described above, or yields a graph class for which NP-completeness of Steiner Forest follows from either our new hardness result or a previously known one.
  Along the way to classifying the hardness for excluded subgraphs, we establish a dichotomy for graphs with $c$-deletion set number at most $k$. Specifically, our results together with pre-existing ones show that Steiner Forest is polynomial-time solvable if (1) $c=1$ and $k\geq 0$, or (2) $c=2$ and $k\leq 2$, or (3) $c\geq 3$ and $k=1$, and is NP-complete otherwise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21859v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tala Eagling-Vose, David C. Kutner, Felicia Lucke, D\'aniel Marx, Barnaby Martin, Dani\"el Paulusma, Erik Jan van Leeuwen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbols frequencies in the Thue--Morse word in base $3/2$ and related conjectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21895v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a binary Thue--Morse-type sequence arising from the base-$3/2$ expansion of integers, an archetypal automatic sequence in a rational base numeration system. Because the sequence is generated by a periodic iteration of morphisms rather than a single primitive substitution, classical Perron--Frobenius methods do not directly apply to determine symbol frequencies. We prove that both symbols ${\tt 0},{\tt 1}$ occur with frequency $1/2$ and we show uniform recurrence and symmetry properties of its set of factors. The proof reveals a structural bridge between combinatorics on words and harmonic analysis: the first difference sequence is shown to be Toeplitz, providing dynamical rigidity, while filtered frequencies naturally encode a dyadic structure that lifts to the compact group of $2$-adic integers. In this $2$-adic setting, desubstitution becomes a linear operator on Fourier coefficients, and a spectral contraction argument enforces uniqueness of limiting densities. Our results answer several conjectures of Dekking (on a sibling sequence) and illustrate how harmonic analysis on compact groups can be fruitfully combined with substitution dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21895v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Cassaigne, Basti\`an Espinoza, Michel Rigo, Manon Stipulanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Permutation Flowshops Under Budgeted Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the robust permutation flowshop problem under the budgeted uncertainty model, where at most a given number of job processing times may deviate on each machine. We show that solutions for this problem can be determined by solving polynomially many instances of the corresponding nominal problem. As a direct consequence, our result implies that this robust flowshop problem can be solved in polynomial time for two machines, and can be approximated in polynomial time for any fixed number of machines. The reduction that is our main result follows from an analysis similar to Bertsimas and Sim (2003) except that dualization is applied to the terms of a min-max objective rather than to a linear objective function. Our result may be surprising considering that heuristic and exact integer programming based methods have been developed in the literature for solving the two-machine flowshop problem. We conclude by showing a logarithmic factor improvement in the overall running time implied by a naive reduction to nominal problems in the case of two machines and three machines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22110v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noam Goldberg, Danny Hermelin, Dvir Shabtay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving the Multiobjective Quasi-Clique Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10896v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a simple undirected graph $G$, a quasi-clique is a subgraph of $G$ whose density is at least $\gamma$ $(0 &lt; \gamma \leq 1)$. Finding a maximum quasi-clique has been addressed from two different perspectives: $i)$ maximizing vertex cardinality for a given edge density; and $ii)$ maximizing edge density for a given vertex cardinality. However, when no a priori preference information about cardinality and density is available, a more natural approach is to consider the problem from a multiobjective perspective. We introduce the Multiobjective Quasi-clique Problem (MOQC), which aims to find a quasi-clique by simultaneously maximizing both vertex cardinality and edge density. To efficiently address this problem, we explore the relationship among MOQC, its single-objective counterpart problems, and a biobjective optimization problem, along with several properties of the MOQC problem and quasi-cliques. We propose a baseline approach using $\varepsilon$-constraint scalarization and introduce a Two-phase strategy, which applies a dichotomic search based on weighted sum scalarization in the first phase and an $\varepsilon$-constraint methodology in the second phase. Additionally, we present a Three-phase strategy that combines the dichotomic search used in Two-phase with a vertex-degree-based local search employing novel sufficient conditions to assess quasi-clique efficiency, followed by an $\varepsilon$-constraint in a final stage. Experimental results on real-world sparse graphs indicate that the integrated use of dichotomic search and local search, together with mechanisms to assess quasi-clique efficiency, makes the Three-phase strategy an effective approach for solving the MOQC problem in terms of running time and ability to produce new efficient quasi-cliques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10896v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ejor.2024.12.018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Journal of Operational Research, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniela Scherer dos Santos, Kathrin Klamroth, Pedro Martins, Lu\'is Paquete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing the Approximate Minimum Degree Ordering Algorithm: Strategies and Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17097v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The approximate minimum degree algorithm is widely used before numerical factorization to reduce fill-in for sparse matrices. While considerable attention has been given to the numerical factorization process, less focus has been placed on parallelizing the approximate minimum degree algorithm itself. In this paper, we explore different parallelization strategies, and introduce a novel parallel framework that leverages multiple elimination on distance-2 independent sets. Our evaluation shows that parallelism within individual elimination steps is limited due to low computational workload and significant memory contention. In contrast, our proposed framework overcomes these challenges by parallelizing the work across elimination steps. To the best of our knowledge, our implementation is the first scalable shared memory implementation of the approximate minimum degree algorithm. Experimental results show that we achieve up to a 7.29x speedup using 64 threads over the state-of-the-art sequential implementation in SuiteSparse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17097v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1137/1.9781611979022.1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. 2026 SIAM Conf. on Parallel Processing for Scientific Computing (PP26), pp. 1-15 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Hsiang Chang, Ayd{\i}n Bulu\c{c}, James Demmel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undecidability of the block gluing classes of homshifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21342v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A homshift is a $d$-dimensional shift of finite type which arises as the space of graph homomorphisms from the grid graph $\mathbb Z^d$ to a finite connected undirected graph $G$. While shifts of finite type are known to be mired by the swamp of undecidability, homshifts seem to be better behaved and there was hope that all the properties of homshifts are decidable. In this paper we build on the work by Gangloff, Hellouin de Menibus and Oprocha (arxiv:2211.04075) to show that finer mixing properties are undecidable for reasons completely different than the ones used to prove undecidability for general multidimensional shifts of finite type. Inspired by the work of Gao, Jackson, Krohne and Seward (arxiv:1803.03872) and elementary algebraic topology, we interpret the square cover introduced by Gangloff, Hellouin de Menibus and Oprocha topologically. Using this interpretation, we prove that it is undecidable whether a homshift is $\Theta(n)$-block gluing or not, by relating this problem to the one of finiteness for finitely presented groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21342v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nishant Chandgotia, Silv\`ere Gangloff, Benjamin Hellouin de Menibus, Piotr Oprocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
