<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM</link>
    <description>cs.DM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 05:16:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multipacking on graphs and Euclidean metric space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A \emph{multipacking} in an undirected graph $G=(V,E)$ is a set $M\subseteq V$ such that for every vertex $v\in V$ and for every integer $r\geq 1$, the ball of radius $ r $ around $ v $ contains at most $r$ vertices of $M$. The \textsc{Multipacking} problem asks whether a graph contains a multipacking of size at least $k$. For more than a decade, it remained open whether \textsc{Multipacking} is \textsc{NP-complete} or polynomial-time solvable, although it is known to be polynomial-time solvable for some classes (e.g., strongly chordal graphs and grids). Foucaud, Gras, Perez, and Sikora [\textit{Algorithmica} 2021] showed it is \textsc{NP-complete} for directed graphs and \textsc{W[1]-hard} when parameterized by the solution size. We resolve the open question by proving \textsc{Multipacking} is \textsc{NP-complete} for undirected graphs and \textsc{W[2]-hard} when parameterized by the solution size. Furthermore, we show it remains \textsc{NP-complete} and \textsc{W[2]-hard} even for chordal, bipartite, claw-free, regular, CONV, and chordal$\cap\frac{1}{2}$-hyperbolic graphs (a superclass of strongly chordal graphs), and we provide approximation algorithms for cactus, chordal, and $\delta$-hyperbolic graphs. Moreover, we study the relationship between multipacking number and broadcast domination number for cactus, chordal, and $\delta$-hyperbolic graphs. Further, we prove that for all $r\geq 2$, \textsc{$r$-Multipacking} is \textsc{NP-complete} even for planar bipartite graphs with bounded degree, and also for bounded-diameter chordal and bounded-diameter bipartite graphs. For geometric variants, in $\mathbb{R}^2$ a maximum $1$-multipacking can be computed in polynomial time, but computing a maximum $2$-multipacking is \textsc{NP-hard}, and we provide approximation and parameterized algorithms for the $2$-multipacking problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07927v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sk Samim Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsplittable Transshipments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07230v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the Unsplittable Transshipment Problem in directed graphs with multiple sources and sinks. An unsplittable transshipment routes given supplies and demands using at most one path for each source-sink pair. Although they are a natural generalization of single source unsplittable flows, unsplittable transshipments raise interesting new challenges and require novel algorithmic techniques. As our main contribution, we give a nontrivial generalization of a seminal result of Dinitz, Garg, and Goemans (1999) by showing how to efficiently turn a given transshipment $x$ into an unsplittable transshipment $y$ with $y_a&lt;x_a+d_{\max}$ for all arcs $a$, where $d_{\max}$ is the maximum demand (or supply) value. Further results include bounds on the number of rounds required to satisfy all demands, where each round consists of an unsplittable transshipment that routes a subset of the demands while respecting arc capacity constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07230v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srinwanti Debgupta, Sarah Morell, Martin Skutella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cops and robber in graphs with bounded vertex cover number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07435v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Meyniel's conjecture states that $n$-vertex connected graphs have cop number $O(\sqrt{n})$. The current best known upper bound is $n/2^{(1-o(1))\sqrt{\log n}}$, proved independently by Lu and Peng (2011), and by Scott and Sudakov (2011). In this paper, we extend their result by showing that every connected graph with vertex cover number $k$ has cop number at most $k/2^{(1-o(1))\sqrt{\log k}}$. This is the first sublinear upper bound on the cop number in terms of the vertex cover number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07435v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prosenjit Bose, Louis Esperet, J\k{e}drzej Hodor, Gwena\"el Joret, Piotr Micek, Cl\'ement Rambaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helly-type problems from a topological perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07552v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss recent progress on topological Helly-type theorems and their variants. We provide an overview of two different proof techniques, one based on the nerve lemma, while the other on non-embeddability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07552v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel Pat\'ak, Zuzana Pat\'akov\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moment generating functions in combinatorial optimization: Bipartite matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07563v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a random model of minimum cost bipartite matching based on exponentially distributed edge costs, we show that the distribution of the cost of the optimal solution can be computed efficiently. The distribution is represented by its moment generating function, which in this model is always a rational function. The complex zeros of this function are of interest as the lack of zeros near the origin indicates a certain regularity of the distribution. We propose a conjecture according to which these moment generating functions never have complex zeros of smaller modulus than their first pole. For minimum cost perfect matching, also known as the assignment problem, such a zero-free disk would imply a Gaussian scaling limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07563v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johan W\"astlund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Parameterized Complexity of Independent Set and More when Excluding a Half-Graph, Co-Matching, or Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07606v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A theorem of Ding, Oporowski, Oxley, and Vertigan implies that any sufficiently large twin-free graph contains a large matching, a co-matching, or a half-graph as a semi-induced subgraph. The sizes of these unavoidable patterns are measured by the matching index, co-matching index, and half-graph index of a graph. Consequently, graph classes can be organized into the eight classes determined by which of the three indices are bounded.
  We completely classify the parameterized complexity of Independent Set, Clique, and Dominating Set across all eight of these classes. For this purpose, we first derive multiple tractability and hardness results from the existing literature, and then proceed to fill the identified gaps. Among our novel results, we show that Independent Set is fixed-parameter tractable on every graph class where the half-graph and co-matching indices are simultaneously bounded. Conversely, we construct a graph class with bounded half-graph index (but unbounded co-matching index), for which the problem is W[1]-hard.
  For the W[1]-hard cases of our classification, we review the state of approximation algorithms. Here, we contribute an approximation algorithm for Independent Set on classes of bounded half-graph index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07606v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Dreier, Nikolas M\"ahlmann, Sebastian Siebertz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determining the Outerthickness of Graphs Is NP-Hard</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07607v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a short, self-contained, and easily verifiable proof that determining the outerthickness of a general graph is NP-hard. This resolves a long-standing open problem on the computational complexity of outerthickness.
  Moreover, our hardness result applies to a more general covering problem $P_F$, defined as follows. Fix a proper graph class $F$ whose membership is decidable. Given an undirected simple graph $G$ and an integer $k$, the task is to cover the edge set $E(G)$ by at most $k$ subsets $E_1,\ldots,E_k$ such that each subgraph $(V(G),E_i)$ belongs to $F$. Note that if $F$ is monotone (in particular, when $F$ is the class of all outerplanar graphs), any such cover can be converted into an edge partition by deleting overlaps; hence, in this case, covering and partitioning are equivalent.
  Our result shows that for every proper graph class $F$ whose membership is decidable and that satisfies all of the following conditions: (a) $F$ is closed under topological minors, (b) $F$ is closed under $1$-sums, and (c) $F$ contains a cycle of length $3$, the problem $P_F$ is NP-hard for every fixed integer $k\ge 3$. In particular:
  For $F$ equal to the class of all outerplanar graphs, our result settles the long-standing open problem on the complexity of determining outerthickness.
  For $F$ equal to the class of all planar graphs, our result complements Mansfield's NP-hardness result for the thickness, which applies only to the case $k=2$.
  It is also worth noting that each of the three conditions above is necessary. If $F$ is the class of all eulerian graphs, then cond. (a) fails. If $F$ is the class of all pseudoforests, then cond. (b) fails. If $F$ is the class of all forests, then cond. (c) fails. For each of these three classes $F$, the problem $P_F$ is solvable in polynomial time for every fixed integer $k\ge 3$, showing that none of the three conditions can be dropped.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07607v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pin-Hsian Lee, Te-Cheng Liu, Meng-Tsung Tsai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boltzmann sampling and optimal exact-size sampling for directed acyclic graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08471v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose two efficient algorithms for generating uniform random directed acyclic graphs, including an asymptotically optimal exact-size sampler that performs $\frac{n^2}{2} + o(n^2)$ operations and requests to a random generator. This was achieved by extending the Boltzmann model for graphical generating functions and by using various decompositions of directed acyclic graphs. The presented samplers improve upon the state-of-the-art algorithms in terms of theoretical complexity and offer a significant speed-up in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08471v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech Gabryelski, Zbigniew Go{\l}\c{e}biewski, Martin P\'epin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Submodular Maximization over a Matroid $k$-Intersection: Multiplicative Improvement over Greedy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08473v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the problem of maximizing a non-negative monotone submodular objective $f$ subject to the intersection of $k$ arbitrary matroid constraints. The natural greedy algorithm guarantees $(k+1)$-approximation for this problem, and the state-of-the-art algorithm only improves this approximation ratio to $k$. We give a $\frac{2k\ln2}{1+\ln2}+O(\sqrt{k})&lt;0.819k+O(\sqrt{k})$ approximation for this problem. Our result is the first multiplicative improvement over the approximation ratio of the greedy algorithm for general $k$. We further show that our algorithm can be used to obtain roughly the same approximation ratio also for the more general problem in which the objective is not guaranteed to be monotone (the sublinear term in the approximation ratio becomes $O(k^{2/3})$ rather than $O(\sqrt{k})$ in this case).
  All of our results hold also when the $k$-matroid intersection constraint is replaced with a more general matroid $k$-parity constraint. Furthermore, unlike the case in many of the previous works, our algorithms run in time that is independent of $k$ and polynomial in the size of the ground set. Our algorithms are based on a hybrid greedy local search approach recently introduced by Singer and Thiery (STOC 2025) for the weighted matroid $k$-intersection problem, which is a special case of the problem we consider. Leveraging their approach in the submodular setting requires several non-trivial insights and algorithmic modifications since the marginals of a submodular function $f$, which correspond to the weights in the weighted case, are not independent of the algorithm's internal randomness. In the special weighted case studied by Singer and Thiery, our algorithms reduce to a variant of their algorithm with an improved approximation ratio of $k\ln2+1-\ln2&lt;0.694k+0.307$, compared to an approximation ratio of $\frac{k+1}{2\ln2}\approx0.722k+0.722$ guaranteed by Singer and Thiery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08473v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moran Feldman, Justin Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Claw, C_3)-free digraphs with unbounded dichromatic number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08736v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct orientations of rook graphs (whose underlying graphs are claw-free) that contain no directed $C_3$ but have unbounded dichromatic number. This disproves a conjecture of Aboulker, Charbit and Naserasr and improves a result of Carbonero, Koerts, Moore and Spirkl.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08736v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Aubian, Luis Kuffner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distortion of Metric Voting with Bounded Randomness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the design of voting rules in the metric distortion framework. It is known that any deterministic rule suffers distortion of at least $3$, and that randomized rules can achieve distortion strictly less than $3$, often at the cost of reduced transparency and interpretability. In this work, we explore the trade-off between these paradigms by asking whether it is possible to break the distortion barrier of $3$ using only "bounded" randomness. We answer in the affirmative by presenting a voting rule that (1) achieves distortion of at most $3 - \varepsilon$ for some absolute constant $\varepsilon &gt; 0$, and (2) selects a winner uniformly at random from a deterministically identified list of constant size. Our analysis builds on new structural results for the distortion and approximation of Maximal Lotteries and Stable Lotteries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08871v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyi Cai, D. D. Gao, Prasanna Ramakrishnan, Kangning Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On prescribing total preorders and linear orders to pairwise distances of points in Euclidean space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.08895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.08895v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that any total preorder on a set with $\binom{n}{2}$ elements coincides with the order on pairwise distances of some point collection of size $n$ in $\mathbb{R}^{n-1}$. For linear orders, a collection of $n$ points in $\mathbb{R}^{n-2}$ suffices. These bounds turn out to be optimal. We also find an optimal bound in a bipartite version for total preorders and a near-optimal bound for a bipartite version for linear orders. Our arguments include tools from convexity and positive semidefinite quadratic forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.08895v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V\'ictor Hugo Almendra-Hern\'andez, Leonardo Mart\'inez-Sandoval</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cops and robbers pebbling in graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00434v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Here we merge the two fields of Cops and Robbers and Graph Pebbling to introduce the new topic of Cops and Robbers Pebbling. Both paradigms can be described by moving tokens (the cops) along the edges of a graph to capture a special token (the robber). In Cops and Robbers, all tokens move freely, whereas, in Graph Pebbling, some of the chasing tokens disappear with movement while the robber is stationary. In Cops and Robbers Pebbling, some of the chasing tokens (cops) disappear with movement, while the robber moves freely. We define the cop pebbling number of a graph to be the minimum number of cops necessary to capture the robber in this context, and present upper and lower bounds and exact values, some involving various domination parameters, for an array of graph classes, including paths, cycles, trees, chordal graphs, high girth graphs, and cop-win graphs, as well as graph products. Furthermore we show that the analogous inequality for Graham's Pebbling Conjecture fails for cop pebbling and posit a conjecture along the lines of Meyniel's Cops and Robbers Conjecture that may hold for cop pebbling. We also offer several new problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00434v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nancy Clarke, Joshua Forkin, Glenn Hurlbert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Erd\H{o}s-P\'{o}sa property of cycles that are far apart</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13893v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that there exist functions $f,g:\mathbb{N}\to\mathbb{N}$ such that for all nonnegative integers $k$ and $d$, for every graph $G$, either $G$ contains $k$ cycles such that vertices of different cycles have distance greater than $d$ in $G$, or there exists a subset $X$ of vertices of $G$ with $|X|\leq f(k)$ such that $G-B_G(X,g(d))$ is a forest, where $B_G(X,r)$ denotes the set of vertices of $G$ having distance at most $r$ from a vertex of $X$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13893v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vida Dujmovi\'c, Gwena\"el Joret, Piotr Micek, Pat Morin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Young domination on Hamming rectangles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03788v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a family of domination-type problems in Cartesian products of two graphs. The framework captures several well-studied topics, including variants of bootstrap percolation, line growth, distance domination, and target set selection. We focus on Cartesian products of two complete graphs and formulate the notion of Young domination number in terms of a growth rule determined by a Young diagram; this number is the smallest cardinality of an initial set that covers the entire vertex set in a prescribed number $L$ of iterations of the rule.
  We compute the Young domination number with $L=1$ for several natural cases, including $k$-domination for Cartesian products of two complete graphs of the same order, thereby proving a conjecture from 2009 due to Burchett, Lane, and Lachniet. We show that the case of $L=1$ of Young domination is equivalent to computing bipartite Tur\'an numbers for families of double stars, yielding implications of our results in extremal graph theory. For arbitrary fixed $L$, we devise constant-factor approximation algorithms for the problem. Our approach is based on a variety of techniques, including duality between Young diagrams, algebraic formulations, explicit constructions, and dynamic programming.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03788v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Janko Gravner, Matja\v{z} Krnc, Martin Milani\v{c}, Jean-Florent Raymond</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colorful Minors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10467v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of colorful minors, which generalizes the classical concept of rooted minors in graphs. A $q$-colorful graph is defined as a pair $(G, \chi),$ where $G$ is a graph and $\chi$ assigns to each vertex a (possibly empty) subset of at most $q$ colors. The colorful minor relation enhances the classical minor relation by merging color sets at contracted edges and allowing the removal of colors from vertices. This framework naturally models algorithmic problems involving graphs with (possibly overlapping) annotated vertex sets. We develop a structural theory for colorful minors by establishing three core theorems characterizing $\mathcal{H}$-colorful minor-free graphs, where $\mathcal{H}$ consists either of a clique or a grid with all vertices assigned all colors, or of grids with colors segregated and ordered on the outer face. Our results reveal that when exclusion is imposed not only on graphs but also to the way colors are distributed in them, a more refined structural landscape appears.
  Leveraging our structural insights, we provide a complete classification -- parameterized by the number $q$ of colors -- of all colorful graphs that exhibit the Erd\H{o}s-P\'osa property with respect to colorful minors. On the algorithmic side, we deduce that colorful minor testing is fixed-parameter tractable. Together with the fact that the colorful minor relation forms a well-quasi-order, this implies that every colorful minor-monotone parameter on colorful graphs admits a fixed-parameter algorithm. Furthermore, we derive two algorithmic meta-theorems (AMTs) whose structural conditions are linked to extensions of treewidth and Hadwiger number on colorful graphs. Our results suggest how known AMTs can be extended to incorporate not only the structure of the input graph but also the way the colored vertices are distributed in it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10467v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Protopapas, Dimitrios M. Thilikos, Sebastian Wiederrecht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization game capture time of trees and outerplanar graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10443v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The localization game is a variant of the game of Cops and Robber in which the robber is invisible and moves between adjacent vertices, but the cops can probe any $k$ vertices of the graph to obtain the distance between probed vertices and the robber. The localization number of a graph is the minimum $k$ needed for cops to be able to locate the robber in finite time. The localization capture time is the number of rounds needed for cops to win.
  The localization capture time conjecture claims that there exists a constant $C$ such that the localization number of every connected graph on $n$ vertices is at most $Cn$. While it is known that the conjecture holds for trees, in this paper we significantly improve the known upper bound for the localization capture time of trees. We also prove the conjecture for a subclass of outerplanar graphs and present a generalization of the localization game that appears useful for making further progress towards the conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10443v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vesna Ir\v{s}i\v{c} Chenoweth, Matija Skrt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diameter Bounds for Friends-and-Strangers Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23511v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Consider two $n$-vertex graphs $X$ and $Y$, where we interpret $X$ as a social network with edges representing friendships and $Y$ as a movement graph with edges representing adjacent positions. The friends-and-strangers graph $\mathsf{FS}(X,Y)$ is a graph on the $n!$ permutations $V(X)\to V(Y)$, where two configurations are adjacent if and only if one can be obtained from the other by swapping two friends located on adjacent positions. Friends-and-strangers graphs were first introduced by Defant and Kravitz, and generalize sliding puzzles as well as token swapping problems. Previous work has largely focused on their connectivity properties.
  In this paper, we study the diameter of the connected components of $\mathsf{FS}(X, Y)$. We extend the result of Kornhauser, Miller, and Spirakis on sliding puzzles to general graphs in two ways. First, we show that the diameter of $\mathsf{FS}(X, Y)$ is polynomially bounded when both the friendship and the movement graphs have large minimum degree. Second, when both the underlying graphs $X$ and $Y$ are Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi random graphs, we show that the distance between any pair of configurations is almost always polynomially bounded under certain conditions on the edge probabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23511v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amogh Akella, Rupert Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Branch-width of connectivity functions is fixed-parameter tractable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.04756v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A connectivity function on a finite set $V$ is a symmetric submodular function $f \colon 2^V \to \mathbb{Z}$ with $f(\emptyset)=0$. We prove that finding a branch-decomposition of width at most $k$ for a connectivity function given by an oracle is fixed-parameter tractable (FPT), by providing an algorithm of running time $2^{O(k^2)} \gamma n^6 \log n$, where $\gamma$ is the time to compute $f(X)$ for any set $X$, and $n = |V|$. This improves the previous algorithm by Oum and Seymour [J. Combin. Theory Ser. B, 2007], which runs in time $\gamma n^{O(k)}$. Our algorithm can be applied to rank-width of graphs, branch-width of matroids, branch-width of (hyper)graphs, and carving-width of graphs. This resolves an open problem asked by Hlin\v{e}n\'y [SIAM J. Comput., 2005], who asked whether branch-width of matroids given by the rank oracle is fixed-parameter tractable. Furthermore, our algorithm improves the best known dependency on $k$ in the running times of FPT algorithms for graph branch-width, rank-width, and carving-width.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.04756v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuukka Korhonen, Sang-il Oum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Additive sink subtraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18715v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Subtraction games are a classical topic in Combinatorial Game Theory. A result of Golomb~(1966) shows that every subtraction game with a finite move set has an eventually periodic nim-sequence, but the known proof yields only an exponential upper bound on the period length. Flammenkamp (1997) conjectures a striking classification for three-move subtraction games: non-additive rulesets exhibit linear period lengths of the form ``the sum of two moves'', where the choice of which two moves displays fractal-like behavior, while additive sets $S=\{a,b,a+b\}$ have purely periodic outcomes with linear or quadratic period lengths. Despite early attention in \emph{Winning Ways} (1982), the general additive case remains open. We introduce and analyze a dual winning convention, which we call {\sc sink subtraction}. Unlike the standard wall convention, where moves to negative positions are forbidden, the sink convention declares a player the winner upon moving to a non-positive position. We show that {\sc additive sink subtraction} admits a complete solution: the nim-sequence is purely periodic with an explicit linear or quadratic period formula, and we conjecture a duality between additive sink subtraction and classical wall subtraction. Keywords: Additive Subtraction Game, Nimber, Periodicity, Sink Convention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18715v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anjali Bhagat, Urban Larsson, Hikaru Manabe, Takahiro Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A two-player version of the assignment problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02628v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the competitive assignment problem, a two-player version of the well-known assignment problem. Given a set of tasks and a set of agents with different efficiencies for different tasks, Alice and Bob take turns picking agents one by one. Once all agents have been picked, Alice and Bob compute the optimal values $s_A$ and $s_B$ for the assignment problem on their respective sets of agents, i.e. they assign their own agents to tasks (with at most one agent per task and at most one task per agent) so as to maximize the sum of the efficiencies. The score of the game is then defined as $s_A-s_B$. Alice aims at maximizing the score, while Bob aims at minimizing it. This problem can model drafts in sports and card games, or more generally situations where two entities fight for the same resources and then use them to compete against each other. We show that the problem is PSPACE-complete, even restricted to agents that have at most two nonzero efficiencies. On the other hand, in the case of agents having at most one nonzero efficiency, the problem lies in XP parameterized by the number of tasks, and the optimal score can be computed in linear time when there are only two tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02628v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Galliot, Nacim Oijid, Jonas S\'enizergues</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quickly excluding an annotated planar graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06516v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide proofs certifying that the structure theorem for vertex sets of bounded bidimensionality holds with polynomial bounds. The bidimensionality of vertex sets is a common generalisation of both treewidth and the face-cover-number of vertex sets in planar graphs. As such, it plays a crucial role in extensions of Courcelle's Theorem to $H$-minor-free graphs. Recently, bidimensionality and similar parameters have emerged as key for extensions of known parameterized algorithms for problems defined on a terminal set $R$. A prominent example for such a problem is Steiner Tree, which admits efficient algorithms on planar graphs whenever $R$ can be covered with few faces.
  Key to the algorithmic applications of bidimensionality is a structure theorem that explains how a graph $G$ can be decomposed into pieces where the behaviour of $R$ is highly controlled. One may see this structure theorem as a rooted analogue of Robertson and Seymour's celebrated Grid Theorem. Combining recent advances in obtaining polynomial bounds in the Graph Minors framework with new techniques for handling annotated vertex sets, we show that all parameters in the structure theorem above admit polynomial bounds. As an application, we also provide a sketch showing how our techniques imply polynomial bounds for the structure theorem for graphs excluding an apex minor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06516v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Gorsky, Evangelos Protopapas, Sebastian Wiederrecht</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
