<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM</link>
    <description>cs.DM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Results on three problems on isolation of graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22856v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The graph isolation problem was introduced by Caro and Hansberg in 2015. It is a vast generalization of the classical graph domination problem and its study is expanding rapidly. In this paper, we address a number of questions that arise naturally. Let $F$ be a graph. We show that the $F$-isolating set problem is NP-complete if $F$ is connected. We investigate how the $F$-isolation number $\iota(G,F)$ of a graph $G$ is affected by the minimum degree $d$ of $G$, establishing a bounded range, in terms of $d$ and the orders of $F$ and $G$, for the largest possible value of $\iota(G,F)$ with $d$ sufficiently large. We also investigate how close $\iota(G,tF)$ is to $\iota(G,F)$, using domination and, in suitable cases, the Erdos-Posa property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22856v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Borg, Yair Caro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flip Distance of Triangulations of Convex Polygons / Rotation Distance of Binary Trees is NP-complete</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22874v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Flips in triangulations of convex polygons arise in many different settings. They are isomorphic to rotations in binary trees, define edges in the 1-skeleton of the Associahedron and cover relations in the Tamari Lattice.
  The complexity of determining the minimum number of flips that transform one triangulation of a convex point set into another remained a tantalizing open question for many decades. We settle this question by proving that computing shortest flip sequences between triangulations of convex polygons, and therefore also computing the rotation distance of binary trees, is NP-hard.
  For our proof we develop techniques for flip sequences of triangulations whose counterparts were introduced for the study of flip sequences of non-crossing spanning trees by Bjerkevik, Kleist, Ueckerdt, and Vogtenhuber~[SODA25] and Bjerkevik, Dorfer, Kleist, Ueckerdt, and Vogtenhuber~[SoCG26].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22874v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Dorfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isolation critical graphs under multiple edge subdivision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22980v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces the notion of $(\iota,q)$-critical graphs. The isolation number of a graph $G$, denoted by $\iota(G)$ and also known as the vertex-edge domination number, is the minimum number of vertices in a set $D$ such that the subgraph induced by the vertices not in the closed neighbourhood of $D$ has no edges.
  A graph $G$ is $(\iota,q)$-critical, $q \ge 1$, if the subdivision of any $q$ edges in $G$ gives a graph with isolation number greater than $\iota(G)$ and there exists a set of $q-1$ edges such that subdividing them gives a graph with isolation number equal to $\iota(G)$.
  We prove that for each integer $q \ge 1$ there exists a $(\iota,q)$-critical graph, while for a given graph $G$, the admissible values of $q$ satisfy $1 \le q \le |E(G)| - 1$. In addition, we provide a general characterisation of $(\iota,1)$-critical graphs as well as a constructive characterisation of $(\iota,1)$-critical trees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22980v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karl Bartolo, Peter Borg, Magda Dettlaff, Magdalena Lema\'nska, Pawe{\l} \.Zyli\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster algorithms for graph homomorphism via tractable constraint satisfaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.23000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.23000v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the existence of a homomorphism from an $n$-vertex graph $G$ to an $h$-vertex graph $H$ can be decided in time $2^{O(n)}h^{O(1)}$ and polynomial space if $H$ comes from a family of graphs that excludes a topological minor. The algorithm is based on a reduction to a single-exponential number of constraint satisfaction problems over tractable languages and can handle cost minimization. We also present an improved randomized algorithm for the special case where the graph $H$ is an odd cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.23000v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Carbonnel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repeated principal indefinite summation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.23025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.23025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Under suitable asymptotic and convexity conditions on a function $g\colon\mathbb{R}_+\to\mathbb{R}$, the solution to $\Delta f=g$, where $\Delta$ is the forward difference operator, is unique up to an additive constant and is called the principal indefinite sum of $g$, generalizing the additive form of Bohr-Mollerup's theorem. We consider the map $\Sigma$, which assigns to each admissible function $g$ its principal indefinite sum that vanishes at $1$, and we naturally explore its iterates, which produce repeated principal indefinite sums, in analogy with the concept of repeated indefinite integrals. Explicit formulas and convergence results are established, highlighting connections with classical combinatorial and special functions, including the multiple gamma functions, for which we also provide integral representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.23025v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Lamby, Jean-Luc Marichal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous separation in bounded degree trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.23096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.23096v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It follows from a classical result of Jordan that every tree with maximum degree at most $r$ containing a vertex set labeled by $[n]$, has a single-edge cut which separates two subsets $A,B \subset [n]$ for which $\min\{|A|,|B|\} \ge (n-1)/r$. Motivated by the tree dissimilarity problem in phylogenetics, we consider the case of separating vertex sets of {\em several} trees: Given $k$ trees with maximum degree at most $r$, containing a common vertex set labeled by $[n]$, we ask for a single-edge cut in each tree which maximizes $min\{|A|,|B|\}$ where $A,B \subset [n]$ are separated by the corresponding cut at each tree. Denoting this maximum by $f(r,k,n)$ and considering the limit $f(r,k) = \lim_{n \rightarrow \infty} f(r,k,n)/n$ (which is shown to always exist) we determine that $f(r,2)=\frac{1}{2r}$ and determine that $f(3,3)=\frac{2}{27}$, which is already quite intricate. The case $r=3$ is especially interesting in phylogenetics and our result implies that any two (three) binary phylogenetic trees over $n$ taxa have a split at each tree which separates two taxa sets of order at least $n/6$ (resp. $2n/27$), and these bounds are asymptotically tight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.23096v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sagi Snir, Raphael Yuster</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coalgebraic analysis of social systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.23211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.23211v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The algebraic analysis of social systems, or algebraic social network analysis, refers to a collection of methods designed to extract information about the structure of a social system represented as a directed graph. Central among these are methods to determine the roles that exist within a given system, and the positions. The analysis of roles and positions is highly developed for social systems that involve only pairwise interactions among actors - however, in contemporary social network analysis it is increasingly common to use models that can take into account higher-order interactions as well. In this paper we take a category-theoretic approach to the question of how to lift role and positional analysis from graphs to hypergraphs, which can accommodate higher-order interactions. We use the framework of universal coalgebra - a 'theory of systems' with origins in computer science and logic - to formalize the main concepts of role and positional analysis and extend them to a large class of structures that includes both graphs and hypergraphs. As evidence for the validity of our definitions, we prove a very general functoriality theorem that specializes, in the case of graphs, to a folkloric observation about the compatibility of positional and role analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.23211v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nima Motamed, Nina Otter, Emily Roff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A polynomial bound on the pathwidth of graphs edge-coverable by $k$ shortest paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02901v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dumas, Foucaud, Perez and Todinca (2024) recently proved that every graph whose edges can be covered by $k$ shortest paths has pathwidth at most $O(3^k)$. In this paper, we improve this upper bound on the pathwidth to a polynomial one; namely, we show that every graph whose edge set can be covered by $k$ shortest paths has pathwidth $O(k^4)$, answering a question from the same paper. Moreover, we prove that when $k\leq 3$, every such graph has pathwidth at most $k$ (and this bound is tight). Finally, we show that even though there exist graphs with arbitrarily large treewidth whose vertex set can be covered by $2$ isometric trees, every graph whose set of edges can be covered by $2$ isometric trees has treewidth at most $2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02901v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Baste, Lucas De Meyer, Ugo Giocanti, Etienne Objois, Timoth\'e Picavet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DRESS and the WL Hierarchy: Climbing One Deletion at a Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21557v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Cai--F\"urer--Immerman (CFI) construction provides the canonical family of hard instances for the Weisfeiler--Leman (WL) hierarchy: distinguishing the two non-isomorphic CFI graphs over a base graph $G$ requires $k$-WL where $k$ meets or exceeds the treewidth of $G$. In this paper, we introduce $\Delta^\ell$-DRESS, which applies $\ell$ levels of iterated node deletion to the DRESS continuous structural refinement framework. $\Delta^\ell$-DRESS runs Original-DRESS on all $\binom{n}{\ell}$ subgraphs obtained by removing $\ell$ nodes, and compares the resulting histograms. We show empirically on the canonical CFI benchmark family that Original-DRESS ($\Delta^0$) already distinguishes $\text{CFI}(K_3)$ (requiring 2-WL), and that each additional deletion level extends the range by one WL level: $\Delta^1$ reaches 3-WL, $\Delta^2$ reaches 4-WL, and $\Delta^3$ reaches 5-WL, distinguishing CFI pairs over $K_n$ for $n = 3, \ldots, 6$. Crucially, $\Delta^3$ fails on $\text{CFI}(K_7)$ (requiring 6-WL), confirming a sharp boundary at $(\ell+2)$-WL. The computational cost is $\mathcal{O}\bigl(\binom{n}{\ell} \cdot I \cdot m \cdot d_{\max}\bigr)$ -- polynomial in $n$ for fixed $\ell$. These results establish $\Delta^\ell$-DRESS as a practical framework for systematically climbing the WL hierarchy on the canonical CFI benchmark family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21557v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduar Castrillo Velilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
