<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.app-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph</link>
    <description>physics.app-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 02:08:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Super-Bandgap Electroluminescence from Cesium Lead Bromide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09702v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Halide perovskites is a new class of semiconductors with exceptional optoelectronic properties. Among many advantages offered by halide perovskites, the bandgap energy can be tuned in a much broader range than what was possible in conventional semiconductors. This was commonly achieved in previous research by mixing different species of halides into solid solutions. The tuned bandgap using this method, however, often underwent an energy shift under optical or electrical stimuli due to halide segregation. In this work, we discovered an alternative approach to achieve super-bandgap electroluminescence from CsPbBr3. The peak energy of the light emission can be 0.7 eV higher than the reported bandgap energy. Evidence pointed to the radiative recombination at the perovskite-PEDOT:PSS interface being responsible for the unexpected blueshift of electroluminescence. We speculated that perovskite nanocrystals were formed therein and produced higher-energy photons due to quantum confinement. The results suggested an alternative strategy to manipulate and stabilize the color of electroluminescence and achieve particularly blue emission in perovskite-based LEDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09702v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin Sculley, Jeremy Kowkabany, Diana K. LaFollette, Carlo Perini, Yan Xin, Juan-Pablo Correa-Baena, Hanwei Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity adjustable in-line high-temperature sensor based on metal microwire optical Fabry-Perot interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09895v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The optical fiber Fabry-Perot interferometer (FPI) has been widely investigated as a potential temperature sensor. To function as a temperature sensor, the cavity of the FPI is typically constructed from either silica fibers or polymers. The silica cavity FPIs can function at temperatures exceeding 1000{\deg}C. However, its temperature sensitivity is constrained by its relatively low thermal optical coefficient and thermal expansion of silica materials. Although the polymer cavity FPI exhibits a high temperature sensitivity, its cavity is susceptible to deterioration in high-temperature environments. Here, to overcome this challenge and achieve high-sensitivity temperature sensing in a high-temperature environment, we propose a new type of temperature FPI sensor by inserting and sealing a section of Cr20Ni80 metal microwire inside a section of silica hollow core fiber (HCF) spliced to standard single-mode fiber (SMF). The FPIs exhibit a high degree of temperature sensitivity due to the high thermal expansion of the Cr20Ni80 metal microwire. Since the Cr20Ni80 metal has a high melting temperature of 1400{\deg}C, such FPIs can function in high-temperature environments. Moreover, the temperature sensitivity of this FPI can be modified without affecting its reflection spectrum by changing the length of the metallic microwire situated within the hollow core fiber. The experimental results indicate that the proposed FPIs exhibit a temperature sensitivity of greater than -0.35nm/{\deg}C within the temperature range of 50{\deg}C to 440{\deg}C. Our proposed metal microwire-based FPIs are economical, robust, simple to fabricate, and capable of functioning in high-temperature environments, rendering them appealing options for practical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09895v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dewen Duan, Zihao Zhao, Yi-Yuan Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new approach for the inversion of residual stress based on acoustoelasticity theory and full waveform inversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10067v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Acoustoelasticity theory has been widely used to evaluate the residual stress (or prestress), almost all the available ultrasonic stress detection methods are based on the relationship between the magnitude of stress and wave speed, but these measurement methods make the assumption that the stress is uniform, only one point or average stress in the direction of ultrasound propagation can be obtained. However, the real stress distribution is usually nonuniform. In order to obtain the stress distribution in the direction of ultrasound propagation, in this paper, we propose a new approach: the inversion of residual stress. In the theory part, the inversion of residual stress is transformed into an optimization problem. The objective function is established, and the gradient of the objective function to the stress is derived using the adjoint method, which has been maturely applied in full waveform inversion. In the numerical simulation part, the welding process is simulated using the finite element method to obtain a database of the residual stress field. Then the residual stress is evaluated by inversion approach and the influence of the number of sources and receivers and the frequency of the excitation wave on the inversion effect is discussed. The results show that the inversion of residual stress is still challenging with a small amount of data, but a more accurate inversion can be obtained by appropriately increasing the number of sources and receivers. This study provides an appropriate method for the evaluation of residual stress distribution and lays the theoretical and simulation foundation for the application of ultrasonic stress testing in it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10067v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Maoyu, Hongjian Zhao, Changsheng Liu, Yu Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The weak form method for acoustoelastic simulation with arbitrary prestress</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Acoustoelastic theory has been widely used to evaluate the residual stress (or prestress). However, most of the research remains focused on plate under simple tensile stress condition. In this paper, we propose a new approach: using weak form PDE modeling for acoustoelastic simulation. In the theory part, the weak form of acoustoelastic theory and semi-analytical finite element (SAFE) method is derived. In the numerical simulation part, two cases: the propagation direction is perpendicular to the prestress and parallel to the prestress are presented. The results are compared with the superposition of partial bulk wave (SPBW) method and the previously commonly used Effective Elastic Constants (EEC) method. The results show that the method proposed in this paper is highly accurate. Compared to the EEC method, this approach has no theoretical flaws and aligns more closely with the theoretical solution, especially in the low frequency range where the EEC method's results are almost incorrect. This study provides an accurate method for the simulation of acoustoelasticity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10099v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Maoyu, Changsheng Liu, Yu Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaseous Scissor-mediated Electrochemical Exfoliation of Halogenated MXenes and its Boosting in Wear-Resisting Tribovoltaic Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional transition metal carbides (MXenes), especially their few-layered nanosheets, have triggered burgeoning research attentions owing to their superiorities including extraordinary conductivity, accessible active surface, and adjustable processability. Molten salts etching route further achieves their controllable surface chemistry. However, the method encounters challenges in achieving few-layer structures due to more complex delamination behaviors. Herein, we present an efficient strategy to fabricate Cl- or Br-terminated MXene nanoflakes with few-layers, achieved by electrochemical intercalation of Li ions and concomitant solvent molecules in the electrolyte solution, with gaseous scissors (propylene molecules) to break up interlayer forces. By controlling cut-off voltages, the optimal protocol results in nanosheets with an ultrahigh yield (~93%) and preserved surface chemistry. The resultant MXenes dispersions were employed as lubricants to enhance tribovoltaic nanogenerators, where Ti3C2Br2 displayed superior electrical output. These findings facilitate the understanding of MXenes' intrinsic physical properties and enable the nanoengineering of advanced electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10214v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Fan, Minghua Chen, Longyi Li, Minghui Li, Chuanxiao Xiao, Tianci Zhao, Long Pan, Ningning Liang, Qing Huang, Laipan Zhu, Michael Naguib, Kun Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intercalation of Functional Materials with Phase Transitions for Neuromorphic Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Introducing foreign ions, atoms, or molecules into emerging functional materials is crucial for manipulating material physical properties and innovating device applications. The intercalation of emerging new materials can induce multiple intrinsic changes, such as charge doping, chemical bonding, and lattice expansion, which facilitates the exploration of structural phase transformations, the tuning of symmetry-breaking-related physics, and the creation of brain-inspired advanced devices. Moreover, incorporating various hosts and intercalants enables a series of crystal structures with a rich spectrum of characteristics, greatly expanding the scope and fundamental understanding of existing materials. Herein, we summarize the methods typically used for the intercalation of functional materials. We highlight recent progress in intercalation-based phase transitions and their emerging physics, i.e., ferroelectric, magnetic, insulator-metal, superconducting, and charge-density-wave phase transitions. We discuss prospective device applications for intercalation-based phase transitions, i.e., neuromorphic devices. Finally, we provide potential future research lines for promoting its further development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10301v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin He, Hua Wang, Jian Sun, Xixiang Zhang, Kai Chang, Fei Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Evaluation and Optimization of Air-to-Air Thermoelectric Heat Pump System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thermoelectric (TE) heat pumps are a promising solid-state technology for space cooling and heating owing to their unique advantages such as environmental friendliness with no harmful refrigerants, small form factors, low noise, robustness with no moving parts, and demand-flexible operation. However, their low coefficient of performance (COP) presents a challenge towards broader adaptation of the technology at the market level. Built on our previous theoretical framework for a modular system design aimed at improving both COP and cooling capacity, this study focuses on experimental characterization and optimization of a unit air-to-air TE heat pump system. We employ double-sided heating/cooling and counterflow configuration for uniform heat transfer with TE modules and heat exchangers. System-level evaluations validate the theoretical model and show the variation of air temperature change and system COP with different electric current inputs and air flowrates. A maximum cooling COP of 4.4 and a maximum heating COP of 6.0 were obtained at optimized current levels. Further analysis shows that parasitic thermal resistances in the system significantly reduced both COP and air temperature change by over 50%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10600v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Je-Hyeong Bahk, Thiraj D. Mohankumar, Abhishek Saini, Sarah J. Watzman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic coil optimization for reduced Lorentz forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09337v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The reduction of magnetic forces on electromagnetic coils is an important consideration in the design of high-field devices such as the stellarator or tokamak. Unfortunately, these forces may be too time-consuming to evaluate by conventional finite element modeling within an optimization loop. Although mutual forces can be computed rapidly by approximating large-bore coils as infinitely thin, this approximation does not hold for self-forces as it leads to an unphysical divergence. Recently, a novel reduced model for the self-field, self-force, and self-inductance of electromagnetic coils based on filamentary models was rigorously derived and demonstrated to be highly accurate and numerically efficient to evaluate. In this paper, we present an implementation of the reduced self-force model employing automatic differentiation within the SIMSOPT stellarator design software and use it in derivative-based coil optimization for a quasi-axisymmetric stellarator. We show that it is possible to significantly reduce point-wise forces throughout the coils, though this comes with trade-offs to fast particle losses and the minimum distance between coils and the plasma surface. The trade-off between magnetic forces and coil-surface distance is mediated by the minimum coil-coil distance for coils near the inboard side of the "bean" cross-section of the plasma. The relationship between forces and fast particle losses is mediated by the normal field error. Coil forces can be lowered to a threshold with minimal deterioration to losses. Importantly, the magnet optimization approach here can be used also for tokamaks, other fusion concepts, and applications outside of fusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09337v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siena Hurwitz, Matt Landreman, Alan Kaptanoglu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Optical Method for Evaluating the Mechanical Properties of Wires Under Impact Tensile Load</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09618v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dynamic properties of materials utilized in architecture or engineering applications can significantly affect their performance under dynamic or impact loading conditions. To evaluate such behavior, force transducers are commonly employed in testing. However, the calibration of force transducers is typically limited to static conditions and relies solely on gravitational forces exerted on standard masses. Thus, assessing the uncertainty in force measurements using force transducers during dynamic loading conditions remains a challenging task, presenting a significant obstacle in accurately characterizing the dynamic behavior of materials. In this work, an optical technique to evaluate the mechanical properties of wires subjected to impact tensile loads is presented. The wire under test is subjected to an impact tensile load by applying the inertial force of a rigid mass, which is supported by utilizing an aerostatic linear bearing with sufficiently small friction. The inertial force applied to the wire can be determined by multiplying the mass of the rigid mass by its acceleration, where the acceleration can be measured employing a Michelson type optical interferometer. The performance of the proposed method is demonstrated through experiments and analysis of the dynamic characteristics of a tungsten wire under impact tensile loading conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09618v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIM.2023.3332347</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Trans. Instrum. Meas. 73 (2024) 1001111</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Phichai Youplao, Hadi Nasbey, Akihiro Takita, Prin Nachaisit, Yusaku Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetically Trapped Nanocrystals with Symmetry-Preserving Shapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09787v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The shape of nanocrystals is crucial in determining their surface area, reactivity, optical properties, mechanical strength, and self-assembly behavior. Traditionally, shape control has been achieved through empirical methods, highlighting the need for a more refined theoretical framework. A comprehensive model should account for the kinetic factors at distinct stages of the shape-formation process to identify the key determinants of nanocrystal morphology. By modulating kinetics at terraces, ledges, and kinks, we reveal that the primary factors are the adatom nucleation energies and the geometry of growth islands. Transient sites dominate the growth process, leading to kinetically trapped, metastable shapes. We illustrate these concepts with face-centered cubic nanocrystals, demonstrating diverse shape evolutions, including surface roughening and the preservation of crystal symmetry in cubes, octahedra, rhombic dodecahedra, and their truncated variants. This study reveals the mechanisms driving the formation of cubic nanocrystal shapes and offers guidance for their precise synthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09787v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos L. Bassani, Michael Engel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Silicon modulator exceeding 110 GHz using tunable time-frequency equalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09816v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Silicon modulators have garnered considerable attention owing to their potential applications in high-density integration and high-speed modulation. However, they are increasingly challenged by the limited 3 dB bandwidth as the demand for modulation speed in optical communications continues to rise, impeding their ability to compete with modulators made of thin-film lithium niobate. This bandwidth limitation arises because of the parasitic resistance and capacitance in the PN junction of the silicon modulators. This study demonstrates the first silicon modulator exceeding 110 GHz without any resonant structure using a tunable time-frequency equalization technique. This substantial breakthrough enables on-off keying modulation at a rate of 140 Gbaud without digital signal processing. These accomplishments represent the highest bandwidth and maximum baud rate achieved without digital signal processing in an all-silicon modulator, reaching the testing limitations of the experimental system. This opens the possibility of attaining modulation rates of up to 200 or even 300 Gbaud by adopting design strategies such as slow light and technologies such as digital signal processing. This advancement extends the speed capabilities of silicon modulators to the level of thin-film lithium niobate modulators, thereby promoting their application in the broader array of fields, such as linear-drive pluggable transceivers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09816v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengsong Yue, Jianbin Fu, Hengwei Zhang, Bo Xiong, Shilong Pan, Tao Chu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Skyrmion-Antiskyrmion Dynamics in Co/Pt Nanocontacts for Spintronic Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmions are topologically protected quasiparticles and have drawn much attention because of their potential applications in next-generation spintronics devices. Their inherent topological stability, nanoscale size, and efficient manipulation via spin currents make them promising candidates for high-density data storage and novel computing paradigms. We micromagnetically investigate the nucleation dynamics of magnetic skyrmion pairs excited underneath two 30 nm nanocontacts with varying separations on top of an extended Co/Pt bilayer thin film. At close separation of 100 nm, the magnetization configurations strongly interact, giving rise to the formation of stable merged skyrmion states. As the separation increases beyond 200 nm, topologically distinct metastable configurations emerge, including the coexistence of tunable skyrmion-antiskyrmion pairs through Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction (DMI) strengths and current pulse amplitudes. These metastable states eventually relax into two stable skyrmions that can be independently toggled ON and OFF using a weak in-plane magnetic field, enabling complex logic operations and more flexible circuit designs. Beyond the fundamental interest in skyrmion interaction dynamics, the independent control of skyrmion-antiskyrmion states holds promise for next-generation spintronic devices, with potential applications in memory, logic, and computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09851v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hind Prakash, Himanshu Fulara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling single-molecules to DNA-based optical antennas with position and orientation control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10400v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optical antennas have been extensively employed to manipulate the photophysical properties of single photon emitters. Coupling between an emitter and a given resonant mode of an optical antenna depends mainly on three parameters: spectral overlap, relative distance, and relative orientation between the emitter's transition dipole moment and the antenna. While the first two have been already extensively demonstrated, achieving full coupling control remains unexplored due to the challenges in manipulating at the same time both the position and orientation of single molecules. Here, we use the DNA origami technique to assemble a dimer optical antenna and position a single fluorescent molecule at the antenna gap with controlled orientation, predominately parallel or perpendicular to the antenna's main axis. We study the coupling for both conditions through fluorescence measurements correlated with scanning electron microscopy images, revealing a 5-fold higher average fluorescence intensity when the emitter is aligned with the antenna's main axis and a maximum fluorescence enhancement of ~ 1400-fold. A comparison to realistic numerical simulations suggests that the observed distribution of fluorescence enhancement arises from small variations in emitter orientation and gap size. This work establishes DNA origami as a versatile platform to fully control the coupling between emitters and optical antennas, trailblazing the way for self-assembled nanophotonic devices with optimized and more homogenous performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10400v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandra K. Adamczyk, Fangjia Zhu, Daniel Schaeafer, Yuya Kanehira, Sergio Kogikoski Jr, Ilko Bald, Sebastian Schluecker, Karol Kolataj, Fernando D. Stefani, Guillermo P. Acuna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative Framework for Engineering Arbitrary Floquet Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10467v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a systematic perturbative framework to engineer an arbitrary target Hamiltonian in the Floquet phase space of a periodically driven oscillator based on Floquet-Magnus expansion. The high-order errors in the engineered Floquet Hamiltonian are mitigated by adding high-order driving potentials perturbatively. Especially, we introduce a bracket transformation that makes the calculation of high-order correction drives feasible. We apply our method to engineering a target Hamiltonian with discrete rotational and chiral symmetries in phase space that are important for fault-tolerant hardware-efficiency bosonic quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10467v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingdan Xu, Lingzhen Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortex Modes in Acoustofluidic Cylindrical Resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10531v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a theoretical investigation of vortex modes in acoustofluidic cylindrical resonators with rigid boundaries and viscous fluids. By solving the Helmholtz equation for linear pressure, incorporating boundary conditions that account for no-slip surfaces and vortex and nonvortex excitation at the base, we analyze both single- and dual-eigenfunction modes near system resonance. The results demonstrate that single vortex modes generate spin angular momentum exclusively along the axial direction, while dual modes introduce a transverse spin component due to the nonlinear interaction between axial and transverse ultrasonic waves, even in the absence of vortex excitation. We find that nonlinear acoustic fields, including energy density, radiation force potential, and spin, scale with the square of the shear wave number, defined as the ratio of the cavity radius to the boundary layer depth. Theoretical predictions align closely with finite element simulations based on a thermoviscous model for an acoustofluidic cavity with adiabatic and rigid walls. These findings hold particular significance for acoustofluidic systems, offering potential applications in the precise control of cells and microparticles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10531v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alisson S. Marques, Glauber T. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersion effects in thermal emission from temporal metamaterials: High-frequency cut-offs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10558v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The latest breakthroughs in time-varying photonics are fueling novel thermal emission phenomena, for example, showing that the dynamic amplification of quantum vacuum fluctuations, induced by the time-modulation of material properties, enables a mechanism to surpass the black-body spectrum. So far, this issue has only been investigated under the assumption of non-dispersive time-modulations. In this work, we identify the existence of a non-physical diverging behavior in the time-modulated emission spectra at high frequencies, and prove that it is actually attributed to the simplistic assumption of a non-dispersive (temporally local) response of the time-modulation associated with memory-less systems. Accordingly, we upgrade the theoretical formalism by introducing a dispersive response function, showing that it leads to a high-frequency cut-off, thereby eliminating the divergence and hence allowing for the proper computation of the emission spectra of time-modulated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10558v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amaia Vertiz-Conde, I\~nigo Liberal, J. Enrique V\'azquez-Lozano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking solid oxide cell electrode microstructural evolution during annealing by scanning 3D X-ray diffraction microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10671v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ni particle coarsening is a primary degradation mechanism in Ni/YSZ solid oxide cells, limiting the lifespan of these devices. In this study, we demonstrate the use of Scanning 3D X-ray diffraction (S3DXRD) with an unprecedented spatial resolution of 100 nm, to monitor the microstructural evolution within the 3D volume of a solid oxide cell subjected to ex situ heat treatment. Unlike conventional tomography, S3DXRD combines crystallographic information with spatial maps, enabling precise identification of grain boundaries and the determination of local curvature changes in the Ni microstructure. Our study reveals that the Ni phase undergoes significant structural changes during annealing, driven by grain growth. This transformation is characterized by a reduction in local curvature, particularly in regions where grains disappear. We observe that the disappearing grains are the smallest grains in the size distribution and are often located near pores. As a result, the most notable reduction in local curvature occurs at the Ni-pore interface. The quantitative characterization of polycrystalline microstructural evolution in Ni/YSZ system provides new insights into the mechanisms of Ni particle coarsening in SOC devices, potentially guiding strategies to enhance the long-term stability of SOC devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10671v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Shukla, S. De Angelis, J. Wright, Y. Zhang, J. Oddershede, H. F. Poulsen, J. W. Andreasen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully Programmable Spatial Photonic Ising Machine by Focal Plane Division</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10689v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ising machines are an emerging class of hardware that promises ultrafast and energy-efficient solutions to NP-hard combinatorial optimization problems. Spatial photonic Ising machines (SPIMs) exploit optical computing in free space to accelerate the computation, showcasing parallelism, scalability, and low power consumption. However, current SPIMs can implement only a restricted class of problems. This partial programmability is a critical limitation that hampers their benchmark. Achieving full programmability of the device while preserving its scalability is an open challenge. Here, we report a fully programmable SPIM achieved through a novel operation method based on the division of the focal plane. In our scheme, a general Ising problem is decomposed into a set of Mattis Hamiltonians, whose energies are simultaneously computed optically by measuring the intensity on different regions of the camera sensor. Exploiting this concept, we experimentally demonstrate the computation with high success probability of ground-state solutions of up to 32-spin Ising models on unweighted maximum cut graphs with and without ferromagnetic bias. Simulations of the hardware prove a favorable scaling of the accuracy with the number of spins. Our fully programmable SPIM enables the implementation of many quadratic unconstrained binary optimization problems, further establishing SPIMs as a leading paradigm in non von Neumann hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10689v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Veraldi, Davide Pierangeli, Silvia Gentilini, Marcello Calvanese Strinati, Jason Sakellariou, James S. Cummins, Airat Kamaletdinov, Marvin Syed, Richard Zhipeng Wang, Natalia G. Berloff, Dimitrios Karanikolopoulos, Pavlos G. Savvidis, Claudio Conti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of BaTiO$_3$-NiO composite as compact Dielectric Resonator Antenna</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08910v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A compact dielectric resonator antenna has been fabricated on a microstrip transmission line for the purpose of C-band wireless communication using a ceramic material made out of a sintered mixture of BTO and NiO. The antenna parameters are optimized using Ansys HFSS software and verified experimentally. Ni replaces both Ba at A site and Ti at B site. Such a solid solution has a limit depending on the amount of NiO provided during sintering. A complete study of the structural changes and the dielectric constant enables the correlation with the resonating property. All the samples retain the ferroelectric tetragonal P4mm phase with a nominal decrease in the c/a ratio. NiO incorporation in BTO decreases the sintering temperature and shows two types of morphology associated with BTO-like and NiO-like phases. It induces prominent reduction in the permittivity and loss tangent (&lt;0.01) in the range 100Hz to 1MHz. These properties make these samples suitable for DRA application in the C-Band range [4-8 GHz]. Experimental and theoretical assessment using HFSS software yields a C-band signal at ~7.27 GHz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08910v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prithwiraj Ganguly, Vince Kumar, P. Maneesha, Saptarshi Ghosh, Somaditya Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of tension-compression asymmetry from a complete phase-field approach to brittle fracture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00368v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The classical variational approach to brittle fracture propagation does not distinguish between strain energy accumulation in tension versus compression and consequently results in physically unrealistic cracking under compression. A variety of energy splits have been proposed as a possible remedy. However, a unique energy split that can describe this asymmetry for general loading conditions has not been found. The main objective of this paper is to show that a complete phase-field theory of brittle fracture nucleation and propagation, one that accounts for the material strength at large, can naturally capture the tension-compression asymmetry without an energy split. One such theory has been recently proposed by Kumar et al. (2018). Over the past few years, several studies have shown that this theory is capable of accurately describing fracture nucleation and propagation for materials soft and hard under arbitrary monotonic loading conditions. However, a systematic study of the tension-compression asymmetry that emerges from this theory has not yet been reported. This paper does precisely that. In particular, this paper reports a comprehensive study of crack propagation in two problems, one involving a symmetric tension-compression state and the other involving larger compressive stresses at the crack tip. The results are compared with popular energy splits used in literature. The results show that, remarkably, for the second problem, only the complete theory is able to produce experimentally consistent results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00368v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Liu, Aditya Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated magneto-photonic non-volatile multi-bit memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02485v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an integrated magneto-photonic device for all-optical switching of non-volatile multi-bit spintronic memory. The bits are based on stand-alone magneto-tunnel junctions which are perpendicularly magnetized with all-optically switchable free layers, coupled onto photonic crystal nanobeam cavities on an indium phosphide based platform. This device enables switching of the magnetization state of the bits by locally increasing the power absorption of light at resonance with the cavity. We design an add/drop network of cavities to grant random access to multiple bits via a wavelength-division multiplexing scheme. Based on a three-dimensional finite-difference time-domain method, we numerically illustrate a compact device capable of switching and accessing 8 bits in different cavities with a 5 nm wavelength spacing in the conventional (C) telecommunication band. Our multi-bit device holds promise as a new paradigm for developing an ultrafast photonically-addressable spintronic memory and may also empower novel opportunities for photonically-driven spintronic-based neuromorphic computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02485v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0221825</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Appl. Phys. 136, 083908 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hamed Pezeshki, Pingzhi Li, Reinoud Lavrijsen, Martijn Heck, Bert Koopmans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global calibration of large-scale photonic integrated circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02207v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The advancing maturity of photonic integrated circuit (PIC) fabrication technology enables the high integration of an increasing number of optical components onto a single chip. With the incremental circuit complexity, the calibration of active phase shifters in a large-scale PIC becomes a crucially important issue. The traditional one-by-one calibration techniques encounter significant hurdles with the propagation of calibration errors, and achieving the decoupling of all phase shifters for independent calibration is not straightforward. To address this issue, we propose a global calibration approach for large-scale PIC. Our method utilizes a custom network to simultaneously learn the nonlinear phase-current relations for all thermo-optic phase shifters on the PIC by minimizing the negative likelihood of the measurement datasets. Moreover, the reflectivities of all static beamsplitter components can also be synchronizedly extracted using this calibration method. As an example, a quantum walk PIC with a circuit depth of 12 is calibrated, and a programmable discrete-time quantum walk is experimentally demonstrated. These results will greatly benefit the applications of large-scale PICs in photonic quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02207v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Hao Zheng, Qin-Qin Wang, Lan-Tian Feng, Yu-Yang Ding, Xiao-Ye Xu, Xi-Feng Ren, Chuan-Feng Li, Guang-Can Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A strategy for fabricating micro-scale freestanding single-crystalline complex oxide device arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10071v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a general fabrication strategy for freestanding single-crystalline complex oxide device arrays via wet chemical etching-based microfabrication processes and epitaxial lift-off. Here, we used 0.5Ba(Zr$_{0.2}$Ti$_{0.8}$)O$_3$-0.5Ba(Zr$_{0.7}$Ti$_{0.3}$)O$_3$ (BCZT) as a model relaxor ferroelectric oxide system and La$_{0.7}$Sr$_{0.3}$MnO$_3$ as the sacrificial layer for demonstration. Arrays of SrRuO$_3$ (SRO) / BCZT / SRO ferroelectric capacitor mesas were first defined and isolated on the growth wafer, and then they were released using epitaxial lift-off with lithography-defined surrounding etching holes, after which the freestanding device arrays were integrated onto a glass substrate. Our proposed strategy sheds light on preparing various freestanding single-crystalline oxide devices and paves the way for their heterogeneous integration onto arbitrary substates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10071v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huandong Chen, Yang Liu, Harish Kumarasubramanian, Mythili Surendran, Jayakanth Ravichandran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review: Quantum Metrology and Sensing with Many-Body Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15323v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The main power of quantum sensors is achieved when the probe is composed of several particles. In this situation, quantum features such as entanglement contribute in enhancing the precision of quantum sensors beyond the capacity of classical sensors. Originally, quantum sensing was formulated for non-interacting particles which are prepared in a special form of maximally entangled states. These probes are extremely sensitive to decoherence and any interaction between particles is detrimental to their performance. An alternative framework for quantum sensing has been developed exploiting quantum many-body systems, where the interaction between particles plays a crucial role. In this review, we investigate different aspects of the latter approach for quantum metrology and sensing. Many-body probes have been used in both equilibrium and non-equilibrium scenarios. Quantum criticality has been identified as a resource for achieving quantum enhanced sensitivity in both scenarios. In equilibrium, various types of criticalities, such as first order, second order, topological, and localization phase transitions have been exploited for sensing purposes. In non-equilibrium scenarios, quantum enhanced sensitivity has been discovered for Floquet, dissipative, and time crystal phase transitions. While each type of these criticalities has its own characteristics, the presence of one feature is crucial for achieving quantum enhanced sensitivity: the energy/quasi-energy gap closing. In non-equilibrium quantum sensing, time is another parameter which can affect the sensitivity of the probe. Typically, the sensitivity enhances as the probe evolves in time. In general, a more complete understanding of resources for non-equilibrium quantum sensors is now rapidly evolving. In this review, we provide an overview of recent progress in quantum metrology and sensing using many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15323v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Montenegro, Chiranjib Mukhopadhyay, Rozhin Yousefjani, Saubhik Sarkar, Utkarsh Mishra, Matteo G. A. Paris, Abolfazl Bayat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser-FLASH: radiobiology at high dose, ultra-high dose-rate, single pulse laser-driven proton source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05086v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Laser-driven proton sources have long been developed with an eye on their potential for medical application to radiation therapy. These sources are compact, versatile, and show peculiar characteristics such as extreme instantaneous dose rates, short duration and broad energy spectrum. Typical temporal modality of laser-driven irradiation, the so-called fast-fractionation, results from the composition of multiple, temporally separated, ultra-short dose fractions. In this paper we present the use of a high-energy laser system for delivering the target dose in a single nanosecond pulse, for ultra-fast irradiation of biological samples. A transport line composed by two permanent magnet quadrupoles and a scattering system is used to improve the dose profile and to control the delivered dose-per-pulse. A single-shot dosimetry protocol for the broad-spectrum proton source using Monte Carlo simulations was developed. Doses as high as 20Gy could be delivered in a single shot, lasting less than 10ns over a 1.0cm diameter sample holder, at a dose-rate exceeding 10^9 Gy/s. Exploratory application of extreme laser-driven irradiation conditions, falling within the FLASH irradiation protocol, are presented for in vitro and in vivo irradiation. A reduction of radiation-induced oxidative stress in-vitro and radiation-induced developmental damage in vivo were observed, whereas anti-tumoral efficacy was confirmed by cell survival assay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05086v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Flacco (Laboratoire d'Optique Appliqu\'ee, ENSTA Paris, CNRS, Ecole Polytechnique, Institut Polytechnique de Paris, Palaiseau, France), E. Bayart (Laboratoire d'Optique Appliqu\'ee, ENSTA Paris, CNRS, Ecole Polytechnique, Institut Polytechnique de Paris, Palaiseau, France), C. Giaccaglia (Laboratoire d'Optique Appliqu\'ee, ENSTA Paris, CNRS, Ecole Polytechnique, Institut Polytechnique de Paris, Palaiseau, France), J. Monzac (Laboratoire d'Optique Appliqu\'ee, ENSTA Paris, CNRS, Ecole Polytechnique, Institut Polytechnique de Paris, Palaiseau, France), L. Romagnani (LULI, CNRS, \'Ecole Polytechnique, Institut Polytechnique de Paris, Palaiseau, France), M. Cavallone (Centre de Protonth\'erapie d'Orsay, Department of Radiation Oncology, Campus Universitaire, Institut Curie, PSL Research University, Orsay, France), A. Patriarca (Centre de Protonth\'erapie d'Orsay, Department of Radiation Oncology, Campus Universitaire, Institut Curie, PSL Research University, Orsay, France), L. DeMarzi (Centre de Protonth\'erapie d'Orsay, Department of Radiation Oncology, Campus Universitaire, Institut Curie, PSL Research University, Orsay, France, INSERM LITO 1288, Campus Universitaire, Institut Curie, PSL Research University, University Paris-Saclay, Orsay, France), C. Fouillade (Institut Curie, INSERM U1021-CNRS UMR 3347, University Paris-Saclay, PSL Research University, Centre Universitaire, Orsay Cedex, France), S. Heinrich (Institut Curie, INSERM U1021-CNRS UMR 3347, University Paris-Saclay, PSL Research University, Centre Universitaire, Orsay Cedex, France), I. Lamarre-Jouenne (Laboratoire d'Optique et Biosciences, Ecole Polytechnique, CNRS, Inserm, Institut Polytechnique de Paris, Palaiseau, France), K. Parodi (Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Faculty of Physics, Department of Medical Physics, Garching b. M\"unchen, Germany), T. R\"osch (Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Faculty of Physics, Department of Medical Physics, Garching b. M\"unchen, Germany), J. Schreiber (Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Faculty of Physics, Department of Medical Physics, Garching b. M\"unchen, Germany), L. Tischendorf (Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Faculty of Physics, Department of Medical Physics, Garching b. M\"unchen, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
