<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.app-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph</link>
    <description>physics.app-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 05:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis and Stability Kinetics of Nanoporous TaC Derived from Ta Precursors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18657v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultra-high temperature ceramics (UHTCs) are promising materials for use in next-generation aerospace structures but have primarily been used as monolithic materials or coatings due to processing limitations. Here, new functionality (e.g., ablation resistance) is introduced to these materials by developing a porous form factor that can be later infiltrated with a secondary phase. This UHTC scaffold is synthesized via gas-phase carburization of nanoporous tantalum to the ultra-high-temperature ceramic, TaC. The kinetics of Ta conversion in a carburizing environment was examined over a range of temperatures to determine rate-limiting behavior and activation energy for the process. A 1-D moving interface model was constructed to predict carburization depth and compare data from the present work to that in the literature. It was found that the activation energy for carburization increases as conversion proceeds, suggesting a transition from grain boundary to bulk diffusion. Additionally, to simulate potential use cases of this nanoporous ceramic, the compositional and morphological stability was evaluated in a high temperature environment. Finally, the utility of this thermally stable porous UHTC was demonstrated through synthesis of a nanostructured composite of TaC and oxidation-resistant material, SiO2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18657v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catherine Ott, Vaibhav Verma, Adam Peters, Ian McCue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic tuning of ENZ wavelength in conductive polymer films via polaron excitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditional metal and n-type doped semiconductor materials serve as emerging epsilon-near-zero (ENZ) materials, showcasing great potential for nonlinear photonic applications. However, a significant limitation for such materials is the lack of versatile ENZ wavelength tuning, and thus dynamic tuning of the ENZ wavelength remains a technical challenge, thereby restricting their potential applications, such as multi-band communications. Here, dynamic tuning of the ENZ wavelength in p-type organic PEDOT: PSS films is achieved through a reversible change in hole concentrations originated from the polaron formation/decoupling following optical excitation, and a tunable ENZ wavelength shift up to 150 nm is observed. Experimental investigations about ultrafast dynamics of polaron excitation reveal an approximately 80 fs time constant for polaron buildup and an approximately 280 fs time constant for polaron decoupling, indicating the potential of reversal ultrafast switching for the ENZ wavelength within subpicosecond time scale. These findings suggest that $p$--type organic semiconductors can serve as a novel platform for dynamically tuning the ENZ wavelength through polaron excitation, opening new possibilities for ENZ--based nonlinear optical applications in flexible optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18878v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongqi Liu, Junjun Jia, Menghui Jia, Chengcan Han, Sanjun Zhang, Hui Ye, Heping Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wavelength Control of Perovskite Metasurface Lasing via Electrical Microheaters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19148v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Perovskites have recently brought significant advances to active nanophotonics, offering a unique combination of gain and phase-change properties for tunable light-emitting devices. However, current wavelength-tunable devices often rely on tuning mechanisms or device architectures that lead to slow modulation or bulky setups. In this study, we overcome limitations on speed and size by demonstrating a compact tunable microlaser embedding electrical microheaters beneath a perovskite metasurface. This architecture allows to efficiently deliver heat and rapidly modulate the phase transition. Our device leverages the optical gain and crystallographic phase tuning of the perovskite, and a high-quality factor cavity design based on bound states in the continuum. With it, we demonstrate reversible laser wavelength switching between 763 nm and 783 nm within 13 ms at 2.3 V. This work unlocks the potential of perovskite metasurfaces for electrically tunable light sources and introduces a flexible platform which can be easily extended to the dynamic control of polarization or directionality for optical communication, sensing and spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19148v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Meiler, Yutao Wang, Saurabh Srivastava, Giorgio Adamo, Ram\'on Paniagua-Dominguez, Arseniy Kuznetsov, Cesare Soci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast opto-acoustics in single nickel cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19267v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mechanical stress produced in nano- and micro-scale structures can enhance materials properties, such as the high mobility of silicon in modern transistors or amplified magnetization dynamics in spintronic devices. Here, we report on the dynamics of coherent acoustic phonons excited by femtosecond light pulses and confined in a single freestanding nickel layer, acting as an acoustic cavity. By combining Fourier transform analysis of the experimental signal and numerical multi-physics simulations, we show that high-frequency (&gt; 10 GHz) longitudinal acoustic pulses can resonate inside the cavity and display lower damping compared to a reference nickel film on SiO2 substrate given that the conditions of total reflection are nearly met in the cavity. Our results provide a thorough understanding of the opto-acoustic response in suspended membranes of magnetic materials, which we foresee can be used to amplify magnetization precession dynamics and to develop magneto-acousto-optical modulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19267v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alba Viejo Rodr\'iguez, Marco Gandolfi, Andrea Rossetti, Yoav Urbina Elgueta, Evgeny B. Modin, Svetlana Starikovskaia, Tatloon Chng, Vasily Temnov, Maria Antonietta Vincenti, Daniele Brida, Paolo Vavassori, Nicol\`o Maccaferri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat panel laser displays enabled by large-scale visible photonic integrated circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Laser-based displays are highly sought after for their superior brightness and color performance, especially in advanced applications like augmented reality (AR). However, their broader adoption has been hindered by bulky projector designs and complex optical module assemblies. Here, we introduce a new laser display architecture enabled by large-scale visible photonic integrated circuits (PICs) to address these challenges. Unlike previous projector-style laser displays, this architecture features an ultra-thin, flat-panel form factor, replacing bulky free-space illumination modules with a single, high-performance photonic chip. Centimeter-scale PIC devices, which integrate thousands of distinct optical components on-chip, are carefully tailored to achieve high display uniformity, contrast, and efficiency. We demonstrate a 2 mm-thick flat-panel laser display combining the PIC with a liquid-crystal-on-silicon (LCoS) panel, achieving 211% of the color gamut and more than 80% volume reduction compared to traditional LCoS displays. We further showcase its application in a see-through AR system. Our work represents a major advancement in the integration of nanophotonics with display technology, enabling a range of new display concepts, from high-performance immersive displays to slim-panel 3D holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19274v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhujun Shi, Risheng Cheng, Guohua Wei, Steven A. Hickman, Min Chul Shin, Peter Topalian, Lei Wang, Dusan Coso, Brian Le, Lizzy Lee, Sean Braxton, Alexander Koshelev, Maxwell F. Parsons, Rahul Agarwal, Barry Silverstein, Yun Wang, Giuseppe Calafiore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Electro-Optic Absorption Modulator for Silicon Nitride Platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19306v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Silicon nitride (SiN) is currently the most prominent platform for photonics at visible and near-IR wavelength bandwidth. However, realizing fast electro-optic (EO) modulators, the key components of any integrated optics platform, remains challenging in SiN. Recently, transparent conductive oxides (TCO) have emerged as a promising platform for photonic integrated circuits. Here we make an important step towards exceeding possibilities of both platforms, reporting for the first-time high-speed ITO electro-optic modulators based on silicon nitride waveguides. The insertion losses of 5.7 dB and bandwidth of about 1 GHz are shown for 300 nm-thickness SiN waveguide platform with 9.3-um-length hybrid waveguide. The fabrication process of devices requires only standard clean room tools, is repeatable and compatible with the CMOS technology. Simulation results of optimized device designs indicate that further improvement is possible and offer promising opportunities towards silicon nitride photonic computation platforms based on ITO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19306v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evgeniy S. Lotkov, Alexander S. Baburin, Ali S. Amiraslanov, Evgeniy Chubchev, Alexander Dorofeenko, Evgeniy Andrianov, Ilya A. Ryzhikov, Evgeny S. Sergeev, Kirill Buzaverov, Sergei S. Avdeev, Alex Kramarenko, Sergei Bukatin, Victor I. Polozov, Olga S. Sorokina, Yuri V. Panfilov, Daria P. Kulikova, Alexander V. Baryshev, Ilya A. Rodionov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High performance Black Phosphorus/Graphitic Carbon Nitride Heterostructure-based Wearable Sensor for Real-time Sweat Glucose Monitoring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19633v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wearable, non-invasive glucose sensors capable of accurate and continuous monitoring are crucial for managing metabolic conditions yet achieving high sensitivity and stability in these devices remains challenging. In this work, we present a Black Phosphorus/Graphitic Carbon Nitride (BP/g-CN) heterostructure engineered to leverage phosphorus-nitrogen interactions for enhanced electrochemical glucose oxidation activity. Compared to pristine gCN, the BP-gCN heterostructure demonstrates a significantly improved electrochemical surface area (ECSA) and nearly two-fold reduction in charge transfer resistance (Rct), achieving remarkable glucose sensitivity of 1.1 uA mM(^-1) cm(^-2) at physiological pH. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations revealed stronger glucose adsorption and higher charge transfer on the BP-gCN heterostructure compared to pristine gCN surface. These theoretical insights complement the experimental findings, highlighting the superior electrocatalytic performance of the heterostructure and the role of oxidized BP surface. Furthermore, the BP-gCN sensor is integrated into a wearable device platform with microfluidic layers and a Near Field Communication (NFC) chip, forming a conformal skin patch that enables real-time sweat glucose monitoring. This demonstration of a high-performance, non-enzymatic wearable glucose sensor based on a heterostructure design underscores the potential of the device for seamless health management and paves the way for next generation biosensing platforms aimed at improving personalized and continuous health monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19633v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ecem Ezgi Ozkahraman, Zafer Eroglu, Vladimir Efremov, Arooba Maryyam, Taher Abbasiasl, Ritu Das, Hadi Mirzajani, Berna Akgenc Hanedar, Levent Beker, Onder Metin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Radiation Hardness of InAs/GaAs Quantum Dot Lasers for Space Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20807v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Semiconductor lasers have great potential for space laser communication. However, excessive radiation in space can cause laser failure. In principle, quantum dot (QD) lasers are more radiation-resistant than traditional semiconductor lasers because of their superior carrier confinement and smaller active regions. However, the multifaceted nature of radiation effects on QDs resulted in ongoing controversies. Comprehensive testing under simulated space conditions is also necessary to validate their performance. In this work, we conducted radiation tests on various In(Ga)As/GaAs QD and quantum well (QW) materials and devices. Our results revealed that InAs/GaAs QDs with filling factors greater than 50% exhibit greater radiation hardness than those below 50%. Furthermore, most InAs/GaAs QDs showed superior radiation resistance compared to InGaAs/GaAs QW when exposed to low proton fluences of 1E11 and 1E12 cm-2, resulting from radiation-induced defects. The linewidth enhancement factor (LEF) of well-designed QD lasers remains remarkably stable and close to zero, even under proton irradiation at a maximum fluence of 7E13 cm-2, owing to their inherent insensitivity to irradiation-induced defects. These QD lasers demonstrate an exceptional average relative intensity noise (RIN) level of -162 dB/Hz, with only a 1 dB/Hz increase in RIN observed at the highest fluence, indicating outstanding stability. Furthermore, the lasers exhibit remarkable robustness against optical feedback, sustaining stable performance even under a feedback strength as high as -3.1 dB. These results highlight the significant potential of QD lasers for space laser communication applications, where high reliability and resilience to radiation and environmental perturbations are critical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20807v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manyang Li, Jianan Duan, Zhiyong Jin, Shujie Pan, Wenkang Zhan, Jinpeng Chen, Jinling Yu, Xiaotian Cheng, Zhibo Ni, Chaoyuan Jin, Tien Khee Ng, Jinxia Kong, Xiaochuan Xu, Yong Yao, Bo Xu, Siming Chen, Zhanguo Wang, Chao Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct calibration of microwave amplification chain on an axion cavity haloscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13350v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In an axion haloscope, the weak photon signal, theoretically converted from axions, is captured by a detection cavity. The signal from the cavity is too weak to be acquired by a signal receiver. The amplification chain assists the signal acquisition by amplifying the signal and requires accurate gain calibration. Typically, the readout line is calibrated using the Y-factor method, involving a switch that directs either the detection line or the calibration line to the amplification chain. The detection and calibration lines may have different transmissions, which leads to the calibration results being less accurate. In response, we propose a calibration method that eliminates the need for a switch. In this approach, the cavity temperature is decoupled to its incoming noise source and can be controlled, resulting in excess or deficiency of the noise spectrum near its resonance frequency. The experimental result shows that the gain of the amplification chain can be calibrated directly using the temperature-varied cavity radiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13350v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsin Chang, Han-Wen Liu, Hien Thi Doan, Yung-Fu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative Framework for Engineering Arbitrary Floquet Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10467v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a systematic perturbative framework to engineer an arbitrary target Hamiltonian in the Floquet phase space of a periodically driven oscillator based on Floquet-Magnus expansion. The high-order errors in the engineered Floquet Hamiltonian are mitigated by adding high-order driving potentials perturbatively. We introduce a transformation method that allows us to obtain an analytical expression of the leading-order correction drive for engineering a target Hamiltonian with discrete rotational and chiral symmetries in phase space. We also provide a numerically efficient procedure to calculate high-order correction drives and apply it to engineer the target Hamiltonian with degenerate eigenstates of multi-component cat states that are important for fault-tolerant hardware-efficiency bosonic quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10467v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingdan Xu, Lingzhen Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
