<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.app-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph</link>
    <description>physics.app-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 01:47:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Field Free Spin-Orbit Torque Controlled Synapse and Stochastic Neuron Devices for Spintronic Boltzmann Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05616v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spintronics offers a promising approach to energy efficient neuromorphic computing by integrating the functionalities of synapses and neurons within a single platform. A major challenge, however, is achieving field-free spin orbit torque SOT control over both synaptic and neuronal devices using an industry-adopted spintronic materials stack. In this study, we present field-free SOT spintronic synapses utilizing a CoFeB ferromagnetic thin film system, where asymmetrical device design and specifically added lateral notches in the CoFeB thin film facilitate effective domain wall DW nucleation, movement, and pinning and depinning. This method yields multiple analog, nonvolatile resistance states with enhanced linearity and symmetry, resulting in programmable and stable synaptic weights. We provide a systematic measurement approach to improve the linearity and symmetry of the synapses. Additionally, we demonstrate nanoscale magnetic tunnel junctions MTJs that function as SOT-driven stochastic neurons, exhibiting current-tunable, Boltzmann-like probabilistic switching behavior, which provides an intrinsic in-hardware Gibbs sampling capability. By integrating these synapses and neurons into a Boltzmann machine complemented by a classifier layer, we achieve recognition accuracies greater than 98 percent on the MNIST dataset and 86 percent on Fashion MNIST. This work establishes a framework for field free synaptic and neuronal devices, setting the stage for practical, materials-compatible, and all spintronic neuromorphic computing hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05616v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aijaz H. Lone, Meng Tang, Camelia Florica, Bin He, Jingkai Xu, Xixiang Zhang, Gianluca Setti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Synapse based on ULTRARAM Memory Device for Neuromorphic Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The memory demands of large-scale deep neural networks (DNNs) require synaptic weight values to be stored and updated in off-chip memory like dynamic random-access memory, which reduces energy efficiency and increases training time. Monolithic crossbar or pseudo-crossbar arrays using analog non-volatile memories, which can store and update weights on-chip, present an opportunity to efficiently accelerate DNN training. In this article, we present on-chip training and inference of a neural network using an ULTRARAM memory device-based synaptic array and complementary metal-oxide-semiconductor (CMOS) peripheral circuits. ULTRARAM is a promising emerging memory exhibiting high endurance (&gt;10^7 P/E cycles), ultra-high retention (&gt;1000 years), and ultra-low switching energy per unit area. A physics-based compact model of ULTRARAM memory device has been proposed to capture the real-time trapping/de-trapping of charges in the floating gate (FG) and utilized for the synapse simulations. A circuit-level macro-model is employed to evaluate and benchmark the on-chip learning performance in terms of area, latency, energy, and accuracy of an ULTRARAM synaptic core. In comparison to CMOS-based design, it demonstrates an overall improvement in area and energy by 1.8x and 1.52x, respectively, with 91% of training accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05671v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Kumar, Peter D. Hodgson, Manus Hayne, Avirup Dasgupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Channel Amplitude-Phase Asymmetric-Encrypted Janus Acoustic Meta-Holograms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Encrypted optical and acoustic meta-holograms only focus on the encrypted hologram in a single channel, viz. modulating spatial amplitude to project a holographic image. In this research, the unique concept of multi-channel amplitude-phase asymmetric-encrypted Janus acoustic meta-holograms is proposed, demonstrating remarkable capabilities of generating, encrypting, and decrypting both amplitude and phase holographic images on both sides of a metascreen. The flexible and decoupled manipulation mechanism for the amplitude-phase of the bidirectional acoustic waves used in our concept offers multiple possibilities to apply various encryption methods. In this work, our system enables single-input, two-faced four-channel asymmetric encryption, which substantially increase the communication capacity of conventional acoustic holograms, and establish a security framework based on mathematical problem, proving its security. Our work can lead to concrete applications including, but not limited to, multi-channel acoustic field communications and acoustic illusion and cloaking in non-transparent media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05789v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haohan Zeng, Zhenyu He, Tianxiang Zhang, Xiao Guo, Xinghao Hu, Youyu Mo, Tingting Li, Feilong Mao, Haiyan Fan, Xudong Fan, Weiwei Kan, Yifan Zhu, Hui Zhang, Guodong Yin, Badreddine Assouar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Feasibility of Acoustophoresis Multimodal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Actuating the acoustic resonance modes of a microfluidic device containing suspended particles (e.g., cells) allows for the manipulation of their individual positions. In this work, we investigate how the number of resonance modes $M$ chosen for actuation and the number of particles $P$ affect the probability of success $S$ of manipulation tasks, denoted Acoustophoretic Control Problems (ACPs). Using simulations, we show that the ratio of locally controllable volume to the state-space volume correlates strongly with $S$. This ratio can be efficiently computed from the pressure field geometry as it does not involve solving a control problem, thus opening possibilities for experimental and numerical device optimization routines. Further, we show numerically that in noise-free 1D systems $S \approx 1 - P/M$, and that in noisy 1D and 2D systems $S$ is accurately predicted by Wendel's Theorem. We also show that the relationship between $M$ and $P$ for a given $S$ is approximately linear, suggesting that as long as $P/M$ is constant, $S$ will remain unchanged. We validate this finding by successfully simulating the control of systems with up to $60$ particles with up to $600$ modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06116v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guilherme Perticarari, Dongjun Wu, Thierry Baasch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory behavior of a randomly driven model glass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05537v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate by atomistic simulations the memory behavior a model glass subjected to random driving protocols. The training consists of a random walk of forward and/or backward shearing sequences bounded by a maximal shear strain of absolute value {\gamma}T . We show that such a stochastic training protocol is able to record the training amplitude. Different read-out protocols are also tested and are shown to be able to retrieve the training amplitude. We then emphasize the ten- sorial character of the memory encoded in the glass sample and then characterize the anisotropic mechanical behavior of the trained samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05537v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roni Chatterjee, Smarajit Karmakar, Muhittin Mungan, Damien Vandembroucq</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High- and medium-entropy nitride coatings from the Cr-Hf-Mo-Ta-W-N system: properties and high-temperature stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05928v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High- and medium-entropy nitride coatings from the Cr-Hf-Mo-Ta-W-N system were studied using ab initio calculations and experiments to clarify the role of entropy and individual elements in phase stability, microstructure, and high-temperature behaviour. Formation energy calculations indicated that nitrogen vacancies stabilise the cubic (fcc) phase, with hafnium and tantalum acting as strong stabilisers, while tungsten destabilises the lattice. Coatings were deposited by reactive magnetron sputtering at approx. 50C (AT) and approx. 580C (HT). All exhibited columnar fcc structures; high-temperature deposition produced denser coatings, lower nitrogen content, and larger crystallites, resulting in higher hardness and elastic modulus. Thermal stability was tested up to 1200C on Si and oxidation at 1400C on sapphire. AT coatings failed early, while most HT coatings endured. Nitrogen loss less than 10 at.% at 1000C was critical for survival. TEM revealed tungsten segregation and HfO2 formation, while fcc nitride remained dominant. Ta enrichment proved essential for superior thermal and oxidation stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05928v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel Sou\v{c}ek, Stanislava Debn\'arov\'a, \v{S}\'arka Zuzjakov\'a, Shuyao Lin, Matej Fekete, Zsolt Czig\'any, Katalin Bal\'azsi, Luk\'a\v{s} Vr\'ana, Tatiana Pito\v{n}\'akov\'a, Ond\v{r}ej Ja\v{s}ek, Petr Zeman, Nikola Koutn\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retardance of lab grown diamond substrates as a function of thickness: momentum-drift random walk model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05932v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work studies the correlation between mean retardance and thickness of diamond substrates grown homoepitaxially via microwave plasma-enhanced chemical vapor deposition (MPCVD). We measure the retardance of a diamond substrate in two orientations: perpendicular and parallel to the growth direction. Our experimental results demonstrate that the correlation between mean retardance and thickness differs for these orientations. When measured perpendicular to the growth direction, the mean retardance is approximately proportional to the square root of the substrate thickness. In contrast, when measured parallel to the growth direction, we observe a generally higher mean retardance and an approximately linear correlation with thickness. This anisotropy arises not from differences in stress magnitude but from differences in the interlayer correlation of the principal stress axes, as evidenced by correlation coefficients between the azimuth angles of consecutive layers in the diamond crystal. To simulate the integrated retardance of diamond wafers, we propose a two-dimensional random walk model with momentum drift, which captures the diamond crystal tendency to preserve the azimuth angle across the samples. By optimizing the momentum factor, we show that the model can closely match experimental data. The momentum factor is found higher along the growth direction, which is consistent with the calculated correlation coefficients. Furthermore, both the model and experiments indicate that retardance-to-thickness ratios of thin samples converge toward similar base retardances in both orientations. These findings establish a quantitative framework for interpreting birefringence in diamond substrates, with implications for material selection and development in thermal management, quantum sensing, high-power electronics, and optical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05932v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanh Tran, Phuong Vo, Thomas Sheppard, Timothy Grotjohn, Paul Quayle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimised spectral purity of unfiltered photons via pump and nonlinearity shaping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06196v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Photonic quantum technologies rely on the efficient generation and interference of indistinguishable photons. Exceptional achievements in this respect have been obtained by domain engineering of quasi-phase-matched parametric down-conversion sources, demonstrating high two-photon interference visibility using only moderate bandpass spectral filtering. Here, we optimised the spectral purity and indistinguishability of photons from telecom-wavelength sources by combining Gaussian quasi-phase-matching with Gaussian pump spectral shaping. Without spectral filtering, we used time-of-flight spectrometry to estimate an upper bound spectral purity of 99.9272(6)%, and achieved visibilities of up to 98.5(8)% in two-photon interference experiments with independent sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06196v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Faleo, Christopher L. Morrison, Rom\'eo Beignon, Francesco Graffitti, Vikas Remesh, Stefan Frick, Alessandro Fedrizzi, Gregor Weihs, Robert Keil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tamm Plasmon-Enhanced Widely Tunable Near-Infrared Nanolaser with Superior Efficiency and Output Power</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04827v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Plasmonic resonances attract significant interest due to their ability to tightly confine electromagnetic fields. Surface plasmon polaritons (SPPs) and localized surface plasmons (LSPs) are widely used in plasmonic nanolasers, but performance is often affected by coupling into reflective and transmissive directions and multiple far-field modes, mainly due to higher-order diffraction from the plasmonic crystal. Here, we utilize the Tamm plasmon mode at the interface between a distributed Bragg reflector (DBR) and a metal layer to achieve lasing in the NIR region with wide tunability. Optical Tamm states are excited at the metal-DBR interface by a pump pulse, and emission is enhanced via extraordinary optical transmission through a metallic nanohole array, which suppresses higher-order diffraction and ensures a directional far-field pattern. A second DBR beneath the pump side further suppresses backward emission and enhances forward lasing intensity. The combination of Tamm plasmon excitation and dual-DBR feedback improves cavity response and overall lasing efficiency. This approach provides a cost-effective and versatile route to plasmonic nanolasers with enhanced efficiency, tunability, and integration potential for next-generation on-chip photonic and quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04827v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Tahsin Alam, Zafrin Jahan Nikita, Ying Yin Tsui, Md. Zahurul Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
