<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.app-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph</link>
    <description>physics.app-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 05:04:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular 9Be+p Fusion Reaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00023v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study (nuclear) fusion reactions in Beryllium. We argue that some are nuclear long-distance molecular processes of interest for low energy nuclear reactions. For these we develop a novel reaction model. We note a chain of reactions that can naturally arise in Beryllium target created by nonequilibrium proton reactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00023v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johann Rafelski, Berndt M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graded Index Couplers for Next Generation Chip-to-Chip and Fiber-to-Chip Photonic Packaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00121v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The transition towards designs which co-package electronic and photonic die together in data center switch packages has created a scaling path to Petabyte per second (Pbps) input/output (I/O) in such systems. In a co-packaged design, the scaling of bandwidth, cost, and energy will be governed by the number of optical I/O channels and the data rate per channel. While optical communication provide an opportunity to exploit wavelength division multiplexing (WDM) to scale data rate, the limited 127 $\mu$m pitch of V-groove based single mode fiber arrays and the use of active alignment and bonding for their packaging present challenges to scaling the number of optical channels. Flip-chip optical couplers which allow for low loss, broadband operation and automated passive assembly represent a solution for continued scaling. In this paper, we propose a novel scheme to vertically couple between silicon based waveguides on separate chips using graded index (GRIN) couplers in combination with an evanescent coupler. Simulation results using a 3D Finite-Difference Time-Domain (FDTD) solver are presented, demonstrating coupling losses below 0.27 dB for a chip-to-chip gap of 11 $\mu$m; 1-dB vertical and lateral alignment tolerances of approximately 2.38 $\mu$m and $\pm$ 2.24 $\mu$m, respectively; and a greater than 360 nm 1-dB bandwidth. These results demonstrate the potential of our coupler as a universal interface in future co-packaged optics systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00121v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Drew Weninger, Christian Duessel, Samuel Serna, Lionel Kimerling, Anuradha Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Framework for Analyzing the Scalability of Ion Trap Geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00218v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A utility-scale trapped-ion quantum information processor will require millions of qubits controlled with fast and high-fidelity gates. Achievable ion number, gate speed, and gate fidelity are all influenced by the trapping field, which depends on the electrode geometry. Here we identify a set of key field-dependent figures of merit: harmonicity of the trapping potential, radial trapping frequency, and trap depth. We also consider fabrication requirements and the path towards integration of peripherals. We apply this framework to three types of traps: a standard surface trap, a surface trap with a grounded top wafer, and a trap with two stacked identical patterned wafers with cross-alignment of rf and dc electrodes. We determine that purely 2D surface traps lack the necessary field properties for large-scale quantum technologies due to their shallow trap depth and low harmonicity. Moving to 3D geometries will be essential to achieve higher radial confinement, better harmonicity, and therefore lower power dissipation. This framework can be applied to future work in designing and demonstrating scalable electrode geometries for trapped-ion quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00218v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Minh Anh Nguyen, Brant Bowers, Sara Mouradian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design of a quantum diamond microscope with efficient scanning confocal readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00252v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the light-sheet confocal quantum diamond microscope (LC-QDM) for widefield 3D quantum sensing with efficient confocal readout. The LC-QDM leverages light-sheet illumination and laser scanning confocal methods to enable high-resolution, high-speed 3D measurements with nitrogen-vacancy (NV) defects in diamond, combining the best of widefield and confocal modalities in a single device and eliminating the need for thin-NV-layer diamond chips. We perform simulations and measurements of NV initialization and readout times to model the anticipated performance of the LC-QDM compared to existing QDM designs. Our findings show that the LC-QDM will provide significant advantages for applications requiring limited laser power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00252v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel G. Ang, Jiashen Tang, Ronald L. Walsworth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current-driven collective control of helical spin texture in van der Waals antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electrical control of quantum magnetic states is essential in spintronic science. Initial studies on the ferromagnetic state control were extended to collinear antiferromagnets and, more recently, noncollinear antiferromagnets. However, electrical control mechanisms of such exotic magnetic states remain poorly understood. Here, we report the first experimental and theoretical example of the current control of helical antiferromagnets, arising from the competition between collinear antiferromagnetic exchange and interlayer Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction in new van-der-Waals (vdW) material Ni1/3NbS2. Due to the intrinsic broken inversion symmetry, an in-plane current generates spin-orbit torque that, in turn, interacts directly with the helical antiferromagnetic order. Our theoretical analyses indicate that a weak ferromagnetic order coexists due to the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction, mediating the spin-orbit torque to collectively rotate the helical antiferromagnetic order. Our Ni1/3NbS2 nanodevice experiments produce current-dependent resistance change consistent with the theoretical prediction. This work widens our understanding of the electrical control of helical antiferromagnets and promotes vdW quantum magnets as interesting material platforms for electrical control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00319v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters XX, XXXX (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kai-Xuan Zhang, Suik Cheon, Hyuncheol Kim, Pyeongjae Park, Yeochan An, Suhan Son, Jingyuan Cui, Jihoon Keum, Joonyoung Choi, Younjung Jo, Hwiin Ju, Jong-Seok Lee, Youjin Lee, Maxim Avdeev, Armin Kleibert, Hyun-Woo Lee, Je-Geun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrically Reconfigurable Intelligent Optoelectronics in 2-D van der Waals Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00347v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In optoelectronics, achieving electrical reconfigurability is crucial as it enables the encoding, decoding, manipulating, and processing of information carried by light. In recent years, two-dimensional van der Waals (2-D vdW) materials have emerged as promising platforms for realizing reconfigurable optoelectronic devices. Compared to materials with bulk crystalline lattice, 2-D vdW materials offer superior electrical reconfigurability due to high surface-to-volume ratio, quantum confinement, reduced dielectric screening effect, and strong dipole resonances. Additionally, their unique band structures and associated topology and quantum geometry provide novel tuning capabilities. This review article seeks to establish a connection between the fundamental physics underlying reconfigurable optoelectronics in 2-D materials and their burgeoning applications in intelligent optoelectronics. We first survey various electrically reconfigurable properties of 2-D vdW materials and the underlying tuning mechanisms. Then we highlight the emerging applications of such devices, including dynamic intensity, phase and polarization control, and intelligent sensing. Finally, we discuss the opportunities for future advancements in this field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00347v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Dehui Zhang, Yihao Song, Jea Jung Lee, Meng Tian, Souvik Biswas, Fengnian Xia, Qiushi Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable photonic-phonoinc integrated circuitry for reconfigurable signal processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00754v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interaction between photons and phonons plays a crucial role in broad areas ranging from optical sources and modulators to quantum transduction and metrology. The performance can be further improved using integrated photonic-phononic devices, promising enhanced interaction strength and large-scale integration. While the enhanced interaction has been widely demonstrated, it is challenging to realize large-scale integrated photonic-phononic circuits due to material limitations. Here, we resolve this critical issue by using gallium nitride on sapphire for scalable photonicphononic integrated circuits. Both optical and acoustic fields are confined in sub-wavelength scales without suspended structures. This enables us to achieve the efficient launching, flexible routing, and reconfigruable processing of optical and acoustic fields simultaneously. With the controlled photonic-phononic interaction and strong piezoelectric effect, we further demonstrate the reconfigurable conversion between frequency-multiplexed RF and optical signals mediated by acoustics. This work provides an ideal platform for achieving ultimate performance of photonic-phononic hybrid systems with high efficiency, multiple functions, and large scalability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00754v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Zhang, Chaohan Cui, Yongzhou Xue, Paokang Chen, Linran Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Fasteners on the Radar Cross-Section performance of Radar Absorbing Air Intake Duct</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00914v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An aircraft consists of various cavities including air intake ducts, cockpit, radome, inlet and exhaust of heat exchangers, passage for engine bay/other bay cooling etc. These cavities are prime radar cross-section (RCS) contributors of aircraft. The major such cavity is air intake duct, and it contributes significantly to frontal sector RCS of an aircraft. The RCS reductions of air intake duct is very important to achieve a low RCS (or stealthy) aircraft configuration. In general, radar absorbing materials (RAM) are getting utilized for RCS reduction of air intake duct. It can also be noticed that a large number of fasteners are used for integration of air intake duct with the aircraft structures. The installation of fasteners on RAS may lead to degradation of RCS performance of air intake. However, no such studies are reported in the literature on the impact of rivets on the RCS performance of RAS air intake duct. In this paper, radar absorbing material of thickness 6.25 mm is designed which givens more than -10 dB reflection loss from 4 to 18GHz of frequencies. Next, the effect of rivet installation on these RAS is carried out using three different rivet configurations. The RCS performance of RAS is evaluated for duct of different lengths from 1 to 18GHz of frequencies. In order to see the RCS performance, five different air intake cases are considered The RCS performance with increase in percentage surface area of rivet heads to RAS is reported in detail. At the last, an open-source aircraft CAD model is considered and the RCS performance of RAS air intake with and without rivets is evaluated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00914v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vijay Kumar Sutrakar, Anjana P K</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interfacial strong coupling and negative dispersion of propagating polaritons in freestanding oxide membranes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01171v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Membranes of complex oxides like perovskite SrTiO3 extend the multi-functional promise of oxide electronics into the nanoscale regime of two-dimensional materials. Here we demonstrate that free-standing oxide membranes supply a reconfigurable platform for nano-photonics based on propagating surface phonon polaritons. We apply infrared near-field imaging and -spectroscopy enabled by a tunable ultrafast laser to study pristine nano-thick SrTiO3 membranes prepared by hybrid molecular beam epitaxy. As predicted by coupled mode theory, we find that strong coupling of interfacial polaritons realizes symmetric and antisymmetric hybridized modes with simultaneously tunable negative and positive group velocities. By resolving reflection of these propagating modes from membrane edges, defects, and substrate structures, we quantify their dispersion with position-resolved nano-spectroscopy. Remarkably, we find polariton negative dispersion is both robust and tunable through choice of membrane dielectric environment and thickness and propose a novel design for in-plane Veselago lensing harnessing this control. Our work lays the foundation for tunable transformation optics at the nanoscale using polaritons in a wide range of freestanding complex oxide membranes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01171v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brayden Lukaskawcez, Shivasheesh Varshney, Sooho Choo, Sang Hyun Park, Dongjea Seo, Liam Thompson, Devon Uram, Hayden Binger, Steve Koester, Sang-Hyun Oh, Tony Low, Bharat Jalan, Alexander McLeod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Tunable THz wave generation using spectral shaping in electro-optic combs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01371v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel method for generating terahertz (THz) waves using cascaded electro-optic modulators (EOMs), providing numerical simulations and experimental validations to demonstrate its effectiveness. The key of this technique is to apply hybrid amplitude and phase modulation to the incident light, which significantly enhances the control capability over the output optical spectrum. This enhanced control turns to be crucial for the efficient generation of THz waves. By carefully adjusting the relative phase offset between microwave RF signals applied to the amplitude and phase modulators and by applying an appropriate DC bias to the amplitude modulator, we can considerably reduce the optical power of unwanted sidebands. This allows us to concentrate more energy on desired frequencies, facilitating the generation of high-purity THz waves through optical heterodyne mixing at the detector. To validate our concept, we have successfully generated a dual-frequency-like laser with as spectral separation of 0.897 THz. This result was accomplished by modulating the phase EOM at 34.5 GHz with a modulation depth of ~4.7, paving the way for the generation of more practical and efficient THz waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01371v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanghoon Chin, Ewelina Obrzud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Programmable Electric Tweezers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01554v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interaction mechanism between a single microscopic object like a cell, a particle, a molecule, or an atom and its interacting electromagnetic field is fundamental in single-object manipulation such as optical trap and magnetic trap. Function-on-demand, single-object manipulation relies on a high degree of freedom control of electromagnetic field at localized scales, which remains challenging. Here we propose a manipulation concept: programmable single-object manipulation, based on programming the electromagnetic field in a multi-bit electrode system. This concept is materialized on a Programmable Electric Tweezer (PET) with four individually addressed electrodes, marking a transition from function-fixed single-object manipulation to function-programmable single-object manipulation. By programming the localized electric field, our PET can provide various manipulation functions for achieving precise trapping, movement and rotation of multiscale single microscopic objects, including single proteins, nucleic acids, microparticles and bacteria. Implementing these functions, we are able not only to manipulate the object of interest on demand but also quantitatively measure the charge to mass ratio of a single microparticle via the Paul trap and the electrical properties of an individual bacterial cell by the rotation analysis. Finally, with superposed single-particle trapping and rotation, we demonstrate the spontaneous relaxation of DNA supercoiling and observe an unexpected pause phenomenon in the relaxation process, highlighting the versatility and the potential of PET in uncovering stochastic biophysical phenomena at the single-molecule level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01554v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuang Chen, Haojing Tan, Jiahua Zhuang, Yang Xu, Chen Zhang, Jiandong Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of O interstitial diffusion in $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$: direct approach via master diffusion equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01735v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Monoclinic $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$, a promising wide band gap semiconducting material, exhibits complex, anisotropic diffusional characteristics and mass transport behavior as a results of its low symmetry crystal structure. From first-principles calculations combined with master diffusion equations, we determine three-dimensional diffusion tensors for neutral ($\text{O}_{\text{i}}^{0}$) and 2- charged oxygen interstitials ($\text{O}_{\text{i}}^{2-}$). Systematic exploration of the configurational space identifies stable configurations in these two dominant charge states and their corresponding formation energies. By connecting every pair of low-energy configurations considering both interstitial or interstitialcy hops, we construct three-dimensional diffusion networks and evaluate hopping barriers of all transition pathways in networks. Combining the collection of (i) defect configurations and their formation energies and (ii) the hopping barriers that link them, we construct and solve the master diffusion equations for $\text{O}_{\text{i}}^{0}$ and $\text{O}_{\text{i}}^{2-}$ separately through the Onsager approach, resulting in respective three-dimensional diffusion tensors D$_{\text{O}_{\text{i}}}^{0}$ and D$_{\text{O}_{\text{i}}}^{2-}$. Both $\text{O}_{\text{i}}^{0}$ and $\text{O}_{\text{i}}^{2-}$ present the fastest diffusion along the $b$-axis, demonstrating significant anisotropy. The predicted self-diffusivities along [100] and [$\overline{2}01$] align well with previously reported values from isotopically labeled oxygen tracer experiments, highlighting the reliability of the approach in capturing complex diffusion mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01735v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grace McKnight, Channyung Lee, Elif Ertekin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A COMSOL framework for predicting hydrogen embrittlement -- Part I: coupled hydrogen transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01736v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hydrogen threatens the structural integrity of metals and thus predicting hydrogen-material interactions is key to unlocking the role of hydrogen in the energy transition. Quantifying the interplay between material deformation and hydrogen diffusion ahead of cracks and other stress concentrators is key to the prediction and prevention of hydrogen-assisted failures. In this work, a generalised theoretical and computational framework is presented that for the first time encompasses: (i) stress-assisted diffusion, (ii) hydrogen trapping due to multiple trap types, rigorously accounting for the rate of creation of dislocation trap sites, (iii) hydrogen transport through dislocations, (iv) equilibrium (Oriani) and non-equilibrium (McNabb-Foster) trapping kinetics, (v) hydrogen-induced softening, and (vi) hydrogen uptake, considering the role of hydrostatic stresses and local electrochemistry. Particular emphasis is placed on the numerical implementation in COMSOL Multiphysics, releasing the relevant models and discussing stability, discretisation and solver details. Each of the elements of the framework is independently benchmarked against results from the literature and implications for the prediction of hydrogen-assisted fractures are discussed. The second part of this work (Part II) shows how these crack tip predictions can be combined with crack growth simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01736v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. D\'iaz, J. M. Alegre, I. I. Cuesta, E. Mart\'inez-Pa\~neda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A COMSOL framework for predicting hydrogen embrittlement -- Part II: phase field fracture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01765v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Prediction of hydrogen embrittlement requires a robust modelling approach and this will foster the safe adoption of hydrogen as a clean energy vector. A generalised computational model for hydrogen embrittlement is here presented, based on a phase field description of fracture. In combination with Part I of this work, which describes the process of hydrogen uptake and transport, this allows simulating a wide range of hydrogen transport and embrittlement phenomena. The material toughness is defined as a function of the hydrogen content and both elastic and elastic-plastic material behaviour are incorporated, enabling to capture both ductile and brittle fractures, and the transition from one to the other. The accumulation of hydrogen near a crack tip and subsequent embrittlement is numerically evaluated in a single-edge cracked plate, a boundary layer model and a 3D vessel case study, demonstrating the potential of the framework. Emphasis is placed on the numerical implementation, which is carried out in the finite element package COMSOL Multiphysics, and the models are made freely available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01765v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. D\'iaz, J. M. Alegre, I. I. Cuesta, E. Mart\'inez-Pa\~neda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-transmitter Multiple-receiver Wireless Power Transfer System Using an Exceptional Point of Degeneracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.10928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.10928v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robust transfer efficiency against the various operating conditions in a wireless power transfer system remains a fundamentally important challenge. This challenge becomes even more critical when transferring power to groups of inductively coupled receivers. We propose a method for efficient wireless power transfer to multiple receivers exploiting the concept of exceptional points of degeneracy (EPD) in a self-oscillating system. In previous studies based on PT symmetry, a receiver's operation has been divided into two strong and weak coupling regimes, and the power transfer efficiency is constant in the strong coupling regime when varying the coupling factor. Here, the concept of strong and weak coupling and constant power efficiency is extended to a system of multiple receivers that do not follow PT symmetry. The transmitter has saturable nonlinear gain and the EPD is analyzed when the system oscillates after reaching saturation. We show that the important feature to have a roughly constant power efficiency, independently of the positions of the receivers, is the existence of an EPD that separates the weak and strong regimes. Our proposed method demonstrates a system with less sensitivity to the coupling change than a conventional system without EPD when the receivers and their couplings to the transmitter are not necessarily identical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.10928v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Mohseni, Amin Hakimi, Alireza Nikzamir, Hung Cao, Filippo Capolino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nanoporous capacitive electrochemical ratchet for continuous ion separations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.00951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.00951v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Directed ion transport in liquid electrolyte solutions underlies many phenomena in Nature and industry. While Nature has devised structures that drive continuous ion flow without Faradaic redox reactions, artificial analogs do not exist. Here we report the first demonstration of an ion pump that drives aqueous ions against a force using a capacitive ratchet mechanism that does not require redox reactions. Modulation of an electric potential between thin metallic layers on either face of a nanoporous alumina wafer immersed in solution resulted in persistent voltages and ionic currents. This occurs due to the non-linear capacitive nature of electric double layers, whose repeated charging and discharging sustains a continuous ion flux. Ratchet driven electrodialysis was demonstrated reaching a 50% decrease in the conductivity of the solution in a dilution cell. These ratchet-based ion pumps can enable continuous desalination and selective ion separation using an electrically powered device with no moving parts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.00951v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rylan Kautz, Alon Herman, Ethan J. Heffernan, Keren Shushan Alshochat, Eden Grossman, Rahul Saxena, Camila Mu\~net\'on, David Larson, Joel W. Ager III, Francesca M. Toma, Shane Ardo, Gideon Segev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lateral Contrast Enhancement in Tomographic Volumetric 3D-Printing via Binary Photoinhibition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.13941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.13941v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tomographic volumetric 3D-printing (TVP) utilizes a nonlinear photoresponse of polymer precursor to cure all points in a three-dimensional (3D) object in parallel. A key challenge in TVP is to build up dose contrast between in-part and out-of-part points in a lateral plane, which relies on coordinated illumination from various projecting angles. This challenge has mainly been tackled by projection optimization. Here we show that designing material responses to photo-excitation can be a more effective way of addressing this challenge. By introducing a secondary photo-inhibitory species that reacts to external ultraviolet (UV) stimulus, we create a binary photoinhibition (BPI) system that greatly enhances the achievable dose contrast in a lateral plane. We first show that, in theory, combining dose subtraction with sufficient projection angles can guarantee an exact mathematical reconstruction of any greyscale design. We then propose a theoretical framework for BPI, in which a single stationary state with swappable stability can be used to realize dose subtraction. We use oxygen-lophyl radical pair as an approximation to show improvements in print quality enabled by enhanced dose contrast. In situ shadowgraphy shows that BPI improves the lateral patterning with various geometric features, creating differentiable changes in refractive index within 54 um or less. We show qualitative improvements in surface features and internal hollowness in physical prints. The direct impacts of UV light on the formation of positive and negative features on vertical and lateral planes of 5 workpieces are analyzed quantitatively. We conclude that introducing BPI with UV irradiation grants us direct control over the formation of negative features on the lateral plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.13941v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Wang, Weichao Sun Hossein Safari, S. Kaveh Hedayati, Jadze P. C. Narag, Thor D. V. Christiansen, Adrian A. Schiefler, Henning O. S{\o}rensen, Jeppe R. Frisvad, Kristoffer Almdal, Aminul Islam, Yi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inorganic electrochromic metasurface in the visible</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11705v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Colour printing based on metallic or dielectric nanostructures has revolutionized colour science due to its unprecedented subwavelength resolution. Evidently, the evolution towards the active control of such structural colours with smart materials is in progress for real applications. Here we experimentally demonstrate a large colour gamut with high intensity and purity, as well as its switching on and off based solely on tungsten trioxide (WO3) cylindrical resonators. The strong resonances in the visible spectral range in these WO3 metasurfaces can be reversibly switched on and off due to its electrochromism by applying alternating voltages of +2.0 V and -0.3 V. Our approach opens up possibilities for the functional diversification of commercial smart windows, as well as the development of new display technologies in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11705v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yohan Lee, Jonas Herbig, Serkan Arslan, Dominik Ludescher, Monika Ubl, Andreas Georg, Mario Hentschel, Harald Giessen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
