<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.app-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph</link>
    <description>physics.app-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 05:01:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Monochromatic Electron Emission from Graphene-Insulator-Semiconductor-Structured Electron Source Utilizing Interference Efficets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The graphene-insulator-semiconductor-structured electron source has garnered significant attention due to its high electron emission efficiency and highly monochromatic electron emission. Graphene, with its c-axis orientation and well-defined interlayer spacing, exhibits electron interference effects that can influence the properties of emitted electrons. In this work, motion of an electron wave packet is numerically calculated to discuss the energy spread of the zero-order and first-order diffracted electron waves by mono- and multilayer graphene. It is found that the effects of multiple reflections of electron between the layers broaden the energy spread especially for the incident energy of 13.4 eV, and that highly monochromatic electron emission can be achieved by using diffracted electron wave with a small aperture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02330v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takao Koichi, Shogo Kawashima, Hiroshi Miyake, Satoshi Abo, Fujio Wakaya, Masayoshi Nagao, Katsuhisa Murakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adjustable Low-Cost Highly Sensitive Microwave Oscillator Sensor for Liquid Level Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores the implementation of a low-cost high-precision microwave oscillator sensor with an adjustable input resistance to enhance its limit of detection (LoD). To achieve this, we introduce a \textit{Z$_{2}$} branch in the input network, comprising a transmission line, a capacitor (\textit{C$_{B}$}) and a resistor (\textit{R$_{V}$}). The sensor is tested with eight different liquids with different dielectric constants, including water, IV fluid, milk, ethanol, acetone, petrol, olive oil, and Vaseline. By fine-tuning the \textit{Z$_{2}$} branch, a clear relationship is found between $\varepsilon_{r}$ of materials and R$_{V}$.Our experimental results demonstrate outstanding characteristics, including remarkable linearity (nonlinearity &lt; 2.44\%), high accuracy with an average sensitivity of 21 kHz/$\mu$m, and an excellent limit of detection (LoD &lt; 0.05 mm). The sensor also exhibits good stability across a range of liquid temperatures and shows robust and repeatable behavior. Considering the strong absorption of microwave energy in liquids with high dielectric constants, this oscillator sensor is a superior choice over capacitive sensors for such applications. We validate the performance of the oscillator sensor using water as a representative liquid. Additionally, we substantiate the sensor's improvement through both experimental results and theoretical analysis. Its advantages, including affordability, compatibility with CMOS and MEMS technologies, and ease of fabrication, make it an excellent choice for small-scale liquid detection applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02724v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mojtaba Joodaki, Mehrdad Jafarian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In situ 2D visualization of hydrogen entry into Zn-coated steels in NaCl solutions: Roles of Zn dissolution and potential distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18362v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The hydrogen entry behavior of a partially Zn-coated steel sheet in NaCl solutions was investigated employing a polyaniline-based hydrogenochromic sensor, electrochemical hydrogen permeation tests, and potential measurements using a scanning Kelvin probe. While the Zn coating mitigated corrosion of the steel substrate, it simultaneously accelerated the hydrogen entry. The hydrogen entry occurred at the bare steel surface regions exposed to the NaCl solution, with the hydrogen flux exhibiting non-uniform distribution: higher near the dissolving Zn coating. While no significant differences in Zn dissolution behavior or galvanic current were observed between 0.1 and 0.01 M NaCl solutions, the total hydrogen flux decreased with decreasing Cl ion concentration. This reduction was attributed to a potential gradient induced by differences in electrolyte conductivity. The results demonstrate that potential distribution, rather than galvanic current, is a dominant factor influencing hydrogen entry under the investigated conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18362v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Kakinuma, Saya Ajito, Koki Okumura, Makoto Akahoshi, Yu Takabatake, Tomohiko Omura, Motomichi Koyama, Eiji Akiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear spin-free 70Ge/28Si70Ge quantum well heterostructures grown on industrial SiGe-buffered wafers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01916v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The coherence of hole spin qubits in germanium planar heterostructures is limited by the hyperfine coupling to the nuclear spin bath due to 29Si and 73Ge isotopes. Thus, removing these nuclear spin-full isotopes is essential to extend the hyperfine-limited coherence times needed to implement robust quantum processors. This work demonstrates the epitaxial growth of device-grade nuclear spin-free 70Ge/28Si70Ge heterostructures on industrial SiGe buffers while minimizing the amounts of highly purified 70GeH4 and 28SiH4 used. The obtained 70Ge/28Si70Ge heterostructures exhibit a dislocation density of 5.3 x 10e6 cm-2 and an isotopic purity exceeding 99.99%, with carbon and oxygen impurities below the detection sensitivity, as revealed by atom probe tomography. Magnetotransport measurements on gated Hall bars demonstrate effective gate control of hole density in nuclear spin-free quantum wells. Negative threshold gate voltages confirm the absence of intentional doping in the wells, while Hall and Shubnikov-de Haas analyses yield consistent carrier densities (1.4 x 10e11 cm-2) and high mobilities (2.4 x 10e5 cm2/Vs). Mobility trends reveal interfacetrap- limited scattering and percolation concentration below 7 x 10e10 cm-2. These analyses, along with atomic-level studies, confirm the high quality of epitaxial 70Ge/28Si70Ge heterostructures and their relevance as a platform for long-coherence spin qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01916v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Daoust, N. Rotaru, D. Biswas, S. Koelling, E. Rahier, A. Dub\'e-Valade, P. Del Vecchio, M. S. Edwards, M. Tanvir, E. Sajadi, J. Salfi, O. Moutanabbir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication and characterization of high-Q silicon nitride membrane resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02166v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Silicon nitride membranes are a powerful and ubiquitous optomechanical resonator technology, enabling high mechanical Q, low optical loss, and enhanced optomechanical coupling via a panoply of strain-, phononic-, and photonic-crystal engineering techniques. Fabrication and characterization of silicon nitride membranes has become a form of tacit knowledge in optomechanics research groups. Here we present a video run-through of the design, fabrication, and characterization of a contemporary silicon nitride membrane resonator (specifically, a centimeter-scale Si3N4 nanoribbon supporting $Q&gt;10^8$ torsion modes). Our tutorial can serve as a starting point or refresher for practitioners in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02166v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3791/68706</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Vis. Exp. (222), e68706, (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Atkin D. Hyatt, Oscar A. Flores, Aman R. Agrawal, Charles A. Condos, Dalziel J. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Spin Coating: Homogeneous All-Inorganic Perovskite Films via High-Pressure Recrystallization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02177v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Metal halide perovskites are promising materials for optoelectronic applications owing to their outstanding optical and electronic properties. Among them, all-inorganic perovskites such as CsPbBr$_3$ offer superior thermal and chemical stability. However, obtaining high-quality CsPbBr$_3$ thin films via solution processing remains challenging due to the precursor's low solubility, and current additive or solvent engineering strategies are often complex and poorly reproducible. High-pressure recrystallization has recently emerged as a promising route to improve film quality, yet its impact on film properties remains insufficiently explored. Here, we systematically investigate the morphological, structural, and optical properties of CsPbBr$_3$ thin films prepared by high-pressure recrystallization, in comparison with standard non-recrystallized films. Optimized recrystallization at 300 bar produces smooth, pinhole-free, single-phase 3D perovskite layers with sub-nanometer roughness, while the film thickness is precisely tunable via precursor concentration. The process enhances both grain and crystallite sizes, leading to amplified spontaneous emission with a reduced excitation threshold and improved photostability. Temperature-dependent X-ray diffraction further reveals the orthorhombic--tetragonal--cubic phase transition, consistent with single-crystal behavior. This study provides fundamental insights into pressure-driven recrystallization and establishes a reproducible, scalable approach for fabricating high-quality CsPbBr$_3$ films for optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02177v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trong Tam Nguyen, Jos\'e Penuelas, Aziz Benamrouche, C\'eline Chevalier, Thi Kim Anh Hoang, Ga\"elle Tripp\'e-Allard, Elsa Cassette, Brice Devif, Emmanuel Drouard, Emmanuelle Deleporte, Hong Hanh Mai, Abdelaziz Bouazizi, Christian Seassal, Hai Son Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanofluidic logic based on chiral skyrmion flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Particle-like chiral magnetic skyrmions can flow in nanotracks and behave like chiral fluids. Using interacting flows to perform logical operations is an important topic in microfluidics and nanofluidics. Here, we report a basic nanofluidic logic computing system based on chiral magnetic skyrmions flowing in parallel pipelines connected by an H-shaped junction. The flow behaviors could be manipulated by adjusting the spin polarization angle, which controls the intrinsic skyrmion Hall angle. We demonstrate that within certain range of the spin polarization angle, fully developed skyrmion flows could lead to fluidic logical operations, which significantly reduce the complexity of skyrmion logic as there is no need for deterministic creation, precise control, and detection of a single isolated skyrmion. Our results suggest that the chiral flow behaviors of magnetic quasiparticles may offer possibilities for spintronic and nanofluidic functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02195v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1073/pnas.2506204122</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 122, e2506204122 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xichao Zhang, Jing Xia, Yan Zhou, Guoping Zhao, Xiaoxi Liu, Yongbing Xu, Masahito Mochizuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal filtered quantum sensing with the nitrogen-vacancy center in diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nitrogen vacancy centers in diamond are among the leading solid state quantum platforms, offering exceptional spatial resolution and sensitivity for applications such as magnetic field sensing, thermometry, and bioimaging. However, in high background environments,such as those encountered in in vitro diagnostics, the performance of NV based sensors can be compromised by strong background fluorescence, particularly from substrates such as nitrocellulose. In this work, we analytically and experimentally investigate the use of pulsed laser excitation combined with time gating techniques to suppress background fluorescence and enhance the signal to noise ratio in NV based quantum sensing, with an emphasis on spin enhanced biosensing. Through experimental studies using mixed ensembles of silicon vacancy and NV centers in bulk diamond, as well as fluorescent nanodiamonds on NC substrates, we demonstrate significant improvements in NV spin resonance visibility, demonstrated by an increase of the SNR by up to 4x, and a resulting measurement time reduction by 16x. The presented technique and results here can help significantly increase the readout efficiency and speed in future applications of NV centers in high background environments, such as in IVD, where the NV centers are used as a fluorescent label for biomolecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02369v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Boehm, Yan Liu, Chengliang Yue, Xianqi Dong, Huaxue Zhou, Dong Wu, E Wu, Renfu Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic Investigation of Crosstalk in Bent Microstrip Lines with Partial and Apertured Shielding: Simulations and Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26908v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents an electromagnetic investigation of the crosstalk between two bent microstrip lines (MLs) separated by a perforated planar shield. As an extension of our previous study, the effects of various discontinuities in either the MLs or the shield along the coupling path are analyzed through numerical simulations and validated by measurements. The underlying electromagnetic mechanisms are also discussed. Furthermore, multimodal wave theory in a rectangular waveguide is applied to predict crosstalk behavior when the shield contains an aperture. This study aims to conceptually elucidate complex crosstalk phenomena that are difficult to model using circuit theory, and successful predictions of crosstalk behavior are presented for different problem cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26908v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Eskandari, Mojtaba Joodaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-Dimensional Electrostatic and Quantum-Confinement Modeling of Silicon Nanowire Double Quantum Dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07831v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a three-dimensional simulation study of silicon nanowire double quantum dots (DQDs) with leads at T = 2 K, which extends beyond traditional effective mass or quasi-1D and quasi-2D approaches typically applied to bulk or planar geometries. A 3-D Poisson solver is self-consistently coupled to 2-D Schrodinger along slices normal to transport (width * thickness) to obtain spatially varying subbands and wavefunctions at T = 2 K. The slice approximation is justified by the large aspect ratio (Ltot/W &gt; 20) and by the small (&lt; 1.2 percent) wavefunction variation observed along the transport direction. The resulting effective conduction-band profile is imported into a full-wave, open-boundary Schrodinger solver to compute the transmission spectrum T(E), and the tunnel coupling (tc) is evaluated from the bonding and antibonding splitting of the first two resonances in T(E). The simulations show that narrow dots (W = 5 nm) provide strong confinement and robust single-electron localization but require higher plunger-gate voltage, whereas wider dots (W = 20 nm) load electrons at lower bias but form shallower, more delocalized states. The tunnel coupling decreases as the dot width and length are increased, due to the reduced wavefunction overlap between the dots, and saturates once W &gt; 2LPG, when longitudinal confinement is dominated by the plunger gate length. The simulated tunnel coupling trend agrees with experimental data reported for the Si DQD device.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07831v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilesh Pandey, Dipanjan Basu, Leonard F Register, Sanjay K Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
