<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.app-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph</link>
    <description>physics.app-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 02:36:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Coupled Microelectromechanical Drum Resonators for Reservoir Computing via Sideband Pumped Phonon-Cavity Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reservoir computing is a bio-inspired machine learning paradigm that exploits the intrinsic dynamics of nonlinear systems with fading memory for efficient temporal information processing. Microelectromechanical resonators offer a promising platform for reservoir computing as they inherently possess the requisite nonlinear and temporal properties while also facilitating the integration of sensing and computing within a single platform. In this work, we experimentally demonstrate a physical reservoir computing platform based on two capacitively coupled drum resonators, operating in the MHz frequency regime. Taking advantage of the concept of phonon-cavity electromechanics, a pump tone is applied at the sideband of the phonon cavity while probing one of the coupled modes, analogous to optomechanical systems, thereby creating nonlinear dynamics in energy transfer between the two resonators. Physical reservoir computing is implemented by exploiting the nonlinear response induced through pump amplitude modulation in combination with a time-delay feedback loop, and the performance is evaluated using both parity and Normalized Auto-Regressive Moving Average benchmarks. This work demonstrates a compact microelectromechanical platform for the integration of sensing and reservoir computing. Moreover, the sideband pumping scheme can further extend conventional single resonator reservoir computing to a multimode architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02617v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theresa Farah, Lo\"ic Flis, Pierre Laly, Guo-En Chang, Jun-Yu Ou, Yoshishige Tsuchiya, Yan Pennec, Bahram Djafari-Rouhani, Xin Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic Analogy of Quantum Baldin Sum Rule for Optimal Causal Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mass law is a cornerstone in predicting sound transmission loss, yet it neglects the constraints of causal dispersion. Current causality-based theories, such as the Rozanov limit, are applicable only to one-port reflective absorbers. Here, we derive a universal sum rule governing causal scattering in acoustic systems, establishing a rigorous analogy to the Baldin sum rule in quantum field theory. This relation reveals that the integral of the extinction cross-section is fundamentally locked by the scatterer's static effective mass and stiffness, which is validated numerically using seminal examples of underwater metamaterials. Furthermore, the proposed sum rule predicts an optimal condition for an anomalously broadened transmission loss bandwidth, as experimentally observed through the spectral shaping effect of an acoustic Fano resonator. Our findings open up an unexplored avenue for enhancing the scattering bandwidth of passive metamaterials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02630v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sichao Qu, Zixiong Yu, Erqian Dong, Min Yang, Nicholas X. Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect Landscape Engineering Suppresses Helium Damage in Ceramics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02946v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Helium accumulation in structural ceramics used in nuclear, fusion, and aerospace systems causes swelling, cracking, and early failure, yet controlling this damage has remained elusive. Here, we introduce defect landscape engineering, the deliberate creation of vacancy clusters prior to helium exposure, as a general strategy to suppress helium-induced degradation. Using {\alpha}-SiC as a model, we combine advanced microscopy, strain mapping, helium depth profiling, positron annihilation spectroscopy, and atomistic simulations to demonstrate that tailored pre-damage transforms helium defect evolution. Instead of forming extended platelets and nanocracks, helium is trapped in stable, uniformly dispersed nanobubbles. Simulations reveal that small vacancy clusters act as dual-function sinks for irradiation-induced interstitials and preferential helium traps, fundamentally altering cascade recombination dynamics. This mechanism is composition-independent and scalable, offering a new design principle for radiation-tolerant ceramics across carbides, nitrides, and oxides. By viewing defect control as a tunable parameter instead of a fixed material property, this work outlines a possible design route toward enhanced radiation tolerance in ceramics used in extreme environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02946v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nabil Daghbouj, Ahmed Tamer AlMotasem, Bingsheng Li, Vladimir Krsjak, Jan Ducho\v{n}, Fang. Ge, Maceig Oskar Liedke, Andreas Wagner, Mohamed Bensalem, Fateh Bahadur, Frans Munnik, Miroslav Karlik, Anna Mackov\'a, Tomas Polcar, William J. Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous Collision of Exceptional Points on Nonorientable Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02442v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Band degeneracies, ranging from Hermitian Dirac points to non-Hermitian exceptional points (EPs), play a central role in topological phase transitions. Beyond the topology of individual degeneracies, their mutual interactions yield richer phenomena. A representative example is the anomalous non-annihilating collision of pairwise-created degeneracies, previously believed to occur only in non-Abelian multiband systems. Here, we theoretically reveal and experimentally demonstrate that such an anomalous collision can emerge even in a simple two-band system without non-Abelian nature. In a two-dimensional non-Hermitian lattice whose Brillouin zone forms a nonorientable Klein bottle, two EPs with opposite topological charges, pairwise created from a hybrid point, merge into a new vortex point upon re-encounter, instead of annihilating. Remarkably, the hybrid point is a defective degeneracy featuring no eigenenergy braiding, whereas the vortex point is a non-defective degeneracy yet exhibits nontrivial eigenenergy braiding. This process manifests a non-Hermitian phase transition from a gapped phase to a gapless phase, a scenario that we directly observe in a hybrid-dimensional acoustic lattice via momentum-resolved band braid and Berry phase measurements. Our findings identify nonorientability as a new arena for engineering band degeneracies and topological phases, and pave the way for experimentally exploring the interplay between exceptional and nonorientable topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02442v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weijia Wang, Qicheng Zhang, Kun Zhang, Shuaishuai Tong, Chunyin Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Synchronization of Driven Self-Oscillators: Modeling and Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02584v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Synchronization of self-sustained oscillators under fixed-frequency and amplitude forcing is well understood, but how time-varying forcing mangles phase locking has been much less explored. Theory predicts that slow, deterministic modulation of the drive amplitude or frequency can lead to a peculiar synchronization regime characterized by intermittent locking of the oscillation phase beyond the Arnold-tongue boundaries associated with fixed harmonic forcing. We test these predictions in a controllable aeroacoustic self oscillator, i.e, a whistle, that exhibits a robust limit cycle and is subject to external acoustic forcing with programmable frequency and amplitude modulation. Under both slowly varying frequency or amplitude of the forcing, three regimes are observed: (i) strict synchronization (ii) intermittent synchronization, characterized by alternating phase locking and brief phase slip episodes and (iii) no synchronization, with regular phase slips. Particularly in strict synchronization regime, the phase of the oscillator will follow arbitrary slowly-varying drive phase and under amplitude modulation its amplitude fluctuations are strongly suppressed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02584v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenwei Xu, Ulrich Kuhl, Nicolas Noiray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-throughput, high-brightness, ultrashort 90 keV electrons at 40 kHz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02597v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radiofrequency-compressed keV electron sources for ultrafast electron diffraction (UED) face competing demands: short pulses require low charge, yet weak scatterers demand high flux; high repetition rates enable signal averaging, yet most systems operate $\lesssim$1 kHz with low detection efficiency. Here, we demonstrate a 90 keV DC-RF source operating at 40 kHz with direct electron detection that address these challenges simultaneously. THz streaking retrieves compressed pulse durations of 97 $\pm$ 3 fs (FWHM) at 370 aC and 114 $\pm$ 47 fs (FWHM) at 2.8 fC. Long-term $t_0$ timing drifts, characterized independently both by convolution analysis of compression data and direct THz streaking measurements, lie between 65 - 95 fs (FWHM), among the lowest reported for RF-based systems. At low charge (17 aC), we report an intrinsic pulse duration of 56 fs (FWHM) from comparison of simulations to measured compression data, among the shortest for keV UED at $&gt;$16 aC. Moreover, 2.8 fC bunches, combined with 40 kHz repetition rate and direct detection, produce a detectable normalized throughput that is one (three-to-four) orders of magnitude higher than existing keV (MeV) sources. This enables practical UED studies of weakly scattering samples and processes previously impractical due to low cross-sections and long acquisition times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02597v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Amini, T. C. H. de Raadt, J. G. H. Franssen, B. Siwick, O. J. Luiten, A. Ryabov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact resistance and interfacial engineering: Advances in high-performance 2D-TMD based devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The development of advanced electronic devices is contingent upon sustainable material development and pioneering research breakthroughs. Traditional semiconductor-based electronic technology faces constraints in material thickness scaling and energy efficiency. Atomically thin two-dimensional (2D) transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) have emerged as promising candidates for next-generation nanoelectronics and optoelectronic applications, boasting high electron mobility, mechanical strength, and a customizable band gap. Despite these merits, the Fermi level pinning effect introduces uncontrollable Schottky barriers at metal-2D-TMD contacts, challenging prediction through the Schottky-Mott rule. These barriers fundamentally lead to elevated contact resistance and limited current-delivery capability, impeding the enhancement of 2D-TMD transistor and integrated circuit properties. In this review, we succinctly outline the Fermi pinning effect mechanism and peculiar contact resistance behavior at metal/2D-TMD interfaces. Subsequently, highlights on the recent advances in overcoming contact resistance in 2D-TMDs devices, encompassing interface interaction and hybridization, van der Waals (vdW) contacts, prefabricated metal transfer and charge-transfer doping will be addressed. Finally, the discussion extends to challenges and offers insights into future developmental prospects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02628v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.pmatsci.2024.101390</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Progress in Materials Science 148,101390(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiongfang Liu, Kaijian Xing, Chi Sin Tang, Shuo Sun, Pan Chen, Dong-Chen Qi, Mark B. H. Breese, Michael S. Fuhrer, Andrew T. S. Wee, Xinmao Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermally adaptive textile inspired by morpho butterfly for all-season comfort and visible aesthetics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02774v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A longstanding challenge in personal thermal management has been transitioning from static, appearance-limited passive radiative cooling (PDRC) materials to systems that are both dynamically adaptive and visually versatile. The central hurdle remains the inherent compromise between color saturation and cooling power. Inspired by organisms such as butterflies, which decouple structural color from thermal function, we present a smart textile that seamlessly merges a dynamic thermochromic layer with static photonic crystals (PCs). This design enables the solar reflectance to be autonomously switched-from approximately 0.6 in the colored state for heating to about 0.9 in the high-reflectance state for cooling. Consequently, outdoor experiments validated substantial temperature regulation: the fabric achieves a surface temperature reduction of 3-4 {\deg}C in summer and a heating difference of &lt;1 {\deg}C in winter compared to commercial reference materials, all while maintaining high-saturation colors. This dual-mode operation offers a viable pathway for achieving adaptive, aesthetic, and energy-free thermal comfort.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02774v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuowen Xie, Yan Wang, Ting-Ting Li, Wangkai Jiang, Honglei Cai, Jun Zhang, Hui Wang, Jianchen Hu, Ke-Qin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonseparability as Time-Averaged Dynamic States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02977v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonseparability - multipartite states that cannot be factorized - is one of the most striking features of quantum mechanics, as it gives rise to entanglement and non-causal correlations. In quantum computing, it also contributes directly to the computational advantage of quantum computers over its digital counterparts. In this work, we introduce a simple mechanism that frames nonseparability as a time-averaged manifestation of an underlying oscillatory process within state space. The central idea is the inclusion of auxiliary angular frequencies that modulate the temporal evolution of composite states. These additional dynamical degrees of freedom act as coherence channels through which nonseparability is mediated. While the proposed formalism could eventually serve as an alternative theoretical handle on the mechanisms of quantum entanglement, its greater significance lies in opening practical routes for simulating multipartite entanglement in controlled classical wave systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02977v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Padlewski, Tim Tuuva, Benjamin Apffel, Herv\'e Lissek, Romain Fleury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shubnikov-de Haas oscillations of two-dimensional electron gases in AlYN/GaN and AlScN/GaN heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03022v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: AlYN and AlScN have recently emerged as promising nitride materials that can be integrated with GaN to form two-dimensional electron gases (2DEGs) at heterojunctions. Electron transport properties in these heterostructures have been enhanced through careful design and optimization of epitaxial growth conditions. In this work, we report for the first time Shubnikov-de Haas (SdH) oscillations of 2DEGs in AlYN/GaN and AlScN/GaN heterostructures, grown by metal-organic chemical vapor deposition. SdH oscillations provide direct access to key 2DEG parameters at the Fermi level: (1) carrier density, (2) electron effective mass (m* ~ 0.24 me for AlYN/GaN and m* ~ 0.25 me for AlScN/GaN), and (3) quantum scattering time (~ 68 fs for AlYN/GaN and ~ 70 fs for AlScN/GaN). These measurements of fundamental transport properties provide critical insights for advancing emerging nitride semiconductors for future high-frequency and power electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03022v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Hsin Chen, Thai-Son Nguyen, Isabel Streicher, Jimy Encomendero, Stefano Leone, Huili Grace Xing, Debdeep Jena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge transport in liquid-crystalline phthalocyanine-based thin-film transistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03058v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate a series of liquid-crystalline phthalocyanines (metal-free and Cu, Zn, Ni, Co complexes) by correlating their vibrational signatures with their electronic performance in organic thin-film transistors (OTFTs). Raman spectroscopy reveals metal-dependent distortions of the phthalocyanine macrocycle, reflected in systematic shifts of the C-N-C and M-N vibrational modes. When integrated into OTFTs, all compounds exhibit markedly enhanced current response under ultrahigh vacuum compared to an N2-rich environment, demonstrating that intrinsic charge transport is strongly suppressed by atmospheric species. Temperature-dependent measurements (100-300 K) show clear threshold-voltage shifts driven by deep interface and bulk traps, while all devices display thermally activated mobility with low activation energies (14-20 meV). These results highlight how mesomorphic order, metal coordination, and environmental conditions collectively govern charge transport in liquid-crystalline phthalocyanines, offering design guidelines for their use as orientable semiconducting materials in organic electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03058v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. B. Avila, Zuchong Yang, Ilknur Hatice Eryilmaz, Lilian Skokan, Leonardo N Furini, Andreas Ruediger, H. Bock, I. H. Bechtold, E. Orgiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open-Source Coil Matching Toolbox for Magnetic Stimulation and Other Electromagnetics (COMATOSE)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03224v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The coil in transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) determines the spatial shape of the electromagnetic field in the head, which structures are concurrently activated, and how focal stimulation is. Most of the readily available coils have been designed intuitively instead of systematic mathematical-physical optimization as there were no methods available at the time. Previous research however demonstrated that these coils are far from optimum, e.g., for pulse energy or efficiency, and leave substantial room for lots of improvements. Techniques for rigorous mathematical optimization have been developed but are only available to very few groups worldwide. This paper presents an open-source toolbox, COMATOSE, to change that situation and make these methods available to a wider community. It incorporates the fundamental formalisms and offers vector space decomposition as well as base mapping as an explicit forward method, which is computationally less demanding than iterative computational optimization but can also form the initial solution for a subsequent optimization run if desired.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03224v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Koehler, Stefan Goetz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Role of Color Temperature and Color Rendering Index of White-Light LEDs on the Theoretical Efficiency Limit of Indoor Photovoltaics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20811v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As the Internet of Things (IoT) continues to grow, the demand for sustainable indoor power sources is increasing. Indoor photovoltaics (IPVs), which are currently in development, present a renewable solution but need to be designed to match specific light sources. While previous studies have emphasized the role of white-light LED correlated color temperature (CCT) in determining IPV efficiency and optimum bandgap energy, the role of color rendering index (CRI) remains less understood. In this study, we employ detailed-balance calculations to assess the theoretical maximum efficiency and optimal bandgap energies of IPVs under commercial white-light LED irradiance varying in both CCT (2200 K to 6500 K) and CRI (70, 80, and 90). Our results confirm that lower CCTs indeed yield higher efficiencies and lower optimal bandgaps. However, contrary to prior assumptions that CRI has negligible impact on IPV material choice and performance, we demonstrate that high-CRI LEDs necessitate the use of materials with significantly lower bandgap energies for optimum efficiency due to the shift towards red in the higher CRI irradiance spectra. We also evaluate the performance of various IPVs at fixed bandgaps, revealing that while optimal IPV performance is achieved with wide-bandgap materials under lower CRI lighting, mature technologies like silicon and CdTe benefit from high-CRI illumination. These findings underscore the need to consider both CCT and CRI in the design, evaluation, and choice of IPVs for indoor IoT applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20811v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditi Sharma, Alexander A. Guaman, Jason A. R\"ohr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optically Switchable Fluorescence Enhancement at Critical Interparticle Distances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11541v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Plasmonic nanostructures provide electric field localization to be used as a fluorescence enhancement tool for the closely located fluorophores. However, metallic structures exhibit non-radiative energy transfer at close proximity, which suppresses the boost in the photoluminescence spectrum due to inhomogeneous medium. Compensation to non-radiative losses is fundamentally restricted, therefore defining the critical interparticle distances, where the fluorescence enhancement is detectable hold utmost importance for device applications. In this work, we numerically identified the critical interparticle distances of a metal nanoparticle (MNP) and quantum emitters (QEs) with angstrom resolution by analyzing the interplay between quantum yield and non-radiative decay. By engaging a collimated light application on silver nanoparticle (AgNP) placed at a critical distance, we simulated an active fluorescence enhancement switch yielding observable 7-fold increase in fluorescence intensity. The provided free space simulation includes the complete response of AgNP with retardation and higher order multi-polar effects for which the previous analytical works fall short. While the model bridges the absorption and emission spectra via corresponding Stokes shift values and presents a general approach for the interaction of QEs and MNPs in Rayleigh regime, it can be extended to Mie regime for larger QEs and can be modified for dielectric device environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11541v5</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adts.202501134</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advanced Theory and Simulations, Volume 8, Issue 9, Sep 2025, e01134</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arda Gulucu, Emre Ozan Polat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Ising to Potts: Physics-inspired Potts machines of coupled oscillators for low-energy sampling and combinatorial optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18379v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $q$-state Potts model is a fundamental model in statistical physics that generalizes the Ising model and plays a key role in the study of phase transitions, critical phenomena, complex systems, and combinatorial optimization. Sampling low-energy configurations of the $q$-state Potts model is essential to these studies, but it remains challenging. While physics-inspired dynamical sampling has been extensively explored for the Ising case ($q=2$) in the form of Ising machines, its generalization to general $q$-state Potts models remains largely unexplored. To fill this gap, we propose a class of physics-inspired dynamical samplers that directly target general $q$-state Potts models, which we refer to as the oscillator Potts machine (OPM). We show, through theoretical analysis and numerical experiments, that the OPM exhibits a systematic low-energy bias with respect to the underlying Potts energy landscape. Furthermore, we demonstrate, via phase perturbation analysis, that the OPM, as overdamped Langevin dynamics, can be realized with a network of self-sustaining oscillators, demonstrating that the OPM is naturally realizable in hardware using standard technology such as CMOS. We design a small-scale ring-oscillator circuit that implements a three-state OPM and validate its operation through transistor-level simulation. Leveraging the low-energy bias of the OPM for Potts models, we then apply it to large-scale max-$K$-cut problems by mapping these instances to $q$-state Potts Hamiltonians and compare its performance against established algorithms. Our results position the OPM as a promising, physically grounded dynamical system framework for multi-state sampling and combinatorial optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18379v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Cheng, Zongli Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design of Microlens Arrays for Thermal Imaging with Spintronic Poisson Bolometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12491v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Infrared (IR) detectors are widely used for their ability to sense thermal radiation. Recently, a room-temperature infrared detector known as the spintronic Poisson bolometer was introduced. Operating in a probabilistic regime governed by Poissonian counting statistics, it establishes a fundamentally different detection mechanism with the potential to beat conventional sensitivity limits. While offering fast digital readout, its sensitivity is currently limited by a small active area and array fill factor. In this work, we present design guidelines for spherical plano-convex microlens arrays that enhance light collection in spintronic Poisson bolometer arrays in the mid-wave infrared (MWIR). Guided by the simulations, we fabricate a microlens array sample to demonstrate that the chosen geometrical parameters are realistic and compatible with the fabrication process. A unique radiometric-stochastic model is used to quantify the resulting sensitivity improvements. Our work is the first systematic integration of microlens design with spintronic Poisson bolometer arrays, bridging microphotonics, spintronics, and thermal imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12491v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyi Yang, Leif Bauer, Zubin Jacob</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
