<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.app-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph</link>
    <description>physics.app-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.app-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 02:39:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The physics of cranberry bogs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The common New England sight of a cranberry bog presents a rich tapestry of fluid dynamics and soft matter phenomena. Here, we present four connected problems exploring the behavior of cranberries in their stages of harvest: the buoyant rise of a cranberry in a flooded bog, the stable floating configuration of a cranberry on the surface, the aggregation and interaction between many floating cranberries collected with a boom, and the piling of cranberries onto a truck for transportation. We model these phenomena from first principles and develop simple computational simulations of their collective behaviors. Additionally, we describe tabletop experiments to accompany these problems, either as in-class demonstrations or lab activities. Throughout, we draw connections to broader physical principles in soft condensed matter and fluids, allowing the real-world example of the cranberry bog to serve as a bridge between the undergraduate curriculum and topics in soft matter research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11593v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caroline M. Barotta, Jack-William Barotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second- and Third-Harmonic Backscatter Through a Bandstop Filter Using Defected Ground Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12087v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this brief, a novel harmonic-backscatter-rectifier (HBR) is introduced for simultaneous rectification and harmonic-based uplink. The proposed (HBR) employs a rectifier to generate both DC power and the harmonic carriers for backscattering communication, and a dual-band reconfigurable band-stop filter using defected ground structure(DGS) to modulate the second and third harmonics with low-power consumption and same input impedance at f0 all the time. As a proof of concept, an HBR prototype operating at 1.85 GHz was designed and experimented. An uplink data rate of 8Mbps (4Mbps x 2 ) was achieved when the HBR was fed with -10 dBm RF power, and the data modulation consumed less than 27.7pJ/bit. In addition, a passive harmonic tag was implemented with the proposed HBR and a low-power binary sequence generator, which demonstrated a continuous uplink of 12 kbps at -6 dBm RF power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12087v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TCSII.2023.3279100</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems II: Express Briefs, vol. 70, no. 11, pp. 4171-4175, Nov. 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dan Che, Changjun Liu, Haoming He, Zhi Hua Ren, Pengde Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A C-band microwave rectifier without capacitors for microwave power transmission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A microwave rectifier at 5.8 GHz without any capacitors is presented, which owns a measured MW-to-DC conversion efficiency of 68.1%. A harmonic rejection filter and a DC pass filter, which replace lumped capacitors in conventional microwave rectifiers, are applied to suppressing the harmonics produced by an HSMS-286 Schottky diode during rectifying. At the fundamental frequency, a microstrip impedance transformer which contains a shunt {\lambda}g/8 short-ended microstrip transmission line and two short series microstrip transmission lines are applied to compensating the imaginary impedance of the diode and matching the input impedance of the rectifier. The measured MW-to-DC conversion efficiency agrees well to the simulated results. The novel rectifier without any lumped passive elements may be applied for power transmission system at higher microwave frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12386v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/S1759078714000889</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Microwave and Wireless Technologies. 2015;7(6):623-628</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Biao Zhang, Wan Jiang, Chengyang Yu, Changjun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cryogenic enhancement of phononic four-wave mixing in AlScN/SiC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Surface acoustic wave platforms based on piezoelectric thin-film heterostructures provide sub-wavelength acoustic confinement, making them attractive for compact nonlinear phononic systems with applications including frequency conversion, parametric interactions, and nonlinear signal processing. Here, we investigate guided surface acoustic wave phononic four-wave mixing at gigahertz frequencies in an aluminum scandium nitride/4H-silicon carbide heterostructure operated at both room temperature (295 K) and cryogenic temperature (4 K). The 500 nm thick aluminum scandium nitride film supports guided Rayleigh and Sezawa modes with distinct displacement and strain energy density distributions, allowing a direct comparison of mode-dependent nonlinear behavior within the same device. Continuous-wave four-wave mixing measurements reveal an enhancement in the extracted modal nonlinear coefficient at 4 K relative to 295 K for both modes. In addition, the Rayleigh mode exhibits a modal nonlinearity approximately two orders of magnitude larger than that of the Sezawa mode across both temperature regimes. These results demonstrate that phononic four-wave mixing is strongly influenced by temperature, mode confinement, and strain localization while establishing aluminum scandium nitride on silicon carbide heterostructures as a promising platform for engineering enhanced nonlinear phononic interactions for future classical and quantum acoustic on-chip signal processing systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12418v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. K. Behera, B. Smith, X. Du, Y. Deng, M. Miller, N. Sagartz, M. Koppa, C. T. Harris, M. Lilly, R. H. Olsson III, M. Eichenfield, L. Hackett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sel-assembled Rhodium Nanoantennas for Single-Protein UV SERS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13043v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Surface-enhanced Raman scattering (SERS) provides critical insights into analyte structure, dynamic processes, and intermolecular interactions at the single-molecule level. By exploiting the hotspot formation in the vicinity of plasmonic structures, SERS constitutes an established tool for fundamental biological research, particularly for early-stage disease diagnostics. In this context, the DNA Origami technique, with its high addressability, enables both the assembly of plasmonic nanostructures with nanometric accuracy, and the deterministic placement of a single analyte molecule precisely at the generated hotspot within them. To date, most DNA Origami based nanoantennas rely on gold or silver nanoparticles (NPs), whose plasmonic resonances are confined to the visible spectrum, severely limiting their use in other spectral ranges. To extend the operating range, we have recently established a robust strategy for self-assembling programmable ultraviolet (UV)-plasmonic dimer antennas using rhodium nanocubes. Herein, we leverage this tailored architecture to systematically investigate its performance for single-molecule UV-SERS. We demonstrated how biofabricated Rh-dimers can be used to detect the characteristic SERS signal of a single streptavidin molecule linked at the dimer s gap. Our results are validated through polarization dependent measurements that yield the expected signal modulation depending on the the dimer orientation only for the DNA origami with a protein at the hotspot. This work establishes a highly sensitive and polarization-tunable UV-SERS platform, laying a solid foundation for label-free optical investigation and bio-spectroscopy of individual biomolecules in the UV spectral range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13043v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanqiu Zou, Nicco Corduri, Francesco DAmico, Karol Kolataj, Huaizhou Jin, Zhenrong Zheng, Yifan Yu, Jie Liu, Shukun Weng, Ali Douaki, Jerome Wenger, Shangzhong Jin, Guillermo Acuna, Denis Garoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of Packed-Bed Energy Storage Systems Based on a Second Law Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Packed-bed sensible heat storage (SHS) is important for balancing energy supply and demand over time. To improve the efficiency of a packed-bed SHS system through second law analysis (SLA), we developed macroscopic entropy and exergy transport equations for fluid flow and heat transfer in porous media based on microscopic transport equations. These equations enable us to identify where and how much exergy is destroyed. Using a packed-bed SHS system developed at the PROMES-CNRS laboratory as a test case, we demonstrated how to apply SLA to optimize an SHS system. Our analysis revealed that, in addition to exit and heat leakage losses at tank surfaces, thermal and solid conduction losses inside the tank significantly contribute to total loss in the studied SHS system. These internal losses occur close to the thermocline. However, their slower transport causes a delay in their emergence. The SLA suggests an optimal tank aspect ratio of D/H = 0.75, at which the total exergy loss coefficient reaches its minimum value when exit loss is not considered. As particle size decreases, the exergy loss coefficient also decreases due to enhanced heat transfer between the fluid and solid phases. The pressure loss for the studied SHS system is negligible. The SLA favors a truncated cone-shaped tank with a slightly larger upper surface. Through the SLA, the exergy loss coefficient is reduced from 4.9% for the original design to 4.1% for the optimized design. This study demonstrates that, when used in conjunction with energy analysis, the SLA is an effective tool for optimizing energy storage systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13329v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Jin, E. Makhova, A. Speerforck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Field Diamond Magnetometry Towards Tokamak Diagnostics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nitrogen vacancy centres (NVC) in diamond have been widely used for near-dc magnetometry. The intrinsic properties of diamonds make them potential candidates for tokamak fusion power diagnostics, where radiation-hard magnetometers will be essential for efficient control. An NVC magnetometer placed in a tokamak will need to operate within a $\geq$ 1 T magnetic field. In this work, we demonstrate fibre-coupled ensemble NVC optically detected magnetic resonance (ODMR) and magnetometry measurements at magnetic fields up to 1.2 T. Sensitivities of approximately 240 to 600 nT/$\sqrt{\textrm{Hz}}$ and 110 nT/$\sqrt{\textrm{Hz}}$ are achieved in a (10-150) Hz frequency range, for non-degenerate and near-$\langle$111$\rangle$ field alignments respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13413v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. M. Graham, C. J. Stephen, A. J. Newman, A. M. Edmonds, M. L. Markham, G. W. Morley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steady-State Exceptional Point Degeneracy and Sensitivity of Nonlinear Saturable Coupled Oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Near exceptional degenerate points in parameter space, coupled oscillator systems display enhanced sensitivity of their saturated steady-state (SS) oscillation frequencies to small changes in system parameters. Linear $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric systems made of two coupled resonators have exceptional point of degeneracy (EPD), around which square-root sensitivity is observed. However, realistic systems with gain are inherently saturable and nonlinear, thereby invalidating linear assumptions, and when $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetry is broken the coupled resonator system becomes unstable, hence it seems that the best working regime is to use such instability to make an SS-EPD-based oscillator. We study the saturated steady-state of a general system of two coupled oscillators with saturable nonlinear gain. Extending previous analyses, we find the steady-state oscillation frequency-gain pairs, and we analytically and numerically derive the sensitivity of the oscillation frequency to system's perturbations around a unique third-order degeneracy which corresponds to SS$\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry because it is the saturated gain that is symmetric to losses. In general, unlike linear systems, we find that at SS, the sensitivity of the oscillation frequency to exhibit linear, square-root, or cube-root dependence on small perturbations. We additionally study the energy and stability of each SS, and demonstrate the application and limitations of this analysis to coupled RLC circuits. We give a comprehensive outlook for exploiting exceptional degeneracy-enhanced sensitivity in nonlinear coupled oscillators and suggest the best operative conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13638v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Bradshaw, Amin Hakimi, Filippo Capolino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional FrBD friction models for rolling contact: extension to linear viscoelasticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13818v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper extends the distributed rolling contact FrBD framework to linear viscoelasticity by considering classic derivative Generalised Maxwell and Kelvin-Voigt rheological representations of the bristle element. With this modelling approach, the dynamics of the bristle, generated friction forces, and internal deformation states are described by a system of 2(n+1) hyperbolic partial differential equations (PDEs), which can capture complex relaxation phenomena originating from viscoelastic behaviours. By appropriately specifying the analytical expressions for the transport and rigid relative velocity, three distributed formulations of increasing complexity are introduced, which account for different levels of spin excitation. For the linear variants, well-posedness and passivity are analysed rigorously, showing that these properties hold for any physically meaningful parametrisation. Numerical experiments complement the theoretical results by illustrating steady-state characteristics and transient relaxation effects. The findings of this paper substantially advance the FrBD paradigm by enabling a unified and systematic treatment of linear viscoelasticity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13818v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Romano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-broadband Mid to Long-wave Infrared Spintronic Poisson Bolometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11733v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Infrared detectors have traditionally been divided into two fundamental classes, mid-wave (MWIR, 3-5 um) and long-wave (LWIR, 8-14 um). Integrating MWIR and LWIR within a single device is challenging due to distinct materials, cooling needs, and detection mechanisms, while such integration is critical for improved object recognition, temperature estimation, and environmental sensing. In this work, we demonstrate a Spintronic Poisson (SP) bolometer enabling room-temperature ultra-broadband sensing across 3-14 um. Unlike conventional bolometers that rely on continuous analog signals, the SP bolometer implements a Poisson-counting detection paradigm, encoding temperature in discrete stochastic events, which turns thermal noise from a limitation into the basis of the estimator itself. We fabricate the SP bolometer using a spintronic transduction layer integrated with a plasmonic nanoantenna array to enhance broadband infrared absorption. Using spintronic transduction, the device achieves the noise-equivalent temperature difference (NETD, thermal sensitivity metric) of 80-100 mK at 300 K, surpassing uncooled detectors and approaching cooled technologies. This work establishes a statistical detection paradigm for room-temperature infrared sensing with broad application potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11733v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed A. Mousa, Leif Bauer, Daien He, Sakshi Gupta, Shubhankar Jape, Utkarsh Singh, Bhagwati Prasad, Partha P. Mukherjee, Angshuman Deka, Zubin Jacob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated nano electro-optomechanical spiking neuron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11857v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neuromorphic computing offers a pathway toward energy-efficient processing of data, yet hardware platforms combining nanoscale integration and multimodal functionality remain scarce. Here we demonstrate a gallium-phosphide electro-optomechanical spiking neuron that integrates optical and electromechanical interfaces within a single nanostructure on a silicon photonic chip operating at telecommunication wavelengths (1550 nm) and exploiting a 3 gigahertz-frequency mechanical mode. Our device displays excitable dynamics, generating optical spikes at its output, as in the spiking activity of neurons and cardiac cells and defined by the calibrated all-or-none response to external perturbations. This dynamic is consistent with the saddle-node on invariant circle scenario and associated features are demonstrated including control of excitable threshold, temporal summation and refractory period. Our device compact footprint and its CMOS-compatible platform make it well suited for edge-computing applications requiring low latency and establish a foundation for versatile brain-inspired optomechanical computing and advanced on-chip optical pulse sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11857v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregorio Beltramo, R\'obert Horv\'ath, Gr\'egoire Beaudoin, Isabelle Sagnes, Sylvain Barbay, R\'emy Braive</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the long-range coupling for multi-dimensional metasurface multiplexer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11875v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Metasurface coupling constitutes a fundamental yet intricate electromagnetic interaction that occurs within a lattice of artificial subwavelength unit cells. Despite its prevalence, such coupling is typically ignored in conventional metasurface design frameworks due to the high characterization complexity, leading to suboptimal device performance. Here, we reveal a distinctive long-range coupling that exceeds an order of magnitude compared with the interaction range of evanescent waves, substantially enriching the metasurface design landscapes. This coupling exhibits pronounced graph topological features, and we design a graph neural network (GNN) to accurately abstract its inherent physics. Through strategic enhancement of the coupling effects, the discrete metasurface responses are transformed into continuous states, thereby unlocking diverse multiplexing channels. By further integrating the GNN into an inverse design agent, we tailor the multi-channel global response of metasurface to support simultaneous multiplexing across angle, frequency, and polarization domains. Experimentally, we demonstrate a compact metasurface multiplexer with eight independent channels, showcasing its potential for next-generation vehicular networks. This work establishes a new paradigm for highly integrated multifunctional metasurfaces, with promising prospects for high-density optical storage, information encryption, and high-capacity wireless communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11875v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ouling Wu, Chao Qian, Guangfeng You, Hongsheng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broadband silicon polarization beam splitter based on Floquet engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11955v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A broadband silicon polarization beam splitter (PBS) is proposed and experimentally demonstrated based on Floquet-engineered directional couplers. The total length of the coupling structure is 20 um . By periodically modulating the waveguide width of the directional couplers, the power exchange between the two waveguides for the transverse-electric (TE) mode is suppressed, whereas the power coupling for the transverse-magnetic (TM) mode is enhanced. The fabricated PBS exhibits polarization extinction ratios (PERs) &gt; 20 dB for both polarizations over a broad wavelength range of 1483 nm-1620 nm. Additionally, the measured insertion losses (ILs) are 0.15 dB and 1.2 dB at 1550 nm for TE and TM polarizations, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11955v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Ma, Yu Chen, Yunjie Li, Ciyuan Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wavefront Shaping of Ultrasound Vortex through the Human Skull Enabled by Binary Acoustic Metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12437v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrasound vortices have rapidly expanded their applications to areas like particle trapping, contactless manipulation, acoustic communications. In ultrasonic imaging and therapy involving bone tissues, these vortex beams offer intriguing possibilities but transmitting them through bone (especially the skull) poses challenges. Traditional acoustic lenses were engineered to rectify skull-induced beam aberration, and their capacity was limited to generating only static ultrasound fields within the brain. To overcome this constraint, our study presents a novel method for transcranially steering focused ultrasound vortex using 3D printed binary acoustic metasurfaces (BAMs) with a thickness of 0.8 {\lambda}. We tackled the challenge of skull-induced phase aberration by computing the phase distribution via a time reversal technique, which concurrently enabled the generation of a steerable focused vortex inside an ex vivo human skull by adjusting the operating frequency. Both numerical and simulations experiments were conducted to validate the capabilities of BAMs. Furthermore, we explored the generation of higher-order topological charge acoustic vortices within the brain utilizing the BAM. This development paves the way for designing cost-effective particle-trapping systems, facilitating clot manipulation, and applying acoustic-radiation forces and torques within or across bone structures, thus presenting a new frontier for potential biomedical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12437v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongtao Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixtenna: A Self-Biased Nonlinear Patch Antenna for Passive Third-Harmonic Radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12462v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A nonlinear rectangular patch antenna (RPA) is presented in which back-to-back Schottky diodes are embedded at high-field regions to enable passive, bias-free harmonic generation. The self-biased diodes introduce a power-dependent impedance that drives efficient frequency up-conversion and selective third-harmonic radiation. A tailored matching network enhances third-harmonic excitation and coupling while preserving radiation efficiency at the fundamental frequency. Analytical modeling combined with SPICE-assisted full-wave time-domain simulations predicts strong odd-harmonic content, and measurements on RPA prototypes employing SMS7630 diodes confirm these results. Simulated and measured S-parameters and far-field patterns at 925 MHz and 2.775 GHz show excellent agreement. The demonstrated approach establishes nonlinear loading as an effective mechanism for passive harmonic control in compact radiators, enabling frequency-agile and spectrum-efficient antenna systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12462v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yishai Brill, Yakir Hadad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale Prediction of Polymer Relaxation Dynamics via Computational and Data-Driven Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12942v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a multiscale modeling approach that integrates molecular dynamics simulations, machine learning, and the Elastically Collective Nonlinear Langevin Equation (ECNLE) theory to investigate the glass transition dynamics of polymer systems. The glass transition temperatures (Tg) of four representative polymers are estimated using simulations and machine learning model trained on experimental datasets. These predicted Tg values are used as inputs to the ECNLE theory to compute the temperature dependence of structural relaxation times and diffusion coefficients, and the dynamic fragility. The Tg values predicted from simulations show good quantitative agreement with experimental data. While machine learning tends to slightly overestimate Tg, the resulting dynamic fragility values remain close to experimental fragilities. Overall, ECNLE calculations using these inputs agree well with broadband dielectric spectroscopy results. Our integrated approach provides a practical and scalable tool for predicting the dynamic behavior of polymers, particularly in systems where experimental data are limited.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12942v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen T. T. Duyen, Ngo T. Que, Anh D. Phan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beta-AlGaO/Ga2O3 Tri-Gate MOSHEMT with 70GHz fT and 55GHz fmax</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13215v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report Beta-AlGaO/Ga2O3 tri-gate heterostructure MOSHEMTs incorporating a thin 5 nm Al2O3 gate oxide layer for improved gate control and reduced leakage. The devices were fabricated on AlGaO/GaO heterostructures grown by ozone MBE on Fe-doped Ga2O3 (010) substrates. The tri-gate MOSHEMTs, with 1 micron-wide fins and Lg=155 nm, exhibit a peak current-gain cut-off frequency fT=70 GHz and a power-gain cut-off frequency fMAX=55 GHz.The fT.L product of 10.85 GHz-micron is the highest among reported Ga2O3 FETs to date. The devices show Vth =-0.5 V, an on/off ratio 10^6 I=80 mA/mm, a peak gm=60 mS/mm, and a low gate leakage current of 10^(-10) mA/mm at Vgs=0.5 V. Passivation with a 100 nm ALD Al2O3 layer effectively removes DC/RF dispersion and maintains stable operation under pulsed IV and repeated RF measurements. These results demonstrate the potential of tri-gate AlGaO/GaO MOSHEMTs for next-generation high-frequency and high-power applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13215v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noor Jahan Nipu, Chinmoy Nath Saha, Uttam Singisetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotating Magnetocaloric Effect in First-order Phase Transition Material Gd5Si2Ge2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13239v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rotating magnetocaloric effect (RMCE) induced by self-demagnetization has been investigated in the giant magnetocaloric effect (GMCE) material Gd$_5$Si$_2$Ge$_2$. This shape-dependent effect had thus far only been reported in pure Gd, marking this as the first analysis of the effect in a sample with a magnetostructural first-order phase transition. By rotating the applied magnetic field vector while keeping its intensity constant, the demagnetizing field within a high-aspect ratio sample changes significantly, resulting in a RMCE. We characterize RMCE by determining the adiabatic temperature change ($\Delta T_{ad}^{rot}$) directly through temperature measurements, and the isothermal entropy change ($\Delta S_M^{rot}$) via magnetometry and magnetostatic simulations. We obtain a remarkable maximum $\Delta T_{ad}^{rot}$ of 1.77 K for a constant external field of 0.8 T, higher than that obtained under 1.0 T. The magnetostatic simulations not only corroborate the highly non-monotonous field-dependence of $|\Delta S_{M}^{rot}|$, which reaches 95\% of its maximum value at 0.8 T, 6.12 J K$^{-1}$ kg$^{-1}$ for the experimentally measured shape, but also estimate a 35\% increase in the maximum $|\Delta S_{M}^{rot}|$ up to 8.67 J K$^{-1}$ kg$^{-1}$ in a simulated shape with higher aspect ratio.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13239v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Almeida, Rodrigo Kiefe, Ricardo Moura Costa Pinto, Jo\~ao Sequeira Amaral, Kyle Dixon-Anderson, Yaroslav Mudryk, Jo\~ao Pedro Ara\'ujo, Jo\~ao Horta Belo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilayer Q-BIC-like Optical Filters with High Throughput Direct-Write Multilayer Lithography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13241v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multilayer metasurfaces provide substantially greater spectral design freedom than single-layer devices, yet their implementation in the visible and near-infrared remains limited by the complexity, cost, and low throughput of conventional nanofabrication. Here, we establish a recently proposed direct-write electron-beam lithography approach as a high-throughput fabrication platform for multilayer resonant metasurfaces, based on an antimony precursor that decomposes in situ into high-index antimony sulfide. This method eliminates deposition-etch cycles and reduces each layer to only two fabrication steps, enabling efficient realization of multilayer architectures. Using this platform, we demonstrate multilayer q-BIC-derived metasurfaces with independently tunable resonance wavelengths and linewidths, allowing the construction of compact multi-resonant filters with spectrally decoupled layers. We experimentally demonstrate three-layer devices supporting three resonances and show independent control of resonance wavelength and Q factor across layers. Leveraging this capability, we generate decorrelated filter arrays for compressive sensing and hyperspectral reconstruction, achieving sets of 9 and 36 filters with average absolute Pearson correlation coefficients of 0.11 and 0.21, surpassing prior metasurface and photonic-crystal implementations. These results establish a practical route toward scalable multilayer resonant metasurfaces for spectral filtering, on-chip spectroscopy, and computational imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13241v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Bilgehan Baspinar, Phillippe Pearson, Andrei Faraon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colossal low-field negative magnetoresistance in CaAl$_{2}$Si$_{2}$-type diluted magnetic semiconductors (Ba,K)(Cd,Mn)$_{2}$As$_{2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13339v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the magnetic and magnetotransport properties of the layered CaAl$_2$Si$_2$-type diluted magnetic semiconductor (Ba$_{1-x}$K$_x$)(Cd$_{1-y}$Mn$_y$)$_2$As$_2$ over a broad Mn (spin) substitution range of $0.05 \le y \le 0.5$. K substitution introduces hole carriers, whereas Mn provides local moments, resulting in bulk ferromagnetism with Curie temperatures up to $\sim 17$ K. Intrinsic magnetic ordering is further supported by an anomalous Hall contribution and a specific-heat anomaly near $T_{\mathrm{C}}$. A key performance feature is a colossal negative magnetoresistance: for heavily Mn-doped compositions ($y \ge 0.3$), $\mathrm{MR}=[\rho(H)-\rho(0)]/\rho(0)$ reaches approximately $-100\%$ at 2 K and nearly saturates at a relatively low magnetic field of $\sim 0.35\,\mathrm{T}$. The combination of soft ferromagnetism, strong spin-charge coupling, and low-field MR saturation highlights (Ba,K)(Cd,Mn)$_2$As$_2$ as a promising bulk platform for low-temperature magnetoresistive functionalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13339v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bijuan Chen, Zheng Deng, Changqing Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Reconstruction of Moving Contact Loads on an Elastic Half-Space Using Prescribed Surface Displacement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13478v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the elastic response of a two-dimensional semi-infinite medium subjected to a moving surface load with a prescribed displacement profile. As a fundamental step, we derive analytical Green's functions for the displacement and stress fields generated by a point load traveling at a constant velocity along the surface, explicitly incorporating elastodynamic effects through Mach number dependence. These moving-load solutions serve as building blocks for constructing more general loading scenarios via linear superposition. Based on Green's functions, an inverse problem is formulated to reconstruct the unknown surface traction responsible for a given surface displacement. The inverse analysis is performed through a Fourier-domain inversion with regularization, which enables a direct and computationally efficient determination of the contact pressure without iterative forward simulations. This framework is applied to a rigid wheel-ground contact problem, where the imposed displacement is dictated by the wheel geometry. The reconstructed surface traction exhibits a smooth, symmetric distribution within the contact region, while the resulting subsurface stress fields are obtained in closed analytical form and involve dilogarithm functions. The principal stress difference reveals characteristic spatial patterns similar to photoelastic fringes, and their asymmetry increases with the Mach number, reflecting the dynamic nature of the moving contact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13478v1</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satoshi Takada, Yosuke Mori, Shintaro Hokada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstration of a novel phase space painting method in a coupled lattice to mitigate space charge in high-intensity hadron beams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13517v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-turn charge-exchange injection is the primary method of creating high-intensity hadron beams in circular accelerators, and phase space painting during injection enables tailoring of the accumulated phase space distribution. A technique we call eigenpainting allows injection of particles into a single mode of a coupled ring, providing full four-dimensional control of the phase space distribution. Under ideal conditions, uniform eigenpainting generates a linear-force equilibrium distribution in the transverse plane, with zero volume in four-dimensional transverse phase space, even including space charge. We have implemented eigenpainting for the first time in the Spallation Neutron Source (SNS) Accumulator Ring. Injecting 8.8 $\mu$C of 800 MeV beam, we obtain a final ratio of intrinsic transverse emittances of $\approx$2.4. We analyze the effect of space charge on the final distribution through comparison of the reconstructed phase space to particle-in-cell simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13517v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas J. Evans, Austin Hoover, Timofey Gorlov, Vasiliy Morozov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the local solution of the DG predictor of the ADER-DG method for solving systems of ordinary differential equations and its applicability to systems of differential-algebraic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13908v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Improved local numerical solution for the ADER-DG numerical method with a local DG predictor for solving the initial value problem for a first-order ODE system is proposed. The improved local numerical solution demonstrates convergence orders of one higher than the convergence order of the local numerical solution of the original ADER-DG numerical method and has the property of continuity at grid nodes. Rigorous proofs of the approximation orders of the local numerical solution and the improved local numerical solution are presented. Obtaining the proposed improved local numerical solution does not require significant changes to the structure of the ADER-DG numerical method. Therefore, all conclusions regarding the convergence orders of the numerical solution at grid nodes, the resulting superconvergence, and the high stability of the ADER-DG numerical method remain unchanged. A wide range of applications of the ADER-DG numerical method is presented for solving specific initial value problems for ODE systems for a wide range of polynomial degrees. The obtained results provide strong confirmation for the developed rigorous theory. The improved local numerical solution is shown to exhibit both higher accuracy and improved smoothness and point-wise comparability. Empirical convergence orders of all individual numerical solutions were calculated for a wide range of error norms, which well agree with the expected convergence orders. The rigorous proof, based on the $\epsilon$-embedding method, of the applicability of the ADER-DG numerical method with a local DG predictor to solving DAE systems is presents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13908v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. S. Popov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated domain and crystallographic orientation mapping in uniaxial ferroelectric polycrystals by interferometric vector piezoresponse force microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13982v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ongoing advances in scanning probe microscopy techniques are continually expanding the possibilities for nanoscale characterization and correlated studies of functional materials. Here, we demonstrate how a recent extension of piezoresponse force microscopy (PFM), known as interferometric vector PFM, can be utilized for simultaneously mapping the local crystallographic orientations and the domain structure of distributed grains in uniaxial ferroelectric polycrystals. By shifting the laser beam position on the cantilever, direction-dependent piezoresponse signals are acquired analogous to classical vector PFM, but without the need to rotate the sample. Using polycrystalline ErMnO$_{3}$ as a model system, we demonstrate that the reconstructed piezoresponse vectors correlate one-to-one with the crystallographic orientations of the micrometer-sized grains, carrying grain-orientation and domain-related information. We establish a versatile approach for rapid, multimodal characterization of polycrystalline uniaxial ferroelectrics, enabling automated, high-throughput reconstruction of polarization and grain orientations with nanoscale precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13982v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruben Dragland, Jan Schulthei{\ss}, Ivan N. Ushakov, Roger Proksch, Dennis Meier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binding Energies of Charged Particles on Dielectric Surfaces in Liquid Nitrogen</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14035v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new approach for determining the binding energies of charged particles, such as ions and electrons, on dielectric surfaces in cryogenic liquids is introduced. The experimental technique outlined in this paper is employed to observe the buildup of charged particles on nonconductive surfaces using the electro-optic Kerr effect. The initial results of binding energy measurements on surfaces of deuterated tetraphenyl butadiene (dTPB)-coated and uncoated polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) in liquid nitrogen are presented. Under these conditions, the ions or electrons displayed binding energies of less than 1 meV. Although these findings were obtained in liquid nitrogen, the methodology is not limited to cryogenic liquids and is applicable to a wide variety of fluids, with no essential dependence on temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14035v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashok Timsina, Wolfgang Korsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersion relations of generalized one-dimensional phononic crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04549v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive method for determining {both exact and approximate} dispersion {relations} for one-dimensional {resonant phononic} crystals, applicable to a wide range of structures, regardless of their specific characteristics. This general framework employs a unified mathematical model, referred to as generalized {one-dimensional (1D) phononic crystal}, in which {different} types of {waves} and scatterers{/resonators} {can be} {considered} by adjusting certain parameters. The generalized {1D phononic crystal} consists of both a host {one-dimensional} homogeneous elastic {material} with physical properties represented in matrix form and an arbitrary set of scatterers {within the unit cell,} including resonators (discrete and continuous), small material inclusions, or variations in cross-sectional area. Based on general assumptions, {and imposing the periodicity and Bloch solutions} we develop a matrix-based algorithm utilizing the plane wave expansion method to derive the solution. Additionally, we propose an iterative procedure that provides analytical expressions for the first- and second-order terms, particularly useful in the context of weak scattering. The convergence conditions of the method are rigorously defined. The {efficiency of the} approach is demonstrated through several numerical examples, highlighting its versatility in different waveguide configurations and scattering scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04549v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1098/rspa.2025.0210</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. Royal Society A: Math., Phys. and Eng. Sci., 2025; 481 (2320): 20250210</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mario L\'azaro, Richard Wiltshaw, Richard V. Craster, Vicent Romero-Garc\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localized necking under global compression in two-scale metallic hierarchical solids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05498v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hierarchically structured cellular solids have attracted increasing attention for their superior mass-specific mechanical properties. Using a remeshing-based continuum finite element (FE) framework, we reveal that two-scale metallic hierarchical solids exhibit a distinct, localized deformation mode that involves necking and fracture of microscale tension members even at small global compressive strains (3-5%). The tensile failure is always preceded by plastic buckling of a complementary compression member. This combined necking-buckling (NB) mode critically underlies the collapse of hexagon-triangle (HTH) hierarchical lattices over a wide range of relative densities and length-scale ratios and is also seen in diamond-triangle (DTH) lattices. In lattices with very slender microscale members, necking is prevented by a competing failure mode that involves coordinated buckling (CB) of multiple members. Our custom remeshing FE framework is critical to resolve the localized large plastic strains, ductile failure, and complex local modes of deformation (including cusp formation) that are characteristic of the NB mode. A theoretical buckling analysis supports the inevitability of the NB and CB modes in HTH lattices. The occurrence of the NB mode has consequences for energy absorption by two-scale hierarchical solids, and hence influences their design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05498v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijmecsci.2025.110830</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Mechanical Sciences, September 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Naresh Chockalingam, Narayan K. Sundaram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero- to low-field J-spectroscopy with a diamond magnetometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05776v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report measurements of zero- to ultra-low-field nuclear magnetic resonance (ZULF NMR) signals at frequencies of a few hertz with a diamond-based magnetic sensor. The sensing diamond is a truncated pyramid with 0.18 mm height and a 0.5 mm x 0.5mm base. The minimum stand-off distance is &lt; 1 mm, and the sensor sensitivity is 13 pT/(Hz)^(1/2) at frequencies f above 5 Hz with 1/f-like behavior at lower frequencies. NMR signals were generated via signal amplification by reversible exchange (SABRE) parahydrogen-based hyperpolarization resulting in zero-field signals at 1.7 Hz and 3.4 Hz corresponding to the expected hetero-nuclear J-coupling pattern of acetonitrile. This work demonstrates a magnet-free platform for detecting chemically specific NMR signals at ultra-low frequencies paving the way for portable noninvasive diagnostics in microscopic sample volumes for biomedicine, industrial sensing through metal enclosures, and field-deployable quantum analytical devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05776v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhib Omar, Jingyan Xu, Raphael Kircher, Pouya Sharbati, Shaowen Zhang, Georgios Chatzidrosos, James Eills, Roman Picazo-Frutos, Dmitry Budker, Danila A. Barskiy, Arne Wickenbrock</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional FrBD friction models for rolling contact</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.06811v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper develops a comprehensive two-dimensional generalisation of the recently introduced Friction with Bristle Dynamics (FrBD) framework for rolling contact problems. The proposed formulation extends the one-dimensional FrBD model to accommodate simultaneous longitudinal and lateral slips, spin, and arbitrary transport kinematics over a finite contact region. The derivation combines a rheological representation of the bristle element with an analytical local sliding-friction law. By relying on an application of the Implicit Function Theorem, the notion of sliding velocity is then eliminated, and a fully dynamic friction model, driven solely by the rigid relative velocity, is obtained. Building upon this local model, three distributed formulations of increasing complexity are introduced, covering standard linear rolling contact, as well as linear and semilinear rolling in the presence of large spin slips. For the linear formulations, well-posedness, stability, and passivity properties are investigated under standard assumptions. In particular, the analysis reveals that the model preserves passivity under almost any parametrisation of practical interest. Numerical simulations illustrate steady-state action surfaces, transient relaxation phenomena, and the effect of time-varying normal loads. The results provide a unified and mathematically tractable friction model applicable to a broad class of rolling contact systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06811v4</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Romano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward a Circular Nanotechnology for Biofuels: Integrating Sustainable Synthesis, Recovery, and Performance Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17548v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This review exhaustively evaluates the role of nanomaterials across the synthesis, characterization and application stages of biofuel systems. Common types of nanomaterials that are used for biofuel applications include metal oxides, carbon-based structures, and hybrids, which are evaluated for their effectiveness in efficient biofuel production. The properties of such nanomaterials are being utilized as an aid to produce biofuels through improved catalysis, enzyme immobilization and thermal stability. Common synthesis methods, such as sol-gel, coprecipitation, and green synthesis, are compared, alongside characterization tools, such as TEM, SEM, FTIR, and BET. This study focuses on transesterification, biomass pretreatment, and fermentation processes, where nanomaterials significantly improve yield and reusability. There are several challenges, despite the merits of using nanomaterials, and the trade-offs include cost, scalability, and environmental impact, which further expand into evaluating the life cycle of such materials. This review outlines the practical potential of nanomaterials in enabling efficient and sustainable biofuel production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17548v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1557/s43578-025-01709-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lydia Lonardi, Caitlyn Lew-Tong, Brian Dunsten Miranda, Chandraleka V. S., Evelyn W Li, Bhaavyaa Sahukari, Harshit Poddar, Keerthana Satheesh, Utkarsh Chadha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optically-Trapped Particle Tracking Velocimetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03676v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a microflow velocimetry based on particle tracking with the aid of optical trapping of tracers, namely, optically-trapped particle tracking velocimetry (ot-PTV). The ot-PTV has two phases: a trap phase, in which individual tracers are trapped by an optical force and held at a measurement position; a release phase, in which the tracer is released and advected by the fluid flow, without interference from the optical force. The released tracer is subsequently trapped again by the optical force. By repeating the set of trap and release phases, we can accumulate the sequential images of the tracer that have the same initial position. Although the data acquisition rate of ot-PTV is lower than that of standard micro-resolution particle image velocimetry ($\mu$PIV) due to the nature of pointwise measurement, an advantage of ot-PTV is that the measurement positions can be chosen by the experimenter. That is, even when tracers are scarce in a test section because of some external effects and/or the small size of the test section -- ill-suited cases for $\mu$PIV since the experimenter has to wait for tracers to diffuse into the test section (i.e., diffusion-limited situation) -- ot-PTV remains efficient. The concept of ot-PTV is validated using a benchmark experiment, i.e., a pressure-driven flow in a straight microchannel with a square cross-section. An application to thermally-induced microflows is also demonstrated, where tracers can be scarce in a test section due to thermophoresis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03676v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tetsuro Tsuji, Shoma Hashimoto, Satoshi Taguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical Quantum Advantage in Constrained Optimization from Encoded Unitary Designs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14296v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the Constraint-Enhanced Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (CE-QAOA), a shallow, constraint-aware ansatz that operates inside the one-hot product space [n]^m, where m is the number of blocks and each block is initialized in an n-qubit W_n state. We give an ancilla-free, depth-optimal encoder that prepares W_n using n-1 two-qubit rotations per block, and a two-local block-XY mixer that preserves the one-hot manifold and has a constant spectral gap on the one-excitation sector. At the level of expressivity, we establish per-block controllability, implying approximate universality per block. At the level of distributional behavior, we show that, after natural block and symbol permutation twirls, shallow CE-QAOA realizes an encoded unitary 1-design and supports approximate second-moment (2-design) behavior; combined with a Paley-Zygmund argument, this yields finite-shot anticoncentration guarantees.
  Algorithmically, we wrap constant-depth sampling with a deterministic feasibility checker to obtain a polynomial-time hybrid quantum-classical solver (PHQC) that returns the best observed feasible solution in O(S n^2) time, where S is a polynomial shot budget. We obtain two advantages. First, when CE-QAOA fixes r &gt;= 1 locations different from the start city, we achieve a Theta(n^r) reduction in shot complexity even against a classical sampler that draws uniformly from the feasible set. Second, against a classical baseline restricted to raw bitstring sampling, we show an exp(Theta(n^2)) minimax separation. In noiseless circuit simulations of traveling salesman problem instances with n in {4,...,10} locations from the QOPTLib benchmark library, we recover the global optimum at depth p = 1 using polynomial shot budgets and coarse parameter grids defined by the problem size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14296v3</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chinonso Onah, Roman Firt, Kristel Michielsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
