<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 04:01:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation versus Dissipation in a Non-Hermitian Anderson Impurity Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the competition between strong correlations and dissipation in quantum impurity systems from the Kondo regime to the valence fluctuation regime by developing a slave-boson theory for a non-Hermitian Anderson impurity model with one-body loss. Notably, in the non-Hermitian Kondo regime, strong correlations qualitatively change the nature of dissipation through renormalization effects, where the effective one-body loss is suppressed and emergent many-body dissipation characterized by the complex-valued hybridization is generated. We unveil the mechanism of a dissipative quantum phase transition of the Kondo state on the basis of this renormalization effect, which counterintuitively enhances the lifetime of the impurity against loss. We also find a crossover from the non-Hermitian Kondo regime to the valence fluctuation regime dominated by one-body dissipation. Our results can be tested in a wide variety of setups such as quantum dots coupled to electronic leads and quantum point contacts in ultracold Fermi gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03494v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Yamamoto, Masaya Nakagawa, Norio Kawakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of total phase fluctuation in cold-atomic quantum simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studying the dynamics of quantum many-body systems is often constrained by the limitations in probing relevant observables, especially in continuous systems. A prominent example is two parallel 1D Bose gases, which simulate 1D quantum field theories through the phase difference probed by interference. Here we introduce a method to extract the total phase of the combined system based on a general principle of reconstructing phase gradient from density dynamics using continuity equation. This approach reveals the previously hidden sector of the sum mode of the two 1D Bose gases. We validate our technique numerically and demonstrate its effectiveness by analysing data from selected experiments, showcasing how our method expands the scope and capabilities of cold-atomic quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03736v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taufiq Murtadho, Federica Cataldini, Sebastian Erne, Marek Gluza, J\"org Schmiedmayer, Nelly H. Y. Ng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipation Driven Coherent Dynamics Observed in Bose-Einstein Condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the first experimental observation of dissipation-driven coherent quantum many-body oscillation, and this oscillation is manifested as the coherent exchange of atoms between the thermal and the condensate components in a three-dimensional partially condensed Bose gas. Firstly, we observe that the dissipation leads to two different atom loss rates between the thermal and the condensate components, such that the thermal fraction increases as dissipation time increases. Therefore, this dissipation process serves as a tool to uniformly ramp up the system's temperature without introducing extra density excitation. Subsequently, a coherent pair exchange of atoms between the thermal and the condensate components occurs, resulting in coherent oscillation of atom numbers in both components. This oscillation, permanently embedded in the atom loss process, is revealed clearly when we inset a duration of dissipation-free evolution into the entire dynamics, manifested as an oscillation of total atom number at the end. Finally, we also present a theoretical calculation to support this physical mechanism, which simultaneously includes dissipation, interaction, finite temperature, and harmonic trap effects. Our work introduces a highly controllable dissipation as a new tool to control quantum many-body dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03815v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye Tian, Yajuan Zhao, Yue Wu, Jilai Ye, Shuyao Mei, Zhihao Chi, Tian Tian, Ce Wang, Zhe-Yu Shi, Yu Chen, Jiazhong Hu, Hui Zhai, Wenlan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commensurate supersolids and re-entrant transitions in an extended Bose-Hubbard ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20107v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the ground state phases of an extended Bose-Hubbard ladder of unit filling via the density-matrix-renormalization-group method and, in particular, the effect of rung-hoppings. In contrast to a single-chain, a commensurate supersolid emerges, and based on the Luttinger parameter, we classify them into two types. The latter leads to a reentrant gapless behavior as the onsite interaction is increased while keeping all other parameters intact. A reentrant gapped transition is also found as a function of nearest-neighbor interactions. Further, we show that the string order characterizing the Haldane phase vanishes for a finite inter-chain hopping amplitude, however small it is. Finally, we propose two experimental platforms to observe our findings, using either dipolar atoms or polar molecules and Rydberg admixed atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20107v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashwath N Madhusudan, Gopal Chandra Santra, Inderpreet Kaur, Weibin Li, Rejish Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel compression algorithm for fast preparation of defect-free atom arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.03047v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Defect-free atom arrays have emerged as a powerful and versatile platform for quantum sciences and technologies, offering high programmability and promising scalability. The arrays can be prepared by rearranging atoms from a partially loaded initial array to the designated target sites. However, achieving large defect-free arrays presents challenges due to atom loss during rearrangement and the vacuum-limited lifetime which is inversely proportional to the array size. Efficient rearrangement algorithms which minimize time cost and atom loss are crucial for successful atom rearrangement. Here we propose a novel parallel compression algorithm which leverages multiple mobile tweezers to transfer atoms simultaneously. The total time cost could be reduced to scale linearly with the number of target sites. This algorithm can be readily implemented in current experimental setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.03047v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shangguo Zhu, Yun Long, Mingbo Pu, Xiangang Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational approach for the two-body problem in a multiband extended-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01117v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Considering a spin-up and a spin-down fermion in a generic tight-binding lattice with a multi-site basis, we investigate the two-body problem using a multiband extended-Hubbard model with finite-ranged hopping and interaction parameters. We derive a linear eigenvalue problem for the entire two-body spectrum, alongside a nonlinear eigenvalue problem for the bound states in the form of a self-consistency equation. Our results, based on an exact variational approach, suggest potential applications across various lattice geometries. As an illustration, we apply them to the linear-chain model and show that the resultant spin singlet and triplet bound states align well with the existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01117v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Iskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low energy excitations in bosonic quantum quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21230v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the first principles construction of the low-energy effective action for bosonic self-organized quantum quasicrystals. Our generalized elasticity approach retains the appropriate number of phase- and corresponding conjugate density- degrees-of-freedom required for a proper description of the Goldstone modes. For the dodecagonal and decagonal quasicrystal structures we obtain collective longitudinal and transversal excitations with an isotropic speed of sound. Meanwhile, for the octagonal structure, the coupling between phononic and phasonic degrees of freedom leads in turn to hybridization of the latter with the condensate sound mode, producing collective excitations with a longitudinal and transversal component, and an anisotropic speed of sound. Finally, we discuss the fate of each excitation mode at the low and high density phase transitions limiting the quantum quasicrystal phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21230v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Mendoza-Coto, Mariano Bonifacio, Francesco Piazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
