<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 04:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-high-amplitude Peregrine solitons induced by helicoidal spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the framework of the model of a spatially non-uniform Bose-Einstein condensate with helicoidal spin-orbit (SO) coupling, we find abnormal Peregrine solitons (PSs) on top of flat and periodic backgrounds, with ultra-high amplitudes. We explore the roles of the SO coupling strength and helicity pitch in the creation of these anomalously tall PSs and find that their amplitude, normalized to the background height, attains indefinitely large values. The investigation of the modulation instability (MI) in the same system demonstrates that these PSs exist in a range of relatively weak MI, maintaining the feasibility of their experimental observation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00322v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cui-Cui Ding, Qin Zhou, B. A. Malomed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium BCS-BEC crossover and unconventional FFLO superfluid in a strongly interacting driven-dissipative Fermi gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a theoretical review of the recent progress in nonequilibrium BCS (Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer)-BEC (Bose-Einstein condensation) crossover physics. As a paradigmatic example, we consider a strongly interacting driven-dissipative two-component Fermi gas where the nonequilibrium steady state is tuned by adjusting the chemical potential difference between two reservoirs that are coupled with the system. As a powerful theoretical tool to deal with this system, we employ the Schwinger-Keldysh Green's function technique. We systematically evaluate the superfluid transition, as well as the single-particle properties, in the nonequilibrium BCS-BEC crossover region, by adjusting the chemical potential difference between the reservoirs and the strength of an s-wave pairing interaction associated with a Feshbach resonance. In the weak-coupling BCS side, the chemical potential difference is shown to imprint a two-step structure on the particle momentum distribution, leading to an anomalous enhancement of pseudogap, as well as the emergence of exotic Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov-type superfluid instability. Since various nonequilibrium situations have recently been realized in ultracold Fermi gases, the theoretical understanding of nonequilibrium BCS-BEC crossover physics would become increasingly important in this research field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00446v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taira Kawamura, Yoji Ohashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Only-phase Popov action: thermodynamic derivation and superconducting electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a thermodynamic derivation of the only-phase Popov action functional, which is often adopted to study the low-energy effective hydrodynamics of a generic nonrelativistic superfluid. It is shown that the crucial assumption is the use of the saddle point approximation after neglecting the quantum-pressure term. As an application, we analyze charged superfluid (superconductors) coupled to the electromagnetic field at zero temperature. Our only-phase and minimally-coupled theory predicts the decay of the electrostatic field inside a superconductor with a characteristic length much smaller than the London penetration depth of the static magnetic field. This result is confirmed also by a relativistic only-phase Popov action we obtain from the Klein-Gordon Lagrangian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00528v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Salasnich, Maria Guglielmina Pelizzo, Francesco Lorenzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent $s$-wave interactions in orbitally active quasi-two-dimensional Fermi gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the scattering properties and bound states of a quasi-two-dimensional (q2D) spin-polarized Fermi gas near a $p$-wave Feshbach resonance. Strong confinement promotes the out-of-plane spatial wave functions to a discrete, gapped orbital degree of freedom. Exchange-antisymmetric orbital pair wave functions are predicted to give rise to low-energy q2D interactions with $s$-wave symmetry. Using radiofrequency (rf) spectroscopy, we observe the signature power-law scaling and the dimensional-crossover feature anticipated for the emergent $s$-wave channel. Additionally, we demonstrate that two types of low-energy dimers, with either $s$-wave and $p$-wave symmetry, could be formed via rf spin-flip association from an orbital mixture. These findings illustrate how gapped orbital degrees of freedom can provide additional control over scattering symmetries in strongly confined ultracold gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00737v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin J. Dale, Kevin G. S. Xie, Kiera Pond Grehan, Shizhong Zhang, Jeff Maki, Joseph H. Thywissen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalised BBGKY hierarchy for near-integrable dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00593v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider quantum or classical many-body Hamiltonian systems, whose dynamics is given by an integrable, contact interactions, plus another, possibly long-range, generic two-body potential. We show how the dynamics of local observables is given in terms of a generalised version of Bogoliubov-Born-Green-Kirkwood-Yvon hierarchy, which we denote as gBBGKY, which is built for the densities, and their correlations, of the quasiparticles of the underlying integrable model. Unlike the usual cases of perturbation theory from free gases, the presence of local interactions in the integrable model "lifts" the so-called kinetic blocking, and the second layer of the hierarchy reproduces the dynamics at all time-scales. The latter consists of a fast pre-equilibration to a non-thermal steady state, and its subsequent thermalisation to a Gibbs ensemble. We show how the final relaxation is encoded into a Boltzmann scattering integral involving three or higher body-scatterings, and which, remarkably, is entirely determined by the diffusion constants of the underlying integrable model. We check our results with exact molecular dynamics simulations, finding perfect agreement. Our results show how gBBGKY can be successfully employed in quantum systems to compute scattering integrals and Fermi's golden rule transition rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00593v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Biagetti, Maciej Lebek, Milosz Panfil, Jacopo De Nardis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling dynamics of $^{164}$Dy supersolids and droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03725v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The tunneling dynamics of a magnetic $^{164}$Dy quantum gas in an elongated or pancake skewed double-well trap is investigated with a time-dependent extended Gross-Pitaevskii approach. Upon lifting the energy offset, different tunneling regimes can be identified. In the elongated trap and for sufficiently large offset, the different configurations exhibit collective macroscopic tunneling. For smaller offset, partial reflection from and transmission through the barrier lead to density accumulation in both wells, and eventually to tunneling-locking. One can also reach the macroscopic self-trapping regime for increasing relative dipolar interaction strength, while tunneling vanishes for large barrier heights. A richer dynamical behavior is observed for the pancake-like trap. For instance, the supersolid maintains its shape, while the superfluid density gets distorted signifying the emergence of peculiar excitation patterns in the macroscopic tunneling regime. The findings reported here may offer new ways to probe distinctive dynamical features in the supersolid and droplet regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03725v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.013323</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. I. Mistakidis, K. Mukherjee, S. M. Reimann, H. R. Sadeghpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Progress toward a zero-magnetic-field environment for ultracold-atom experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19565v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The minimization of the magnetic field plays a crucial role in ultracold gas research. For instance, the contact interaction dominates all the other energy scales in the zero magnetic field limit, giving rise to novel quantum phases of matter. However, lowering magnetic fields well below the mG level is often challenging in ultracold gas experiments. In this article, we apply Landau-Zener spectroscopy to characterize and reduce the magnetic field on an ultracold gas of sodium atoms to a few tens of {\mu}G. The lowest magnetic field achieved here opens to observing novel phases of matter with ultracold spinor Bose gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19565v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.013319</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 013319 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Rogora, Riccardo Cominotti, Cosetta Baroni, Diego Andreoni, Giacomo Lamporesi, Alessandro Zenesini, Gabriele Ferrari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next nearest neighbour coupling with spinor polariton condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.04210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.04210v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report on experimental observation of next-nearest-neighbour coupling between ballistically expanding spinor exciton-polariton condensates in a planar semiconductor microcavity. All-optical control over the coupling strength between neighbouring condensates is demonstrated through distance-periodic pseudospin screening of their ballistic particle outflow due to the inherent splitting of the planar cavity transverse-electric (TE) and transverse-magnetic (TM) modes. By screening the nearest-neighbour coupling we overcome the conventional spatial coupling hierarchy between condensates. This offers a promising route towards creating unconventional non-planar many-body Hamiltonians using networks of ballistically expanding spinor exciton-polariton condensates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.04210v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.108.L161301</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dmitriy Dovzhenko, Denis Aristov, Lucy Pickup, Helgi Sigurdsson, Pavlos G. Lagoudakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum vortex lattice: Lifshitz duality, topological defects and multipole symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13794v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study an effective field theory of a vortex lattice in a two-dimensional neutral rotating superfluid. Utilizing particle-vortex dualities, we explore its formulation in terms of a $U(1)$ gauge theory coupled to elasticity, that at low energies reduces to a compact Lifshitz theory augmented with a Berry phase term encoding the vortex dynamics in the presence of a superflow. Utilizing elasticity- and Lifshitz-gauge theory dualities, we derive dual formulations of the vortex lattice in terms of a traceless symmetric scalar-charge theory and demonstrate low-energy equivalence of our dual gauge theory to its elasticity-gauge theory dual. We further discuss a multipole symmetry of the vortex lattice and its dual gauge theory's multipole one-form symmetries. We also study its topological crystalline defects, where the multipole one-form symmetry plays a prominent role. It classifies the defects, explains their restricted mobility, and characterizes descendant vortex phases, which includes a novel vortex supersolid phase. Using the dual gauge theory, we also develop a mean-field theory for the quantum melting transition from a vortex crystal to a vortex supersolid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13794v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Hsien Du, Ho Tat Lam, Leo Radzihovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic quasibound states and tachyonic instabilities from binary Bose-Einstein condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02557v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider two-component Bose-Einstein condensates (BECs) and introduce the BEC vortex in $1+2$ dimensions. We focus on two types of gapped excitations induced by the modes of two-component BECs with relative phases of $0$ and $\pi$, analogous to the massive scalar field with positive and negative mass squared, respectively. The inclusion of space-dependent Rabi coupling can induce an effective space-dependent mass term. We study superradiant instabilities resulting from the quasibound states corresponding to positive mass squared and the tachyonic instabilities arising from negative mass squared in both the frequency and time domains. These instabilities resemble two possible mechanisms that make Kerr black holes unstable in scalar-tensor gravity with the presence of matter around the black hole. Our proposed phenomena could potentially be implemented in future experiments, drawing from the success of recent analog rotating black hole implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02557v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Can Syu, Da-Shin Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survival Probability, Particle Imbalance, and Their Relationship in Quadratic Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05500v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We argue that the dynamics of particle imbalance in quadratic fermionic models is, for the majority of initial many-body product states in site occupation basis, virtually indistinguishable from the dynamics of survival probabilities of single-particle states. We then generalize our statement to a similar relationship between the non-equal time and space density correlation functions in many-body states and the transition probabilities of single-particle states at nonzero distances. Finally, we study the equal time connected density-density correlation functions in many-body states, which exhibit certain qualitative analogies with the survival and transition probabilities of single-particle states. Our results are numerically tested for two paradigmatic models of single-particle localization: the 3D Anderson model and the 1D Aubry-Andr\'e model. This work gives affirmative answer to the question whether it is possible to measure features of the single-particle survival and transition probabilities by the dynamics of observables in many-body states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05500v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/e26080656</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Entropy 26(8), 656 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Miroslav Hopjan, Lev Vidmar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low energy excitations in bosonic quantum quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21230v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the first principles construction of the low-energy effective action for bosonic self-organized quantum quasicrystals. Our generalized elasticity approach retains the appropriate number of phase- and corresponding conjugate density- degrees-of-freedom required for a proper description of the Goldstone modes. For the dodecagonal and decagonal quasicrystal structures we obtain collective longitudinal and transversal excitations with an isotropic speed of sound. Meanwhile, for the octagonal structure, the coupling between phononic and phasonic degrees of freedom leads in turn to hybridization of the latter with the condensate sound mode, producing collective excitations with a longitudinal and transversal component, and an anisotropic speed of sound. Finally, we discuss the fate of each excitation mode at the low and high density phase transitions limiting the quantum quasicrystal phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21230v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Mendoza-Coto, Mariano Bonifacio, Francesco Piazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of Krylov state complexity in qubit dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze the properties of Krylov state complexity in qubit dynamics, considering a single qubit and a qubit pair. A geometrical picture of the Krylov complexity is discussed for the single-qubit case, whereas it becomes non-trivial for the two-qubit case. Considering the particular case of interacting Rydberg atoms, we show that the Krylov basis obtained using an effective Hamiltonian minimizes the complexity compared to that obtained from the original Hamiltonian. We further generalize the latter property to an arbitrary Hamiltonian in which the entire Hilbert space comprises two subspaces with a weak coupling between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21776v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Seetharaman, Chetanya Singh, Rejish Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
