<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 04:01:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Meson Mass Sets Onset Time of Anomalous Dynamical Quantum Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamical quantum phase transitions (DQPTs) have been established as a rigorous framework for investigating far-from-equilibrium quantum many-body criticality. Although initially thought to be trivially connected to an order parameter flipping sign, a certain kind of \textit{anomalous} DQPTs have been discovered that exhibit no direct connection to the order parameter and have been shown to arise in the presence of confinement. Here, we show in two paradigmatic models how the onset time of anomalous DQPTs is directly connected, through a power law, to the meson mass in the confined regime of a global symmetry-broken phase. This relation becomes more prominent the closer the initial parameters are to the equilibrium quantum critical point, where a relativistic quantum field theory emerges. Our findings draw a direct connection between mesons and anomalous DQPTs, highlighting the power of the latter to classify exotic far-from-equilibrium criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse J. Osborne, Johannes Knaute, Ian P. McCulloch, Jad C. Halimeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott-glass phase induced by long-range correlated disorder in a one-dimensional Bose gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We determine the phase diagram of a one-dimensional Bose gas in the presence of disorder with short- and long-range correlations, the latter decaying with distance as $1/|x|^{1+\sigma}$. When $\sigma&lt;0$, the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition between the superfluid and the localized phase is driven by the long-range correlations and the Luttinger parameter $K$ takes the critical value $K_c(\sigma)=3/2-\sigma/2$. The localized phase is a Bose glass for $\sigma&gt;\sigma_c=3-\pi^2/3\simeq -0.289868$, and a Mott glass -- characterized by a vanishing compressibility and a gapless conductivity -- when $\sigma&lt;\sigma_c$. Our conclusions, based on the nonperturbative functional renormalization group and perturbative renormalization group, are confirmed by the study of the case $\sigma=-1$, corresponding to a perfectly correlated disorder in space, where the model is exactly solvable in the semiclassical limit $K\to 0^+$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03430v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Dupuis, Andrei A. Fedorenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarons in supersolids: path-integral treatment of an impurity in a one-dimensional dipolar supersolid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03505v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The supersolid phase of a dipolar Bose-Einstein condensate has an intriguing excitation spectrum displaying a band structure. Here, the dressing of an impurity in a one-dimensional dipolar supersolid with the excitations of the supersolid is studied. The ground-state energy of the supersolid polaron is calculated using a variational path integral approach, which obtained accurate results for other polaron systems within the Bogoliubov and Fr\"ohlich approximations. A divergence is observed at the superfluid-supersolid phase transition. The polaron radius is also computed, showing that for strong impurity-atom interactions, the polaron can become localized to a single droplet, behaving like a small solid-state polaron.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03505v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurent H. A. Simons, Michiel Wouters, Jacques Tempere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crow instability of vortex lines in dipolar superfluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In classical inviscid fluids, parallel vortices perturbed by Kelvin waves may exhibit the Crow instability, where the mutual interaction of the Kelvin modes renders them dynamically unstable. This results in the mutual approach and reconnection of the vortices, leading to a cascaded decay into smaller and smaller vortex loops. We study the Crow instability of quantum vortex lines in a superfluid enjoying the anisotropic, long-ranged dipole-dipole interaction through mean-field simulations of the dynamics of the superfluid order parameter. We observe that both the strength and direction of the dipole-dipole interaction play a crucial role in determining the Kelvin modes that are dynamically favoured. This is shown to be linked to effective enhancements or suppressions of the vortices' curvature and can be explained by the effective dipole-dipole interaction between the vortex lines themselves. This paves the way to a deeper understanding of vortex reconnection dynamics, vortex loop cascading and turbulence in dipolar superfluids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04177v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srivatsa B. Prasad, Andrew W. Baggaley, Nick G. Parker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Phase Fluctuations in Narrow Superfluid Rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04229v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using matter-wave interference, we have investigated thermal phase fluctuations in narrow coplanar, concentric rings of ultracold fermionic superfluids. We found that the correlation length decreases with number density, consistent with theoretical expectations. We also observed that increasing the coupling between the rings leads to greater overall coherence in the system. The phase fluctuations increased with a change from periodic to closed boundary conditions as we applied a potential barrier at one point in a ring. These results are relevant for the implementation of proposals to utilize ultracold quantum gases in large and elongated circuit-like geometries, especially those that require deterministic preparation and control of quantized circulation states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04229v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parth Sabharwal, Daniel G. Allman, Pradipta Debnath, Kevin C. Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized circular dichroism on the edge of quantum Hall systems: The many-body Chern number as seen from the edge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Hall states are characterized by a topological invariant, the many-body Chern number, which determines the quantized value of the Hall conductivity. Interestingly, this topological property can also be accessed through a dissipative response, by subjecting the system to a circular drive and comparing excitation rates obtained for opposite orientations of the drive. This quantized circular dichroism assumes that only the bulk contributes to the response. Indeed, in a confined and isolated system, the edge contribution exactly cancels the bulk response. This work explores an important corollary of the latter observation: If properly isolated, the circular dichroic response stemming from the edge of a quantum Hall droplet must be quantized, thus providing an appealing way to probe the many-body Chern number. Importantly, we demonstrate that this quantized edge response is entirely captured by low-energy chiral edge modes, allowing for a universal description of this effect based on Wen's edge theory. Its low-energy nature implies that the quantized edge response can be distinguished from the bulk response in the frequency domain. We illustrate our findings using realistic models of integer and fractional Chern insulators, with different edge geometries, and propose detection schemes suitable for ultracold atoms. Edge dichroic responses emerge as a practical probe for strongly-correlated topological phases, accessible in cold-atom experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04639v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Nur \"Unal, A. Nardin, N. Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ballistic Modes as a Source of Anomalous Charge Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03412v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Steady-state currents generically occur both in systems with continuous translation invariance and in nonequilibrium settings with particle drift. In either case, thermal fluctuations advected by the current act as a source of noise for slower hydrodynamic modes. This noise is unconventional, since it is highly correlated along spacetime rays. We argue that, in quasi-one-dimensional geometries, the correlated noise from ballistic modes generically gives rise to anomalous full counting statistics (FCS) for diffusively spreading charges. We present numerical evidence for anomalous FCS in two settings: (1) a two-component continuum fluid, and (2) the totally asymmetric exclusion process (TASEP) initialized in a nonequilibrium state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03412v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ewan McCulloch, Romain Vasseur, Sarang Gopalakrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deconfined quantum critical points in fermionic systems with spin-charge separation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04073v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deconfined quantum critical points are exotic transition points not predicted by the Landau-Ginzburg-Wilson symmetry-breaking paradigm. They are associated to a one-point gap closing between distinct locally ordered phases, thus to a continuous phase transition. Because of this intrinsic criticality, at deconfined quantum critical points algebraic decay of all the correlation functions is expected. Here, we show that it is possible to go beyond this assumption. Specifically, we consider one dimensional interacting fermions where the phenomenon of spin-charge separation arises. We first explore the low energy regimes where a sine-Gordon Hamiltonian can provide accurate results. By means of a field theory approach we find that continuous phase transitions between different locally ordered phases can occur. As a consequence of the decoupled spin and charge degrees of freedom, we find that in two cases only one gap vanishes while the other remains finite. We then derive a microscopic model where such phase transitions take place. By performing a numerical analysis, we unambiguously find that deconfined quantum critical points can indeed be further characterized by the long-range order of a parity operator signaling the presence of a finite gap. Our results provide new interesting insights on the widely investigated topic of quantum phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04073v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niccol\`o Baldelli, Arianna Montorsi, Sergi Juli\`a-Farr\'e, Maciej Lewenstein, Matteo Rizzi, Luca Barbiero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative time crystal in a strongly interacting Rydberg gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.20070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.20070v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The notion of spontaneous symmetry breaking has been well established to characterize classical and quantum phase transitions of matter, such as in condensation, crystallization or quantum magnetism. Generalizations of this paradigm to the time dimension can lead to a time crystal phase, which spontaneously breaks the time translation symmetry of the system. Whereas the existence of a continuous time crystal at equilibrium has been challenged by no-go theorems, this difficulty can be circumvented by dissipation in an open system. Here, we report the experimental observation of such dissipative time crystalline order in a room-temperature atomic gas, where ground-state atoms are continuously driven to Rydberg states. The emergent time crystal is revealed by persistent oscillations of the photon transmission, and we show that the observed limit cycles arise from the coexistence and competition between distinct Rydberg components. The nondecaying autocorrelation of the oscillation, together with the robustness against temporal noises, indicate the establishment of true long-range temporal order and demonstrates the realization of a continuous time crystal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.20070v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02542-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Phys. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoling Wu, Zhuqing Wang, Fan Yang, Ruochen Gao, Chao Liang, Meng Khoon Tey, Xiangliang Li, Thomas Pohl, Li You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal duality of the nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation: Theory and applications to parameter estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.17720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.17720v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation (NLSE) is a rich and versatile model, which in one spatial dimension has stationary solutions similar to those of the linear Schr\"odinger equation as well as more exotic solutions such as solitary waves and quantum droplets. Here we present the unified theory of the NLSE, showing that all stationary solutions of the local one-dimensional cubic-quintic NLSE can be classified according to a single number called the cross-ratio. Any two solutions with the same cross-ratio can be converted into one another using a conformal transformation, and the same also holds true for traveling wave solutions. Further, we introduce an optimization afterburner that relies on this conformal symmetry to substantially improve NLSE parameter estimation from noisy empirical data. The new method therefore should have far reaching practical applications for nonlinear physical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.17720v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David B. Reinhardt, Dean Lee, Wolfgang P. Schleich, Matthias Meister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polariton Fluids as Quantum Field Theory Simulators on Tailored Curved Spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01392v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum fields in curved spacetime exhibit a wealth of effects like Hawking radiation from black holes. While quantum field theory in black holes can only be studied theoretically, it can be tested in controlled laboratory experiments. In experiments, a fluid going from sub- to supersonic speed creates an effectively curved spacetime for the acoustic field, with a horizon where the speed of the fluid equals the speed of sound. The challenge to test predictions like the Hawking effect in such systems lies in the control of the spacetime curvature and access to the field spectrum thereon. Here, we create tailored stationary effective curved spacetimes in a polaritonic quantum fluid of light in which either massless or massive excitations can be created, with smooth and steep horizons and various supersonic fluid speeds. Using a recently developed spectroscopy method we measure the spectrum of collective excitations on these spacetimes, crucially observing negative energy modes in the supersonic regions, which signals the formation of a horizon. Control over the horizon curvature and access to the spectrum on either side demonstrates the potential of quantum fluids of light for the study of field theories on curved spacetimes, and we discuss the possibility of investigating emission and spectral instabilities with a horizon or in an effective Exotic Compact Object configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01392v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K\'evin Falque, Adri\`a Delhom, Quentin Glorieux, Elisabeth Giacobino, Alberto Bramati, Maxime J Jacquet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Many-Body Quantum Chaos: Bose-Hubbard systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17744v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work develops a quantum control application of many-body quantum chaos for ultracold bosonic gases trapped in optical lattices. It is long known how to harness exponential sensitivity to changes in initial conditions for control purposes in classically chaotic systems. In the technique known as targeting, instead of a hindrance to control, the instability becomes a resource. Recently, this classical targeting has been generalized to quantum systems either by periodically countering the inevitable quantum state spreading or by introducing a control Hamiltonian, where both enable localized states to be guided along special chaotic trajectories toward any of a broad variety of desired target states. Only strictly unitary dynamics are involved; i.e., it gives a coherent quantum targeting. In this paper, the introduction of a control Hamiltonian is applied to Bose-Hubbard systems in chaotic dynamical regimes. Properly selected unstable mean field solutions can be followed quite rapidly to states possessing precise phase relationships and occupancies. In essence, the method generates a quantum simulation technique that can access rather special states. The protocol reduces to a time-dependent control of the chemical potentials, opening up the possibility for application in optical lattice experiments. Explicit applications to custom state preparation and stabilization of quantum many-body scars are presented in one- and two-dimensional lattices (three-dimensional applications are similarly possible).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17744v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1367-2630/ad5752</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Beringer, Mathias Steinhuber, Juan Diego Urbina, Klaus Richter, Steven Tomsovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum of density, spin and pairing fluctuations of an attractive two-dimensional Fermi gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13636v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We leverage random phase approximation and unbiased auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo methods to compute dynamical correlations for a dilute homogeneous two-dimensional attractive Fermi gas. Our main purpose is to quantitatively study the collective excitations of the system to generate robust benchmark results and to shed light into fermionic superfluidity in the strongly correlated regime. In particular we are motivated by a recent paper suggesting that the Higgs mode can be detected in the spectrum of spin fluctuations. Despite the fact that we are somewhat limited by finite-size effects, our study pinpoints indeed a clear peak in the spin channel at low momentum, but a detailed analysis suggests that such a peak, though certainly interesting, does not correspond to the Higgs mode. We propose a different explanation for the shape of the spin structure factor. On the other hand, our results clearly show that the Higgs mode can be detected in the density channel at very small wave vectors, although very good resolution is necessary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13636v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Apostoli, Patrick Kelly, Annette Lopez, Kaelyn Dauer, Gianluca Bertaina, Davide Emilio Galli, Ettore Vitali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a zero magnetic field environment for ultracold atoms experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19565v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The minimization of the magnetic field plays a crucial role in ultracold gas research. For instance, the contact interaction dominates all the other energy scales in the zero magnetic field limit, giving rise to novel quantum phases of matter. However, lowering magnetic fields well below the mG level is often challenging in ultracold gas experiments. In this article, we apply Landau-Zener spectroscopy to characterize and reduce the magnetic field on an ultracold gas of sodium atoms to a few tens of {\mu}G. The lowest magnetic field achieved here opens to observing novel phases of matter with ultracold spinor Bose gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19565v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Rogora, Riccardo Cominotti, Cosetta Baroni, Diego Andreoni, Giacomo Lamporesi, Alessandro Zenesini, Gabriele Ferrari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking and trapping Cooper pairs by Rydberg-molecule spectroscopy in atomic Fermi superfluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01401v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a spectroscopic probe of the breaking and localization of Cooper pairs in an atomic Fermi superfluid interacting with a Rydberg impurity. This is achieved by monitoring the formation of diatomic and triatomic ultralong-range molecular species in the superfluid across the BCS - Bose Einstein condensation (BEC) crossover. The triatomic Rydberg molecule in the BEC regime heralds the trapping of a tightly-bound Cooper pair, reminiscent of pion capture in nuclear matter, while the breaking of a Cooper pair on the BCS side by a diatomic Rydberg molecule is evocative of binary-star tidal disruption by a black hole. Spectroscopy of the Fermi superfluid and Rydberg molecules allows for an estimation of the Cooper-pair size while the Rydberg molecule binding energies discern many-body pairing effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01401v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Chun Chien, Simeon I. Mistakidis, Hossein R. Sadeghpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An energy-dependent broadening of Rashba-like spin splitting in Au2Sb surface alloy with periodic structural defect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06183v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Here, we report a novel AuSb 2D superstructure on Au(111) that shows agreements and discrepancies to the expected electronic features of the ideal 2D surface alloys with $\sqrt{3}\times\sqrt{3}$ periodicity. Using spin- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, we find a spin splitting of the alloy bands with antiparallel spin polarization, stemming from Rashba spin-orbit coupling. However, the observed Rashba bands are significantly broadened. Taking advantage of the good agreement between the experimental results and DFT calculations, we determine that the broadening of the Rashba band is due to the perturbations from the 3-pointed-star-shaped defects acting as nonresonant impurities in the Au2Sb superstructure. These periodic defects can shift the energy position of the Rashba band without breaking the in-plane rotational symmetry and mirror symmetry, which suggests that introducing periodic defects into a Rashba SOC system possesses a great potential in engineering the spin-dependent properties of spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06183v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinbang Hu, Xiansi Wang, Justin Wells</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic quantum trajectories in engineered reservoirs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.11937v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze the efficiency of protocols for adiabatic quantum state transfer assisted by an engineered reservoir. The target dynamics is a quantum trajectory in the Hilbert space and is a fixed point of a time-dependent master equation in the limit of adiabatic dynamics. We specialize to quantum state transfer in a qubit and determine the optimal schedule for a class of time-dependent Lindblad equations. The speed limit on state transfer is extracted from a physical model of a qubit coupled to a reservoir, from which the Lindblad equation is derived in the Born-Markov limit. Our analysis shows that the resulting efficiency is comparable to the efficiency of the optimal unitary dynamics. Numerical studies indicate that reservoir-engineered protocols could outperform unitary protocols outside the regime of the Born-Markov master equation, namely, when correlations between the qubit and reservoir become relevant. Our study contributes to the theory of shortcuts to adiabaticity for open quantum systems and to the toolbox of protocols of the NISQ era.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.11937v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma C. King, Luigi Giannelli, Rapha\"el Menu, Johannes N. Kriel, Giovanna Morigi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Continuous Time Crystal in Dissipative Quantum Spin System without Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08476v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Time crystal, a nonequilibrium phenomenon extending spontaneous symmetry breaking into the temporal dimension, holds fundamental significance in understanding quantum many-body physics. In this work, we explore the nonequilibrium phase diagram of a two-dimensional dissipative Heisenberg spin system without explicit coherent or incoherent external driving. We numerically identify the emergence of novel nonstationary oscillatory states by analyzing the spin dynamics. These states are categorized as limit cycle and chaos based on the Lyapunov exponent. Remarkably, the observed limit cycle behavior represents a continuous time crystal (CTC), spontaneously breaking the continuous time translation symmetry of the system. We further confirm those oscillatory behaviors by studying the stability against local perturbations applied to the system. Finally, we investigate the robustness of the emergent CTC by introducing isotropic Gaussian-type white noise into the interactions. This study provides many insights into the intricate interplay between the dissipation-induced spin downwards and anisotropic-interaction-induced spin precession or spin fluctuation, opening a new avenue for realizing dissipation-induced, heating-immune TCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08476v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu Yang, Zeqing Wang, Libin Fu, Jianwen Jie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Path integral approach to bosonisation and nonlinearities in exciton-polariton systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15529v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large exciton-polariton optical nonlinearities present a key mechanism for photonics-based communication, ultimately in the quantum regime. Enhanced nonlinear response from various materials hosting excitons and allowing for their strong coupling with light is therefore the topic of intense studies, both in theoretical and experimental domains. Reports on the scattering rates arising due to various system's nonlinearities, such as the exciton-exciton Coulomb interaction and the Pauli blocking that leads to the saturation of the exciton oscillator strength, however, are contradictory. In this work, we develop a formalism allowing to track the exciton nonlinearities appearing in the regime of strong coupling with photons, that includes finite temperatures, mixing of the exciton excited states, and the dark exciton contributions to saturation self-consistently. The equilibrium path integration approach employed here to address the polariton composite nature, leads to a transparent hierarchy of various contributions to nonlinearity. At the same time, by taking the simplest limit of zero temperature and so-called "rigid" excitons, through our framework we retrieve the expressions derived in conventional approaches for exciton interaction constants. In particular, our theory allows to clearly show that such interaction constants cannot be used as fitting parameters tunable in a wide range of values, as they are strictly defined by the material properties, and that other explanations are due for large optical nonlinearities recently reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15529v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna M. Grudinina, Nina S. Voronova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimentally Tractable Generation of High-Order Rogue Waves in Bose-Einstein Condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06869v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we study a prototypical, experimentally accessible scenario that enables the systematic generation of so-called high-order rogue waves in atomic Bose-Einstein condensates. These waveforms lead to significantly and controllably more extreme focusing events than the famous Peregrine soliton. In one spatial dimension, we showcase conclusive numerical evidence that our scheme generates the focusing behavior associated with the first four rogue waves from the relevant hierarchy. We then extend considerations to anisotropic two-dimensional and even three-dimensional settings, establishing that the scheme can generate second order rogue waves despite the well-known limitation of finite-time blow up of focusing nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06869v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jimmie Adriazola, Panayotis Kevrekidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
