<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 04:01:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Honeycomb supersolid -- Dirac points and shear-instability induced crystal transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The honeycomb supersolid state is predicted to form in a dipolar Bose-Einstein condensate with a planar confining potential. Our results for its excitation spectrum reveal the gapless bands and the emergence of Dirac points at the Brillouin zone edge, manifesting as points where the second sound and transverse sound bands touch. The honeycomb supersolid has three sound speeds that we connect to its elastic parameters through hydrodynamic theory. From this analysis we find conditions where a shear instability occurs as the honeycomb rigidity disappears. This gives insight into the nonequilibrium dynamics following an interaction quench, where the honeycomb pattern melts and different crystal orders emerge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15754v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. B. Blakie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An experimental platform for studying the heteronuclear Efimov effect with an ultracold mixture of $^6$Li and $^{133}$Cs atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16031v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the experimental apparatus enabling the observation of the heteronuclear Efimov effect in an optically trapped ultracold mixture of $^6$Li-$^{133}$Cs with high-resolution control of the interactions. A compact double-species Zeeman slower consisting of four interleaving helical coils allows for a fast-switching between two optimized configurations for either Li or Cs and provides an efficient sequential loading into their respective MOTs. By means of a bichromatic optical trapping scheme based on species-selective trapping we prepare mixtures down to 100 nK of 1$\times$ 10$^4$ Cs atoms and 7$\times$ 10$^3$ Li atoms. Highly stable magnetic fields allow high-resolution atom-loss spectroscopy and enable to resolve splitting in the loss feature of a few tens of milligauss. These features allowed for a detailed study of the Efimov effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16031v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleonora Lippi, Manuel Gerken, Stephan H\"afner, Marc Repp, Rico Pires, Michael Rautenberg, Tobias Krom, Eva D. Kuhnle, Binh Tran, Juris Ulmanis, Bing Zhu, Lauriane Chomaz, Matthias Weidem\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersonic shear waves in dipolar supersolids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16060v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dipolar supersolids--quantum states which are simultaneously superfluid and solid--have had their superfluid nature rigorously tested, while its solid nature remains uncharted. Arguably, the defining characteristic of a solid is the existence of elastic shear waves. In this work, we investigate transverse wave packet propagation in dipolar supersolids with triangular and honeycomb structure. Remarkably, the honeycomb supersolid displays anomalous dispersion, supporting waves traveling faster than the transverse speed of sound: a supersonic shear wave. For both supersolid phases, we calculate the shear modulus, a key parameter that quantifies the material's rigidity. Our findings are pertinent to current experimental efforts scrutinizing the fundamental properties of supersolids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16060v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Bland, Pramodh Senarath Yapa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum dynamics of atoms in number-theory-inspired potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13988v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study transitions of atoms between energy levels of several number-theory-inspired atom potentials, under the effect of time-dependent perturbations. First, we simulate in detail the case of a trap whose one-particle spectrum is given by prime numbers. We investigate one-body Rabi oscillations and the excitation lineshape for two resonantly coupled energy levels. We also show that techniques from quantum control are effective in reducing the transition time, compared to the case of a periodic perturbation. Next, we investigate cascades of such transitions. To this end, we pose the following question: can one construct a quantum system where the existence of a continuous resonant cascade is predicted on the validity of a particular statement in number theory? We find that a one-body trap with a log-natural spectrum, parametrically driven with a perturbation of a log-natural frequency, provides such a quantum system. Here, powers of a given natural number will form a ladder of equidistant energy levels; absence of gaps in this ladder is an indication of the validity of the number theory statement in question. Ideas for two more resonance cascade experiments are presented as well: they are designed to illustrate the validity of the Diophantus-Brahmagupta-Fibonacci identity (the set of sums of two squares of integers is closed under multiplication) and the validity of the Goldbach conjecture (every even number is a sum of two primes).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13988v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Cassettari, O. V. Marchukov, B. Carruthers, H. Kendell, J. Ruhl, B. De Mitchell Pierre, C. Zara, C. A. Weidner, A. Trombettoni, M. Olshanii, G. Mussardo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering dark states by non-Hermiticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14914v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark states, which are incapable of absorbing and emitting light, have been widely applied in multiple disciplines of physics. However, the existence of dark states relies on certain strict constraints on the system. For instance, in the fundamental {\Lambda} system, a perturbation breaking the degeneracy between two energy levels may destroy the destructive interference and demolish the dark state. Here, we show that non-Hermiticity can be exploited as a constructive means to restore a dark state. By compensating for the undesired perturbations, non-Hermiticity produces unidirectional couplings such that the dark state remains decoupled from the rest of the system. Implementing this scheme in many-body systems, flat bands and edge states can be recovered by losses and gains. Further taking into account interactions, a range of novel quantum phases could arise in such non-Hermitian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14914v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-Enriched Nontrivial Topology at Quantum Criticality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15395v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Periodically driven (Floquet) systems have attracted growing attention due to the emergence of intriguing phenomena that are absent in equilibrium physics. In this letter, we identify a new class of Floquet criticality characterized by nontrivial topology. For generic driven Majorana fermion chains with chiral symmetry, we analytically demonstrate that Floquet driving can enrich the transition point, resulting in topologically distinct quantum critical lines that are absent in undriven systems. Furthermore, we provide an intuitive physical explanation for the underlying mechanism of the nontrivial topology at Floquet criticality and generalize our results to higher dimensions. This work not only extends the scope of topological physics in Floquet systems but also deepens our understanding of gapless topological phases of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15395v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longwen Zhou, Xue-Jia Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of quantum information collapse-and-revival in a strongly-interacting Rydberg atom array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15455v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Interactions of isolated quantum many-body systems typically scramble local information into the entire system and make it unrecoverable. Ergodicity-breaking systems possess the potential to exhibit fundamentally different information scrambling dynamics beyond this paradigm. For many-body localized systems with strong ergodicity breaking, local transport vanishes and information scrambles logarithmically slowly. Whereas in Rydberg atom arrays, local qubit flips induce dynamical retardation on surrounding qubits through the Rydberg blockade effect, giving rise to quantum many-body scars that weakly break ergodicity, and resulting in the predicted unconventional quantum information spreading behaviours. Here, we present the first measurements of out-of-time-ordered correlators and Holevo information in a Rydberg atom array, enabling us to precisely track quantum information scrambling and transport dynamics. By leveraging these tools, we observe a novel spatio-temporal collapse-and-revival behaviour of quantum information, which differs from both typical chaotic and many-body localized systems. Our experiment sheds light on the unique information dynamics in many-body systems with kinetic constraints, and demonstrates an effective digital-analogue approach to coherently reverse time evolution and steer information propagation in near-term quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15455v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>De-Sheng Xiang, Yao-Wen Zhang, Hao-Xiang Liu, Peng Zhou, Dong Yuan, Kuan Zhang, Shun-Yao Zhang, Biao Xu, Lu Liu, Yitong Li, Lin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of anomalous information scrambling in a Rydberg atom array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16174v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum information scrambling, which describes the propagation and effective loss of local information, is crucial for understanding the dynamics of quantum many-body systems. In general, a typical interacting system would thermalize under time evolution, leading to the emergence of ergodicity and linear lightcones of information scrambling. Whereas, for a many-body localized system, strong disorders give rise to an extensive number of conserved quantities that prevent the system from thermalization, resulting in full ergodicity breaking and a logarithmic lightcone for information spreading. Here, we report the experimental observation of anomalous information scrambling in an atomic tweezer array. Working in the Rydberg blockade regime, where van der Waals interaction dominates, we observe a suppressed linear lightcone of information spreading characterized by out-of-time-order correlators for the initial N\'eel state, accompanied by persistent oscillations within the lightcone. Such an anomalous dynamics differs from both generic thermal and many-body localized scenarios. It originates from weak ergodicity breaking and is the characteristic feature for quantum many-body scars. The high-quality single-atom manipulations and coherent constraint dynamics, augmented by the effective protocol for time-reversed evolution we demonstrate, establish a versatile hybrid analog-digital simulation approach to explore diverse exotic non-equilibrium dynamics with atomic tweezer arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16174v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinhui Liang, Zongpei Yue, Yu-Xin Chao, Zhen-Xing Hua, Yige Lin, Meng Khoon Tey, Li You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order and fractional discrete time crystals in Floquet-driven Rydberg atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13657v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Higher-order and fractional discrete time crystals (DTCs) are exotic phases of matter where the discrete time translation symmetry is broken into higher-order and non-integer category. Generation of these unique DTCs has been widely studied theoretically in different systems. However, no current experimental methods can probe these higher-order and fractional DTCs in any quantum many-body systems. We demonstrate an experimental approach to observe higher-order and fractional DTCs in Floquet-driven Rydberg atomic gases. We have discovered multiple $n$-DTCs with integer values of $n$ = 2, 3, and 4, and others ranging up to 14, along with fractional $n$-DTCs with $n$ values beyond the integers. The system response can transition between adjacent integer DTCs, during which the fractional DTCs are investigated. Study of higher-order and fractional DTCs expands fundamental knowledge of non-equilibrium dynamics and is promising for discovery of more complex temporal symmetries beyond the single discrete time translation symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13657v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bang Liu, Li-Hua Zhang, Qi-Feng Wang, Yu Ma, Tian-Yu Han, Jun Zhang, Zheng-Yuan Zhang, Shi-Yao Shao, Qing Li, Han-Chao Chen, Bao-Sen Shi, Dong-Sheng Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed-channel parameters of Feshbach resonances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14962v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work investigates how the closed channel of a Feshbach resonance is characterised by experimental observables. Surprisingly, it is found that the two-body observables associated with the Feshbach resonance can be insensitive to the properties of the closed channel. In particular, it is impossible in this situation to determine the energy of the bound state causing the resonance from the usual experimental data. This is the case for all magnetic Feshbach resonances in ultracold atoms, due to their deep two-body interaction potentials. This insensitivity highlights a major difference with Feshbach resonances that involve shallow interaction potentials, such as hadron resonances. It appears however that short-range two-body correlations and three-body observables are affected by a parameter of the closed channel called the "closed-channel scattering length". A photoassociation experiment is proposed to measure this parameter in ultracold atom systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14962v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Naidon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-band superconductors have enhanced critical temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17297v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a multi-band BCS free energy functional and prove that for a multi-band superconductor the effect of inter-band coupling can only increase the critical temperature, irrespective of its attractive or repulsive nature and its strength. Further, for weak coupling and weaker inter-band coupling, we prove that the dependence of the increase in critical temperature on the inter-band coupling is (1) linear, if there are two or more equally strongly superconducting bands, or (2) quadratic, if there is only one dominating band.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17297v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joscha Henheik, Edwin Langmann, Asbj{\o}rn B{\ae}kgaard Lauritsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
