<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 04:01:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>One-dimensional Fermi polaron after a kick: two-sided singularity of the momentum distribution, Bragg reflection and other exact results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A mobile impurity particle immersed in a quantum fluid forms a polaron - a quasiparticle consisting of the impurity and a local disturbance of the fluid around it. We ask what happens to a one-dimensional polaron after a kick, i.e. an abrupt application of a force that instantly delivers a finite impulse to the impurity. In the framework of an integrable model describing an impurity in a one-dimensional gas of fermions or hard-core bosons, we calculate the distribution of the polaron momentum established when the post-kick relaxation is over. A remarkable feature of this distribution is a two-sided power-law singularity that can correspond to one of two processes. In the first process, the whole impulse is transferred to the polaron, without creating phonon-like excitations of the fluid. In the second process, the impulse is shared between the polaron and the center-of-mass motion of the fluid, again without creating any fluid excitations. The latter process is, in fact, a Bragg reflection at the edge of the emergent Brillouin zone. We carefully analyze the conditions for each of the two cases and derive the asymptotic form of the distribution in the vicinity of the singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02099v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandr Gamayun, Oleg Lychkovskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational approach for the two-body problem in a multiband extended-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Considering a spin-up and a spin-down fermion in a generic tight-binding lattice with a multi-site basis, here we study the two-body problem using a multiband extended-Hubbard model with arbitrary but finite-ranged hopping and interaction parameters. We derive a linear eigenvalue problem for the entire two-body spectrum, alongside a nonlinear eigenvalue problem for the bound states in the form of a self-consistency equation. Our results are based on an exact variational approach and their versatility offers practical applications in a broad range of lattice geometries. As an illustration, we apply them to the linear-chain model and demonstrate that the resultant spin singlet and triplet bound states are in perfect agreement with the existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01117v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Iskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier-Matsubara series expansion for imaginary-time correlation functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A Fourier-Matsubara series expansion is derived for imaginary-time correlation functions that constitutes the imaginary-time generalization of the infinite Matsubara series for equal-time correlation functions. The expansion is consistent with all known exact properties of imaginary-time correlation functions and opens up new avenues for the utilization of quantum Monte Carlo simulation data. Moreover, the expansion drastically simplifies the computation of imaginary-time density-density correlation functions with the finite temperature version of the self-consistent dielectric formalism. Its existence underscores the utility of imaginary-time as a complementary domain for many-body physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01838v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panagiotis Tolias, Fotios Kalkavouras, Tobias Dornheim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Hall effect in a CVD-grown oxide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02104v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional electron systems (2DES) are promising for investigating correlated quantum phenomena. In particular, 2D oxides provide a platform that can host various quantum phases such as quantized Hall effect, superconductivity, or magnetism. The realization of such quantum phases in 2D oxides heavily relies on dedicated heterostructure growths. Here we show the integer quantum Hall effect achieved in chemical vapor deposition grown Bi2O2Se - a representative member of a more accessible oxide family. A single or few sub-band 2DES can be prepared in thin films of Bi2O2Se, where the film thickness acts as the sole design parameter and the sub-band occupation is determined by the electric field effect. This new oxide platform exhibits characteristic advantages in structural flexibility due to its layered nature, making it suitable for scalable growth. The unique small mass distinguishes Bi2O2Se from other high-mobility oxides, providing a new platform for exploring quantum Hall physics in 2D oxides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02104v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandr Zheliuk, Yuliia Kreminska, Qundong Fu, Davide Pizzirani, Andrew A. L. N. Ammerlaan, Ying Wang, Sardar Hameed, Puhua Wan, Xiaoli Peng, Steffen Wiedmann, Zheng Liu, Jianting Ye, Uli Zeitler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation, manipulation and detection of snake state trajectories of a neutral atom in a ring-cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.11926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2002.11926v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a set-up to create and detect the atomic counterpart of snake state trajectories which occur at the interface where the magnetic field reverses direction. Such a magnetic field is generated by coupling two counter-propagating modes of a ring cavity to a two-level atom. The spatial distribution and the strength of the induced magnetic field are controlled by the transverse mode profile of the cavity modes and the number of photons in the two modes, respectively. By analysing the atomic motion in such a magnetic field while including the cavity back-action, we find that the atom follows snake state trajectories which can be non-destructively detected and reconstructed from the phase and the intensity of the light field leaking from the cavity. We finally show that the system parameters can be tuned to modify the transport properties of the snake states and even amplify the effect of cavity feedback which can completely alter their topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2002.11926v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Poornima Shakya (IIT Delhi), Nishant Dogra (Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge University), Sankalpa Ghosh (IIT Delhi)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Few particles with an impurity in a one-dimensional harmonic trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.17943v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive study of the static properties of a mobile impurity interacting with a bath with a few particles trapped in a one-dimensional harmonic trap. We consider baths with either identical bosons or distinguishable particles and we focus on the limiting case where the bath is non-interacting. We provide numerical results for the energy spectra and density profiles by means of the exact diagonalization of the Hamiltonian, and find that these systems show non-trivial solutions, even in the limit of infinite repulsion. A detailed physical interpretation is provided for the lowest energy states. In particular, we find a seemingly universal transition from the impurity being localized in the center of the trap to being expelled outside the majority cloud. We also develop an analytical ansatz and a mean-field solution to compare them with our numerical results in limiting configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.17943v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/ad3301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Scr. 99 045408 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abel Rojo-Franc\`as, Felipe Isaule, Bruno Juli\'a-D\'iaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fracton quantum gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.05670v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Starting from a simple dipole-conserving Hamiltonian model, after introducing a proper quantisation framework, we construct the linear-response theory of a fracton quantum gas. We show how to consistently construct the density operator and we calculate the density-density linear-response function in the limit of large number of (fracton) flavours. We show how to construct its random-phase approximation, from which we calculate the fracton-plasmon dispersion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.05670v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leone Di Mauro Villari, Alesssandro Principi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full Counting Statistics of Charge in Quenched Quantum Gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02929v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Unless constrained by symmetry, measurement of an observable on an ensemble of identical quantum systems returns a distribution of values which are encoded in the full counting statistics. While the mean value of this distribution is important for determining certain properties of a system, the full distribution can also exhibit universal behavior. In this paper we study the full counting statistics of particle number in one dimensional interacting Bose and Fermi gases which have been quenched far from equilibrium. In particular we consider the time evolution of the Lieb-Liniger and Gaudin-Yang models quenched from a Bose-Einstein condensate initial state and calculate the full counting statistics of the particle number within a subsystem. We show that the scaled cumulants of the charge in the initial state and at long times are simply related and in particular the latter are independent of the model parameters. Using the quasi-particle picture we obtain the full time evolution of the cumulants and find that although their endpoints are fixed, the finite time dynamics depends strongly on the model parameters. We go on to construct the scaled cumulant generating functions and from this determine the limiting charge probability distributions at long time which are shown to exhibit distinct non-trivial and non-Gaussian fluctuations and large deviations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02929v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.109.043302</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review A 109 (2024) 043302</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David X. Horvath, Colin Rylands</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
