<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 01:29:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi polarons with the finite-range fermion-impurity interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a problem of an infinitely heavy impurity introduced into a polarized Fermi gas, which can be solved exactly with the help of Fumi's theorem. We consider the regime of finite-range fermion-impurity interactions beyond the standard $s$-wave scattering regime and investigate how this affects the energy of the polaron. We show how one can account for the effective range effects as well as the contribution from higher angular momentum channels, which are important for the study of ionic and Rydberg polarons. Our findings have relevance for atomic gas mixtures with a large mass imbalance and for the impurities trapped inside the optical tweezers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19491v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolay Yegovtsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A phenomenological universal expression for the condensate fraction in strongly-correlated two-dimensional Bose gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the relation between non-local and energetic properties in 2D quantum systems of zero-temperature bosons. By analyzing numerous interaction potentials across densities spanning from perturbative to strongly correlated regime, we discover a novel high-precision quantum phenomenological universality: the condensate fraction can be expressed through kinetic energy and quantum energy, defined as total energy relative to classical crystal state. Quantum Monte Carlo simulations accurately validate our analytical expression. Furthermore, we test the obtained relation on the fundamental example of a non-perturbative system, namely, the liquid helium. The proposed relation is relevant to experiments with excitons in transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDC) materials, as well as ultracold atoms and other quantum systems in reduced dimensionality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19615v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. E. Astrakharchik, I. L. Kurbakov, N. A. Asriyan, Yu. E. Lozovik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitonic skin effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that strong interactions combined with band-dependent imaginary vector potentials give rise to boundary localization of particle-hole pairs, which we term the excitonic skin effect. In a bilayer system with layer-specific gain/loss and an in-plane magnetic field, excitons experience a net imaginary vector potential, resulting in directional amplification of particle-hole pairs. Including nearest-neighbor interactions leads to a non-Hermitian bosonic Kitaev model, where the pairing effects grow exponentially with the size of the system, revealing a unique form of critical skin effect in interacting systems. Our framework applies to both atomic and electronic platforms and is directly testable in current experiments. These results also provide a route to explore non-Hermitian analogs of tensor gauge fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20027v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhui Xu, Qi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated decoherence and thermometry with mobile impurities in a 1D Fermi gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the correlated decoherence dynamics of two mobile impurities trapped within a gas of ultracold fermionic atoms. We use a mean-field approximation to self-consistently describe the effect of impurity-gas collisions on impurity motion, while decoherence of the impurities' internal state is computed exactly within a functional determinant approach. At equilibrium, we find that the impurities undergo bath-induced localisation as the impurity-gas interaction strength is increased. We then study the non-equilibrium dynamics induced by a sudden change of the impurities' internal state, which can be experimentally probed by Ramsey interferometry. Our theoretical approach allows us to investigate the effect of impurity motion on decoherence dynamics, finding strong deviations from the universal behaviour associated with Anderson's orthogonality catastrophe when the mass imbalance between impurity and gas atoms is small. Finally, we show that mobile impurities can be used as thermometers of their environment and that bath-mediated correlations can be beneficial for thermometric performance at low temperatures, even in the presence of non-trivial impurity motion. Our results showcase the interesting open quantum dynamics of mobile impurities dephasing in a common environment, and could help provide more precise temperature estimates of ultracold fermionic mixtures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20050v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sindre Brattegard, Thom\'as Fogarty, Thomas Busch, Mark T. Mitchison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A cryogenic chamber setup for superfluid helium experiments with optical fiber and electrical access</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19962v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superfluid helium is a prototypical quantum liquid. As such, it has been a prominent platform for the study of quantum many body physics. More recently, the outstanding mechanical and optical properties of superfluid helium, such as low mechanical dissipation and low optical absorption, have positioned superfluid helium as a promising material platform in applications ranging from dark matter and gravitational wave detection to quantum computation. However, experiments with superfluid helium incur a high barrier to entry as they require incorporation of complex optical and electrical setups within a hermetically sealed cryogenic chamber to confine the superfluid. Here, we report on the design and construction of a helium chamber setup for operation inside a dilution refrigerator at Millikelvin temperatures, featuring electrical and optical fiber access. By incorporating an automated gas handling system, we can precisely control the amount of helium gas inserted into the chamber, rendering our setup particularly promising for experiments with superfluid helium thin films, such as superfluid thin film optomechanics. Using silicon nanophotonic resonators, we demonstrate precise control and in-situ tuning of the thickness of a superfluid helium film on the sub-nanometer level. By making use of the exceptional tunability of the superfluid film thickness, we demonstrate optomechanically induced phonon lasing of phononic crystal cavity third sound modes in the superfluid film and show that the lasing threshold crucially depends on the film thickness. The large internal volume of our chamber (V_chamber = 1l) is adaptable for integration of various optical and electrical measurement and control techniques. Therefore, our setup provides a versatile platform for a variety of experiments in fundamental and applied superfluid helium research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19962v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0249931</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Sci. Instrum. 96, 083903 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander R. Korsch, Niccol\`o Fiaschi, Simon Gr\"oblacher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extrinsic and Intrinsic Nonlinear Hall Effects across Berry-Dipole Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.02972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.02972v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Three-dimensional Hopf insulators are a class of topological phases beyond the tenfold-way classification. The critical point separating two rotation-invariant Hopf insulator phases with distinct Hopf invariants is quite different from the usual Dirac-type or Weyl-type critical points and uniquely characterized by a quantized Berry dipole. Close to such Berry-dipole transitions, we find that the extrinsic and intrinsic nonlinear Hall conductivity tensors in the weakly doped regime are characterized by two universal functions of the ratio between doping level and bulk energy gap, and are directly proportional to the change in Hopf invariant across the transition. Our work suggests that the nonlinear Hall effects display a general-sense quantized behavior across Berry-dipole transitions, establishing a correspondence between nonlinear Hall effects and Hopf invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.02972v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.107.L161102</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Yang Zhuang, Zhongbo Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
