<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 02:03:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking a superfluid harmonic dam: Observation and theory of rarefaction flow, Riemann invariants and sonic horizon dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dilute-gas Bose-Einstein condensates are a prime testbed for the study of superfluid hydrodynamics. In a channel geometry, these systems are known to host prototypical hydrodynamic effects such as shocks, rarefaction waves and solitons, forming a bridge between classical and quantum dynamics. Here, we present a combined experimental and theoretical study of the dry-bed dam-break problem in a channel geometry, a hallmark problem of nonlinear dynamics. Our setup extends the canonical setting by adding harmonic confinement, or an effective bathymetry, along the channel, further enhancing the richness of dynamics. We obtain an analytical solution of the 1D Gross-Pitaevskii (GP) equation for the harmonic dam-break problem that provides further insight. Experimentally, we characterize the flow by measuring its Riemann invariant coordinates and find good agreement with computations of the 3D GP equation as well as with the analytical solution. Our experimental observation of a sonic horizon, and the prediction of collisions between such horizons at longer times, offer an intriguing perspective for further studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23246v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashwat Sharan, Judith Gonzalez Sorribes, Patrick Sprenger, Mark A. Hoefer, P. Engels, Boaz Ilan, M. E. Mossman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical lattice quantum simulator of dynamics beyond Born-Oppenheimer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here, we propose a platform based on ultra-cold fermionic molecules trapped in optical lattices to simulate nonadiabatic effects as they appear in certain molecular dynamical problems. The idea consists in a judicious choice of two rotational states as the simulated electronic or nuclear degrees of freedom, in which their dipolar interactions induce the required attractive or repulsive interactions between them. We benchmark our proposal by studying the scattering of an electron or a proton against a hydrogen atom, showing the effect of electronic exchange and inelastic ionization as the mass ratio between the simulated nuclei and electrons (a tunable experimental parameter in our simulator) becomes comparable. These benchmarks illustrate how the simulator can qualitatively emulate phenomena like those appearing in molecular dynamical problems even if the simulated interaction occurs in two-dimensions with a dipolar scaling. Beyond the molecular implementation proposed here, our proposal can be readily extrapolated to other atomic platforms, e.g., based on fermionic Rydberg atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23464v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Arg\"uello-Luengo, Alejandro Gonz\'alez-Tudela, J. Ignacio Cirac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplitude mode at the superfluid-insulator transition on a random lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23499v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the superfluid-insulator quantum phase transition of interacting bosons by means of large-scale Monte Carlo simulations in the presence of both topological and generic quenched disorders. Recent work has demonstrated that the amplitude mode at this transition broadens and localizes in the presence of dilution disorder, whereas it remains a well-defined delocalized excitation for topological (connectivity) disorder. Here, we analyze the crossover between systems with purely topological disorder and systems with additional bond randomness to disentangle the roles that disorder and interactions play for amplitude mode localization. Specifically, we analyze the scalar susceptibility and its spectral density on both sides of the quantum phase transition. We also discuss the implications of our results for the potential observation of amplitude mode localization in experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23499v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishnu Pulloor Kuttanikkad, Rajesh Narayanan, Thomas Vojta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double commutator method for a two band Bose-Einstein condensate: superfluid density of a flat band superfluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23656v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a double commutator method for a general two-band bosonic superfluid. First and foremost, we prove that the sum of the superfluid and normal densities is equal to the weight of the f-sum rule. This weight can be easily determined by analyzing the ground state wave function. Once we have determined the excitation gap of the upper band, we can calculate the normal density by evaluating the average value of a double commutator between the velocity operator and the Hamiltonian. As an application of this method, we investigate the superfluid density of a flat band Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC). Using the Bogoliubov method, we calculate the sound velocity and excitation gap, which allows us to obtain the normal and superfluid densities explicitly. Our findings indicate that the superfluid density is directly proportional to the product of the square of the sound velocity and the compressibility. Furthermore, the existence of a non-vanishing superfluid density depends on the form of the interaction. For example, in the case of U(2) invariant interactions, the superfluid density is zero. Additionally, we have observed that for small interactions, the superfluid density is directly proportional to the product of the interaction parameter and the quantum metric. The double commutator method indicates that the correction of the excitation gap by interactions is the origin of the non-vanishing superfluid density of a flat band BEC. Up to the linear order of the interaction parameters, all the results for the excitation gap, the normal and superfluid densities in a flat band BEC can also be obtained through a simple perturbation theory. Our work provides another unique perspective on the superfluid behavior of a flat band BEC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23656v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Cai Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement-induced phase transitions for free fermions in a quasiperiodic potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamics under continuous measurements for free fermions in a quasiperiodic potential by using the Aubry-Andr\'{e}-Harper model with hopping rate $J$ and potential strength $V$. On the basis of the quantum trajectory method, we obtain the phase diagram for the steady-state entanglement entropy and demonstrate that robust logarithmic system-size scaling emerges up to a critical potential strength $V_c/J \sim 2.3$. Moreover, we find that the measurement induces entanglement phase transitions from the logarithmic-law phase to the area-law phase for the potential strength $V&lt; V_c$, while any finite measurement stabilizes the area-law phase for $V&gt;V_c$. This result is distinct from the entanglement scaling in the unitary limit, where volume-law and area-law phases undergo a transition at $V/J=2$. To further support the phase diagram, we analyze the connected correlation function and find that it shows algebraic decay in the logarithmic-law phase, while it decays quickly in the area-law phase. Our results can be tested in ultracold atoms by introducing quasiperiodic potentials and continuously monitoring the local occupation number with an off-resonant probe light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23807v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toranosuke Matsubara, Kazuki Yamamoto, Akihisa Koga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semisuper Efimov effect induced by resonant pair exchange in mixed dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new member to the class of semisuper Efimov effect, where infinite bound states emerge with their binding energies obeying the universal scaling law of $E_n\sim e^{-2(\pi n/\gamma)^2}$ for sufficiently high excitation $n\in\mathbb{N}$. Our system consists of a pair of two-component fermions in three dimensions at infinite scattering length, which furthermore interact with a boson confined in two dimensions so as to form a three-body bound state at zero energy. When another boson is added, exchange of the resonant pair of fermions between two bosons leads to the semisuper Efimov effect of such four particles with the scaling exponent $\gamma$ determined by the mass ratio of boson to fermion. If bosons live in three dimensions, infinite bound states do not emerge but some of them may survive for a large mass ratio, making our findings potentially relevant to two-neutron halo nuclei as well as ultracold atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23909v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Nishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How interacting Bose gases scatter light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The innate tendency of identical bosons to bunch, seen in the Hanbury Brown-Twiss effect and Bose-Einstein condensation, is a primary manifestation of quantum statistics. This tendency can enhance the rates of fundamental processes such as atom-atom and atom-light scattering if the atoms scatter into already occupied quantum states. For non-interacting bosons, the enhancement of light scattering is simply given by the bosonic-stimulation factor $1 + N_{\rm f}$, where $N_{\rm f}$ is the occupation of the atom's final momentum state. Here, we study scattering between off-resonant light and atoms in a quasi-homogeneous Bose gas with tunable interactions and show that even weak interactions, which do not significantly alter the momentum distribution, have a dramatic effect on the atom-light scattering. Due to (spatially local) beyond-mean-field atomic correlations, weak repulsive interactions can completely suppress the bosonic enhancement of scattering, while attractive ones increase the scattering rate. Moreover, if the interactions are rapidly tuned, light scattering reveals correlation dynamics that are orders of magnitude faster than the momentum-space population dynamics. Its extreme sensitivity to dynamical beyond-mean-field effects makes off-resonant light scattering a simple and powerful probe of many-body physics in ultracold atomic gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24386v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Konstantinou, Yansheng Zhang, Paul H. C. Wong, Feiyang Wang, Yu-Kun Lu, Nishant Dogra, Christoph Eigen, Tanish Satoor, Wolfgang Ketterle, Zoran Hadzibabic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the scaling properties of quasicrystalline potentials of eightfold rotational symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22213v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a special class of quasi-periodic potentials arising in the physics of photonic systems and possessing rotational symmetry of the 8th order. We are interested in the ``scaling'' properties of such potentials, namely, the growth rate of their closed level lines near the percolation threshold. Estimates of the corresponding scaling indices allow, in particular, to carry out some comparison of such potentials with various models of random potentials on the plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22213v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Ya. Maltsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-color magneto-optical trapping of ytterbium atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report laser cooling and trapping of ytterbium atoms in a two-color magneto-optical trap (MOT). Benefited from both the broad singlet transition ($^1\text{S}_0\rightarrow {}^1\text{P}_1$) and the narrow intercombination transition ($^1\text{S}_0\rightarrow {}^3\text{P}_1$) of ytterbium atoms, the two-color MOT enables rapid loading and efficient cooling. We systematically investigate the shielding effect of the intercombination transition by examining the atom loading and loss rates of single-color and two-color MOTs. Our findings are general and can be extended to other alkaline earth(-like) atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24383v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Li, Yufei Wang, Ligeng Yu, Bo Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual Phonon Universe in a Spinor Bose Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20267v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show the possibility of simulating a dual universe in a pseudospin-1/2 Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC), wherein two phononic modes experience distinct curved spacetime metrics. Through ramping the interspecies interaction of the BEC, we observe that one universe expands, and in the mean time, the other contracts. These findings can be directly verified in existing cold-atom experimental setups by detecting the correlators of the scaled density contrast (SDC): The sizes of the expanded/contracted universes can be deduced from the SDC's oscillating frequencies, while the expanding/contracting histories are reflected in the SDC's amplitude. Our study demonstrates the great potential of spinor BECs for exploring multiverse-related physics in laboratory settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20267v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiabin Wang, Yunfei Xue, Li Chen, Ren Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological effect on order-disorder transitions in U(1) sigma models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18969v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: U(1) non-linear sigma model (NLSM) with a one-dimensional (1D) Berry phase is studied by a renormalization group theory. Order-disorder transition in U(1) NLSMs in $D \!\ (\ge 2)$-dimensional space ($d+1$-dimensional spacetime; $d\ge 1$) is instigated by the proliferation of vortex excitations, where the 1D Berry phase term confers finite phase factors upon those vortex excitations that have finite projection in a subspace complementary to a topological direction with the 1D Berry phase. A destructive interference effect caused by the phase factors may help to develop an intermediate quasi-disorder phase between ordered and disorder phases, which has a divergent order-parameter correlation length along the topological direction, and a finite correlation length along the other directions. In order to explore such a possibility in $D=3$, we develop a perturbative renormalization group theory of a 3D model of vortex loops, in which loop segments interact via a $1/r$ Coulomb interaction. We derive renormalization group (RG) equations among vortex-loop fugacity, Berry phase term, and the Coulomb potential. Approximate analyses of the RG equations show that near an order-disorder transition point, vortex loops are anomalously elongated along the topological direction. Utilizing a duality mapping to a lattice model of a type-II superconductor under a magnetic field, we also argue that a global phase diagram of the 3D U(1) sigma model with 1D Berry phase must have the quasi-disorder phase between ordered and disorder phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18969v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryuichi Shindou, Pengwei Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
