<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 05:03:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced strong interaction effect in synthetic spin-orbit coupling with mixed spin symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07188v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Synthetic spin-orbit coupling in cold atoms couples the pseudo-spin and spatial degrees of freedom, and therefore the inherent spin symmetry of the system plays an important role. In systems of two pseudo-spin degrees, two particles contain symmetric states and anti-symmetric states, but the spin symmetry can be mixed for more particles. This mixed spin symmetry has been overlooked and has not been investigated thoroughly. We study the role of mixed spin symmetry in the presence of spin-orbit coupling and consider the system of three bosons with two hyper-fine states trapped in a harmonic potential. We investigate the ground state and the energy spectrum by implementing exact diagonalization. Similarly to two-particle systems, the interplay between spin-orbit coupling and repulsive interactions between anti-aligned pseudo-spins increases the population of the unaligned spin components in the ground state. Also, the emergence of the mixed spin symmetric states compensates for the rise of the interaction energy. In contrast to two-particle systems, the pair correlation of the ground state is analogous to the Tonks-Girardeau gas even for relatively small contact interactions, and this feature is enhanced by the spin-orbit coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07188v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.111.023305</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 111, 023305 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ayaka Usui, Abel Rojo-Franc\`as, James Schloss, Bruno Juli\'a-D\'iaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density-Dependent Gauge Field with Raman Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06777v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of the gauge field is an everlasting topic in modern physics. Spin-orbit coupling is a powerful tool in ultracold atomic systems, resulting in an artificial gauge field that can be easily manipulated and observed in a tabletop environment. Combining optical Raman lattices and atom-atom interaction, the artificial gauge field can be made density-dependent. In this work, we propose a straightforward way to engineer one-dimensional density-dependent gauge field in a Bose-Hubbard model in spin-orbit coupled Raman lattices. Next, we study the model from two perspectives: few-body quantum walk dynamics and many-body ground state. In the first perspective, we show that large spin-flipped tunneling can lead to a deep two-body bound state. In the second perspective, mean-field and density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) calculations consistently reveal three different phases, i.e. the Mott insulator phase, the superfluid phase, and the magnetic superfluid phase. Finally, we discuss the experimental protocol with Raman lattices based on existing experimental platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06777v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.111.013319</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xiang-Can Cheng, Zong-Yao Wang, Jinyi Zhang, Shuai Chen, Xiaotian Nie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of renormalized interactions using one-dimensional few-body systems as a testbed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10052v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Even though the one-dimensional contact interaction requires no regularization, renormalization methods have been shown to improve the convergence of numerical ab initio calculations considerably. In this work, we compare and contrast these methods: `the running coupling constant' where the two-body ground state energy is used as a renormalization condition, and two effective interaction approaches that include information about the ground as well as excited states. In particular, we calculate the energies and densities of few-fermion systems in a harmonic oscillator with the configuration interaction method, and compare the results based upon renormalized and bare interactions. We find that the use of the running coupling constant instead of the bare interaction improves convergence significantly. A comparison with an effective interaction, which is designed to reproduce the relative part of the energy spectrum of two particles, showed a similar improvement. The effective interaction provides an additional improvement if the center-of-mass excitations are included in the construction. Finally, we discuss the transformation of observables alongside the renormalization of the potential, and demonstrate that this might be an essential ingredient for accurate numerical calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10052v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.111.013303</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 111, 013303 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Brauneis, Hans-Werner Hammer, Stephanie M. Reimann, Artem G. Volosniev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-induced Josephson oscillations and self-trapping in a supersolid dipolar quantum gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17142v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Josephson effect characterizes superfluids and superconductors separated by a weak link, the so-called Josephson junction. A recent experiment has shown that Josephson oscillations can be observed also in a supersolid, where the weak link is not due to an external barrier, but is self-induced by interparticle interactions. Here we show theoretically that supersolids -- despite their self-induced character -- feature all the standard properties of bosonic Josephson junction arrays, including macroscopic quantum self-trapping. We focus on the harmonically trapped dipolar supersolids of interest for current experiments, and show that they can be described with a generalized Josephson model that takes into account spatial inhomogeneities. Our work shades new light on the dynamics of supersolids and opens the way to the study of a novel class of Josephson junctions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17142v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatrice Donelli, Nicol\`o Antolini, Giulio Biagioni, Marco Fattori, Andrea Fioretti, Carlo Gabbanini, Massimo Inguscio, Luca Tanzi, Giovanni Modugno, Augusto Smerzi, Luca Pezz\`e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical manifestations and bounds of topological Euler class</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07545v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze quantum-geometric bounds on optical weights in topological phases with pairs of bands hosting nontrivial Euler class, a multigap invariant characterizing non-Abelian band topology. We show how the bounds constrain the combined optical weights of the Euler bands at different dopings and further restrict the size of the adjacent band gaps. In this process, we also consider the associated interband contributions to dc conductivities in the flat-band limit. We physically validate these results by recasting the bound in terms of transition rates associated with the optical absorption of light, and demonstrate how the Euler connections and curvatures can be determined through the use of momentum and frequency-resolved optical measurements, allowing for a direct measurement of this multiband invariant. Additionally, we prove that the bound holds beyond the degenerate limit of Euler bands, resulting in nodal topology captured by the patch Euler class. In this context, we deduce optical manifestations of Euler topology within $\vec{k} \cdot \vec{p}$ models, which include quantized optical conductivity, and third-order jerk photoconductivities. We showcase our findings with numerical validation in lattice-regularized models that benchmark effective theories for real materials and are realizable in metamaterials and optical lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07545v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.L081103</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, L081103 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech J. Jankowski, Arthur S. Morris, Adrien Bouhon, F. Nur \"Unal, Robert-Jan Slager</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal correlations in chaotic many-body quantum states: Fock-space formulation of Berrys random wave model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10132v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The apparent randomness of chaotic eigenstates in interacting quantum systems hides subtle correlations dynamically imposed by their finite energy per particle. These correlations are revealed when Berrys approach for chaotic eigenfunctions in single-particle systems is lifted into many-body space. We achieve this by a many-body semiclassics analysis, appropriate for the mesoscopic regime of large but finite number of particles. We then identify the universality of both the cross-correlations and the Gaussian distribution of expansion coefficients as the signatures of chaotic eigenstates. Combined, these two aspects imprint a distinctive backbone to the morphology of eigenstates that we check against extensive quantum simulations. The universality of eigenstate correlations for fixed energy density is then a further signature of many-body quantum chaos that, while consistent with the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis, lies beyond random matrix theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10132v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.010404</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 010404, Published 2 January, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Florian Schoeppl, Remy Dubertrand, Juan-Diego Urbina, Klaus Richter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiparticle cooling algorithms for quantum many-body state preparation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12175v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Probing correlated states of many-body systems is one of the central tasks for quantum simulators and processors. A promising approach to state preparation is to realize desired correlated states as steady states of engineered dissipative evolution. A recent experiment with a Google superconducting quantum processor [X. Mi et al., Science 383, 1332 (2024)] demonstrated a cooling algorithm utilizing auxiliary degrees of freedom that are periodically reset to remove quasiparticles from the system, thereby driving it towards its ground state. In this work, we develop a kinetic theory framework to describe quasiparticle cooling dynamics, and employ it to compare the efficiency of different cooling algorithms. In particular, we introduce a protocol where coupling to auxiliaries is modulated in time to minimize heating processes, and demonstrate that it allows a high-fidelity preparation of ground states in different quantum phases. We verify the validity of the kinetic theory description by an extensive comparison with numerical simulations for the examples of a 1d transverse-field Ising model, the transverse-field Ising model with an additional integrability-breaking field, and a non-integrable antiferromagnetic Heisenberg spin ladder. In all cases we are able to efficiently cool into the many-body ground state. The effects of noise, which limits efficiency of variational quantum algorithms in near-term quantum processors, are investigated through the lens of the kinetic theory: we show how the steady state quasiparticle populations depend on the noise rate, and we establish maximum noise values for achieving high-fidelity ground states. This work establishes quasiparticle cooling algorithms as a practical, robust method for many-body state preparation on near-term quantum processors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12175v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jerome Lloyd, Alexios Michailidis, Xiao Mi, Vadim Smelyanskiy, Dmitry A. Abanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing lossy state preparation for quantum sensing using Hamiltonian engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00098v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: One of the most prominent platforms for demonstrating quantum sensing below the standard quantum limit is the spinor Bose-Einstein condensate. While a quantum advantage using several tens of thousands of atoms has been demonstrated in this platform, it faces an important challenge: atom loss. Atom loss is a Markovian error process modelled by Lindblad jump operators, and a no-go theorem, which we also show here, states that the loss of atoms in all spin components reduces the quantum advantage to a constant factor. Here, we show that this no-go theorem can be circumvented if we constrain atom losses to a single spin component. Moreover, we show that in this case, the maximum quantum Fisher information with $N$ atoms scales as $N^{3/2}$, establishing that a scalable quantum advantage can be achieved despite atom loss. Although Lindblad jump operators are generally non-Hermitian and non-invertible, we use their Moore-Penrose inverse to develop a framework for constructing several states with this scaling of Fisher information in the presence of losses. We use Hamiltonian engineering with realistic Hamiltonians to develop experimental protocols for preparing these states. Finally, we discuss possible experimental techniques to constrain the losses to a single spin mode.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00098v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bharath Hebbe Madhusudhana</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
