<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 05:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A coreless giant vortex in a very strongly dipolar condensate of NaCs molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09903v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A strongly dipolar $^{164}$Dy condensate of dipolar length $a_{\mathrm{dd}}=130.8a_0$, with $a_0$ the Bohr radius, hosts a wide variety of eigenstates, such as droplet, droplet-lattice, and ring-topology states, and self-bound droplets. Motivated by the observation of a very strongly dipolar condensate of NaCs molecules [Bigagli N et al. 2024 Nature 631 289], we demonstrate by numerical simulation, using an improved mean-field model, including the Lee-Huang-Yang interaction, that in a very strongly dipolar NaCs condensate with $a_{\mathrm{dd}} = 2000a_0$, most of the above-mentioned states continue to exist and can appear for a much smaller number $N$ of particles ($N \lessapprox 1000$) within the present experimental possibility. However, in a single-component harmonically-trapped rotating NaCs condensate, a new type of coreless giant-vortex states, with a phase drop of $2 \pi L$ along a closed path around the axis of rotation, appear, where $L$ is the angular momentum of the vortex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09903v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S K Adhikari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary superfluids: low-energy properties and dissipative processes from spontaneous emission of massive phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10194v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss the low-energy properties of binary superfluids with density-dependent interactions. Adding an intra-species coupling that induces an explicit soft symmetry-breaking, we determine the background pressure and we show that the low-energy spectrum consists of a massless Nambu- Goldstone boson and a massive (pseudo) Nambu-Goldstone boson. When the background velocities of the two superfluids are transonic, the system is characterized by two distinct acoustic horizons: the hydrodynamic analogue of the black hole event horizon. The Hawking-like emission occurring at these horizons produces an effective friction on the fluids. We compute the viscosity-to-entropy ratios close to the two acoustic horizons, finding that the emission of pseudo Nambu-Goldstone bosons violates the bound conjectured by Kovtun, Son and Starinet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10194v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Trabucco, Luca Lepori, Maria Luisa Chiofalo, Massimo Mannarelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Assembled Chains and Solids of Dipolar Atoms in a Multilayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14511v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We predict that ultracold bosonic dipolar gases, confined within a multilayer geometry, may undergo self-assembling processes, leading to the formation of chain gases and solids. These dipolar chains, with dipoles aligned across different layers, emerge at low densities and resemble phases observed in liquid crystals, such as nematic and smectic phases. We calculate the phase diagram using quantum Monte Carlo methods, introducing a newly devised trial wave function designed for describing the chain gas, where dipoles from different layers form chains without in-plane long-range order. We find gas, solid, and chain phases, along with quantum phase transitions between these states. Specifically, we predict the existence of quantum phase transitions from gaseous to self-ordered phases, as the interlayer distance is decreased. Remarkably, in the self-organized phases, the mean interparticle distance can significantly exceed the characteristic length of the interaction potential, yielding solids and chain gases with densities several orders of magnitude lower than those of conventional quantum solids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14511v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.233402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 233402 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. Guijarro, G. E. Astrakharchik, G. Morigi, J. Boronat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-linear regime of atomic arrays at low drive intensity: controlled generation of multiple subradiant excitations via a multi-photon resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01386v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Atomic arrays have emerged as an interesting light-matter platform displaying strong and controllable collective effects. In subwavelength regimes, they are characterized by a manifold of subradiant eigenstates, which can host rich quantum many-body physics and might be useful for applications. Nevertheless, their controlled excitation by a weak coherent drive is prevented by their subradiant nature. While this is true at a linear level, and although the weak-drive regime has been often described using linear theories, we point out that this regime is instead strongly non-linear for regular arrays. Using a dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) approach, we show that by driving weakly a non-linear two-particle resonance, a steady-state with a controlled population of subradiant modes can be obtained. This features a non-zero density of interacting subradiant excitations, displaying multi-mode squeezing correlations and long-range correlations that survive many-body heating effects, even at non-zero drive intensities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01386v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Orazio Scarlatella, Nigel R. Cooper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normal liquid $^3$He studied by Path Integral Monte Carlo with a parametrized partition function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01569v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the energy per particle of normal liquid ${}^3$He in the temperature range $0.15-2$ K using Path Integral Monte Carlo simulations, leveraging a recently proposed method to overcome the sign problem -- a long-standing challenge in many-body fermionic simulations. This approach is based on introducing a parameter $\xi$ into the partition function, which allows a generalization from bosons ($\xi=1$) to fermions ($\xi=-1$). By simulating systems with $\xi \geq 0$, where the sign problem is absent, one can then extrapolate to the fermionic case at $\xi = -1$. Guided by an independent particle model that uncovers non-analytic behavior due to the superfluid transition, which is moderated by finite-size effects, we develop a tailored extrapolation strategy for liquid ${}^3$He that departs from the extrapolation schemes shown to be accurate in those cases were quantum degeneracy effects are weak, and enables accurate results in the presence of Bose-Einstein Condensation and superfluidity for $\xi &gt; 0$. Our approach extends the previously proposed framework and yields energy per particle values in good agreement with experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01569v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Morresi, Giovanni Garberoglio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-equilibrium Dynamics of Fermi Polarons Driven by Time-dependent Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08444v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically studied the dynamics of Fermi polarons driven by time-dependent scattering length using a time-dependent variational method. Starting from the non-interacting initial state, we calculated the evolution behavior of the contact, energy, and quasiparticle residue of this system as the scattering length $a_s(t)$ increases from zero. In the short-time evolution, we obtained analytical results, verifying that when $a_s(t)$ grows as $\sqrt{t}$, the contact $C(t)$ and energy $E(t)$ exhibit the maximum growth rate. Furthermore, we numerically solved the long-time evolution, when $a_s(t)$ is diven with a strength $\beta$ and a power $\alpha$ as $a_s(t) = {\sqrt{2}\beta}/{k_F} {(\epsilon_Ft)}^{\alpha}$. For large driving strength, due to the interference between the polaron states and the non-interacting states, $C(t)$ and $Z(t)$ exhibit oscillatory behavior; For small $\beta$, the oscillatory behavior disappears due to the decay of the repulsive polaron into the continuum, and $C(t)$ and $Z(t)$ gradually relax to zero. The energy always saturates over long times for different driving strength. Additionally, our method is applicable to any time-dependent form of the scattering length.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08444v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Yang, Ran Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Hierarchical Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13519v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The capacity to custom tailor the properties of quantum matter and materials is a central requirement for enlarging their range of possible functionalities. A particularly promising route is the use of driving protocols to engineer specific desired properties with a high degree of control and flexibility. Here, we present such a program for the tunable generation of sequences of symmetries on controllable timescales. Concretely, our general driving protocol for many-body systems generates a sequence of prethermal regimes, each exhibiting a lower symmetry than the preceding one. We provide an explicit construction of effective Hamiltonians exhibiting these symmetries, which imprints emergent quasiconservation laws hierarchically, enabling us to engineer the respective symmetries and concomitant orders in nonequilibrium matter. We provide explicit examples, including spatiotemporal and topological phenomena, as well as a spin chain realizing the symmetry ladder $\text{SU(2)}{\rightarrow}\text{U(1)} {\rightarrow} \mathbb{Z}_2{\rightarrow} E$. Our results have direct applications in experiments with quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13519v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevX.14.041070</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. X 14, 041070 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhanpeng Fu, Roderich Moessner, Hongzheng Zhao, Marin Bukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact eigenstates with off-diagonal long-range order for interacting bosonic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11509v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fermions and hardcore bosons share the same restriction: no more than one particle can occupy a single site in a lattice system. Specifically, in one dimension, two systems can share the same matrix representation. In this work, we investigate both the fermion and hardcore-boson models with nearest-neighbor (NN) interaction in a ring lattice. We construct the exact eigenstates of the hardcore-boson model with resonant NN interaction and show that they possess off-diagonal long-range order (ODLRO) in the thermodynamic limit. In comparison, the fermionic counterpart does not support such a feature due to the different particle statistics, although they share an identical energy spectrum. In addition, we examine the effect of the periodic boundary condition on the dynamics of the condensate states through numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11509v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. H. Zhang, Z. Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
