<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas</link>
    <description>cond-mat.quant-gas updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.quant-gas" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 05:03:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleation and wetting transitions in three-component Bose-Einstein condensates in Gross-Pitaevskii theory: exact results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21220v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nucleation and wetting transitions are studied in a three-component Bose-Einstein condensate mixture within Gross-Pitaevskii theory. For special cases of intermediate segregation between components 1 and 2, the nucleation phase transition of a surfactant film of component 3 is obtained by exact solution. Additional exact results for the nucleation transition are derived in the limit of strong segregation between components 1 and 2. In this limit the exact first-order wetting phase boundary is obtained using analytical and numerical methods, and is contrasted with the exact nucleation and wetting phase boundary derived previously for a two-component Bose-Einstein condensate mixture at a hard optical wall. Exact results for the three-component mixture are compared with results from the double-parabola approximation used in an earlier work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21220v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Berx, Nguyen Van Thu, Joseph O. Indekeu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of interacting bosons in a two-leg ring ladder with artificial magnetic flux and ac-driven modulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nonequilibrium dynamics of interacting bosons in a two-leg ring ladder pierced by an artificial magnetic flux, where the particles are initially localized in the central sites of both rings, and the ac-driven local energy shifts are applied to the remaining lattice sites. Within the mean-field approximation, we demonstrate the emergence of nonlinear self-trapping for strong interparticle interactions, and characterize the distinct excitation regimes in the absence of the inter-ring tunneling. The artificial magnetic flux typically introduces Peierls phase factors, which induces complex-valued hopping amplitudes and leads to directed net particle currents along the chains. By further incorporating the finite inter-ring coupling and biased intra-ring hopping, we reveal that the tuning of the drive frequency and Peierls phase allows the precise control over both the intensity and direction of particle currents, which facilitates the transition between chiral and antichiral dynamics. These findings offer insights into the coherent manipulation of matter-wave transports in closed-loop lattice configurations and the exploration of nonequilibrium synthetic quantum systems in related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21445v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Q. Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time Monitoring of Neon Film Growth for Electron-on-Neon Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20765v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electron-on-neon (eNe) charge states coupled to superconducting circuits are a promising platform for quantum computing. Control over the formation of these charge states requires techniques to track and control the growth of solid Ne films on the circuit surface. We demonstrate a real-time Ne film-growth monitor using high-transition-temperature (high-$T_c$) YBCO microwave resonators. The high $T_c$ enables tracking of the film thickness near Ne's triple temperature and below. Across more than 300 solidification experiments, we find that the final Ne thickness varies stochastically from a few nm to a few $\mu$m for films solidified from the liquid phase. By increasing the driving power in the resonator, we consistently reduce the final thickness to below 100 nm. These results represent an important step toward controlled formation of Ne films for eNe qubits and highlight the broader utility of high-$T_c$ resonators for hybrid quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20765v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sidharth Duthaluru, Kaiwen Zheng, Erik A. Henriksen, Kater W. Murch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kibble-Zurek Meets Tricriticality: Breakdown of Adiabatic-Impulse and New Scaling Forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21386v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Kibble-Zurek effect is studied around a tricritical point, where the adiabatic-impulse scenario breaks down. Several new scaling forms are also proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21386v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/0256-307X/43/1/010001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chin. Phys. Lett. 43, 010001 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chengshu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichroism from Thermoelectric Chiral Drives: Generalized Sum Rules for Orbital and Heat Magnetizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21599v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a unified framework that relates orbital and heat magnetizations to experimentally accessible excitation spectra, through thermoelectric probes and generalized sum rules. By analyzing zero-temperature transport coefficients and applying Kramers-Kronig relations, we derive spectral representations of magnetization densities from thermoelectric correlation functions. Excitation rates under thermoelectric chiral drives then naturally emerge as direct probes of these Kubo-type correlators, placing orbital and heat magnetizations on equal footing with the topological Chern number. As a direct consequence of our formalism, we introduce a hierarchical construction that organizes orbital and heat magnetizations into distinct physical contributions accessible through sum rules, and also derive real-space markers of these magnetizations. From an experimental standpoint, we propose concrete implementations of thermoelectric dichroic measurements in quantum-engineered platforms based on modulated strain fields. These results establish thermoelectric dichroic measurements as a versatile route to access and disentangle fundamental ground-state properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21599v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Bermond, Lucila Peralta Gavensky, Ana\"is Defossez, Nathan Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double Supersolid Phase in a Bosonic t-J-V Model with Rydberg Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16820v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in Rydberg tweezer arrays bring novel opportunities for programmable quantum simulations beyond previous capabilities. In this work, we investigate a bosonic t-J-V model currently realized with Rydberg atoms. Through large-scale quantum Monte Carlo simulations, we uncover an emergent double supersolid (DSS) phase with the coexistence of two superfluids and crystalline order. Tunable long-range tunneling and repulsive hole-hole interactions enable a rich phase diagram featuring a double superfluid phase, a DSS phase, and an antiferromagnetic insulator. Intriguingly, within the DSS regime we observe an unconventional thermal enhancement of crystalline order. Our results establish the bosonic t-J-V model as a promising and experimentally accessible platform for exploring exotic quantum phases in Rydberg atom arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16820v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuangjie Chen, Yang Qi, Zheng Yan, Xiaopeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiply quantized vortex spectroscopy in a quantum fluid of light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14539v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The formation of quantized vortices is a unifying feature of quantum mechanical systems, making it a premier means for fundamental and comparative studies of different quantum fluids. Being excited states of motion, vortices are normally unstable towards relaxation into lower energy states. However, here we exploit the driven-dissipative nature of polaritonic fluids of light to create stationary, multiply charged vortices. We measure the spectrum of collective excitations and observe negative energy modes at the core and positive energy modes at large radii. Their coexistence at the same frequency normally causes the dynamical instability, but here intrinsic losses stabilize the system, allowing for phase pinning by the pump on macroscopic scales. We observe generic features of quantized vortices in quantum fluids and other rotating geometries like astrophysical compact objects, opening the way to the study of generic amplification phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14539v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Killian Guerrero, Kevin Falque, Elisabeth Giacobino, Alberto Bramati, Maxime J Jacquet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal efficiency boost in prethermal quantum heat engines at negative temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02044v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Heat engines near the adiabatic limit typically assume a working medium at thermal equilibrium. However, quantum many-body systems often showcase conservation laws that hinder thermalization, leading to prethermalization in exotic stationary phases. This work explores whether prethermalization enhances or reduces engine efficiency. We investigate Otto cycles in quantum systems with varying numbers of conserved quantities. We find that additional conservation laws reduce efficiency at positive temperatures, but enhance it in regimes of negative temperatures. Our findings stem from general thermodynamic inequalities for infinitesimal cycles, and we provide evidence for integrable models undergoing finite cycles using the theoretical framework of Generalized Hydrodynamics. The relevance of our results for quantum simulators is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02044v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-66424-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, 10593 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Brollo, Adolfo del Campo, Alvise Bastianello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity entanglement and coherent multi-qubit mapping in an atom array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13632v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutral atoms in optical tweezer arrays possess broad applicability for quantum information science, in computing, simulation, and metrology. Among atomic species, Ytterbium-171 is unique as it hosts multiple qubits, each of which is impactful for these distinct applications. Consequently, this atom is an ideal candidate to bridge multiple disciplines, which, more broadly, has been an increasingly effective strategy within the field of quantum science. Realizing the full potential of this synergy requires high-fidelity generation and transfer of many-particle entanglement between these distinct qubit degrees of freedom, and thus between these distinct applications. Here we demonstrate the creation and coherent mapping of entangled quantum states across multiple qubits in Ytterbium-171 tweezer arrays. We map entangled states onto the optical clock qubit from the nuclear spin qubit or the Rydberg qubit. We coherently transfer up to 20 atoms of a $Z_2$-ordered Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state from the interacting Rydberg manifold to the metastable nuclear spin manifold. The many-body state is generated via a novel disorder-robust pulse in a two-dimensional ladder geometry. We further find that clock-qubit-based spin detection applied to Rydberg and nuclear spin qubits facilitates atom-loss-detectable qubit measurements and $&gt;90\%$ Rydberg decay detection. This enables mid-circuit and delayed erasure detection, yielding an error-detected two-qubit gate fidelity of $99.78(4)\%$ in the metastable qubits. This error detection also enables Rydberg qubit evolution with an effective lifetime of $1.2(2)$ ms, enhancing the fidelity of the observed many-body dynamics. These results establish a versatile architecture that advances multiple fields of quantum information science while also establishing bridges between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13632v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aruku Senoo, Alexander Baumg\"artner, Joanna W. Lis, Gaurav M. Vaidya, Zhongda Zeng, Giuliano Giudici, Hannes Pichler, Adam M. Kaufman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
