<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 02:07:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Maximizing Riesz capacity ratios: conjectures and theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A shape optimization program is developed for the ratio of Riesz capacities $\text{Cap}_q(K)/\text{Cap}_p(K)$, where $K$ ranges over compact sets in $\mathbb{R}^n$. In different regions of the $pq$-parameter plane, maximality is conjectured for the ball, the vertices of a regular simplex, or the endpoints of an interval. These cases are separated by a symmetry-breaking transition region where the shape of maximizers remains unclear.
  On the boundary of $pq$-parameter space one encounters existing theorems and conjectures, including: Watanabe's theorem minimizing Riesz capacity for given volume, the classical isodiametric theorem that maximizes volume for given diameter, Szeg\H{o}'s isodiametric theorem maximizing Newtonian capacity for given diameter, and the still-open isodiametric conjecture for Riesz capacity. The first quadrant of parameter space contains P\'{o}lya and Szeg\H{o}'s conjecture on maximizing Newtonian over logarithmic capacity for planar sets. The maximal shape for each of these scenarios is known or conjectured to be the ball.
  In the third quadrant, where both $p$ and $q$ are negative, the maximizers are quite different: when one of the parameters is $-\infty$ and the other is suitably negative, maximality is proved for the vertices of a regular simplex or endpoints of an interval. Much more is proved in dimensions $1$ and $2$, where for large regions of the third quadrant, maximizers are shown to consist of the vertices of intervals or equilateral triangles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14809v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carrie Clark, Richard S. Laugesen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bidiagonal factorization of recurrence banded matrices in mixed multiple orthogonality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper demonstrates how to explicitly construct a bidiagonal factorization of the banded recurrence matrix that appears in mixed multiple orthogonality on the step-line in terms of the coeffcients of the mixed multiple orthogonal polynomials. The construction is based on the \(LU\) factorization of the moment matrix and Christoffel transformations applied to the matrix of measures and the associated mixed multiple orthogonal polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15363v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Am\'ilcar Branquinho, Juan EF D\'iaz, Ana Foulqui\'e-Moreno, H\'elder Lima, Manuel Ma\~nas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bailey pairs and an identity of Chern-Li-Stanton-Xue-Yee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15408v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show how Bailey pairs can be used to give a simple proof of an identity of Chern, Li, Stanton, Xue, and Yee. The same method yields a number of related identities as well as false theta companions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15408v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashank Kanade, Jeremy Lovejoy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restricted weighted weak boundedness for product type operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a bilinear (or sub-bilinear) operator $B$, we prove restricted weighted weak type inequalities of the form $$ ||B(f_1, f_2)||_{L^{p, \infty}(w_1^{p/p_1}w_2^{p/p_2})}\lesssim ||f_1||_{L^{p_1, 1}(w_1)}||f_2||_{L^{p_2, 1}(w_2)}, $$ whenever $B(f_1, f_2)= (T_1f_1) (T_2 f_2)$ is the product of two singular integral operators satisfying Dini conditions. Additionally, we also establish, as an application, the boundedness of a certain class of bounded variation bilinear Fourier multipliers solving a question posted in [Bilinear Fourier multipliers of bounded variation; Int. Math. Res. Not. (2023), no.24, 21943--21975 by Baena-Miret, Carro, Luque and Sanchez-Pascuala].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15759v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mar\'ia Jes\'us Carro, Sheldy Ombrosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A short proof on the boundedness of triangular Hilbert transform along curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15791v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a short and elementary proof of the boundedness of triangular Hilbert transform along non-flat curves definable in a polynomially bounded o-minimal structure. We also provide a criterion on the multiplier to determine whether the associated fiber-wisely defined bilinear operator admits a smoothing inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15791v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Hsu, Fred Yu-Hsiang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the equality of generalized Bajraktarevi\'c means under first-order differentiability assumptions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16074v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the equality problem of generalized Bajraktarevi\'c means, i.e., we are going to solve the functional equation \begin{equation}\label{E0}\tag{*}
  f^{(-1)}\bigg(\frac{p_1(x_1)f(x_1)+\dots+p_n(x_n)f(x_n)}{p_1(x_1)+\dots+p_n(x_n)}\bigg)=g^{(-1)}\bigg(\frac{q_1(x_1)g(x_1)+\dots+q_n(x_n)g(x_n)}{q_1(x_1)+\dots+q_n(x_n)}\bigg), \end{equation} which holds for all $x=(x_1,\dots,x_n)\in I^n$, where $n\geq 2$, $I$ is a nonempty open real interval, the unknown functions $f,g:I\to\mathbb{R}$ are strictly monotone, $f^{(-1)}$ and $g^{(-1)}$ denote their generalized left inverses, respectively, and the vector-valued weight functions $p=(p_1,\dots,p_n):I\to\mathbb{R}_{+}^n$ and $q=(q_1,\dots,q_n):I\to\mathbb{R}_{+}^n$ are also unknown. This equality problem in the symmetric two-variable case (i.e., when $n=2$ and $p_1=p_2$, $q_1=q_2$) was solved under sixth-order regularity assumptions by Losonczi in 1999. The authors of this paper improved this result in 2023 by reaching the same conclusion assuming only first-order differentiability. In the nonsymmetric case, assuming third-order differentiability of $f$, $g$ and the first-order differentiability of at least three of the functions $p_1,\dots,p_n$, Gr\"unwald and P\'ales proved that \eq{0} holds if and only if there exist four constants $a,b,c,d\in\mathbb{R}$ with $ad\neq bc$ such that $$
  cf+d&gt;0,\qquad
  g=\frac{af+b}{cf+d},\qquad\mbox{and}\qquad q_\ell=(cf+d)p_\ell\qquad (\ell\in\{1,\dots,n\}). $$ The main goal of this paper is to establish the same conclusion under first-order differentiability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16074v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zsolt P\'ales, Amr Zakaria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal approximation results for neural networks with non-polynomial activation function over non-compact domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14759v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we generalize the universal approximation property of single-hidden-layer feed-forward neural networks beyond the classical formulation over compact domains. More precisely, by assuming that the activation function is non-polynomial, we derive universal approximation results for neural networks within function spaces over non-compact subsets of a Euclidean space, e.g., weighted spaces, $L^p$-spaces, and (weighted) Sobolev spaces over unbounded domains, where the latter includes the approximation of the (weak) derivatives. Furthermore, we provide some dimension-independent rates for approximating a function with sufficiently regular and integrable Fourier transform by neural networks with non-polynomial activation function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14759v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Neufeld, Philipp Schmocker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On rectifiability of Delone sets in intermediate regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14933v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we deal with Delone sets and their rectifiability under different classes of regularity. By pursuing techniques developed by Rivi\`ere and Ye, and Aliste-Prieto, Coronel and Gambaudo, we give sufficient conditions for a Delone set to be equivalent to the standard lattice by bijections having regularity in between bi-Lipschitz and bi-H\"older-homogeneous. From this criterion, we improve a result of McMullen by showing that, for any dimension $d\geq 1$, there exists a threshold of moduli of continuity $\mathcal{M}_d$, including the class of the H\"{o}lder ones, such that for every $\omega\in\mathcal{M}_d$, any two Delone sets in $\mathbb{R}^d$ cannot be distinguished under bi-$\omega$-equivalence. Also, we extend a result due to Aliste, Coronel, and Gambaudo, which establishes that every linearly repetitive Delone set in $\mathbb{R}^d$ is rectifiable by extending it to a broader class of repetitive behaviors. Moreover, we show that for the modulus of continuity $\omega(t)=t(\log(1/t))^{1/d}$, every $\omega$-repetitive Delone set in $\mathbb{R}^d$ is equivalent to the standard lattice by a bi-$\omega$-homogeneous map. Finally, we address a problem of continuous nature related to the previous ones about finding solutions to the prescribed volume form equation in intermediate regularity, thereby extending the results of Rivi\`ere and Ye.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14933v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irene Inoquio-Renteria, Rodolfo Viera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is an inductive mean?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15717v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An inductive mean is a mean defined as a limit of a convergence sequence of other means. Historically, this notion of inductive means obtained as limits of sequences was pioneered independently by Lagrange and Gauss for defining the arithmetic-geometric mean. In this note, we first explain several generalizations of the scalar geometric mean to symmetric positive-definite matrices, and then present several inductive mean mechanisms for sets of symmetric positive-definite matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15717v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1090/noti2832</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Notices of the American Mathematical Society, volume 70, number 11, pages 1851-1855, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Frank Nielsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral theoretic characterisation of Markov chain convergence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15829v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we characterise the statistics of Markov chains by constructing an associated sequence of periodic differential operators. Studying the density of states of these operators reveals the absolutely continuous invariant measure of the Markov chain. This approach also leads to a direct proof of convergence to the invariant measure, along with explicit convergence rates. We show how our method can be applied to a class of related Markov chains including the logistic map, the tent map and Chebyshev maps of arbitrary order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15829v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bryn Davies, Yu Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On finite configurations in the spectra of singular measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.12036v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish various forms of the following certainty principle: a set $S \subset \mathbb{R}^{n}$ contains a given finite linear pattern, provided that $S$ is a support of the Fourier transform of a sufficiently singular probability measure on $\mathbb{R}^{n}$. As its main corollary, we provide new dimensional estimates for PDE- and Fourier-constrained vector measures. Those results, in certain cases of restrictions given by homogeneous operators, improve known bounds related to the notion of the $k$-wave cone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.12036v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rami Ayoush</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular examples of the Matrix Bochner Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.14305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.14305v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Matrix Bochner Problem aims to classify which weight matrices have their sequence of orthogonal polynomials as eigenfunctions of a second-order differential operator. Casper and Yakimov, in [4], demonstrated that, under certain hypotheses, all solutions to the Matrix Bochner Problem are noncommutative bispectral Darboux transformations of a direct sum of classical scalar weights. This paper aims to provide the first proof that there are solutions to the Matrix Bochner Problem that do not arise through a noncommutative bispectral Darboux transformation of any direct sum of classical scalar weights. This initial example could contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of the general solution to the Matrix Bochner Problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.14305v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jat.2024.106082</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Approximation Theory (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio Bono Parisi, In\'es Pacharoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Power-Weighted Birman--Hardy--Rellich-type Inequalities on Finite Intervals and Annuli</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01884v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive an optimal power-weighted Hardy-type inequality in integral form on finite intervals and subsequently prove the analogous inequality in differential form. We note that the optimal constant of the latter inequality differs from the former. Moreover, by iterating these inequalities we derive the sequence of power-weighted Birman-Hardy-Rellich-type inequalities in integral form on finite intervals and then also prove the analogous sequence of inequalities in differential form.
  We use the one-dimensional Hardy-type result in differential form to derive an optimal multi-dimensional version of the power-weighted Hardy inequality in differential form on annuli (i.e., spherical shell domains), and once more employ an iteration procedure to derive the Birman-Hardy-Rellich-type sequence of power-weighted higher-order Hardy-type inequalities for annuli.
  In the limit as the annulus approaches $\mathbb{R}^n$, we recover well-known prior results on Rellich-type inequalities on $\mathbb{R}^n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01884v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fritz Gesztesy, Michael M. H. Pang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear non-periodic homogenization: Existence, local uniqueness and estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06705v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider periodic homogenization with localized defects of boundary value problems for semilinear ODE systems of the type $$ \Big((A(x/\varepsilon)+B(x/\varepsilon))u'(x)+c(x,u(x))\Big)'= d(x,u(x)) \mbox{ for } x \in (0,1),\; u(0)=u(1)=0. $$ For small $\varepsilon&gt;0$ we show existence of weak solutions $u=u_\varepsilon$ as well as their local uniqueness for $\|u-u_0\|_\infty \approx 0$, where $u=u_0$ is a given solution to the homogenized problem $$ \Big(A_0u'+c(x,u(x))\Big)'= d(x,u(x)) \mbox{ for } x \in (0,1),\; u(0)=u(1)=0,\; A_0:=\left(\int_0^1A(y)^{-1}dy\right)^{-1} $$ such that the linearized problem $$ \Big(A_0u'+\partial_uc(x,u_0(x))u(x)\Big)'= \partial_ud(x,u_0(x))u(x) \mbox{ for } x \in (0,1),\; u(0)=u(1)=0 $$ does not have weak solutions $u\not=0$. Further, we prove that $\|u_\varepsilon-u_0\|_\infty\to 0$ and, if $c(\cdot,u)\in W^{1,\infty}((0,1);\mathbb{R}^n)$, that $\|u_\varepsilon-u_0\|_\infty=O(\varepsilon)$ for $\varepsilon \to 0$.
  We assume that $A \in L^\infty(\mathbb{R};\mathbb{M}_n)$ is 1-periodic, $B \in L^\infty(\mathbb{R};\mathbb{M}_n)\cap L^1(\mathbb{R};\mathbb{M}_n)$, $A(y)$ and $A(y)+B(y)$ are positive definite uniformly with respect to $y$, $c(x,\cdot),d(x,\cdot)\in C^1(\mathbb{R}^n;\mathbb{R}^n)$ and $c(\cdot,u),d(\cdot,u) \in L^\infty((0,1);\mathbb{R}^n)$.
  The main tool of the proofs is an abstract result of implicit function theorem type which has been tailored for applications to nonlinear singular perturbation and homogenization problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06705v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lutz Recke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal Fourier Analysis on Domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15361v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we go over the history of the Fuglede or Spectral Set Conjecture as it has developed over the last 30 years or so. We do not aim to be exhaustive and we do not cover important areas of development such as the results on the problem in classes of finite groups or the version of the problem that focuses on spectral measures instead of sets. The selection of the material has been strongly influenced by personal taste, history and capabilities. We are trying to be more descriptive than detailed and we point out several open questions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15361v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mihail N. Kolountzakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carnot rectifiability and Alberti representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.01376v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A metric measure space is said to be Carnot-rectifiable if it can be covered up to a null set by countably many biLipschitz images of compact sets of a fixed Carnot group. In this paper, we give several characterisations of such notion of rectifiability both in terms of Alberti representations of the measure and in terms of differentiability of Lipschitz maps with values in Carnot groups.
  In order to obtain this characterisation, we develop and study the analogue of the notion of Lipschitz differentiability space by Cheeger, using Carnot groups and Pansu derivatives as models. We call such metric measure spaces Pansu differentiability spaces (PDS).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.01376v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gioacchino Antonelli, Enrico Le Donne, Andrea Merlo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic approximations for the distribution of the product of correlated normal random variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07734v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We obtain asymptotic approximations for the probability density function of the product of two correlated normal random variables with non-zero means and arbitrary variances. As a consequence, we deduce asymptotic approximations for the tail probabilities and quantile functions of this distribution, as well as an asymptotic approximation for the widely used risk measures value at risk and tail value at risk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07734v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert E. Gaunt, Zixin Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirichlet spaces over chord-arc domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11577v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: If $U$ is a $C^{\infty}$ function with compact support in the plane, we let $u$ be its restriction to the unit circle $\mathbb{S}$, and denote by $U_i,\,U_e$ the harmonic extensions of $u$ respectively in the interior and the exterior of $\mathbb S$ on the Riemann sphere. About a hundred years ago, Douglas has shown that \begin{align*}
  \iint_{\mathbb{D}}|\nabla U_i|^2(z)dxdy&amp;= \iint_{\bar{\mathbb{C}}\backslash\bar{\mathbb{D}}}|\nabla U_e|^2(z)dxdy
  &amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi}\iint_{\mathbb S\times\mathbb S}\left|\frac{u(z_1)-u(z_2)}{z_1-z_2}\right|^2|dz_1||dz_2|, \end{align*} thus giving three ways to express the Dirichlet norm of $u$. On a rectifiable Jordan curve $\Gamma$ we have obvious analogues of these three expressions, which will of course not be equal in general. The main goal of this paper is to show that these $3$ (semi-)norms are equivalent if and only if $\Gamma$ is a chord-arc curve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11577v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00208-024-02946-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Huaying Wei, Michel Zinsmeister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Lebesgue measure of one generalised set of subsums of geometric series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00694v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present paper, we study a set that can be treated as a generalised set of subsums for a geometric series. This object was discovered independently in various mathematical aspects. For instance, it is closely related to various systems of representation of real numbers. The main object of this paper was particularly studied by R. Kenyon, who brought up a question about the Lebesgue measure of the set and conjectured that it is positive. Further, Z. Nitecki confirmed the hypothesis by using nontrivial topological techniques. However, the aforementioned result is quite limited, as this particular case should satisfy a rigid condition of homogeneity. Despite the limited progress, the problem remained understudied in a general framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00694v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Makarchuk, Dmytro Karvatskyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
