<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 06:57:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>High-low analysis and small cap decoupling over non-Archimedean local fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a small cap decoupling theorem for the parabola over a general non-Archimedean local field for which $2\neq 0$. We obtain polylogarithmic dependence on the scale parameter $R$ and polynomial dependence in the residue prime, except for the prime 2 for which the polynomial depends on degree. Our constants are fully explicit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09163v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Johnsrude</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the product of the extreme zeros of Laguerre polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The purpose of this note is twofold: firstly, it intends to bring to light an apparently unknown property of the product of the extreme zeros of Laguerre polynomials, which in a very particular case leads to a twenty-year-old conjecture for Hermite polynomials posed by Gazeau, Josse-Michaux, and Moncea while developing numerical methods in quantum mechanics; and secondly to progress towards the solution of this problem as an application of a parametric eigenvalue problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09405v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Castillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The number of real zeros of polynomials with constrained coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use Jensen's formula to give an upper bound for the number of real zeros of polynomials with constrained coefficients. We prove that there is an absolute constant $c &gt; 0$ such that every polynomial $P$ of the form $$P(z) = \sum_{j=0}^{n}{a_jz^j}\,, \quad |a_0| = 1\,, \quad |a_j| \leq M\,, \quad a_j \in \Bbb{C}\,, \quad M \geq 1\,,$$ has at most $cn^{1/2}(1+\log M)^{1/2}$ zeros in the interval $[-1,1]$. This result is sharp up to the multiplicative constant $c &gt; 0$ and extends an earlier result of Borwein, Erd\'elyi, and K\'os from the case $M=1$ to the case $M \geq $1. This has also been proved recently with the factor $(1+\log M)$ rather than $(1+\log M)^{1/2}$ in the Appendix of a recent paper by Jacob and Nazarov by using a different method. We also prove that there is an absolute constant $c &gt; 0$ such that every polynomial $P$ of the above form has at most $(c/a)(1+\log M)$ zeros in the interval $[-1+a,1-a]$ with $a \in (0,1)$. Finally we correct a somewhat incorrect proof of an earlier result of Borwein and Erd\'elyi by proving that there is a constant $\eta &gt; 0$ such that every polynomial $P$ of the above form with $M = 1$ has at most $\eta n^{1/2}$ zeros inside any polygon with vertices on the unit circle, where the multiplicative constant $\eta &gt; 0$ depends only on the polygon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09553v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tam\'as Erd\'elyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-similar Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Differential equations where the graph of some derivative of a function is composed of a finite number of similarity transformations of the graph of the function itself are defined. We call these self-similar differential equations (SSDEs) and prove existence and uniqueness of solution under certain conditions. While SSDEs are not ordinary differential equations, the technique for demonstrating existence and uniqueness of SSDEs parallels that for ODEs. This paper appears to be the first work on equations of this nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09943v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leon Q. Brin, Joe Fields</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A relation between the Dirichlet and the Regularity problem for Parabolic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09197v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the relationship between the Dirichlet and Regularity problem for parabolic operators of the form $ L = \mbox{div}(A\nabla\cdot) - \partial_t $ on cylindrical domains $ \Omega = \mathcal O \times \mathbb R $, where the base $ \mathcal O \subset \mathbb R^{n} $ is a $1$-sided chord arc domain (and for one result Lipschitz) in the spatial variables.
  In the paper we answer the question when the solvability of the $L^p$ Regularity problem for $L$ (denoted by $ (R_L)_{p} $) can be deduced from the solvability of the $ L^{p'} $ Dirichlet problem for the adjoint operator $L^*$ (denoted $ (D_L^*)_{p'} $).
  We show that this holds if for at least of $q\in(1,\infty)$ the problem $ (R_L)_{q} $ is solvable.
  This result is a parabolic equivalent of two elliptic results of Kenig-Pipher (1993) and Shen (2006), the combination of which establishes the elliptic version of our result. For the converse, see Dindo\v{s}-Dyer (2019) where it is shown that $ (R_L)_{p}$ implies $ (D_L^*)_{p'}$ on parabolic $\mbox{Lip}(1,1/2)$ domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09197v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Dindo\v{s}, Erika S\"atterqvist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit Expressions for Iterates of Power Series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present five different formulas for both discrete and fractional iterations of an invertible power series $f$ utilizing a novel and unifying approach from umbral calculus. Established formulas are extended, and their proofs simplified, while new formulas are introduced. In particular, through the use of $q$-calculus identities, we eliminate the requirement for $f'(0)$ to equal $1$ and, consequently, the corresponding new expressions for the iterative logarithm are derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09809v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beauduin Kei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A BBP-style computation for $\pi$ in base 10</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10097v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We articulate about how to compute (promptly) the digits of $\pi$, in bases 5 and 10, from a given place without computing preceding ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10097v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wadim Zudilin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Self-Adjoint Hill Operators whose Spectrum is a Real Interval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10266v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $H = -d^2/dx^2 + q(x)$, $x \in \mathbb{R}$, where $q(x)$ is a periodic potential, and suppose that the spectrum $\sigma(H)$ of $H$ is the positive semi-axis $[0, \infty)$. In the case where $q(x)$ is real-valued (and locally square-integrable) a well-known result of G. Borg states that $q(x)$ must vanish almost everywhere. However, as it was first observed by M.G. Gasymov, there is an abundance of complex-valued potentials for which $\sigma(H) = [0, \infty)$.
  In this article we conjecture a characterization of all complex-valued potentials whose spectrum is $[0, \infty)$. We also present an analog of Borg's result for complex potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10266v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vassilis G. Papanicolaou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pointwise convergence of bilinear polynomial averages over the primes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10510v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that on a $\sigma$-finite measure preserving system $X = (X,\nu, T)$, the non-conventional ergodic averages $$ \mathbb{E}_{n \in [N]} \Lambda(n) f(T^n x) g(T^{P(n)} x)$$ converge pointwise almost everywhere for $f \in L^{p_1}(X)$, $g \in L^{p_2}(X)$, and $1/p_1 + 1/p_2 \leq 1$, where $P$ is a polynomial with integer coefficients of degree at least $2$. This had previously been established with the von Mangoldt weight $\Lambda$ replaced by the constant weight $1$ by the first and third authors with Mirek, and by the M\"obius weight $\mu$ by the fourth author. The proof is based on combining tools from both of these papers, together with several Gowers norm and polynomial averaging operator estimates on approximants to the von Mangoldt function of ''Cram\'er'' and ''Heath-Brown'' type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10510v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Krause, Hamed Mousavi, Terence Tao, Joni Ter\"av\"ainen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental inequalities for the iterated Fourier-cosine convolution with Gaussian weight and its application</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03609v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Derived from the results in (Math. Nachr., 283(12):1758-1770, 2010), in this paper, we devoted to studying the boundedness properties for Fourier-cosine convolution weighted by Gaussian functions via Young's type theorem and Saitoh's type inequality. New norm estimations in the weighted space are obtained and application of the corresponding class of convolutions in Fredholm's second kind of integral equation is discussed. The conditions for the solvability of this equation in $L_1$ space are also found, along with the analysis of an illustrative example, which exemplifies that the present object and method solve cases that are not under the conditions of previously known techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03609v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Thi Hong Phuong, Trinh Tuan, Lai Tien Minh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-sided bell-shaped sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11274v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A nonnegative real function f is bell-shaped if it converges to zero at plus and minus infinity and the nth derivative of f changes sign n times for every n = 0, 1, 2, ... Similarly, a two-sided nonnegative sequence a(k) is bell-shaped if it converges to zero at plus and minus infinity and the nth iterated difference of a(k) changes sign n times for every n = 0, 1, 2, ... A characterisation of bell-shaped functions was given by Thomas Simon and the first named author, and recently a similar result for one-sided bell-shaped sequences was found by the authors. In the present article we give a complete description of two-sided bell-shaped sequences. Our main result proves that bell-shaped sequences are convolutions of P\'olya frequency sequences and what we call absolutely monotone-then-completely monotone sequences, and it provides an equivalent, and relatively easy to verify, condition in terms of holomorphic extensions of the generating function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11274v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateusz Kwa\'snicki, Jacek Wszo{\l}a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonexistence of time-periodic solutions of the Dirac equation in nonextreme Kerr-Newman-AdS spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1608.05249</link>
      <description>arXiv:1608.05249v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In non-extreme Kerr-Newman-AdS spacetime, we prove that there is no nontrivial Dirac particle which is $L^p$ for $0&lt;p\leq\frac{4}{3}$ with arbitrary eigenvalue $\lambda$, and for $\frac{4}{3}&lt;p\leq\frac{4}{3-2q}$, $0&lt;q&lt;\frac{3}{2}$ with eigenvalue $|\lambda|&gt;q \kappa $, outside and away from the event horizon. By taking $q=\frac{1}{2}$, we show that there is no normalizable massive Dirac particle with mass greater than $\frac{\kappa}{2} $ outside and away from the event horizon in non-extreme Kerr-Newman-AdS spacetime, and they must either disappear into the black hole or escape to infinity, and this recovers the same result of Belgiorno and Cacciatori in the case of $Q=0$ obtained by using spectral methods. Furthermore, we prove that any Dirac particle with eigenvalue $|\lambda|&lt;\frac{\kappa}{2}$ must be $L^2$ outside and away from the event horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1608.05249v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science China Mathematics, 61(2018),73-82</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yaohua Wang, Xiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absolute continuity of degenerate elliptic measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.04860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.04860v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\Omega \subset \mathbb{R}^{n+1}$ be an open set whose boundary may be composed of pieces of different dimensions. Assume that $\Omega$ satisfies the quantitative openness and connectedness, and there exist doubling measures $m$ on $\Omega$ and $\mu$ on $\partial \Omega$ with appropriate size conditions. Let $Lu=-\mathrm{div}(A\nabla u)$ be a real (not necessarily symmetric) degenerate elliptic operator in $\Omega$. Write $\omega_L$ for the associated degenerate elliptic measure. We establish the equivalence between the following properties: (i) $\omega_L \in A_{\infty}(\mu)$, (ii) the Dirichlet problem for $L$ is solvable in $L^p(\mu)$ for some $p \in (1, \infty)$, (iii) every bounded null solution of $L$ satisfies Carleson measure estimates with respect to $\mu$, (iv) the conical square function is controlled by the non-tangential maximal function in $L^q(\mu)$ for all $q \in (0, \infty)$ for any null solution of $L$, and (v) the Dirichlet problem for $L$ is solvable in $\mathrm{BMO}(\mu)$. On the other hand, we obtain a qualitative analogy of the previous equivalence. Indeed, we characterize the absolute continuity of $\omega_L$ with respect to $\mu$ in terms of local $L^2(\mu)$ estimates of the truncated conical square function for any bounded null solution of $L$. This is also equivalent to the finiteness $\mu$-almost everywhere of the truncated conical square function for any bounded null solution of $L$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.04860v5</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Funct. Anal. (2025), 110673</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mingming Cao, K\^oz\^o Yabuta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrability of pushforward measures by analytic maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.12446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.12446v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a map $\phi:X\rightarrow Y$ between $F$-analytic manifolds over a local field $F$ of characteristic $0$, we introduce an invariant $\epsilon_{\star}(\phi)$ which quantifies the integrability of pushforwards of smooth compactly supported measures by $\phi$. We further define a local version $\epsilon_{\star}(\phi,x)$ near $x\in X$. These invariants have a strong connection to the singularities of $\phi$.
  When $Y$ is one-dimensional, we give an explicit formula for $\epsilon_{\star}(\phi,x)$, and show it is asymptotically equivalent to other known singularity invariants such as the $F$-log-canonical threshold $\operatorname{lct}_{F}(\phi-\phi(x);x)$ at $x$.
  In the general case, we show that $\epsilon_{\star}(\phi,x)$ is bounded from below by the $F$-log-canonical threshold $\lambda=\operatorname{lct}_{F}(\mathcal{J}_{\phi};x)$ of the Jacobian ideal $\mathcal{J}_{\phi}$ near $x$. If $\dim Y=\dim X$, equality is attained. If $\dim Y&lt;\dim X$, the inequality can be strict; however, for $F=\mathbb{C}$, we establish the upper bound $\epsilon_{\star}(\phi,x)\leq\lambda/(1-\lambda)$, whenever $\lambda&lt;1$.
  Finally, we specialize to polynomial maps $\varphi:X\rightarrow Y$ between smooth algebraic $\mathbb{Q}$-varieties $X$ and $Y$. We geometrically characterize the condition that $\epsilon_{\star}(\varphi_{F})=\infty$ over a large family of local fields, by showing it is equivalent to $\varphi$ being flat with fibers of semi-log-canonical singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.12446v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itay Glazer, Yotam I. Hendel, Sasha Sodin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial progressions in topological fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.00670v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $P_1, \ldots, P_m \in K[y]$ be polynomials with distinct degrees, no constant terms and coefficients in a general locally compact topological field $K$. We give a quantitative count of the number of polynomial progressions $x, x+P_1(y), \ldots, x + P_m(y)$ lying in a set $S\subseteq K$ of positive density. The proof relies on a general $L^{\infty}$ inverse theorem which is of independent interest. This inverse theorem implies a Sobolev improving estimate for multilinear polynomial averaging operators which in turn implies our quantitative estimate for polynomial progressions. This general Sobolev inequality has the potential to be applied in a number of problems in real, complex and $p$-adic analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.00670v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Krause, Mariusz Mirek, Sarah Peluse, James Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector calculus on weighted reflexive Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03684v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study first-order Sobolev spaces on reflexive Banach spaces via relaxation, test plans, and divergence. We show the equivalence of the different approaches to the Sobolev spaces and to the related tangent bundles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03684v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Pasqualetto, Tapio Rajala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counterexamples and weak (1,1) estimates of wave operators for fourth-order Schr\"odinger operators in dimension three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06768v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper is dedicated to investigating the $L^p$-bounds of wave operators $W_\pm(H,\Delta^2)$ associated with fourth-order Schr\"odinger operators $H=\Delta^2+V$ on $\mathbb{R}^3$. We consider that real potentials satisfy $|V(x)|\lesssim \langle x\rangle^{-\mu}$ for some $\mu&gt;0$. A recent work by Goldberg and Green \cite{GoGr21} has demonstrated that wave operators $W_\pm(H,\Delta^2)$ are bounded on $L^p(\mathbb{R}^3)$ for all $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$ under the condition that $\mu&gt;9$, and zero is a regular point of $H$. In this paper, we aim to further establish endpoint estimates for $W_\pm(H,\Delta^2)$ in two significant ways. First, we provide counterexamples that illustrate the unboundedness of $W_\pm(H,\Delta^2)$ on the endpoint spaces $L^1(\mathbb{R}^3)$ and $L^\infty(\mathbb{R}^3)$, even for non-zero compactly supported potentials $V$. Second, we establish weak (1,1) estimates for the wave operators $W_\pm(H,\Delta^2)$ and their dual operators $W_\pm(H,\Delta^2)^*$ in the case where zero is a regular point and $\mu&gt;11$. These estimates depend critically on the singular integral theory of Calder\'on-Zygmund on a homogeneous space $(X,d\omega)$ with a doubling measure $d\omega$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06768v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruya Mizutani, Zijun Wan, Xiaohua Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A law of large numbers concerning the number of critical points of isotropic Gaussian functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14383v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\Phi$ be a smooth isotropic random Gaussian function $\Phi$ on $\mathbb{R}^m$. Denote by $Z_N(\Phi)$ the number of critical points of $\Phi$ inside the cube $[0,N]^m$. We prove that $N^{-m}Z_N(\Phi)$ converges a.s. and $L^2$ to a universal explicit constant $C_m(\Phi)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14383v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liviu I. Nicolaescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
