<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 04:02:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sums of infinite series involving the Dirichlet lambda function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08347v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $$ \lambda(s)=\sum_{n=1}^{\infty}\frac{1}{(2n+1)^{s}},~\textrm{Re}(s)&gt;1 $$ be Dirichlet's lambda function, which was firstly studied by Euler in the real axis under the notation $N(s)$. In this paper, by applying the partial fractional decomposition of the function $\pi\tan(\pi x)$, the explicit calculation of the integral $\int_0^{\frac12}x^{2m-1}\cos(2k\pi x) dx$ and the zeta-values representation of the integral $\int_0^{\frac12}x^{m-1}\log\cos(\pi x)dx$, we establish closed-form expressions for several classes of infinite series involving $\lambda(s)$. As a by product, we show that the lambda-values $\lambda(2k)$ appears as the constant terms of the Eisenstein series for the congruence subgroup $\Gamma_{0}(2).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08347v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Su Hu, Min-Soo Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric Sextic Freud Weight</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08522v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the properties of the sequence of coefficients \((\b_n)_{n\geq0}\) in the recurrence relation satisfied by the sequence of monic symmetric polynomials, orthogonal with respect to the symmetric sextic Freud weight \[ \omega(x; \tau, t) = \exp(-x^6 + \tau x^4 + t x^2), \qquad x \in \mathbb{R}, \] with real parameters $\tau$ and $t$. We derive a fourth-order nonlinear discrete equation satisfied by $\beta_n$, which is shown to be a special case of {the second} member of the discrete Painlev\'{e} I hierarchy. Further, we analyse differential and differential-difference equations satisfied by the recurrence coefficients. The emphasis is to offer a comprehensive study of the intricate evolution {in} the behaviour of these recurrence coefficients as the pair of parameters \((\tau,t)\) change. A comprehensive numerical and computational analysis is carried out for critical parameter ranges, and graphical plots are presented to illustrate the behaviour of the recurrence coefficients as well as the complexity of the associated Volterra lattice hierarchy. The corresponding symmetric sextic Freud polynomials are shown to satisfy a second-order differential equation with rational coefficients. The moments of the weight are examined in detail, including their integral representations, differential equations, and recursive structure. Closed-form expressions for moments are obtained in several special cases, and asymptotic expansions for the recurrence coefficients are provided. The results highlight rich algebraic and analytic structures underlying the symmetric sextic Freud weight and its connections to integrable systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08522v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter A. Clarkson, Kerstin Jordaan, Ana Loureiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral gaps and Fourier decay for self-conformal measures in the plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11688v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\Phi$ be a $C^\omega (\mathbb{C})$ self-conformal IFS on the plane, satisfying some mild non-linearity and irreducibility conditions. We prove a uniform spectral gap estimate for the transfer operator corresponding to the derivative cocycle and every given self-conformal measure. Building on this result, we establish polynomial Fourier decay for any such measure. Our technique is based on a refinement of a method of Oh-Winter (2017) where we do not require separation from the IFS or the Federer property for the underlying measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11688v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Algom, Federico Rodriguez Hertz, Zhiren Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
