<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 01:26:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate direct and inverse scattering for the AKNS system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05525v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the direct and inverse scattering problems for the AKNS (Ablowitz-Kaup-Newell-Segur) system. New representations for the Jost solutions are obtained in the form of the power series in terms of a transformed spectral parameter. In terms of that parameter, the Jost solutions are convergent power series in corresponding unit disks. For the coefficients of the series simple recurrent integration procedures are devised. Solution of the direct scattering problem reduces to computing the coefficients and locating zeros of corresponding analytic functions in the interior of the unit disk. Solution of the inverse scattering problem reduces to the solution of two systems of linear algebraic equations for the power series coefficients, while the potentials are recovered from the first coefficients. The overall approach leads to a simple and efficient method for the numerical solution of both direct and inverse scattering problems, which is illustrated by numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05525v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladislav V. Kravchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier frames on smooth surfaces with nonvanishing Gaussian curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is known that a small spherical cap (rigorously its surface measure) admits Fourier frames, while the whole sphere does not. In this paper, we prove more general results. Consequences indclude that a small spherical cap in $\mathbb{R}^d$ near the north pole cannot have a frame spectrum near the $x_d$-axis, and $S$ does not admit any Fourier frame if its interior contains a closed hemisphere. We also resolve the endpoint case, that is, a hemisphere does not admit any Fourier frame. This answers a question of Kolountzakis and Lai. Our results also hold on more general smooth surfaces with nonvanishing Gaussian curvature. In particular, any compact $(d-1)$-dimensional smooth submanifold immersed in $\mathbb{R}^d$ with nonvanishing Gaussian curvature does not admit any Fourier frame. This generalizes a previous result of Iosevich, Lai, Wyman and the second author on the boundary of convex bodies, as well as improves a recent result of Kolountzakis and Lai from tight frame to frame.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05777v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Chen, Bochen Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entrywise transforms preserving matrix positivity and non-positivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize real and complex functions which, when applied entrywise to square matrices, yield a positive definite matrix if and only if the original matrix is positive definite. We refer to these transformations as sign preservers. Compared to classical work on entrywise preservers of Schoenberg and others, we completely resolve this problem in the harder fixed dimensional setting, extending a similar recent classification of sign preservers obtained for matrices over finite fields. When the matrix dimension is fixed and at least $3$, we show that the sign preservers are precisely the positive scalar multiples of the continuous automorphisms of the underlying field. This is in contrast to the $2 \times 2$ case where the sign preservers are extensions of power functions. These results are built on our classification of $2 \times 2$ entrywise positivity preservers over broader complex domains. Our results yield a complementary connection with a work of Belton, Guillot, Khare, and Putinar (2023) on negativity-preserving transforms. We also extend our sign preserver results to matrices with a structure of zeros, as studied by Guillot, Khare, and Rajaratnam for the entrywise positivity preserver problem. Finally, in the spirit of sign preservers, we address a natural extension to monotone maps, classically studied by Loewner and many others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06076v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominique Guillot, Himanshu Gupta, Prateek Kumar Vishwakarma, Chi Hoi Yip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Young's convolutions inequality and its reverse form on the hypercube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06115v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish sharp forms of Young's convolution inequality and its reverse on the discrete hypercube $\{0,1\}^d$ in the diagonal case $p=q$. As applications, we derive bounds for additive energies and sumsets. We also investigate the non-diagonal regime $p\neq q$, providing necessary conditions for the inequality to hold, along with partial results in the case $r = 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06115v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Beltran, Paata Ivanisvili, Jos\'e Madrid, Lekha Patil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cauchy Data for 1D singular Schr\"odinger operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05772v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study semiclassical 1D Schr\"odinger operators with a power-like singularity at $0$. We show that WKB expansions can be extended on any interval of the form [h^{1-},b]. Using a different approximation near 0 and a matching procedure we obtain an asymptotic expansion for the Cauchy Data at 0 of such WKB solutions that involves non-integer powers of h.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05772v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Hillairet, Jeremy L. Marzuola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embeddings of Sobolev spaces of differential forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We continue the~study of embedding between different classes of Sobolev spaces of differential forms started in 2006 in a~paper by Gol'dshtein and Troyanov. As in this paper, our study is based on relations between $L_{q,p}$-cohomology and Sobolev type inequalities. The~main results are estimates for the norms of the embedding operators for $q=p$ and $p&gt;\frac{n-1}{k-1}$ in the~Euclidean $r$-ball $B(r)$ and its bi-Lipschitz images. The~compactness of such operators also studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05851v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Gol'dshtein, Yaroslav Kopylov, Roman Panenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incidence Estimates for Tubes in Complex Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.05477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.05477v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove a complex version of the incidence estimate of Guth, Solomon and Wang for tubes obeying certain strong spacing conditions, and we use one of our new estimates to resolve a discretized variant of Falconer's distance set problem in $\mathbb{C}^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.05477v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah Tammen, Lingxian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Fourier transforms of fractal measures on the parabola</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17867v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $s \in [0,1]$ and $t \in [0,\min\{3s,s + 1\})$. Let $\sigma$ be a Borel measure supported on the parabola $\mathbb{P} = \{(x,x^{2}) : x \in [-1,1]\}$ satisfying the $s$-dimensional Frostman condition $\sigma(B(x,r)) \leq r^{s}$. Answering a question of the first author, we show that there exists an exponent $p = p(s,t) \geq 1$ such that $$\|\hat{\sigma}\|_{L^{p}(B(R))} \leq C_{s,t}R^{(2 - t)/p}, \qquad R \geq 1.$$ Moreover, when $s \geq 2/3$ and $t \in [0,s + 1)$, the previous inequality is true for $p \geq 6$.
  We also obtain the following fractal geometric counterpart of the previous results. If $K \subset \mathbb{P}$ is a Borel set with $\dim_{\mathrm{H}} K = s \in [0,1]$, and $n \geq 1$ is an integer, then $$ \dim_{\mathrm{H}}(nK) \geq \min\{3s - s \cdot 2^{-(n - 2)},s + 1\}.$$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17867v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuomas Orponen, Carmelo Puliatti, Aleksi Py\"or\"al\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An evolution of matrix-valued orthogonal polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18362v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish new explicit connections between classical (scalar) and matrix Gegenbauer polynomials, which result in new symmetries of the latter and further give access to several properties that have been out of reach before: generating functions, distribution of zeros for individual entries of the matrices and new type of differential-difference structure. We further speculate about other potentials of the connection formulas found. Part of our proofs makes use of creative telescoping in a matrix setting$-$the strategy which is not yet developed algorithmically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18362v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik Koelink, Pablo Rom\'an, Wadim Zudilin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Path-by-path uniqueness for stochastic differential equations under Krylov-R\"ockner condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.06802v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that any stochastic differential equation (SDE) driven by Brownian motion with drift satisfying the Krylov-R\"ockner condition has exactly one solution in an ordinary sense for almost every trajectory of the Brownian motion. Consequentially, such SDE is strongly complete and forms a random dynamical system. Also, a further application to a boundary value problem is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.06802v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Anzeletti, Khoa L\^e, Chengcheng Ling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inner Functions, M\"obius Distortion and Angular Derivatives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03414v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that an inner function has finite $\mathcal{L} (p)$-entropy if and only if its accumulated M\"obius distortion is in $L^p$, $0&lt;p&lt;\infty$. We also study the support of the positive singular measures such that their corresponding singular inner functions have finite $\mathcal{L} (p)$-entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03414v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Bampouras, Artur Nicolau</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
