<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 04:03:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Stability estimates for adaptive focused time-frequency transforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This contribution is a follow-up of a recent paper by the authors on adaptive, non-linear time-frequency transforms, focusing on the STFT based transforms. The adaptivity is provided by a focus function, that depends on the analyzed function or signal, and that adapts dynamically the time-frequency resolution of the analysis. Sticking to the continuous case setting, this work provides new stability results for the transform (stability with respect with the focus function). It also investigates in some details focus functions based upon regularized R{\'e}nyi entropies and show corresponding continuity results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08637v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Warion (I2M), Bruno Torr\'esani (I2M)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Higher-Order Dynamic Equation with Polynomial Growth and Mixed Boundary Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the existence of solutions for a class of nonlinear higher-order dynamic equations subject to mixed boundary conditions. We consider boundary value problems in which the nonlinear reaction functions satisfy polynomial growth conditions both in the interior of the domain and on the boundary. Our analysis employs a systematic approach based on fixed-point theorems for expansive mappings combined with completely continuous operators to establish stronger existence results. Under appropriate growth conditions on the nonlinear terms, we first prove the existence of at least one classical solution, which is not guaranteed to be nonnegative. We then strengthen our hypotheses to establish the existence of at least three nonnegative solutions. The theoretical framework relies on cone theory and carefully constructed open bounded subsets within function spaces equipped with appropriate norms. Our methodology provides a unified approach to multiple solution problems for higher-order</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08808v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shalmali Bandyopadhyay, Svetlin G. Georgiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fourier transform in variable exponent Lebesgue spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we define a Fourier transform for each $f\in L^{p(\cdot)}(\mathbb{R})$, for a large class of exponent functions $p(\cdot)$, as the distributional derivative of a H\"older continuous function. A norm is defined in the space of such Fourier transforms so that it is isometrically isomorphic to $L^{p(\cdot)}(\mathbb{R})$. We also prove several properties of this Fourier transform, such as inversion in norm and an exchange theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08891v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e Pedroso Kowacs, Wagner Augusto Almeida de Moraes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiversion of the Hausdorff--Young inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08494v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a family of jointly Gaussian random vectors $\xi_j \in \mathbb{R}^{k_j}$, each standard normal but possibly correlated, and investigate when\[ \mathbb{E}\, F\!\Bigl(B\bigl(|T_{z_1} f_1(\xi_1)|,\dots,|T_{z_n} f_n(\xi_n)|\bigr)\Bigr) \;\;\le\;\; F\!\Bigl(\,\mathbb{E}\,B\bigl(|f_1(\xi_1)|,\dots,|f_n(\xi_n)|\bigr)\Bigr) \] holds, where $T_{z}$ is either a Mehler transform $(z \in \mathbb{C})$ or a noise operator $(z \in \mathbb{R})$. This framework unifies and extends real and complex hypercontractivity to multi-function settings, yielding multiversions of the sharp Hausdorff--Young inequality, the log-Sobolev inequality, and a noisy Gaussian--Jensen inequality. Applications include a new covariance-based characterization of the Brascamp--Lieb inequality in the presence of noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08494v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paata Ivanisvili, Pavlos Kalantzopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Support bound for differential elimination in polynomial dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study an important special case of the differential elimination problem: given a polynomial dynamical system $\mathbf{x}' = \mathbf{g}(\mathbf{x})$ and a polynomial observation function $y = f(\mathbf{x})$, find the minimal differential equation satisfied by $y$. In our previous work, for the case $y = x_1$, we established a bound on the support of such a differential equation and shown that it can be turned into an algorithm via the evaluation-interpolation approach. The main contribution of the present paper is a generalization of the aforementioned result in two directions: to allow any polynomial function $y = f(\mathbf{x})$, not just a single coordinate, and to allow $\mathbf{g}$ and $f$ depend on unknown symbolic parameters. We conduct computation experiments to evaluate the accuracy of our new bound and show that the approach allows to perform elimination for some cases out of reach for the state of the art software.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08824v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yulia Mukhina, Gleb Pogudin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
