<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperelliptic values of the Gamma function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.09198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.09198v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show how to calculate particular values of the Gamma function for specific rational arguments in the interval (0,1) without using the Elliptic K-function. By introducing hyperelliptic generalisations of the trigonometric functions, we obtain a halving formula. We show that the constants used in this formula are transcendental in specific cases. We generalise Euler's arcsine proof and state a useful formula by K\"onigsberger. Finally, we apply the Gamma values to various equations like the area of superellipses and the butterfly curve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.09198v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan L\"ugering</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier transforms and iterated function systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00585v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss the problem of bounding the Fourier transforms of stationary measures of iterated function systems (IFSs) and how the pseudo-randomness of the IFS either due to arithmetic, algebraic or geometric reasons is reflected in the behaviour of the Fourier transform. We outline various methods that have been built to estimate the Fourier transform of stationary measures arising e.g. from thermodynamical formalism, additive combinatorics, random walks on groups and hyperbolic dynamics. Open problems, prospects and recent links to quantum chaos are also highlighted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00585v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuomas Sahlsten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the end-point of Stein-Weiss inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19528v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper has two purposes. First, we show that the classical Stein-Weiss inequality is true for p=1. Second, by considering a family of strong fractional integral operators whose kernels have singularity on every coordinate subspace, we extend this end-point result to the multi-parameter setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19528v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuhan Sun, Zipeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Change of Variable Formula Integrals, do they have equal value?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12679v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Assuming that the two integrals in the Change of Variable Formula for the unidimensional Riemann integral are finite, one can ask if they have equal value. We give a positive answer to this question. The proof is very easy to follow and to keep in mind. An example is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12679v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oswaldo Rio Branco de Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp stability for Sobolev and log-Sobolev inequalities, with optimal dimensional dependence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.08651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.08651v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a sharp quantitative version for the stability of the Sobolev inequality with explicit constants. Moreover, the constants have the correct behavior in the limit of large dimensions, which allows us to deduce an optimal quantitative stability estimate for the Gaussian log-Sobolev inequality with an explicit dimension-free constant. Our proofs rely on several ingredients such as competing symmetries, a flow based on continuous Steiner symmetrization that interpolates continuously between a function and its symmetric decreasing rearrangement, and refined estimates on the Sobolev functional in the neighborhood of the optimal Aubin--Talenti functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.08651v5</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Dolbeault, Maria J. Esteban, Alessio Figalli, Rupert L. Frank, Michael Loss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector valued estimates for matrix weighted maximal operators and product $\mathrm{BMO}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider maximal operators acting on vector valued functions, that is functions taking values on $\mathbb{C}^d,$ that incorporate matrix weights in their definitions. We show vector valued estimates, in the sense of Fefferman--Stein inequalities, for such operators. These are proven using an extrapolation result for convex body valued functions due to Bownik and Cruz-Uribe. Finally, we show an $\mathrm{H}^1$-$\mathrm{BMO}$ duality for matrix valued functions and we apply the previous vector valued estimates to show upper bounds for biparameter paraproducts. For the reader's convenience, we include an appendix explaining how to adapt the extrapolation for real convex body valued functions of Bownik and Cruz-Uribe to the setting of complex convex body valued functions that we treat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16776v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spyridon Kakaroumpas, Od\'i Soler i Gibert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variations on a theme of Ap\'ery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10090v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ap\'ery's remarkable discovery of rapidly converging continued fractions with small coefficients for $\zeta(2)$ and $\zeta(3)$ has led to a flurry of important activity in an incredible variety of different directions. Our purpose is to show that modifications of Ap\'ery's continued fractions can give interesting results including new rapidly convergent continued fractions for certain interesting constants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10090v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henri Cohen, Wadim Zudilin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
