<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 05:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Microlocal analysis of Radon transforms over quadric surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12453v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the microlocal properties of generalized Radon transforms over a family of quadric hypersurfaces whose centers lie on an orientable hypersurface $S$. The quadric surfaces we consider are level sets of the quadratic form associated to a symmetric, invertible matrix $A$, with real entries. We study the singularities of the right and left projections of the canonical relation associated with these operators and show that they are determined by the signature of the matrix $A$ and the hypersurface $S$. If the matrix is positive/negative definite (i.e., the surface of integration is an ellipsoid) and $S$ is strictly convex, we prove that the singularities are folds. If the matrix is indefinite (i.e., the surface of integration is a hyperboloid-type quadric) and $S$ is either strictly convex or a cylinder, then cusp, fold, or blowdown singularities are present. We also study the case when the surface of integration is a paraboloid and show that the Bolker condition is satisfied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12453v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaik Ambartsoumian, Raluca Felea, Venkateswaran P. Krishnan, Clifford J. Nolan, Eric Todd Quinto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric separation and constructive universal approximation with two hidden layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12482v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a geometric construction of neural networks that separate disjoint compact subsets of $\Bbb R^n$, and use it to obtain a constructive universal approximation theorem. Specifically, we show that networks with two hidden layers and either a sigmoidal activation (i.e., strictly monotone bounded continuous) or the ReLU activation can approximate any real-valued continuous function on an arbitrary compact set $K\subset\Bbb R^n$ to any prescribed accuracy in the uniform norm. For finite $K$, the construction simplifies and yields a sharp depth-2 (single hidden layer) approximation result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12482v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chanyoung Sung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential trace inequalities via a Calder\'on-type theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03986v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we develop a general theoretical tool for the establishment of the boundedness of notoriously difficult operators (such as potentials) on certain specific types of rearrangement-invariant function spaces from analogous properties of operators that are easier to handle (such as fractional maximal operators). A principal example of the new results one obtains by our analysis is the following inequality, which generalizes a result of Korobkov and Kristensen (who had treated the case $\mu=\mathcal{L}^n$, the Lebesgue measure on $\mathbb{R}^n$): There exists a constant $C&gt;0$ such that \[\int_{\mathbb{R}^n} |I_\alpha^\mu f|^p d\nu \leq C \|f\|_{L^{p,1}(\mathbb{R}^n,\mu)}^p\] for all $f$ in the Lorentz space $L^{p,1}(\mathbb{R}^n,\mu)$, where $\mu, \nu$ are Radon measures such that \[\sup_{Q} \frac{\mu(Q)}{l(Q)^{d}} &lt; \infty \quad \text{and} \quad \sup_{\mu(Q)&gt;0} \frac{\nu(Q)}{\quad\mu(Q)^{1-\frac{\alpha p}{d}}} &lt; \infty,\] and $I_\alpha^\mu$ is the Riesz potential defined with respect to $\mu$ of order $\alpha \in (0,d)$. More broadly, we obtain inequalities in this spirit in the context of rearrangement-invariant spaces through a result of independent interest, an extension of an interpolation theorem of Calder\'on where the target space in one endpoint is a space of bounded functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03986v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zden\v{e}k Mihula, Lubo\v{s} Pick, Daniel Spector</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
