<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA</link>
    <description>math.CA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 02:42:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nonautonomous Linear Systems: Exponential Dichotomy and its Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The first purpose of this work is to provide a friendly introduction to the theory of nonautonomous linear systems of ordinary differential equations, the property of exponential dichotomy and its corresponding spectral theory. The second purpose of this work is disseminate the linearization results carried out by the authors in a nonautonomous framework.
  The actual structure of this work is a consequence of several elective courses (2014, 2016, 2019, 2021 and 2023) carried out by the authors for undergraduate and graduated students at the Department of Mathematics of the Universidad de Chile. The monography assumes a good knowledge of multivariate calculus, linear algebra and ordinary differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11759v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Alvaro Casta\~neda, Gonzalo Robledo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Supershifts and their associated Cauchy Evolution problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we extend the notion of supershifts and superoscillation sequence to fractional Fock spaces based on Gelfond-Leontiev fractional derivatives. We first introduce the fractional supershifts sequence, and then discuss the associated evolution Cauchy problem with the fractional supershifts as initial condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11829v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natanael Alpay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unbounded banded matrices with positive bidiagonal factorization and mixed-type multiple orthogonal polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12453v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A spectral Favard theorem is proved for semi-infinite banded matrices admitting a positive bidiagonal factorization, without assuming boundedness of the associated operator, thus covering both the bounded and unbounded settings. The result yields a matrix-valued spectral measure and an explicit spectral representation of the matrix powers in terms of the associated mixed-type multiple orthogonal polynomials. The argument follows the constructive truncation scheme: principal truncations are oscillatory, hence have simple positive spectra, and a suitable choice of initial conditions ensures positivity of the Christoffel coefficients and of the resulting discrete matrix-valued measures supported at the truncation eigenvalues. The main difficulty is the passage to the limit of these discrete measures beyond the bounded case. This is resolved by combining the available Gaussian quadrature structure with a Helly-type compactness argument, leading to a limiting matrix-valued measure and completing the spectral theorem. The role of normality (maximal degree pattern) for the mixed-type families is also addressed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12453v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Am\'ilcar Branquinho, Ana Foulqui\'e-Moreno, Manuel Ma\~nas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric preparation of systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12458v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we generalize the Weierstrass and Malgrange preparation theorems to the symmetric matrix valued case, proving symmetric preparation of analytic and smooth symmetric systems that vanish of first order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12458v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nils Dencker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrals of products of four modified Bessel functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12590v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We evaluate definite integrals involving the product of four modified Bessel functions of the first and second kind and a power function. We provide general formulas expressed in terms of the Meijer $G$-function and generalized hypergeometric and Lauricella $F_C$ functions, and study a number of special cases in which the integrals can be evaluated in terms of simpler special functions or indeed take an elementary form. As a consequence, we deduce some new formulas for definite integrals of products of four Airy functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12590v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert E. Gaunt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of eigenfunctions of the Laplacian having exponential growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1993, Robert Strichartz proved a characterization for the bounded eigenfunctions of Laplacian $\Delta=-\sum_{j=1}^d \frac{\partial^2}{\partial x_j^2} $ on $\mathbb{R}^d$: If $\left\{f_k \right\}_{k\in \mathbb{Z}}$ be a doubly infinite sequence of functions on $\mathbb{R}^d$ such that $\Delta f_k=f_{k+1}$ and $ \|f_k\|_{L^{\infty}(\mathbb{R}^d)} \leq C$ for all $ k \in \mathbb{Z}$, for some $C&gt;0$, then $f_0$ is an eigenfunction of $\Delta$. Observing the existence of unbounded eigenfunctions of the Laplacian, Howard and Reese generalized Strichartz's theorem to characterize eigenfunctions of the Laplacian having at most polynomial growth. In this article, we shall prove an extended version of Strichartz's theorem to characterize eigenfunctions of the Laplacian having exponential growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13017v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Basil Paul, Pradeep Boggarapu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second order periodic boundary value problems with reflection and piecewise constant arguments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we analyze a second-order differential equation with a piecewise constant argument and reflection coupled to periodic boundary conditions. Our main contribution is the construction of the related Green's function and a detailed analysis of its properties. In particular, we determine the region in which the Green's function has constant sign, depending on the parameters $m$ and $M$ on which it depends. In some cases, we are able to characterize these parameter values in terms of the first eigenvalue related to suitable Dirichlet problems. Building in these results, we apply the Krasnosel'skii method to establish the existence of solutions for different nonlinear problems, and prove the existence of a positive solution of a perturbed Schrodinger equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13291v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Cabada, Paula Cambeses-Franco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizations of a class of Musielak--Orlicz BMO spaces via commutators of Riesz potential operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13788v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fractional integral operators $I_\alpha$ can be used to characterize the Musielak--Orlicz Hardy spaces. This paper shows that for $b\in \rm BMO(\mathbb R^n)$, the commutators $[b,I_\alpha]$ generated by fractional integral operators $I_\alpha$ with $b$ are bounded from the Musielak--Orlicz Hardy spaces $H^{\varphi_1}(\mathbb R^n)$ to the Musielak--Orlicz spaces $L^{\varphi_2}(\mathbb R^n)$ (where $1&lt;u&lt;\infty$ and $\varphi_1$, $\varphi_2$ are growth functions) if and only if $b\in \mathcal {BMO}_{\varphi_1,u}(\mathbb R^n)$, which are a class of non-trivial subspaces of $\rm BMO(\mathbb R^n)$. Additionally, we obtain the boundedness of the commutator $[b,I_\alpha]$ from $H^{\varphi_1}(\mathbb R^n)$ to $H^{\varphi_2}(\mathbb R^n)$. The corresponding results are also provided for commutators of fractional integrals associated with general homogeneous kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13788v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanyan Han, Hongwei Huang, Jinghan Shao, Huoxiong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry-Driven Conditioning of Multivariate Vandermonde Matrices in High-Degree Regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study multivariate monomial Vandermonde matrices $V_N(Z)$ with arbitrary distinct nodes $Z=\{z_1,\dots,z_s\}\subset B_2^n$ in the high-degree regime $N\ge s-1$. Introducing a projection-based geometric statistic -- the \emph{max-min projection separation} $\rho(Z,j)$ and its minimum $\kappa(Z)=\min_j\rho(Z,j)$ -- we construct Lagrange polynomials $Q_j\in\mathcal P_N^n$ with explicit coefficient bounds $$ \|Q_j\|_\infty \lesssim s\Bigl(\frac{4n}{\rho(Z,j)}\Bigr)^{s-1}. $$ These polynomials yield quantitative distance-to-span estimates for the rows of $V_N(Z)$ and, as consequences, $$ \sigma_{\min}(V_N(Z)) \gtrsim \frac{\kappa(Z)^{s-1}}{(4n)^{s-1} s\sqrt{s \nu(n,N)}}, \quad \nu(n,N)={N+n\choose N}, $$ and an explicit right inverse $V_N(Z)^+$ with operator-norm control $$ \|V_N(Z)^+\| \lesssim s^{3/2}\sqrt{\nu(n,N)}\Bigl(\frac{4n}{\kappa(Z)}\Bigr)^{s-1}. $$ Our estimates are dimension-explicit and expressed directly in terms of the local geometry parameter $\kappa(Z)$; they apply to \emph{every} distinct node set $Z\subset B_2^n$ without any \emph{a priori} separation assumptions. In particular, $V_N(Z)$ has full row rank whenever $N\ge s-1$. The results complement the Fourier-type theory (on the complex unit circle/torus), where lower bounds for $\sigma_{\min}$ hinge on uniform separation or cluster structure; here stability is quantified instead via high polynomial degree and the projection geometry of $Z$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13915v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omer Friedland, Yosef Yomdin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization and interpolation of parabolic $L^p$ Neumann problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12429v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show a localization estimate for local solutions to the parabolic equation $-\partial_t u+\mbox{div} (A\nabla u)=0$ with zero Neumann data, assuming that the $L^p$ Neumann problem and $L^{p'}$ Dirichlet problem for the adjoint operator are solvable in a Lipschitz cylinder for some $p\in(1,\infty)$. Using this result, we establish the solvability of the Neumann problem in the atomic Hardy space for parabolic operators with bounded, measurable, time-dependent coefficients, and hence obtain the interpolation of solvability of the $L^p$ Neumann problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12429v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Dindo\v{s}, Linhan Li, Jill Pipher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A formula for the local Heun solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The local Heun solution is the unique solution to Heun's equation which is analytic in the unit disk centered at $0\in\mathbb{C}$ and taking the value $1$ at the center of the disk. In this paper, as an application of the theory of orthogonal polynomials, we are able to express the coefficients in the corresponding power series as finite multiple sums. In addition, the obtained formula can be used to derive an explicit estimate on the coefficients giving a hint on their asymptotic behavior for large indices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12888v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel \v{S}\v{t}ov\'i\v{c}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On rough ideal convergence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We continue the study of ideal convergence for sequences $(x_n)$ with values in a topological space $X$ with respect to a family $\{F_\eta:\eta\in X\}$ of subsets of $X$ with $\eta\in F_\eta$, where each $F_\eta$ measures the allowed ``roughness'' of convergence toward $\eta$.
  More precisely, after introducing the corresponding notions of cluster and limit points, we prove several inclusion and invariance properties, discuss their structural properties, and give examples showing that the rough notions are genuinely different from the classical ideal ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13805v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Leonetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LU-type factorizations for birth--death processes and their Darboux transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study LU-type factorizations of the infinitesimal generator of a birth--death process on $\mathbb{N}_0$. Our goal is to characterize those factorizations whose Darboux transformations (that is, inverting the order of the factors) yield new infinitesimal generators of birth--death processes. Two types are considered: lower--upper (LU), which is unique and upper--lower (UL), which involves a free parameter. For both cases, we determine the conditions under which such factorizations can occur, derive explicit formulas for their coefficients, and provide a probabilistic interpretation of the factors. The spectral properties and associated orthogonal polynomials of the Darboux transformations are also analyzed. Finally, the general results are applied to classical examples such as the $M/M/1$ and $M/M/\infty$ queues and to different cases of linear birth--death processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14074v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Arcia-Manoleskos, Manuel Dom\'inguez de la Iglesia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quaternion-Valued Wavelets on the Plane: A Construction via the Douglas-Rachford Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12614v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a reformulation of the construction of nonseparable multiresolution quaternion-valued wavelets on the plane as a feasibility problem. The constraint sets in the feasibility problem are derived from the standard conditions of smoothness, compact support, and orthonormality. To solve the resulting feasibility problems, we employ a product space formulation of the Douglas-Rachford algorithm. This approach yields novel examples of nonseparable, multiresolution, compactly supported, smooth, and orthonormal quaternion-valued wavelets on the plane. Additionally, by introducing a symmetry-promoting constraint, we construct symmetric quaternion-valued scaling functions on the plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12614v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neil D. Dizon, Jeffrey A. Hogan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform bounds for bilinear symbols with linear K-quasiconformally embedded singularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11661v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove bounds in the strict local $L^{2}(\mathbb{R}^{d})$ range for trilinear Fourier multiplier forms with a $d$-dimensional singular subspace. Given a fixed parameter $K \ge 1$, we treat multipliers with non-degenerate singularity that are push-forwards by $K$-quasiconformal matrices of suitable symbols. As particular applications, our result recovers the uniform bounds for the one-dimensional bilinear Hilbert transforms in the strict local $L^{2}$ range, and it implies the uniform bounds for two-dimensional bilinear Beurling transforms, which are new, in the same range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11661v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2140/apde.2025.18.2293</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Analysis &amp; PDE 18 (2025) 2293-2323</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marco Fraccaroli, Olli Saari, Christoph Thiele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bilinear Rough Singular Integrals near the Critical Integrability via Sharp Fourier Multiplier Criteria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15785v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish boundedness results for bilinear singular integral operators with rough homogeneous kernels whose restriction to the unit sphere belongs to the Orlicz space $L(\log L)^\alpha$. This improves the previously best known condition for boundedness of such bilinear operators obtained in the paper of the first and third authors, and provides estimates close to the conjectured endpoint of integrability suggested by the linear theory. The proof is based on a new sharp boundedness criterion for bilinear Fourier multiplier operators associated with sums of dyadic dilations of a fixed symbol $m_0$, compactly supported away from the origin. This criterion admits the best possible behavior with respect to a modulation of $m_0$ and is intimately connected with sharp shifted square function estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15785v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Dosidis, Bae Jun Park, Lenka Slavikova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A positive product formula of integral kernels of $k$-Hankel transforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03554v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $k$-Hankel transform $F_{k,1}$ (or the $(k,1)$-generalized Fourier transform) is the Dunkl analogue of the unitary inversion operator in the minimal representation of a conformal group initiated by T. Kobayashi and G. Mano. It is one of the two most significant cases in $(k,a)$-generalized Fourier transforms. We will establish a positive radial product formula for the integral kernels of $F_{k,1}$. Such a product formula is equivalent to a representation of the generalized spherical mean operator in terms of the probability measure $\sigma_{x,t}^{k,1}(\xi)$. We will then study the representing measure $\sigma_{x,t}^{k,1}(\xi)$ and analyze the support of the measure, and derive a weak Huygens's principle for the deformed wave equation in $(k,1)$-generalized Fourier analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03554v5</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wentao Teng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certain Inequalities for the generalized polar derivative of a polynomial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02775v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently Rather et al. \cite{NT} considered the generalized derivative and the generalized polar derivative and studied the relative position of zeros of generalized derivative and generalized polar derivative with respect to the zeros of polynomial.\\ \indent In this paper, we establish some inequalities that estimate the maximum modulus of generalized derivative and the generalized polar derivative of the polynomial $P(z)$, which is also the extension of recently known results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02775v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. A. Rathe, D. R. Bhat, I. Dar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability for Strichartz inequalities: Existence of minimizers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07174v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the quantitative stability associated with the adjoint Fourier restriction inequality, focusing on the paraboloid and two-dimensional sphere cases. We show that these Strichartz-stability inequalities admit minimizers attaining their sharp constants, provided that these sharp constants are strictly smaller than the corresponding spectral-gap constants. Furthermore, for the two-dimensional sphere case, we obtain the existence of minimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07174v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boning Di, Dunyan Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Complex-Analytic Models to Sparse Domination: A Dyadic Approach of Hypersingular Operators via Bourgain's Interpolation Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24972v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by the work of Cheng--Fang--Wang--Yu on the hypersingular Bergman projection, we develop a real-variable and dyadic framework for hypersingular operators in regimes where strong-type estimates fail at the critical line. The main new input is a hypersingular sparse domination principle combined with Bourgain's interpolation method, which provides a flexible mechanism to establish critical-line (and endpoint) estimates.
  In the unit disc setting with $1&lt;t&lt;3/2$, we obtain a full characterization of the $(p,q)$ mapping theory for the dyadic hypersingular maximal operator $\mathcal M_t^{\mathcal D}$, in particular including estimates on the critical line $1/q-1/p=2t-2$ and a weighted endpoint criterion in the radial setting. In addition, we establish a novel two-weight estimate for $\mathcal M_t^{\mathcal D}$ in the range $p&gt;q$, valid for any $t&gt;0$. We also prove endpoint estimates for the hypersingular Bergman projection \[ K_{2t}f(z)=\int_{\mathbb D}\frac{f(w)}{(1-z\overline w)^{2t}}\,dA(w), \] including a restricted weak-type bound at $(p,q)=\bigl(\tfrac{1}{3-2t},1\bigr)$. Finally, we introduce a class of hypersingular cousin of sparse operators in $\mathbb R^n$ associated with \emph{graded} sparse families, quantified by the sparseness $\eta$ and a new structural parameter (the \emph{degree}) $K_{\mathcal S}$, and we characterize the corresponding strong/weak/restricted weak-type regimes in terms of $(n,t,\eta,K_{\mathcal S})$.
  Our real-variable perspective addresses an inquiry raised by Cheng--Fang--Wang--Yu on developing effective real-analytic tools in the hypersingular regime for $K_{2t}$, and it also provides a new route toward the critical-line analysis of Forelli--Rudin type operators and related hypersingular operators in both real and complex settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24972v4</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bingyang Hu, Xiaojing Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On oscillator death in the Winfree model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01203v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that for the standard sinusoidal Winfree model, a coupling strength exceeding twice the maximal magnitude of the intrinsic frequencies guarantees the convergence of the system for Lebesgue almost every initial data. This is proven by first showing, via an order parameter bootstrapping argument, that the pathwise critical coupling strength is upper bounded by a function of the order parameter, and then showing by a volumetric argument that for Lebesgue almost every data the order parameter cannot stay below and be bounded away from 1 for all time; this is a Winfree model counterpart of the analysis of Ha and the author (2020) performed for the Kuramoto model. Using concentration of measure and the aforementioned volumetric argument, we show that, except possibly on a set of very small measure, oscillator death is observed in finite time; this rigorously demonstrates the existence of the oscillator death regime numerically observed by Ariaratnam and Strogatz (2001). These results are robust under many other choices of interaction functions often considered for the Winfree model. We demonstrate that the asymptotic dynamics described in this paper are sharp by analyzing the equilibria of the Winfree model, and we bound the total number of equilibria using a polynomial description.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01203v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung-Yeon Ryoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local dimension spectrum for dominated planar self-affine sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13626v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The local dimension spectrum provides a framework for quantifying the fractal properties of a measure, and it is well understood for non-overlapping self-similar measures. In this article, we study the local dimension spectrum for dominated self-affine measures. By analyzing exact dimensionality, we obtain deterministic results that extend the scope of the local dimension spectrum beyond the almost-sure setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13626v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Batsis, Antti K\"aenm\"aki, Tom Kempton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calogero-Sutherland hyperbolic system and Heckman-Opdam $\mathfrak{gl}_n$ hypergeometric function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18864v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove equivalence of two integral representations for the wave functions of hyperbolic Calogero-Sutherland system. For this we study two families of Baxter operators related to hyperbolic Calogero-Sutherland and rational Ruijsenaars models; the first one as a limit from hyperbolic Ruijsenaars system, while the second one independently. Besides, computing asymptotics of integral representations and also the value at zero point, we identify them with renormalized Heckman-Opdam $\mathfrak{gl}_n$ hypergeometric function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18864v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Belousov, L. Cherepanov, S. Derkachov, S. Khoroshkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold graphs are globally synchronizing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12646v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Kuramoto model describes phase oscillators on the unit circle whose interactions are encoded by a graph. Each edge acts like a spring that pulls adjacent oscillators toward each other whenever their phases differ. A central question is to determine which graphs are globally synchronizing, meaning that trajectories of the Kuramoto dynamics converge to the fully synchronized state from almost all initial conditions. This property is tightly linked to the benign nonconvexity of the model's energy landscape. Existing guarantees for global synchronization typically require every node to connect to sufficiently many neighbors, which in turn enforces rather homogeneous degree sequences and highly dense graphs. In this work, we identify threshold graphs as a class of graphs that lie outside this regime yet nevertheless exhibit global synchronization. More precisely, connected threshold graphs realize all admissible edge densities ranging from \(2/n\) to \(1\), and their degree sequences are maximally left-skewed among all graphs with the same edge density, when ordered in nonincreasing order. Our proof relies on a phasor-geometric analysis of the stationary points of the associated energy landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12646v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongjin Wu, Ulrik Brandes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kuznecov formulae for fractal measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18379v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $(M,g)$ be a compact, connected Riemannian manifold of dimension $n\ge 2$, and let $\{e_j\}_{j=0}^\infty$ be an orthonormal basis of Laplace eigenfunctions $-\Delta_g e_j=\lambda_j^2 e_j$. Given a finite Borel measure $\mu$ on $M$, consider the Kuznecov sum \[
  N_\mu(\lambda):=\sum_{\lambda_j\le \lambda}\Bigl|\int_M e_j\,d\mu\Bigr|^2. \] Assume that $\mu$ admits an averaged $s$-density constant $A_\mu$ with correlation dimension $s\in(0,n)$. We prove that \[N_\mu(\lambda)= (2\pi)^{-(n-s)}\,{\rm vol}(B^{\,n-s})\,A_\mu\,\lambda^{n-s}+ o(\lambda^{n-s})\qquad (\lambda\to\infty). \] The averaged $s$-density condition is necessary for such a one-term asymptotic, and in general, the remainder $o(\lambda^{n-s})$ is sharp in the sense that it cannot be improved uniformly to a power-saving error term. This extends the classical Kuznecov formula of Zelditch for smooth submanifold measures to a broad class of singular and fractal measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18379v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yakun Xi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New discretised polynomial expander and incidence estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01264v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present two applications of recent developments in incidence geometry. One is a $\delta$-discretised version of a particular `Elekes--R\'onyai' expander problem. The second application is an incidence estimate addressing the scenario when both tubes, squares and their shadings satisfy non-concentration assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01264v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ciprian Demeter, William O'Regan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
