<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT</link>
    <description>math.CT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 04:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On Dialectica and Differentiation, via Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Godel's Dialectica has been introduced and developed as a logical transformation. Only recently has it been related with the, a priori unrelated, notion of differentiation: we can now read it as a differentiable program transformation. Building on that, we formulate the relation between these two notions categorically, in the framework of differential categories. Moreover, we study the relation between differential categories and Dialectica categories. We do this by taking the point of view of fibrations and (dependent) lenses, which allows us to keep a geometrical intuition in mind by considering reverse tangent categories. The viewpoint we propose opens many interesting further developments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22494v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Barbarossa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functors Preserving Effective Descent Morphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective descent morphisms, originally defined in Grothendieck's descent theory, form a class of special epimorphisms within a category. Essentially, an effective descent morphism enables bundles over its codomain to be fully described as bundles over its domain endowed with additional algebraic structure (or, more generally, descent data). Like the study of epimorphisms, studying effective descent morphisms is interesting in its own right, providing deeper insights into the category under consideration. Moreover, studying these morphisms is part of the foundations of several applications of descent theory, notably including Janelidze-Galois theory (also known as categorical Galois theory).
  Traditionally, the study of effective descent morphisms has focused on investigating and exploiting the reflection properties of certain functors. In contrast, we introduce a novel approach by establishing general results on the preservation of effective descent morphisms. We demonstrate that these preservation results enhance the toolkit for studying such morphisms, by observing that all Grothendieck (op)fibrations satisfying mild conditions fit our framework. To illustrate these findings, we provide several examples of Grothendieck (op)fibrations that preserve effective descent morphisms, including topological functors and other forgetful functors of significant interest in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22876v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Lucatelli Nunes, Rui Prezado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sectional number of a morphism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The genus of a fibration was introduced by Schwarz in 1962. Given a continuous map $g:A\to B$, the usual sectional number $\text{sec}_u(g)$ is the least integer~$m$ such that $B$ can be covered by $m$ open subsets, each of which admits a local section of~$g$. Likewise, the sectional category $\text{secat}(g)$ is the least integer~$m$ such that $B$ can be covered by $m$ open subsets, each of which admits a local homotopy section of~$g$. In the case that $g$ is a fibration, the usual sectional number and the sectional category of $g$ coincide with the Schwarz's genus of $g$. In this paper, we introduce a notion of sectional number for a morphism in a category with covers, which extends the usual sectional number and sectional category (and, of course, Schwarz's notion). We study the invariance property, the behaviour under weak pullbacks and continuous functors, and present upper bounds in terms of a notion of LS category and projective covering number for an object. In addition, we introduce a notion of multiplicative cohomology theory on a category with covers, and we use it to present a cohomological lower bound for the sectional number. Several examples of this invariant are presented to support this theory. For instance, our sectional number yields a family of new numerical invariants in Top; we also express the twin prime conjecture and Goldbach's conjecture in terms of sectional numbers in the category of sets. Our unified concept is relevant in this new setting because it provides a foundation for sectional theory in category theory and builds bridges between new areas in mathematics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22515v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cesar A. Ipanaque Zapata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorics of higher-categorical diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07273v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This is a book on higher-categorical diagrams, including pasting diagrams. It aims to provide a thorough and modern reference on the subject, collecting, revisiting and expanding results scattered across the literature, informed by recent advances and practical experience with higher-dimensional diagram rewriting.
  We approach the subject as a kind of directed combinatorial topology: a diagram is a map from a "directed cell complex", encoded combinatorially as a face poset together with orientation data. Unlike previous expositions, we adopt from the beginning a functorial viewpoint, focussing on morphisms and categorical constructions. We do not tie ourselves to a specific model of higher categories, and instead treat diagrams as independent combinatorial structures that admit functorial interpretations in various contexts.
  Topics covered include the theory of layerings of diagrams; acyclicity properties and their consequences; constructions including Gray products, suspensions, and joins; special shapes such as globes, oriented simplices, cubes, and positive opetopes; the interpretation of diagrams in strict omega-categories and their geometric realisation as simplicial and CW complexes; and Steiner's theory of directed chain complexes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07273v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amar Hadzihasanovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Silting reduction and picture categories of 0-Auslander extriangulated categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00593v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{C}$ be an extriangulated category and let $\mathcal{R}\subseteq \mathcal{C}$ be a rigid subcategory. Generalizing Iyama--Yang silting reduction, we devise a technical condition $\textbf{(gCP)}$ on $\mathcal{R}$ which is sufficient for the Verdier quotient $\mathcal{C}/\mathrm{thick}(\mathcal{R})$ to be equivalent to an ideal quotient. In particular, the Verdier quotient $\mathcal{C}/\mathrm{thick}(\mathcal{R})$ will admit an extriangulation in such a way that the localization functor $L_{\mathcal{R}}\colon \mathcal{C} \rightarrow \mathcal{C}/\mathrm{thick}(\mathcal{R})$ is extriangulated. When $\mathcal{C}$ is 0-Auslander, the condition $\textbf{(gCP)}$ holds for all rigid subcategories $\mathcal{R}$ admitting Bongartz completions. Furthermore, we prove that the Verdier quotient $\mathcal{C}/\mathrm{thick}(\mathcal{R})$ then remains 0-Auslander. As an application, we define the picture category of a connective $0$-Auslander exact dg category $\mathscr{A}$ with Bongartz completions, which generalizes the notion of $\tau$-cluster morphism category. We show that the picture category of $\mathscr{A}$ is a cubical category, in the sense of Igusa. The picture group of $\mathscr{A}$ is defined as the fundamental group of its picture category. When $H_0\mathscr{A}$ is $\mathbf{g}$-finite, the picture group of $\mathscr{A}$ is finitely presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00593v4</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erlend D. B{\o}rve</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compositional imprecise probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09391v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Imprecise probability is concerned with uncertainty about which probability distributions to use. It has applications in robust statistics and machine learning.
  We look at programming language models for imprecise probability. Our desiderata are that we would like our model to support all kinds of composition, categorical and monoidal; in other words, guided by dataflow diagrams. Another equivalent perspective is that we would like a model of synthetic probability in the sense of Markov categories.
  Imprecise probability can be modelled in various ways, with the leading monad-based approach using convex sets of probability distributions. This model is not fully compositional because the monad involved is not commutative, meaning it does not have a proper monoidal structure. In this work, we provide a new fully compositional account. The key idea is to name the non-deterministic choices. To manage the renamings and disjointness of names, we use graded monads. We show that the resulting compositional model is maximal and relate it with the earlier monadic approach, proving that we obtain tighter bounds on the uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09391v2</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Liell-Cock, Sam Staton</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
