<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT</link>
    <description>math.CT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 05:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Correspondences between codensity and coupling-based liftings, a practical approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12333v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kantorovich distance is a widely used metric between probability distributions. The Kantorovich-Rubinstein duality states that it can be defined in two equivalent ways: as a supremum, based on non-expansive functions into [0, 1], and as an infimum, based on probabilistic couplings. Orthogonally, there are categorical generalisations of both presentations proposed in the literature, in the form of codensity liftings and what we refer to as coupling-based liftings. Both lift endofunctors on the category Set of sets and functions to that of pseudometric spaces, and both are parameterised by modalities from coalgebraic modal logic. A generalisation of the Kantorovich-Rubinstein duality has been more nebulous-it is known not to work in some cases. In this paper we propose a compositional approach for obtaining such generalised dualities for a class of functors, which is closed under coproducts and products. Our approach is based on an explicit construction of modalities and also applies to and extends known cases such as that of the powerset functor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12333v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Humeau (ENS de Lyon, LIP, PLUME), Daniela Petrisan (IRIF), Jurriaan Rot (ICIS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular $\mathbb{Z}_2$-Crossed Tambara-Yamagami-like Categories for Even Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12251v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explicitly construct nondegenerate braided $\mathbb{Z}_2$-crossed tensor categories of the form $\operatorname{Vect}_\Gamma\oplus\operatorname{Vect}_{\Gamma/2\Gamma}$. They are $\mathbb{Z}_2$-crossed extensions, in the sense of arXiv:0909.3140, of the braided tensor category $\operatorname{Vect}_\Gamma$ with $\mathbb{Z}_2$-action given by $-\mathrm{id}$ on the finite, abelian group $\Gamma$. Thus, we obtain generalisations of the Tambara-Yamagami categories, where now the abelian group $\Gamma$ may have even order and the nontrivial sector $\operatorname{Vect}_{\Gamma/2\Gamma}$ more than one simple object.
  The idea for this construction comes from a physically motivated approach in arXiv:2409.16357 to construct $\mathbb{Z}_2$-crossed extensions of $\operatorname{Vect}_\Gamma$ for any $\Gamma$ from an infinite Tambara-Yamagami category $\operatorname{Vect}_{\mathbb{R}^d}\oplus\operatorname{Vect}$, which itself is not fully rigorously defined, and then using condensation from $\operatorname{Vect}_{\mathbb{R}^d}$ to $\operatorname{Vect}_\Gamma$, which we prove commutes with crossed extensions.
  The $\mathbb{Z}_2$-equivariantisation of $\operatorname{Vect}_\Gamma\oplus\operatorname{Vect}_{\Gamma/2\Gamma}$ yields new modular tensor categories, which correspond to the orbifold of an arbitrary lattice vertex operator algebra under a lift of $-\mathrm{id}$, as discussed in arXiv:2409.16357.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12251v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'esar Galindo, Simon Lentner, Sven M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards enriched universal algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11972v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following the classical approach of Birkhoff, we suggest an enriched version of enriched universal algebra. Given a suitable base of enrichment $\mathcal V$, we define a language $\mathbb L$ to be a collection of $(X,Y)$-ary function symbols whose arities are taken among the objects of $\mathcal V$. The class of $\mathbb L$-terms is constructed recursively from the symbols of $\mathbb L$, the morphisms in $\mathcal V$, and by incorporating the monoidal structure of $\mathcal V$. Then, $\mathbb L$-structures and interpretations of terms are defined, leading to enriched equational theories. In this framework we characterize algebras for finitary monads on $\mathcal V$ as models of an equational theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11972v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji\v{r}\'i Rosick\'y, Giacomo Tendas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Arboreal Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.10088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.10088v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Arboreal categories, introduced by Abramsky and Reggio, axiomatise categories with tree-shaped objects. These categories provide a categorical language for formalising behavioural notions such as simulation, bisimulation, and resource-indexing. In this paper, we strengthen the axioms of an arboreal category to exclude `branching' behaviour, obtaining a notion of `linear arboreal category'. We then demonstrate that every arboreal category satisfying a linearisability condition has an associated linear arboreal subcategory related via an adjunction. This identifies the relationship between the pebble-relation comonad, of Montacute and Shah, and the pebbling comonad, of Abramsky, Dawar, and Wang, and generalises it further. As another outcome of this new framework, we obtain a linear variant of the arboreal category for modal logic. By doing so we recover different linear-time equivalences between transition systems as instances of their categorical definitions. We conclude with new preservation and characterisation theorems relating trace inclusion and trace equivalence with different linear fragments of modal logic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.10088v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samson Abramsky, Yo\`av Montacute, Nihil Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
