<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT</link>
    <description>math.CT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 04:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the equivalence invariance of formal category theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a result of equivalence invariance of formal category theory for statements that can be expressed within an equipment. To do this, we exploit Henry and Bardomiano Mart\'inez's link between Makkai's FOLDS (first order logic with dependent sorts) and abstract homotopy theory. In the process, we construct a model structure on the category DblCat of double categories and double functors, whose trivial fibrations are the double functors that are surjective on objects, full on horizontal and vertical morphisms, and fully faithful on squares, and whose fibrant objects are the equipments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04255v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paula Verdugo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cartesian Linearly Distributive Categories: Revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linearly distributive categories (LDC) were introduced by Cockett and Seely to provide an alternative categorical semantics for multiplicative linear logic. In contrast to Barr's $\ast$-autonomous categories, LDCs take multiplicative conjunction and disjunction as primitive notions. Thus, a LDC is a category with two monoidal products that interact via linear distributors. A cartesian linearly distributive category (CLDC) is a LDC whose two monoidal products coincide with categorical products and coproducts. Initially, it was believed that CLDCs and distributive categories would coincide, but this was later found not to be the case. Consequently, the study on CLDCs was not pursued further at the time. With recent developments for and applications of LDCs, there has been renewed interest in CLDCs. This paper revisits CLDCs, demonstrating strong structural properties they all satisfy and investigating two key classes of examples: posetal distributive categories and semi-additive categories. Additionally, we re-examine a previously assumed class of CLDCs, the Kleisli categories of exception monads of distributive categories, and show that they are not, in fact, CLDCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04435v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rose Kudzman-Blais, Jean-Simon Pacaud Lemay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An axiomatic approach to analytic $1$-affineness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04341v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The notion of $1$-affineness was originally formulated by Gaitsgory in the context of derived algebraic geometry. Motivated by applications to rigid and analytic geometry, we introduce two very general and abstract frameworks where it makes to ask for objects to be $1$-affine with respect to some sheaf of categories. The first framework is suited for studying the problem of $1$-affineness when the sheaf of categories arises from an operation in a six-functor formalism over $\mathscr{C}$; we apply it to the setting of analytic stacks and condensed mathematics. The second one concerns $1$-affineness in the context of quasi-coherent sheaves of categorical modules over stable module categories: it simultaneously generalizes the algebro-geometric setting of Gaitsgory and makes it possible to formulate the problem also when dealing with rigid analytic varieties and categories of nuclear modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04341v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Montagnani, Emanuele Pavia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polygraphs: From Rewriting to Higher Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00429v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polygraphs are a higher-dimensional generalization of the notion of directed graph. Based on those as unifying concept, this monograph on polygraphs revisits the theory of rewriting in the context of strict higher categories, adopting the abstract point of view offered by homotopical algebra. The first half explores the theory of polygraphs in low dimensions and its applications to the computation of the coherence of algebraic structures. It is meant to be progressive, with little requirements on the background of the reader, apart from basic category theory, and is illustrated with algorithmic computations on algebraic structures. The second half introduces and studies the general notion of n-polygraph, dealing with the homotopy theory of those. It constructs the folk model structure on the category of strict higher categories and exhibits polygraphs as cofibrant objects. This allows extending to higher dimensional structures the coherence results developed in the first half.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00429v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/9781009498968</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dimitri Ara, Albert Burroni, Yves Guiraud, Philippe Malbos, Fran\c{c}ois M\'etayer, Samuel Mimram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Riemannian diffeology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04170v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a framework for Riemannian diffeology. To this end, we use the tangent functor in the sense of Blohmann and one of the options of a metric on a diffeological space in the sense of Iglesias-Zemmour. As a consequence, the category consisting of weak Riemannian diffeological spaces and isometries is established. With a technical condition for a definite weak Riemannian metric, we show that the psudodistance induced by the metric is indeed a distance. As examples of weak Riemannian diffeological spaces, an adjunction space of manifolds, a space of smooth maps and the mixed one are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04170v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katsuhiko Kuribayashi, Keiichi Sakai, Yusuke Shiobara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homological Mirror Symmetry Course at SIMIS: Introduction and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14779v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The present work consists of topics covered through a course currently taught by the author at SIMIS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14779v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Veronica Pasquarella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher Segal spaces and partial groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05437v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The d-Segal conditions of Dyckerhoff and Kapranov are exactness properties for simplicial objects based on the geometry of cyclic polytopes in d-dimensional Euclidean space. 2-Segal spaces are also known as decomposition spaces, and most activity has focused on this case. We study the interplay of these conditions with the partial groups of Chermak, a class of symmetric simplicial sets. The d-Segal conditions simplify for symmetric simplicial objects, and take a particularly explicit form for partial groups. We show partial groups provide a rich class of d-Segal sets for d &gt; 2, by undertaking a systematic study of the "degree" of a partial group X, namely the smallest nonnegative integer k such that X is 2k-Segal. We develop effective tools to explicitly compute the degree based on the discrete geometry of actions of partial groups, which we define and study. Applying these tools involves solving Helly-type problems for abstract closure spaces. We carry out degree computations in concrete settings, including for the punctured Weyl groups introduced here, where we find that the degree is closely related to the maximal dimension of an abelian subalgebra of the associated semisimple Lie algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05437v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Hackney, Justin Lynd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recursive Reward Aggregation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08537v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In reinforcement learning (RL), aligning agent behavior with specific objectives typically requires careful design of the reward function, which can be challenging when the desired objectives are complex. In this work, we propose an alternative approach for flexible behavior alignment that eliminates the need to modify the reward function by selecting appropriate reward aggregation functions. By introducing an algebraic perspective on Markov decision processes (MDPs), we show that the Bellman equations naturally emerge from the recursive generation and aggregation of rewards, allowing for the generalization of the standard discounted sum to other recursive aggregations, such as discounted max and Sharpe ratio. Our approach applies to both deterministic and stochastic settings and integrates seamlessly with value-based and actor-critic algorithms. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach effectively optimizes diverse objectives, highlighting its versatility and potential for real-world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08537v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuting Tang, Yivan Zhang, Johannes Ackermann, Yu-Jie Zhang, Soichiro Nishimori, Masashi Sugiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
