<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT</link>
    <description>math.CT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 01:29:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Anchored Planar Algebras and 3-Categorical Graphical Calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00995v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Anchored planar algebras, a generalized notion of Vaughan Jones' planar algebras, have recently seen use in higher category theory, functional analysis, and TQFT applications. These algebras are equipped with a natural 3-dimensional graphical calculus. We compare this graphical calculus with the 3-dimensional graphical calculus associated to tricategories, and we show that anchored planar algebras can be thought of as living in a particular tricategory. This allows for more general techniques to be applied to anchored planar algebras and expands the types of diagrams that anchored planar algebras can interpret.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00995v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brett Hungar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>McKinsey-Tarski algebras and Raney extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of Raney morphism between MT-algebras and show that the resulting category is equivalent to the category of Raney extensions. This is done by generalizing the construction of the Funayama envelope of a frame. The resulting notion of the $T_0$-hull of a Raney extension generalizes that of the $T_D$-hull of a frame.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01233v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guram Bezhanishvili, Ranjitha Raviprakash, Anna Laura Suarez, Joanne Walters-Wayland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of the categories of categorical groups and cssc-crossed modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01417v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In [8] we proved that any categorical group defines a c-crossed module, which is a cssc-crossed module defined in the same paper. In [9] we constructed a categorical group for any cssc-crossed module. In the presented paper we prove that these correspondences define functors between the corresponding categories, which realize an equivalence of the categories of categorical groups and cssc-crossed modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01417v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamar Datuashvili, Osman Mucuk, Nazmiye Alemdar, Tun\c{c}ar \c{S}ahan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Permutation twisted cohomology, remixed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We generalize Balmer and Gallauer's (permutation) twisted cohomology ring, working towards an alternative deduction of the Balmer spectrum of the derived category of permutation modules for any finite $p$-group. The construction comes equipped with a canonical comparison map from the Balmer spectrum to the homogeneous spectrum of the twisted cohomology ring, which we deduce is injective and an open immersion when the twisted cohomology ring is noetherian. For elementary abelian $p$-groups, the twisted cohomology ring coincides with Balmer and Gallauer's original construction.
  To perform this construction, we utilize endotrivial complexes (i.e. the invertible objects of the derived category of permutation modules) arising (up to a shift) from Bredon homology of representation spheres. This topological structure allows us to construct certain $p$-local isomorphisms, from which we build a refined open cover of the Balmer spectrum indexed by conjugacy classes of subgroups of $G$. Under this open cover, every endotrivial complex is isomorphic to a shift of the tensor unit in each localization, thus verifying that all endotrivial complexes are line bundles. When the twisted cohomology ring is noetherian, this open cover endows the Balmer spectrum with Dirac scheme structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00954v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam K. Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The singularity category as a stable module category</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01056v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the stabilization $\mathcal{S}$ of the module category over an artinian ring $\Lambda$ by formally inverting the tensor endofunctor given by the bimodule of relative noncommutative differential $1$-forms. It turns out that $\mathcal{S}$ is a Frobenius abelian category, which is equivalent to the category of finitely presented modules over the zeroth component $L_0$ of the Leavitt ring $L$. It follows that $L_0$ is an FC ring in the sense of Damiano, which is usually not quasi-Frobenius. Moreover, the singularity category of $\Lambda$ is triangle equivalent to the stable module category over $L_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01056v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Wu Chen, Zhengfang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-dimensional modules over associative equivariant map algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01386v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $X$ and $\mathfrak{a}$ be an affine scheme and (respectively) a finite-dimensional associative algebra over an algebraically-closed field $\Bbbk$, both equipped with actions by a linearly-reductive linear algebraic group $G$. We describe the simple finite-dimensional modules over the algebra of $G$-equivariant maps $X\to \mathfrak{a}$ in terms of the representation theory of the fixed-point subalgebras $\mathfrak{a}^x:=\mathfrak{a}^{G_x}\le \mathfrak{a}$, $G_x$ being the respective isotropy groups of closed-orbit $k$-points $x\in X$. This answers a question of E. Neher and A. Savage, extending an analogous result for (also linearly-reductive) finite-group actions. Moreover, the full category of finite-dimensional modules admits a direct-sum decomposition indexed by closed orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01386v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandru Chirvasitu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open 2D TFTs admit initial open-closed extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that any open 2-dimensional topological field theory valued in a symmetric monoidal $\infty$-category (with suitable colimits) extends canonically to an open-closed field theory whose value at the circle is the Hochschild homology object of its value at the disk. As a corollary, we obtain an action of the moduli spaces of surfaces on the Hochschild homology object of $E_1$-Calabi-Yau algebras. This provides a space level refinement of previous work of Costello over $\mathbb{Q}$ and Wahl-Westerland and Wahl over $\mathbb{Z}$, and serves as a crucial ingredient to Lurie's "non-compact cobordism hypothesis" in dimension 2. As part of the proof we also give a description of slice categories of the d-dimensional bordism category with boundary, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02553v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaul Barkan, Jan Steinebrunner, Adela YiYu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifting independence along functors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14813v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a functor $F: \mathcal{C} \to \mathcal{D}$ and a model-theoretic independence relation on $\mathcal{D}$, we can lift that independence relation along $F$ to $\mathcal{C}$ by declaring a commuting square in $\mathcal{C}$ to be independent if its image under $F$ is independent. For each property that an independence relation can have we give assumptions on the functor that guarantee the property to be lifted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14813v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Kamsma, Ji\v{r}\'i Rosick\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composable Uncertainty in Symmetric Monoidal Categories for Design Problems (Extended Version)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17274v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Applied category theory often studies symmetric monoidal categories (SMCs) whose morphisms represent open systems. These structures naturally accommodate complex wiring patterns, leveraging (co)monoidal structures for splitting and merging wires, or compact closed structures for feedback. A key example is the compact closed SMC of design problems (DP), which enables a compositional approach to co-design in engineering. However, in practice, the systems of interest may not be fully known. Recently, Markov categories have emerged as a powerful framework for modeling uncertain processes. In this work, we demonstrate how to integrate this perspective into the study of open systems while preserving consistency with the underlying SMC structure. To this end, we employ the change-of-base construction for enriched categories, replacing the morphisms of a symmetric monoidal $\mathcal{V}$-category $\mathcal{C}$ with parametric maps $A \to \mathcal{C}(X,Y)$ in a Markov category induced by a symmetric monoidal monad. This results in a symmetric monoidal 2-category $N_*\mathcal{C}$ with the same objects as $\mathcal{C}$ and reparametrization 2-cells. By choosing different monads, we capture various types of uncertainty. The category underlying $\mathcal{C}$ embeds into $N_*\mathcal{C}$ via a strict symmetric monoidal functor, allowing (co)monoidal and compact closed structures to be transferred. Applied to DP, this construction leads to categories of practical relevance, such as parametrized design problems for optimization, and parametrized distributions of design problems for decision theory and Bayesian learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17274v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius Furter, Yujun Huang, Gioele Zardini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triangular spectra and their applications to derived categories of noetherian schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.03168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.03168v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent work, for a triangulated category $\cT$, the author introduced a topological space $\tSpec(\cT)$ which we call the triangular spectrum of $\cT$ as a tensor-free analog of the Balmer spectrum for a tensor triangulated category. In this paper, we use the triangular spectrum to reconstruct a noetherian scheme $X$ from its perfect derived category $\dpf(X)$. As an application, we give an alternative proof of the Bondal-Orlov-Ballard reconstruction theorem in the special case (when both varieties have ample or anti-ample canonical bundles). Moreover, we define the structure sheaf on $\tSpec(\cT)$ and compare the triangular spectrum and the Balmer spectrum as ringed spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.03168v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Matsui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terminal Coalgebras in Countably Many Steps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11071v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a collection of results that imply that an endofunctor on a category has a terminal object obtainable as a countable limit of its terminal-coalgebra chain. This holds for finitary endofunctors preserving nonempty binary intersections on locally finitely presentable categories, assuming that the posets of strong quotients and subobjects of finitely presentable objects satisfy the descending chain condition. This allows one to adapt finiteness arguments that were originally advanced by Worrell concerning terminal coalgebras for finitary set functors. Examples include the categories of sets, posets, vector spaces, graphs, nominal sets, and presheaves on finite sets. Worrell also described, without proof, the terminal-coalgebra chain of the finite power-set functor. We provide a detailed proof following his ideas.
  We then turn to polynomial endofunctors on the categories of Hausdorff topological spaces and metric spaces. The Vietoris space of compact subsets of a given Hausdorff space yields an endofunctor $\mathscr{V}$ on the category of Hausdorff spaces. Vietoris polynomial endofunctors on that category are built from $\mathscr{V}$, the identity and constant functors by forming products, coproducts and compositions. We present an analogous class of endofunctors on the category of extended metric spaces, using in lieu of $\mathscr{V}$ the Hausdorff functor $\mathcal{H}$. We prove that the ensuing Hausdorff polynomial functors have terminal coalgebras and initial algebras. We show that every finitary endofunctor on the category of vector spaces over a fixed field again has a terminal coalgebra obtained in $\omega+\omega$ steps. Whereas the canonical constructions of terminal coalgebras for Vietoris polynomial functors takes $\omega$ steps, one needs $\omega + \omega$ steps in general for our other concrete settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11071v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji\v{r}\'i Ad\'amek, Stefan Milius, Lawrence S. Moss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Term Assignment and Categorical Models for Intuitionistic Linear Logic with Subexponentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12360v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a typed lambda calculus ${\bf SILL}(\lambda)_{\Sigma}$, a type-theoretic version of intuitionistic linear logic with subexponentials, that is, we have many resource comonadic modalities with some interconnections between them given by a subexponential signature. We also give proof normalisation rules and prove the strong normalisation and Church-Rosser properties for $\beta$-reduction by adapting the Tait-Girard method to subexponential modalities. Further, we analyse subexponentials from the point of view of categorical logic. We introduce the concepts of a Cocteau category and a $\Sigma$-assemblage to characterise models of linear type theories with a single exponential and affine and relevant subexponentials and a more general case respectively. We also generalise several known results from linear logic and show that every Cocteau category and a $\Sigma$-assemblage can be viewed as a symmetric monoidal closed category equipped with a family of monoidal adjunctions of a particular kind. In the final section, we give a stronger 2-categorical characterisation of Cocteau categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12360v4</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Rogozin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
