<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT</link>
    <description>math.CT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:01:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Abelian geometry of VI-modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short note, we study the spectrum of prime Serre ideals of global represen tations for noetherian families. In particular, we prove that the spectrum of prime Serre ideals of finitely generated VI-modules is homeomorphic to N^{*}, the one-point compactification of N, which differs from the Balmer spectrum of derived VI-modules. Our method could also be applied to the category of finitely generated FI-modules and the category of global representations for the family of cyclic p-groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14020v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partial Linearity in Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study partial linearity in a category by replacing isomorphism between coproducts and products in a linear category with isomorphism between suitable monoidal structures on a category. The main results a coherence theorem and a generalization of the theory of central morphisms from unital categories to our context of partial linearity</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14237v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roy Ferguson, Zurab Janelidze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Igusa-Todorov properties of recollements of abelian categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12702v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the behavior of Igusa-Todorov properties under recollements of abelian categories. In particular, we study how the Igusa-Todorov distances of the categories involved in a recollement are related. Applications are given to Artin algebras, especially to Morita context rings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12702v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peiru Yang, Yajun Ma, Yu-Zhe Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cofiniteness and $P(z)$-tensor product bifunctors in orbifold theories associated to abelian but not-necessarily-finite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12834v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $V$ be a M\"{o}bius vertex algebra and $G$ an abelian group of automorphisms of $V$. We construct $P(z)$-tensor product bifunctors for the category of $C_{n}$-cofinite grading-restricted generalized $g$-twisted $V$-modules (without $g$-actions) for $g\in G$ and the category of $C_{n}$-cofinite grading-restricted generalized $g$-twisted $V$-modules with $G$-actions for $g\in G$. In this paper, an automorphism $g$ of $V$ can be of infinite order and does not have to act semisimply on $V$, and the group $G$ can be an infinite abelian group containing nonsemisimple automorphisms of $V$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12834v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Zhi Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stone Duality for Preordered Topological Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12932v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A preordered topological space is a topological space with a preordering. We exhibit a Stone-like duality for preordered topological spaces, Inspired by a similar duality for bitopological spaces, due to Jung-Moshier and Jakl, and by a duality for preordered sets due to Bonsangue, Jacobs and Kok.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12932v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Goubault-Larrecq</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locally involutive semigroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13301v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce locally involutive semigroups and embed them into the category of ordered groupoids. This embedding restricts to a correspondence between quasi-involutive semigroups and ordered groupoids with mediator, extending the classical ESN-correspondence between inverse semigroups and inductive groupoids. An important subcategory of locally involutive semigroups is formed by left involutive semigroups because the classifying topos of an inverse semigroup S is equivalent to the category of left involutive semigroups \'etale over S [4]. We recover this equivalence from a general adjointness and use the latter to determine when a left involutive semigroup \'etale over S is actually an involutive semigroup. Any left involutive semigroup \'etale over S embeds into an involutive S-algebra as we call it. The underlying semigroup of this algebra is involutive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13301v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Berger, Jonathon Funk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative Minkowski integral inequality and a unitary categorification criterion for fusion rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13490v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a noncommutative analogue of Minkowski's integral inequality for commuting squares of tracial von Neumann algebras. The inequality implies a necessary condition for a quadruple of graphs to be realized as inclusion graphs of a commuting square of multi-matrix algebras. As a corollary, we obtain a unitary categorification criterion for based rings, in particular, fusion rings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13490v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junhwi Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free monoids and Riguet congruences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15767v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We begin by associating to $\mathbf{A}^{\star}$, the free monoid on a set $A$, a category $\mathsf{C}(\mathbf{A}^{\star})$ -- an instance of the free coproduct completion of a discrete category -- which is in general non-skeletal, and by proving that it is equivalent to $\mathsf{Set}^{A}_{\mathrm{f}}$, the category of finite $A$-sorted sets. Next, as a step toward constructing a skeletal quotient category of $\mathsf{C}(\mathbf{A}^{\star})$ via the notion of a Riguet congruence on a category, we recall this notion, correct and complete it, and examine its relationship with generalized congruences from both lattice-theoretic and category-theoretic perspectives. In particular, after introducing the notion of strong generalized congruence on a category, we prove that, for any category $\mathsf{C}$, there exists an isotone and Scott continuous morphism from $(\mathrm{RCgr}(\mathsf{C}),\subseteq)$, the bounded directed-complete ordered set of Riguet congruences on $\mathsf{C}$ to $(\mathrm{GCgr}(\mathsf{C}),\subseteq)$, the algebraic lattice of generalized congruences on $\mathsf{C}$, that sends a Riguet congruence $\Phi$ on $\mathsf{C}$ to the strong generalized congruence $\Phi^{\natural}$ on $\mathsf{C}$. Finally, for a suitable Riguet congruence on $\mathsf{C}(\mathbf{A}^{\star})$, denoted by $\equiv^{A}$, we construct a skeletal quotient category $\mathsf{Q}(\mathbf{A}^{\star})$ of $\mathsf{C}(\mathbf{A}^{\star})$ and prove that it is equivalent to $\mathsf{Set}^{A}_{\mathrm{f}}$ and also to $\mathsf{C}(\mathbf{A}^{\star})/{\equiv^{A\natural}}$, where $\equiv^{A\natural}$ is the strong generalized congruence on $\mathsf{C}(\mathbf{A}^{\star})$ canonically associated to $\equiv^{A}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15767v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Climent Vidal, Enric Cosme Ll\'opez, Ra\'ul Ruiz Mora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A decomposition theorem for the Hochschild homology of symmetric powers of a dg category</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03269v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a conjecture by Belmans, Fu and Krug concerning the Hochschild homology of the symmetric powers of a small dg category $\mathscr{C}$. More precisely, we show that these groups decompose into pieces that only depend on the Hochschild homology of the dg category $\mathscr{C}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03269v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ville Nordstrom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some properties of the A$_{\infty}$-nerve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1609.00566</link>
      <description>arXiv:1609.00566v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to prove that the A$_{\infty}$-nerve of two quasi-equivalent A$_{\infty}$-categories (linear over a commutative ring) are weak-equivalent in the Joyal model structure. As a consequence we prove that the A$_{\infty}$-nerve of a pretriangulated A$_{\infty}$-category is a stable $\infty$-category.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1609.00566v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Ornaghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflexive graph lenses in univalent foundations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07854v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Martin-L\"of's identity types provide a generic (albeit opaque) notion of identification or "equality" between any two elements of the same type, embodied in a canonical reflexive graph structure $(=_A, \mathbf{refl})$ on any type $A$. The miracle of Voevodsky's univalence principle is that it ensures, for essentially any naturally occurring structure in mathematics, that this the resultant notion of identification is equivalent to the type of isomorphisms in the category of such structures. Characterisations of this kind are not automatic and must be established one-by-one; to this end, several authors have employed reflexive graphs and displayed reflexive graphs to organise the characterisation of identity types. We contribute reflexive graph lenses, a new family of intermediate abstractions lying between families of reflexive graphs and displayed reflexive graphs that simplifies the characterisation of identity types for complex structures. Every reflexive graph lens gives rise to a (more complicated) displayed reflexive graph, and our experience suggests that many naturally occurring displayed reflexive graphs arise in this way. Evidence for the utility of reflexive graph lenses is given by means of several case studies, including the theory of reflexive graphs itself as well as that of polynomial type operators. Finally, we exhibit an equivalence between the type of reflexive graph fibrations and the type of univalent reflexive graph lenses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07854v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Sterling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics, data and reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19734v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The goal of data-driven learning of dynamical systems is to interpret time series as a continuous observation of an underlying dynamical system. This task is not well-posed for a variety of reasons - such as multiple co-existing sub-systems, topologically inter-weaving of these sub-systems; and more importantly, the non-injectivity of the correspondence between dynamical systems and time series. We show how these ambiguities are circumvented if one considers dynamical systems and measurement maps collectively. Dynamical systems, observed dynamical systems, and time series data - each of these three collections have an extensive network of relations within them, which gives them the mathematical structure of a category. One of the new concepts proposed is a rigorous definition of time series data as a chain of measurement sequences with decreasing information content. This definition subsumes the familiar notions of sequences, time series and even subshifts. Using these notions it is shown that the entire process of converting an observed dynamical systems into a time series object is functorial, and passes through a number of phases each bearing its own categorical structure. This discovery sheds new light on the nature of reconstruction algorithms. Under mild conditions of consistency, reconstruction itself is shown to be functorial operation. This provides a new category theoretic perspective on the nature and limits of reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19734v5</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suddhasattwa Das, Tomoharu Suda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rationality patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07151v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish general categorical frameworks that extend Loewy's classification scheme for finite-dimensional real irreducible representations of groups and Borel--Tits' criterion for the existence of rational forms of representations of $\bar{F}\otimes_F G$ for a connected reductive algebraic group $G$ over a field $F$ of characteristic zero and its algebraic closure $\bar{F}$. We also discuss applications of these general formalisms to the theory of Harish-Chandra modules, specifically to classify irreducible Harish-Chandra modules over fields $F$ of characteristic zero and to identify smaller fields of definition of irreducible Harish-Chandra modules over $\bar{F}$, particularly in the case of cohomological irreducible essentially unitarizable modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07151v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuma Hayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit Computation Over Posets via Minimal Initial Functors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.00209v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is well known that limits can be computed by restricting along an initial functor, and that this often simplifies limit computation. We systematically study the algorithmic implications of this idea for diagrams indexed by a finite poset. We say an initial functor $F\colon C\to D$ with $C$ small is \emph{minimal} if the sets of objects and morphisms of $C$ each have minimum cardinality, among the sources of all initial functors with target $D$. For $Q$ a finite poset or $Q\subseteq \mathbb N^d$ an interval (i.e., a convex, connected subposet), we describe all minimal initial functors $F\colon P\to Q$ and in particular, show that $F$ is always a subposet inclusion. We give efficient algorithms to compute a choice of minimal initial functor. In the case that $Q\subseteq \mathbb N^d$ is an interval, we give asymptotically optimal bounds on $|P|$, the number of relations in $P$ (including identities), in terms of the number $n$ of minima of $Q$: We show that $|P|=\Theta(n)$ for $d\leq 3$, and $|P|=\Theta(n^2)$ for $d&gt;3$. We apply these results to give new bounds on the cost of computing $\lim G$ for a functor $G \colon Q\to \mathbf{Vec}$ valued in vector spaces. For $Q$ connected, we also give new bounds on the cost of computing the \emph{generalized rank} of $G$ (i.e., the rank of the induced map $\lim G\to \mathop{\mathrm{colim}} G$), which is of interest in topological data analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.00209v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamal K. Dey, Michael Lesnick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rewriting Systems on Arbitrary Monoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10564v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce monoidal rewriting systems (MRS), an abstraction of string rewriting in which reductions are defined over an arbitrary ambient monoid rather than a free monoid of words. This shift is partly motivated by logic: the class of free monoids is not first-order axiomatizable, so "working in the free setting" cannot be treated internally when applying first-order methods to rewriting presentations.
  To analyze these systems categorically, we define $\mathbf{NCRS_2}$ as the 2-category of Noetherian Confluent MRS. We then prove the existence of a canonical biadjunction between $\mathbf{NCRS_2}$ and $\mathbf{Mon}$.
  Finally, we classify all Noetherian Confluent MRS that present a given fixed monoid. For this, we introduce Generalized Elementary Tietze Transformations (GETTs) and prove that any two presentations of a monoid are connected by a (possibly infinite) sequence of these transformations, yielding a complete characterization of generating systems up to GETT-equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10564v2</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Magalh\~aes</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
