<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.TO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.TO</link>
    <description>q-bio.TO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.TO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Large deformation diffeomorphic cardiac strain mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cardiac deformation is a crucial biomarker for the evaluation of cardiac function. Current methods for estimating cardiac strain might underestimate local deformation due to through-plane motion and segmental averaging. Mesh-based mapping methods are gaining interest for localized analysis of cardiac motion and strain, yet they often do not consider important properties of cardiac tissue. In this work, we propose an extension of the large deformation diffeomorphic metric mapping framework to incorporate near incompressibility into the loss function that guides the mapping. As such, our mechanically regularized mLDDMM allows for accurate and mechanically coherent estimation of volume displacement and strain tensors from time-resolved three-dimensional meshes. We benchmark our method against the results of a finite element simulation of cardiac contraction and find a very good agreement between our estimation and the simulated ground truth. Our method forms a promising technique to extract volume displacement and strain tensors from time-resolved meshes while accounting for the incompressibility of cardiac tissue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03291v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatrice Moscoloni, Patrick Segers, Mathias Peirlinck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BioX-CPath: Biologically-driven Explainable Diagnostics for Multistain IHC Computational Pathology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20880v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The development of biologically interpretable and explainable models remains a key challenge in computational pathology, particularly for multistain immunohistochemistry (IHC) analysis. We present BioX-CPath, an explainable graph neural network architecture for whole slide image (WSI) classification that leverages both spatial and semantic features across multiple stains. At its core, BioX-CPath introduces a novel Stain-Aware Attention Pooling (SAAP) module that generates biologically meaningful, stain-aware patient embeddings. Our approach achieves state-of-the-art performance on both Rheumatoid Arthritis and Sjogren's Disease multistain datasets. Beyond performance metrics, BioX-CPath provides interpretable insights through stain attention scores, entropy measures, and stain interaction scores, that permit measuring model alignment with known pathological mechanisms. This biological grounding, combined with strong classification performance, makes BioX-CPath particularly suitable for clinical applications where interpretability is key. Source code and documentation can be found at: https://github.com/AmayaGS/BioX-CPath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20880v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amaya Gallagher-Syed, Henry Senior, Omnia Alwazzan, Elena Pontarini, Michele Bombardieri, Costantino Pitzalis, Myles J. Lewis, Michael R. Barnes, Luca Rossi, Gregory Slabaugh</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
