<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.TO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.TO</link>
    <description>q-bio.TO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.TO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 05:01:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The mechanics of the $\textit{Less In More Out}$ artificial heart: modeling fabric-based soft robotic devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14984v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, the Less In More Out device, a fluidically actuated soft total artificial heart was proposed. This device uses arrays of pouch motors to achieve a positive fluidic lever when pneumatically actuated against physiological hemodynamic conditions. Extensive experimental characterization demonstrated its potential; however, experiments alone cannot resolve the internal mechanical fields that govern device durability and performance. Here, we develop a computational framework to investigate intrinsic device mechanics, such as stress concentrations, strain paths, and fatigue life, and to explore targeted design modifications that improve durability and efficiency. We show that our model reproduces the nonlinear deformation and pressure-volume relationships measured experimentally under varying hemodynamic conditions. Across designs, devices with fewer pouches deliver higher stroke volumes but exhibit up to 50% higher peak von Mises stresses, which reduces their fatigue life. Our simulations further identify heat-sealed seams and buckling regions as durability-limiting features. As a proof of concept, we vary the valve support aspect ratio and relative endocardial-epicardial pouch fabric compliance, reducing the peak von Mises stress by ~10% while maintaining identical physiological outputs and improving mechanical efficiency. Overall, our framework enables detailed evaluation of stress hotspots, buckling, and fatigue life, and offers a foundation for optimizing artificial hearts and other fluidically actuated fabric-based soft robotic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14984v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marin Lauber, Maziar Arfaee, Mathias Peirlinck</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
