<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 04:02:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic limit in learning period three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08825v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A continuous one-dimensional map with period three includes all periods. This raises the following question: Can we obtain any types of periodic orbits solely by learning three data points? We consider learning period three with random neural networks and report the universal property associated with it. We first show that the trained networks have a thermodynamic limit that depends on the choice of target data and network settings. Our analysis reveals that almost all learned periods are unstable and each network has its characteristic attractors (which can even be untrained ones). Here, we propose the concept of characteristic bifurcation expressing embeddable attractors intrinsic to the network, in which the target data points and the scale of the network weights function as bifurcation parameters. In conclusion, learning period three generates various attractors through characteristic bifurcation due to the stability change in latently existing numerous unstable periods of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08825v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuichiro Terasaki, Kohei Nakajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable synchronization cluster in networked chaotic oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08844v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cluster synchronization in synthetic networks of coupled chaotic oscillators is investigated. It is found that despite the asymmetric nature of the network structure, a subset of the oscillators can be synchronized as a cluster while the other oscillators remain desynchronized. Interestingly, with the increase of the coupling strength, the cluster is expanding gradually by recruiting the desynchronized oscillators one by one. This new synchronization phenomenon, which is named ``scalable synchronization cluster", is explored theoretically by the method of eigenvector-based analysis, and it is revealed that the scalability of the cluster is attributed to the unique feature of the eigenvectors of the network coupling matrix. The transient dynamics of the cluster in response to random perturbations are also studied, and it is shown that in restoring to the synchronization state, oscillators inside the cluster are stabilized in sequence, illustrating again the hierarchy of the oscillators. The findings shed new light on the collective behaviors of networked chaotic oscillators, and are helpful for the design of real-world networks where scalable synchronization clusters are concerned.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08844v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huawei Fan, Yafeng Wang, Yao Du, Haibo Qiu, Xingang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
