<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 05:00:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Transition from topological to chaos in the nonlinear Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent studies on topological insulators have expanded into the nonlinear regime, while the bulk-edge correspondence in strongly nonlinear systems has been unelucidated. Here, we reveal that nonlinear topological edge modes can exhibit a transition to spatial chaos by increasing nonlinearity, which can be a universal mechanism of the breakdown of the bulk-edge correspondence. Specifically, we unveil the underlying dynamical system describing the spatial distribution of zero modes and show the emergence of chaos. We also propose the correspondence between the absolute value of the topological invariant and the dimension of the stable manifold under sufficiently weak nonlinearity. Our results provide a general guiding principle to investigate the nonlinear bulk-edge correspondence that can potentially be extended to arbitrary dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03038v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Sone, Motohiko Ezawa, Zongping Gong, Taro Sawada, Nobuyuki Yoshioka, Takahiro Sagawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid data assimilation techniques using the adjoint method in a coupled Lorenz system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03166v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A hybrid 4D-variational data assimilation method for numerical climate models is introduced using the Lorenz '63 model. This new approach has the potential to optimise a high complexity Earth system model (ESM) by utilising the adjoint equations of an intermediate complexity ESM. The method is conceptually demonstrated by consecutively synchronising two Lorenz '63 systems to observations before optimisation. The first represents a 'high complexity' model and the second an 'intermediate complexity' model which has adjoint equations. This method will save computational power for a full ESM and has negligible error and uncertainty change compared to the optimisation of a single model with adjoint equations. A similar setup can be applied to sparse observations. An alternative assimilation setup, with two identical models, is used to filter noisy data. This reduces optimised parametric model uncertainty by approximately one third. Such a precision gain could prove valuable for seasonal, annual, and decadal predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03166v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip David Kennedy, Abhirup Banerjee, Armin K\"ohl, Detlef Stammer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
