<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 01:48:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Statistics for Differential Topological Properties between Data Sets with an Application to Reservoir Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04571v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is common for researchers to record long, multiple time series from experiments or calculations. But sometimes there are no good models for the systems or no applicable mathematical theorems that can tell us when there are basic relationships between subsets of the time series data such as continuity, differentiability, embeddings, etc. The data is often higher dimensional and simple plotting will not guide us. At that point fitting the data to polynomials, Fourier series, etc. becomes uncertain. Even at the simplest level, having data that shows there is a function between the data subsets is useful and a negative answer means that more particular data fitting or analysis will be suspect and probably fail. We show here statistics that test time series subsets for basic mathematical properties and relations between them that not only indicate when more specific analyses are safe to do, but whether the systems are operating correctly. We apply these statistics to examples from reservoir computing where an important property of reservoir computers is that the reservoir system establishes an embedding of the drive system in order to make any other calculations with the reservoir computer successful.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04571v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Pecora, Thomas Carroll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical scattering and fragmentation of clusters of ions in helical confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the scattering dynamics of classical Coulomb-interacting clusters of ions confined to a helical geometry. Ion clusters of equally charged particles constrained to a helix can form many-body bound states, i.e. they exhibit stable motion of Coulomb-interacting identical ions. We analyze the scattering and fragmentation behavior of two ion clusters, thereby understanding the rich phenomenology of their dynamics. The scattering dynamics is complex in the sense that it exhibits cascades of decay processes involving strongly varying cluster sizes. These processes are governed by the internal energy flow and the underlying oscillatory many-body potential. We specifically focus on the impact of the collision energy on the dynamics of individual ions during and immediately after the collision of two clusters, and on the internal dynamics of ion clusters that are excited during a cluster collision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04852v1</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ansgar Siemens (Zentrum f\"ur Optische Quantentechnologien, Fachbereich Physik, Universit\"at Hamburg), Peter Schmelcher (Zentrum f\"ur Optische Quantentechnologien, Fachbereich Physik, Universit\"at Hamburg, Hamburg Center for Ultrafast Imaging, Universit\"at Hamburg)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate deep learning-based filtering for chaotic dynamics by identifying instabilities without an ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04739v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the ability to discover data assimilation (DA) schemes meant for chaotic dynamics with deep learning. The focus is on learning the analysis step of sequential DA, from state trajectories and their observations, using a simple residual convolutional neural network, while assuming the dynamics to be known. Experiments are performed with the Lorenz 96 dynamics, which display spatiotemporal chaos and for which solid benchmarks for DA performance exist. The accuracy of the states obtained from the learned analysis approaches that of the best possibly tuned ensemble Kalman filter, and is far better than that of variational DA alternatives. Critically, this can be achieved while propagating even just a single state in the forecast step. We investigate the reason for achieving ensemble filtering accuracy without an ensemble. We diagnose that the analysis scheme actually identifies key dynamical perturbations, mildly aligned with the unstable subspace, from the forecast state alone, without any ensemble-based covariances representation. This reveals that the analysis scheme has learned some multiplicative ergodic theorem associated to the DA process seen as a non-autonomous random dynamical system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04739v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Bocquet, Alban Farchi, Tobias S. Finn, Charlotte Durand, Sibo Cheng, Yumeng Chen, Ivo Pasmans, Alberto Carrassi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium Thermodynamics of a Superconducting Szilard Engine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20418v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We implement a Szilard engine using a 2-bit logical unit consisting of inductively coupled quantum flux parametrons (QFPs) -- Josephson-junction superconducting circuits with applications in both the classical and quantum information processing regimes. Detailed simulations show that it is highly thermodynamically efficient while functioning as a Maxwell demon -- converting heat to work. The physically-calibrated design is targeted to direct experimental exploration. However, variations in Josephson junction fabrication introduce asymmetries that result in energy inefficiency and low operational fidelity. We provide a design solution that mitigates these practical challenges. The resulting platform is ideally suited to probe the thermodynamic foundations of information processing devices far from equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20418v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuen Wai Tang, Kyle J. Ray, James P. Crutchfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
