<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 08:13:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Computational Efficiency of Motor Imagery BCI Classification with Block-Toeplitz Augmented Covariance Matrices and Siegel Metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16909v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electroencephalographic signals are represented as multidimensional datasets. We introduce an enhancement to the augmented covariance method (ACM), exploiting more thoroughly its mathematical properties, in order to improve motor imagery classification.Standard ACM emerges as a combination of phase space reconstruction of dynamical systems and of Riemannian geometry. Indeed, it is based on the construction of a Symmetric Positive Definite matrix to improve classification. But this matrix also has a Block-Toeplitz structure that was previously ignored. This work treats such matrices in the real manifold to which they belong: the set of Block-Toeplitz SPD matrices. After some manipulation, this set is can be seen as the product of an SPD manifold and a Siegel Disk Space.The proposed methodology was tested using the MOABB framework with a within-session evaluation procedure. It achieves a similar classification performance to ACM, which is typically better than -- or at worse comparable to -- state-of-the-art methods. But, it also improves consequently the computational efficiency over ACM, making it even more suitable for real time experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16909v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Carrara (UniCA, CRONOS), Theodore Papadopoulo (UniCA, CRONOS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning for Prediction and Classifying the Dynamical behaviour of Piecewise Smooth Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17001v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper explores the prediction of the dynamics of piecewise smooth maps using various deep learning models. We have shown various novel ways of predicting the dynamics of piecewise smooth maps using deep learning models. Moreover, we have used machine learning models such as Decision Tree Classifier, Logistic Regression, K-Nearest Neighbor, Random Forest, and Support Vector Machine for predicting the border collision bifurcation in the 1D normal form map and the 1D tent map. Further, we classified the regular and chaotic behaviour of the 1D tent map and the 2D Lozi map using deep learning models like Convolutional Neural Network (CNN), ResNet50, and ConvLSTM via cobweb diagram and phase portraits. We also classified the chaotic and hyperchaotic behaviour of the 3D piecewise smooth map using deep learning models such as the Feed Forward Neural Network (FNN), Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM), and Recurrent Neural Network (RNN). Finally, deep learning models such as Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) and Recurrent Neural Network (RNN) are used for reconstructing the two parametric charts of 2D border collision bifurcation normal form map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17001v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vismaya V S, Bharath V Nair, Sishu Shankar Muni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum fingerprints of self-organization in spin chains coupled to a Kuramoto model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17062v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Floquet theory is a widely used framework to describe the dynamics of periodically-driven quantum systems. The usual set up to describe such kind of systems is to consider the effect of an external control with a definite period in time that can act either globally or locally on the system of interest. However, besides the periodicity, there is no classical correlation or other well defined structures in the drive. In this work, we consider drives that exhibit self-organization phenomena reaching periodic steady states with emergent symmetries. To substantiate our results, we consider two examples of a one-dimensional quantum spin chains in a transverse field coupled to a classical Kuramoto model. In the case of all-to-tall coupling, the Kuramoto model drives the Ising chain into a time-periodic steady state with an emergent translational symmetry. For a Kuramoto model in a Zig-zag lattice, the XX spin chain is trimerized and the dynamics exhibit topological behavior that can be exploited to perform topological pumping. Our results can be experimentally implemented in near-term quantum devices in digital and analog platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17062v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. M. Bastidas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximation and decomposition of attractors of a Hopfield neural network system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07567v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, the Parameter Switching (PS) algorithm is used to approximate numerically attractors of a Hopfield Neural Network (HNN) system. The PS algorithm is a convergent scheme designed for approximating attractors of an autonomous nonlinear system, depending linearly on a real parameter. Aided by the PS algorithm, it is shown that every attractor of the HNN system can be expressed as a convex combination of other attractors. The HNN system can easily be written in the form of a linear parameter dependence system, to which the PS algorithm can be applied. This work suggests the possibility to use the PS algorithm as a control-like or anticontrol-like method for chaos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07567v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius-F. Danca, Guanrong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Numerical Proof of Shell Model Turbulence Closure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.09289v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The development of turbulence closure models, parametrizing the influence of small non-resolved scales on the dynamics of large resolved ones, is an outstanding theoretical challenge with vast applicative relevance. We present a closure, based on deep recurrent neural networks, that quantitatively reproduces, within statistical errors, Eulerian and Lagrangian structure functions and the intermittent statistics of the energy cascade, including those of subgrid fluxes. To achieve high-order statistical accuracy, and thus a stringent statistical test, we employ shell models of turbulence. Our results encourage the development of similar approaches for 3D Navier-Stokes turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.09289v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevFluids.7.L082401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Fluids. 7, L082401, 2022</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Ortali, Alessandro Corbetta, Gianluigi Rozza, Federico Toschi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
