<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 04:02:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of chaotic relaxation processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The established thermodynamic formalism of chaotic dynamics,valid at statistical equilibrium, is here generalized to systems out of equilibrium, that have yet to relax to a steady state. A relation between information, escape rate, and the phase-space average of an integrated observable (e.g. Lyapunov exponent, diffusion coefficient) is obtained for finite time. Most notably, the thermodynamic treatment may predict the finite-time distributions of any integrated observable from the leading and subleading eigenfunctions of the Perron-Frobenius/Koopman transfer operator. Examples of that equivalence are shown, and the theory is tested numerically in three paradigms of chaos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09130v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domenico Lippolis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal analysis of inner and outer motions in near-wall turbulent flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08907v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we study the causality of near-wall inner and outer turbulent motions. Here we define the inner motions as the self-sustained near-wall cycle and the outer motions as those living in the logarithmic layer exhibiting a footprint on the near-wall region. We perform causal analysis using two different methods: one is the transfer entropy, based on the information theory, and the other one is the Liang--Kleeman information-flow theory. The causal-analysis methods are applied to several scenarios, including a linear and a non-linear problem, a low-dimensional model of the near-wall cycle of turbulence, as well as the interaction between inner and outer turbulent motions in a channel at a friction Reynolds number of $Re_{\tau}=1000$. We find that both methods can well predict the causal links in the linear problem, and the information flow can identify more of the nonlinear problem. Despite richer causalities revealed by the transfer entropy for turbulent-flow problems, both methods can successfully identify the streak-vortex regeneration mechanism that majorly sustains the near-wall turbulence. It is also indicated that both bottom-up and top-down influences of inner and outer motions may coexist in addition to the multiscale self-sustaining mechanism. Lastly, we mention that the computation of the information flow is much more efficient than the transfer entropy. The present study suggests that the information flow can have great potential in causal inference for turbulent-flow problems besides the transfer entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08907v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingxuan Zhang, Zhengping Zhu, Ricardo Vinuesa, Ruifeng Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Gain, Operator Spreading, and Sensitivity to Perturbations as Quantifiers of Chaos in Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09464v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We adopt a continuous weak measurement tomography protocol to explore the signatures of chaos in the quantum system(s). We generate the measurement record as a series of expectation values of an observable evolving under the desired dynamics, which can show a transition from integrability to chaos. We find that the rate of information gain depends on the degree of chaos in the dynamics, the choice of initial observable, and how well the operator is aligned along the density matrix. The amount of operator spreading in the Krylov subspace, as quantified by the fidelity in quantum tomography and various other metrics of information gain, increases with the degree of chaos in the system. We study operator spreading in many-body quantum systems by its potential to generate an informationally complete measurement record. Our quantifiers for operator spreading are more consistent indicators of quantum chaos than Krylov complexity. Our study gives an operational interpretation for operator spreading in terms of fidelity gain in quantum tomography.
  Continuing in our journey of finding the footprints of chaos in the quantum domain, we explore the growth of errors in noisy tomography. For random states, when the measurement record is obtained from a random operator, the subsequent drop in the fidelity obtained is inversely correlated to the degree of chaos in the dynamics. This gives us an operational interpretation of Loschmidt echo for operators by connecting it to the performance of quantum tomography. We find a quantity to capture the scrambling of errors, an out-of-time-ordered correlator (OTOC) between two operators under perturbed and unperturbed dynamics that serves as a signature of chaos. Our results demonstrate a fundamental link between Loschmidt echo and scrambling of errors, as captured by OTOCs, with operational consequences in quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09464v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abinash Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking the distance to criticality in systems with unknown noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14791v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many real-world systems undergo abrupt changes in dynamics as they move across critical points, often with dramatic consequences. Much existing theory on identifying the time-series signatures of nearby critical points -- such as increased variance and slower timescales -- is derived for the case of fixed, low-amplitude noise. However, real-world systems are often corrupted by unknown levels of noise that can distort these temporal signatures. Here we aimed to develop noise-robust indicators of the distance to criticality (DTC) for systems affected by dynamical noise in two cases: when the noise amplitude is fixed, or is unknown and variable across recordings. To approach this problem, we compare the ability of over 7000 candidate time-series features to track the DTC in the vicinity of a supercritical Hopf bifurcation. We recover existing theory in the fixed-noise case, highlighting conventional time-series features that accurately track the DTC. But in the variable-noise setting, where these conventional indicators perform poorly, we highlight new types of high-performing time-series features and show that their success is accomplished by capturing the shape of the invariant density (which depends on both the DTC and the noise amplitude) relative to the spread of fast fluctuations (which depends on the noise amplitude). We introduce a new high-performing time-series statistic, the Rescaled Auto-Density (RAD), that combines these two algorithmic components. We then use RAD to provide new evidence that brain regions higher in the visual hierarchy are positioned closer to criticality, supporting existing hypotheses about patterns of brain organization that are not detected using conventional metrics of the DTC. Our results demonstrate how large-scale algorithmic comparison can yield theoretical insights that can motivate new theory and interpretable algorithms for real-world problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14791v3</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brendan Harris, Leonardo L. Gollo, Ben D. Fulcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Transport Barriers with Swimming Microorganisms in Chaotic Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14284v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the effects of bacterial activity on the mixing and transport properties of a passive scalar in time-periodic flows in experiments and in a simple model. We focus on the interactions between swimming E. coli and the Lagrangian Coherent Structures (LCSs) of the flow, which are computed from experimentally measured velocity fields. Experiments show that such interactions are non-trivial and can lead to transport barriers through which the scalar flux is significantly reduced. Using the Poincar\'e map, we show that these transport barriers coincide with the outermost members of elliptic LCSs known as Lagrangian vortex boundaries. Numerical simulations further show that elliptic LCSs can repel elongated swimmers and lead to swimmer depletion within Lagrangian coherent vortices. A simple mechanism shows that such depletion is due to the preferential alignment of elongated swimmers with the tangents of elliptic LCSs. Our results provide insights into understanding the transport of microorganisms in complex flows with dynamical topological features from a Lagrangian viewpoint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14284v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranjiangshang Ran, Paulo E. Arratia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase reduction explains chimera shape: when multi-body interaction matters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05366v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an extension of the Kuramoto-Sakaguchi model for networks, deriving the second-order phase approximation for a paradigmatic model of oscillatory networks - an ensemble of non-identical Stuart-Landau oscillators coupled pairwisely via an arbitrary adjacency matrix. We explicitly demonstrate how this matrix translates into the coupling structure in the phase equations. To illustrate the power of our approach and the crucial importance of high-order phase reduction, we tackle a trendy setup of non-locally coupled oscillators exhibiting a chimera state. We reveal that our second-order phase model reproduces the dependence of the chimera shape on the coupling strength that is not captured by the typically used first-order Kuramoto-like model. Our derivation contributes to a better understanding of complex networks' dynamics, establishing a relation between the adjacency matrix and multi-body interaction terms in the high-order phase model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05366v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik T. K. Mau, Oleh E. Omel'chenko, Michael Rosenblum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic learning of synchronization in nonlinear coupled systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11691v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Synchronization phenomena are pervasive in nonlinear systems across the natural world and engineering domains. Understanding how to dynamically identify the parameter space (or network structure) of nonlinear systems in a synchronized state is crucial for the study of system synchronization. To address the challenge of achieving stable synchronization in nonlinear coupled systems, we develop a set of mathematical optimization techniques for dynamic learning of synchronization (DLS) inspired by machine learning. This technology captures the state differences between nodes within the system and dynamically adjusts weights, allowing nonlinear coupled systems to maintain a stable state of synchronization after appropriate weight adjustments. We introduce several variants of the DLS technique, including adaptive, supervised, and hybrid methods, effectively promoting synchronization in heterogeneous networks such as small-world, scale-free, and random networks. The efficacy of this technique is validated through its application to simple FitzHugh-Nagumo neural networks and complex Hodgkin-Huxley neuronal networks, examining its impact on both global and local synchronization. The DLS technique proposed in this study offers a new solution to synchronization problems in dynamic network environments, addressing the deficiencies in adaptability and flexibility of existing technologies and providing a fresh perspective for understanding and implementing synchronization phenomena in nonlinear systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11691v3</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong Wu, Qianming Ding, Weifang Huang, Ya Jia, Tianyu Li, Dong Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Parameter and Parameterization Inference with Uncertainty Quantification through Differentiable Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02215v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurate representations of unknown and sub-grid physical processes through parameterizations (or closure) in numerical simulations with quantified uncertainty are critical for resolving the coarse-grained partial differential equations that govern many problems ranging from weather and climate prediction to turbulence simulations. Recent advances have seen machine learning (ML) increasingly applied to model these subgrid processes, resulting in the development of hybrid physics-ML models through the integration with numerical solvers. In this work, we introduce a novel framework for the joint estimation of physical parameters and machine learning parameterizations with uncertainty quantification. Our framework incorporates online training and efficient Bayesian inference within a high-dimensional parameter space, facilitated by differentiable programming. This proof of concept underscores the substantial potential of differentiable programming in synergistically combining machine learning with differential equations, thereby enhancing the capabilities of hybrid physics-ML modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02215v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongquan Qu, Mohamed Aziz Bhouri, Pierre Gentine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A logarithm law for nonautonomous systems fastly converging to equilibrium and mean field coupled systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03241v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that if a nonautonomous system has in a certain sense a fast convergence to equilibrium (faster than any power law behavior) then the time $\tau _{r}(x,y)$ needed for a typical point $x$ to enter for the first time in a ball $B(y,r)$ centered in $y$, with small radius \ $r $ scales as the local dimension of the equilibrium measure \ $\mu $ at $y$, i.e. $$ \underset{r\rightarrow 0}{\lim }\frac{\log \tau _{r}(x,y)}{-\log r}% =d_{\mu }(y).$$
  We then apply the general result to concrete systems of different kind, showing such a logarithm law for asymptotically authonomous solenoidal maps and mean field coupled expanding maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03241v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Galatolo, Davide Faranda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rosenzweig Porter model revisited for the three Wigner Dyson symmetry classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05755v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present numerical results for the Rosenzweig Porter model for all symmetry classes of the Dyson threefold way. We analyzed the fluctuation properties in the eigenvalue spectra, and compared them with existing and new analytical results. Based on these results we propose characteristics of the spectral properties as measures to explore the transition from Poisson to Wigner Dyson WD statistics. Furthermore, we performed thorough studies of the properties of the eigenvectors in terms of the fractal dimensions, the Kullback Leibler KL divergences and the fidelity susceptibility. The ergodic and Anderson transitions take place at the same parameter values and a finite size scaling analysis of the KL divergences at the transitions yields the same critical exponents for all three WD classes, thus indicating superuniversality of these transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05755v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tilen Cadez, Dillip Nandy, Dario Rosa, Alexei Andreanov, Barbara Dietz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
