<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 04:04:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable subdiffusion in the Caputo fractional standard map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10752v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Caputo fractional standard map (C-fSM) is a two-dimensional nonlinear map with memory given in action-angle variables $(I,\theta)$. It is parameterized by $K$ and $\alpha\in(1,2]$ which control the strength of nonlinearity and the fractional order of the Caputo derivative, respectively. In this work we perform a scaling study of the average squared action $\left&lt; I^2 \right&gt;$ along strongly chaotic orbits, i.e. when $K\gg1$. We numerically prove that $\left&lt; I^2 \right&gt;\propto n^\mu$ with $0\le\mu(\alpha)\le1$, for large enough discrete times $n$. That is, we demonstrate that the C-fSM displays subdiffusion for $1&lt;\alpha&lt;2$. Specifically, we show that diffusion is suppressed for $\alpha\to1$ since $\mu(1)=0$, while standard diffusion is recovered for $\alpha=2$ where $\mu(2)=1$. We describe our numerical results with a phenomenological analytical estimation. We also contrast the C-fSM with the Riemann-Liouville fSM and Chirikov's standard map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10752v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. A. Mendez-Bermudez, R. Aguilar-Sanchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization-delocalization transition for light particles in turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10630v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Small bubbles in fluids raise to the surface due to Archimede's force. Remarkably, in turbulent flows this process is severely hindered by the presence of vortex filaments, which act as moving potential wells, dynamically trapping light particles and bubbles. Quantifying the statistical weights and roles of vortex filaments in turbulence is, however, still an outstanding experimental and computational challenge due to their small scale, fast chaotic motion, and transient nature. Here we show that, under the influence of a modulated oscillatory forcing, the collective bubble behaviour switches from a dynamically localized (insulator) to a delocalized (conductor) state. Additionally, we find that by varying the forcing frequency and amplitude, a remarkable resonant phenomenon between light particles and small-scale vortex filamenents emerges, likening particle behavior to a forced damped oscillator. We discuss how these externally actuated bubbles can be used as a new type of microscopic probes to investigate the space-time statistical properties of the smallest turbulence scales, allowing to quantitatively measure physical characteristics of vortex filaments. We develop a superposition model that is in excellent agreement with the simulation data of the particle dynamics which reveals the fraction of localized/delocalized particles as well as characteristics of the potential landscape induced by vortices in turbulence. Our approach paves the way to innovative ways to accurately measure turbulent properties and to the possibility to control light particles and bubble motions in turbulence with potential applications to wave breaking, medical imaging, drug/gene delivery, chemical reactions, wastewater treatment, and industrial mixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10630v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqi Wang, Xander M de Wit, Federico Toschi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinearity-induced Scattering Zero Degeneracies for Spectral Management of Coherent Perfect Absorption in Complex Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a Coherent Perfect Absorption (CPA) protocol for cases where scale invariance is violated due to the presence of nonlinear mechanisms. We demonstrate, using a microwave setting that lacks geometrical symmetries, that the nonlinearity offers new reconfigurable modalities: the destruction or formation of nonlinear CPAs (NL-CPAs), and their frequency positioning and bandwidth management using the incident power as a control knob. The latter occurs via the formation of exceptional point degeneracies of the zeroes of nonlinear scattering processes. Our results establish NL-CPA protocols as a versatile scheme for the creation of reconfigurable hot/cold-spots in complicated enclosures (e.g. buildings or vessels) with applications to next-generation telecommunications, long-range wireless power transfer, and electromagnetic warfare.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10690v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Zhen Wang, John Guillamon, William Tuxbury, Ulrich Kuhl, Tsampikos Kottos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impulsive Lorenz semiflows: Physical measures, statistical stability and entropy stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10909v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study semiflows generated via impulsive perturbations of Lorenz flows. We prove that such semiflows admit a finite number of physical measures. Moreover, if the impulsive perturbation is small enough, we show that the physical measures of the semiflows are close, in the weak* topology, to the unique physical measure of the Lorenz flow. A similar conclusion holds for the entropies associated with the physical measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10909v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e F. Alves, Wael Bahsoun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trajectory Class Fluctuation Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.03612v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Trajectory Class Fluctuation Theorem (TCFT) substantially strengthens the Second Law of Thermodynamics -- that, in point of fact, can be a rather weak bound on resource fluxes. Practically, it improves empirical estimates of free energies, a task known to be statistically challenging, and has diagnosed successful and failed information processing in experimentally-implemented Josephson-junction information engines. The development here justifies that empirical analysis, explicating its mathematical foundations.
  The TCFT reveals the thermodynamics induced by macroscopic system transformations for each measurable subset of system trajectories. In this, it directly combats the statistical challenge of extremely rare events that dominate thermodynamic calculations. And, it reveals new forms of free energy -- forms that can be solved for analytically and practically estimated. Conceptually, the TCFT unifies a host of previously-established fluctuation theorems, interpolating from Crooks' Detailed Fluctuation Theorem (single trajectories) to Jarzynski's Equality (trajectory ensembles).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.03612v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory Wimsatt, Alexander B. Boyd, James P. Crutchfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction renormalization and validity of kinetic equations for turbulent states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00033v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider turbulence of waves that interact weakly via four-wave scattering (sea waves, plasma waves, spin waves, and many others). In the first non-vanishing order in the interaction, the occupation number of waves satisfy a closed kinetic equation which has stationary solutions describing turbulent cascades. We show that a straightforward perturbation theory beyond the kinetic equation gives terms that generally diverge both at small (IR) and large (UV) wavenumbers for a direct cascade. The analysis up to the third order identifies the most UV-divergent terms. In order to gain qualitative analytic control, we sum a subset of the most UV divergent term, to all orders, giving a perturbation theory which is generally free from UV divergence, showing that turbulence becomes independent of the dissipation scale when it goes to zero. On the contrary, the ever-present IR divergence means that the effective coupling is parametrically larger than the naive estimate and grows with the pumping scale (similar to anomalous scaling in fluid turbulence). This suggests that the kinetic equation does not describe wave turbulence even of arbitrarily small level if the cascade is sufficiently long. We show that the character of strong turbulence is determined by the sign of the coupling, that is, whether the effective four-wave interaction is enhanced or suppressed by collective effects. The enhancement possibly signals that strong turbulence is dominated by multi-wave bound states (solitons, shocks, cusps), similar to confinement in quantum chromodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00033v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Rosenhaus, Gregory Falkovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurrence analysis of meteorological data from climate zones in India</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09438v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a study on the spatio-temporal pattern underlying the climate dynamics in various locations spread over India, including the Himalayan region, coastal region, central and northeastern parts of India. We try to capture the variations in the complexity of their dynamics derived from temperature and relative humidity data from 1948-2022. By estimating the recurrence-based measures from the reconstructed phase space dynamics using a sliding window analysis on the data sets, we study the climate variability in different spatial locations. The study brings out the variations in the complexity of the underlying dynamics as well as their heterogeneity across the locations in India. We find almost all locations indicate shifts to more irregular and stochastic dynamics for temperature data around 1972-79 and shifts back to more regular dynamics beyond 2000. These patterns correlate with reported shifts in the climate and Indian Summer Monsoon related to strong and moderate ENSO events and confirm their associated regional variability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09438v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshin John Bejoy, G. Ambika</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
