<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 02:46:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Control of the classical dynamics of a particle in the Morse-soft-Coulomb potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06199v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the one-dimensional Morse-soft-Coulomb (MsC) potential consisting of a Morse repulsive barrier smoothly connected with a soft-core Coulomb potential at the origin. This new potential has a single parameter that controls the softness of the repulsive barrier and the well depth. When this softening-depth parameter tends to zero, the MsC potential approaches the Coulomb potential with an infinite repulsive barrier, a known successful model for the hydrogen atom. We investigate the classical chaotic dynamics of the MsC potential subjected to time-dependent external fields, comparing the results with the Coulomb potential. We show that the MsC potential reproduces the dynamics and the ionization probabilities of the Coulomb potential for sufficiently small values of the softening parameter. We also investigate the role of the softening parameter in the phase-space structures, showing that the increasing of its value leads to the increasing of the chaotic sea and consequently to the rise of the ionization probability. Finally, we address the problem of controlling the dynamics of a particle in the MsC potential from the perspective of optimal control theory, which cannot be easily applied in the case of the Coulomb potential due to the singularity at the origin. We analize a particular optimal solution to the problem of transferring a given amount of energy to the system at minimum cost. Our results show that the MsC potential can be a useful simple model for investigating the hydrogen atom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06199v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Albertin Amici, Jos\'e Andr\'es Guzm\'an Mor\'an, Emanuel Fernandes de Lima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity measure of extreme events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Complexity is an important metric for appropriate characterization of different classes of irregular signals, observed in the laboratory or in nature. The literature is already rich in the description of such measures using a variety of entropy and disequilibrium measures, separately or in combination. Chaotic signal was given prime importance in such studies while no such measure was proposed so far, how complex were the extreme events when compared to non-extreme chaos. We address here this question of complexity in extreme events and investigate if we can distinguish them from non-extreme chaotic signal. The normalized Shannon entropy in combination with disequlibrium is used for our study and it is able to distinguish between extreme chaos and non-extreme chaos and moreover, it depicts the transition points from periodic to extremes via Pomeau-Manneville intermittency and, from small amplitude to large amplitude chaos and its transition to extremes via interior crisis. We report a general trend of complexity against a system parameter that increases during a transition to extreme events, reaches a maximum, and then starts decreasing. We employ three models, a nonautonomous Lienard system, 2-dimensional Ikeda map and a 6-dimensional coupled Hindmarh-Rose system to validate our proposition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06755v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhiman Das, Arnob Ray, Chittaranjan Hens, Dibakar Ghosh, Md. Kamrul Hassan, Artur Dabrowski, Tomasz Kapitaniak, Syamal K. Dana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Events in Noise-Driven Oscillators: Markov Renewal Processes and the "Unruly" Breakdown of Phase-Reduction Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05792v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce an extension to the standard reduction of oscillatory systems to a single phase variable. The standard reduction is often insufficient, particularly when the oscillations have variable amplitude and the magnitude of each oscillatory excursion plays a defining role in the impact of that oscillator on other systems, i.e. on its output. For instance, large excursions in bursting or mixed-mode neural oscillators may constitute events like action potentials, which trigger output to other neurons, while smaller, sub-threshold oscillations generate no output and therefore induce no coupling between neurons. Noise induces diffusion-like dynamics of the oscillator phase on top of its otherwise constant rate-of-change, resulting in the irregular occurrence of these output events. We model the events as corresponding to distinguished crossings of a Poincare section. Using a linearization of the noisy Poincare map and its description under phase-isostable coordinates, we determine the diffusion coefficient for the occurrence and timing of the events using Markov renewal theory. We show that for many oscillator models the corresponding point process can exhibit "unruly" diffusion: with increasing input noise strength the diffusion coefficient vastly increases compared to the standard phase reduction analysis, and, strikingly, it also decreases when the input noise strength is increased further. We provide a thorough analysis in the case of planar oscillators, which exhibit unruliness in a finite region of the natural parameter space. Our results in part explain the surprising synchronization behavior obtained in pulse-coupled, mixed-mode oscillators as they arise, e.g., in neural systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05792v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avinash J. Karamchandani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Widespread neuronal chaos induced by slow oscillating currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the origin and onset of chaos in a mathematical model of an individual neuron, arising from the intricate interaction between 3D fast and 2D slow dynamics governing its intrinsic currents. Central to the chaotic dynamics are multiple homoclinic connections and bifurcations of saddle equilibria and periodic orbits. This neural model reveals a rich array of codimension-2 bifurcations, including Shilnikov-Hopf, Belyakov, Bautin, and Bogdanov-Takens points, which play a pivotal role in organizing the complex bifurcation structure of the parameter space. We explore various routes to chaos occurring at the intersections of quiescent, tonic-spiking, and bursting activity regimes within this space, and provide a thorough bifurcation analysis. Despite a high dimensionality of the model, its fast-slow dynamics allow a reduction to a one-dimensional return map, accurately capturing and explaining the complex dynamics of the neural model. Our approach integrates parameter continuation analysis, newly developed symbolic techniques, and Lyapunov exponents, collectively unveiling the intricate dynamical and bifurcation structures present in the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06304v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Scully, Carter Hinsley, David Bloom, Hil G. E. Meijer, Andrey L. Shilnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Eigenspaces and Pseudospectra of Nonnormal and Defective Matrix-Valued Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider nonnormal matrix-valued dynamical systems with discrete time. For an eigenvalue of matrix, the number of times it appears as a root of the characteristic polynomial is called the algebraic multiplicity. On the other hand, the geometric multiplicity is the dimension of the linear space of eigenvectors associated with that eigenvalue. If the former exceeds the latter, then the eigenvalue is said to be defective and the matrix becomes nondiagonalizable by any similarity transformation. The discrete-time of our dynamics is identified with the geometric multiplicity of the zero eigenvalue $\lambda_0=0$. Its algebraic multiplicity takes about half of the matrix size at $t=1$ and increases stepwise in time, which keeps excess to the geometric multiplicity until their coincidence at the final time. Our model exhibits relaxation processes from far-from-normal to near-normal matrices, in which the defectivity of $\lambda_0$ is recovering in time. We show that such processes are realized as size reductions of pseudospectrum including $\lambda_0$. Here the pseudospectra are the domains on the complex plane which are not necessarily exact spectra but in which the resolvent of matrix takes extremely large values. The defective eigenvalue $\lambda_0$ is sensitive to perturbation and the eigenvalues of the perturbed systems are distributed densely in the pseudospectrum including $\lambda_0$. By constructing generalized eigenspace for $\lambda_0$, we give the Jordan block decomposition for the resolvent of matrix and characterize the pseudospectrum dynamics. Numerical study of the systems perturbed by Gaussian random matrices supports the validity of the present analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06472v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saori Morimoto, Makoto Katori, Tomoyuki Shirai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human game experiment to verify the equilibrium selection controlled by design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06847v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We conducted a laboratory experiment involving human subjects to test the theoretical hypothesis that equilibrium selection can be impacted by manipulating the games dynamics process, by using modern control theory. Our findings indicate that human behavior consists with the predictions derived from evolutionary game theory paradigm. The consistency is supported by three key observations: (1) the long-term distribution of strategies in the strategy space, (2) the cyclic patterns observed within this space, and (3) the speed of convergence to the selected equilibrium. These findings suggest that the design of controllers aimed at equilibrium selection can indeed achieve their theoretical intended purpose. The location of this study in the knowledge tree of evolutionary game science is presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06847v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang Zhijian, Shan Lixia, Yao Qinmei, Wang Yijia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting time-irreversibility in multiscale systems: correlation and response functions in the Lorenz96 model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07005v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Due to their relevance to geophysical systems, the investigation of multiscale systems through the lens of statistical mechanics has gained popularity in recent years. The aim of our work is the characterization of the nonequilibrium properties of the well-known two-scales Lorenz96 model, a dynamical system much used for testing ideas in geophysics, by studying either higher-order correlation functions or response to external perturbations of the energy. These tools in both equilibrium (inviscid) or non-equilibrium (viscous) systems provide clear evidence of their suitability for detecting time-reversal symmetry breaking and for characterizing transport properties also in this class of models. In particular, we characterize how localized energy perturbations are transported between the different scales, highlighting that perturbations of synoptic variables greatly impact advective variables but perturbations of the latter have a practically negligible effect on synoptic scales. Finally, we show that responses of global observables to finite size perturbations strongly depend on the perturbation protocol. This prevents the physical understanding of the system from observations of the relaxation process alone, a fact often overlooked.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07005v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niccol\`o Cocciaglia, Dario Lucente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven ODE modeling of the high-frequency complex dynamics via a low-frequency dynamics model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00668v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In our previous paper [N. Tsutsumi, K. Nakai and Y. Saiki, Chaos 32, 091101 (2022)], we proposed a method for constructing a system of differential equations of chaotic behavior from only observable deterministic time series, which we call the radial function-based regression (RfR) method. However, when the targeted variable's behavior is rather complex, the direct application of the RfR method does not function well. In this study, we propose a novel method of modeling such dynamics, including the high-frequency intermittent behavior of a fluid flow, by considering another variable (base variable) showing relatively simple, less intermittent behavior. We construct an autonomous joint model composed of two parts: the first is an autonomous system of a base variable, and the other concerns the targeted variable being affected by a term involving the base variable to demonstrate complex dynamics. The constructed joint model succeeded in not only inferring a short trajectory but also reconstructing chaotic sets and statistical properties obtained from a long trajectory such as the density distributions of the actual dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00668v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natsuki Tsutsumi, Kengo Nakai, Yoshitaka Saiki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Guided Actor-Critic Reinforcement Learning for Swimming in Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10242v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Turbulent diffusion causes particles placed in proximity to separate. We investigate the required swimming efforts to maintain an active particle close to its passively advected counterpart. We explore optimally balancing these efforts by developing a novel physics-informed reinforcement learning strategy and comparing it with prescribed control and physics-agnostic reinforcement learning strategies. Our scheme, coined the actor-physicist, is an adaptation of the actor-critic algorithm in which the neural network parameterized critic is replaced with an analytically derived physical heuristic function, the physicist. We validate the proposed physics-informed reinforcement learning approach through extensive numerical experiments in both synthetic BK and more realistic Arnold-Beltrami-Childress flow environments, demonstrating its superiority in controlling particle dynamics when compared to standard reinforcement learning methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10242v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Koh, Laurent Pagnier, Michael Chertkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the shifts of orbits and periodic orbits under perturbation and the change of Poincar\'e map Jacobian of periodic orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08079v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Periodic orbits and cycles, respectively, play a significant role in discrete- and continuous-time dynamical systems (i.e. maps and flows). To succinctly describe their shifts when the system is applied perturbation, the notions of functional and functional derivative are borrowed from functional analysis to consider the whole system as an argument of the geometric representation of the periodic orbit or cycle. The shifts of an orbit/trajectory and periodic orbit/cycle are analyzed and concluded as formulae for maps/flows, respectively. The theory shall be beneficial for analyzing sensitivity to perturbations, and optimizing and controlling various systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08079v5</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenyin Wei, Alexander Knieps, Yunfeng Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A concept of antifragility for dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17953v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper defines antifragility for dynamical systems as convexity of a newly introduced "logarithmic rate". It shows how to compute this rate for positive linear systems, and it interprets antifragility in terms of pulsed alternations of extreme strategies in comparison to average uniform strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17953v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo D. Sontag</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
