<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 05:05:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-efficient recurrence quantification analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recurrence quantification analysis (RQA) is a widely used tool for studying complex dynamical systems, but its standard implementation requires computationally expensive calculations of recurrence plots (RPs) and line length histograms. This study introduces strategies to compute RQA measures directly from time series or phase space vectors, avoiding the need to construct RPs. The calculations can be further accelerated and optimised by applying a random sampling procedure, in which only a subset of line structures is evaluated. These modifications result in shorter run times, less memory use and access, and lower overall energy consumption during analysis while maintaining accuracy. This makes them especially appealing for large-scale data analysis and machine learning applications. The ideas are not limited to diagonal line measures, but can likewise be applied to vertical line-based measures and to recurrence network measures. By lowering computational costs, the proposed strategies contribute to energy saving and sustainable data analysis, and broaden the applicability of recurrence-based methods in modern research contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20684v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norbert Marwan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet thermalization by power-law induced permutation symmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21284v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Permutation symmetry plays a central role in the understanding of collective quantum dynamics. On the other hand, interactions are rarely uniform in real systems. By introducing power law couplings that algebraically decay with the distance between the spins $r$ as $1/r^{\alpha}$, we break this symmetry with a non-zero $\alpha$, and probe the emergence of new dynamical behaviors, including thermalization. As we increase $\alpha$, the system interpolates from an infinite range spin system at $\alpha=0$ exhibiting permutation symmetry, to a short range integrable model as $\alpha \rightarrow \infty$ where this permutation symmetry is absent. We focus on the change in the behavior of the system as $\alpha$ is tuned, using dynamical quantities like total angular momentum operator $J^2$ and the von Neumann entropy $S_{N/2}$. Starting from the chaotic limit of the permutation symmetric Hamiltonian at $\alpha=0$, we find that for small $\alpha$, the steady state values of these quantities remain close to the permutation symmetric subspace values corresponding to $\alpha=0$. At intermediate $\alpha$ values, these show signatures of thermalization exhibiting values corresponding to that of random states in full Hilbert space. On the other hand, the large $\alpha$ limit approaches the values corresponding to integrable kicked Ising model. In addition, we also study the dependence of thermalization on the driving period $\tau$, with results indicating the onset of thermalization for smaller values of $\alpha$ when $\tau$ is large, thereby extending the intermediate range of $\alpha$. We further confirm these results using effective dimension and spectral statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21284v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manju C, Uma Divakaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Stochastic Dynamics from Non-Sequential Data (IDyNSD)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17690v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inferring stochastic dynamics from data is central across the sciences, yet in many applications only unordered, non-sequential measurements are available-often restricted to limited regions of state space-so standard time-series methods do not apply. We introduce IDyNSD, a first-principles framework that identifies unknown dynamical parameters from such non-sequential data by minimizing Fokker-Planck residuals. We develop two complementary routes: a local route that handles region-restricted data via locally estimated scores, and a global route that fits dynamics from globally sampled data using a kernel Stein discrepancy without explicit density or score estimation. When the dynamics are affine in the unknown parameters, we prove a necessary-and-sufficient condition for the existence and uniqueness of the inferred parameters and derive a sensitivity analysis that identifies which parameters are tightly constrained by the data and which remain effectively free under over-parameterization. For general non-affine case, both routes define differentiable losses amenable to gradient-based optimization. As demonstrations, we recover (i) the three parameters of a stochastic Lorenz system from non-sequential data (region-restricted data for the local route and full steady-state data for the global route) and (ii) a 3x7interaction matrix of a nonlinear gene-regulatory network derived from a published B-cell differentiation model, using only unordered steady-state samples and applying the global route. Finally, we show that the same Fokker-Planck residual viewpoint supports a "dynamics-to-density" complement that trains a normalized density estimator directly from known dynamics without any observations. Overall, IDyNSD provides two first-principles routes for system-identification from non-sequential data, grounded in the Fokker-Planck equation, that link data, density, and stochastic dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17690v3</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhixin Lu, {\L}ukasz Ku\'smierz, Stefan Mihalas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First observation of turbulence in dense algal suspensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03834v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Active turbulence arises typically in systems ranging from microorganisms and biopolymers to synthetic colloids, where chaotic flows are closely associated with motile topological defects in collectively swarming suspensions. Here, we report the first experimental observation of turbulence in a fundamentally different class of systems: dense monolayers of motile unicellular alga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii that exhibit neither orientational order nor topological defects. Nevertheless, the system displays rich spatiotemporal flow patterns with pronounced small-scale intermittency. We uncover strongly non-Gaussian velocity distribution, a feature distinct from both bacterial and classical fluid turbulence. Furthermore, we observe power-law regimes in the kinetic energy spectra, characterized by unique scaling exponents. Not only do our results provide compelling evidence for active turbulence in systems devoid of nematic or polar structures, but they also challenge current theoretical models. Our work opens new avenues for understanding emergent dynamics in active-matter systems and suggests intriguing biological implications, including enhanced mixing and transport in dense cell suspensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03834v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prince Vibek Baruah, Nadia Bihari Padhan, Biswajit Maji, Rahul Pandit, Prerna Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
