<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 04:01:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-expansion cascade: an origin of randomness of turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14941v3 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Randomness is one of the most important characteristics of turbulence, but its origin remains an open question. By means of a ``thought experiment'' via several clean numerical experiments based on the Navier-Stokes equations for two-dimensional turbulent Kolmogorov flow, we reveal a new phenomenon, which we call the ``noise-expansion cascade'' whereby all micro-level noises/disturbances at different orders of magnitudes in the initial condition of Navier-Stokes equations enlarge consistently, say, one by one like an inverse cascade, to macro-level. More importantly, each noise/disturbance input may greatly change the macro-level characteristics and statistics of the resulting turbulence, clearly indicating that micro-level noise/disturbance might have great influence on macro-level characteristics and statistics of turbulence. Besides, the noise-expansion cascade closely connects randomness of micro-level noise/disturbance and macro-level disorder of turbulence, thus revealing an origin of randomness of turbulence. This also highly suggests that unavoidable thermal fluctuations must be considered when simulating turbulence, even if such fluctuations are several orders of magnitudes smaller than other external environmental disturbances. Hopefully, the ``noise-expansion cascade'' as a fundamental property of the NS equations could greatly deepen our understandings about turbulence, and besides is helpful for attacking the fourth millennium problem posed by Clay Mathematics Institute in 2000.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14941v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/jfm.2025.140</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Fluid Mech. (2025), vol. 1009, A2</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Liao, Shijie Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clean numerical simulation (CNS) of three-dimensional turbulent Kolmogorov flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Turbulence holds immense importance across various scientific and engineering disciplines. The direct numerical simulation (DNS) of turbulence proposed by Orszag in 1970 is a milestone in fluid mechanics, which began an era of numerical experiment for turbulence. Many researchers have reported that turbulence should be chaotic, since spatiotemporal trajectories are very sensitive to small disturbance. In 2006 E.D. Lorenz discovered that numerical noise might have a great influence on statistic characteristics of chaotic systems. The above-mentioned facts logically lead to the conclusion that numerical noises of turbulence (as a chaotic system) might have great influence on turbulent flows. This is indeed true for a two-dimensional (2D) Kolmogorov turbulent flow, as currently revealed by a much more accurate algorithm than DNS, namely the ``clean numerical simulation'' (CNS). Different from DNS, CNS can greatly reduce both of truncation error and round-off error to any required small level so that artificial numerical noise can be rigorously negligible throughout a time interval long enough for calculating statistics. However, In physics, 3D turbulent flow is more important than 2D turbulence, as pointed out by Nobel Prize winner T.D. Lee. So, for the first time, we solve a 3D turbulent Kolmogorov flow by means of CNS in this paper, and compare our CNS result with that given by DNS in details. It is found that the spatial-temporal trajectories of the 3D Kolmogorov turbulent flow given by DNS are badly polluted by artificial numerical noise rather quickly, and the DNS result has huge deviations from the CNS benchmark solution not only in the flow field and the energy cascade but also even in statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11805v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijie Qin, Shijun Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eulerian-Lagrangian scaling of the Lyapunov exponent in homogeneous turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19972v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a heuristic derivation of the maximal Lyapunov exponent $\gamma$ of homogeneous turbulence which yields two new relations, a sweeping relation and the scaling of the uncertainty field's integral length $L_{\Delta}$. These relations and the maximal Lyapunov exponent's scaling that they imply are confirmed by periodic turbulence simulations. As the Reynolds number $Re_\lammbda$ increases, $L_\Delta$ and $\gamma^{-1}$ decrease towards values smaller than the Kolmogorov length and time scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19972v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/zv93-zkkv</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ge, J., Rolland, J., &amp; Vassilicos, J. C. (2025). Eulerian-Lagrangian scaling of the Lyapunov exponent in homogeneous turbulence. Physical Review Fluids, 10(7), L072601</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jin Ge, Joran Rolland, John Christos Vassilicos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PySHRED: A Python package for SHallow REcurrent Decoding for sparse sensing, model reduction and scientific discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: SHallow REcurrent Decoders (SHRED) provide a deep learning strategy for modeling high-dimensional dynamical systems and/or spatiotemporal data from dynamical system snapshot observations. PySHRED is a Python package that implements SHRED and several of its major extensions, including for robust sensing, reduced order modeling and physics discovery. In this paper, we introduce the version 1.0 release of PySHRED, which includes data preprocessors and a number of cutting-edge SHRED methods specifically designed to handle real-world data that may be noisy, multi-scale, parameterized, prohibitively high-dimensional, and strongly nonlinear. The package is easy to install, thoroughly-documented, supplemented with extensive code examples, and modularly-structured to support future additions. The entire codebase is released under the MIT license and is available at https://github.com/pyshred-dev/pyshred.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20954v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Ye, Jan Williams, Mars Gao, Stefano Riva, Matteo Tomasetto, David Zoro, J. Nathan Kutz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital cluster-based network modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01109v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel reduced-order methodology to describe complex multi-frequency fluid dynamics from time-resolved snapshot data. Starting point is the Cluster-based Network Model (CNM) thanks to its fully automatable development and human interpretability. Our key innovation is to model the transitions from cluster to cluster much more accurately by replacing snapshot states with short-term trajectories ("orbits") over multiple clusters, thus avoiding nonphysical intra-cluster diffusion in the dynamic reconstruction. The proposed orbital CNM (oCNM) employs functional clustering to coarse-grain the short-term trajectories. Specifically, different filtering techniques, resulting in different temporal basis expansions, demonstrate the versatility and capability of the oCNM to adapt to diverse flow phenomena. The oCNM is illustrated on the Stuart-Landau oscillator and its post-transient solution with time-varying parameters to test its ability to capture the amplitude selection mechanism and multi-frequency behaviours. Then, the oCNM is applied to the fluidic pinball across varying flow regimes at different Reynolds numbers, including the periodic, quasi-periodic, and chaotic dynamics. This orbital-focused perspective enhances the understanding of complex temporal behaviours by incorporating high-frequency behaviour into the kinematics of short-time trajectories while modelling the dynamics of the lower frequencies. In analogy to Spectral Proper Orthogonal Decomposition, which marked the transition from spatial-only modes to spatio-temporal ones, this work advances from analysing temporal local states to examining piecewise short-term trajectories, or orbits. By merging advanced analytical methods, such as the functional representation of short-time trajectories with CNM, this study paves the way for new approaches to dissect the complex dynamics characterising turbulent systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01109v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Colanera, Nan Deng, Matteo Chiatto, Luigi de Luca, Bernd R. Noack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental study of the distributions of off-diagonal scattering-matrix elements of quantum graphs with symplectic symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09573v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report on experimental studies of the distribution of the off-diagonal elements of the scattering matrix of open microwave networks with symplectic symmetry and a chaotic wave dynamics. These consist of two geometrically identical subgraphs with unitary symmetry described by complex conjugate Hamiltonians, that are coupled by a pair of bonds. The results are compared to random-matrix theory predictions obtained on the basis of the Heidelberg approach for the scattering matrix of open quantum-chaotic systems. We demonstrate that deviations from random-matrix theory predictions observed in the distributions may be attributed to the fact that the subgraphs are not fully connected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09573v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiongning Che, Nils Gluth, Simon K\"ohnes, Thomas Guhr, Barbara Dietz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
