<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.CD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD</link>
    <description>nlin.CD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.CD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nudged Particle Filter with Optimal Resampling Applied to the Duffing Oscillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02837v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficiently solving the continuous-time signal and discrete-time observation filtering problem for chaotic dynamical systems presents unique challenges in that the advected distribution between observations may encounter a separatrix structure that results in the prior distribution being far from the observation or the distribution may become split into multiple disjoint components. In an attempt to sense and overcome these dynamical issues, as well as approximate a non-Gaussian distribution, a nudged particle filtering approach has been introduced. In the nudged particle filter method a control term is added, but has the potential drawback of degenerating the weights of the particles. To counter this issue, we introduce an intermediate resampling approach based on the modified Cram\'er-von Mises distance. The new method is applied to a challenging scenario of the non-chaotic, unforced nonlinear Duffing oscillator, which possesses a separatrix structure. Our results show that it consistently outperforms the standard particle filter with resampling and original nudged particle filter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02837v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryne Beeson, Uwe Hanebeck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing and quantifying weak chaos in fractional dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A particularly intriguing and unique feature of fractional dynamical systems is the cascade of bifurcations type trajectories (CBTT). We examine the CBTTs in a generalized version of the standard map that incorporates the Riemann-Liouville fractional derivative, known as the Riemann-Liouville Fractional Standard Map (RLFSM). Due to the memory effects inherent in fractional maps, traditional techniques for characterizing the dynamics, such as Lyapunov exponents, are not applicable. Instead, we propose a methodology using two quantifiers based only on the system's time series: the Hurst exponent and the recurrence time entropy. This approach allows us to effectively characterize the dynamics of the RLFSM, including regions of CBTT and chaotic behavior. Our analysis demonstrates that regions of CBTT are associated with trajectories that exhibit lower values of these quantifiers compared to strong chaotic regions, indicating weakly chaotic dynamics during the CBTTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03007v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Borin, Jos\'e Danilo Szezech Jr., Matheus Rolim Sales</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plain Convolution Encryption as an Alternative to Overcoming the Limitations of Synchronization-Based Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper revisits the send/retrieve message process using synchronization of the Lorenz system with a monochromatic message. We analyze how the fidelity of the retrieved signal depends on the message frequency and demonstrate message hacking through Fourier spectrum analysis. Various parameters affecting fidelity and noise in the hacked signal are also examined. Additionally, we transmit text messages recovered through synchronization and investigate their vulnerability to hacking. As a countermeasure, we propose a method to send both types of messages using the convolution as the encryption function to hide the message in the chaotic signal. This approach enhances retrieval fidelity and significantly increases resistance to hacking compared to synchronization-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03027v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Flavio Rosales-Infante, M. L. Romero-Amezcua, Iv\'an \'Alvarez-Rios, F. S. Guzm\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leapfrogging of a deterministic model for microeconomic systems in competitive markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02835v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Behrens-Feichtinger model provides a deterministic picture for the co-evolution of sales of two firms, producing the same goods and competing in a common market. The model involves an active investment strategy such that the temporary investment of each of the two firms depends on its relative position in the market. In this work we are interested in a specific regime of evolution referred to as leapfrogging regime, in which each firm has the possibility to dominate the market alternately during some finite period of time. We examine conditions favoring the leapfrogging dynamics of the model by introducing two appropriate variables, namely the sale difference and total sale of the two firms at any time. An analysis of stability of fixed points of the resulting coupled discrete nonlinear equations is carried out, and the bifurcation diagrams of the sale difference and sum with respect to the elasticity coefficient, are generated. A time-series analysis suggests that the leapfrogging regime, characterized by periodic oscillations of the sale difference from positive to negative branches, is stabilized by specific values of characteristic parameters of the model and when in addition the elasticity coefficient, related to the difference in investment strategies of the two firms, is reasonably high. A positive sign of cumulated sales at any time is required to ensure the availability of goods during the leapfrogging dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02835v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.GN</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alain M. Dikande, H. Ntahombagana Matabaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic instability of wormlike micelle solution flow in serpentine channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02951v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wormlike micelle (WLM) solutions are abundant in energy, environmental, and industrial applications, which often rely on their flow through tortuous channels. How does the interplay between fluid rheology and channel geometry influence the flow behavior? Here, we address this question by experimentally visualizing and quantifying the flow of a semi-dilute WLM solution in millifluidic serpentine channels. At low flow rates, the base flow is steady and laminar, with strong asymmetry and wall slip. When the flow rate exceeds a critical threshold, the flow exhibits an elastic instability, producing spatially-heterogeneous, unsteady three-dimensional (3D) flow characterized by two notable features: (i) the formation and persistence of stagnant but strongly-fluctuating and multistable "dead zones" in channel bends, and (ii) intermittent 3D "twists" throughout the bulk flow. The geometry of these dead zones and twisting events can be rationalized by considering the minimization of local streamline curvature to reduce flow-generated elastic stresses. Altogether, our results shed new light into how the interplay between solution rheology and tortuous boundary geometry influences WLM flow behavior, with implications for predicting and controlling WLM flows in a broad range of complex environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02951v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Y. Chen, Sujit S. Datta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic reduced-order Koopman model for turbulent flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22649v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A stochastic data-driven reduced-order model applicable to a wide range of turbulent natural and engineering flows is presented. Combining ideas from Koopman theory and spectral model order reduction, the stochastic low-dimensional inflated convolutional Koopman model (SLICK) accurately forecasts short-time transient dynamics while preserving long-term statistical properties. A discrete Koopman operator is used to evolve convolutional coordinates that govern the temporal dynamics of spectral orthogonal modes, which in turn represent the energetically most salient large-scale coherent flow structures. Turbulence closure is achieved in two steps: first, by inflating the convolutional coordinates to incorporate nonlinear interactions between different scales, and second, by modeling the residual error as a stochastic source. An empirical dewhitening filter informed by the data is used to maintain the second-order flow statistics within the long-time limit. The model uncertainty is quantified through either Monte Carlo simulation or by directly propagating the model covariance matrix. The model is demonstrated on the Ginzburg-Landau equations, large-eddy simulation (LES) data of a turbulent jet, and particle image velocimetry (PIV) data of the flow over an open cavity. In all cases, the model is predictive over time horizons indicated by a detailed error analysis and integrates stably over arbitrary time horizons, generating realistic surrogate data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22649v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyi Chu, Oliver T. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
