<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.data-an updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an</link>
    <description>physics.data-an updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 04:00:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Estimation of waveform deformation with the matched filter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In many particle physics experiments the data processing is based on the analysis of the digitized waveforms provided by the detector. While the waveform amplitude is usually correlated to the event energy, the shape may carry useful information for event discrimination. Thanks to the high signal to noise ratio they provide, matched filters are often applied. Their original design is however intended for the estimation of the waveform amplitude only.
  In this work we introduce an analytical extension of the original matched filter for the estimation of a possible shape deformation with respect to a reference template. The new filter is validated on simulations and, with respect to shape parameters calculated on unfiltered waveforms or derived from the original matched filter, it improves the discrimination capability by at least a factor 2 both at low and high signal to noise ratios, making it applicable to the data of several experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02300v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Cappelli, Giorgio del Castello, Marco Vignati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping cascaded random matrix models: correlations in permutations of matrix products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02541v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Random matrix theory is a useful tool in the study of the physics of multiple scattering systems, often striking a balance between computation speed and physical rigour. Propagation of waves through thick disordered media, as arises in for example optical scattering or electron transport, typically necessitates cascading of multiple random matrices drawn from an underlying ensemble for thin media, greatly increasing computational burden. Here we propose a dual pool based bootstrapping approach to speed up statistical studies of scattering in thick random media. We examine how potential matrix reuse in a pool based approach can impact statistical estimates of population averages. Specifically, we discuss how both bias and additional variance in the sample mean estimator are introduced through bootstrapping. In the diffusive scattering regime, the extra estimator variance is shown to originate from samples in which cascaded transfer matrices are permuted matrix products. Through analysis of the combinatorics and cycle structure of permutations we quantify the resulting correlations. Proofs of several analytic formulae enumerating the frequency with which correlations of different strengths occur are derived. Extension to the ballistic regime is briefly considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02541v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niall Byrnes, Gary R. W. Greaves, Matthew R. Foreman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bayesian mixture model approach to quantifying the empirical nuclear saturation point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02748v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The equation of state (EOS) in the limit of infinite symmetric nuclear matter exhibits an equilibrium density, $n_0 \approx 0.16 \, \mathrm{fm}^{-3}$, at which the pressure vanishes and the energy per particle attains its minimum, $E_0 \approx -16 \, \mathrm{MeV}$. Although not directly measurable, the nuclear saturation point $(n_0,E_0)$ can be extrapolated by density functional theory (DFT), providing tight constraints for microscopic interactions derived from chiral effective field theory (EFT). However, when considering several DFT predictions for $(n_0,E_0)$ together, a discrepancy between model classes emerges at high confidence levels that each model prediction's uncertainty cannot explain. How can we leverage these DFT constraints to rigorously benchmark nuclear saturation properties of chiral interactions? To address this question, we present a Bayesian mixture model that combines multiple DFT predictions for $(n_0,E_0)$ using an efficient conjugate prior approach. The inferred posterior distribution for the saturation point's mean and covariance matrix follows a Normal-inverse-Wishart class, resulting in posterior predictives in the form of correlated, bivariate $t$-distributions. The DFT uncertainty reports are then used to mix these posteriors using an ordinary Monte Carlo approach. At the 95% credibility level, we estimate $n_0 \approx 0.157 \pm 0.010 \, \mathrm{fm}^{-3}$ and $E_0 \approx -15.97 \pm 0.40 \, \mathrm{MeV}$ for the marginal (univariate) $t$-distributions. Combined with chiral EFT calculations of the pure neutron matter EOS, we obtain bivariate normal distributions for the nuclear symmetry energy and its slope parameter evaluated at $n_0$: $S_v \approx 32.0 \pm 1.1 \, \mathrm{MeV}$ and $L\approx 52.6\pm 8.1 \, \mathrm{MeV}$ (95%), respectively. Our Bayesian framework is publicly available, so practitioners can readily use and extend our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02748v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Drischler, P. G. Giuliani, S. Bezoui, J. Piekarewicz, F. Viens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Koopman neural operator as a mesh-free solver of non-linear partial differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.10022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.10022v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The lacking of analytic solutions of diverse partial differential equations (PDEs) gives birth to a series of computational techniques for numerical solutions. Although numerous latest advances are accomplished in developing neural operators, a kind of neural-network-based PDE solver, these solvers become less accurate and explainable while learning long-term behaviors of non-linear PDE families. In this paper, we propose the Koopman neural operator (KNO), a new neural operator, to overcome these challenges. With the same objective of learning an infinite-dimensional mapping between Banach spaces that serves as the solution operator of the target PDE family, our approach differs from existing models by formulating a non-linear dynamic system of equation solution. By approximating the Koopman operator, an infinite-dimensional operator governing all possible observations of the dynamic system, to act on the flow mapping of the dynamic system, we can equivalently learn the solution of a non-linear PDE family by solving simple linear prediction problems. We validate the KNO in mesh-independent, long-term, and5zero-shot predictions on five representative PDEs (e.g., the Navier-Stokes equation and the Rayleigh-B{\'e}nard convection) and three real dynamic systems (e.g., global water vapor patterns and western boundary currents). In these experiments, the KNO exhibits notable advantages compared with previous state-of-the-art models, suggesting the potential of the KNO in supporting diverse science and engineering applications (e.g., PDE solving, turbulence modelling, and precipitation forecasting).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.10022v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Xiong, Xiaomeng Huang, Ziyang Zhang, Ruixuan Deng, Pei Sun, Yang Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
