<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.data-an updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an</link>
    <description>physics.data-an updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 19:07:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Correlations versus noise in the NFT market</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15495v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The non-fungible token (NFT) market emerges as a recent trading innovation leveraging blockchain technology, mirroring the dynamics of the cryptocurrency market. To deepen the understanding of the dynamics of this market, in the current study, based on the capitalization changes and transaction volumes across a large number of token collections on the Ethereum platform, the degree of correlation in this market is examined by using the multivariate formalism of detrended correlation coefficient and correlation matrix. It appears that correlation strength is lower here than that observed in previously studied markets. Consequently, the eigenvalue spectra of the correlation matrix more closely follow the Marchenko-Pastur distribution, still, some departures indicating the existence of correlations remain. The comparison of results obtained from the correlation matrix built from the Pearson coefficients and, independently, from the detrended cross-correlation coefficients suggests that the global correlations in the NFT market arise from higher frequency fluctuations. Corresponding minimal spanning trees (MSTs) for capitalization variability exhibit a scale-free character while, for the number of transactions, they are somewhat more decentralized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15495v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcin W\k{a}torek, Pawe{\l} Szyd{\l}o, Jaros{\l}aw Kwapie\'n, Stanis{\l}aw Dro\.zd\.z</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of complexity in the built environment on vehicular routing behavior: Insights from an empirical study of taxi mobility in Beijing, China</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15589v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The modeling of disaggregated vehicular mobility and its associations with the ambient urban built environment is essential for developing operative transport intervention and urban optimization plans. However, established vehicular route choice models failed to fully consider the bounded behavioral rationality and the complex characteristics of the urban built environment affecting drivers' route choice preference. Therefore, the spatio-temporal characteristics of vehicular mobility patterns were not fully explained, which limited the granular implementation of relevant transport interventions. To address this limitation, we proposed a vehicular route choice model that mimics the anchoring effect and the exposure preference while driving. The proposed model enables us to quantitatively examine the impact of the built environment on vehicular routing behavior, which has been largely neglected in previous studies. Results show that the proposed model performs 12% better than the conventional vehicular route choice model based on the shortest path principle. Our empirical analysis of taxi drivers' routing behavior patterns in Beijing, China uncovers that drivers are inclined to choose routes with shorter time duration and with less loss at traversal intersections. Counterintuitively, we also found that drivers heavily rely on circuitous ring roads and expressways to deliver passengers, which are unexpectedly longer than the shortest paths. Moreover, characteristics of the urban built environment including road eccentricity, centrality, average road length, land use diversity, sky visibility, and building coverage can affect drivers' route choice behaviors, accounting for about 5% of the increase in the proposed model's performance. We also refine the above explorations according to the modeling results of trips that differ in departure time, travel distance, and occupation status.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15589v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaogui Kang, Zheren Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Message-Passing on Hypergraphs: Detectability, Phase Transitions and Higher-Order Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00708v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hypergraphs are widely adopted tools to examine systems with higher-order interactions. Despite recent advancements in methods for community detection in these systems, we still lack a theoretical analysis of their detectability limits. Here, we derive closed-form bounds for community detection in hypergraphs. Using a Message-Passing formulation, we demonstrate that detectability depends on hypergraphs' structural properties, such as the distribution of hyperedge sizes or their assortativity. Our formulation enables a characterization of the entropy of a hypergraph in relation to that of its clique expansion, showing that community detection is enhanced when hyperedges highly overlap on pairs of nodes. We develop an efficient Message-Passing algorithm to learn communities and model parameters on large systems. Additionally, we devise an exact sampling routine to generate synthetic data from our probabilistic model. With these methods, we numerically investigate the boundaries of community detection in synthetic datasets, and extract communities from real systems. Our results extend the understanding of the limits of community detection in hypergraphs and introduce flexible mathematical tools to study systems with higher-order interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00708v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1742-5468/ad343b</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\`o Ruggeri, Alessandro Lonardi, Caterina De Bacco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Machine Learning to Separate Cherenkov and Scintillation Light in Hybrid Neutrino Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05184v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This research investigates the separation of Cherenkov and Scintillation light signals within a simulated Water-based Liquid Scintillator (WbLS) detector, utilizing the XGBoost machine learning algorithm. The simulation data were gathered using the Rat-Pac software, which was built on the Geant4 architecture. The use of the WbLS medium has the capability to generate both Scintillation and Cherenkov light inside a single detector. To show the separation power of these two physics events, we will use the supervised learning approach. The assessment utilized a confusion matrix, classification report, and ROC curve, with the ROC curve indicating a performance result of $0.96 \pm 1.2\times 10^{-4}$. The research also aimed to identify essential parameters for effectively distinguishing these physics events through machine learning. For this, the study also introduced the SHAP methodology, utilizing game theory to assess feature contributions. The findings demonstrated that the number of hits has a significant effect on the trained model, while the mean hit time has a somewhat smaller impact. This research advances the utilization of AI and simulation data for accurate Cherenkov and Scintillation light separation in neutrino detectors</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05184v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1748-0221/19/04/P04027</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JINST 19 P04027 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ayse Bat</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
