<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.data-an updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an</link>
    <description>physics.data-an updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 05:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Actuation manifold from snapshot data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03653v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a data-driven methodology to learn a low-dimensional manifold of controlled flows. The starting point is resolving snapshot flow data for a representative ensemble of actuations. Key enablers for the actuation manifold are isometric mapping as encoder and a combination of a neural network and a k-nearest-neighbour interpolation as decoder. This methodology is tested for the fluidic pinball, a cluster of three parallel cylinders perpendicular to the oncoming uniform flow. The centres of these cylinders are the vertices of an equilateral triangle pointing upstream. The flow is manipulated by constant rotation of the cylinders, i.e. described by three actuation parameters. The Reynolds number based on a cylinder diameter is chosen to be 30. The unforced flow yields statistically symmetric periodic shedding represented by a one-dimensional limit cycle. The proposed methodology yields a five-dimensional manifold describing a wide range of dynamics with small representation error. Interestingly, the manifold coordinates automatically unveil physically meaningful parameters. Two of them describe the downstream periodic vortex shedding. The other three describe the near-field actuation, i.e. the strength of boat-tailing, the Magnus effect and forward stagnation point. The manifold is shown to be a key enabler for control-oriented flow estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03653v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/jfm.2024.593</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Fluid Mech. 996 (2024) A26</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Marra, Guy Y. Cornejo Maceda, Andrea Meil\'an-Vila, Vanesa Guerrero, Salma Rashwan, Bernd R. Noack, Stefano Discetti, Andrea Ianiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into Dark Matter Direct Detection Experiments: Decision Trees versus Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10372v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The detection of Dark Matter (DM) remains a significant challenge in particle physics. This study exploits advanced machine learning models to improve detection capabilities of liquid xenon time projection chamber experiments, utilizing state-of-the-art transformers alongside traditional methods like Multilayer Perceptrons and Convolutional Neural Networks. We evaluate various data representations and find that simplified feature representations, particularly corrected S1 and S2 signals as well as a few shape-related features including the time difference between signals, retain critical information for classification. Our results show that while transformers offer promising performance, simpler models like XGBoost can achieve comparable results with optimal data representations. We also derive exclusion limits in the cross-section versus DM mass parameter space, showing minimal differences between XGBoost and the best performing deep learning models. The comparative analysis of different machine learning approaches provides a valuable reference for future experiments by guiding the choice of models and data representations to maximize detection capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10372v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/057</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 01 (2025) 057</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel E. Lopez-Fogliani, Andres D. Perez, Roberto Ruiz de Austri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian technique to combine independently-trained Machine-Learning models applied to direct dark matter detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21008v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We carry out a Bayesian analysis of dark matter (DM) direct detection data to determine particle model parameters using the Truncated Marginal Neural Ratio Estimation (TMNRE) machine learning technique. TMNRE avoids an explicit calculation of the likelihood, which instead is estimated from simulated data, unlike in traditional Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithms. This considerably speeds up, by several orders of magnitude, the computation of the posterior distributions, which allows to perform the Bayesian analysis of an otherwise computationally prohibitive number of benchmark points. In this article we demonstrate that, in the TMNRE framework, it is possible to include, combine, and remove different datasets in a modular fashion, which is fast and simple as there is no need to re-train the machine learning algorithm or to define a combined likelihood. In order to assess the performance of this method, we consider the case of WIMP DM with spin-dependent and independent interactions with protons and neutrons in a xenon experiment. After validating our results with MCMC, we employ the TMNRE procedure to determine the regions where the DM parameters can be reconstructed. Finally, we present CADDENA, a Python package that implements the modular Bayesian analysis of direct detection experiments described in this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21008v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/038</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 01 (2025) 038</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Cerdeno, Martin de los Rios, Andres D. Perez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markov-type state models to describe non-Markovian dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08660v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When clustering molecular dynamics (MD) trajectories into a few metastable conformational states, the Markov state models (MSMs) assumption of timescale separation between fast intrastate fluctuations and rarely occurring interstate transitions is often not valid. Hence, the naive estimation of the macrostate transition matrix via simply counting transitions between the states leads to significantly too short implied timescales and thus to too fast population decays. In this work, we discuss advanced approaches to estimate the transition matrix. Assuming that Markovianity is at least given at the microstate level, we consider the Laplace-transform based method by Hummer and Szabo, as well as a direct microstate-to-macrostate projection, which by design yields correct macrostate population dynamics. Alternatively, we study the recently proposed quasi-MSM ansatz of Huang and coworkers to solve a generalized master equations, as well as a hybrid method that employs MD at short times and MSM at long times. Adopting a one-dimensional toy model and an all-atom folding trajectory of HP35, we discuss the virtues and shortcomings of the various approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08660v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sofia Sartore, Franziska Teichmann, Gerhard Stock</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
