<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.data-an updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an</link>
    <description>physics.data-an updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 04:00:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate Estimation of Mutual Information in High Dimensional Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mutual information (MI) is a measure of statistical dependencies between two variables, widely used in data analysis. Thus, accurate methods for estimating MI from empirical data are crucial. Such estimation is a hard problem, and there are provably no estimators that are universally good for finite datasets. Common estimators struggle with high-dimensional data, which is a staple of modern experiments. Recently, promising machine learning-based MI estimation methods have emerged. Yet it remains unclear if and when they produce accurate results, depending on dataset sizes, statistical structure of the data, and hyperparameters of the estimators, such as the embedding dimensionality or the duration of training. There are also no accepted tests to signal when the estimators are inaccurate. Here, we systematically explore these gaps. We propose and validate a protocol for MI estimation that includes explicit checks ensuring reliability and statistical consistency. Contrary to accepted wisdom, we demonstrate that reliable MI estimation is achievable even with severely undersampled, high-dimensional datasets, provided these data admit accurate low-dimensional representations. These findings broaden the potential use of machine learning-based MI estimation methods in real-world data analysis and provide new insights into when and why modern high-dimensional, self-supervised algorithms perform effectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00330v1</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eslam Abdelaleem, K. Michael Martini, Ilya Nemenman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequentist Uncertainties on Neural Density Ratios with wifi Ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00113v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce wifi ensembles as a novel framework to obtain asymptotic frequentist uncertainties on density ratios, with a particular focus on neural ratio estimation in the context of high-energy physics. When the density ratio of interest is a likelihood ratio conditioned on parameters, wifi ensembles can be used to perform simulation-based inference on those parameters. After training the basis functions f_i(x), uncertainties on the weights w_i can be straightforwardly propagated to the estimated parameters without requiring extraneous bootstraps. To demonstrate this approach, we present an application in quantum chromodynamics at the Large Hadron Collider, using wifi ensembles to estimate the likelihood ratio between generated quark and gluon jets. We use this learned likelihood ratio to estimate the quark fraction in a synthetic mixed quark/gluon sample, showing that the resultant uncertainties empirically satisfy the desired coverage properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00113v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sean Benevedes, Jesse Thaler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unique Reconstruction From Mean-Field Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00301v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We address the inverse problem of reconstructing both the structure and dynamics of a network from mean-field measurements, which are linear combinations of node states. This setting arises in applications where only a few aggregated observations are available, making network inference challenging. We focus on the case when the number of mean-field measurements is smaller than the number of nodes. To tackle this ill-posed recovery problem, we propose a framework that combines localized initial perturbations with sparse optimization techniques. We derive sufficient conditions that guarantee the unique reconstruction of the network's adjacency matrix from mean-field data and enable recovery of node states and local governing dynamics. Numerical experiments demonstrate the robustness of our approach across a range of sparsity and connectivity regimes. These results provide theoretical and computational foundations for inferring high-dimensional networked systems from low-dimensional observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00301v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Narcicegi Kiran, Tiago Pereira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Time Ptychography for one-dimensional phase retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00492v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Phase retrieval is at the heart of adaptive optics and modern high-resolution imaging. Without phase information, optical systems are limited to intensity-only measurements, hindering full reconstruction of object structures and wavefront dynamics essential for advanced applications. Here, we address a one-dimensional phase problem linking energy and time, which arises in X-ray scattering from ultrasharp nuclear resonances. We leverage the M\"ossbauer effect, where nuclei scatter radiation without energy loss to the lattice, and are sensitive to their magneto-chemical environments. Rather than using traditional spectroscopy with radioactive gamma-ray sources, we measure nuclear forward scattering of synchrotron X-ray pulses in the time domain, providing superior sensitivity and faster data acquisition. Extracting spectral information from a single measurement is challenging due to the missing phase information, typically requiring extensive modeling. Instead, we use multiple energetically overlapping measurements to retrieve both the transmission spectrum and the phase of the scattering response, similar to ptychographic phase retrieval in imaging. Our robust approach can overcome the bandwidth limitations of gamma-ray sources, opening new research directions with modern X-ray sources and M\"ossbauer isotopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00492v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankita Negi, Leon Merten Lohse, Sven Velten, Ilya Sergeev, Olaf Leupold, Sakshath Sadashivaiah, Dimitrios Bessas, Aleksandr Chumakhov, Christina Brandt, Lars Bocklage, Guido Meier, Ralf R\"ohlsberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbolic Higher-Order Analysis of Multivariate Time Series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00508v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Identifying patterns of relations among the units of a complex system from measurements of their activities in time is a fundamental problem with many practical applications. Here, we introduce a method that detects dependencies of any order in multivariate time series data. The method first transforms a multivariate time series into a symbolic sequence, and then extract statistically significant strings of symbols through a Bayesian approach. Such motifs are finally modelled as the hyperedges of a hypergraph, allowing us to use network theory to study higher-order interactions in the original data. When applied to neural and social systems, our method reveals meaningful higher-order dependencies, highlighting their importance in both brain function and social behaviour.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00508v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Civilini, Fabrizio de Vico Fallani, Vito Latora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Open and Collaborative Database of Properties of Materials for High-Temperature Superconducting-Based Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01617v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The successful integration of high-temperature superconductors (HTS) into modern technologies requires consistent, accessible, and comprehensive material data, a need that is currently unmet due to the fragmented and incomplete nature of existing resources. This paper introduces a new collaborative, open-access database specifically designed to address this gap by providing standardized data on HTS materials and crucial auxiliary components for HTS applications. The database encompasses extensive data on structural, cryogenic, electrical, magnetic, and superconducting materials, supporting diverse requirements from HTS modelling to magnet design. Developed through collaborative efforts and organized using an ontology-driven data model, this platform is dynamically adaptable, ensuring that it can grow as new materials and data emerge. Key features include user-driven contributions, peer-reviewed data validation, and advanced filtering capabilities for efficient data retrieval. This innovative database, to the knowledge of the authors, being the largest publicly available for material properties of HTS technologies is positioned as a valuable tool for the HTS community, promoting more efficient research and development processes, accelerating the practical application of HTS, and fostering a collaborative approach to knowledge sharing within the field. The database is available at https://sc.hi-scale.grisenergia.pt/app.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01617v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TASC.2025.3570458</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Applied Superconductivity</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Cayado, Jo\~ao Rosas, Jo\~ao Murta-Pina, Harold S. Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo Simulation and Dosimetric Analysis of Gold Nanoparticles (AuNPs) in Breast Tissue</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precise radiation delivery is critical for effective radiotherapy, and gold nanoparticles (AuNPs) have emerged as promising tools to enhance local dose deposition while sparing the surrounding healthy tissue. In this study, the PENELOPE Monte Carlo code was used to investigate the dosimetry of AuNPs under different conditions and models. The Dose Enhancement Ratio (DER) was studied in water and breast tissue with spherical shapes and in agreement with previously published results. To further analyse the physical interactions of the particles around the AuNP, a Phase Space File (PSF) in a volume around the AuNPs was created. This showed that larger AuNPs lead to increased doses, as expected, yielding DER values exceeding 100 times. Finally, results reveal that in the volume surrounding the AuNP, 80% of emitted electrons originate from photoelectric absorption, leading to Auger electron emission cascades which were analysed in detail. It was also possible to establish a direct relation between number of secondaries and the particle volumes. The Local Effect Model (LEM) was used to determine sur- vival curves in AuNPs of different sizes at different gold concentrations. The last part of this work consisted in analysing a distribution of AuNPs within a flattened cell typical of clonogenic assays where a log-normal distribution of dose was observed. This led to the development of a new, mechanistic, Local Effect Model which, if further validated, can have further applications in-vitro and in-silico.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01878v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Teles, Catarina Dias, Jo\~ao H. Belo, C\'elia Sousa, Paula Boaventura, Isabel Bravo, Jo\~ao Santos, Marissa Rylander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Learning in Structural Dynamics: A Comprehensive Review and Emerging Trends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22223v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bayesian learning has emerged as a compelling and vital research direction in the field of structural dynamics, offering a probabilistic lens to understand and refine the analysis of complex dynamical systems. This review meticulously traces the three-decade evolution of Bayesian learning in structural dynamics, illuminating core principles, groundbreaking methodologies, and diverse applications that have significantly influenced the field. The narrative commences by delving into the basics of Bayesian theory, clarifying essential concepts, and introducing primary methods for deriving posterior distributions, with an in-depth exploration of three types: Laplace approximation, stochastic sampling, and variational inference. Subsequently, the text explores the implementation of two types of Bayesian learning in structural dynamics: physical model learning and data-centric statistical model learning. Physical model learning emphasizes inferring physical model parameters within a Bayesian framework for system identification and prediction, while statistical model learning integrates Bayesian learning methodologies into data-centric statistical modeling within probabilistic machine learning. Both types resonate across various applications, such as modal analysis, model updating, damage detection, and reliability updating, highlighting their pivotal role in enhancing comprehension of dynamical systems and decision-making. The paper also navigates obstacles by proposing ways to enhance existing Bayesian inference strategies. Distinguished from previous research, this study offers a thorough examination of both traditional and cutting-edge Bayesian methods. It not only underscores the transformative influence of Bayesian approaches but also serves as a beacon, guiding researchers in the judicious selection and refinement of suitable methods for various challenges in structural dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22223v2</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang-Ji Yan, Lin-Feng Mei, Yuan-Wei Yin, Jiang Mo, Costas Papadimitriou, Ka-Veng Yuen, Michael Beer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Training of Deep Neural Operator Networks via Randomized Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13280v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural operators (NOs) employ deep neural networks to learn mappings between infinite-dimensional function spaces. Deep operator network (DeepONet), a popular NO architecture, has demonstrated success in the real-time prediction of complex dynamics across various scientific and engineering applications. In this work, we introduce a random sampling technique to be adopted during the training of DeepONet, aimed at improving the generalization ability of the model, while significantly reducing the computational time. The proposed approach targets the trunk network of the DeepONet model that outputs the basis functions corresponding to the spatiotemporal locations of the bounded domain on which the physical system is defined. While constructing the loss function, DeepONet training traditionally considers a uniform grid of spatiotemporal points at which all the output functions are evaluated for each iteration. This approach leads to a larger batch size, resulting in poor generalization and increased memory demands, due to the limitations of the stochastic gradient descent (SGD) optimizer. The proposed random sampling over the inputs of the trunk net mitigates these challenges, improving generalization and reducing memory requirements during training, resulting in significant computational gains. We validate our hypothesis through three benchmark examples, demonstrating substantial reductions in training time while achieving comparable or lower overall test errors relative to the traditional training approach. Our results indicate that incorporating randomization in the trunk network inputs during training enhances the efficiency and robustness of DeepONet, offering a promising avenue for improving the framework's performance in modeling complex physical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13280v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharmila Karumuri, Lori Graham-Brady, Somdatta Goswami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homophily Within and Across Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07901v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Homophily-the tendency to connect with similar others-plays a central role in shaping network structure and function. It is often treated as a uniform, global parameter, independent from other structural features. Here, we propose a maximum-entropy framework that decomposes homophily into contributions within and across groups, with the stochastic block model emerging as a special case. Our exponential-family formulation, parameterized by group size, fits real-world social networks well and allows homophily to be captured with a single parameter per group size. This decomposition shows that aggregate metrics often obscure group-level variation. We also find that the scale-dependent distribution of homophily has a significant impact on network percolation, influencing epidemic thresholds, the spread of ideas or behaviors, and the effectiveness of intervention strategies. Ignoring this heterogeneity can lead to distorted conclusions about connectivity and dynamics in complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07901v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abbas K. Rizi, Riccardo Michielan, Clara Stegehuis, Mikko Kivel\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning for Single-Ended Event Reconstruction in PROSPECT Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06727v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Precision Reactor Oscillation and Spectrum Experiment, PROSPECT, was a segmented antineutrino detector that successfully operated at the High Flux Isotope Reactor in Oak Ridge, TN, during its 2018 run. Despite challenges with photomultiplier tube base failures affecting some segments, innovative machine learning approaches were employed to perform position and energy reconstruction, and particle classification. This work highlights the effectiveness of convolutional neural networks and graph convolutional networks in enhancing data analysis. By leveraging these techniques, a 3.3% increase in effective statistics was achieved compared to traditional methods, showcasing their potential to improve analysis performance. Furthermore, these machine learning methodologies offer promising applications for other segmented particle detectors, underscoring their versatility and impact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06727v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Andriamirado, A. B. Balantekin, C. D. Bass, O. Benevides Rodrigues, E. P. Bernard, N. S. Bowden, C. D. Bryan, R. Carr, T. Classen, A. J. Conant, G. Deichert, A. Delgado, M. J. Dolinski, A. Erickson, M. Fuller, A. Galindo-Uribarri, S. Gokhale, C. Grant, S. Hans, A. B. Hansell, T. E. Haugen, K. M. Heeger, B. Heffron, D. E. Jaffe, S. Jayakumar, J. Koblanski, P. Kunkle, C. E. Lane, B. R. Littlejohn, A. Lozano Sanchez, X. Lu, F. Machado, J. Maricic, M. P. Mendenhall, A. M. Meyer, R. Milincic, P. E. Mueller, H. P. Mumm, R. Neilson, C. Roca, R. Rosero, D. Venegas-Vargas, J. Wilhelmi, M. Yeh, C. Zhang, X. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
