<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.data-an updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an</link>
    <description>physics.data-an updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:01:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing next token prediction based pre-training for jet foundation models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04149v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Next token prediction is an attractive pre-training task for jet foundation models, in that it is simulation free and enables excellent generative capabilities that can transfer across datasets. Here we study multiple improvements to next token prediction, building on the initial work of OmniJet-$\alpha$. Instead of tokenizing particles and subsequently only using the token-ID as the model input for both the generative and the classification task, we adopt a hybrid setup, which allows us to use continuous feature vectors as model input while only using token-IDs in the next token prediction target. Secondly, we explore a combined pre-training strategy that combines masked particle modeling and generative learning objectives. Taken together, these changes greatly improve the performance in downstream classification tasks without any loss in generative performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04149v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joschka Birk, Anna Hallin, Gregor Kasieczka, Nikol Madzharova, Ian Pang, David Shih</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resummed Distribution Functions: Making Perturbation Theory Positive and Normalized</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fixed-order perturbative calculations for differential cross sections can suffer from non-physical artifacts: they can be non-positive, non-normalizable, and non-finite, none of which occur in experimental measurements. We propose a framework, the Resummed Distribution Function (RDF), that, given a perturbative calculation for an observable to some finite order in $\alpha_s$, will ``resum'' the expression in a way that is guaranteed to match the original expression order-by-order and be positive, normalized, and finite. Moreover, our ansatz parameterizes all possible finite, positive, and normalized completions consistent with the original fixed-order expression, which can include N$^n$LL resummed expressions. The RDF also enables a more direct notion of perturbative uncertainties, as we can directly vary higher-order parameters and treat them as nuisance parameters. We demonstrate the power of the RDF ansatz by matching to thrust to $\mathcal{O}(\alpha_s^3)$ and extracting $\alpha_s$ with perturbative uncertainties from fitting the RDF to ALEPH data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04160v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rikab Gambhir, Radha Mastandrea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reliable Statistical Guarantees for Conformal Predictors with Small Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04566v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Surrogate models (including deep neural networks and other machine learning algorithms in supervised learning) are capable of approximating arbitrarily complex, high-dimensional input-output problems in science and engineering, but require a thorough data-agnostic uncertainty quantification analysis before these can be deployed for any safety-critical application. The standard approach for data-agnostic uncertainty quantification is to use conformal prediction (CP), a well-established framework to build uncertainty models with proven statistical guarantees that do not assume any shape for the error distribution of the surrogate model. However, since the classic statistical guarantee offered by CP is given in terms of bounds for the marginal coverage, for small calibration set sizes (which are frequent in realistic surrogate modelling that aims to quantify error at different regions), the potentially strong dispersion of the coverage distribution around its average negatively impacts the reliability of the uncertainty model, often obtaining coverages below the expected value, resulting in a less applicable framework. After providing a gentle presentation of uncertainty quantification for surrogate models for machine learning practitioners, in this paper we bridge the gap by proposing a new statistical guarantee that offers probabilistic information for the coverage of a single conformal predictor. We show that the proposed framework converges to the standard solution offered by CP for large calibration set sizes and, unlike the classic guarantee, still offers reliable information about the coverage of a conformal predictor for small data sizes. We illustrate and validate the methodology in a suite of examples, and implement an open access software solution that can be used alongside common conformal prediction libraries to obtain uncertainty models that fulfil the new guarantee.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04566v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel S\'anchez-Dom\'inguez, Lucas Lacasa, Javier de Vicente, Gonzalo Rubio, Eusebio Valero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The dynamical memory of tidal stellar streams: Joint inference of the Galactic potential and the progenitor of GD-1 with flow matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04600v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stellar streams offer one of the most sensitive probes of the Milky Way`s gravitational potential, as their phase-space morphology encodes both the tidal field of the host galaxy and the internal structure of their progenitors. In this work, we introduce a framework that leverages Flow Matching and Simulation-Based Inference (SBI) to jointly infer the parameters of the GD-1 progenitor and the global properties of the Milky Way potential. Our aim is to move beyond traditional techniques (e.g. orbit-fitting and action-angle methods) by constructing a fully Bayesian, likelihood-free posterior over both host-galaxy parameters and progenitor properties, thereby capturing the intrinsic coupling between tidal stripping dynamics and the underlying potential. To achieve this, we generate a large suite of mock GD-1-like streams using our differentiable N-body code \textsc{\texttt{Odisseo}}, sampling self-consistent initial conditions from a Plummer sphere and evolving them in a flexible Milky Way potential model. We then apply conditional Flow Matching to learn the vector field that transports a base Gaussian distribution into the posterior, enabling efficient, amortized inference directly from stream phase-space data. We demonstrate that our method successfully recovers the true parameters of a fiducial GD-1 simulation, producing well-calibrated posteriors and accurately reproducing parameter degeneracies arising from progenitor-host interactions. Flow Matching provides a powerful, flexible framework for Galactic Archaeology. Our approach enables joint inference on progenitor and Galactic parameters, capturing complex dependencies that are difficult to model with classical likelihood-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04600v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Viterbo, Tobias Buck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian stepwise estimation of qubit rotations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work investigates Bayesian stepwise estimation (Se) for measuring the two parameters of a unitary qubit rotation. While asymptotic analysis predicts a precision advantage for SE over joint estimation (JE) in regimes where the quantum Fisher information matrix is near-singular ("sloppy" models), we demonstrate that this advantage is mitigated within a practical Bayesian framework with limited resources. We experimentally implement a SE protocol using polarisation qubits, achieving uncertainties close to the classical Van Trees bounds. However, comparing the total error to the ultimate quantum Van Trees bound for JE reveals that averaging over prior distributions erases the asymptotic SE advantage. Nevertheless, the stepwise strategy retains a significant practical benefit as it operates effectively with simple, fixed measurements, whereas saturating the JE bound typically requires complex, parameter-dependent operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04898v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mylenne Manrique, Marco Barbieri, Assunta Di Vizio, Miranda Parisi, Gabriele Bizzarri, Ilaria Gianani, Matteo G. A. Paris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amortized Inference of Multi-Modal Posteriors using Likelihood-Weighted Normalizing Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel technique for amortized posterior estimation using Normalizing Flows trained with likelihood-weighted importance sampling. This approach allows for the efficient inference of theoretical parameters in high-dimensional inverse problems without the need for posterior training samples. We implement the method on multi-modal benchmark tasks in 2D and 3D to check for the efficacy. A critical observation of our study is the impact of the topology of the base distributions on the modelled posteriors. We find that standard unimodal base distributions fail to capture disconnected support, resulting in spurious probability bridges between modes. We demonstrate that initializing the flow with a Gaussian Mixture Model that matches the cardinality of the target modes significantly improves reconstruction fidelity, as measured by some distance and divergence metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04954v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajneil Baruah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CNN on `Top': In Search of Scalable &amp; Lightweight Image-based Jet Taggers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05031v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While Transformer-based and standard Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have proven to be the best performers in classifying different types of jets, they require substantial computational power. We explore the scope of using a lightweight and scalable version of the EfficientNet architecture, along with global features of the jet. The end product is computationally inexpensive but is capable of competitive performance. We showcase the efficacy of our network for tagging top-quark jets in a sea of other light-quark and gluon jets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05031v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajneil Baruah, Subhadeep Mondal, Sunando Kumar Patra, Satyajit Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-stationarity of the Dyson Brownian motion with collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08467v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the ergodic behavior of a system of particules, subject to collisions, before it exits a fixed subdomain of its state space. This system is composed of several one-dimensional ordered Brownian particules in interaction with electrostatic repulsions, which is usually referred as the (generalized) Dyson Brownian motion. The starting points of our analysis are the work [E. C{\'e}pa and D. L{\'e}pingle, 1997 Probab. Theory Relat. Fields] which provides existence and uniqueness of such a system subject to collisions via the theory of multivalued SDEs and a Krein-Rutman type theorem derived in [A. Guillin, B. Nectoux, L. Wu, 2020 J. Eur. Math. Soc.].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08467v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnaud Guillin (LMBP), Boris Nectoux (LMBP), Liming Wu (LMBP)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dara: Automated multiple-hypothesis phase identification and refinement from powder X-ray diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19667v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) is a foundational technique for characterizing crystalline materials. However, the reliable interpretation of XRD patterns, particularly in multiphase systems, remains a manual and expertise-demanding task. As a characterization method that only provides structural information, multiple reference phases can often be fit to a single pattern, leading to potential misinterpretation when alternative solutions are overlooked. To ease humans' efforts and address the challenge, we introduce Dara (Data-driven Automated Rietveld Analysis), a framework designed to automate the robust identification and refinement of multiple phases from powder XRD data. Dara performs an exhaustive tree search over all plausible phase combinations within a given chemical space and validates each hypothesis using a robust Rietveld refinement routine (BGMN). Key features include structural database filtering, automatic clustering of isostructural phases during tree expansion, peak-matching-based scoring to identify promising phases for refinement. When ambiguity exists, Dara generates multiple hypothesis which can then be decided between by human experts or with further characteriztion tools. By enhancing the reliability and accuracy of phase identification, Dara enables scalable analysis of realistic complex XRD patterns and provides a foundation for integration into multimodal characterization workflows, moving toward fully self-driving materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19667v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxing Fei, Matthew J. McDermott, Christopher L. Rom, Shilong Wang, Gerbrand Ceder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing thermal versus quantum annealing using probability-flux signatures across interaction networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16457v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Simulated annealing provides a heuristic solution to combinatorial optimization problems. The cost function of a problem is mapped onto the energy function of a physical many-body system, and, by using thermal or quantum fluctuations, the system explores the state space to find the ground state, which corresponds to the optimal solution of the problem. Studies have highlighted both the similarities and differences between thermal and quantum fluctuations. Nevertheless, fundamental understanding of thermal and quantum annealing remains incomplete, making it unclear how quantum annealing outperforms thermal annealing in which problem instances. Here, we investigate the many-body dynamics of thermal and quantum annealing by examining all possible interaction networks of $\pm J$ Ising spin systems up to seven spins. Our comprehensive investigation reveals that differences between thermal and quantum annealing emerge for particular interaction networks, indicating that the structure of the energy landscape distinguishes the two dynamics. We identify the microscopic origin of these differences through probability fluxes in state space, finding that the two dynamics are broadly similar, but that quantum tunnelling produces qualitative differences. Our results provide insight into how thermal and quantum fluctuations navigate a system toward the ground state in simulated annealing, and are experimentally verifiable in atomic, molecular, and optical systems. Furthermore, these insights may improve mappings of optimization problems to Ising spin systems, yielding more accurate solutions in faster simulated annealing and thus benefiting real-world applications in industry. Our comprehensive survey of interaction networks and visualization of probability flux can help to understand, predict, and control quantum advantage in quantum annealing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16457v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiaki Horiike, Yuki Kawaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
