<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.data-an updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an</link>
    <description>physics.data-an updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.data-an" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 02:34:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge-Mediated Contagion: A Quantum Electrodynamics-Inspired Framework for Non-Local Epidemic Dynamics and Superdiffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a gauge-mediated Epidemiological Model inspired by Quantum Electrodynamics (QED). In this model, the ``direct contact'' paradigm of classical SIR models is replaced by a gauge-mediated interaction where the environment, represented by a pathogen field $\varphi$, plays a fundamental role in the epidemic dynamics. In this model, the non-local characteristics of epidemics appear naturally by integrating out the pathogen field. Utilizing the Doi-Peliti formalism, we derive the effective action of the system and the standard Feynman rules that can be used to compute perturbatively any observables. Using standard QED techniques, we show how to relate renormalized pathogen mass, Debye screening, to epidemiological concepts and we compute at first order the effective reproductive number,$R_{eff}$, and how the condition to have an epidemic is related to a phase transition in the pathogen mass. We show that the superspreading hosts can be included easily in this formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13913v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose de Jesus Bernal-Alvarado, David Delepine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential-energy gating for robust state estimation in bistable stochastic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11712v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce potential-energy gating, a method for robust state estimation in systems governed by double-well stochastic dynamics. The observation noise covariance of a Bayesian filter is modulated by the local value of a known or assumed potential energy function: observations are trusted when the state is near a potential minimum and progressively discounted as it approaches the barrier separating metastable wells. This physics-based mechanism differs from statistical robust filters, which treat all state-space regions identically, and from constrained filters, which bound states rather than modulating observation trust. The approach is especially relevant in non-ergodic or data-scarce settings where only a single realization is available and statistical methods alone cannot learn the noise structure. We implement gating within Extended, Unscented, Ensemble, and Adaptive Kalman filters and particle filters, requiring only two additional hyperparameters. Monte Carlo benchmarks (100 replications) on a Ginzburg-Landau double-well with 10% outlier contamination show 57-80% RMSE improvement over the standard Extended Kalman Filter, all statistically significant (p &lt; 10^{-15}, Wilcoxon test). A naive topological baseline using only well positions achieves 57%, confirming that the continuous energy landscape adds ~21 percentage points. The method is robust to misspecification: even with 50% parameter errors, improvement never falls below 47%. Comparing externally forced and spontaneous Kramers-type transitions, gating retains 68% improvement under noise-induced transitions whereas the naive baseline degrades to 30%. As an empirical illustration, we apply the framework to Dansgaard-Oeschger events in the NGRIP delta-18O ice-core record, estimating asymmetry gamma = -0.109 (bootstrap 95% CI: [-0.220, -0.011]) and showing that outlier fraction explains 91% of the variance in filter improvement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11712v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Simeone</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
