<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG</link>
    <description>cs.CG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Convex Hulls for Simple Paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the planar dynamic convex hull problem. In the literature, solutions exist supporting the insertion and deletion of points in poly-logarithmic time and various queries on the convex hull of the current set of points in logarithmic time. If arbitrary insertion and deletion of points are allowed, constant time updates and fast queries are known to be impossible. This paper considers two restricted cases where worst-case constant time updates and logarithmic time queries are possible. We assume all updates are performed on a deque (double-ended queue) of points. The first case considers the monotonic path case, where all points are sorted in a given direction, say horizontally left-to-right, and only the leftmost and rightmost points can be inserted and deleted. The second case assumes that the points in the deque constitute a simple path. Note that the monotone case is a special case of the simple path case. For both cases, we present solutions supporting deque insertions and deletions in worst-case constant time and standard queries on the convex hull of the points in $O(\log n)$ time, where $n$ is the number of points in the current point set. The convex hull of the current point set can be reported in $O(h+\log n)$ time, where $h$ is the number of edges of the convex hull. For the 1-sided monotone path case, where updates are only allowed on one side, the reporting time can be reduced to $O(h)$, and queries on the convex hull are supported in $O(\log h)$ time. All our time bounds are worst case. In addition, we prove lower bounds that match these time bounds, and thus our results are optimal. For a quick comparison, the previous best update bounds for the simple path problem were amortized $O(\log n)$ time by Friedman, Hershberger, and Snoeyink [SoCG 1989].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05697v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruce Brewer, Gerth St{\o}lting Brodal, Haitao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solution-Hashing Search Based on Layout-Graph Transformation for Unequal Circle Packing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06211v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The problem of packing unequal circles into a circular container stands as a classic and challenging optimization problem in computational geometry. This study introduces a suite of innovative and efficient methods to tackle this problem. Firstly, we present a novel layout-graph transformation method that represents configurations as graphs, together with an inexact hash method facilitating fast comparison of configurations for isomorphism or similarity. Leveraging these advancements, we propose an Iterative Solution-Hashing Search algorithm adept at circumventing redundant exploration through efficient configuration recording. Additionally, we introduce several enhancements to refine the optimization and search processes, including an adaptive adjacency maintenance method, an efficient vacancy detection technique, and a Voronoi-based locating method. Through comprehensive computational experiments across various benchmark instances, our algorithm demonstrates superior performance over existing state-of-the-art methods, showcasing remarkable applicability and versatility. Notably, our algorithm surpasses the best-known results for 56 out of 179 benchmark instances while achieving parity with the remaining instances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06211v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianrong Zhou, Jiyao He, Kun He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Efficient Solution to the 2D Visibility Problem in Cartesian Grid Maps and its Application in Heuristic Path Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel, lightweight method to solve the visibility problem for 2D grids. The proposed method evaluates the existence of lines-of-sight from a source point to all other grid cells in a single pass with no preprocessing and independently of the number and shape of obstacles. It has a compute and memory complexity of $\mathcal{O}(n)$, where $n = n_{x}\times{} n_{y}$ is the size of the grid, and requires at most ten arithmetic operations per grid cell. In the proposed approach, we use a linear first-order hyperbolic partial differential equation to transport the visibility quantity in all directions. In order to accomplish that, we use an entropy-satisfying upwind scheme that converges to the true visibility polygon as the step size goes to zero. This dynamic-programming approach allows the evaluation of visibility for an entire grid orders of magnitude faster than typical ray-casting algorithms. We provide a practical application of our proposed algorithm by posing the visibility quantity as a heuristic and implementing a deterministic, local-minima-free path planner, setting apart the proposed planner from traditional methods. Lastly, we provide necessary algorithms and an open-source implementation of the proposed methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06494v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ibrahim Ibrahim, Joris Gillis, Wilm Decr\'e, Jan Swevers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Algorithm for Correct Computation of Reeb Spaces for PL Bivariate Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Reeb space is a topological structure which is a generalization of the notion of the Reeb graph to multi-fields. Its effectiveness has been established in revealing topological features in data across diverse computational domains which cannot be identified using the Reeb graph or other scalar-topology-based methods. Approximations of Reeb spaces such as the Mapper and the Joint Contour Net have been developed based on quantization of the range. However, computing the topologically correct Reeb space dispensing the range-quantization is a challenging problem. In the current paper, we develop an algorithm for computing a correct net-like approximation corresponding to the Reeb space of a generic piecewise-linear (PL) bivariate field based on a multi-dimensional Reeb graph (MDRG). First, we prove that the Reeb space is homeomorphic to its MDRG. Subsequently, we introduce an algorithm for computing the MDRG of a generic PL bivariate field through the computation of its Jacobi set and Jacobi structure, a projection of the Jacobi set into the Reeb space. This marks the first algorithm for MDRG computation without requiring the quantization of bivariate fields. Following this, we compute a net-like structure embedded in the corresponding Reeb space using the MDRG and the Jacobi structure. We provide the proof of correctness and complexity analysis of our algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06564v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Chattopadhyay, Yashwanth Ramamurthi, Osamu Saeki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Guided Abnormal Trajectory Gap Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06268v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given trajectories with gaps (i.e., missing data), we investigate algorithms to identify abnormal gaps in trajectories which occur when a given moving object did not report its location, but other moving objects in the same geographic region periodically did. The problem is important due to its societal applications, such as improving maritime safety and regulatory enforcement for global security concerns such as illegal fishing, illegal oil transfers, and trans-shipments. The problem is challenging due to the difficulty of bounding the possible locations of the moving object during a trajectory gap, and the very high computational cost of detecting gaps in such a large volume of location data. The current literature on anomalous trajectory detection assumes linear interpolation within gaps, which may not be able to detect abnormal gaps since objects within a given region may have traveled away from their shortest path. In preliminary work, we introduced an abnormal gap measure that uses a classical space-time prism model to bound an object's possible movement during the trajectory gap and provided a scalable memoized gap detection algorithm (Memo-AGD). In this paper, we propose a Space Time-Aware Gap Detection (STAGD) approach to leverage space-time indexing and merging of trajectory gaps. We also incorporate a Dynamic Region Merge-based (DRM) approach to efficiently compute gap abnormality scores. We provide theoretical proofs that both algorithms are correct and complete and also provide analysis of asymptotic time complexity. Experimental results on synthetic and real-world maritime trajectory data show that the proposed approach substantially improves computation time over the baseline technique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06268v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arun Sharma, Shashi Shekhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Distances for Extended Persistence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.01834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2007.01834v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The extended persistence diagram is an invariant of piecewise linear functions, which is known to be stable under perturbations of functions with respect to the bottleneck distance as introduced by Cohen-Steiner, Edelsbrunner, and Harer. We address the question of universality, which asks for the largest possible stable distance on extended persistence diagrams, showing that a more discriminative variant of the bottleneck distance is universal. Our result applies more generally to settings where persistence diagrams are considered only up to a certain degree. We achieve our results by establishing a functorial construction and several characteristic properties of relative interlevel set homology, which mirror the classical Eilenberg--Steenrod axioms. Finally, we contrast the bottleneck distance with the interleaving distance of sheaves on the real line by showing that the latter is not intrinsic, let alone universal. This particular result has the further implication that the interleaving distance of Reeb graphs is not intrinsic either.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2007.01834v5</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Bauer, Magnus Bakke Botnan, Benedikt Fluhr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReMatching: Low-Resolution Representations for Scalable Shape Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.09274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.09274v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce \emph{ReMatching}, a novel shape correspondence solution based on the functional maps framework. Our method, by exploiting a new and appropriate \emph{re}-meshing paradigm, can target shape-\emph{matching} tasks even on meshes counting millions of vertices, where the original functional maps does not apply or requires a massive computational cost. The core of our procedure is a time-efficient remeshing algorithm which constructs a low-resolution geometry while acting conservatively on the original topology and metric. These properties allow translating the functional maps optimization problem on the resulting low-resolution representation, thus enabling efficient computation of correspondences with functional map approaches. Finally, we propose an efficient technique for extending the estimated correspondence to the original meshes. We show that our method is more efficient and effective through quantitative and qualitative comparisons, outperforming state-of-the-art pipelines in quality and computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.09274v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Maggioli, Daniele Baieri, Emanuele Rodol\`a, Simone Melzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Assembly of Patterns in the abstract Tile Assembly Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16284v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the abstract Tile Assembly Model, self-assembling systems consisting of tiles of different colors can form structures on which colored patterns are ``painted.'' We explore the complexity, in terms of the numbers of unique tile types required, of assembling various patterns. We first demonstrate how to efficiently self-assemble a set of simple patterns, then show tight bounds on the tile type complexity of self-assembling 2-colored patterns on the surfaces of square assemblies. Finally, we demonstrate an exponential gap in tile type complexity of self-assembling an infinite series of patterns between systems restricted to one plane versus those allowed two planes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16284v2</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phillip Drake, Matthew J. Patitz, Scott M. Summers, Tyler Tracy</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
