<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG</link>
    <description>cs.CG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 04:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topolow: Force-Directed Euclidean Embedding of Dissimilarity Data with Robustness Against Non-Metricity and Sparsity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01733v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The problem of embedding a set of objects into a low-dimensional Euclidean space based on a matrix of pairwise dissimilarities is fundamental in data analysis, machine learning, and statistics. However, the assumptions of many standard analytical methods are violated when the input dissimilarities fail to satisfy metric or Euclidean axioms. We present the mathematical and statistical foundations of Topolow, a physics-inspired, gradient-free optimization framework for such embedding problems. Topolow is conceptually related to force-directed graph drawing algorithms but is fundamentally distinguished by its goal of quantitative metric reconstruction. It models objects as particles in a physical system, and its novel optimization scheme proceeds through sequential, stochastic pairwise interactions, which circumvents the need to compute a global gradient and provides robustness against convergence to local optima, especially for sparse data. Topolow maximizes the likelihood under a Laplace error model, robust to outliers and heterogeneous errors, and properly handles censored data. Crucially, Topolow does not require the input dissimilarities to be metric, making it a robust solution for embedding non-metric measurements into a valid Euclidean space, thereby enabling the use of standard analytical tools. We demonstrate the superior performance of Topolow compared to standard Multidimensional Scaling (MDS) methods in reconstructing the geometry of sparse and non-Euclidean data. This paper formalizes the algorithm, first introduced as Topolow in the context of antigenic mapping in (Arhami and Rohani, 2025) (open access), with emphasis on its metric embedding and mathematical properties for a broader audience. The general-purpose function Euclidify is available in the R package topolow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01733v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omid Arhami, Pejman Rohani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categorizing Merge Tree Edit Distances by Stability using Minimal Vertex Perturbation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel stability measure for edit distances between merge trees of piecewise linear scalar fields. We apply the new measure to various metrics introduced recently in the field of scalar field comparison in scientific visualization. While previous stability measures are unable to capture the fine-grained hierarchy of the considered distances, we obtain a classification of stability that fits the efficiency of current implementations and quality of practical results. Our results induce several open questions regarding the lacking theoretical analysis of such practical distances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02352v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Wetzels, Christoph Garth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Direct-Access Ranked Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01108v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the problem of Direct-Access Ranked Retrieval (DAR) for interactive data tooling, where evolving data exploration practices, combined with large-scale and high-dimensional datasets, create new challenges. DAR concerns the problem of enabling efficient access to arbitrary rank positions according to a ranking function, without enumerating all preceding tuples. To address this need, we formalize the DAR problem and propose a theoretically efficient algorithm based on geometric arrangements, achieving logarithmic query time. However, this method suffers from exponential space complexity in high dimensions. Therefore, we develop a second class of algorithms based on $\varepsilon$-sampling, which consume a linear space. Since exactly locating the tuple at a specific rank is challenging due to its connection to the range counting problem, we introduce a relaxed variant called Conformal Set Ranked Retrieval (CSR), which returns a small subset guaranteed to contain the target tuple. To solve the CSR problem efficiently, we define an intermediate problem, Stripe Range Retrieval (SRR), and design a hierarchical sampling data structure tailored for narrow-range queries. Our method achieves practical scalability in both data size and dimensionality. We prove near-optimal bounds on the efficiency of our algorithms and validate their performance through extensive experiments on real and synthetic datasets, demonstrating scalability to millions of tuples and hundreds of dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01108v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Dehghankar, Raghav Mittal, Suraj Shetiya, Abolfazl Asudeh, Gautam Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotropic Remeshing with Inter-Angle Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13641v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As an important metric for mesh quality evaluation, the isotropy property holds significant value for applications such as texture UV-mapping, physical simulation, and discrete geometric analysis. Classical isotropy remeshing methods adjust vertices and edge lengths, which exhibit certain limitations in terms of input data sensitivity, geometric consistency control, and convergence speed. In this paper, we propose an improved isotropy remeshing solution with inter-angle optimization during mesh editing to enhance shape control capability and accelerate convergence. The advantage of the solution lies in its ability to predict the impact of edge length adjustments on subsequent optimization by monitoring angle transformations. It avoids inefficient editing that may cause performance fluctuations, thereby improving efficiency. Experiments demonstrate that the proposed method effectively improves the overall efficiency of mesh optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13641v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanbing Zheng, Chenlei Lv</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blown up by an equilateral: Poncelet triangles about the incircle and their degeneracies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19464v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We tour several Euclidean properties of Poncelet triangles inscribed in an ellipse and circumscribing the incircle, including loci of triangle centers and envelopes of key objects. We also show that a number of degenerate behaviors are triggered by the presence of an equilateral triangle in the family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19464v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Helman, Ronaldo A. Garcia, Dan Reznik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>chipfiring: A Python Package for Efficient Mathematical Analysis of Chip-Firing Games on Multigraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00269v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents `chipfiring`, a comprehensive Python package for the mathematical analysis of chip-firing games on finite graphs. The package provides a robust toolkit for defining graphs and chip configurations (divisors), performing chip-firing operations, and analyzing fundamental properties such as winnability, linear equivalence, and divisor rank. We detail the core components of the library, including its object-oriented graph and divisor implementations, integrated Laplacian matrix computations, and an efficient implementation of Dhar's algorithm for determining the solvability of the dollar game. The `chipfiring` package is designed for researchers and students in graph theory, combinatorics, and algebraic geometry, providing essential algorithms and data structures for exploring these rich mathematical models. We describe the library's architecture, illustrate its usage with comprehensive examples, and highlight its specialized contributions compared to general-purpose graph libraries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00269v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhyey Dharmendrakumar Mavani, Tairan Ji, Nathan Pflueger</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
