<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG</link>
    <description>cs.CG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 01:20:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Undecidability of Tiling with a Tromino</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a periodic placement of copies of a tromino (either L or I), we prove co-RE-completeness (and hence undecidability) of deciding whether it can be completed to a plane tiling. By contrast, the problem becomes decidable if the initial placement is finite, or if the tile is a domino instead of a tromino (in any dimension). As a consequence, tiling a given periodic subset of the plane with a given tromino (L or I) is co-RE-complete.
  We also prove co-RE-completeness of tiling the entire plane with two polyominoes (one of which is disconnected and the other of which has constant size), and of tiling 3D space with two connected polycubes (one of which has constant size). If we restrict to tiling by translation only (no rotation), then we obtain co-RE-completeness with one more tile: two trominoes for a periodic subset of 2D, three polyominoes for the 2D plane, and three connected polycubes for 3D space.
  Along the way, we prove several new complexity and algorithmic results about periodic (infinite) graphs. Notably, we prove that Periodic Planar (1-in-)3SAT-3, 3DM, and Graph Orientation are co-RE-complete in 2D and PSPACE-complete in 1D; we extend basic results in graph drawing to 2D periodic graphs; and we give a polynomial-time algorithm for perfect matching in bipartite periodic graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07906v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ULB CompGeom Group, Zachary Abel, Hugo Akitaya, Lily Chung, Erik D. Demaine, Jenny Diomidova, Della Hendrickson, Stefan Langerman, Jayson Lynch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiGS: Accurate and Complete Surface Reconstruction from 3D Gaussians via Direct SDF Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07493v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) has recently emerged as a powerful paradigm for photorealistic view synthesis, representing scenes with spatially distributed Gaussian primitives. While highly effective for rendering, achieving accurate and complete surface reconstruction remains challenging due to the unstructured nature of the representation and the absence of explicit geometric supervision. In this work, we propose DiGS, a unified framework that embeds Signed Distance Field (SDF) learning directly into the 3DGS pipeline, thereby enforcing strong and interpretable surface priors. By associating each Gaussian with a learnable SDF value, DiGS explicitly aligns primitives with underlying geometry and improves cross-view consistency. To further ensure dense and coherent coverage, we design a geometry-guided grid growth strategy that adaptively distributes Gaussians along geometry-consistent regions under a multi-scale hierarchy. Extensive experiments on standard benchmarks, including DTU, Mip-NeRF 360, and Tanks&amp; Temples, demonstrate that DiGS consistently improves reconstruction accuracy and completeness while retaining high rendering fidelity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07493v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenzhi Guo, Bing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbolic Constraints in Polyhedral Enclosure and Tetrahedral Decomposition in Genus-0 Polyhedra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18222v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I present a coordinate-free, symbolic framework for determining whether a given set of polygonal faces can form a closed, genus-zero polyhedral surface and for predicting how such a surface could be decomposed into internal tetrahedra. The method uses only discrete incidence variables, such as the number of internal tetrahedra $T$, internal gluing triangles $N_i$, and internal triangulation segments $S_i$, and applies combinatorial feasibility checks before any geometric embedding is attempted. For polyhedra in \emph{normal form}, I record exact incidence identities linking $V,E,F$ to a flatness parameter $S:=\sum_f(\tmop{deg} f-3)$, and I identify parity-sensitive effects in $E$, $F$, and $S$. The external identities and parity-sensitive bounds hold universally for genus-0 polyhedral graphs. For internal quantities, I prove exact relations $N_i=2T-V+2$ and $T-N_i+S_i=1$ (with $S_i$ taken to be the number of interior edges) and obtain restricted linear ranges for internally decomposed polyhedra with the minimal number of added internal edges. Consequently, I propose a symbolic workflow that yields rapid pre-checks for structural impossibility, reducing the need for costly geometric validation in computational geometry, graphics, and automated modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18222v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moustapha Itani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A geometric proof of the infinite $(p, q)$-theorem for hyperplane piercing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10012v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a geometric proof of the $(\aleph_{0}, d+1)$-theorem for piercing compact connected sets by hyperplanes. Our argument uses only elementary properties of convex sets and clarifies the core geometric structure behind the theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10012v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sutanoya Chakraborty, Arijit Ghosh, Soumi Nandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disk and Partial Disk Inspection: Worst- to Average-Case and Pareto Upper Bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15391v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider $n$ unit-speed mobile agents initially positioned at the center of a unit disk, tasked with inspecting all points on the disk's perimeter. A perimeter point is considered covered if an agent located outside the disk's interior has unobstructed visibility of it, treating the disk itself as an obstacle. For $n=1$, this problem is known as the shoreline problem with a known distance. Isbell (1957) derived an optimal trajectory that minimizes the worst-case inspection time for this problem, while Gluss (1961) proposed heuristics for its average-case version. The one-agent case was originally introduced as a more tractable variant of Bellman's famous lost-in-the-forest problem.
  Our contributions are threefold. First, as a warm-up, we extend Isbell's findings by deriving worst-case optimal trajectories for partial inspection of a section of the disk, thereby providing an alternative proof of optimality for inspection with $n \geq 2$ agents. Second, we improve Gluss's bounds on the average-case inspection time under a uniform distribution of perimeter points (equivalent to randomized inspection algorithms), and we also strengthen the methodology by combining spatial discretization with Nonlinear Programming (NLP) to build feasible solutions to the continuous problem and compare them with NLP solutions. Third, we establish Pareto-optimal bounds for the multi-objective problem of jointly minimizing the worst-case and average-case inspection times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15391v4</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Conley, Konstantinos Georgiou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
