<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG</link>
    <description>cs.CG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 04:05:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On Quad Mesh Extraction From Messy Grid Preserving Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extracting a quad mesh from a grid preserving map is straightforward in theory, but typical inputs are not exactly grid preserving maps. Previous works can manage minor deviations from grid preserving maps, but without a clear specification of what is acceptable. This work clarifies how typical inputs differ from a grid preserving map, and shows how the differences with a grid preserving map can be reflected by a sequence of operations acting on a discrete structure. It opens research opportunities for the design of a robust quad extraction algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15404v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Ray (PIXEL)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrajLens: Visual Analysis for Constructing Cell Developmental Trajectories in Cross-Sample Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15620v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Constructing cell developmental trajectories is a critical task in single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) analysis, enabling the inference of potential cellular progression paths. However, current automated methods are limited to establishing cell developmental trajectories within individual samples, necessitating biologists to manually link cells across samples to construct complete cross-sample evolutionary trajectories that consider cellular spatial dynamics. This process demands substantial human effort due to the complex spatial correspondence between each pair of samples. To address this challenge, we first proposed a GNN-based model to predict cross-sample cell developmental trajectories. We then developed TrajLens, a visual analytics system that supports biologists in exploring and refining the cell developmental trajectories based on predicted links. Specifically, we designed the visualization that integrates features on cell distribution and developmental direction across multiple samples, providing an overview of the spatial evolutionary patterns of cell populations along trajectories. Additionally, we included contour maps superimposed on the original cell distribution data, enabling biologists to explore them intuitively. To demonstrate our system's performance, we conducted quantitative evaluations of our model with two case studies and expert interviews to validate its usefulness and effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15620v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qipeng Wang, Shaolun Ruan, Rui Sheng, Yong Wang, Min Zhu, Huamin Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$k$-PCA for (non-squared) Euclidean Distances: Polynomial Time Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14631v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given an integer $k\geq1$ and a set $P$ of $n$ points in $\REAL^d$, the classic $k$-PCA (Principle Component Analysis) approximates the affine \emph{$k$-subspace mean} of $P$, which is the $k$-dimensional affine linear subspace that minimizes its sum of squared Euclidean distances ($\ell_{2,2}$-norm) over the points of $P$, i.e., the mean of these distances. The \emph{$k$-subspace median} is the subspace that minimizes its sum of (non-squared) Euclidean distances ($\ell_{2,1}$-mixed norm), i.e., their median. The median subspace is usually more sparse and robust to noise/outliers than the mean, but also much harder to approximate since, unlike the $\ell_{z,z}$ (non-mixed) norms, it is non-convex for $k&lt;d-1$.
  We provide the first polynomial-time deterministic algorithm whose both running time and approximation factor are not exponential in $k$. More precisely, the multiplicative approximation factor is $\sqrt{d}$, and the running time is polynomial in the size of the input. We expect that our technique would be useful for many other related problems, such as $\ell_{2,z}$ norm of distances for $z\not \in \br{1,2}$, e.g., $z=\infty$, and handling outliers/sparsity.
  Open code and experimental results on real-world datasets are also provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14631v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Greenhut, Dan Feldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variable Min-Cut Max-Flow Bounds and Algorithms in Finite Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The maximum achievable capacity from source to destination in a network is limited by the min-cut max-flow bound; this serves as a converse limit. In practice, link capacities often fluctuate due to dynamic network conditions. In this work, we introduce a novel analytical framework that leverages tools from computational geometry to analyze throughput in heterogeneous networks with variable link capacities in a finite regime. Within this model, we derive new performance bounds and demonstrate that increasing the number of links can reduce throughput variability by nearly $90\%$. We formally define a notion of network stability and show that an unstable graph can have an exponential number of different min-cut sets, up to $O(2^{|E|})$. To address this complexity, we propose an algorithm that enforces stability with time complexity $O(|E|^2 + |V|)$, and further suggest mitigating the delay-throughput tradeoff using adaptive rateless random linear network coding (AR-RLNC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14852v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rivka Gitik, Alejandro Cohen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing the second and third systoles of a combinatorial surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13479v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a weighted, undirected graph $G$ cellularly embedded on a topological surface $S$, we describe algorithms to compute the second shortest and third shortest closed walks of $G$ that are neither homotopically trivial in $S$ nor homotopic to the shortest non-trivial closed walk or to each other. Our algorithms run in $O(n^2\log n)$ time for the second shortest walk and in $O(n^3)$ time for the third shortest walk. We also show how to reduce the running time for the second shortest homotopically non-trivial closed walk to $O(n\log n)$ when both the genus and the number of boundaries are fixed.
  Our algorithms rely on a careful analysis of the configurations of the first three shortest homotopically non-trivial curves in $S$. As an intermediate step, we also describe how to compute a shortest essential arc between \emph{one} pair of vertices or between \emph{all} pairs of vertices of a given boundary component of $S$ in $O(n^2)$ time or $O(n^3)$ time, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13479v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthijs Ebbens, Francis Lazarus</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
