<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG</link>
    <description>cs.CG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 01:46:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ellipsoidal Filtration for Topological Denoising of Recurrent Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce ellipsoidal filtration, a novel method for persistent homology, and demonstrate its effectiveness in denoising recurrent signals. Unlike standard Rips filtrations, which use isotropic neighbourhoods and ignore the signal's direction of evolution, our approach constructs ellipsoids aligned with local gradients to capture trajectory flow. The death scale of the most persistent H_1 feature defines a data-driven neighbourhood for averaging. Experiments on synthetic signals show that our method achieves better noise reduction than both topological and moving-average filters, especially for low-amplitude components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16682v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omer Bahadir Eryilmaz, Cihan Katar, Max A. Little</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow-Aware Ellipsoidal Filtration for Persistent Homology of Recurrent Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One common use of persistent homology is to explore the shape of point clouds, where points are assumed to be sampled from a geometric object. We propose a novel filtration, called ellipsoidal filtration, which assumes that point clouds are sampled from a dynamic smooth flow. Instead of creating topologies from point clouds at increasing scales using isotropic balls (for example, Vietoris-Rips filtration), ellipsoidal filtration creates ellipsoids around points based on local flow variances, approximating the flow's manifold as the scale increases. We show that constructing ellipsoidal neighbourhoods improves the denoising of recurrent signals and the estimation of recurrence times, especially when the data contain bottlenecks. Choosing ellipsoids according to the maximum persistence of the H1 class provides a data-driven threshold for both denoising and recurrence-time estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17735v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omer Bahadir Eryilmaz, Cihan Katar, Max A. Little</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who Needs Crossings?: Noncrossing Linkages are Universal, and Deciding (Global) Rigidity is Hard</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We exactly settle the complexity of graph realization, graph rigidity, and graph global rigidity as applied to three types of graphs: "globally noncrossing" graphs, which avoid crossings in all of their configurations; matchstick graphs, with unit-length edges and where only noncrossing configurations are considered; and unrestricted graphs (crossings allowed) with unit edge lengths (or in the global rigidity case, edge lengths in $\{1,2\}$). We show that all nine of these questions are complete for the class $\exists\mathbb{R}$, defined by the Existential Theory of the Reals, or its complement $\forall\mathbb{R}$; in particular, each problem is (co)NP-hard.
  One of these nine results--that realization of unit-distance graphs is $\exists\mathbb{R}$-complete--was shown previously by Schaefer (2013), but the other eight are new. We strengthen several prior results. Matchstick graph realization was known to be NP-hard (Eades \&amp; Wormald 1990, or Cabello et al.\ 2007), but its membership in NP remained open; we show it is complete for the (possibly) larger class $\exists\mathbb{R}$. Global rigidity of graphs with edge lengths in $\{1,2\}$ was known to be coNP-hard (Saxe 1979); we show it is $\forall\mathbb{R}$-complete.
  The majority of the paper is devoted to proving an analog of Kempe's Universality Theorem--informally, "there is a linkage to sign your name"--for globally noncrossing linkages. In particular, we show that any polynomial curve $\phi(x,y)=0$ can be traced by a noncrossing linkage, settling an open problem from 2004. More generally, we show that the regions in the plane that may be traced by a noncrossing linkage are precisely the compact semialgebraic regions (plus the trivial case of the entire plane). Thus, no drawing power is lost by restricting to noncrossing linkages. We prove analogous results for matchstick linkages and unit-distance linkages as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17737v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.20382/jocg.v16i1a12</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Computational Geometry, 16(1), 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Abel, Erik D. Demaine, Martin L. Demaine, Sarah Eisenstat, Jayson Lynch, Tao B. Schardl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural Tree Extraction from 3D Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15886v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a method to extract a hierarchical tree representation from 3D unorganized polygonal data. The proposed approach first extracts a graph representation of the surface, which serves as the foundation for structural analysis. A Steiner tree is then generated to establish an optimized connection between key terminal points, defined according to application-specific criteria. The structure can be further refined by leveraging line-of-sight constraints, reducing redundancy while preserving essential connectivity. Unlike traditional skeletonization techniques, which often assume volumetric interpretations, this method operates directly on the surface, ensuring that the resulting representation remains relevant for navigation-aware geometric analysis. The method is validated through two use cases: extracting structural representations from tile-based elements for procedural content generation, and identifying key points and structural metrics for automated level analysis. Results demonstrate its ability to produce simplified, coherent representations, supporting applications in procedural generation, spatial reasoning, and map analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15886v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diogo de Andrade, Nuno Fachada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truly Subquadratic Time Algorithms for Diameter and Related Problems in Graphs of Bounded VC-dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16346v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give the first truly subquadratic time algorithm, with $O^*(n^{2-1/18})$ running time, for computing the diameter of an $n$-vertex unit-disk graph, resolving a central open problem in the literature. Our result is obtained as an instance of a general framework, applicable to different graph families and distance problems. Surprisingly, our framework completely bypasses sublinear separators (or $r$-divisions) which were used in all previous algorithms. Instead, we use low-diameter decompositions in their most elementary form. We also exploit bounded VC-dimension of set systems associated with the input graph, as well as new ideas on geometric data structures. Among the numerous applications of the general framework, we obtain:
  1. An $\tilde{O}(mn^{1-1/(2d)})$ time algorithm for computing the diameter of $m$-edge sparse unweighted graphs with constant VC-dimension $d$. The previously known algorithms by Ducoffe, Habib, and Viennot [SODA 2019] and Duraj, Konieczny, and Pot\c{e}pa [ESA 2024] are truly subquadratic only when the diameter is a small polynomial. Our result thus generalizes truly subquadratic time algorithms known for planar and minor-free graphs (in fact, it slightly improves the previous time bound for minor-free graphs).
  2. An $\tilde{O}(n^{2-1/12})$ time algorithm for computing the diameter of intersection graphs of axis-aligned squares with arbitrary size. The best-known algorithm by Duraj, Konieczny, and Pot\c{e}pa [ESA 2024] only works for unit squares and is only truly subquadratic in the low-diameter regime.
  3. The first algorithms with truly subquadratic complexity for other distance-related problems, including all-vertex eccentricities, Wiener index, and exact distance oracles. (... truncated to meet the arXiv abstract requirement.)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16346v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy M. Chan, Hsien-Chih Chang, Jie Gao, S\'andor Kisfaludi-Bak, Hung Le, Da Wei Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integer points in dilates of polytopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study how the number of integer points in a polytope grows as we dilate the polytope. We prove new and essentially tight bounds on this quantity by specifically studying dilates of the Hadamard polytope.
  Our motivation for studying this quantity comes from the problem of understanding the maximal number of monomials in a factor of a multivariate polynomial with $s$ monomials. A recent result by Bhargava, Saraf, and Volkovich showed that if $f$ is an $n$-variate polynomial, where each variable has degree $d$, and $f$ has $s$ monomials, then any factor of $f$ has at most $s^{O(d^2 \log n)}$ monomials. The key technical ingredient of their proof was to show that any polytope with $s$ vertices, where each vertex lies in $\{0,..,d\}^n$, can have at most $s^{O(d^2 \log n)}$ integer points. The precise dependence on $d$ of the number of integer points was left open. We show that this bound, particularly the dependence on $d$, is essentially tight by studying dilates of the Hadamard polytope and proving new lower bounds on the number of its integer points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16481v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubhangi Saraf, Narmada Varadarajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Escaping a Polygon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2007.08965v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Suppose an escaping player ("human") moves continuously at maximum speed $1$ in the interior of a region, while a pursuing player ("zombie") moves continuously at maximum speed $r$ outside the region. For what $r$ can the first player escape the region, that is, reach the boundary a positive distance away from the pursuing player, assuming optimal play by both players? We formalize a model for this infinitesimally alternating 2-player game and prove that it has a unique winner in any locally rectifiable region. Our model thus avoids pathological behaviors (where both players can have "winning strategies") previously identified for pursuit-evasion games such as the Lion and Man problem in certain metric spaces. For some specific regions, including both equilateral triangle and square, we give exact results for the critical speed ratio, above which the pursuing player can win and below which the escaping player can win (and at which the pursuing player can win). For simple polygons, we give a simple formula and polynomial-time algorithm that is guaranteed to give a 10.89898-approximation to the critical speed ratio, and we give a pseudopolynomial-time approximation scheme for approximating the critical speed ratio arbitrarily closely. On the negative side, we prove NP-hardness of the problem for polyhedral domains in 3D, and prove stronger results (PSPACE-hardness and NP-hardness even to approximate) for generalizations to multiple escaping and pursuing players.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2007.08965v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Abel, Hugo Akitaya, Erik D. Demaine, Martin L. Demaine, Adam Hesterberg, Jason S. Ku, Jayson Lynch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Closed Quasigeodesics on Convex Polyhedra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.00589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2008.00589v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A closed quasigeodesic is a closed curve on the surface of a polyhedron with at most $180^\circ$ of surface on both sides at all points; such curves can be locally unfolded straight. In 1949, Pogorelov proved that every convex polyhedron has at least three (non-self-intersecting) closed quasigeodesics, but the proof relies on a nonconstructive topological argument. We present the first finite algorithm to find a closed quasigeodesic on a given convex polyhedron, which is the first positive progress on a 1990 open problem by O'Rourke and Wyman. The algorithm also establishes a pseudopolynomial upper bound on the total number of visits to faces (number of line segments), namely, $O\left(\frac{n \, L^2}{\epsilon^2 \, \ell^2}\right)$ where $n$ is the number of vertices of the polyhedron, $\epsilon$ is the minimum curvature of a vertex, $L$ is the length of the longest edge, and $\ell$ is the smallest distance within a face between a vertex and a nonincident edge (minimum feature size of any face). On the real RAM, the algorithm's running time is also pseudopolynomial, namely $O\left(\frac{L^2}{\epsilon^2 \, \ell^2} \, n \lg n\right)$. On a word RAM, the running time grows to $O\left(\frac{b^2 \, \Delta^{36} \, L^{146}}{\epsilon^{98} \, \ell^{146}} \, n \lg n \cdot 2^{O(|R|)}\right)$, where $\Delta \leq n$ is the polyhedron's maximum vertex degree, assuming the polyhedron's intrinsic geometry is given by constant-size radical expressions with $b$-bit integers and at most $|R|$ distinct square-roots. Along the way, we introduce the expression RAM model of computation, formalizing a connection between the real RAM and word RAM hinted at by past work on exact geometric computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2008.00589v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik D. Demaine, Adam C. Hesterberg, Jason S. Ku</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Sampling of Confined Polygons in Linear Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04885v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an algorithm for sampling tightly confined random equilateral closed polygons in three-space which has runtime linear in the number of edges. Using symplectic geometry, sampling such polygons reduces to sampling a moment polytope, and in our confinement model this polytope turns out to be very natural from a combinatorial point of view. This connection to combinatorics yields both our fast sampling algorithm and explicit formulas for the expected distances of vertices to the origin. We use our algorithm to investigate the expected total curvature of confined polygons, leading to a very precise conjecture for the asymptotics of total curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04885v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clayton Shonkwiler, Kandin Theis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
