<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG</link>
    <description>cs.CG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 01:49:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-sparsity Generalization for Variational Mesh Denoising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13372v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a new variational framework for 3D surface denoising over triangulated meshes, which is inspired by the success of semi-sparse regularization in image processing. Differing from the uniformly sampled image data, mesh surfaces are typically represented by irregular, non-uniform structures, which thus complicate the direct application of the standard formulation and pose challenges in both model design and numerical implementation. To bridge this gap, we first introduce the discrete approximations of higher-order differential operators over triangle meshes and then develop a semi-sparsity regularized minimization model for mesh denoising. This new model is efficiently solved by using a multi-block alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) and achieves high-quality simultaneous fitting performance -- preserving sharp features while promoting piecewise-polynomial smoothing surfaces. To verify its effectiveness, we also present a series of experimental results on both synthetic and real scanning data, showcasing the competitive and superior results compared to state-of-the-art methods, both visually and quantitatively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13372v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junqing Huang, Haihui Wang, Michael Ruzhansky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiGumi: Making Tightly Coupled Integral Joints Millable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13168v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditional integral wood joints, despite their strength, durability, and elegance, remain rare in modern workflows due to the cost and difficulty of manual fabrication. CNC milling offers a scalable alternative, but directly milling traditional joints often fails to produce functional results because milling induces geometric deviations, such as rounded inner corners, that alter the target geometries of the parts. Since joints rely on tightly fitting surfaces, such deviations introduce gaps or overlaps that undermine fit or block assembly. We propose to overcome this problem by (1) designing a language that represent millable geometry, and (2) co-optimizing part geometries to restore coupling. We introduce Millable Extrusion Geometry (MXG), a language for representing geometry as the outcome of milling operations performed with flat-end drill bits. MXG represents each operation as a subtractive extrusion volume defined by a tool direction and drill radius. This parameterization enables the modeling of artifact-free geometry under an idealized zero-radius drill bit, matching traditional joint designs. Increasing the radius then reveals milling-induced deviations, which compromise the integrity of the joint. To restore coupling, we formalize tight coupling in terms of both surface proximity and proximity constraints on the mill-bit paths associated with mating surfaces. We then derive two tractable, differentiable losses that enable efficient optimization of joint geometry. We evaluate our method on 30 traditional joint designs, demonstrating that it produces CNC-compatible, tightly fitting joints that approximates the original geometry. By reinterpreting traditional joints for CNC workflows, we continue the evolution of this heritage craft and help ensure its relevance in future making practices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13168v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Ganeshan, Kurt Fleischer, Wenzel Jakob, Ariel Shamir, Daniel Ritchie, Takeo Igarashi, Maria Larsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tight Parameterized (In)tractability of Layered Crossing Minimization: Subexponential Algorithms and Kernelization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13335v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The starting point of our work is a decade-old open question concerning the subexponential parameterized complexity of \textsc{2-Layer Crossing Minimization}. In this problem, the input is an $n$-vertex graph $G$ whose vertices are partitioned into two independent sets $V_1$ and $V_2$, and a non-negative integer $k$. The question is whether $G$ admits a 2-layered drawing with at most $k$ crossings, where each $V_i$ lies on a distinct line parallel to the $x$-axis, and all edges are straight lines. We resolve this open question by giving the first subexponential fixed-parameter algorithm for this problem, running in time $2^{O(\sqrt{k}\log k)} + n \cdot k^{O(1)}$.
  We then ask whether the subexponential phenomenon extends beyond two layers. In the general $h$-Layer Crossing Minimization problem, the vertex set is partitioned into $h$ independent sets $V_1, \ldots, V_h$, and the goal is to decide whether an $h$-layered drawing with at most $k$ crossings exists. We present a subexponential FPT algorithm for three layers with running time $2^{O(k^{2/3}\log k)} + n \cdot k^{O(1)}$ for $h = 3$ layers. In contrast, we show that for all $h \ge 5$, no algorithm with running time $2^{o(k/\log k)} \cdot n^{O(1)}$ exists unless the Exponential-Time Hypothesis fails.
  Finally, we address polynomial kernelization. While a polynomial kernel was already known for $h=2$, we design a new polynomial kernel for $h=3$. These kernels are essential ingredients in our subexponential algorithms. Finally, we rule out polynomial kernels for all $h \ge 4$ unless the polynomial hierarchy collapses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13335v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fedor V. Fomin, Petr A. Golovach, Tanmay Inamdar, Saket Saurabh, Meirav Zehavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better Late than Never: the Complexity of Arrangements of Polyhedra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03960v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{A}$ be the subdivision of $\mathbb{R}^d$ induced by $m$ convex polyhedra having $n$ facets in total. We prove that $\mathcal{A}$ has combinatorial complexity $O(m^{\lceil d/2 \rceil} n^{\lfloor d/2 \rfloor})$ and that this bound is tight. The bound is mentioned several times in the literature, but no proof for arbitrary dimension has been published before.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03960v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Aronov, Sang Won Bae, Sergio Cabello, Otfried Cheong, David Eppstein, Christian Knauer, Raimund Seidel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bijective Image Retargeting Algorithm Based on Conformal Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18074v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Image retargeting, which resizes images to one with a prescribed aspect ratio by determining an optimal warping map, has gained substantial interest in imaging science. Despite significant advances, existing methods often fail to ensure bijective warping maps essential for preserving visual information. This paper introduces a novel bijective image retargeting model through conformal energy minimization of the deformation field. The proposed model establishes mathematical rigor by proving the well-posedness for the optimal warping map in both continuous and discrete settings and showing that the discrete solutions converge to their continuous counterpart under mesh refinement. Numerical experiments corroborate the model's efficacy and the convergence of discrete solutions during progressive mesh subdivision processes, validating both theoretical guarantees and practical performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18074v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengyang Liu, Michael K. Ng</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
