<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG</link>
    <description>cs.CG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Tight Spanning Ratio of the Rectangle Delaunay Triangulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.11987v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spanner construction is a well-studied problem and Delaunay triangulations are among the most popular spanners. Tight bounds are known if the Delaunay triangulation is constructed using an equilateral triangle, a square, or a regular hexagon. However, all other shapes have remained elusive. In this paper, we extend the restricted class of spanners for which tight bounds are known. We prove that Delaunay triangulations constructed using rectangles with aspect ratio $A$ have spanning ratio at most $\sqrt{2} \sqrt{1+A^2 + A \sqrt{A^2 + 1}}$, which matches the known lower bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.11987v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\`e van Renssen, Yuan Sha, Yucheng Sun, Sampson Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting Equilibria of the Electrostatic Potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05315v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 1873, James C. Maxwell conjectured that the electric field generated by $n$ point charges in generic position has at most $(n-1)^2$ isolated zeroes. The first (non-optimal) upper bound was only obtained in 2007 by Gabrielov, Novikov and Shapiro, who also posed two additional interesting conjectures.
  In this article, we give the best upper bound known to date on the number of zeroes of the electric field, and construct a counterexample to a conjecture of Gabrielov, Novikov and Shapiro that the number of equilibria cannot exceed those of the distance function defined by the unit point charges.
  Finally, we note that it is quite possible that Maxwell's quadratic upper bound is not tight, so it is prudent to find smaller bounds. Hence, we also explore examples and construct configurations of charges achieving the highest ratios of the number of electric field zeroes by point charges found to this day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05315v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Herbert Edelsbrunner, Christopher Fillmore, Gon\c{c}alo Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
