<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Extension of Kirkwood-Buff theory: Partial enthalpies, fluctuations of energy density, temperature, and pressure, and solute-induced effects in a mixture solvent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a statistical mechanical theory of multi-component fluids, where we consider the correlation functions of the number densities and the energy density in the grand canonical ensemble. In terms of their space integrals we express the partial volumes ${\bar v}_i$, the partial enthalpies ${\bar H}_i$, and other thermodynamic derivatives. These ${\bar v}_i$ and ${\bar H}_i$ assume simple forms for binary mixtures and for ternary mixtures with a dilute solute. They are then related to the space-dependent thermal fluctuations of the temperature and the pressure. The space averages of these fluctuations are those introduced by Landau and Lifshits in the isothermal-isobaric ($T$-$p$) ensemble. We also give expressions for the long-range (nonlocal) correlations in the canonical and $T$-$p$ ensembles, which are inversely proportional to the system volume. For a mixture solvent, we examine the solvent-induced solute-solute attraction and the osmotic enthalpy changes due to the solute doping using the correlation function integrals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05471v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akira Onuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster statistics of critical Ising and Ashkin-Teller models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent progress on the scaling behavior of entanglement entropy, we study the scaling behavior of the number of clusters crossing the boundary between two subsystems for several classical statistical models in two dimension. This number exhibits a subleading logarithmic dependence of the linear dimension of the boundary when the model is at critical, in analogy to the entanglement entropy of a quantum system. It is shown that the logarithmic scaling of the cluster number originates from the conformal invariance of the critical system. We check this numerically for Ising and Ashkin-Teller models by using Monte Carlo simulations, and show that whether a universal coefficient of the logarithmic term can be observed numerically may strongly depend on the geometry and boundary condictions of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05747v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaonian Xu, Rong Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep thermalization in continuous-variable quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05470v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We uncover emergent universality arising in the equilibration dynamics of multimode continuous-variable systems. Specifically, we study the ensemble of pure states supported on a small subsystem of a few modes, generated by Gaussian measurements on the remaining modes of a globally pure bosonic Gaussian state. We find that beginning from sufficiently complex global states, such as random Gaussian states and product squeezed states coupled via a deep array of linear optical elements, the induced ensemble attains a universal form, independent of the choice of measurement basis: it is composed of unsqueezed coherent states whose displacements are distributed normally and isotropically, with variance depending on only the particle-number density of the system. We further show that the emergence of such a universal form is consistent with a generalized maximum entropy principle, which endows the limiting ensemble, which we call the "Gaussian Scrooge distribution", with a special quantum information-theoretic property of having minimal accessible information. Our results represent a conceptual generalization of the recently introduced notion of "deep thermalization" in discrete-variable quantum many-body systems -- a novel form of equilibration going beyond thermalization of local observables -- to the realm of continuous-variable quantum systems. Moreover, it demonstrates how quantum information-theoretic perspectives can unveil new physical phenomena and principles in quantum dynamics and statistical mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05470v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Liu, Qi Camm Huang, Wen Wei Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing (quasi-)long-range order in a two-dimensional driven crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05621v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It has been recently shown that 2D systems can exhibit crystalline phases with long-range translational order showcasing a striking violation of the Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner (HMW) theorem which is valid at equilibrium. This is made possible by athermal driving mechanisms that inject energy into the system without exciting long wavelength modes of the density field. However, as thermal fluctuations are superimposed on the non-equilibrium driving, long-range translational order is inevitably lost. In this paper, we discuss the possibility of exploiting non-equilibrium effects to suppress arbitrarily large density fluctuations even when a global thermal bath is coupled to the system. We introduce a model of a harmonic crystal driven both by a global thermal bath and by a momentum conserving noise, where the typical observables related to density fluctuations and long-range translational order can be analytically derived and put in relation. This model allows us to rationalize the violation of the HMW theorem observed in previous studies through the prediction of large-wavelength phonons which thermalize at a vanishing effective temperature when the global bath is switched off. The conceptual framework introduced through this theory is then applied to numerical simulations of a hard-disk solid in contact with a thermal bath and driven out-of-equilibrium by active collisions. Our numerical analysis demonstrates how varying driving and dissipative parameters can lead to an arbitrary enhancement of the quasi-long-range order in the system regardless of the applied global noise amplitude. Finally, we outline a possible experimental procedure to apply our results to a realistic granular system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05621v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Maire, A. Plati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intermediate spectral statistics of rational triangular quantum billiards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Triangular billiards whose angles are rational multiples of $\pi$ are one of the simplest examples of pseudo-integrable models with intriguing classical and quantum properties. We perform an extensive numerical study of spectral statistics of eight quantized rational triangles, six belonging to the family of right-angled Veech triangles and two obtuse rational triangles. Large spectral samples of up to one million energy levels were calculated for each triangle which permits to determine their spectral statistics with great accuracy. It is demonstrated that they are of the intermediate type, sharing some features with chaotic systems, like level repulsion and some with integrable systems, like exponential tails of the level spacing distributions. Another distinctive feature of intermediate spectral statistics is a finite value of the level compressibility.
  The short range statistics such as the level spacing distributions, and long-range statistics such as the number variance and spectral form factors were analyzed in detail. An excellent agreement between the numerical data and the model of gamma distributions is revealed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05783v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\v{C}rt Lozej, Eugene Bogomolny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-monotonic conductivity of aqueous electrolytes: beyond the first Wien effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05882v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The conductivity of strong electrolytes increases under high electric fields, a nonlinear response known as the first Wien effect. Here, using molecular dynamics simulations we show that this nonlinear response is non-monotonic for moderately concentrated aqueous electrolytes. We attribute this unanticipated behavior to the fact that, under high electric fields, the permittivity of water decreases and becomes anisotropic. The permittivity tensor measured in the simulations can be reproduced by a model of water molecules as dipoles. We incorporate the resulting anisotropic interactions between the ions into a generalised Stochastic Density Field Theory and calculate ionic correlations as well as corrections to the Nernst-Einstein conductivity which are in good agreement with the numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05882v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H\'el\`ene Berthoumieux, Vincent D\'emery, A. C. Maggs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion from Measurement: The Role of Symmetry of Quantum Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quantum mechanics, measurements are dynamical processes and thus they should be capable of inducing currents. The symmetries of the Hamiltonian and measurement operator provide an organizing principle for understanding the conditions for such currents to emerge. The central role is played by the inversion and time-reversal symmetries. We classify the distinct behaviors that emerge from single and repeated measurements, with and without coupling to a dissipative bath. While the breaking of inversion symmetry alone is sufficient to generate currents through measurements, the breaking of time-reversal symmetry by the measurement operator leads to a dramatic increase in the magnitude of the currents. We consider the dependence on the measurement rate and find that the current is non-monotonic. Furthermore, nondegenerate measurements can lead to current loops within the steady state even in the Zeno limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05946v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luka Antonic, Yariv Kafri, Daniel Podolsky, Ari M. Turner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confusion concerning the extrapolated endpoint. When will it ever end?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02448v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a paper on ``the Brownian motion analog of the well-known Milne problem in radiative transfer theory'' [\textit{J Stat Phys} 25 (1981) 569--82], Burschka and Titulaer reported: ``The value we find for this `Milne extrapolation length' is, in the appropriate dimensionless units, approximately twice the value found in the radiative transfer problem.'' A study by Ziff [\textit{J Stat Phys} 65 (1991) 1217--33], concerned with the absorption of particles executing a Rayleigh flight (randomly directed displacements of equal length $l$) by a black sphere of radius $R$, led to a value for the extrapolation length $\gamma$ about half as small as the benchmark result (for $R\gg l)$. The first discrepancy is shown to result from the disparity of the two length scales; the second, from the zero variance of the jump lengths. Ziff's finding that $\gamma$ is independent of $R$ for $0&lt;l\leq 2R$, cannot be reconciled with studies based on the Lorentz-Boltzmann equation and the Klein-Kramers equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02448v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Razi Naqvi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coarsening in Bent-core Liquid Crystals: Intermediate Splay Bend State en route to the Twist Bend Phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03189v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use molecular dynamics simulations to study coarsening dynamics in achiral banana-shaped bent-core liquid crystals following a quench from the high concentration polar smectic (SmX) phase to lower concentrations that favor the exotic twist-bend (TB) phase. Our novel result is the identification of an intermediate splay-bend state emerging prior to the eventual TB phase. The latter coarsens via the annihilation of {\it beta lines} which are analogous to string defects in nematic liquid crystals. Our findings are relevant for a large class of chiral systems assembled from achiral entities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03189v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nishant Birdi, Nigel B. Wilding, Sanjay Puri, Varsha Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact calculation of the probabilities of rare events in cluster-cluster aggregation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04201v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop an action formalism to calculate probabilities of rare events in cluster-cluster aggregation for arbitrary collision kernels and establish a pathwise large deviation principle with total mass being the rate. As an application, the rate function for the number of surviving particles as well as the optimal evolution trajectory are calculated exactly for the constant, sum and product kernels. For the product kernel, we argue that the second derivative of the rate function has a discontinuity. The theoretical results agree with simulations tailored to the calculation of rare events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04201v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Rajesh, V. Subashri, Oleg Zaboronski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalization Group Analysis of the Anderson Model on Random Regular Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.14965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.14965v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a renormalization group analysis of the problem of Anderson localization on a Random Regular Graph (RRG) which generalizes the renormalization group of Abrahams, Anderson, Licciardello, and Ramakrishnan to infinite-dimensional graphs. The renormalization group equations necessarily involve two parameters (one being the changing connectivity of sub-trees), but we show that the one-parameter scaling hypothesis is recovered for sufficiently large system sizes for both eigenstates and spectrum observables. We also explain the non-monotonic behavior of dynamical and spectral quantities as a function of the system size for values of disorder close to the transition, by identifying two terms in the beta function of the running fractal dimension of different signs and functional dependence. Our theory provides a simple and coherent explanation for the unusual scaling behavior observed in numerical data of the Anderson model on RRG and of Many-Body Localization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.14965v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Vanoni, Boris L. Altshuler, Vladimir E. Kravtsov, Antonello Scardicchio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network science Ising states of matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13604v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Network science provides very powerful tools for extracting information from interacting data. Although recently the unsupervised detection of phases of matter using machine learning has raised significant interest, the full prediction power of network science has not yet been systematically explored in this context. Here we fill this gap by providing an in-depth statistical, combinatorial, geometrical and topological characterization of 2D Ising snapshot networks (IsingNets) extracted from Monte Carlo simulations of the $2$D Ising model at different temperatures, going across the phase transition. Our analysis reveals the complex organization properties of IsingNets in both the ferromagnetic and paramagnetic phases and demonstrates the significant deviations of the IsingNets with respect to randomized null models. In particular percolation properties of the IsingNets reflect the existence of the symmetry between configurations with opposite magnetization below the critical temperature and the very compact nature of the two emerging giant clusters revealed by our persistent homology analysis of the IsingNets. Moreover, the IsingNets display a very broad degree distribution and significant degree-degree correlations and weight-degree correlations demonstrating that they encode relevant information present in the configuration space of the $2$D Ising model. The geometrical organization of the critical IsingNets is reflected in their spectral properties deviating from the one of the null model. This work reveals the important insights that network science can bring to the characterization of phases of matter. The set of tools described hereby can be applied as well to numerical and experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13604v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.109.054305</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hanlin Sun, Rajat Kumar Panda, Roberto Verdel, Alex Rodriguez, Marcello Dalmonte, Ginestra Bianconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic in generalized Rokhsar-Kivelson wavefunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08463v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Magic is a property of a quantum state that characterizes its deviation from a stabilizer state, serving as a useful resource for achieving universal quantum computation e.g., within schemes that use Clifford operations. In this work, we study magic, as quantified by the stabilizer Renyi entropy, in a class of models known as generalized Rokhsar-Kivelson systems, i.e., Hamiltonians that allow a stochastic matrix form (SMF) decomposition. The ground state wavefunctions of these systems can be written explicitly throughout their phase diagram, and their properties can be related to associated classical statistical mechanics problems, thereby allowing powerful analytical and numerical approaches that are not usually available in conventional quantum many body settings. As a result, we are able to express the SRE in terms of wave function coefficients that can be understood as a free energy difference of related classical problems. We apply this insight to a range of quantum many body SMF Hamiltonians, which affords us to study numerically the SRE of large high-dimensional systems, and in some cases to obtain analytical results. We observe that the behaviour of the SRE is relatively featureless across quantum phase transitions in these systems, although it is indeed singular (in its first or higher order derivative, depending on the nature of the transition). On the contrary, we find that the maximum of the SRE generically occurs at a cusp away from the quantum critical point, where the derivative suddenly changes sign. Furthermore, we compare the SRE and the logarithm of overlaps with specific stabilizer states, asymptotically realised in the ground state phase diagrams of these systems. We find that they display strikingly similar behaviors, which in turn establish rigorous bounds on the min-relative entropy of magic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08463v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Poetri Sonya Tarabunga, Claudio Castelnovo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mathematical theory of the critical point of ferromagnetic Ising systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14757v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a theory of the critical point of the ferromagnetic Ising model, whose basic objects are the ergodic (pure) states of the infinite system. It proves the existence of anomalous critical fluctuations, for dimension $\nu=2$ and, under a standard assumption, for $\nu=3$, for the model with nearest neighbor interaction, in a way which is consistent with the probabilistic approach of Cassandro, Jona-Lasinio and several others, reviewed in Jona-Lasinio's article in Phys. Rep. 352, 439 (2001). We propose to single out the state at the critical temperature $T_{c}$ among the ergodic thermal states associated to temperatures $0 \le T \le T_{c}$, by a condition of non-summable clustering of the connected two-point function. The analogous condition for the connected $(2r)-$ point functions for $r \ge 2$, together with a scaling hypothesis, proves that the (macroscopic) fluctuation state is quasi-free, also at the critical temperature, after a proper rescaling, also at the critical temperature, in agreement with a theorem by Cassandro and Jona-Lasinio, whose proof is, however, shown to be incomplete. Other subjects include topics related to universality, including spontaneous breaking of continuous symmetries and violations of universality in problems of energetic and dynamic stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14757v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domingos H. U. Marchetti, Manfred Requardt, Walter F. Wreszinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence rate in random Lindblad dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04705v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Open quantum systems undergo decoherence, which is responsible for the transition from quantum to classical behavior. The time scale in which decoherence takes place can be analyzed using upper limits to its rate. We examine the dynamics of open chaotic quantum systems governed by random Lindblad operators sourced from Gaussian and Ginibre ensembles with Wigner-Dyson symmetry classes. In these systems, the ensemble-averaged purity decays monotonically as a function of time. This decay is governed by the decoherence rate, which is upper-bounded by the dimension of their Hilbert space and is independent of the ensemble symmetry. These findings hold upon mixing different ensembles, indicating the universal character of the decoherence rate limit. Moreover, our findings reveal that open chaotic quantum systems governed by random Lindbladians tend to exhibit the most rapid decoherence, regardless of the initial state. This phenomenon is associated with the concentration of the decoherence rate near its upper bound. Our work identifies primary features of decoherence in dissipative quantum chaos, with applications ranging from quantum foundations to high-energy physics and quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04705v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifeng Yang, Zhenyu Xu, Adolfo del Campo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum many-body scars with unconventional superconducting pairing symmetries via multi-body interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02914v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic framework to construct model Hamiltonians that have unconventional superconducting pairing states as exact energy eigenstates, by incorporating multi-body interactions (i.e., interactions among more than two particles). The multi-body interactions are introduced in a form of the local density-density coupling in such a way that any pair configuration in real space has a constant interaction energy by cancelling the two-body and multi-body interactions. Our approach is applicable to both spinless and spinful models in any spatial dimensions and on any bipartite lattices, facilitating an exhaustive extension of Yang's $s$-wave $\eta$-pairing state to various other unconventional pairing symmetries ($p$-wave, $d$-wave, $f$-wave, etc.). Particularly, the constructed eigenstates have off-site pairs with finite center-of-mass momentum, which leads to superconducting states with either even-parity and spin-triplet or odd-parity and spin-singlet symmetry. We verify that the two-dimensional spinful Hubbard model on a square lattice with the multi-body interactions has the spin-triplet $d$-wave pairing state as an energy eigenstate, which can be regarded as a quantum many-body scar state as evidenced from the numerical analysis of the pair correlation function, entanglement entropy, and level statistics. We also discuss other examples, including spin-triplet $f$-wave pairing states on a honeycomb lattice and spin-singlet $p$-wave pairing states in a one dimensional chain. These findings open up the possibility of realizing nonequilibrium unconventional superconductivity in a long-lived manner protected against thermalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02914v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shohei Imai, Naoto Tsuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
