<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 01:40:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic analysis of boundary correlation functions for the hyperbolic-lattice Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze boundary spin correlation functions of the hyperbolic-lattice Ising model from the holographic point of view. Using the corner-transfer-matrix renormalization group (CTMRG) method, we demonstrate that the boundary correlation function exhibits power-law decay with quasi-periodic oscillation, while the bulk correlation function always decays exponentially. On the basis of the geometric relation between the bulk correlation path and distance along the outer edge boundary, we find that scaling dimensions for the boundary correlation function can be well explained by the combination of the bulk correlation length and background curvatures inherent to the hyperbolic lattice. We also investigate the cutoff effect of the bond dimension in CTMRG, revealing that the long-distance behavior of the boundary spin correlation is accurately described even with a small bond dimension. In contrast, the sort-distance behavior rapidly loses its accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14689v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kouichi Okunishi, Tomotoshi Nishino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covariant currents and a thermodynamic uncertainty relation on curved manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A framework for defining stochastic currents associated with diffusion processes on curved Riemannian manifolds is presented. This is achieved by introducing an overdamped Stratonovich-Langevin equation that remains fully covariant under non-linear transformations of state variables. The approach leads to a covariant extension of the thermodynamic uncertainty relation, describing a trade-off between the total entropy production rate and thermodynamic precision associated with short-time currents in curved spaces and arbitrary coordinate systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15405v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry J. D. Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New renormalization group study of the 3-state Potts model and related statistical models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15497v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The critical behavior of three-state statistical models invariant under the full symmetry group $S_3$ and its dependence on space dimension have been a matter of interest and debate. In particular, the phase transition of the 3-state Potts model in three dimensions is believed to be of the first order, without a definitive proof of absence of scale invariance in three-dimensional field theory with $S_3$ symmetry. This scale invariance should appear as a non-trivial fixed point of the renormalization group, which has not been found. Our new search, with the non-perturbative renormalization group, finds such a fixed point, as a bifurcation from the trivial fixed point at the critical space dimension $d=10/3$, which extends continuously to $d=3$. It does not correspond to a second-order phase transition of the 3-state Potts model, but is interesting in its own right. In particular, it shows how the $\varepsilon$-expansion can fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15497v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Gaite</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kardar-Parisi-Zhang universality class in the synchronization of oscillator lattices with time-dependent noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Systems of oscillators subject to time-dependent noise typically achieve synchronization for long times when their mutual coupling is sufficiently strong. The dynamical process whereby synchronization is reached can be thought of as a growth process in which an interface formed by the local phase field gradually roughens and eventually saturates. Such a process is here shown to display the generic scale invariance of the one-dimensional Kardar-Parisi-Zhang universality class, including a Tracy-Widom probability distribution for phase fluctuations around their mean. This is revealed by numerical explorations of a variety of oscillator systems: rings of generic phase oscillators and rings of paradigmatic limit-cycle oscillators, like Stuart-Landau and van der Pol. It also agrees with analytical expectations derived under conditions of strong mutual coupling. The nonequilibrium critical behavior that we find is robust and transcends the details of the oscillators considered. Hence, it may well be accessible to experimental ensembles of oscillators in the presence of e.g. thermal noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15634v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Gutierrez, Rodolfo Cuerno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal-work protocols for inertial particles in non-harmonic traps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The progress of miniaturized technology allows controlling physical systems at nanoscale with remarkable precision in regimes where thermal fluctuations are non-negligible. Experimental advancements have sparked interest in control problems in stochastic thermodynamics, typically concerning a time-dependent potential applied to a nanoparticle to reach a target stationary state in a given time with minimal energy cost. We study this problem for a particle subject to thermal fluctuations in a regime that takes into account the effects of inertia, and, building on the results of [1], provide a numerical method to find optimal controls even for non-Gaussian initial and final conditions corresponding to non-harmonic confinements. We show that the momentum mean tends to a constant value along the trajectory except at the boundary and the evolution of the variance is non-trivial. Our results also support that the lower bound on the optimal entropy production computed from the overdamped case is tight in the adiabatic limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15678v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Sanders, Marco Baldovin, Paolo Muratore-Ginanneschi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selection pressure/Noise driven cooperative behaviour in the thermodynamic limit of repeated games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider the scenario where an infinite number of players (i.e., the \textit{thermodynamic} limit) find themselves in a Prisoner's dilemma type situation, in a \textit{repeated} setting. Is it reasonable to anticipate that, in these circumstances, cooperation will emerge? This paper addresses this question by examining the emergence of cooperative behaviour, in the presence of \textit{noise} (or, under \textit{selection pressure}), in repeated Prisoner's Dilemma games, involving strategies such as \textit{Tit-for-Tat}, \textit{Always Defect}, \textit{GRIM}, \textit{Win-Stay, Lose-Shift}, and others. To analyze these games, we employ a numerical Agent-Based Model (ABM) and compare it with the analytical Nash Equilibrium Mapping (NEM) technique, both based on the \textit{1D}-Ising chain. We use \textit{game magnetization} as an indicator of cooperative behaviour. A significant finding is that for some repeated games, a discontinuity in the game magnetization indicates a \textit{first}-order \textit{selection pressure/noise}-driven phase transition. The phase transition is particular to strategies where players do not severely punish a single defection. We also observe that in these particular cases, the phase transition critically depends on the number of \textit{rounds} the game is played in the thermodynamic limit. For all five games, we find that both ABM and NEM, in conjunction with game magnetization, provide crucial inputs on how cooperative behaviour can emerge in an infinite-player repeated Prisoner's dilemma game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15801v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajdeep Tah, Colin Benjamin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal scaling solution for a rigidity transition: renormalization group flows near the upper critical dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14586v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rigidity transitions induced by the formation of system-spanning disordered rigid clusters, like the jamming transition, can be well-described in most physically relevant dimensions by mean-field theories. However, we lack a theoretical description of these kinds of rigidity transitions that can detect an upper critical dimension below which mean-field theory fails and predict corrections to the theory in and below this upper critical dimension. Towards that end, we show that the critical exponents for a continuous isotropic rigidity transition predicted by a simple dynamical effective medium theory (the Coherent Potential Approximation, CPA) are not mean-field-like, dimension-independent quantities. Instead, we find that the theory has an upper critical dimension $d_{u}=2$, in which there are the usual logarithmic corrections and below which the critical exponents are modified. We recapitulate Ken Wilson's phenomenology of the $(4-\epsilon)$-dimensional Ising model, but with the upper critical dimension reduced to $2$. We interpret this using normal form theory as a transcritical bifurcation in the RG flows, and posit their explicit forms, incorporating a dangerously irrelevant variable becoming marginal in $d=2$. We also derive universal scaling functions from the CPA sufficient to predict all linear response in randomly diluted isotropic elastic systems. These results indicate the types of corrections one expects to disordered rigidity transitions in $2$ dimensions and provide a pathway to understanding the critical phenomena in such systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14586v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen J. Thornton, Danilo B. Liarte, Itai Cohen, James P. Sethna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong-Coupling Extrapolation of Gell-Mann--Low Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14891v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gell-Mann-Low functions can be calculated by means of perturbation theory and expressed as truncated series in powers of asymptotically small coupling parameters. However, it is necessary to know there behavior at finite values of the parameter and, moreover, their behavior at asymptotically large coupling parameters is also important. The problem of extrapolation of weak-coupling expansions to the region of finite and even infinite coupling parameters is considered. A method is suggested allowing for such an extrapolation. The basics of the method are described and illustrations of its applications are given for the examples where its accuracy and convergence can be checked. It is shown that in some cases the method allows for the exact reconstruction of the whole functions from their weak-coupling asymptotic expansions. Gell-Mann-Low functions in multicomponent field theory, quantum electrodynamics, and quantum chromodynamics are extrapolated to their strong-coupling limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14891v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Part. Nucl. 55 (2024) 1026--1032</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Yukalov, E. P. Yukalova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binding and dimerization control phase separation in a compartment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15179v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Biological cells exhibit a hierarchical spatial organization, where various compartments harbor condensates that form by phase separation. Cells can control the emergence of these condensates by affecting compartment size, the amount of the involved molecules, and their physical interactions. While physical interactions directly affect compartment binding and phase separation, they can also cause oligomerization, which has been suggested as a control mechanism. Analyzing an equilibrium model, we illustrate that oligomerization amplifies compartment binding and phase separation, which reinforce each other. This nonlinear interplay can also induce multistability, which provides additional potential for control. Our work forms the basis for deriving thermodynamically consistent kinetic models to understand how biological cells can regulate phase separation in their compartments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15179v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Rossetto, Gerrit Wellecke, David Zwicker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic Information Dynamics: The Landauer Principle and Cosmological Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15231v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the information loss at the cosmological apparent horizon in an expanding universe has a direct correspondence with the Landauer principle of information dynamics. We show that the Landauer limit is satisfied in this case, which implies that the information erasure at the cosmological apparent horizon happens in the most efficient way possible. We also show that our results hold for extensions of the standard entropy formulations. This is the first work which directly provides a correspondence between information dynamics and expanding cosmic horizons, and we discuss several interesting implications of this result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15231v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oem Trivedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement in quenched extended Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model with anomalous dynamical quantum phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15331v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Research on topological models unveils fascinating physics, especially in the realm of dynamical quantum phase transitions (DQPTs). However, the understanding of entanglement structures and properties near DQPT in models with longer-range hoppings is far from complete. In this work, we study DQPTs in the quenched extended Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) model. Anomalous DQPTs, where the number of critical momenta exceeds the winding number differences between the pre-quench and post-quench phases, are observed. We find that the entanglement exhibits local maximum (minimum) around the anomalous DQPTs, in line with the level crossings (separations) around the middle of the correlation matrix spectrum. We further categorize the phases in the equilibrium model into two classes and distinctive features in the time evolution of the entanglement involving quenches within and across the two classes are identified. The findings pave the way to a better understanding of topological models with longer-range hoppings in the out-of-equilibrium regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15331v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheuk Yiu Wong, Tsz Hin Hui, P. D. Sacramento, Wing Chi Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-repellent branching random walk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15533v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a discrete-time binary branching random walk with independent standard normal increments subject to a penalty $\b$ for every pair of particles that get within distance $\e$ of each other at any time. We give a precise description of the most likely configurations of the particles under this law for $N$ large and $\b,\e$ fixed. Particles spread out over a distance $2^{2N/3}$, essentially in finite time, and subsequently arrange themselves so that at time $2N/3$ they cover a grid of width $\e$ with one particle per site. After time $2N/3$, the bulk of the particles and their descendants do not move anymore, while the particles in a boundary layer of width $2^{N/3}$ form a ``staircase" to the particles in the bulk. At time $N$, each site in the boundary layer is occupied by $2^{N/3}$ particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15533v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Bovier, Lisa Hartung, Frank den Hollander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic parameter optimization analysis of dynamical quantum critical phenomena in long-range transverse-field Ising chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.14121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.14121v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quantum phase transition of the one-dimensional long-range transverse-field Ising model is explored by combining the quantum Monte Carlo method and stochastic parameter optimization, specifically achieved by tuning correlation ratios so that space and imaginary time are isotropic. In our simulations, the simulator automatically determines the parameters to sample from, even without prior knowledge of the critical point and universality class. The leading order finite-size corrections are eliminated by comparing two systems with different sizes; this procedure is also performed automatically. Varying the decay exponent of the long-range interaction, $\sigma$, we investigate $\sigma$-dependence of the dynamical exponent and the other critical exponents precisely in the mean-field, non-universal, and two-dimensional classical Ising universality regimes. We successfully determine the universality boundary between the latter two as $\sigma = 7/4$ based on the dynamical exponent and settle a long-standing dispute on the location of the universality boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.14121v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sora Shiratani, Synge Todo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On relativistic thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.00354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.00354v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: 'Relativistic thermodynamics' should be understood not as a generalization of a non-relativistic theory but as an application of a general thermodynamic framework, neutral as to spacetime setting and allowing arbitrary conserved quantities, to the specific case of relativity. That framework gives an unambiguous result as to the thermodynamics of relativistically moving systems (an answer coinciding with Einstein's, and Planck's, original results.) Thermodynamic temperature is unambiguously defined as rate of change of energy with entropy at constant momentum; that said, its operational significance is limited and other measures of energy/entropy covariance, which incorporate momentum transfer, are often more useful.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.00354v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Wallace</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Price of information in games of chance: a statistical physics approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17251v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Information in the form of data, which can be stored and transferred between users, can be viewed as an intangible commodity, which can be traded in exchange for money. Determining the fair price at which a string of data should be traded is an important and open problem in many settings. In this work we develop a statistical physics framework that allows to determine analytically the fair price of information exchanged between players in a game of chance. For definiteness, we consider a game where $N$ players bet on the binary outcome of a stochastic process and share the entry fees pot if successful. We assume that one player holds information about past outcomes of the game, which they may either use exclusively to improve their betting strategy or offer to sell to another player. We find a sharp transition as the number of players $N$ is tuned across a critical value, between a phase where the transaction is always profitable for the seller and one where it may not be. In both phases, different regimes are possible, depending on the "quality" of information being put up for sale: we observe symbiotic regimes, where both parties collude effectively to rig the game in their favor, competitive regimes, where the transaction is unappealing to the data holder as it overly favors a competitor for scarce resources, and even prey-predator regimes, where an exploitative data holder could be giving away bad-quality data to undercut a competitor. Our analytical framework can be generalized to more complex settings and constitutes a flexible tool to address the rich and timely problem of pricing information in games of chance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17251v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Gamberi, Alessia Annibale, Pierpaolo Vivo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-reversible Monte Carlo: an example of 'true' self-repelling motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.19494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.19494v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We link the large-scale dynamics of non-reversible Monte Carlo algorithms as well as a lifted TASEP to an exactly soluble model of self-repelling motion. We present arguments for the connection between the problems and perform simulations, where we show that the empirical distribution functions generated from Monte Carlo are well described by the analytic solution of self-repelling motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.19494v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1209/0295-5075/ad64ff</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Europhysics Letters (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. C. Maggs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-file dynamics with general charge measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14378v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study charge fluctuations in single-file dynamics with general charge measures. The exact finite-time distribution of charge fluctuations is obtained in terms of a dressing transformation acting on the finite-time distribution of particle fluctuations. The transformation is mapped to a simple substitution rule for corresponding full-counting statistics. By taking the asymptotics of the dressing transformation we analyze typical and large scale charge fluctuations. Typical charge fluctuations in equilibrium states with vanishing mean charge are anomalous while large charge fluctuations undergo first and second order dynamical phase transitions out of equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14378v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\v{Z}iga Krajnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering nonequilibrium from unresolved events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00837v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Closely related to the laws of thermodynamics, the detection and quantification of disequilibria are crucial in unraveling the complexities of nature, particularly those beneath observable layers. Theoretical developments in nonequilibrium thermodynamics employ coarse-graining methods to consider a diversity of partial information scenarios that mimic experimental limitations, allowing the inference of properties such as the entropy production rate. A ubiquitous but rather unexplored scenario involves observing events that can possibly arise from many transitions in the underlying Markov process--which we dub $\textit{multifilar events}$--as in the cases of exchanges measured at particle reservoirs, hidden Markov models, mixed chemical and mechanical transformations in biological function, composite systems, and more. We relax one of the main assumptions in a previously developed framework, based on first-passage problems, to assess the non-Markovian statistics of mutifilar events. By using the asymmetry of event distributions and their waiting-times, we put forward model-free tools to detect nonequilibrium behavior and estimate entropy production, while discussing their suitability for different classes of systems and regimes where they provide no new information, evidence of nonequilibrium, a lower bound for entropy production, or even its exact value. The results are illustrated in reference models through analytics and numerics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00837v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro E. Harunari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time evolution of the Boltzmann entropy for a nonequilibrium dilute gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07519v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the time evolution of the Boltzmann entropy of a dilute gas of N particles, N&gt;&gt;1, as it undergoes a free expansion doubling its volume. The microstate of the system, a point in the 4N dimensional phase space, changes in time via Hamiltonian dynamics. Its entropy, at any time $t$, is given by the logarithm of the phase space volume of all the microstates giving rise to its macrostate at time $t$. The macrostates that we consider are defined by coarse graining the one-particle phase space into cells $\Delta_\alpha$. The initial and final macrostates of the system are equilibrium states in volumes $V$ and $2V$, with the same energy $E$ and particle number $N$. Their entropy per particle is given, for sufficiently large systems, by the thermodynamic entropy as a function of the particle and energy density, whose leading term is independent of the size of the $\Delta_\alpha$. The intermediate (non-equilibrium) entropy does however depend on the size of the cells $\Delta_\alpha$. Its change with time is due to (i) dispersal in physical space from free motion and to (ii) the collisions between particles which change their velocities. The former depends strongly on the size of the velocity coarse graining $\Delta v$: it produces entropy at a rate proportional to $\Delta v$. This dependence is investigated numerically and analytically for a dilute two-dimensional gas of hard discs. It becomes significant when the mean free path between collisions is of the same order or larger than the length scale of the initial spatial inhomogeneity. In the opposite limit, the rate of entropy production is essentially independent of $\Delta v$ and is given by the Boltzmann equation for the limit $\Delta v\rightarrow 0$. We show that when both processes are active the time dependence of the entropy has a scaling form involving the ratio of the rates of its production by the two processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07519v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. L. Garrido, S. Goldstein, D. A. Huse, J. L. Lebowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden zero modes and topology of multiband non-Hermitian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09728v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a finite one-dimensional non-Hermitian system, the number of zero modes does not necessarily reflect the topology of the system. This is known as the breakdown of the bulk-boundary correspondence and has lead to misconceptions about the topological protection of edge modes in such systems. Here we show why this breakdown does occur and that it typically results in hidden zero modes, extremely long-lived zero energy excitations, which are only revealed when considering the singular value instead of the eigenvalue spectrum. We point out, furthermore, that in a finite multiband non-Hermitian system with Hamiltonian $H$, one needs to consider also the reflected Hamiltonian $\tilde H$, which is in general distinct from the adjoint $H^\dagger$, to properly relate the number of protected zeroes to the winding number of $H$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09728v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Monkman, J. Sirker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speed-accuracy trade-off for the diffusion models: Wisdom from nonequilibrium thermodynamics and optimal transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04495v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss a connection between a generative model, called the diffusion model, and nonequilibrium thermodynamics for the Fokker-Planck equation, called stochastic thermodynamics. Based on the techniques of stochastic thermodynamics, we derive the speed-accuracy trade-off for the diffusion models, which is a trade-off relationship between the speed and accuracy of data generation in diffusion models. Our result implies that the entropy production rate in the forward process affects the errors in data generation. From a stochastic thermodynamic perspective, our results provide quantitative insight into how best to generate data in diffusion models. The optimal learning protocol is introduced by the conservative force in stochastic thermodynamics and the geodesic of space by the 2-Wasserstein distance in optimal transport theory. We numerically illustrate the validity of the speed-accuracy trade-off for the diffusion models with different noise schedules such as the cosine schedule, the conditional optimal transport, and the optimal transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04495v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kotaro Ikeda, Tomoya Uda, Daisuke Okanohara, Sosuke Ito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A theorem on extensive ground state entropy and some related models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06236v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The physics of the paradigmatic one-dimensional transverse field quantum Ising model $H= J \sum_{\langle i,j \rangle} \sigma^x_i \sigma^x_j + h \sum_i \sigma^z_i$ is well-known. Instead, let us imagine "applying" the transverse field via a transverse Ising coupling of the spins to partner auxiliary spins, i.e. $H= J_x \sum_{\langle i,j \rangle} \sigma^x_i \sigma^x_j + J_z \sum_i \sigma^z_i \sigma^z_{\text{partner of }i}$. If each spin of the chain has a unique auxiliary partner, then the theorem states that the resultant eigenspectrum is still the same as that of the quantum Ising model with $\frac{h}{J} = \frac{J_z}{J_x}$ and the degeneracy of the entire spectrum is $2^{\text{number of auxiliary spins}}$. This follows from the existence of extensively large and mutually anticommuting sets of conserved quantities for $H$. We can interpret this as the auxiliary spins remaining paramagnetic down to zero temperature with an extensive ground state degeneracy. This is lost upon the loss of the unique partner condition for the full spin chain. Other cases where such extensive degeneracy survives or gets lost are also discussed. Thus this theorem forms the basis for an exact statement on the existence of extensive ground state entropy in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06236v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumiran Pujari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel translationally invariant supersymmetric chain with inverse-square interactions: partition function, thermodynamics and criticality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13827v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel family of translationally-invariant su$(m|n)$ supersymmetric spin chains with long-range interaction not directly associated to a root system. We study the symmetries of these models, establishing in particular the existence of a boson-fermion duality characteristic of this type of systems. Taking advantage of the relation of the new chains with an associated many-body supersymmetric spin dynamical model, we are able to compute their partition function in closed form for all values of $m$ and $n$ and for an arbitrary number of spins. When both $m$ and $n$ are even, we show that the partition function factorizes as the product of the partition functions of two supersymmetric Haldane-Shastry spin chains, which in turn leads to a simple expression for the thermodynamic free energy per spin in terms of the Perron eigenvalue of a suitable transfer matrix. We use this expression to study the thermodynamics of a large class of these chains, showing in particular that the specific heat presents a single Schottky peak at approximately the same temperature as a suitable $k$-level model. We also analyze the critical behavior of the new chains, and in particular the ground state degeneracy and the existence of low energy excitations with a linear energy-momentum dispersion relation. In this way we are able to show that the only possible critical chains are the ones with $m=0,1,2$. In addition, using the explicit formula for the partition function we are able to establish the criticality of the su$(0|n)$ and su$(2|n)$ chains with even $n$, and to evaluate the central charge of their associated conformal field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13827v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bireswar Basu-Mallick, Federico Finkel, Artemio Gonz\'alez-L\'opez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boltzmann machine learning and regularization methods for inferring evolutionary fields and couplings from a multiple sequence alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.05006</link>
      <description>arXiv:1909.05006v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The inverse Potts problem to infer a Boltzmann distribution for homologous protein sequences from their single-site and pairwise amino acid frequencies recently attracts a great deal of attention in the studies of protein structure and evolution. We study regularization and learning methods and how to tune regularization parameters to correctly infer interactions in Boltzmann machine learning. Using $L_2$ regularization for fields, group $L_1$ for couplings is shown to be very effective for sparse couplings in comparison with $L_2$ and $L_1$. Two regularization parameters are tuned to yield equal values for both the sample and ensemble averages of evolutionary energy. Both averages smoothly change and converge, but their learning profiles are very different between learning methods. The Adam method is modified to make stepsize proportional to the gradient for sparse couplings. It is shown by first inferring interactions from protein sequences and then from Monte Carlo samples that the fields and couplings can be well recovered, but that recovering the pairwise correlations in the resolution of a total energy is harder for the natural proteins than for the protein-like sequences. Selective temperature for folding/structural constrains in protein evolution is also estimated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1909.05006v5</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TCBB.2020.2993232</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE/ACM Transactions on Computational Biology and Bioinformatics, 2022 Jan-Feb;19(1):328-342</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sanzo Miyazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle exchange statistics beyond fermions and bosons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.05203v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is commonly believed that there are only two types of particle exchange statistics in quantum mechanics, fermions and bosons, with the exception of anyons in two dimension. In principle, a second exception known as parastatistics, which extends outside of two dimensions, has been considered but was believed to be physically equivalent to fermions and bosons. In this paper we show that nontrivial parastatistics inequivalent to either fermions or bosons can exist in physical systems. These new types of identical particles obey generalized exclusion principles, leading to exotic free-particle thermodynamics distinct from any system of free fermions and bosons. We formulate our theory by developing a second quantization of paraparticles, which naturally includes exactly solvable non-interacting theories, and incorporates physical constraints such as locality. We then construct a family of exactly solvable quantum spin models in one and two dimensions where free paraparticles emerge as quasiparticle excitations, and their exchange statistics can be physically observed and is notably distinct from fermions and bosons. This demonstrates the possibility of a new type of quasiparticle in condensed matter systems, and, more speculatively, the potential for previously unconsidered types of elementary particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.05203v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Wang, Kaden R. A. Hazzard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Interacting Bosons on the Sawtooth Lattice with a Flat Band</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03979v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum many-body systems are expected to relax to a thermal state over time, with some exceptions such as systems with atypical eigenstates. In this study, we investigate the effect of the existence of spatially localized eigenstates on the relaxation dynamics of interacting bosons loaded into a one-dimensional sawtooth lattice, which exhibits a flat band in the single-particle spectrum by tuning the hopping rates. Using the time-evolving block decimation algorithm, we simulate the time evolution of the local density profile based on the Bose-Hubbard model with different initial conditions. Our results show the presence of the flat band leads to a significant slowing down of relaxation for weak interactions. Even for strong interaction, when the initial state includes an isolated localized single-particle eigenstate in the superposition, remnants of the initial bias in the density profile persist for a long time. This particular relaxation dynamics can be tested using ultracold atoms in optical lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03979v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.93.074004</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of the Physical Society of Japan 93, 074004 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ko Gondaira, Nobuo Furukawa, Daisuke Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broken detailed balance and entropy production in directed networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.19157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.19157v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The structure of a complex network plays a crucial role in determining its dynamical properties. In this work, we show that the the degree to which a network is directed and hierarchically organised is closely associated with the degree to which its dynamics break detailed balance and produce entropy. We consider a range of dynamical processes and show how different directed network features affect their entropy production rate. We begin with an analytical treatment of a 2-node network followed by numerical simulations of synthetic networks using the preferential attachment and Erd\"os-Renyi algorithms. Next, we analyse a collection of 97 empirical networks to determine the effect of complex real-world topologies. Finally, we present a simple method for inferring broken detailed balance and directed network structure from multivariate time-series and apply our method to identify non-equilibrium dynamics and hierarchical organisation in both human neuroimaging and financial time-series. Overall, our results shed light on the consequences of directed network structure on non-equilibrium dynamics and highlight the importance and ubiquity of hierarchical organisation and non-equilibrium dynamics in real-world systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.19157v4</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ram\'on Nartallo-Kaluarachchi, Malbor Asllani, Gustavo Deco, Morten L. Kringelbach, Alain Goriely, Renaud Lambiotte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computer-Based Verification of Quantum Thermodynamic Uncertainty Relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.19293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.19293v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum thermodynamic uncertainty relations establish the fundamental trade-off between precision and thermodynamic costs, yet their empirical verification is scarce. To extend the range of real-world tests, we present an approach that utilizes a noisy quantum computer for verifying a general quantum thermodynamic uncertainty relation. We employ a three-fold methodology to tackle the limitations of current quantum processors: generalizing a thermodynamic uncertainty relation to arbitrary observables under completely positive trace-preserving maps, proposing a method to measure the thermodynamic cost (survival activity) in the weak coupling regime, and reducing the required circuit depth by exploiting the properties of our thermodynamic uncertainty relation. We apply our bound to a quantum time correlator measurement protocol on IBM's cloud-based quantum processor. The empirical results show that our bound tightly constrains precision, with the relative variance approaching the theoretical limit within a single order of magnitude. Furthermore, our approach enables the saturation of our thermodynamic uncertainty relation by constructing the optimal observable that requires entangled measurements. This study highlights the potential and limitations of noisy quantum computers for demonstrating quantum thermodynamic trade-offs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.19293v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nobumasa Ishida, Yoshihiko Hasegawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On bond anisotropy for the ising model through the geometry of numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00662v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We associate to each unit volume lattice of $\R^d$ the Ising model with bond variables equal to the inverse successive minima of that lattice. This induces the notion of a critical temperature for a random lattice for which integrability exponents are proven.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00662v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ren\'e R\"uhr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of network structure and talent configuration on wealth dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04175v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The economic success of individuals is often determined by a combination of talent, luck, and assistance from others. We introduce a new agent-based model that simultaneously considers talent, luck, and social interaction. This model allows us to explore how network structure (how agents interact) and talent distribution among agents affect the dynamics of capital accumulation through analytical and numerical methods. We identify a phenomenon as ``talent configuration effect", which refers to the influence of how talent is allocated to individuals (nodes) in the network. We analyze this effect through two key properties: talent assortativity (TA) and talent-degree correlation (TD). In particular, we focus on three economic indicators: growth rate ($n_{\rm rate}$), Gini coefficient (inequality: $n_{\rm Gini}$), and meritocratic fairness ($n_{LT}$). This investigation helps us understand the interplay between talent configuration and network structure on capital dynamics. We find that, in the short term, positive correlations exist between TA and TD for all three economic indicators. Furthermore, the dominant factor influencing capital dynamics depends on the network topology. In scale-free networks, TD has a stronger influence on the economic indices than TA. Conversely, in lattice-like networks, TA plays a more significant role. Our findings address that high socioeconomic homophily can create a dilemma between growth and equality, and that hub monopolization by few highly talented agents makes economic growth strongly dependent on their performances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04175v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaeseok Hur, Meesoon Ha, Hawoong Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalised Hydrodynamics of $\mathrm{T\bar{T}}$-Deformed Integrable Quantum Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06564v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we evaluate the averages of conserved densities and currents associated to charges of generic spin in (1+1)-dimensional massive integrable Quantum Field Theories perturbed by the irrelevant $\mathrm{T\bar{T}}$ operator. By making use of the Thermodynamic Bethe Ansatz approach and of the theory of Generalised Hydrodynamics, we study the non-equilibrium steady state averages of conserved densities and currents in a partitioning protocol. We show that in particular limits, averages can be evaluated exactly in terms of quantities known from the unperturbed theory. In the massless limit we recover known results for the energy and momentum currents and generalise those to any higher spin conserved quantities. We extend some of our results to perturbations of the generalised $\mathrm{T\bar{T}}$ type. For the massive free fermion theory, we find an analytic expression for the effective inverse temperature after at $\mathrm{T\bar{T}}$ perturbation in terms of the bare inverse temperature by making use of Lambert's $W$ function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06564v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Travaglino, Michele Mazzoni, Olalla A. Castro-Alvaredo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoinduced non-reciprocal magnetism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05957v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Out of equilibrium, the action-reaction symmetry of the interactions is often broken, leading to the emergence of various collective phenomena with no equilibrium counterparts. Although ubiquitous in classical active systems, implementing such non-reciprocal interactions in solid-state systems has remained challenging, as the known quantum schemes require precise control over the system on a single-site level. Here, we propose a novel dissipation-engineering protocol to induce non-reciprocal interactions in solid-state platforms with light, which we expect to be achievable with state-of-the-art experimental techniques. Focusing on magnetic metals for concreteness, we show microscopically that a light injection that introduces the decay channel to a virtually excited state gives rise to non-reciprocal interactions between localized spins. One can even realize a situation where spin A tries to align with spin B but the B tries the opposite, resulting in a chase-and-runaway dynamics. Applying our scheme to layered ferromagnets, we show that a non-reciprocal phase transition from a static to a many-body time-dependent chiral phase emerges. Our work paves the way to bring solid-state systems to the realm of non-reciprocal science, providing yet another possibility to control quantum matter with light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05957v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryo Hanai, Daiki Ootsuki, Rina Tazai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling limit of the ground state Bethe roots for the inhomogeneous XXZ spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12102v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is known that for the Heisenberg XXZ spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ chain in the critical regime, the scaling limit of the vacuum Bethe roots yields an infinite set of numbers that coincide with the energy spectrum of the quantum mechanical 3D anharmonic oscillator. The discovery of this curious relation, among others, gave rise to the approach referred to as the ODE/IQFT (or ODE/IM) correspondence. Here we consider a multiparametric generalization of the Heisenberg spin chain, which is associated with the inhomogeneous six-vertex model. When quasi-periodic boundary conditions are imposed the lattice system may be explored within the Bethe Ansatz technique. We argue that for the critical spin chain, with a properly formulated scaling limit, the scaled Bethe roots for the ground state are described by second order differential equations, which are multi-parametric generalizations of the Schr\"{o}dinger equation for the anharmonic oscillator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12102v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2024.116624</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl. Phys. B 1006 (2024) 116624</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sascha Gehrmann, Gleb A. Kotousov, Sergei L. Lukyanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity Scaling of Liquid Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19858v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: According to excess-entropy scaling, dynamic properties of liquids like viscosity and diffusion coefficient are determined by the entropy. This link between dynamics and thermodynamics is increasingly studied and of interest also for industrial applications, but hampered by the challenge of calculating entropy efficiently. Utilizing the fact that entropy is basically the Kolmogorov complexity, which can be estimated from optimal compression algorithms [Avinery et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 123, 178102 (2019); Martiniani et al., Phys. Rev. X 9, 011031 (2019)], we here demonstrate that the diffusion coefficients of four simple liquids follow a quasiuniversal exponential function of the optimal compression length of a single equilibrium configuration. We conclude that "complexity scaling" has the potential to become a useful tool for estimating dynamic properties of any liquid from a single configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19858v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian M. Douglass, Jeppe C. Dyre, Lorenzo Costigliola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clustering of conditional mutual information and quantum Markov structure at arbitrary temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05835v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent investigations have unveiled exotic quantum phases that elude characterization by simple bipartite correlation functions. In these phases, long-range entanglement arising from tripartite correlations plays a central role. Consequently, the study of multipartite correlations has become a focal point in modern physics. In these, Conditional Mutual Information (CMI) is one of the most well-established information-theoretic measures, adept at encapsulating the essence of various exotic phases, including topologically ordered ones. Within the realm of quantum many-body physics, it has been a long-sought goal to establish a quantum analog to the Hammersley-Clifford theorem that bridges the two concepts of the Gibbs state and the Markov network. This theorem posits that the correlation length of CMI remains short-range across all thermal equilibrium quantum phases. In this work, we demonstrate that CMI exhibits exponential decay concerning distance, with its correlation length increasing polynomially with the inverse temperature. While this clustering theorem has previously been established for high temperatures devoid of thermal phase transitions, it has remained elusive at low temperatures, where genuine long-range entanglement is corroborated to exist by the quantum topological order. Our findings unveil that, even at low temperatures, a broad class of tripartite entanglement cannot manifest in the long-range regime. To achieve the proof, we establish a comprehensive formalism for analyzing the locality of effective Hamiltonians on subsystems, commonly known as the `entanglement Hamiltonian' or `Hamiltonian of mean force.' As one outcome of our analyses, we enhance the prior clustering theorem concerning bipartite entanglement. In essence, this means that we investigate genuine bipartite entanglement that extends beyond the limitations of the Positive Partial Transpose (PPT) class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05835v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomotaka Kuwahara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of symmetry in the correlated orientational disordered phase of entropic crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09637v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The crystalline solids with lack of orientational ordering serve the purpose of studying the disordered systems with many fundamental applications in contemporary research. Despite the orientational disorder, the constituent particles sometime follow some conserved laws or correlation while maintaining the translational order depicted by the crystal structure. Such phase is called ``correlated orientational disordered'' phase in the crystal. Polyhedral particles in the presence of hard-core interaction provide a great opportunity to study the orientational order and disorder in entropy driven self-assembly. We report the computational evidence of the role of symmetry of the polyhedral particles and cubic crystalline structures exhibiting the correlated disordered phases, which are obtained from the simulations of single-component systems. The point groups of the particle and crystal structure appear to be directly connected with the existence of multiple unique orientations satisfying a few other orientational features. In this phase, the systems exhibit orientationally frozen states at sufficiently higher packing fractions and discrete orientational hopping at comparatively lower ones while all the signatures of the correlation are preserved. This symmetry relationship appears to control all the aspects of orientational correlation in the crystalline solids which might be useful to draw fundamental insights about the disordered phases with orientational correlation as well as designing the disorder in the crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09637v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumitava Kundu, Kaustav Chakraborty, Avisek Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Energy: Teleporting Current, Charge, and More</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12359v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As an homage to Quantum Energy Teleportation, we generalize the idea to arbitrary physical observables, not limited to energy, and prove a rigorous upper bound on the activated ("teleported") quantity. The essence of this protocol is a quantum feedback control with respect to the entangled ground state of a quantum many-body system. To demonstrate the concept, we explore a (1+1)-dimensional chiral Dirac system and execute the protocol for the electric current and charge. One of the most significant results is the creation of long-range correlations across the system after applying control operations only to one local site. Consequently but surprisingly, the induced charge susceptibility fully reconstructs the phase diagram, despite the model initially having no charge. Moreover, we find an activation of novel chiral dynamics induced by feedback control operations, which can be experimentally confirmed using trapped ions and neutral atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12359v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
