<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 02:56:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Reaction Rates in Quasiequilibrium States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-Maxwellian distributions are commonly observed across a wide range of systems and scales. While direct observations provide the strongest evidence for these distributions, they also manifest indirectly through their influence on processes and quantities that strongly depend on the energy distribution, such as reaction rates. In this paper, we investigate reaction rates in the general context of quasiequilibrium systems, which exhibit only local equilibrium. The hierarchical structure of these systems allows their statistical properties to be represented as a superposition of statistics, i.e., superstatistics. Focusing on the three universality classes of superstatistics--$\chi^2$, inverse-$\chi^2$, and log-normal--we examine how these nonequilibrium distributions influence reaction rates. We analyze, both analytically and numerically, reaction rates for processes involving tunneling phenomena, such as fusion, and identify conditions under which quasiequilibrium distributions outperform Maxwellian distributions in enhancing fusion reactivities. To provide a more detailed quantitative analysis, we further employ semi-empirical cross sections to evaluate the effect of these nonequilibrium distributions on ionization and recombination rates in a plasma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10407v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamel Ourabah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact solution of the three-dimensional (3D) Z2 lattice gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, the origin of nonlocal effects is inspected and the contributions of nontrivial topological structures to physical properties are investigated in details for both the 3D Ising model and the Z2 lattice gauge model. Then the exact solution for the 3D Z2 lattice gauge theory is derived by the duality between the two models. Several fundamental issues, such as dimensionality, duality, symmetry, manifold, degenerate states, are investigated for these many-body interacting spin systems. The connections with superfluid, superconductors, etc. are evaluated. Furthermore, physical significances and mathematical aspects of the 3D Z2 lattice gauge theory are discussed with respect to topology, geometry, and algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10412v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhidong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo Analysis of Boid Simulations with Obstacles: A Physics-Based Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Boids, developed by Craig W. Reynolds in 1986, is one of the earliest emergent models where the global pattern emerges from the interaction between many individuals within the local scale. In the original model, Boids follow three rules: separation, alignment, and cohesion; which allow them to move around and create a flock without intention in the empty environment. In the real world, however, the Boids' movement also faces obstacles preventing the flock's direction. In this project, I propose two new simple rules of the Boids model to represent the more realistic movement in nature and analyze the model from the physics perspective using the Monte Carlo method. From those results, the physics metrics related to the forming of the flocking phenomenon show that it is reasonable to explain why birds or fishes prefer to move in a flock, rather than sole movement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10420v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quoc Chuong Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Catene ideali con numero fissato di auto-intersezioni</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10485v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this thesis we study in detail the self-intersection properties of Random Walks. Although notoriously hard to tackle, these properties are crucially related to the excluded-volume effect and other central features of real polymers. Our main purpose will be to study ideal chains (Random Walks) on lattice where the ratio between the number of self-intersections and the total length is fixed to some number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10485v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Franchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localized fermions on the triangular lattice with Ising-like interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The model of localized fermions on the triangular lattice is analyzed in means of the Monte Carlo simulations in the grand canonical ensemble. The Hamiltonian of the system has a form of the extended Hubbard model (at the atomic limit) with nearest-neighbor Ising-like magnetic $J$ interactions and onsite Coulomb $U$ interactions. The model is investigated for both signs of $J$, arbitrary $U$ interaction and arbitrary chemical potential $\mu$ (or, equivalently, arbitrary particle concentration $n$). Based on the specific heat capacity and sublattice magnetization analyses, the phase diagrams of the model are determined. For ferromagnetic case ($J&lt;0$), the transition from the ordered phase (which is a standard ferromagnet and can be stable up to $k_{B}T/|J| \approx 0.61$) is found to be second-order (for sufficiently large temperatures $k_{B}T/|J| \gtrsim 0.2$) or first-order (for $-1&lt;U/|J|&lt;-0.65$ at the half-filling, i.e., $n=1$). In the case of $J&gt;0$, the ordered phase occurs in a range of $-1/2&lt;U/|J|&lt;0$ (for $n=1$), while for larger $U$ the state with short-range order is also found (also for $n \neq 1$). The ordered phase is characterized by an antiferromagnetic arrangement of magnetic moments in two sublattices forming the hexagonal lattice. The transition from this ordered phase, which is found also for $\mu \neq 0$ ($n \neq 1$) and $U/|J|&gt;-1/2$ is always second-order for any model parameters. The ordered phase for $J&gt;0$ can be stable up to $k_{B}T/|J| \approx 0.06$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10808v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lubom\'ira Regeciov\'a (Institute of Experimental Physics Slovak Academy of Sciences, Ko\v{s}ice, Slovakia), Konrad Jerzy Kapcia (Institute of Spintronics,Quantum Information, Faculty of Physics,Astronomy, Adam Mickiewicz University in Pozna\'n, Poland)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality in the tape-peeling trace</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11101v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spatiotemporal patterns, which are of interest in statistical physics and nonlinear dynamics, form on the tape-peeling trace. Recently, we have proposed a mathematical model to describe these pattern formation in the tape-peeling trace. In this paper, we further investigate the tape-peeling model from the perspective of its universality class. We confirm that our model belongs to the 1-dimensional directed percolation universality class. Furthermore, the experimental results from a previous study are re-analyzed, and it is suggested that the tape-peeling trace can also be classified within the 1-dimensional directed percolation universality class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11101v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keisuke Taga, Akihiko Toda, Yoshihiro Yamazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Langevin equation far from equilibrium: Riemann-Liouville fractional Brownian motion, spurious nonergodicity and aging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the fractional Langevin equation far from equilibrium (FLEFE) to describe stochastic dynamics which do not obey the fluctuation-dissipation theorem, unlike the conventional fractional Langevin equation (FLE). The solution of this equation is Riemann-Liouville fractional Brownian motion (RL-FBM), also known in the literature as FBM II. Spurious nonergodicity, stationarity, and aging properties of the solution are explored for all admissible values $\alpha&gt;1/2$ of the order $\alpha$ of the time-fractional Caputo derivative in the FLEFE. The increments of the process are asymptotically stationary. However when $1/2&lt;\alpha&lt;3/2$, the time-averaged mean-squared displacement (TAMSD) does not converge to the mean-squared displacement (MSD). Instead, it converges to the mean-squared increment (MSI) or structure function, leading to the phenomenon of spurious nonergodicity. When $\alpha\ge 3/2$, the increments of FLEFE motion are nonergodic, however the higher order increments are asymptotically ergodic. We also discuss the aging effect in the FLEFE by investigating the influence of an aging time $t_a$ on the mean-squared displacement, time-averaged mean-squared displacement and autocovariance function of the increments. We find that under strong aging conditions the process becomes ergodic, and the increments become stationary in the domain $1/2&lt;\alpha&lt;3/2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11559v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing Wei, Wei Wang, Yifa Tang, Ralf Metzler, Aleksei Chechkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emptiness Instanton in Quantum Polytropic Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11686v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The emptiness formation problem is addressed for a one-dimensional quantum polytropic gas characterized by an arbitrary polytropic index $\gamma$, which defines the equation of state $P \sim \rho^\gamma$, where $P$ is the pressure and $\rho$ is the density. The problem involves determining the probability of the spontaneous formation of an empty interval in the ground state of the gas. In the limit of a macroscopically large interval, this probability is dominated by an instanton configuration. By solving the hydrodynamic equations in imaginary time, we derive the analytic form of the emptiness instanton. This solution is expressed as an integral representation analogous to those used for correlation functions in Conformal Field Theory. Prominent features of the spatiotemporal profile of the instanton are obtained directly from this representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11686v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander G. Abanov, Dimitri M. Gangardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density of states in liquids: quadratic or linear, and what each means?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11734v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A lot has been said about the vibrational density of states (DoS) in liquids. A more recent discussion introduces contradictions with earlier results, and here I briefly review several pieces of evidence from modeling, experiments and theory showing this. I then show that the origin of contradictions often comes from misinterpreting the nature of excitations in liquids. Classic quadratic DoS corresponds to propagating (albeit damped) phonons as in solids and applies to any medium at low frequency, whereas the linear DoS comes from overdamped modes, localised particle motions. This has implications for interpreting simulations, experiments and a theory of liquids. I also introduce a new mechanism where the exponent of quadratic DoS reduces to close to 1 due to the asymmetry of the scattering intensity, reducing the effective phonon frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11734v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Brazhkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Model for a Piezoelectric Energy Harvester Driven by Broadband Vibrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an experimental and numerical study of a piezoelectric energy harvester driven by broadband vibrations. This device can extract power from random fluctuations and can be described by a stochastic model, based on an underdamped Langevin equation with white noise, which mimics the dynamics of the piezoelectric material. A crucial point in the modelisation is represented by the appropriate description of the coupled load circuit that is necessary to harvest electrical energy. We consider a linear load (resistance) and a nonlinear load (diode bridge rectifier connected to the parallel of a capacitance and a load resistance), and focus on the characteristic curve of the extracted power as a function of the load resistance, in order to estimate the optimal values of the parameters that maximise the collected energy. In both cases, we find good agreement between the numerical simulations of the theoretical model and the results obtained in experiments. In particular, we observe a non-monotonic behaviour of the characteristic curve which signals the presence of an optimal value for the load resistance at which the extracted power is maximised. We also address a more theoretical issue, related to the inference of the non-equilibrium features of the system from data: we show that the analysis of high-order correlation functions of the relevant variables, when in the presence of nonlinearities, can represent a simple and effective tool to check the irreversible dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11816v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/e26121097</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Entropy 26(12), 1097 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Angelo Sanfelice, Luigi Costanzo, Alessandro Lo Schiavo, Alessandro Sarracino, Massimo Vitelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Echo State network for coarsening dynamics of charge density waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An echo state network (ESN) is a type of reservoir computer that uses a recurrent neural network with a sparsely connected hidden layer. Compared with other recurrent neural networks, one great advantage of ESN is the simplicity of its training process. Yet, despite the seemingly restricted learnable parameters, ESN has been shown to successfully capture the spatial-temporal dynamics of complex patterns. Here we build an ESN to model the coarsening dynamics of charge-density waves (CDW) in a semi-classical Holstein model, which exhibits a checkerboard electron density modulation at half-filling stabilized by a commensurate lattice distortion. The inputs to the ESN are local CDW order-parameters in a finite neighborhood centered around a given site, while the output is the predicted CDW order of the center site at the next time step. Special care is taken in the design of couplings between hidden layer and input nodes to ensure lattice symmetries are properly incorporated into the ESN model. Since the model predictions depend only on CDW configurations of a finite domain, the ESN is scalable and transferrable in the sense that a model trained on dataset from a small system can be directly applied to dynamical simulations on larger lattices. Our work opens a new avenue for efficient dynamical modeling of pattern formations in functional electron materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11982v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clement Dinh, Yunhao Fan, Gia-Wei Chern</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Hamiltonian and orthogonal polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12021v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the entanglement Hamiltonian for free-fermion chains with a particular form of inhomogeneity. The hopping amplitudes and chemical potentials are chosen such that the single-particle eigenstates are related to discrete orthogonal polynomials of the Askey scheme. Due to the bispectral properties of these functions, one can construct an operator which commutes exactly with the entanglement Hamiltonian and corresponds to a linear or parabolic deformation of the physical one. We show that this deformation is interpreted as a local inverse temperature and can be obtained in the continuum limit via methods of conformal field theory. Using this prediction, the properly rescaled eigenvalues of the commuting operator are found to provide a very good approximation of the entanglement spectrum and entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12021v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre-Antoine Bernard, Riccarda Bonsignori, Viktor Eisler, Gilles Parez, Luc Vinet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sufficient conditions, lower bounds and trade-off relations for quantumness in Kirkwood-Dirac quasiprobability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08324v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kirkwood-Dirac (KD) quasiprobability is a quantum analog of classical phase space probability. It offers an informationally complete representation of quantum state wherein the quantumness associated with quantum noncommutativity manifests in its nonclassical values, i.e., the nonreal and/or negative values of the real part. This naturally raises a question: how does such form of quantumness comply with the uncertainty principle which also arise from quantum noncommutativity? Here, first, we obtain sufficient conditions for the KD quasiprobability defined relative to a pair of PVM (projection-valued measure) bases to have nonclassical values. Using these nonclassical values, we then introduce two quantities which capture the amount of KD quantumness in a quantum state relative to a single PVM basis. They are defined respectively as the nonreality, and the classicality which captures both the nonreality and negativity, of the associated KD quasiprobability over the PVM basis of interest, and another PVM basis, and maximized over all possible choices of the latter. We obtain their lower bounds, and derive trade-off relations respectively reminiscent of the Robertson and Robertson-Schr\"odinger uncertainty relations but with lower bounds maximized over the convex sets of Hermitian operators whose complete sets of eigenprojectors are given by the PVM bases. We discuss their measurement using weak value measurement and classical optimization, and suggest information theoretical and operational interpretations in terms of optimal estimation of the PVM basis and state disturbance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08324v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agung Budiyono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Centrality and Universality in Scale-Free Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel paradigm for modeling real-world scale-free networks, where the integration of new nodes is driven by the combined attractiveness of degree and betweenness centralities, the competition of which (expressed by a parameter $0\le p\le 1$) shapes the structure of the evolving network. We reveal the ability to seamlessly explore a vast landscape of scale-free networks, unlocking an entirely new class of complex networks that we call \textit{stars-with-filament} structure. Remarkably, the average degree $\bar k$ of these networks grows like $\log t$ to some power, where $t$ is time and the average shortest path length grows logarithmically with the system size for intermediate $p$ values, offering fresh insights into the structural dynamics of scale-free systems. Our approach is backed by a robust mean-field theory, which nicely captures the dynamics of $\bar{k}$. We further unveil a rich, $p$-dependent phase diagram, encompassing 47 real-world scale-free networks, shedding light on previously hidden patterns. This work opens exciting new avenues for understanding the universal properties of complex networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10406v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Adami, S. Emdadi-Mahdimahalleh, H. J. Herrmann, M. N. Najafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-Thermalization via Instantons near Dynamical Freezing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10498v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Periodically driven Floquet quantum many-body systems have revealed new insights into the rich interplay of thermalization, and growth of entanglement. The phenomenology of dynamical freezing, whereby a translationally invariant many-body system exhibits emergent conservation laws and a slow growth of entanglement entropy at certain fixed ratios of a drive amplitude and frequency, presents a novel paradigm for retaining memory of an initial state upto late times. Previous studies of dynamical freezing have largely been restricted to a high-frequency Floquet-Magnus expansion, and numerical exact diagonalization, which are unable to capture the slow approach to thermalization (or lack thereof) in a systematic fashion. By employing Floquet flow-renormalization, where the time-dependent part of the Hamiltonian is gradually decoupled from the effective Hamiltonian using a sequence of unitary transformations, we unveil the universal approach to dynamical freezing and beyond, at asymptotically late times. We analyze the fixed-point behavior associated with the flow-renormalization at and near freezing using both exact-diagonalization and tensor-network based methods, and contrast the results with conventional prethermal phenomenon. For a generic non-integrable spin Hamiltonian with a periodic cosine wave drive, the flow approaches an unstable fixed point with an approximate emergent symmetry. We observe that at freezing the thermalization timescales are delayed compared to away from freezing, and the flow trajectory undergoes a series of instanton events. Our numerical results are supported by analytical solutions to the flow equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10498v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Mukherjee, Haoyu Guo, Debanjan Chowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lanes and lattice structures in a repulsive model for self-propelled agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10577v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate a simple Vicsek-type rule-based model for self-propelled particles, where each particle orients itself antiparallel to the average orientation of particles within a defined neighborhood of radius $R$. The particle orientation is updated asynchronously and randomly across the system. In steady state, particles self-organize into clusters-despite the repulsive interaction-and form two interwoven hexagonal lattices moving in opposite directions chosen spontaneously. Increasing noise in the reorientation step reduces the laning effect, but the global crystalline order remains intact at sufficiently high densities. The mean-squared displacement exhibits super-diffusive growth $ \sim t^{3/2} $ in the transient phase, transitioning to ballistic motion $ \sim t^2 $ in the steady state in the high density and zero noise regime. With an increase in noise and/or decrease in density, the mean-squared displacement grows diffusively $ \sim t $. We observe a cutoff for the ratio $ \frac{R}{L} \sim 0.2-0.3 $, below which laning and crystallization is achieved, suggesting a local but non-microscopic sphere of influence is required to initiate laning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10577v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Bisht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology and Spectrum in Measurement-Induced Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11097v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Competition among repetitive measurements of noncommuting observables and unitary dynamics can give rise to a rich variety of entanglement phases. We here characterize topological phases in monitored quantum systems by their spectrum and many-body topological invariants. We analyze (1+1)-dimensional monitored circuits for Majorana fermions, which have topological and trivial area-law entangled phases and a critical phase with sub-volume-law entanglement, through the Lyapunov spectrum. We uncover the presence (absence) of edge-localized zero modes inside the bulk gap in the topological (trivial) area-law phase and a bulk gapless spectrum in the critical phase. Furthermore, by suitably exploiting the fermion parity with twisted measurement outcomes at the boundary, we construct a topological invariant that sharply distinguishes the two area-law phases and dynamically characterizes the critical phase. Our work thus paves the way to extend the bulk-edge correspondence for topological phases from equilibrium to monitored quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11097v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hisanori Oshima, Ken Mochizuki, Ryusuke Hamazaki, Yohei Fuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating through Economic Complexity: Phase Diagrams &amp; Parameter Sloppiness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11259v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We argue that establishing the phase diagram of Agent Based Models (ABM) is a crucial first step, together with a qualitative understanding of how collective phenomena come about, before any calibration or more quantitative predictions are attempted. Computer-aided *gedanken* experiments are by themselves of genuine value: if we are not able to make sense of emergent phenomena in a world in which we set all the rules, how can we expect to be successful in the real world? ABMs indeed often reveal the existence of Black Swans/Dark Corners i.e. discontinuity lines beyond which runaway instabilities appear, whereas most classical economic/finance models are blind to such scenarii. Testing for the overall robustness of the phase diagram against changes in heuristic rules is a way to ascertain the plausibility of such scenarii. Furthermore, exploring the phase diagrams of ABM in high dimensions should benefit enormously from the identification of ``stiff'' and ``sloppy'' directions in parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11259v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Philippe Bouchaud (Capital Fund Management,Acad\'emie des Sciences)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jordan-Wigner transformation constructed for spinful fermions at spin-1/2 in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11339v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently a Jordan-Wigner transformation was constructed for spinful fermions at S=1/2 spins in one dimension connecting the spin-1/2 operators to genuine spinful canonical Fermi operators. In the presented paper this exact transformation is generalized to two dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11339v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zsolt Gulacsi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure and Dynamic Evolution of Interfaces between Polymer Solutions and Gels and Polymer Interdiffusion: A Molecular Dynamics Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11346v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Letting free polymers diffuse from solution into a crosslinked polymer gel is often a crucial processing step in the synthesis of multiphase polymer-based gels, e.g., core-shell microgels. Here we use coarse-grained molecular dynamics simulations to obtain molecular insights into this process. We consider idealized situations where the gel is modeled as a regular polymer network with the topology of a diamond lattice, and all free polymers and strands have the same length and consist of the same type of monomer. After bringing the gel and the polymer solution into contact, two time regimes are observed: An initial compression of the gel caused by the osmotic pressure of the solution, followed by an expansion due to swelling. We characterize the time evolution of density profiles, the penetration of free polymers into the gel and the connection between the gel and solution phase. The interfacial structure locally equilibrates after roughly 100 chain relaxation times. At late times, the free chains inside the gel undergo a percolation transition if the polymer concentration in the gel exceeds a critical value, which is of the same order as the overlap concentration. The fluctuations of the interface can be described by a capillary wave model that accounts for the elasticity of the gel. Based on this, we extract the interfacial tension of the gel-solution interface. Interestingly, both the interfacial tension and the local interfacial width increase with increasing free polymer concentration - in contrast to liquid-liquid interfaces, where these two quantities are typically anticorrelated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11346v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.macromol.4c00459</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Macromolecules 2024 57 (11), 5545-5559</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jude Ann Vishnu, Torsten Gereon Linder, Sebastian Seiffert, Friederike Schmid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-induced phase transitions and critical phases in nonreciprocal non-Hermitian quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11623v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-Hermitian phenomena, such as exceptional points, non-Hermitian skin effects, and topologically nontrivial phases, have attracted continued attention. In this work, we reveal how interactions and nonreciprocal hopping could collectively influence the behavior of two interacting bosons on quasiperiodic lattices. Focusing on the Bose-Hubbard model with Aubry-Andr\'e-Harper quasiperiodic modulations and hopping asymmetry, we discover that the interaction could enlarge the localization transition point of the noninteracting system into a critical phase, in which localized doublons formed by bosonic pairs can coexist with delocalized states. Under the open boundary condition, the bosonic doublons could further show non-Hermitian skin effects, realizing doublon condensation at the edges, and their direction of skin-localization can be flexibly tuned by the hopping parameters. A framework is developed to characterize the spectral, localization, and topological transitions accompanying these phenomena. Our work advances the understanding of localization and topological phases in non-Hermitian systems, particularly in relation to multiparticle interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11623v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yalun Zhang, Longwen Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body dynamics with explicitly time-dependent neural quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11830v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulating the dynamics of many-body quantum systems is a significant challenge, especially in higher dimensions where entanglement grows rapidly. Neural quantum states (NQS) offer a promising tool for representing quantum wavefunctions, but their application to time evolution faces scaling challenges. We introduce the time-dependent neural quantum state (t-NQS), a novel approach incorporating explicit time dependence into the neural network ansatz. This framework optimizes a single, time-independent set of parameters to solve the time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation across an entire time interval. We detail an autoregressive, attention-based transformer architecture and techniques for extending the model's applicability. To benchmark and demonstrate our method, we simulate quench dynamics in the 2D transverse field Ising model and the time-dependent preparation of the 2D antiferromagnetic state in a Heisenberg model, demonstrating state of the art performance, scalability, and extrapolation to unseen intervals. These results establish t-NQS as a powerful framework for exploring quantum dynamics in strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11830v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anka Van de Walle, Markus Schmitt, Annabelle Bohrdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reentrant phase behavior in binary topological flocks with nonreciprocal alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a binary metric-free Vicsek model involving two species of self-propelled particles aligning with their Voronoi neighbors, focusing on a weakly nonreciprocal regime, where species $A$ aligns with both $A$ and $B$, but species $B$ does not align with either. Using agent-based simulations, we find that even with a small fraction of $B$ particles, the phase behavior of the system can be changed qualitatively, which becomes reentrant as a function of noise strength: traveling bands arise not only near the flocking transition, but also in the low-noise regime, separated in the phase diagram by a homogeneous polar liquid regime. We find that the ordered bands in the low-noise regime travel through an ordered background, in contrast to their metric counterparts. We develop a coarse-grained field theory, which can account for the reentrant phase behavior qualitatively, provided the higher-order angular modes are taken into consideration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11871v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian Tang, Yu Duan, Yu-qiang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic thermodynamic bounds on logical circuit operation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.00670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.00670v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using a thermodynamically consistent, mesoscopic model for modern complementary metal-oxide-semiconductor transistors, we study an array of logical circuits and explore how their function is constrained by recent thermodynamic uncertainty relations when operating near thermal energies. For a single NOT gate, we find operating direction-dependent dynamics, and a trade-off between dissipated heat and operation time certainty. For a memory storage device, we find an exponential relationship between the memory retention time and energy required to sustain that memory state. For a clock, we find that the certainty in the cycle time is maximized at biasing voltages near thermal energy, as is the trade-off between this certainty and the heat dissipated per cycle. We identify a control mechanism that can increase the cycle time certainty without an offsetting increase in heat dissipation by working at a resonance condition for the clock. These results provide a framework for assessing thermodynamic costs of realistic computing devices, allowing for circuits to be designed and controlled for thermodynamically optimal operation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.00670v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phillip Helms, Songela W. Chen, David T. Limmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analysis of the drying pattern of coffee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.12132v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we experimentally study the dried pattern droplets of coffee with and without sugar. We statistically analyze the rough surface formed after the stain becomes dried. The amount of sugar is controlled by the mass $m$. Along with the formation of the coffee ring, we discuss the Marangoni effect, in the system, and also analyzed the statistics of the cracks. For large enough $m$ values, the exponents approach to the ones for the Gaussian free field (GFF) (the loop fractal dimension $\frac{3}{2}$, loop and gyration radius distribution exponents $\tau_l=\frac{7}{3}$ and $\tau_r=3$ respectively). Using the multifractal analysis (MA) for the mass configuration of the dried pattern, we numerically show that, the mass-fractal dimension is $1.76\pm 0.04$ for the case without sugar, which decreases increasing the sugar. This is explained by the fact that the droplet becomes more hydrophilic, resulting in more sparse spatial patterns, in agreement compatible with the contact angle analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.12132v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Cheraghalizadeh, S. Tizdast, N. Valizadeh, S. Doostdari, M. N. Najafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on eigenstate thermalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.10069v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The eigenstate thermalization hypothesis (ETH), which asserts that every eigenstate of a many-body quantum system is indistinguishable from a thermal ensemble, plays a pivotal role in understanding thermalization of isolated quantum systems. Yet, no evidence has been obtained as to whether the ETH holds for any few-body operators in a chaotic system; such few-body operators include crucial quantities in statistical mechanics, such as the total magnetization, the momentum distribution, and their low-order thermal and quantum fluctuations. Here, we show the existence of upper and lower bounds on $m_{\ast}$ such that all $m$-body operators with $m &lt; m_{\ast}$ satisfy the ETH. For $N$-particles systems, these bounds are given in the form ${\alpha}_L \leq m_{\ast} / N \leq {\alpha}_U$, where ${\alpha}_L$ and ${\alpha}_U$ are $N$-independent positive numbers. We rigorously prove this statement for systems with Haar-distributed energy eigenstates and provide numerical evidence for generic systems with local and few-body interactions. Our results imply that generic systems satisfy the ETH for any few-body operators, including their thermal and quantum fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.10069v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoki Sugimoto, Ryusuke Hamazaki, Masahito Ueda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting a long lived false vacuum with quantum quenches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08340v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Distinguishing whether a system supports alternate low-energy (locally stable) states -- stable (true vacuum) versus metastable (false vacuum) -- by direct observation can be difficult when the lifetime of the state is very long but otherwise unknown. Here we demonstrate, in a tractable model system, that there are physical phenomena on much shorter time scales that can diagnose the difference. Specifically, we study the time evolution of the magnetization following a quench in the tilted quantum Ising model, and show that its magnitude spectrum is an effective diagnostic. Small transition bubbles are more common than large ones, and we see characteristic differences in the size dependence of bubble lifetimes even well below the critical size for false vacuum decay. We expect this sort of behavior to be generic in systems of this kind. We show such signatures persist in a continuum field theory. This also opens the possibility of similar signatures of the potential metastable false vacuum of our universe well before the beginning of a decay process to the true vacuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08340v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.240402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 240402 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Lagnese, Federica Maria Surace, Sid Morampudi, Frank Wilczek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusive oscillators capture the pulsating states of deformable particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14370v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a model of diffusive oscillators whose internal states are subject to a periodic drive. These models are inspired by the dynamics of deformable particles with pulsating sizes, where repulsion leads to arrest the internal pulsation at high density. We reveal that, despite the absence of any repulsion between the diffusive oscillators, our model still captures the emergence of dynamical arrest. We demonstrate that arrest here stems from the discrete nature of internal states which enforces an effective energy landscape analogous to that of deformable particles. Moreover, we show that the competition between arrest and synchronisation promotes spiral waves reminiscent of the pulsating states of deformable particles. Using analytical coarse-graining, we derive and compare the collective dynamics of diffusive oscillators with that of deformable particles. This comparison leads to rationalize the emergence of spirals in terms of a rotational invariance at the coarse-grained level, and to elucidate the role of hydrodynamic fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14370v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Manacorda, \'Etienne Fodor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining classical and quantum chaos through adiabatic transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01927v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a formalism which defines chaos in both quantum and classical systems in an equivalent manner by means of \textit{adiabatic transformations}. The complexity of adiabatic transformations which preserve classical time-averaged trajectories (quantum eigenstates) in response to Hamiltonian deformations serves as a measure of chaos. This complexity is quantified by the (properly regularized) fidelity susceptibility. Physically this measure quantifies long time instabilities of physical observables due to small changes in the Hamiltonian of the system. Our exposition clearly showcases the common structures underlying quantum and classical chaos and allows us to distinguish integrable, chaotic but non-thermalizing, and ergodic/mixing regimes. We apply the fidelity susceptibility to a model of two coupled spins and demonstrate that it successfully predicts the universal onset of chaos, both for finite spin $S$ and in the classical limit $S\to\infty$. Interestingly, we find that finite $S$ effects are anomalously large close to integrability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01927v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cedric Lim, Kirill Matirko, Hyeongjin Kim, Anatoli Polkovnikov, Michael O. Flynn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Green and Kubo forge the arrow of time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09291v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Transport theory describes the response of a macroscopic current to a thermodynamic force, thus producing entropy and apparently violating time-reversal symmetry. In this note I report a pedagogical derivation of the Green-Kubo formula for transport coefficients that highlights the intrinsically dynamical nature of this formula and showcases the relation between the apparent breach of time-reversal symmetry and the non-commutativity of the low-frequency / low-wavevector limits of the conserved-density susceptibilities, from which the formula can be established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09291v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1080/00268976.2024.2388300</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Molecular Physics (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Baroni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic thermodynamics of Fisher information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15685v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this manuscript, we investigate the stochastic thermodynamics of Fisher information (FI), meaning we characterize both the \textit{fluctuations} of FI, introducing a parastatistics of that quantity, and thermodynamic quantities. We introduce two initial conditions: an equilibrium initial condition and a minimum entropy initial condition, both under a protocol that drives the system to equilibrium. Its results indicate a dependence of the average FI on both the initial condition and path taken. Furthermore, the results point the chosen parameter directly affects the FI of thermodynamic quantities such as irreversible work and entropy, along with fluctuations of a stochastic FI. Last, we assess the further role of FI of the distribution of thermal quantities within the context of thermostatistical inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15685v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro B. Melo, S\'ilvio M. D. Queir\'os, Welles A. M. Morgado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inference of entropy production for periodically driven systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12792v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The problem of estimating entropy production from incomplete information in stochastic thermodynamics is essential for theory and experiments. Whereas a considerable amount of work has been done on this topic, arguably, most of it is restricted to the case of nonequilibrium steady states driven by a fixed thermodynamic force. Based on a recent method that has been proposed for nonequilibrium steady states, we obtain an estimate of the entropy production based on the statistics of visible transitions and their waiting times for the case of periodically driven systems. The time-dependence of transition rates in periodically driven systems produces several differences in relation to steady states, which is reflected in the entropy production estimation. More specifically, we propose an estimate that does depend on the time between transitions but is independent of the specific time of the first transition, thus it does not require tracking the protocol. Formally, this elimination of the time-dependence of the first transition leads to an extra term in the inequality that involves the rate of entropy production and its estimate. We analyze a simple model of a molecular pump to understand the relation between the performance of the method and physical quantities such as energies, energy barriers, and thermodynamic affinity. Our results with this model indicate that the emergence of net motion in the form of a probability current in the space of states is a necessary condition for a relevant estimate of the rate of entropy production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12792v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro E. Harunari, Carlos E. Fiore, Andre C. Barato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Networks with many structural scales: a Renormalization Group perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19104v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scale invariance profoundly influences the dynamics and structure of complex systems, spanning from critical phenomena to network architecture. Here, we propose a precise definition of scale-invariant networks by leveraging the concept of a constant entropy-loss rate across scales in a renormalization-group coarse-graining setting. This framework enables us to differentiate between scale-free and scale-invariant networks, revealing distinct characteristics within each class. Furthermore, we offer a comprehensive inventory of genuinely scale-invariant networks, both natural and artificially constructed, demonstrating, e.g., that the human connectome exhibits notable features of scale invariance. Our findings open new avenues for exploring the scale-invariant structural properties crucial in biological and socio-technological systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19104v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Poggialini, Pablo Villegas, Miguel A. Mu\~noz, Andrea Gabrielli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional Brownian motion with dependent components: turning angle analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06374v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Brownian motion in one or more dimensions is extensively used as a stochastic process to model natural and engineering signals, as well as financial data. Most works dealing with multidimensional Brownian motion consider the different dimensions as independent components. In this article, we investigate a model of correlated Brownian motion in $\mathbb{R}^2$, where the individual components are not necessarily independent. We explore various statistical properties of the process under consideration, going beyond the conventional analysis of the second moment. Our particular focus lies on investigating the distribution of turning angles. This distribution reveals particularly interesting characteristics for processes with dependent components that are relevant to applications in diverse physical systems. Theoretical considerations are supported by numerical simulations and analysis of two real-world datasets: the financial data of the Dow Jones Industrial Average and the Standard and Poor's 500, and trajectories of polystyrene beads in water. Finally, we show that the model can be readily extended to trajectories with correlations that change over time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06374v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Balcerek, Adrian Pacheco-Pozo, Agnieszka Wy{\l}omanska, Krzysztof Burnecki, Diego Krapf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of boundary functionals of random processes in statistical physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17934v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The potential applications of boundary functionals of random processes, such as the extreme values of these processes, the moment of first reaching a fixed level, the value of the process at the moment of reaching the level, the moment of reaching extreme values, the time the process stays above a fixed level, and other functionals, are considered for the description of physical, chemical, and biological problems. Definitions of these functionals are provided, and characteristic functions are presented for the model with an exponential distribution of incoming demands. A generalization of these limitations is also considered. The potential uses of boundary functionals are demonstrated through examples such as a unicyclic network with affinity A, an asymmetric random walk, nonlinear diffusion, two-level model, Brownian motion, and multiple diffusing particles with reversible target-binding kinetics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17934v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Ryazanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrodynamic equations and near critical large deviations of active lattice gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04105v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using a path integral approach, we derive and study the hydrodynamic equations and large deviation functions for three active lattice gases. After a review of the path integral for master equations, we first look at a one dimensional model of motility induced phase separation (MIPS), re-deriving the large deviation function that was previously found through a mapping to the ABC model. After extracting the deterministic hydrodynamic equations from the large deviation function, we analyse them perturbatively near the MIPS critical point using a weakly non-linear analysis. Doing this we show that they reduce to equilibrium Model B very close to criticality, with non-equilibrium, or Active Model B terms emerging as we leave the critical region. The same type of weakly non-linear analysis is then applied to the full large deviation function, and we show that the near critical stationary probability distribution is given by the exponential of a $\phi^4$ free energy, as expected in ordinary equilibrium phase separation. Similar calculations are then done for the two other lattice gases one which is another MIPS model, and another which models flocking, and in both cases we find analogous results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04105v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke Neville</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solvation Free Energies from Neural Thermodynamic Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15815v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a method for computing free-energy differences using thermodynamic integration with a neural network potential that interpolates between two target Hamiltonians. The interpolation is defined at the sample distribution level, and the neural network potential is optimized to match the corresponding equilibrium potential at every intermediate time-step. Once the interpolating potentials and samples are well-aligned, the free-energy difference can be estimated using (neural) thermodynamic integration. To target molecular systems, we simultaneously couple Lennard-Jones and electrostatic interactions and model the rigid-body rotation of molecules. We report accurate results for several benchmark systems: a Lennard-Jones particle in a Lennard-Jones fluid, as well as the insertion of both water and methane solutes in a water solvent at atomistic resolution using a simple three-body neural-network potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15815v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B\'alint M\'at\'e, Fran\c{c}ois Fleuret, Tristan Bereau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On dynamical behaviors in the fractional generalized Langevin equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09111v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The focus of our study in this paper is on the active dynamics and a fractional generalized Langevin equation with a memory kernel K(t). The Fokker-Planck equation is obtained by deriving it from a second-order differential equation. The joint probability density we obtained enables us to calculate various statistical quantities such as mean squared displacement and mean squared velocity in different three-time domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09111v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun Jeong Kang, Kyungsik Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Average Spectral Density of Multiparametric Gaussian Ensembles of Complex Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.08850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.08850v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A statistical description of part of a many body system often requires a non-Hermitian random matrix ensemble with nature and strength of randomness sensitive to underlying system conditions. For the ensemble to be a good description of the system, the ensemble parameters must be determined from the system parameters. This in turn makes its necessary to analyze a wide range of multi-parametric ensembles with different kinds of matrix elements distributions. The spectral statistics of such ensembles is not only system-dependent but also non-ergodic as well as non-stationary.
  A change in system conditions can cause a change in the ensemble parameters resulting an evolution of the ensemble density and it is not sufficient to know the statistics for a given set of system conditions. This motivates us to theoretically analyze a multiparametric evolution of the ensemble averaged spectral density of a multiparametric Gaussian ensemble on the complex plane. Our analysis reveals the existence of an evolutionary route common to the ensembles belonging to same global constraint class and thereby derives a complexity parameter dependent formulation of the spectral density for the non-equilibrium regime of the spectral statistics, away from Ginibre equilibrium limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.08850v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohd. Gayas Ansari, Pragya Shukla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics, structure and dynamics of cylindrically confined hard spheres: The role of excess helical twist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.04134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.04134v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hard spheres confined to narrow quasi-one-dimensional cylindrical channels form perfect helical structures at close packing. Here, we use molecular dynamics simulation to show that the thermodynamics, structure and dynamics of the fluid below close packing are dominated by the presence of topological defects that reverse the local twist direction of the helix. When compressed from a random, low density state, or decompressed from high density ordered states with zero excess helical twist, the system equilibrates to an achiral fluid that exhibits two heat capacity maxima along the equation of state. The low density heat capacity maximum corresponds to the onset of helix formation and the high density maximum occurs when the system rapidly loses defects in a Schottky-like anomaly. The local twist auto-correlation function in the achiral fluid exhibits a stretched exponential decay and the structural relaxation times undergo a fragile-to-strong crossover located at the high density heat capacity maximum. We also study the effect of excess helical twist by using initial starting configurations consisting of two helical domains with opposite twist directions of different lengths. This leads to the formation of topologically protected states that are characterized by the presence of loosely bound defect pairs which become more tightly bound with increasing excess helical twist. The local twist auto-correlation function in the chiral fluid decays as a power law at long times. The possible kinetic or thermodynamic origin of this topological protection is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.04134v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdi Zarif, Richard K. Bowles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete-phase-space method for driven-dissipative dynamics of strongly interacting bosons in optical lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16170v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a discrete truncated Wigner method to analyze the real-time evolution of dissipative SU(${\cal N}$) spin systems coupled with a Markovian environment. This semiclassical approach is not only numerically efficient but also particularly capable of accurately capturing local loss processes due to its local linearity in the dynamical equations. We apply the method to a state-of-the-art experiment involving an analog quantum simulator of a three-dimensional dissipative Bose-Hubbard model in a strongly interacting regime. Our numerical results show good agreement with experimental data, specifically capturing the continuous quantum Zeno effect in the dynamics subjected to a gradual change of the ratio between the hopping amplitude and the onsite interaction across the superfluid-Mott insulator crossover. Furthermore, we present comparative analyses with the continuous truncated Wigner method, derived as an effective Fokker-Planck equation for SU(${\cal N}$) classical spin variables, showing that the discrete method outperforms the continuous one in simulating the long-time dynamics of SU(2) and SU(3) spin models. The discrete phase space framework offers a versatile and powerful tool for exploring a wide range of open quantum many-body systems in dimensions higher than one dimension, where numerically exact methods are impractical due to the exponential growth of the Hilbert space dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16170v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.063310</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 063310 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kazuma Nagao, Ippei Danshita, Seiji Yunoki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional topological paramagnets protected by $\mathbb{Z}_3$ symmetry: Properties of the boundary Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15095v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically construct two-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_3$ symmetry-protected topological (SPT) three-state Potts paramagnets with gapless edge modes on a triangular lattice. First, we study microscopic lattice models for the gapless edge and, using the density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) approach, investigate the finite size scaling of the low-lying excitation spectrum and the entanglement entropy. Based on the obtained results, we identify the universality class of the critical edge, namely the corresponding conformal field theory and the central charge. Finally, we discuss the inherent symmetries of the edge models and the emergent winding symmetry distinguishing between two SPT phases. As a result, the two topologically nontrivial and the trivial phases define a general one-dimensional chain supporting a tricriticality, which we argue supports a gapless SPT order in one dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15095v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hrant Topchyan, Vasilii Iugov, Mkhitar Mirumyan, Tigran S. Hakobyan, Tigran A. Sedrakyan, Ara G. Sedrakyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Species Cohesion: Humans, machinery, AI and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17410v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The global chaos caused by the 19 July 2024 technology meltdown highlights the need for a theory of what large-scale cohesive behaviors -- dangerous or desirable -- could suddenly emerge from future systems of interacting humans, machinery and software including AI; when will they emerge; and how will they evolve and be controlled. Here we offer answers by introducing an aggregation model that accounts for the interacting entities' inter- and intra-species diversities. It yields a novel multi-dimensional generalization of existing aggregation physics. We derive exact analytic solutions for the time-to-cohesion and growth-of-cohesion for two species, and some generalizations for an arbitrary number of species. These solutions reproduce -- and offer a microscopic explanation for -- an anomalous nonlinear growth feature observed in various current real-world systems. Our theory suggests good and bad 'surprises' will appear sooner and more strongly as humans-machinery-AI etc. interact more -- but it also offers a rigorous approach for understanding and controlling this.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17410v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.247401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 247401 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Frank Yingjie Huo, Pedro D. Manrique, Neil F. Johnson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of systems with varying number of particles: from Liouville equations to general master equations for open systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14517v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A varying number of particles is one of the most relevant characteristics of systems of interest in nature and technology, ranging from the exchange of energy and matter with the surrounding environment to the change of particle number through internal dynamics such as reactions. The physico-mathematical modeling of these systems is extremely challenging, with the major difficulty being the time dependence of the number of degrees of freedom and the additional constraint that the increment or reduction of the number and species of particles must not violate basic physical laws. Theoretical models, in such a case, represent the key tool for the design of computational strategies for numerical studies that deliver trustful results. In this manuscript, we review complementary physico-mathematical approaches of varying number of particles inspired by rather different specific numerical goals. As a result of the analysis on the underlying common structure of these models, we propose a unifying master equation for general dynamical systems with varying number of particles. This equation embeds all the previous models and can potentially model a much larger range of complex systems, ranging from molecular to social agent-based dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14517v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio J. del Razo, Luigi Delle Site</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expansion of net correlations in terms of partial correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01734v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The marginal correlation between two variables is a measure of their linear dependence. The two original variables need not interact directly, because marginal correlation may arise from the mediation of other variables in the system. The underlying network of direct interactions can be captured by a weighted graphical model. The connection between two variables can be weighted by their partial correlation, defined as the residual correlation left after accounting for the linear effects of mediating variables. While matrix inversion can be used to obtain marginal correlations from partial correlations, in large systems this approach does not reveal how the former emerge from the latter. Here we present an expansion of marginal correlations in terms of partial correlations, which shows that the effect of mediating variables can be quantified by the weight of the paths in the graphical model that connect the original pair of variables. The expansion is proved to converge for arbitrary probability distributions. The graphical interpretation reveals a close connection between the topology of the graph and the marginal correlations. Moreover, the expansion shows how marginal correlations change when some variables are severed from the graph, and how partial correlations change when some variables are marginalised out from the description. It also establishes the minimum number of latent variables required to replicate the exact effect of a collection of variables that are marginalised out, ensuring that the partial and marginal correlations of the remaining variables remain unchanged. Notably, the number of latent variables may be significantly smaller than the number of variables that they effectively replicate. Finally, for Gaussian variables, marginal correlations are shown to be related to the efficacy with which information propagates along the paths in the graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01734v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bautista Arenaza, Sebasti\'an Risau-Gusman, In\'es Samengo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral properties of Levy Rosenzweig-Porter model via supersymmetric approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15072v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By using the Efetov's super-symmetric formalism we computed analytically the mean spectral density $\rho(E)$ for the L\'evy and the L\'evy -Rosenzweig-Porter random matrices which off-diagonal elements are strongly non-Gaussian with power-law tails. This makes the standard Hubbard-Stratonovich transformation inapplicable to such problems. We used, instead, the functional Hubbard-Stratonovich transformation which allowed to solve the problem analytically for large sizes of matrices. We show that $\rho(E)$ depends crucially on the control parameter that drives the system through the transition between the ergodic and the fractal phases and it can be used as an order parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15072v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizaveta Safonova, Mikhail Feigelman, Vladimir Kravtsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality defect in a deformed transverse-field Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17317v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Physical quantities with long lifetimes have both theoretical significance in the study of quantum many-body systems and practical implications for quantum technologies. In this manuscript, we investigate the roles played by topological defects in the construction of quasi-conserved quantities, using as a prototypical example the Kramers-Wannier duality defect in a deformed 1d quantum transverse field Ising model. We construct the duality defect Hamiltonian in three different ways: half-chain Kramers-Wannier transformation, utilization of techniques in the Ising fusion category, and defect-modified weak integrability breaking deformation. The third method is also applicable for the study of generic integrable defects under weak integrability breaking deformations. We also work out the deformation of defect-modified higher charges in the model and study their slower decay behavior. Furthermore, we consider the corresponding duality defect twisted deformed Floquet transverse field Ising model, and investigate the stability of the isolated zero mode associated with the duality defect in the integrable Floquet Ising model, under such weak integrability breaking deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17317v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Yan, Robert Konik, Aditi Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ambient space and integration of the trace anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03842v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use the ambient space construction, in which spacetime is mapped into a special lightcone of a higher dimensional manifold, to derive the integrable terms of the trace anomaly in even dimensions. We argue that the natural topological anomaly is the so-called $Q$-curvature, which, when projected from the ambient space, always comes with a Weyl covariant operator that can naturally be adopted for the integration of the anomaly itself in the form of a nonlocal action. The use of the ambient space makes trasparent the fact that there are some new ambiguities in the integration of the anomaly, which we now understand geometrically from the ambient point of view. These ambiguities, which manifest themselves as undetermined parameters in the integrated nonlocal action, become more severe in dimensions $d\geq 6$ and do not seem to be related to a choice of the renormalization scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03842v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregorio Paci, Omar Zanusso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractal decompositions and tensor network representations of Bethe wavefunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00923v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the entanglement structure of a generic $M$-particle Bethe wavefunction (not necessarily an eigenstate of an integrable model) on a 1d lattice by dividing the lattice into L parts and decomposing the wavefunction into a sum of products of $L$ local wavefunctions. We show that a Bethe wavefunction accepts a fractal multipartite decomposition: it can always be written as a linear combination of $L^M$ products of $L$ local wavefunctions, where each local wavefunction is in turn also a Bethe wavefunction. Building upon this result, we then build exact, analytical tensor network representations with finite bond dimension $\chi=2^M$, for a generic planar tree tensor network (TTN), which includes a matrix product states (MPS) and a regular binary TTN as prominent particular cases. For a regular binary tree, the network has depth $\log_{2}(N/M)$ and can be transformed into an adaptive quantum circuit of the same depth, composed of unitary gates acting on $2^M$-dimensional qudits and mid-circuit measurements, that deterministically prepares the Bethe wavefunction. Finally, we put forward a much larger class of generalized Bethe wavefunctions, for which the above decompositions, tensor network and quantum circuit representations are also possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00923v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhayan Sahu, Guifre Vidal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The generalized CV conjecture of Krylov complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08925v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend the ``complexity=volume" (CV) conjecture in the wormhole to the quantum states in the framework of information geometry. In particular, we conjecture that Krylov complexity equals the volume of the Fubini-Study metric in the information geometry. In order to test our conjecture, we study the general Hermitian two-mode Hamiltonian according to the Weyl algebra both in the closed and open systems. By employing the displacement operator, we find that the wave function for a closed system corresponds to the well-known two-mode squeezed state. For an open system, we can create a wave function known as the open two-mode squeezed state by using the second kind of Meixner polynomials. Remarkably, in both cases, the resulting volume of the corresponding Fubini-Study metric provides strong evidence for the generalized CV conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08925v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke-Hong Zhai, Lei-Hua Liu, Hai-Qing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
