<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 01:37:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice polymers near a permeable interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the localisation of lattice polymer models near a permeable interface in two dimensions. Localisation can arise due to an interaction between the polymer and the interface, and can be altered by a preference for the bulk solvent on one side or by the application of a force to manipulate the polymer. Different combinations of these three effects give slightly different statistical mechanical behaviours. The canonical lattice model of polymers is the self-avoiding walk which we mainly study with Monte Carlo simulation to calculate the phase diagram and critical phenomena. For comparison, a solvable directed walk version is also defined and the phase diagrams are compared for each case. We find broad agreement between the two models, and most minor differences can be understood as due to the different entropic contributions. In the limit where the bulk solvent on one side is overwhelmingly preferred we see how the localisation transition transforms to the adsorption transition; the permeable interface becomes effectively an impermeable surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16228v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C J Bradly, N R Beaton, A L Owczarek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between two mechanisms of resistivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mechanisms of resistivity can be divided into two basic classes: one is dissipative (like scattering on phonons) and another is quasi-elastic (like scattering on static impurities). They are often treated by the empirical Matthiessen rule, which says that total resistivity is just the sum of these two contributions, which are computed separately. This is quite misleading for two reasons. First, the two mechanisms are generally correlated. Second, computing the elastic resistivity alone masks the fundamental fact that the linear-response approximation has a vanishing validity interval at vanishing dissipation. Limits of zero electric field and zero dissipation do not commute for the simple reason that one needs to absorb the Joule heat quadratic in the applied field. Here, we present a simple model that illustrates these two points. The model also illuminates the role of variational principles for non-equilibrium steady states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16284v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Kapustin, Gregory Falkovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passive Particle Driven by Brownian Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the overdamped dynamics of a `passive' particle driven by nonreciprocal interaction with a `driver' Brownian particle. When the interaction between them is short-ranged, the long-time behavior of the driven particle is remarkably universal -- the mean-squared displacement (MSD) and the typical position of the driven particle exhibits the same qualitative behaviors independent of the specific form of the potential. In particular, the MSD grows as $t^{1/2}$ in one dimension and $\log t$ in two spatial dimensions. We compute the exact scaling functions for the position distribution in $d=1$ and $d=2$. These functions are universal when the interaction is short-ranged. For long-ranged interactions, the MSD of the driven particle grows as $t^{\phi}$ with exponent $\phi$ depending on the tail of the potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16436v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Urna Basu, P. L. Krapivsky, Satya N. Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy cascade and "Burgulence" in the Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamics of initial long-wavelength excitations of the Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou chain has been the subject of intense investigations since the pioneering work of Fermi and collaborators. We have recently found a new regime where the spectrum of the Fourier modes decays with a power-law and we have interpreted this regime as a transient turbulence associated with the Burgers equation. In this paper we present the full derivation of the latter equation from the lattice dynamics using a newly developed infinite dimensional Hamiltonian perturbation theory. This theory allows us to relate the time evolution of the Fourier spectrum $E_k$ of the Burgers equation to the one of the Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou chain. As a consequence, we derive analytically both the shock time and the power-law $-8/3$ of the spectrum at this time. Using the shock time as a unit, we follow numerically the time-evolution of the spectrum and observe the persistence of the power $-2$ over an extensive time window. The exponent $-2$ has been widely discussed in the literature on the Burgers equation. The analysis of the Burgers equation in Fourier space also gives information on the time evolution of the energy of each single mode which, at short time, is also a power-law depending on the $k$-th wavenumber $E_k \sim t^{2k-2}$. This approach to the FPUT dynamics opens the way to a wider study of scaling regimes arising from more general initial conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16534v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Gallone, Antonio Ponno, Stefano Ruffo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A tale of three approaches: dynamical phase transitions for weakly bound Brownian particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate a system of Brownian particles weakly bound by attractive parity-symmetric potentials that grow at large distances as $V(x) \sim |x|^\alpha$, with $0 &lt; \alpha &lt; 1$. The probability density function $P(x,t)$ at long times reaches the Boltzmann-Gibbs equilibrium state, with all moments finite. However, the system's relaxation is not exponential, as is usual for a confining system with a well-defined equilibrium, but instead follows a stretched exponential $e^{- \mathrm{const} \, t^\nu}$ with exponent $\nu=\alpha/(2+\alpha)$. This problem is studied from three perspectives. First, we propose a straightforward and general scaling rate-function solution for $P(x,t)$. This rate-function, which is an important tool from large deviation theory, also displays anomalous time scaling and a dynamical phase transition. Second, through the eigenfunctions of the Fokker-Planck operator, we obtain, using the WKB method, more complete solutions that reproduce the rate function approach. Finally, we show how the alternative path-integral formalism allows us to recover the same results, with the above rate-function being the solution of the classical Hamilton-Jacobi equation describing the most probable path. Properties such as parity, the role of initial conditions, and the dynamical phase transition are thoroughly studied in all three approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16598v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucianno Defaveri, Eli Barkai, David A. Kessler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studying the 3d Ising surface CFTs on the fuzzy sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15914v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Boundaries not only are fundamental elements in nearly all realistic physical systems, but also greatly enrich the structure of quantum field theories. In this paper, we demonstrate that conformal field theory (CFT) with a boundary, known as surface CFT in three dimensions, can be studied with the setup of fuzzy sphere. We consider the example of surface criticality of the 3D Ising CFT. We propose two schemes by cutting a boundary in the orbital space or the real space to realise the ordinary and the normal surface CFTs on the fuzzy sphere. We obtain the operator spectra through state-operator correspondence. We observe integer spacing of the conformal multiplets, and thus provide direct evidence of conformal symmetry. We identify the ordinary surface primary $o$, the displacement operator $\mathrm{D}$ and their conformal descendants and extract their scaling dimensions. We also study the one-point and two-point correlation functions and extract the bulk-to-surface OPE coefficients, some of which are reported for the first time. In addition, using the overlap of the bulk CFT state and the polarised state, we calculate the boundary central charges of the 3D Ising surface CFTs non-perturbatively. Other conformal data obtained in this way also agrees with prior methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15914v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Zhou, Yijian Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New boundary criticality in topological phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15916v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the boundary criticality enriched by boundary fermions, which ubiquitously emerge in topological phases of matter, with a focus on topological insulators and topological superconductors. By employing dimensional regularization and bosonization techniques, we uncover several unprecedented boundary universality classes. These include the boundary Gross-Neveu-Yukawa critical point and the special Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) transition, both resulting from the interplay between edge modes and bulk bosons. We present a comprehensive sketch of the phase diagram that accommodates these boundary criticalities and delineate their critical exponents. Additionally, we explore a 1+1D conformal defect decorated with fermions, where a defect BKT transition is highlighted. We conclude with a discussion on potential experimental realizations of these phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15916v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyang Shen, Zhengzhi Wu, Shao-Kai Jian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic transition in measurement-only circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15939v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magic, also known as nonstabilizerness, quantifies the distance of a quantum state to the set of stabilizer states, and it serves as a necessary resource for potential quantum advantage over classical computing. In this work, we study magic in a measurement-only quantum circuit with competing types of Clifford and non-Clifford measurements, where magic is injected through the non-Clifford measurements. This circuit can be mapped to a classical model that can be simulated efficiently, and the magic can be characterized using any magic measure that is additive for tensor product of single-qubit states. Leveraging this observation, we study the magic transition in this circuit using large-scale numerical simulations. Our results demonstrate the presence of a magic transition between two different phases with extensive magic scaling, separated by a critical point in which the mutual magic exhibits logarithmic scaling. We further show that these two distinct phases can be distinguished by the topological magic. In a different regime, with vanishing rate of non-Clifford measurements, we find that the magic saturates in both phases. Our work sheds light on the behavior of magic and its linear combinations in quantum circuits, employing genuine magic measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15939v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Poetri Sonya Tarabunga, Emanuele Tirrito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ising BCFT from Fuzzy Hemisphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15948v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the recently introduced fuzzy sphere technique for the 3d Ising CFT to the case of boundary CFT (BCFT) using the fuzzy hemisphere. This allows to study conformal boundary conditions, and we investigate the three boundary universality classes of the 3d Ising CFT. These include the ordinary, extraordinary, and special boundary conditions. We identify the qualitative signatures of boundary conformal invariance, and in the cases of ordinary and extraordinary boundary conditions, obtain numerical estimates for the spectrum of low-lying boundary primaries. For the special boundary conditions, we are only able to see their qualitative features, while reliable estimates of the scaling dimensions of boundary primaries are left for the future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15948v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mykola Dedushenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residue imaginary velocity induces many-body delocalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Localization and delocalization are historic topics central to quantum and condensed matter physics. We discover a new delocalization mechanism attributed to a residue imaginary (part of) velocity $\operatorname{Im}(v)$, feasible for ground states or low-temperature states of non-Hermitian quantum systems under periodic boundary conditions. Interestingly, a disorder field contributing to $\operatorname{Im}(v)$ may allow strong-disorder-limit delocalization when $\operatorname{Im}(v)$ prevails over the Anderson localization. We demonstrate such delocalization with correlation and entanglement behaviors, as well as its many-body nature and generalizability to finite temperatures and interactions. Thus, the nontrivial physics of $\operatorname{Im}(v)$ significantly enriches our understanding of delocalization and breeds useful applications, e.g., in quantum adiabatic processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15954v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Xin Hu, Yong-Xu Fu, Yi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coplanarity of rooted spanning-tree vectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Employing a recent technology of tree surgery we prove a ``deletion-constriction'' formula for products of rooted spanning trees on weighted directed graphs that generalizes deletion-contraction on undirected graphs. The formula implies that, letting $\tau_x^\varnothing$, $\tau_x^+$, and $\tau_x^-$ be the rooted spanning tree polynomials obtained respectively by removing an edge in both directions or by forcing the tree to pass through either direction of that edge, the vectors $(\tau_x^\varnothing, \tau_x^+, \tau_x^-)$ are coplanar for all roots $x$. We deploy the result to give an alternative derivation of a recently found mutual linearity of stationary currents of Markov chains. We generalize deletion-constriction and current linearity among two edges, and conjecture that similar results may hold for arbitrary subsets of edges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16093v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Polettini, Pedro E. Harunari, Sara Dal Cengio, Vivien Lecomte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hermitian and non-Hermitian topology in active matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16143v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Self-propulsion is a quintessential aspect of biological systems, which can induce nonequilibrium phenomena that have no counterparts in passive systems. Motivated by biophysical interest together with recent advances in experimental techniques, active matter has been a rapidly developing field in physics. Meanwhile, over the past few decades, topology has played a crucial role to understand certain robust properties appearing in condensed matter systems. For instance, the nontrivial topology of band structures leads to the notion of topological insulators, where one can find robust gapless edge modes protected by the bulk band topology. We here review recent progress in an interdisciplinary area of research at the intersection of these two fields. Specifically, we give brief introductions to active matter and band topology in Hermitian systems, and then explain how the notion of band topology can be extended to nonequilibrium (and thus non-Hermitian) systems including active matter. We review recent studies that have demonstrated the intimate connections between active matter and topological materials, where exotic topological phenomena that are unfeasible in passive systems have been found. A possible extension of the band topology to nonlinear systems is also briefly discussed. Active matter can thus provide an ideal playground to explore topological phenomena in qualitatively new realms beyond conservative linear systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16143v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Sone, Kazuki Yokomizo, Kyogo Kawaguchi, Yuto Ashida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>q-deformed evolutionary dynamics in simple matrix games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider evolutionary games in which the agent selected for update compares their payoff to q neighbours, rather than a single neighbour as in standard evolutionary game theory. Through studying fixed point stability and fixation times for 2x2 games with all-to-all interactions, we find that the flow changes significantly as a function of q. Further, we investigate the effects of changing the underlying topology from an all-to-all interacting system to an uncorrelated graph via the pair approximation. We also develop the framework for studying games with more than two strategies, such as the rock-paper-scissors game where we show that changing q leads to the emergence of new types of flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16380v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher R. Kitching, Tobias Galla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic Action Principle for $T\bar{T}$-deformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16391v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the action principle for the holographic $T\bar{T}$-deformation. We develop a scheme in which one can holographically reproduce the action of the Liouville theory deformed by $T\bar{T}$-insertion. This scheme necessitates considering the bending energy of the finite cut-off surface. Following our proposal, one observes a perfect match between the actions of deformed theory on the field theory and gravity sides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16391v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amin Faraji Astaneh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect interactions in the non-reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16547v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a computational study of the pairwise interactions between defects in the recently introduced non-reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard model. The evolution of a defect pair exhibits dependence upon their corresponding topological charges, initial separation, and the non-reciprocity coupling constant $\alpha$. We find that the stability of isolated topologically neutral targets significantly affects the pairwise defect interactions. At large separations, defect interactions are negligible and a defect pair is stable. When positioned in relatively close proximity, a pair of oppositely charged spirals or targets merge to form a single target. At low $\alpha$, like-charged spirals form rotating bound pairs, which are however torn apart by spontaneously formed targets at high $\alpha$. Similar preference for charged or neutral solutions is also seen for a spiral target pair where the spiral dominates at low $\alpha$, but concedes to the target at large $\alpha$. Our work sheds light on the complex phenomenology of non-reciprocal active matter systems when their collective dynamics involves topological defects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16547v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Navdeep Rana, Ramin Golestanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive time-stepping for aggregation-shattering kinetics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16559v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose an experimental study of adaptive time-stepping methods for efficient modeling of the aggregation-fragmentation kinetics. Precise modeling of this phenomena usually requires utilization of the large systems of nonlinear ordinary differential equations and intensive computations. We concentrate on performance of three explicit Runge-Kutta time-integration methods and provide simulations for two types of problems: finding of equilibrium solutions and simulations for kinetics with periodic solutions. The first class of problems may be analyzed through the relaxation of the solution to the stationary state after large time. In this case, the adaptive time-stepping may help to reach it using big steps reducing cost of the calculations without loss of accuracy. In the second case, the problem becomes numerically unstable at certain points of the phase space and may require tiny steps making the simulations very time-consuming. Adaptive criteria allows to increase the steps for most of points and speedup simulations significantly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16559v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey A. Matveev, Viktor Zhilin, Alexander P. Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse resistance due to electronic inhomogeneities in superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16662v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Phase transitions in many-body systems are often associated with the emergence of spatial inhomogeneities. Such features may develop at microscopic lengthscales and are not necessarily evident in measurements of macroscopic quantities. In this work, we address the topic of distribution of current paths in superconducting films. Typical lengthscales associated with superconductivity are in the range of nanometres. Accordingly, measurements of electrical resistance over much larger distances are supposed to be insensitive to details of spatial inhomogeneities of electronic properties. We observe that, contrary to expectations, current paths adopt a highly non-uniform distribution at the onset of the superconducting transition which is manifested in the development of a finite transverse resistance. The anisotropic distribution of current density is unrelated to the structural properties of the superconducting films, and indicates the emergence of electronic inhomogeneities perceivable over macroscopic distances. Our experiments reveal the ubiquitous nature of this phenomenon in conventional superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16662v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shamashis Sengupta, Alireza Farhadizadeh, Joe Youssef, Sara Loucif, Florian Pallier, Louis Dumoulin, Kasturi Saha, Sumiran Pujari, Magnus Oden, Claire Marrache-Kikuchi, Miguel Monteverde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic parameter optimization analysis of dynamical quantum critical phenomena in long-range transverse-field Ising chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.14121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.14121v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quantum phase transition of the one-dimensional long-range transverse-field Ising model is explored by combining the quantum Monte Carlo method and stochastic parameter optimization, specifically achieved by tuning correlation ratios so that space and imaginary time are isotropic. In our simulations, the simulator automatically determines the parameters to sample from, even without prior knowledge of the critical point and universality class. The leading order finite-size corrections are eliminated by comparing two systems with different sizes; this procedure is also performed automatically. Varying the decay exponent of the long-range interaction, $\sigma$, we investigate $\sigma$-dependence of the dynamical exponent and the other critical exponents precisely in the mean-field, non-universal, and two-dimensional classical Ising universality regimes. We successfully determine the universality boundary between the latter two as $\sigma = 7/4$ based on the dynamical exponent and settle a long-standing dispute on the location of the universality boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.14121v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sora Shiratani, Synge Todo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying vegetation patterns for a qualitative assessment of land degradation using a cellular automata model and satellite imagery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12232v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We aim to identify the spatial distribution of vegetation and its growth dynamics with the purpose of obtaining a qualitative assessment of vegetation health and land degradation. To do so, we compare a statistical model of vegetation growth and real-world Earth observation data. Specifically, we analyze a stochastic cellular automata model and data obtained from satellite images, namely using the Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) and the Leaf Area Index (LAI). In the experimental data, we look for areas where vegetation is broken into small patches and qualitatively compare it to the percolating, fragmented, and degraded states that appear in the cellular automata model. We model the periodic effect of seasons, finding numerical evidence of a periodic fragmentation and recovery phenomenology if the model parameters are sufficiently close to the model's percolation transition. We qualitatively recognize these effects in real-world vegetation images and consider them a signal of increased environmental stress and vulnerability. Finally, we show an estimation of the environmental stress in land images by considering both the vegetation density and its clusterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12232v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hediye Yarahmadi, Yves Desille, John Goold, Francesca Pietracaprina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative construction of conserved quantities in dissipative nearly integrable systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03809v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Integrable systems offer rare examples of solvable many-body problems in the quantum world. Due to the fine-tuned structure, their realization in nature and experiment is never completely accurate, therefore effects of integrability are observed only transiently. One way to overcome this limitation is to weakly couple nearly integrable systems to baths and driving: these will stabilize integrable effects up to arbitrary time and encode them in the stationary state approximated by a generalized Gibbs ensemble. However, the description of such driven dissipative nearly integrable models is challenging and no exact analytical methods have been proposed so far. Here, we develop an iterative scheme in which integrability breaking perturbations (baths) determine the conserved quantities that play the leading role in a highly efficient truncated generalized Gibbs ensemble description. Our scheme paves the way for easier calculations in thermodynamically large systems and can be used to construct unknown conserved quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03809v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.230402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 230402 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Iris Ul\v{c}akar, Zala Lenar\v{c}i\v{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete time crystals in the presence of non-Markovian dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06890v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study discrete time crystals (DTCs) in periodically driven quantum systems, in the presence of non-Markovian dissipation. In contrast to DTCs observed in earlier works in the presence of Markovian dynamics, using the open Dicke model in presence of Jaynes-Cummings-like dissipation, we show that non-Markovian regime can be highly beneficial for stabilizing DTCs over a wide range of parameter values. This may be attributed to periodically varying dissipation rates even at long times in the case of non-Markovian dynamics. Further the Markovian and non-Markovian regimes show sharp distinctions for intermediate strengths of the dissipator coefficient, with a time-independent steady-state in the Markovian regime being replaced by varied dynamical phases, including DTC order, in the non-Markovian regime. We also verify the robustness of the DTC phase in the non-Markovian regime by introducing errors both in the Hamiltonian as well as in the dissipation. Our study shows the possibility of using DTC as a probe for non-Markovian dynamics in periodically modulated open quantum systems, at long times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06890v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.012208</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev. A 110, 012208 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bandita Das, Noufal Jaseem, Victor Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensive Long-Range Entanglement at Finite Temperatures from a Nonequilibrium Bias</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10822v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Thermal equilibrium states of local quantum many-body systems are notorious for their spatially decaying correlations, which place severe restrictions on the types of many-body entanglement structures that may be observed at finite temperatures. These restrictions may however be defied when an out-of-equilibrium steady state is considered instead. In this paper, we study the entanglement properties of free fermions on a one-dimensional lattice that contains a generic charge- and energy-conserving noninteracting impurity, and that is connected at its edges to two reservoirs with different equilibrium energy distributions. These distributions may differ in either temperature, chemical potential, or both, thereby inducing an external bias. We analytically derive exact asymptotic expressions for several quantum information measures -- the mutual information, its R\'enyi generalizations, and the fermionic negativity -- that quantify the correlation and entanglement between two subsystems located on opposite sides of the impurity. We show that all these measures scale (to a leading order) linearly with the overlap between one subsystem and the mirror image of the other (upon reflection of the latter about the impurity), independently of the distance between the subsystems. While a simple proportionality relation between the negativity and R\'enyi versions of the mutual information is observed to hold at zero temperature, it breaks down at finite temperatures, suggesting that these quantities represent strong long-range correlations of different origins. Our results generalize previous findings that were limited to the case of a chemical-potential bias at zero temperature, rigorously demonstrating that the effect of long-range volume-law entanglement is robust at finite temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10822v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.035149</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 035149 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shachar Fraenkel, Moshe Goldstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of non-reciprocal interactions on colloidal self-assembly with tunable anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12108v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Non-reciprocal (NR) effective interactions violating Newton's third law occur in many biological systems, but can also be engineered in synthetic, colloidal systems. Recent research has shown that such NR interactions can have tremendous effects on the overall collective behaviour and pattern formation, but can also influence aggregation processes on the particle scale. Here we focus on the impact of non-reciprocity on the self-assembly of an (originally passive) colloidal system with anisotropic interactions whose character is tunable by external fields. In the absence of non-reciprocity, that is, under equilibrium conditions, the colloids form aggregates with extremely long life times [Kogler et al., Soft Matter 11, 7356 (2015)], indicating kinetic trapping. Here we study, based on Brownian Dynamics (BD) simulations in 2D, a NR version of this model consisting of two species with reciprocal isotropic, but NR anisotropic interactions. We find that NR induces an effective propulsion of particle pairs and small aggregates forming at initial stages of self-assembly, an indication of the NR-induced non-equilibrium. The shape and stability of these initial clusters strongly depends on the degree of anisotropy. At longer times we find, for weak NR interactions, large (even system-spanning) clusters where single particles can escape and enter at the boundaries, in stark contrast to the small rigid aggregates appearing at the same time in the passive case. In this sense, weak NR shortcuts the aggregation. Increasing the degree of NR (and thus, propulsion), we even observe large-scale phase separation if the interactions are weakly anisotropic. In contrast, system with strong NR and anisotropy remain essentially disordered. Overall, NR interactions are shown to destabilize the rigid aggregates interrupting self-assembly in the passive case, helping the system to overcome kinetic barriers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12108v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salman Fariz Navas, Sabine H. L. Klapp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate inverse measurement channel for shallow shadows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11813v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classical shadows are a versatile tool to probe many-body quantum systems, consisting of a combination of randomised measurements and classical post-processing computations. In a recently introduced version of the protocol, the randomization step is performed via unitary circuits of variable depth $t$, defining the so-called shallow shadows. For sufficiently large $t$, this approach allows one to get around the use of non-local unitaries to probe global properties such as the fidelity with respect to a target state or the purity. Still, shallow shadows involve the inversion of a many-body map, the measurement channel, which requires non-trivial computations in the post-processing step, thus limiting its applicability when the number of qubits $N$ is large. In this work, we put forward a simple approximate post-processing scheme where the infinite-depth inverse channel is applied to the finite-depth classical shadows and study its performance for fidelity and purity estimation. The scheme allows for different circuit connectivity, as we illustrate for geometrically local circuits in one and two spatial dimensions and geometrically non-local circuits made of two-qubit gates. For the fidelity, we find that the resulting estimator coincides with a known linear cross-entropy, achieving an arbitrary small approximation error $\delta$ at depth $t=O(\log (N/\delta))$ (independent of the circuit connectivity). For the purity, we show that the estimator becomes accurate at a depth $O(N)$. In addition, at those depths, the variances of both the fidelity and purity estimators display the same scaling with $N$ as in the case of global random unitaries. We establish these bounds by analytic arguments and extensive numerical computations in several cases of interest. Our work extends the applicability of shallow shadows to large system sizes and general circuit connectivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11813v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Cioli, Elisa Ercolessi, Matteo Ippoliti, Xhek Turkeshi, Lorenzo Piroli</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
