<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A study of the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition in the XY model in a honeycomb lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we examined the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) phase transition in the two-dimensional XY model on a honeycomb lattice. The XY model consists of normalized vectors arranged in a plane and is used to represent two-dimensional magnetic systems. It has applications in areas such as spintronics, superconductivity, and topological quantum computing. To calculate the thermodynamic properties of the system, we used numerical Monte Carlo simulations with the Metropolis algorithm and the Simulated Annealing protocol. The transition temperature was calculated using the second and fourth-order helicity modulus as the order parameter. We also calculated the vortex density and the formation energy of vortex-antivortex pairs. Our findings suggest that the critical temperature is $T_{BKT} = 0.576 \pm 0.001$, and the vortex formation energy is $2\mu=4.0 \pm 0.5$. When compared to the square lattice, both results support the notion of the honeycomb lattice's instability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12076v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe E. F. de Andrade, L. N. Jorge, Claudio J. DaSilva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient mapping of phase diagrams with conditional normalizing flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The accurate prediction of phase diagrams is of central importance for both the fundamental understanding of materials as well as for technological applications in material sciences. However, the computational prediction of the relative stability between phases based on their free energy is a daunting task, as traditional free energy estimators require a large amount of simulation data to obtain uncorrelated equilibrium samples over a grid of thermodynamic states. In this work, we develop deep generative machine learning models for entire phase diagrams, employing normalizing flows conditioned on the thermodynamic states, e.g., temperature and pressure, that they map to. By training a single normalizing flow to transform the equilibrium distribution sampled at only one reference thermodynamic state to a wide range of target temperatures and pressures, we can efficiently generate equilibrium samples across the entire phase diagram. Using a permutation-equivariant architecture allows us, thereby, to treat solid and liquid phases on the same footing. We demonstrate our approach by predicting the solid-liquid coexistence line for a Lennard-Jones system in excellent agreement with state-of-the-art free energy methods while significantly reducing the number of energy evaluations needed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12378v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Schebek, Michele Invernizzi, Frank No\'e, Jutta Rogal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lindblad quantum dynamics from correlation functions of classical spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12396v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Lindblad quantum master equation is one of the central approaches to the physics of open quantum systems. In particular, boundary driving enables the study of transport, where a steady state emerges in the long-time limit, which features a constant current and a characteristic density profile. While the Lindblad equation complements other approaches to transport in closed quantum systems, it has become clear that a connection between closed and open systems exists in certain cases. Here, we build on this connection for magnetization transport in the spin-1/2 XXZ chain with and without integrability-breaking perturbations. Specifically, we show that the time evolution of the open quantum system can be described on the basis of classical correlation functions, as generated by the Hamiltonian equations of motion for real vectors. By comparing to exact numerical simulations of the Lindblad equation, we demonstrate the accuracy of this description for a range of model parameters, but also point out counterexamples. While this agreement is an interesting physical observation, it also suggests that classical mechanics can be used to solve the Lindblad equation for comparatively large system sizes, which lie outside the possibilities of a quantum mechanical treatment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12396v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Kraft, Mariel Kempa, Jiaozi Wang, Robin Steinigeweg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring kinetics and entropy production from observable transitions in partially accessible, periodically driven Markov networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a network of discrete states with a periodically driven Markovian dynamics, we develop an inference scheme for an external observer who has access to some transitions. Based on waiting-time distributions between these transitions, the periodic probabilities of states connected by these observed transitions and their time-dependent transition rates can be inferred. Moreover, the smallest number of hidden transitions between accessible ones and some of their transition rates can be extracted. We prove and conjecture lower bounds on the total entropy production for such periodic stationary states. Even though our techniques are based on generalizations of known methods for steady states, we obtain original results for those as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12657v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander M. Maier, Julius Deg\"unther, Jann van der Meer, Udo Seifert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using operator covariance to disentangle scaling dimensions in lattice models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In critical lattice models, distance ($r$) dependent correlation functions contain power laws $r^{-2\Delta}$ governed by scaling dimensions $\Delta$ of an underlying continuum field theory. In Monte Carlo simulations and other numerical approaches, the leading dimensions can be extracted by data fitting, which can be difficult when two or more powers contribute significantly. Here a method utilizing covariance between multiple lattice operators is developed where the $r$ dependent eigenvalues of the covariance matrix represent scaling dimensions of individual field operators. The scheme is tested on symmetric operators in the two-dimensional tricritical Blume-Capel model, where the two relevant dimensions, as well as some irrelevant ones, are isolated along with their corresponding eigenvectors. The method will be broadly useful in studies of classical and quantum models at multicritical points and for targeting irrelevant operators at simple critical (or multicritical) points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12681v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anders W. Sandvik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inference of entropy production for periodically driven systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The problem of estimating entropy production from incomplete information in stochastic thermodynamics is essential for theory and experiments. Whereas a considerable amount of work has been done on this topic, arguably, most of it is restricted to the case of nonequilibrium steady states driven by a fixed thermodynamic force. Based on a recent method that has been proposed for nonequilibrium steady states, we obtain an estimate of the entropy production based on the statistics of visible transitions and their waiting times for the case of periodically driven systems. The time-dependence of transition rates in periodically driven systems produces several differences in relation to steady states, which is reflected in the entropy production estimation. More specifically, we propose an estimate that does depend on the time between transitions but is independent of the specific time of the first transition, thus it does not require tracking the protocol. Formally, this elimination of the time-dependence of the first transition leads to an extra term in the inequality that involves the rate of entropy production and its estimate. We analyze a simple model of a molecular pump to understand the relation between the performance of the method and physical quantities such as energies, energy barriers, and thermodynamic affinity. Our results with this model indicate that the emergence of net motion in the form of a probability current in the space of states is a necessary condition for a relevant estimate of the rate of entropy production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12792v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro E. Harunari, Carlos E. Fiore, Andre C. Barato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge Spin fractionalization in one-dimensional spin-$S$ quantum antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11955v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We argue that the anisotropic quantum spin chain with spin $S$ (XXZ$-S$) exhibits exponentially localized fractional $\pm \frac{S}{2}$ edge modes in the gapped antiferromagnetic phase of the model. Moreover, we claim that this phenomenon is very general and exists in any $U(1)$ symmetric spin chain in its gapped antiferromagnetic regime with explicitly or spontaneously broken $\mathbb Z_2$ symmetry. We examine our argument for integrable and non integrable chains. By using the Bethe Ansatz method, we show that $XXZ-\frac{1}{2}$ and a $XXZ-1$ integrable chains have $\pm \frac{S}{2}$ fractionalized edge modes. Employing the density matrix renormalization group technique, we extend this analysis to {\it generic} XXZ-$S$ chains with $S\leq 3$ and demonstrate that these fractional spins emerge as robust quantum observables, substantiated by the observation of a variance of the associated fractional spin operators that is consistent with a vanishing functional form in the thermodynamic limit. Moreover, we find that the edge modes are robust to disorder that couples to the N\'eel order parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11955v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradip Kattel, Yicheng Tang, J. H. Pixley, Natan Andrei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling limit of the ground state Bethe roots for the inhomogeneous XXZ spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12102v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is known that for the Heisenberg XXZ spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ chain in the critical regime, the scaling limit of the vacuum Bethe roots yields an infinite set of numbers that coincide with the energy spectrum of the quantum mechanical 3D anharmonic oscillator. The discovery of this curious relation, among others, gave rise to the approach referred to as the ODE/IQFT (or ODE/IM) correspondence. Here we consider a multiparametric generalization of the Heisenberg spin chain, which is associated with the inhomogeneous six-vertex model. When quasi-periodic boundary conditions are imposed the lattice system may be explored within the Bethe Ansatz technique. We argue that for the critical spin chain, with a properly formulated scaling limit, the scaled Bethe roots for the ground state are described by second order differential equations, which are multi-parametric generalizations of the Schr\"{o}dinger equation for the anharmonic oscillator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12102v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sascha Gehrmann, Gleb A. Kotousov, Sergei L. Lukyanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlled Erasure as a Building Block for Universal Thermodynamically-Robust Superconducting Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12153v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reducing the energy inefficiency of conventional CMOS-based computing devices -- which rely on logically irreversible gates to process information -- remains both a fundamental engineering challenge and a practical social challenge of increasing importance. In this work, we extend an alternative computing paradigm which utilizes distributions of microstates to store information in the metastable minima determined by an effective potential energy landscape. These minima serve as mesoscopic memory states which are manipulated by a dynamic landscape to perform information processing. Central to our results is the control erase (CE) protocol, which manipulates the landscape's metastable minima to control whether information is preserved or erased. Importantly, successive executions of this protocol can implement a NAND gate -- a logically-irreversible universal logic gate. We show how to practically implement this in a device created by two inductively coupled superconducting quantum interference devices (SQUIDs). We identify circuit parameter ranges that give rise to effective CEs and characterize the protocol's robustness by comparing relevant protocol timescales. Due to their superconducting operational temperatures, performing optimized CEs with SQUIDs can serve as a platform for highly energy-efficient universal computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12153v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Z. Pratt, Kyle J. Ray, James P. Crutchfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cover times with stochastic resetting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12154v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cover times quantify the speed of exhaustive search. In this work, we compute exactly the mean cover time associated with a one-dimensional Brownian search under exponentially distributed resetting. We also approximate the moments of cover times of a wide range of stochastic search processes in $d$-dimensional continuous space and on an arbitrary discrete network under frequent stochastic resetting. These results hold for a large class of resetting time distributions and search processes including diffusion and Markov jump processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12154v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samantha Linn, Sean D Lawley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence and evolution of electronic modes with temperature in spin-gapped Mott and Kondo insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electronic modes emerge within the band gap at nonzero temperature in strongly correlated insulators such as Mott and Kondo insulators, exhibiting momentum-shifted magnetic dispersion relations from the band edges. As the temperature increases, the emergent modes gain considerable spectral weights and form robust bands that differ from the zero-temperature bands. Here, the origin of the emergent modes, their relation to doping-induced modes, and how their spectral weights increase with temperature are clarified in the ladder and bilayer Hubbard models and one- and two-dimensional Kondo lattice models using effective theory for weak inter-unit-cell hopping and numerical calculations. The results indicate that the temperature-driven change in the band structure reflecting spin excitation, including the change in the number of bands, can be observed in various strongly correlated insulators even with a spin gap, provided that the temperature increases up to about spin-excitation energies. The controlled analyses developed in this study significantly contribute to the fundamental understanding of the band structure of strongly correlated insulators at nonzero temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12310v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masanori Kohno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement swapping in critical quantum spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The transfer of quantum information between many-qubit states is a subject of fundamental importance in quantum science and technology. We consider entanglement swapping in critical quantum spin chains, where the entanglement between the two chains is induced solely by the Bell-state measurements. We employ a boundary conformal field theory (CFT) approach and describe the measurements as conformal boundary conditions in the replicated field theory. We show that the swapped entanglement exhibits a logarithmic scaling, whose coefficient takes a universal value determined by the scaling dimension of the boundary condition changing operator. We apply our framework to the critical spin-1/2 XXZ chain and determine the universal coefficient by the boundary CFT analysis. We also numerically verify these results by the tensor-network calculations. Possible experimental relevance to Rydberg atom arrays is briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12377v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Hoshino, Masaki Oshikawa, Yuto Ashida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrability of open boundary driven quantum circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12695v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we address the problem of Yang-Baxter integrability of doubled quantum circuit of qubits (spins 1/2) with open boundary conditions where the two circuit replicas are only coupled at the left or right boundary. We investigate the cases where the bulk is given by elementary six vertex unitary gates of either the free fermionic XX type or interacting XXZ type. By using the Sklyanin's construction of reflection algebra, we obtain the most general solutions of the boundary Yang-Baxter equation for such a setup. We use this solution to build, from the transfer matrix formalism, integrable circuits with two step discrete time Floquet (aka brickwork) dynamics. We prove that, only if the bulk is a free-model, the boundary matrices are in general non-factorizable, and for particular choice of free parameters yield non-trivial unitary dynamics with boundary interaction between the two chains. Then, we consider the limit of continuous time evolution and we give the interpretation of a restricted set of the boundary terms in the Lindbladian setting. Specifically, for a particular choice of free parameters, the solutions correspond to an open quantum system dynamics with the source terms representing injecting or removing particles from the boundary of the spin chain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12695v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Paletta, Toma\v{z} Prosen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towrad mean-field bound for critical temperature on Nishimori line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12728v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The critical inverse temperature of the mean-field approximation gives a lower bound of the true critical inverse temperature in a broad class of ferromagnetic spin models, which is called the mean-field bound for the critical temperature. In this study, we explore the possibility of a corresponding mean-field bound for the critical temperature in Ising spin-glass models with Gaussian randomness on the Nishimori line. On the Nishimori line, the critical inverse temperature of the mean-field approximation is given by $\beta_{MF}^{NL}=\sqrt{1/z}$, where $z$ denotes the coordination number. Using the Griffiths inequalities on the Nishimori line, we prove that there is zero spontaneous magnetization in the high-temperature region $\beta &lt; \beta_{MF}^{NL}/2$. In other words, the true critical inverse temperature $\beta_c^{NL}$ of the Nishimori line is always bounded by $\beta_c^{NL} \ge \beta_{MF}^{NL}/2$. Unfortunately, we did not succeed in obtaining the corresponding mean-field bound $\beta_c^{NL} \ge \beta_{MF}^{NL}$ on the Nishimori line.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12728v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manaka Okuyama, Masayuki Ohzeki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic behaviour of determinants through the expansion of the Moyal star product</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12781v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We work out a generalization of the Szeg\"o limit theorems on the determinant of large matrices. We focus on matrices with nonzero leading principal minors and elements that decay to zero exponentially fast with the distance from the main diagonal, but we relax the constraint of the Toeplitz structure. We obtain an expression for the asymptotic behaviour of the determinant written in terms of the factors of a left and right Wiener-Hopf type factorization of an appropriately defined symbol. For matrices with elements varying slowly along the diagonals (e.g., in locally Toeplitz sequences), we propose to apply the analogue of the semiclassical expansion of the Moyal star product in phase-space quantum mechanics. This is a systematic method that provides approximations up to any order in the typical scale of the inhomogeneity and allows us to obtain explicit asymptotic formulas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12781v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurizio Fagotti, Vanja Mari\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Coulomb driven nematicity in a multi-valley two-dimensional electron gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12825v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The properties of a two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) in a semiconductor host with two valleys related by an underlying $C_4$ rotational symmetry are studied using Hartree-Fock (HF) and various other many-body approaches. A familiar artifact of the HF approach is a degeneracy between the valley polarized - ``Ising nematic'' - and spin polarized - ferromagnetic - phases, which is inconsistent with recent variational Monte Carlo (VMC) results. Correlation effects, computed either within the random phase approximation (RPA) or the T-matrix approximation, enhance the valley susceptibility relative to the spin susceptibility. Extrapolating the results to finite interaction strength, we find a direct first-order transition from a symmetry-unbroken state to a spin unpolarized Ising nematic fluid with full valley polarization, in qualitative agreement with VMC. The RPA results are also reminiscent of experiments on the corresponding 2DEG in AlAs heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12825v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Calvera, Agnes Valenti, Sebastian D. Huber, Erez Berg, Steven A. Kivelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Borromean supercounterfluids at finite temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While the properties of standard (single-component) superfluids are well understood, principal differences arise in a special type of multicomponent systems -- the so-called Borromean supercounterfluids -- in which (i) supertransport is possible only in the counterflow regime and (ii) there are three or more counterflowing components. Borromean supercounterfluids's correlation and topological properties distinguish them from their single- and two-component counterparts.
  The component-symmetric case characterized by a distinctively different universality class of the supercounterfluid-to-normal phase transition is especially interesting. Using the recently introduced concept of compact-gauge invariance as the guiding principle, we develop the finite-temperature description of Borromean supercounterfluids in terms of an asymptotically exact long-wave effective action. We formulate and study Borromean XY and loop statistical models, capturing the universal long-range properties and allowing us to perform efficient worm algorithm simulations. Numeric results demonstrate perfect agreement with analytic predictions. Particularly instructive is the two-dimensional case, where the Borromean nature of the system is strongly manifested while allowing for an asymptotically exact analytic description.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12833v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandru Golic, Igor Timoshuk, Egor Babaev, Boris Svistunov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kuramoto model subject to subsystem resetting: How resetting a part of the system may synchronize the whole of it</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14921v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce and investigate the effects of a new class of stochastic resetting protocol called subsystem resetting, whereby a subset of the system constituents in a many-body interacting system undergoes bare evolution interspersed with simultaneous resets at random times, while the remaining constituents evolve solely under the bare dynamics. We pursue our investigation within the ambit of the well-known Kuramoto model of coupled phase-only oscillators of distributed natural frequencies. Here, the reset protocol corresponds to a chosen set of oscillators being reset to a synchronized state at random times. We find that the mean $\omega_0$ of the natural frequencies plays a defining role in determining the long-time state of the system. For $\omega_0=0$, the system reaches a synchronized stationary state at long times, characterized by a time-independent non-zero value of the synchronization order parameter. Moreover, we find that resetting even an infinitesimal fraction of the total number of oscillators has the drastic effect of synchronizing the entire system, even when the bare evolution does not support synchrony. By contrast, for $\omega_0 \ne 0$, the dynamics allows at long times either a synchronized stationary state or an oscillatory synchronized state, with the latter characterized by an oscillatory behavior as a function of time of the order parameter, with a non-zero time-independent time average. Our results thus imply that the non-reset subsystem always gets synchronized at long times through the act of resetting of the reset subsystem. Our results, analytical using the Ott-Antonsen ansatz as well as those based on numerical simulations, are obtained for two representative oscillator frequency distributions, namely, a Lorentzian and a Gaussian. We discuss how subsystem resetting may be employed as an efficient mechanism to control attainment of global synchrony.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14921v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.109.064137</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 109, 064137 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rupak Majumder, Rohitashwa Chattopadhyay, Shamik Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Langevin equation in heterogeneous landscapes: how to choose the interpretation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11928v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Langevin equation is a common tool to model diffusion at a single-particle level. In non-homogeneous environments, such as aqueous two-phase systems or biological condensates with different diffusion coefficients in different phases, the solution to a Langevin equation is not unique unless the interpretation of stochastic integrals involved is selected. We analyze the diffusion of particles in such systems and evaluate the mean, the mean square displacement, and the distribution of particles, as well as the variance of the time-averaged mean-squared displacements. Our analytical results provide a method to choose the interpretation parameter from single particle tracking experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11928v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Pacheco-Pozo, Micha{\l} Balcerek, Agnieszka Wy{\l}oma\'nska, Krzysztof Burnecki, Igor M. Sokolov, Diego Krapf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning irreversibility of mesoscopic processes using hydrodynamic interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00800v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optically confined colloidal particles, when placed in close proximity, form a dissipatively coupled system through hydrodynamic interactions. Here, we demonstrate that these interactions can be harnessed to design systems with non-trivial and highly tunable non-equilibrium characteristics, directly quantifiable from experimental data. Furthermore, we clarify that such interactions do not modify the underlying potential energy function, nor do they violate the energy balance at the level of individual trajectories, as was believed earlier. Moreover, they offer new opportunities for tailored control and design of mesoscale systems with emergent and targeted nonequilibrium properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00800v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Biswajit Das, Sreekanth K Manikandan, Shuvojit Paul, Avijit Kundu, Supriya Krishnamurthy, Ayan Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Brownian motion with fluctuating diffusivities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03836v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite the success of fractional Brownian motion (fBm) in modeling systems that exhibit anomalous diffusion due to temporal correlations, recent experimental and theoretical studies highlight the necessity for a more comprehensive approach of a generalization that incorporates heterogeneities in either the tracers or the environment. This work presents a modification of Levy's representation of fBm for the case in which the generalized diffusion coefficient is a stochastic process. We derive analytical expressions for the autocovariance function and both ensemble- and time-averaged mean squared displacements. Further, we validate the efficacy of the developed framework in two-state systems, comparing analytical asymptotic expressions with numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03836v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Pacheco-Pozo, Diego Krapf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review and Prospect of Algebraic Research in Equivalent Framework between Statistical Mechanics and Machine Learning Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10234v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mathematical equivalence between statistical mechanics and machine learning theory has been known since the 20th century, and researches based on such equivalence have provided novel methodology in both theoretical physics and statistical learning theory. For example, algebraic approach in statistical mechanics such as operator algebra enables us to analyze phase transition phenomena mathematically. In this paper, for theoretical physicists who are interested in artificial intelligence, we review and prospect algebraic researches in machine learning theory. If a learning machine has hierarchical structure or latent variables, then the random Hamiltonian cannot be expressed by any quadratic perturbation because it has singularities. To study an equilibrium state defined by such a singular random Hamiltonian, algebraic approach is necessary to derive asymptotic form of the free energy and the generalization error. We also introduce the most recent advance, in fact, theoretical foundation for alignment of artificial intelligence is now being constructed based on algebraic learning theory. This paper is devoted to the memory of Professor Huzihiro Araki who is a pioneer founder of algebraic research in both statistical mechanics and quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10234v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumio Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly correlated two-dimensional electron fluid in best-quality GaAs quantum wells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.01035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2105.01035v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Magnetotransport phenomena in high-quality quantum wells often shed a light on the nature of microscopic states of two-dimensional electrons in these systems. In particular, the independence of photoresistance on the polarization helicity of incident radiation have been treated an important puzzling result, which had no well-established explanation up to now. Here we propose a theoretical model of dynamics of a strongly non-ideal two-dimensional electron liquid in moderate magnetic fields. In this system, in particular, successive collisions of electrons joined in pairs are as important as single collisions of statistically independent electrons. The resulting fluid photoresistance exhibits an irregular shape of magnetooscillations, the absence of the dependence on the helicity of the circular polarization of incident radiation, and a large peak near the doubled cyclotron frequency. All these effects were observed in experiments on best-quality GaAs quantum wells. We conclude that 2D electrons in such nanostructures in moderate magnetic fields form a novel type of highly correlated fluids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2105.01035v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. S. Alekseev, A. P. Alekseeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timeliness criticality in complex systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.15070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.15070v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In complex systems, external parameters often determine the phase in which the system operates, i.e., its macroscopic behavior. For nearly a century, statistical physics has extensively studied systems' transitions across phases, (universal) critical exponents, and related dynamical properties. Here we consider the functionality of systems, notably operations in socio-technical ones, production in economic ones and, more generally, any schedule-based system, where timing is of crucial importance. We introduce a stylized model of delay propagation on temporal networks, where the magnitude of delay-mitigating buffer acts as a control parameter. The model exhibits {\it timeliness criticality}, a novel form of critical behavior. We characterize fluctuations near criticality, commonly referred to as ``avalanches'', and identify the corresponding critical exponents. The model exhibits timeliness criticality also when run on real-world temporal systems such as production networks. Additionally, we explore potential connections with the Mode-Coupling Theory of glasses, the depinning transition and the directed polymer problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.15070v3</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02525-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Physics 2024, advanced online publication</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Moran, Matthijs Romeijnders, Pierre Le Doussal, Frank P. Pijpers, Utz Weitzel, Debabrata Panja, Jean-Philippe Bouchaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $g$-function and Defect Changing Operators from Wavefunction Overlap on a Fuzzy Sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00039v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Defects are common in physical systems with boundaries, impurities or extensive measurements. The interaction between bulk and defect can lead to rich physical phenomena. Defects in gapless phases of matter with conformal symmetry usually flow to a defect conformal field theory (dCFT). Understanding the universal properties of dCFTs is a challenging task. In this paper, we propose a computational strategy applicable to a line defect in arbitrary dimensions. Our main assumption is that the defect has a UV description in terms of a local modification of the Hamiltonian so that we can compute the overlap between low-energy eigenstates of a system with or without the defect insertion. We argue that these overlaps contain a wealth of conformal data, including the $g$-function, which is an RG monotonic quantity that distinguishes different dCFTs, the scaling dimensions of defect creation operators $\Delta^{+0}_\alpha$ and changing operators $\Delta^{+-}_\alpha$ that live on the intersection of different types of line defects, and various OPE coefficients. We apply this method to the fuzzy sphere regularization of 3D CFTs and study the magnetic line defect of the 3D Ising CFT. Using exact diagonalization and DMRG, we report the non-perturbative results $g=0.602(2),\Delta^{+0}_0=0.108(5)$ and $\Delta^{+-}_0=0.84(5)$ for the first time. We also obtain other OPE coefficients and scaling dimensions. Our results have significant physical implications. For example, they constrain the possible occurrence of spontaneous symmetry breaking at line defects of the 3D Ising CFT. Our method can be potentially applied to various other dCFTs, such as plane defects and Wilson lines in gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00039v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Zhou, Davide Gaiotto, Yin-Chen He, Yijian Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature inversion in a confined plasma atmosphere: coarse-grained effect of temperature fluctuations at its base</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10713v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Prompted by the relevant problem of temperature inversion (i.e. gradient of density anti-correlated to the gradient of temperature) in astrophysics, we introduce a novel method to model a gravitationally confined multi-component collisionless plasma in contact with a fluctuating thermal boundary. We focus on systems with anti-correlated (inverted) density and temperature profiles, with applications to solar physics. The dynamics of the plasma is analytically described via the coupling of an appropriated coarse-grained distribution function and temporally coarse-grained Vlasov dynamics. We derive a stationary solution of the system and predict the inverted density and temperature profiles of the two-species for scenarios relevant for the corona. We validate our method by comparing the analytical results with kinetic numerical simulations of the plasma dynamics in the context of the two-species Hamiltonian mean-field model (HMF). Finally, we apply our theoretical framework to the problem of the temperature inversion in the solar corona obtaining density and temperature profiles in remarkably good agreement with the observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10713v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Barbieri, Emanuele Papini, Pierfrancesco Di Cintio, Simone Landi, Andrea Verdini, Lapo Casetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing Artificial and Natural Intelligence: From Statistical Mechanics to AI and Back to Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17993v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The paper reflects on the future role of AI in scientific research, with a special focus on turbulence studies, and examines the evolution of AI, particularly through Diffusion Models rooted in non-equilibrium statistical mechanics. It underscores the significant impact of AI on advancing reduced, Lagrangian models of turbulence through innovative use of deep neural networks. Additionally, the paper reviews various other AI applications in turbulence research and outlines potential challenges and opportunities in the concurrent advancement of AI and statistical hydrodynamics. This discussion sets the stage for a future where AI and turbulence research are intricately intertwined, leading to more profound insights and advancements in both fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17993v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Chertkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal Entanglement Profiles in Dual-Unitary Clifford Circuits with Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14374v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study temporal entanglement in dual-unitary Clifford circuits with probabilistic measurements preserving spatial unitarity. We exactly characterize the temporal entanglement barrier in the measurement-free regime, exhibiting ballistic growth and decay and a volume-law peak. In the presence of measurements, we relate the temporal entanglement to the scrambling properties of the circuit. For "good scramblers" measurements do not qualitatively change the temporal entanglement profile but only result in a reduced entanglement velocity, whereas for "poor scramblers" the initial ballistic growth of temporal entanglement with bath size is modified to diffusive. This difference is understood through a mapping of the underlying operator dynamics to a biased and an unbiased persistent random walk respectively. In the latter case measurements additionally modify the ballistic decay to the perfect dephaser limit, with vanishing temporal entanglement, to an exponential decay, which we describe through a spatial transfer matrix method. This spatial dynamics is shown to be described by a non-Hermitian hopping model, exhibiting a PT-breaking transition at a critical measurement rate $p=1/2$. In all cases the peak value of the temporal entanglement barrier exhibits volume-law scaling for all measurement rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14374v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiangtian Yao, Pieter W. Claeys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of annealed disorder on the plasticity of amorphous solids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07360v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of annealed disorder on the mechanical properties and plasticity of a modeled amorphous solid by introducing a small fraction of heavy impurities into the material which resembles real experimental systems. The disorder being mobile, the total degrees of freedom and the potential energy landscape of the pure system are preserved in our model. The mechanical failure and the shear band formation in the amorphous solid in the presence of annealed disorder are studied at the microscopic level by employing the finite shear deformation protocol at nonzero temperature. A significant enhancement in the shear modulus and yield stress is observed as a function of the heaviness of the impurity particles. Via the analysis of the non-affine displacement field and the microscopic strain fluctuations and the nature of their spatial correlations we find that the shear band formation in the plastic regime is gradually suppressed with increasing impurity mass. Eventually, a critical mass of the disordered particles is identified above which the plastic events become completely localized. This is marked by a transition from a power law to an exponential decay in the spatial correlations non-affine displacement field. Likewise, a similar change is observed in the strain correlation function, transitioning from a slower $1/r$ decay to a more rapid $1/r^3$ decay. Finally, the effect shear rate on the plastic events in the presence of annealed disorder is explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07360v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meenakshi L., Bhaskar Sen Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
