<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 19:07:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-stable states in the Ising model with Glauber-Kawasaki competing dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Meta-stable states are identified in the Ising model with competition between the Glauber and Kawasaki dynamics. The model of interaction between magnetic moments was implemented on a network where the degree distribution follows a power-law of the form, $P(k)\sim k^{-\alpha}$. The evolution towards the stationary state occurred through the competition between two dynamics, driving the system out of equilibrium. In this competition, with probability $q$, the system was simulated in contact with a heat bath at temperature $T$ by the Glauber dynamics, while with probability $1-q$, the system experienced an external energy influx governed by the Kawasaki dynamics. The phase diagrams of $T$ versus $q$ were obtained, which are dependent on the initial state of the system, and exhibit first- and second-order phase transitions. In all diagrams, for intermediate values of $T$, the phenomenon of self-organization between the ordered phases was observed. In the regions of second-order phase transitions, we have verified the universality class of the system through the critical exponents of the order parameter $\beta$, susceptibility $\gamma$, and correlation length $\nu$. Furthermore, in the regions of first-order phase transitions, we have demonstrated the instability due to transitions between the ordered phases through hysteresis-like curves of the order parameter, in addition to the existence of absorbing states. We also estimated the value of the tricritical points when the discontinuity in the order parameter in the phase transitions was no longer observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15460v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. A. Dumer, M. Godoy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Springs and a stopwatch: neural units with time-dependent multifunctionality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Several branches of computing use a system's physical dynamics to do computation. We show that the dynamics of an underdamped harmonic oscillator can perform multifunctional computation, solving distinct problems at distinct times within a single dynamical trajectory. Oscillator computing usually focuses on the oscillator's phase as the information-carrying component. Here we focus on the time-resolved amplitude of an oscillator whose inputs influence its frequency, which has a natural parallel as the activity of a time-dependent neural unit. Because the activity of the unit at fixed time is a nonmonotonic function of the input, the unit can solve nonlinearly-separable problems such as XOR. Because the activity of the unit at fixed input is a nonmonotonic function of time, the unit is multifunctional in a temporal sense, able to carry out distinct nonlinear computations at distinct times within the same dynamical trajectory. Time-resolved computing of this nature can be done in or out of equilibrium, with the natural time evolution of the system giving us multiple computations for the price of one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15545v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Whitelam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Violent relaxation in one-dimensional self-gravitating system: deviation from the Vlasov limit due to finite-$N$ effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15787v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of a finite particle number $N$ on the violent relaxation leading to the Quasi-Stationary State (QSS) in a one-dimensional self-gravitating system. From the theoretical point of view, we demonstrate that the local Poissonian fluctuations embedded in the initial state give rise to an additional term proportional to $1/N$ in the Vlasov equation. This term designates the strength of the local mean-field variations by fluctuations. Because it is of the mean-field origin, we interpret it differently from the known collision term in the way that it effects the violent relaxation stage. Its role is to deviate the distribution function from the Vlasov limit, in the collisionless manner, at a rate proportional to $1/N$ while the violent relaxation is progressing. This hypothesis is tested by inspecting the QSSs in simulations of various $N$. We observe that the core phase-space density can exceed the limiting density deduced from the Vlasov equation and its deviation degree is in accordance with the $1/N$ estimate. This indicates the deviation from the standard mean-field approximation of the violent relaxation process by that $1/N$ term. In conclusion, the finite-$N$ effect has a significant contribution to the QSS apart from that it plays a role in the collisional stage that takes place long after. The conventional collisionless Vlasov equation might not be able to describe the violent relaxation of a system of particles properly without the correction term of the local finite-$N$ fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15787v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tirawut Worrakitpoonpon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact propagators of one-dimensional self-interacting random walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Self-interacting random walks (SIRWs) show long-range memory effects that result from the interaction of the random walker at time $t$ with the territory already visited at earlier times $t'&lt;t$. This class of non-Markovian random walks has applications in contexts as diverse as foraging theory, the behaviour of living cells, and even machine learning. Despite this importance and numerous theoretical efforts, the propagator, which is the distribution of the walker's position and arguably the most fundamental quantity to characterize the process, has so far remained out of reach for all but a single class of SIRW. Here we fill this gap and provide an exact and explicit expression for the propagator of two important classes of SIRWs, namely, the once-reinforced random walk and the polynomially self-repelling walk. These results give access to key observables, such as the diffusion coefficient, which so far had not been determined. We also uncover an inherently non-Markovian mechanism that tends to drive the walker away from its starting point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15853v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Br\'emont, Olivier B\'enichou, Rapha\"el Voituriez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous random flights and time-fractional run-and-tumble equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15941v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Random flights (also called run-and-tumble walks or transport processes) represent finite velocity random motions changing direction at any Poissonian time. These models in d-dimension, can be studied giving a general formulation of the problem valid at any spatial dimension. The aim of this paper is to extend this general analysis to time-fractional processes arising from a non-local generalization of the kinetic equations. The probabilistic interpretation of the solution of the time-fractional equations leads to a time-changed version of the original transport processes. The obtained results provides a clear picture of the role played by the time-fractional derivatives in this kind of random motions. They displayed an anomalous behavior and are useful to describe several complex systems arising in statistical physics and biology. In particular, we focus on the one-dimensional random flight, called telegraph process, studying the time-fractional version of the classical telegraph equation and providing a suitable interpretation of its stochastic solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15941v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Angelani, Alessandro De Gregorio, Roberto Garra, Francesco Iafrate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quantum adiabatic algorithm suppresses the proliferation of errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15397v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The propagation of errors severely compromises the reliability of quantum computations. The quantum adiabatic algorithm is a physically motivated method to prepare ground states of classical and quantum Hamiltonians. Here, we analyze the proliferation of a single error event in the adiabatic algorithm. We give numerical evidence using tensor network methods that the intrinsic properties of adiabatic processes effectively constrain the amplification of errors during the evolution for geometrically local Hamiltonians. Our findings indicate that low energy states could remain attainable even in the presence of a single error event, which contrasts with results for error propagation in typical quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15397v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin F. Schiffer, Adrian Franco Rubio, Rahul Trivedi, J. Ignacio Cirac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of a Universal Speed Limit on Fast Scrambling in Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15403v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that the time required for sustained information scrambling in any Hamiltonian quantum system is universally at least logarithmic in the entanglement entropy of scrambled states. This addresses two foundational problems in nonequilibrium quantum dynamics. (1) It sets the earliest possible time for the applicability of equilibrium statistical mechanics in a quantum system coupled to a bath at a finite temperature. (2) It proves a version of the fast scrambling conjecture, originally motivated in models associated with black holes, as a fundamental property of quantum mechanics itself. Our result builds on a refinement of the energy-time uncertainty principle in terms of the infinite temperature spectral form factor in quantum chaos. We generalize this formulation to arbitrary initial states of the bath, including finite temperature states, by mapping Hamiltonian dynamics with any initial state to nonunitary dynamics at infinite temperature. A regularized spectral form factor emerges naturally from this procedure, whose decay is universally constrained by analyticity in complex time. This establishes an exact speed limit on information scrambling by the most general quantum mechanical Hamiltonian, without any restrictions on locality or the nature of interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15403v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Vikram, Laura Shou, Victor Galitski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of a small quantum system open to a bath with thermostat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15568v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate dynamics of a small quantum system open to a bath with thermostat. We introduce another bath, called super bath, weakly coupled with the bath to provide it with thermostat, which has either the Lindblad or Redfield type. We treat the interaction between the system and bath via a rigorous perturbation theory. Due to the thermostat, the bath behaves dissipative and stochastic, for which the usual Born-Markov assumption is not needed. We consider a specific example of a harmonic oscillator system, and a photonic bath in a large container, and a super bath of the Caldeira-Legget oscillators distributed on the inner surface of the container. We use the $P$-representation for the total harmonic system. We derive the reduced time-evolution equation for the system by explicitly finding the correlation between the system and bath beyond the product state, that was not obtainable in the previous theory for the system and bath isolated from environment, and marginalizing bath degrees of freedom. Remarkably, the associated dynamic equation for the system density matrix is of the same form as the Redfield master equation with different coefficients depending on thermostat used. We find steady state does not depend on thermostat, but time-dependent state does, that agrees with common expectation. We expect to apply our theory to general systems. Unlike the usual quantum master equations, our reduced dynamics allows investigation for time-dependent protocols and non-equilibrium quantum stochastic dynamics will be investigated in future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15568v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chulan Kwon, Ju-Yeon Gyhm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Minimal Framework for Optimizing Vaccination Protocols Targeting Highly Mutable Pathogens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A persistent public health challenge is finding immunization schemes that are effective in combating highly mutable pathogens such as HIV and influenza viruses. To address this, we analyze a simplified model of affinity maturation, the Darwinian evolutionary process B cells undergo during immunization. The vaccination protocol dictates selection forces that steer affinity maturation to generate antibodies. We focus on determining the optimal selection forces exerted by a generic time-dependent vaccination protocol to maximize production of broadly neutralizing antibodies (bnAbs) that can protect against a broad spectrum of pathogen strains. The model lends itself to a path integral representation and operator approximations within a mean-field limit, providing guiding principles for optimizing time-dependent vaccine-induced selection forces to enhance bnAb generation. We compare our analytical mean-field results with the outcomes of stochastic simulations and discuss their similarities and differences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15634v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saeed Mahdisoltani, Pranav Murugan, Arup K Chakraborty, Mehran Kardar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inertia and Activity: Spiral transitions in semi-flexible, self-avoiding polymers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15748v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a two-dimensional, tangentially active, semi-flexible, self-avoiding polymer to find a dynamical re-entrant transition between motile open chains and spinning achiral spirals with increasing activity. Utilizing probability distributions of the turning number, we ascertain the comparative stability of the spiral structure and present a detailed phase diagram within the activity inertia plane. The onset of spiral formation at low activity levels is governed by a torque balance and is independent of inertia. At higher activities, however, inertial effects lead to spiral destabilization, an effect absent in the overdamped limit. We further delineate alterations in size and shape by analyzing the end-to-end distance distribution and the radius of gyration tensor. The Kullback-Leibler divergence from equilibrium distributions exhibits a non-monotonic relationship with activity, reaching a peak at the most compact spirals characterized by the most persistent spinning. As inertia increases, this divergence from equilibrium diminishes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15748v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chitrak Karan, Abhishek Chaudhuri, Debasish Chaudhuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic signature of resonant thermal transport: Ordered form of heat conduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermal transport in crystals is influenced by chemistry, boundaries, and nanostructure. The phonon band structure extracted from molecular-dynamics simulations provides an illuminating view of both the type and extent of prevalence of wavelike mechanisms underlying the transport, yet falls short of elucidating the nature of thermal evolution for different phonon regimes. Here we present an analysis framework for the characterization of the entropic signature of the mechanisms induced by the existence of boundaries and nanostructure, using both equilibrium and nonequilibrium atomistic simulations. Specifically, we examine the effects of phonon confinement, Bragg scattering, and local resonances on the configurational phase space in room-temperature nanostructured silicon, and quantify how each modifies the rate of entropy production and thermal relaxation. We reveal that the presence of phonon local resonances spanning the full spectrum enables a highly ordered regime of heat conduction, where irreversible evolution and entropy maximization are severely hindered by extensive mode hybridizations caused by the resonances. This unique regime of transport paves the way for ultra-precise phonon control for a wide range of applications in condensed matter physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15831v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albert Beardo, Prajit Rawte, Chia-Nien Tsai, Mahmoud I. Hussein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confinement-induced resonance from the generalized Gross-Pitaevskii equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15872v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The confinement-induced resonances for trapped bosons in the cigar-shaped and pancake geometries are studied within the generalized Gross-Pitaevskii equations, which are a simplified version of the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov approximation. Although the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov method is considered applicable only for small interparticle interactions, the resonance denominators for the chemical potential are obtained in both quasi-one and quasi-two dimensions. A useful integral representation of the one-particle Green's function are found for the cylindrical confinement. We find the position of a smoothed resonance for the chemical potential in the pancake geometry at positive scattering length.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15872v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Yu. Cherny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addendum to "Power-law decay of the fraction of the mixed eigenstates in kicked top model with mixed-type classical phase space"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15874v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By using the Krylov subspace technique to generate the spin coherent states in kicked top model, a prototype model for studying quantum chaos, the accessible system size for studying the Husimi functions of eigenstates can be much larger than that reported in the literature and our previous study Phys. Rev. E 108, 054217 (2023) [arXiv:2308.04824]. In the fully chaotic kicked top, we find that the mean Wehrl entropy localization measure approaches the prediction given by the Circular Unitary Ensemble. In the mixed-type case, we identify mixed eigenstates by the overlap of the Husimi function with regular and chaotic regions in classical compact phase space. Numerically, we show that the fraction of mixed eigenstates scales as $j^{-\zeta}$, a power-law decay as the system size $j$ increases, across nearly two orders of magnitude. This provides supporting evidence for the principle of uniform semiclassical condensation of Husimi functions and the Berry-Robnik picture in the semiclassical limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15874v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua Yan, Qian Wang, Marko Robnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong coupling non-Markovian quantum thermodynamics using exact dynamics of a central spin surrounded by a spin bath and the role of a canonical Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15915v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The focus is on understanding the quantum thermodynamics of strongly coupled non-Markovian quantum systems. To this end, a non-trivial, non-Markovian model of a central spin surrounded by a spin bath is taken up, and its exact evolution is derived for arbitrary system-bath couplings. The fundamental quantum thermodynamic quantities, such as system and bath internal energies, work, heat, entropy production, and ergotropy, are calculated using the dynamics and original system (bath) Hamiltonian. An explicit expression for the work, a mismatch between the system and bath internal energies, is derived. Further, an interesting observation relevant to the spin bath acting as a charger is made in a scenario where the central spin is envisaged as a quantum battery. The role of a canonical Hamiltonian in calculating the above thermodynamic quantities, a recently developed technique, is also investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15915v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Devvrat Tiwari, Baibhab Bose, Subhashish Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity Measure Diagnostics of Ergodic to Many-Body Localization Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15940v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce new diagnostics of the transition between the ergodic and many-body localization phases, which are based on complexity measures defined via the probability distribution function of the Lanczos coefficients of the tri-diagonalized Hamiltonian. We use these complexity measures to analyze the power-law random banded matrix model as a function of the correlation strength and show that the moments and the entropy of the distribution diagnose the ergodic to many-body transition, as well as the distinctive feature of the phases concerning the memory of the initial conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15940v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khen Cohen, Yaron Oz, De-liang Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new non-extensive equation of state for the fluid phases of argon including the metastable states, from the melting line to 2300 K and 50 GPa</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1504.00633</link>
      <description>arXiv:1504.00633v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new equation of state for argon has been developed in view to extend the range of validity of the equation of state previously proposed by Tegeler et al. (Ref. 4) and to obtain a better physical description of the experimental thermodynamic data for the whole fluid region (single-phase, metastable and saturation states). As proposed by Tegeler et al., this equation is also based on a functional form of the residual part of the reduced Helmholtz free energy. However in this work, the fundamental equation for the Helmholtz free energy has been derived from the measured quantities CV(rho,T) and P(rho,T). The empirical description of the isochoric heat capacity CV(rho,T) is based on an original empirical description containing explicitly the metastable states. The thermodynamic properties (internal energy, entropy, free energy) are then obtained by combining integration of CV(rho,T). The arbitrary functions introduced by the integration process have been deduced from a comparison between calculated and experimental pressure P(rho,T) data. The new formulation is valid for the whole fluid region from the melting line to 2300 K and for pressures up to 50 GPa. It also predicts existence of a maximum of the isochoric heat capacity CV along isochors as experimentally observed in several other fluids. For many applications, an approximate form of the equation of state for the liquid phase may be sufficient. A Tait-Tammann equation is therefore proposed between the triple point temperature and 148 K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1504.00633v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/fluids9050102</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Fluids 2024, 9, 102</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>F. Aitken, A. Denat, F. Volino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derivation of the generalized Zurek's bound from a detailed fluctuation theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16269v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The minimal heat that must be released to the reservoir when a single input $x$ is mapped to a single output $y$ is considered. It was previously argued by Zurek in an informal style that the minimal heat should be $K(x|y)$. Recently, Kolchinsky has rigorously proved a generalized Zurek's bound in the Hamiltonian "two-point measurement" scheme, which implies a trade-off between heat, noise and protocol complexity in a computation from $x$ to $y$. Here we propose another proof of the generalized Zurek's bound from a detailed fluctuation theorem, showing that the generalized Zurek's bound holds in any system that satisfies a DFT. Several applications of the bound are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16269v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihai Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical separation of charge and energy transport in one-dimensional Mott insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16234v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: One-dimensional Mott insulators can be described using the sine-Gordon model, an integrable quantum field theory that provides the low-energy effective description of several one-dimensional gapped condensed matter systems, including recent realizations with trapped ultra-cold atoms. Employing the theory of Generalized Hydrodynamics, we demonstrate that this model exhibits separation of the transport of topological charge vs. energy. Analysis of the quasiparticle dynamics reveals that the mechanism behind the separation is the reflective scattering between topologically charged kinks/antikinks. The effect of these scattering events is most pronounced at strong coupling and low temperatures, where the distribution of quasiparticles is narrow compared to the reflective scattering amplitude. This effect results in a distinctively shaped "arrowhead" light cone for the topological charge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16234v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.L161112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>F. M{\o}ller, B. C. Nagy, M. Kormos and G. Tak\'acs, Phys. Rev. B 109, L161112 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Frederik M{\o}ller, Botond C. Nagy, M\'arton Kormos, G\'abor Tak\'acs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum dynamics of the effective field theory of the Calogero-Sutherland model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10011v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the known effective field theory of the Calogero-Sutherland model in the thermodynamic limit of large number of particles, obtained from the standard procedure in conformal field theory: the Hilbert space is constructed a priori in terms of irreducible representations of the symmetry algebra, and not by diagonalization of the hamiltonian, which is given in terms of fields that carry representations of the W-infinity algebra (representing the incompressibility of the Fermi sea). Nevertheless, the role of the effective hamiltonian of the theory is to establish a specific dynamics, which deserves further consideration. We show that the time evolution of the (chiral or antichiral) density field is given by the quantum Benjamin-Ono equation, in agreement with previous results obtained from the alternative description of the continuous limit of the model, based on quantum hydrodynamics. In this study, all calculations are performed at the quantum operator level, without making any assumption on the semiclassical limit of the fields and their equations of motion. This result may be considered as a reliable indication of the equivalence between the quantum field theoretic and quantum hydrodynamical formulations of the effective theories of the model. A one-dimensional quantum compressible fluid that includes both chiralities is the physical picture that emerges for the continuous limit of the Calogero-Sutherland model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10011v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico L. Bottesi, Guillermo R. Zemba</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
