<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 05:01:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral Instabilities in Driven-Dissipative Quantum Liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nonequilibrium dynamics of periodically driven Tomonaga-Luttinger liquids (TLLs) coupled to a thermal bath using a Floquet-Lindblad approach. When the coupling to the bath satisfies detailed balance, we obtain a condition for parametric instabilities to be suppressed, symmetrically for both chiralities. Remarkably, by designing a purely chiral coupling to the bath, instead of instability suppression, we uncover a driven-dissipative phase transition between the former symmetric parametric instability and a new chiral parametric instability. In the latter, a single chirality of bosonic quasiparticles gets exponentially amplified, leading to a dynamical chiral imbalance within the TLL, reminiscent of the non-Hermitian skin effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04443v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Xing Lin, Bastien Lapierre, Per Moosavi, Shinsei Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enskog and Enskog-Vlasov equations with a slightly modified correlation factor and their H theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A novel modification of the original Enskog equation is proposed. The modification is much simpler than that is made in the modified (or revised) Enskog equation proposed by van Beijeren \&amp; Ernst in 1973 and does not require a consideration of many-body configuration. The proposed modification is general enough to be adapted to various equations of states for non-ideal gases. It is shown that the H-theorem can be established for the Enskog and the Enskog--Vlasov equation with the proposed modification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04744v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shigeru Takata, Aoto Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact value theorem for electric double layers with modulated surface charge density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The contact value theorem was originally derived for Coulomb fluids of mobile charged particles in thermal equilibrium, in the presence of interfaces carrying a {\em uniform} surface charge density and in the absence of dielectric discontinuities. It relates the pressure (the effective force) between two parallel electric double layers to the particle number density and the surface charge density at the interface, separately for each of the two electric double layers. In this paper, we generalise the contact value theorem to electric double layers with interfaces carrying a {\em modulated} surface charge density. The derivation is based on balance of forces exerted on interfaces. The relevance of particular terms of the contact value theorem is tested on an exactly solvable two-dimensional Coulomb system with counterions only at the coupling constant $\Gamma=2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04862v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 58 (2025) 065001</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ladislav \v{S}amaj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling corrections in driven critical dynamics: Application to a two-dimensional dimerized quantum Heisenberg model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Driven critical dynamics in quantum phase transitions holds significant theoretical importance, and also practical applications in fast-developing quantum devices. While scaling corrections have been shown to play important roles in fully characterizing equilibrium quantum criticality, their impact on nonequilibrium critical dynamics has not been extensively explored. In this work, we investigate the driven critical dynamics in a two-dimensional quantum Heisenberg model. We find that in this model the scaling corrections arising from both finite system size and finite driving rate must be incorporated into the finite-time scaling form in order to properly describe the nonequilibrium scaling behaviors. In addition, improved scaling relations are obtained from the expansion of the full scaling form. We numerically verify these scaling forms and improved scaling relations for different starting states using the nonequilibrium quantum Monte Carlo algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04927v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Wen Liu, Shuai Yin, Yu-Rong Shu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy dynamics in a class of local random matrix Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Random matrix theory yields valuable insights into the universal features of quantum many-body chaotic systems. Although all-to-all interactions are traditionally studied, many interesting dynamical questions, such as transport of a conserved density, require a notion of spatially local interactions. We study the transport of the energy, the most basic conserved density, in few-body and 1D chains of nearest-neighbor random matrix terms that square to one. In the few-body but large local Hilbert space dimension case, we develop a mapping for the energy dynamics to a single-particle hopping picture. This allows for the computation of the energy density autocorrelators and an out-of-time-ordered correlator of the energy density. In the 1D chain, we numerically study the energy transport for a small local Hilbert space dimension. We also discuss the density of states throughout and touch upon the relation to free probability theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05045v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kl\'ee Pollock, Jonathan D. Kroth, Nathan Pagliaroli, Thomas Iadecola, Jonathan Riddell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derivation and thermodynamiclly consistent coupling of a Debye-H\"uckel type energy to a steric electrolyte model and application to the apparent molar volume and phase boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04344v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose to determine the size parameters of a steric electrolyte model from the experimental data of apparent molar volume obtained from mass density measurements. Thereby, we avoid the difficulties associated with modeling the complex structure of the double layer. To this end, we derive a Debye-H\"uckel-like model of the electric ion-ion interaction for non-constant dielectric susceptibility, which does not depend on any kind of charging process due to its foundation in the general framework of non-equilibrium electro-thermodynamics. The derivation, however, leads to a novel thermodynamic consistency condition for the temperature dependence of the susceptibility. Due to its contributions to the total pressure, the consistent coupling of this new contribution to the free energy requires subtle modifications in the derivation of the simple mixing model for electrolytes. The coupled model is then applied to the apparent molar volume for various related monovalent salts over a wider range of salt concentrations and temperatures, and classical tests of the electrolyte theory at phase boundaries are investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04344v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang Dreyer, R\"udiger M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry Properties of Quantum Dynamical Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04442v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the relation between the Alicki-Fannes-Lindblad (AFL) quantum dynamical entropy and quantum symmetries. We show that, while the cumulative AFL entropy generally saturates to the dimensional bound at late times for chaotic dynamics, this saturation value is distinctively lower when the partitions (measurements) respect the symmetries. We provide rigorous analysis to this lowered value in three cases: Abelian symmetries, anticommuting unitaries, and non-Abelian symmetries. We further support our analytical results with numerical simulations of the perturbed quantum cat maps. Our findings highlight the complex relationship between the cumulative AFL entropy and symmetries, and suggest that caution is needed when interpreting it as an indicator of quantum chaos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04442v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric D. Schultz, Keiichiro Furuya, Laimei Nie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why ETH? On thermalization and locality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04784v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The eigenstate thermalization hypothesis (ETH) is foundational to modern discussions of thermalization in closed quantum systems. In this work, we expand on traditional explanations for the prevalence of ETH by emphasizing the role of operator locality. We introduce an operator-specific perturbation problem that can be thought of as a means of understanding the onset or breakdown of ETH for specific classes of operators in a given system. We derive explicit functional forms for the off-diagonal variances of operator matrix elements for typical local operators under various `scrambling ansatzes', expressed in terms of system parameters and parameters of the corresponding perturbation problem. We provide simple tests and illustrations of these ideas in chaotic spin chain systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04784v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Eccles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirac's variational approach to semiclassical Kramers problem in Smoluchowski limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05079v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kramers escape from a metastable state in the presence of both thermal and quantum fluctuations under strong damping is treated as a thermally activated process in a quantum modified semiclassical potential. Dirac's time-dependent variational method together with the Jackiw-Kerman function is employed to derive the semiclassical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05079v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Choon-Lin Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling the Effects of Curvature and Misorientation on the Shrinkage Behavior of Loop-Shaped Grain Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05112v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The material properties of polycrystals are strongly affected by the evolution and coarsening of their internal grain structures. Yet, studying this process is challenging due to the complex interactions within grain boundary networks. Here, we systematically investigate the shrinkage of isolated loop-shaped grain boundaries in 2D colloidal crystals. Unexpectedly, we find that shear coupling decreases with increasing grain misorientation, contrary to geometric predictions. This counterintuitive result is attributed to enhanced concurrent sliding driven by the annihilation of dislocations. Furthermore, by focusing on the evolution of the grain size, we reveal a transition in shrinkage kinetics between small and large loop sizes, offering an explanation for previously observed discrepancies in grain boundary mobility. These findings reveal a more intricate dependence of grain boundary behavior on curvature and misorientation than previously reported, offering new insights into polycrystal coarsening dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05112v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Camerin, Susana Mar\'in-Aguilar, Tim Griffioen, Mathieu G. Baltussen, Roel P. A. Dullens, Berend van der Meer, Marjolein Dijkstra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation thermometry of an atom-resolved quantum gas: Beyond the fluctuation-dissipation theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermometry is essential for studying many-body physics with ultracold atoms. Accurately measuring low temperatures in these systems, however, remains a significant challenge due to the absence of a universal thermometer. Most widely applicable methods, such as fitting of in-situ density profiles or standard fluctuation thermometry, are limited by the requirement of global thermal equilibrium and inapplicability to homogeneous systems. In this work, we introduce a novel in-situ thermometry for quantum gases, leveraging single-atom resolved measurements via quantum gas microscopy, and demonstrate it on an ideal Fermi gas. By analyzing number fluctuations in probe volumes with approximately one atom on average, we extract both global and local temperatures over a broad dynamic range. Unlike traditional fluctuation thermometry, our method does not rely on the fluctuation-dissipation theorem and is based instead on the exact relationship between number fluctuations and density-density correlations. In the low-temperature regime, it allows us to observe significant deviations from fluctuation-dissipation predictions, uncovering sub-extensive fluctuations. Our method is applicable to systems with arbitrary trapping potentials, requiring neither precise trap calibration nor global thermal equilibrium. This nearly universal thermometer for quantum gases overcomes key limitations of existing techniques, paving the way for more accurate and versatile temperature measurements in ultracold quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05132v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Dixmerias, Joris Verstraten, Cyprien Daix, Bruno Peaudecerf, Tim de Jongh, Tarik Yefsah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of a dynamic magneto-chiral instability in photoexcited tellurium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a system of charged chiral fermions driven out of equilibrium, an electric current parallel to the magnetic field can generate a dynamic instability by which electromagnetic waves become amplified. Whether a similar instability can occur in chiral solid-state systems remains an open question. Using time-domain terahertz (THz) emission spectroscopy, we detect signatures of what we dub a ``dynamic magneto-chiral instability" in elemental tellurium, a structurally chiral crystal. Upon transient photoexcitation in a moderate external magnetic field, tellurium emits THz radiation consisting of coherent modes that amplify over time. An explanation for this amplification is proposed using a theoretical model based on a dynamic instability of electromagnetic waves interacting with infrared-active oscillators of impurity acceptor states in tellurium to form an amplifying polariton. Our work not only uncovers the presence of a magneto-chiral instability but also highlights its promise for THz-wave amplification in chiral materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05170v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yijing Huang, Nick Abboud, Yinchuan Lv, Penghao Zhu, Azel Murzabekova, Changjun Lee, Emma A. Pappas, Dominic Petruzzi, Jason Y. Yan, Dipanjan Chauduri, Peter Abbamonte, Daniel P. Shoemaker, Rafael M. Fernandes, Jorge Noronha, Fahad Mahmood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed fixed resources exchanging particles: Phases of an asymmetric exclusion process connected to two reservoirs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05945v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose and study a conceptual one-dimensional model to explore how the combined interplay between fixed resources and particle exchanges between different parts of an extended system can affect the stationary densities in a current carrying channel connecting different parts of the system. To this end, we consider a model composed of a totally asymmetric simple exclusion process (TASEP) connecting two particle reservoirs without any internal dynamics but which can directly exchange particles between each other, ensuring nonvanishing currents in the steady states. The total particle number in the system that defines the "resources" available, although is kept constant by the model dynamics, can take any value independent of the model parameters that define the dynamics of the model. We show how the resulting phase diagrams of the model are controlled by the parameters, which define the various dynamical update rules together with the total available resources. These control parameters can be tuned to make the density on the TASEP lane globally uniform or piecewise continuous with localized domain walls, and can also control populations of the two reservoirs. In general, the phase diagrams are quite different from a TASEP with open boundaries. In the limit of large amount of resources, the phase diagrams in the plane of the control parameters become topologically identical to that for an open TASEP together with delocalization of domain walls.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05945v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Pal, Parna Roy, Abhik Basu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backbone exponent and annulus crossing probability for planar percolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06419v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the recent derivation of the backbone exponent for 2D percolation. In contrast to previously known exactly solved percolation exponents, the backbone exponent is a transcendental number, which is a root of an elementary equation. We also report an exact formula for the probability that there are two disjoint paths of the same color crossing an annulus. The backbone exponent captures the leading asymptotic, while the other roots of the elementary equation capture the asymptotic of the remaining terms. This suggests that the backbone exponent is part of a conformal field theory (CFT) whose bulk spectrum contains this set of roots. Our approach is based on the coupling between SLE curves and Liouville quantum gravity (LQG), and the integrability of Liouville CFT that governs the LQG surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06419v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Nolin, Wei Qian, Xin Sun, Zijie Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo Transitions in the Finite-Size Blume-Capel Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01743v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article investigates the pseudo transitions of the Blume-Capel model on two-dimensional finite-size lattices. By employing the Wang-Landau sampling method and microcanonical inflection point analysis, we identified the positions of phase transitions as well as higher-order phase transitions. Through Metropolis sampling and canonical ensemble analysis, we determined the geometric characteristics of the system at these transition points. When the crystal field parameter $D$ exceeds 1.965, crossing the tricritical point, no third-order dependent phase transition is observed. However, a fourth-order independent transition was identified in the high-temperature region, and through Metropolis sampling analysis, a phase transition from the ordered paramagnetic phase to the disordered paramagnetic phase was confirmed, enhancing the phase diagram. Furthermore, the positions of the third-order phase transition obtained from both microcanonical and canonical analyses are consistent and mutually corroborative. We speculate that third-order dependent transitions vanish in the presence of strong first-order phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01743v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Shi, Wei Liu, Xiang Li, Xin Zhang, Fangfang Wang, Kai Qi, Zengru Di</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Correlation Unifies Nonequilibrium Response Theory for Arbitrary Markov Jump Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01050v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding how systems respond to external perturbations is a fundamental challenge in physics, particularly for non-equilibrium and non-stationary processes. The fluctuation-dissipation theorem provides a complete framework for near-equilibrium systems, and various bounds are recently reported for specific non-equilibrium regimes. Here, we present an exact response equality for arbitrary Markov processes that decompose system response into spatial correlations of local dynamical events. This decomposition reveals that response properties are encoded in correlations between transitions and dwelling times across the network, providing a natural generalization of the fluctuation-dissipation theorem to generic non-equilibrium processes. Our theory unifies existing response bounds, extends them to time-dependent processes, and reveals fundamental monotonicity properties of the tightness of multi-parameter response inequalities. Beyond its theoretical significance, this framework enables efficient numerical evaluation of response properties from sampling unperturbed trajectory, offering significant advantages over traditional finite-difference approaches for estimating response properties of complex networks and biological systems far from equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01050v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiming Zheng, Zhiyue Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superdiffusive transport in chaotic quantum systems with nodal interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08381v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a class of interacting fermionic quantum models in $d$ dimensions with nodal interactions that exhibit superdiffusive transport. We establish non-perturbatively that the nodal structure of the interactions gives rise to long-lived quasiparticle excitations that result in a diverging diffusion constant, even though the system is fully chaotic. Using a Boltzmann equation approach, we find that the charge mode acquires an anomalous dispersion relation at long wavelength $\omega(q) \sim q^{z} $ with dynamical exponent $z={\rm min}[(2n+d)/2n,2]$, where $n$ is the order of the nodal point in momentum space. We verify our predictions in one dimensional systems using tensor-network techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08381v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Peng Wang, Jie Ren, Sarang Gopalakrishnan, Romain Vasseur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation Dissipation Relations for the Non-Reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02524v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent results demonstrate how deviations from equilibrium fluctuation-dissipation theorem can be quantified for active field theories by deriving exact fluctuations dissipation relations that involve the entropy production [M. K. Johnsrud and R. Golestanian, arXiv:2409.14977]. Here we develop and employ diagrammatic tools to perform perturbative calculations for a paradigmatic active field theory, the Non-Reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard (NRCH) model. We obtain analytical results, which serve as an illustration of how to implement the recently developed framework to active field theories, and help to illuminate the specific non-equilibrium characteristics of the NRCH field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02524v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Kj{\o}llesdal Johnsrud, Ramin Golestanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigid clusters in shear-thickening suspensions: a nonequilibrium critical transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15165v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The onset and growth of rigid clusters in a two-dimensional (2D) suspension in shear flow are studied by numerical simulations. The suspension exhibits the lubricated-to-frictional rheology transition, but the key results here are for stresses above the levels that cause extreme shear-thickening. At large solid fraction, $\phi$, but below the stress-dependent jamming fraction, we find a critical $\phi_{c}(\sigma,\mu)$ where $\sigma$ is a dimensionless shear stress and $\mu$ is the interparticle friction coefficient. For $\phi&gt;\phi_c$, the proportion of particles in rigid clusters grows sharply, as $f_{\rm rig} \sim |\phi-\phi_{c}|^{\beta}$ with $\beta=1/8$. The fluctuations in the fraction of particles in rigid clusters yield a susceptibility measure $\chi_{\rm rig} \sim |\phi-\phi_{c}|^{-\gamma}$ with $\gamma = 7/4$. The system is thus found to exhibit criticality. The results are shown to depend on an effective field $h(\mu)$, which provides data collapse near $\phi_c$ for both $f_{\rm rig}$ and $\chi_{\rm rig}$. This behavior occurs over a range of stresses, with $\phi_c(\sigma,\mu)$ increasing as the stress decreases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15165v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aritra Santra, Michel Orsi, Bulbul Chakraborty, Jeffrey F. Morris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential of mean force and underscreening of polarizable colloids in concentrated electrolytes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01512v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study uses advanced numerical methods to estimate the mean force potential (PMF) between charged, polarizable colloidal particles in dense electrolytes. We observe that when the Debye screening length, $\lambda_{\mathrm{D}}$, is below the hydrated ion size, the PMF shows discernible oscillations of purely electrostatic origin as opposed to chemical affinity, in addition to the expected decay in DLVO theory. Moreover, our findings suggest concentrated electrolytes are significantly less efficient at muting electrostatic interactions in electrostatically stabilized colloidal suspensions, potentially having significant implications for our understanding of colloidal stability and the forces that govern the behavior of concentrated charged soft matter systems beyond DLVO theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01512v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Krucker-Velasquez, Martin Z. Bazant, Alfredo Alexander-Katz, James W. Swan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous time crystals as a PT symmetric state and the emergence of critical exceptional points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09018v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Continuous time-translation symmetry is often spontaneously broken in open quantum systems, and the condition for their emergence has been actively investigated. However, there are only a few cases in which its condition for appearance has been fully elucidated. In this Letter, we show that a Lindbladian parity-time ($\mathcal{PT}$) symmetry can generically produce persistent periodic oscillations in a wide class of systems. This includes one-collective spin models, which have been studied thoroughly in the context of dissipative continuous time crystals, and spatially extended bipartite bosonic systems with conserved particle number. Interestingly, the periodic orbits in the PT-symmetric phase are found to be center-type, implying an initial state dependence. These results are established by proving that the Lindbladian $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry at the microscopic level implies a nonlinear PT symmetry, and by performing a linear stability analysis near the transition point. This research will further our understanding of novel non-equilibrium phases of matter and phase transitions with spontaneous anti-unitary symmetry breaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09018v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuma Nakanishi, Ryo Hanai, Tomohiro Sasamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic spreading in random quantum circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03929v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Magic is the resource that quantifies the amount of beyond-Clifford operations necessary for universal quantum computing. It bounds the cost of classically simulating quantum systems via stabilizer circuits central to quantum error correction and computation. How rapidly do generic many-body dynamics generate magic resources under the constraints of locality and unitarity? We address this central question by exploring magic spreading in brick-wall random unitary circuits. We explore scalable magic measures intimately connected to the algebraic structure of the Clifford group. These metrics enable the investigation of the spreading of magic for system sizes of up to $N=1024$ qudits, surpassing the previous state-of-the-art, which was restricted to about a dozen qudits. We demonstrate that magic resources equilibrate on timescales logarithmic in the system size, akin to anti-concentration and Hilbert space delocalization phenomena, but qualitatively different from the spreading of entanglement entropy. As random circuits are minimal models for chaotic dynamics, we conjecture that our findings describe the phenomenology of magic resources growth in a broad class of chaotic many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03929v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xhek Turkeshi, Emanuele Tirrito, Piotr Sierant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Interplay of Heterogeneity and Product Detachment in Templated Polymer Copying</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21488v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Templated copolymerization, in which information stored in the sequence of a heteropolymer template is copied into another polymer product, is the mechanism behind all known methods of genetic information transfer. A key aspect of templated copolymerization is the eventual detachment of the product from the template. A second key feature of natural biochemical systems is that the template-binding free energies of both correctly-matched and incorrect monomers are heterogeneous. Previous work has considered the thermodynamic consequences of detachment, and the consequences of heterogeniety for polymerisation speed and accuracy, but the interplay of both separation and heterogeniety remains unexplored. In this work, we investigate a minimal model of templated copying that simultaneously incorporates both detachment from behind the leading edge of the growing copy and heterogeneous interactions. We first extend existing coarse-graining methods for models of polymerisation to allow for heterogeneous interactions. We then show that heterogeneous copying systems with explicit detachment do not exhibit the subdiffusive behaviour observed in the absence of detachment when near equilibrium. Next, we show that heterogeneity in correct monomer interactions tends to result in slower, less accurate copying, while heterogeneity in incorrect monomer interactions tends to result in faster, more accurate copying, due to an increased roughness in the free energy landscape of either correct or incorrect monomer pairs. Finally, we show that heterogeneity can improve on known thermodynamic efficiencies of homogeneous copying, but these increased thermodynamic efficiencies do not always translate to increased efficiencies of information transfer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21488v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy E. B. Guntoro, Benjamin J. Qureshi, Thomas E. Ouldridge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal projections of hypercubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10257v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Projections of hypercubes are widely used for visualizing high-dimensional binary state spaces across various scientific fields. Conventional methods for projecting hypercubes, however, face practical difficulties. Manual methods require nontrivial adjustments of the projection basis, while optimization-based algorithms limit the interpretability and reproducibility of the resulting plots. These limitations motivate the exploration of theoretically analyzable projection algorithms such as principal component analysis (PCA). Here, we investigate the mathematical properties of PCA for projecting hypercubes. Our numerical and analytical results show that PCA effectively captures polarized distributions within the state space. This property enables the assessment of the asymptotic distribution of projected vertices and error bounds, thus characterizing the performance of PCA in the projected space. We demonstrate the application of PCA to visualize the hypercubic energy landscapes of Ising spin systems. By adding projected hypercubic edges, these visualizations reveal pathways of correlated spin flips. Our work contributes to a better understanding of how PCA can be applied to explore high-dimensional binary data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10257v2</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiaki Horiike, Shin Fujishiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
