<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 02:38:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Partition Function Zeros of Paths and Normalization Zeros of ASEPS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14953v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We exploit the equivalence between the partition function of an adsorbing Dyck walk model and the Asymmetric Simple Exclusion Process (ASEP) normalization to obtain the thermodynamic limit of the locus of the ASEP normalization zeros from a conformal map. We discuss the equivalence between this approach and using an electrostatic analogy to determine the locus, both in the case of the ASEP and the random allocation model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14953v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zdzislaw Burda, Desmond A. Johnston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete classification of integrability and non-integrability of S=1/2 spin chains with symmetric next-nearest-neighbor interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study S=1/2 quantum spin chains with shift-invariant and inversion-symmetric next-nearest-neighbor interaction, also known as zigzag spin chains. We completely classify the integrability and non-integrability of the above class of spin systems. We prove that in this class there are only two integrable models, a classical model and a model solvable by the Bethe ansatz, and all the remaining systems are non-integrable. Our classification theorem confirms that within this class of spin chains, there is no missing integrable model. This theorem also implies the absence of intermediate models with a finite number of local conserved quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15506v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoto Shiraishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving accuracy of tree-tensor network approach by optimization of network structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Numerical methods based on tensor networks have been extensively explored in the research of quantum many-body systems in recent years. It has been recognized that the ability of tensor networks to describe a quantum many-body state crucially depends on the spatial structure of the network. In the previous work, we proposed an algorithm based on tree tensor networks (TTNs) that automatically optimizes the structure of TTN according to the spatial profile of entanglement in the state of interest. In this paper, we precisely analyze how detailed updating schemes in the structural optimization algorithm affect its computational accuracy for the random XY-exchange model under random magnetic fields and the Richardson model. We then find that for the random XY model, on the one hand, the algorithm achieves improved accuracy, and the stochastic algorithm, which selects the local network structure probabilistically, is notably effective. For the Richardson model, on the other hand, the resulting numerical accuracy subtly depends on the initial TTN and the updating schemes. In particular, the algorithm without the stochastic updating scheme certainly improves the accuracy, while the one with the stochastic updates results in poor accuracy due to the effect of randomizing the network structure at the early stage of the calculation. These results indicate that the algorithm successfully improves the accuracy of the numerical calculations for quantum many-body states, while it is essential to appropriately choose the updating scheme as well as the initial TTN structure, depending on the systems treated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15514v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toshiya Hikihara, Hiroshi Ueda, Kouichi Okunishi, Kenji Harada, Tomotoshi Nishino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing and Ergodicity in Systems with Long-Range Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a theory of collisionless relaxation in systems with long-range interactions. Contrary to Lynden-Bell's theory of violent relaxation, which assumes global ergodicity and mixing, we show that quasi-stationary states (qSS) observed in these systems exhibit broken global ergodicity. We propose that relaxation towards equilibrium occurs through a process of local mixing, where particles spread over energy shells defined by the manifold to which their trajectories are confined. To demonstrate our theory, we study the Hamiltonian Mean Field (HMF) model, a paradigmatic system with long-range interactions. Our theory accurately predicts the particle distribution functions in qSS observed in molecular dynamics simulations without any adjustable parameters. Additionally, it precisely forecasts the phase transitions observed in the HMF model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15593v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tarc\'isio Nunes Teles, Renato Pakter, Yan Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Virial Expansion in Hard Sphere Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Virial expansion is a traditional approach in statistical mechanics that expresses thermodynamic quantities, such as pressure $p$, as power series of density or chemical potential. Its radius of convergence can serve as a potential indicator of phase transition. In this study, we investigate the virial expansion of the hard-sphere model, using the known dimensionless virial coefficients $\tilde{B}_k^{}~(k=1,2,\cdots)$ up to the $12$th order. We find that it is well fitted by $\tilde{B}_k^{}=1.28\times k^{1.90}$, corresponding to the analytic continuation of the virial expansion of the pressure as $\sim \mathrm{Li}_{-1.90}^{}(\eta)$, where $\eta$ is the packing fraction and $\mathrm{Li}_s^{}(x)$ is the polylogarithm function. This implies the absence of singular behavior in the physical parameter space $\eta\leq \eta_{\mathrm{max}}^{}\approx 0.74$ and no indication of phase transition in the virial expansion approach. In addition, we calculate the cluster-integral coefficients $\{b_l^{}\}_{l=1}^\infty$ and observe that their asymptotic behavior resembles the results obtained in the large dimension limit ($D\rightarrow \infty$), suggesting that $D=3$ might be already regarded as large dimension. However, the existence of phase transition in the hard-sphere model has been confirmed by numerous simulations, which clearly indicates that a naive extrapolation of the virial series can lead to unphysical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15766v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiyoharu Kawana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Sandpiles to Complex Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we address a longstanding challenge in self-organized criticality (SOC) systems: establishing a connection between sandpiles and complex networks. Our approach employs a similarity-based transfer function characterized by two parameters, $\mathcal{R}=(r_1, r_2)$. Here, $r_1$ quantifies the similarity of local activities, while $r_2$ governs the filtration process used to convert a weighted network into a binary one. We reveal that the degree centrality distribution of the resulting network follows a generalized Gamma distribution (GGD), which transitions to a power-law distribution under specific conditions. The GGD exponents, estimated numerically, exhibit a dependency on $\mathcal{R}$. Notably, while both decreasing $r_1$ and $r_2$ lead to denser networks, $r_2$ plays a more significant role in influencing network density. Furthermore, the Shannon entropy is observed to decrease linearly with increasing $r_2$, whereas its variation with $r_1$ is more gradual. An analytical expression for the Shannon entropy is proposed. To characterize the network structure, we investigate the clustering coefficient ($cc$), eigenvalue centrality ($e$), closeness centrality ($c$), and betweenness centrality ($b$). The distributions of $cc$, $e$, and $c$ exhibit peaked profiles, while $b$ displays a power-law distribution over a finite interval of $k$. Additionally, we explore correlations between the exponents and identify a specific parameter regime of $\mathcal{R}$ and $k$ where the $e-k$, $c-k$, and $b-k$ correlations become negative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15845v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abbas Shoja-Daliklidash, Morteza Nattagh-Najafi, Nasser Sepehri-Javan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreversible thermodynamics and Glansdorff-Prigogine principle derived from stochastic thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the main equations of irreversible thermodynamic including the expression for the Glansdorff-Prigogine extremal principle from stochastic thermodynamics. To this end, we analyze a system that is subject to gradients of temperature and external forces that induce the appearance of fluxes of several sorts and the creation of entropy. We show that the rate of entropy production is a convex function of the fluxes, from which follows that the excess entropy production is nonnegative, which is an expression of the Glansdorff-Prigogine principle. We show that the Lyapunov function associated with the excess entropy production can be identified with a thermodynamic potential in the special case where the gradients of temperature are absent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16059v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T\^ania Tom\'e, M\'ario J. de Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussian density fluctuations in the Dean-Kawasaki equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computing analytically the $n$-point density correlations in systems of interacting particles is a long-standing problem of statistical physics, with a broad range of applications, from the interpretation of scattering experiments in simple liquids, to the quantitative description of the slow and cooperative dynamics in glass formers. For Brownian particles, i.e. with overdamped Langevin dynamics, the microscopic density obeys a stochastic evolution equation, known as the Dean-Kawasaki equation. In spite of the importance of this equation, its complexity makes it very difficult to analyze the statistics of the microscopic density beyond simple Gaussian approximations. In this work, resorting to a path-integral description of the stochastic dynamics and relying on the formalism of macroscopic fluctuation theory, we go beyond the usual linearization of the Dean-Kawasaki equation, and we compute perturbatively the three-point density correlation functions, in the limit of high-density and weak interactions between the particles. This exact result opens the way to using the Dean-Kawasaki beyond the simple Gaussian treatments, and could find applications to understand many fluctuation-related effects in soft and active matter systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16206v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Illien</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring full counting statistics in a quantum simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14424v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quantum mechanics, the probability distribution function (PDF) and full counting statistics (FCS) play a fundamental role in characterizing the fluctuations of quantum observables, as they encode the complete information about these fluctuations. In this letter, we measure these two quantities in a trapped-ion quantum simulator for the transverse and longitudinal magnetization within a subsystem. We utilize the toolbox of classical shadows to postprocess the measurements performed in random bases. The measurement scheme efficiently allows access to the FCS and PDF of all possible operators on desired choices of subsystems of an extended quantum system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14424v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lata Kh Joshi, Filiberto Ares, Manoj K. Joshi, Christian F. Roos, Pasquale Calabrese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turing in the shadows of Nobel and Abel: an algorithmic story behind two recent prizes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15312v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The 2021 Nobel Prize in physics was awarded to Giorgio Parisi ``for the discovery of the interplay of disorder and fluctuations in physical systems from atomic to planetary scales,'' and the 2024 Abel Prize in mathematics was awarded to Michel Talagrand ``for his groundbreaking contributions to probability theory and functional analysis, with outstanding applications in mathematical physics and statistics.'' What remains largely absent in the popular descriptions of these prizes, however, is the profound contributions the works of both individuals have had to the field of \emph{algorithms and computation}. The ideas first developed by Parisi and his collaborators relying on remarkably precise physics intuition, and later confirmed by Talagrand and others by no less remarkable mathematical techniques, have revolutionized the way we think algorithmically about optimization problems involving randomness. This is true both in terms of the existence of fast algorithms for some optimization problems, but also in terms of our persistent failures of finding such algorithms for some other optimization problems.
  The goal of this article is to highlight these developments and explain how the ideas pioneered by Parisi and Talagrand have led to a remarkably precise characterization of which optimization problems admit fast algorithms, versus those which do not, and furthermore to explain why this characterization holds true.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15312v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Notices of AMS, May 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Gamarnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure induced Structure Change and Anomalies in Thermodynamic Quantities and Transport Properties in Liquid Lithium Hydride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understand the nature of liquid structure and its evolution under different conditions is a major challenge in condensed physics and materials science. Here, we report a pressure-induced structure change spanning a wide pressure range in liquid-state lithium hydride (LiH) by first-principles molecular dynamic simulations. This behavior can be described as a continuous crossover from low pressure liquid with Li$^+$-H$^-$ duality symmetry to high pressure one with broken of duality symmetry. The thermodynamic quantities such as heat capacity and ionic transport properties such as diffusivity are also saliently impacted. It is important to stress that such behavior is firstly predicted for this category of materials, which is ubiquitous in universe as well as in industry applications. Lastly, a comprehensive high-pressure high-temperature phase diagram of LiH is constructed, which embodies rich physics in this previously-thought-simple ionic compound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15532v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.024102</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 024102 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>X. Z. Yan, Y. M. Chen, Hua Y. Geng, Y. F. Wang, Y. Sun, L. L. Zhang, H. Wang, Y. L. Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Mechanical Strain on Magnetic and Structural Properties of 2D Materials: A Monte Carlo study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15626v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The inherent flexibility of two dimensional materials allows for efficient manipulation of their physical properties through strain application, which is essential for the development of advanced nanoscale devices. This study aimed to understand the impact of mechanical strain on the magnetic properties of two dimensional materials using Monte Carlo simulations. The effects of several strain states on the magnetic properties were investigated using the Lennard Jones potential and bond length-dependent exchange interactions. The key parameters analyzed include the Lindemann coefficient, radial distribution function, and magnetization in relation to temperature and magnetic field. The results indicate that applying biaxial tensile strain generally reduces the critical temperature. In contrast, the biaxial compressive strain increased Tc within the elastic range, but decreased at higher strain levels. Both compressive and tensile strains significantly influence the ferromagnetic properties and structural ordering, as evidenced by magnetization hysteresis. Notably, pure shear strain did not induce disorder, leaving the magnetization unaffected. In addition, our findings suggest the potential of domain-formation mechanisms. This study provides comprehensive insights into the influence of mechanical strain on the magnetic behavior and structural integrity of 2D materials, offering valuable guidance for future research and advanced material design applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15626v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0227208</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>This article published in J. Chem. Phys. 161, 124705 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aytac Celik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-reciprocal interactions drive emergent chiral crystallites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a new type of 2D active material that exhibits macroscopic phases with two emergent broken symmetries: self-propelled achiral particles that form dense hexatic clusters, which spontaneously rotate. We experimentally realise active colloids that self-organise into both polar and hexatic crystallites, exhibiting exotic emergent phenomena. This is accompanied by a field theory of coupled order parameters formulated on symmetry principles, including non-reciprocity, to capture the non-equilibrium dynamics. We find that the presence of two interacting broken symmetry fields leads to the emergence of novel chiral phases built from (2D) achiral active colloids (here Quincke rollers). These phases are characterised by the presence of both clockwise and counterclockwise rotating clusters. We thus show that spontaneous rotation can emerge in non-equilibrium systems, even when the building blocks are achiral, due to non-reciprocally coupled broken symmetries. This interplay leads to self-organized stirring through counter-rotating vortices in confined colloidal systems, with cluster size controlled by external electric fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15996v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. J. Kole, Xichen Chao, Abraham Mauleon-Amieva, Ryo Hanai, C. Patrick Royall, Tanniemola B. Liverpool</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp low-temperature spectral asymptotics for reversible diffusions in temperature-dependent domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive novel sharp low-temperature asymptotics for the spectrum of the infinitesimal generator of the overdamped Langevin dynamics. The novelty is that this operator is endowed with homogeneous Dirichlet conditions at the boundary of a domain which depends on the temperature. From the point of view of stochastic processes, this gives information on the long-time behavior of the diffusion conditioned on non-absorption at the boundary, in the so-called quasistationary regime. Our results provide sharp estimates of the spectral gap and principal eigenvalue, extending the Eyring--Kramers formula. The phenomenology is richer than in the case of a fixed boundary and gives new insight into the sensitivity of the spectrum with respect to the shape of the domain near critical points of the energy function. Our work is motivated by--and is relevant to--the problem of finding optimal hyperparameters for accelerated molecular dynamics algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16082v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>No\'e Blassel, Tony Leli\`evre, Gabriel Stoltz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Melting through Barrier-Crossing: The Role of Equilibrium Thermally Activated Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16183v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Melting is often understood in purely equilibrium terms, where crystalline order disappears once the free energy of the solid equals that of the liquid. Yet at the microscopic level, the initiating events for melting can often be traced to the formation of defects or local ``jumps'' over interatomic barriers. In this work, we offer a unified interpretation of melting by focusing on the equilibrium fraction of particles whose energy exceeds a characteristic barrier \(E_a\). We show that when this fraction surpasses a small but critical threshold \cite{Feder1958,Kraftmakher1998} (on the order of \(10^{-4}\)-\(10^{-3}\)), the crystal loses its rigidity, thus reconciling Born's mechanical-instability picture with the older Lindemann notion of large atomic displacements. We derive this threshold condition from standard Boltzmann (and Bose/Fermi) statistics, ensuring consistency with standard thermodynamics. Our approach naturally extends to vortex lattices in superconductors (where vortex activation energies play the role of \(E_a\)) and to quantum-lattice systems (Hubbard-type models). Crucially, while the interpretation emphasizes barrier crossing, the criterion itself is built on equilibrium statistical mechanics, offering a transparent link between defect formation rates and the macroscopic transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16183v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongchao Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the phonon theory of liquid heat capacity: low-frequency shear modes and intramolecular vibrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16187v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modeling the heat capacity of liquids present fundamental difficulties due to the strong intermolecular particle interactions and large diffusive-like displacements. Based on the experimental evidence that the microscopic dynamics of liquids closely resemble those of solids, a phonon theory of liquid thermodynamics has been developed. Despite its success, the phonon theory of liquids relies on the questionable assumption that low-frequency shear excitations are propagating in nature and follow a Debye density of states. Furthermore, the same framework does not capture the contribution of intramolecular vibrations, which play a significant role in molecular liquids. In this work, we revisit the phonon theory of liquid heat capacity, introducing alternative approaches to model low-frequency shear modes. In particular, we consider the recently proposed idea of treating such modes as pure kinetic and we propose a novel approach based on identifying those low-frequency excitations as overdamped liquid-like modes with linear in frequency density of states. Moreover, we complete the theory by incorporating the effects of intramolecular vibrations. By comparing the theoretical predictions from these different approaches with the available data for the heat capacity of several liquids, we present a comprehensive evaluation of the original model and the newly proposed extensions. Despite all approaches perform well at low-temperatures, our results indicate that modeling low-frequency modes as overdamped liquid-like excitations yields the most accurate agreement with the data in the whole temperature range. Conversely, we demonstrate that treating these excitations as purely gas-like leads to significant inaccuracies, particularly at high temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16187v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Liu, Matteo Baggioli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic dynamics and Bose-Einstein condensation in liquid helium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.06323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.06323v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We review fundamental problems involved in liquid theory including both classical and quantum liquids. Understanding classical liquids involves exploring details of their microscopic dynamics and its consequences. Here, we apply the same general idea to quantum liquids. We discuss momentum condensation in liquid helium which is consistent with microscopic dynamics in liquids and high mobility of liquid atoms. We propose that mobile transit atoms accumulate in the finite-energy state where the transit speed is close to the speed of sound. In this state, the transit energy is close to the zero-point energy. In momentum space, the accumulation operates on a sphere with the radius set by interatomic spacing and corresponds to zero net momentum. We show that this picture is supported by experiments, including the kinetic energy of helium atoms below the superfluid transition and sharp peaks of scattered intensity at predicted energy. We discuss the implications of this picture including the macroscopic wave function and superfluidity. The superfluid transition temperature is evaluated to be within 15% of the experimental value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.06323v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/acaba3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter 35, 085101 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>K. Trachenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small-amplitude synchronisation in driven Potts models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14980v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study driven $q$-state Potts models with thermodynamically consistent dynamics and global coupling. For a wide range of parameters, these models exhibit a dynamical phase transition from decoherent oscillations into a synchronised phase. Starting from a general microscopic dynamics for individual oscillators, we derive the normal form of the high-dimensional Hopf-Bifurcation that underlies the phase transition. The normal-form equations are exact in the thermodynamic limit and close to the bifurcation. Exploiting the symmetry of the model, we solve these equations and thus uncover the intricate stable synchronisation patterns of driven Potts models, characterised by a rich phase diagram. Making use of thermodynamic consistency, we show that synchronisation reduces dissipation in such a way that the most stable synchronised states dissipate the least entropy. Close to the phase transition, our findings condense into a linear dissipation-stability relation that connects entropy production with phase-space contraction, a stability measure. At finite system size, our findings suggest a minimum-dissipation principle for driven Potts models that holds arbitrarily far from equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14980v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.044114</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E, 110, 044114 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jan Meibohm, Massimiliano Esposito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimum-dissipation principle for synchronised stochastic oscillators far from equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14982v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a linear stability-dissipation relation (SDR) for $q$-state Potts models driven far from equilibrium by a nonconservative force. At a critical coupling strength, these models exhibit a synchronisation transition from a decoherent into a synchronised state. In the vicinity of this transition, the SDR connects the entropy production rate per oscillator to the phase-space contraction rate, a measure of stability, in a simple way. For large but finite systems, we argue that the SDR implies a minimum-dissipation principle for driven Potts models as the dynamics selects stable non-equilibrium states with least dissipation. This principle holds arbitrarily far from equilibrium, for any stochastic dynamics, and for all $q$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14982v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.L042102</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 110, L042102 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jan Meibohm, Massimiliano Esposito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lindblad quantum dynamics from correlation functions of classical spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12396v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Lindblad quantum master equation is one of the central approaches to the physics of open quantum systems. In particular, boundary driving enables the study of transport, where a steady state emerges in the long-time limit, which features a constant current and a characteristic density profile. While the Lindblad equation complements other approaches to transport in closed quantum systems, it has become clear that a connection between closed and open systems exists in certain cases. Here, we build on this connection for magnetization transport in the spin-1/2 XXZ chain with and without integrability-breaking perturbations. Specifically, we study the question whether the time evolution of the open quantum system can be described on the basis of classical correlation functions, as generated by the Hamiltonian equations of motion for real vectors. By comparing to exact numerical simulations of the Lindblad equation, we find a good accuracy of such a description for a range of model parameters, which is consistent with previous studies on closed systems. While this agreement is an interesting physical observation, it also suggests that classical mechanics can be used to solve the Lindblad equation for comparatively large system sizes, which lie outside the possibilities of a quantum mechanical treatment. We also point out counterexamples and limitations for the quantitative extraction of transport coefficients. Remarkably, our classical approach to large open systems allows to detect superdiffusion at the isotropic point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12396v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Kraft, Mariel Kempa, Jiaozi Wang, Robin Steinigeweg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonuniversality in random criticality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04548v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider $N$ two-dimensional Ising models coupled in presence of quenched disorder and use scale invariant scattering theory to exactly show the presence of a line of renormalization group fixed points for any fixed value of $N$ other than 1. We show how this result relates to perturbative studies and sheds light on numerical simulations. We also observe that the limit $N\to 1$ may be of interest for the Ising spin glass, and point out potential relevance for nonuniversality in other contexts of random criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04548v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1742-5468/ada695</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Stat. Mech. (2025) 013211</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gesualdo Delfino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor network Monte Carlo simulations for the two-dimensional random-bond Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06538v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Disordered lattice spin systems are crucial in both theoretical and applied physics. However, understanding their properties poses significant challenges for Monte Carlo simulations. In this work, we investigate the two-dimensional random-bond Ising model using the recently proposed Tensor Network Monte Carlo (TNMC) method. This method generates biased samples from conditional probabilities computed via tensor network contractions and corrects the bias using the Metropolis scheme. Consequently, the proposals provided by tensor networks function as block updates for Monte Carlo simulations. Through extensive numerical experiments, we demonstrate that TNMC simulations can be performed on lattices as large as $1024\times 1024$ spins with moderate computational resources, a substantial increase from the previous maximum size of $64\times 64$ in MCMC. Notably, we observe an almost complete absence of critical slowing down, enabling the efficient collection of unbiased samples and averaging over a large number of random realizations of bond disorders. We successfully pinpoint the multi-critical point along the Nishimori line with significant precision and accurately determined the bulk and surface critical exponents. Our findings suggest that TNMC is a highly efficient algorithm for exploring disordered and frustrated systems in two dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06538v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Chen, Erdong Guo, Wanzhou Zhang, Pan Zhang, Youjin Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the time complexity analysis of numerical percolation threshold estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11874v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main purpose of percolation theory is to model phase transitions in a variety of random systems, which is highly valuable in fields related to materials physics, biology, or otherwise unrelated areas like oil extraction or even quantum computing. Thus, one of the problems encountered is the calculation of the threshold at which such transition occurs, known as percolation threshold. Since there are no known closed forms to determine the threshold in an exact manner in systems with particular properties, it is decided to rely on numerical methods as the Monte Carlo approach, which provides a sufficiently accurate approximation to serve as a valid estimate in the projects or research where it is involved. However, in order to achieve an exact characterization of the threshold in two-dimensional systems with site percolation, in this work it is performed an analysis of the complexity, both temporal and spatial, of an algorithm that implements its computation from the aforementioned numerical method. Specifically, the conduction of an accurate analysis of the cost of such algorithm implies a deep enough knowledge about certain metrics regarding its duration, or work completed per iteration, which along with its formalization may contribute to the determination of the threshold based on these metrics. Nevertheless, as a result, various bounds are achieved for the best, average and worst cases of the execution on systems spanning several dimensions, revealing that in 1 and 2 the complexity is directly conditioned by the duration, although from 3 onwards no proof for this point has been found, notwithstanding the evidence suggesting its compliance. Furthermore, based on the average case, several methods are proposed that could be applied to characterize the threshold, although they have not been thoroughly explored beyond what is necessary for the complexity analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11874v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Garc\'ia Solla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric properties of the additional third-order transitions in the two-dimensional Potts model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00423v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Within the canonical ensemble framework, this paper investigates the presence of higher-order transition signals in the $q$-state Potts model (for $q \geq 3$), using two geometric order parameters: isolated spins number and the average perimeter of clusters. Our results confirm that higher-order transitions exist in the Potts model, where the number of isolated spins reliably indicates third-order independent transitions. This signal persists regardless of the system's phase transition order, even at higher values of $q$. In contrast, the average perimeter of clusters, used as an order parameter for detecting third-order dependent transitions, shows that for $q = 6$ and $q = 8$, the signal for third-order dependent transitions disappears, indicating its absence in systems undergoing first-order transitions. These findings are consistent with results from microcanonical inflection-point analysis, further validating the robustness of this approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00423v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Liu, Xin Zhang, Lei Shi, Kai Qi, Xiang Li, Fangfang Wang, Zengru Di</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perspective: Time irreversibility in systems observed at coarse resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02675v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A broken time-reversal symmetry, i.e. broken detailed balance, is central to non-equilibrium physics and is a prerequisite for life. However, it turns out to be quite challenging to unambiguously define and quantify time-reversal symmetry (and violations thereof) in practice, that is, from observations. Measurements on complex systems have a finite resolution and generally probe low-dimensional projections of the underlying dynamics, which are well known to introduce memory. In situations where many microscopic states become "lumped" onto the same observable "state" or when introducing "reaction coordinates" to reduce the dimensionality of data, signatures of a broken time-reversal symmetry in the microscopic dynamics become distorted or masked. In this perspective we highlight why in defining and discussing time-reversal symmetry, and quantifying its violations, the precise underlying assumptions on the microscopic dynamics, the coarse graining, and further reductions, are not a technical detail. These assumptions decide whether the conclusions that are drawn are physically sound or inconsistent. We summarize recent findings in the field and reflect upon key challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02675v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cai Dieball, Alja\v{z} Godec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of absence of local conserved quantities in two- and higher-dimensional quantum Ising models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the Ising models with transverse and longitudinal fields on the hypercubic lattices with dimensions higher than one have no local conserved quantities other than the Hamiltonian. This holds for any value of the longitudinal field, including zero, as far as the transverse field and the Ising interactions are nonzero. The conserved quantity considered here is ``local'' in a very weak sense: it can be written as a linear combination of operators whose side lengths of the supports in one direction do not exceed half the system size, while the side lengths in the other directions are arbitrary. We also prove that the above result holds even in the ladder system. Our results extend the recently developed technique of the proof of absence of local conserved quantities in one-dimensional systems to higher dimensions and to the ladder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18903v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuuya Chiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corrections to the Hamiltonian induced by finite-strength coupling to the environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.00643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.00643v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: If a quantum system interacts with the environment, then the Hamiltonian acquires a correction known as the Lamb-shift term. There are two other corrections to the Hamiltonian, related to the stationary state. Namely, the stationary state is to first approximation a Gibbs state with respect to original Hamiltonian. However, if we have finite coupling, then the true stationary state will be different, and regarding it as a Gibbs state to some effective Hamiltonian, one can extract a correction, which is called "steady-state" correction. Alternatively, one can take a static point of view, and consider the reduced state of total equilibrium state, i.e., system plus bath Gibbs state. The extracted Hamiltonian correction is called the "mean-force" correction. This paper presents several analytical results on second-order corrections (in coupling strength) of the three types mentioned above. Instead of the steady state, we focus on a state annihilated by the Liouvillian of the master equation, labeling it as the "quasi-steady state." Specifically, we derive a general formula for the mean-force correction as well as the quasi-steady state and Lamb-shift correction for a general class of master equations. Furthermore, specific formulas for corrections are obtained for the Davies, Bloch-Redfield, and cumulant equation (refined weak coupling). In particular, the cumulant equation serves as a case study of the Liouvillian, featuring a nontrivial fourth-order generator. This generator forms the basis for calculating the diagonal quasi-steady-state correction. We consider spin-boson model as an example, and in addition to using our formulas for corrections, we consider mean-force correction from the reaction-coordinate approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.00643v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.014144</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 110, 014144. July, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marcin {\L}obejko, Marek Winczewski, Gerardo Su\'arez, Robert Alicki, Micha{\l} Horodecki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar Conformal Field Theories from Lattice Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.12028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.12028v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss scalar conformal field theories (CFTs) that can be realized in structural phase transitions. The Landau condition and Lifshitz condition are reviewed, which are necessary conditions for a structural phase transition to be second order. We also review the perturbative analysis in $4-\epsilon$ expansion of the corresponding Landau actions, which were already analyzed thoroughly in the 80s. By identifying the global symmetries of these fixed points, it turns out that in perturbation theory only 6 different CFTs can be realized by commensurate structural phase transitions. ${\rm \textbf{Updated in version 2:}}$ We discuss how to classify all the phases of a Landau theory using the computer algebra system GAP. We also discuss the fully packed quantum loop model on the triangular lattice, where the Cubic CFT is realized.
  This is a lecture note based on a series of talks given by the author. The goal of the lecture note is to bridge the gap between condensed matter physicists and conformal field theorists. The note will be further updated in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.12028v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junchen Rong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Timescales of Quantum Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09410v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Due to the inevitable existence of quantum effects, a classical description generically breaks down after a finite quantum break-time $t_q$. We aim to find criteria for determining $t_q$. To this end, we construct a new prototype model that features numerous dynamically accessible quantum modes. Using explicit numerical time evolution, we establish how $t_q$ depends on the parameters of the system such as its particle number $N$. The presence of a classical instability leads to $t_q \sim \ln N$ or $t_q\sim \sqrt{N}$. In the stable case, we observe $t_q\sim N$, although full quantum breaking may not take place at all. We find that the different regimes merge smoothly with $t_q\sim N^\gamma$ ($0&lt;\gamma&lt;1$). As an outlook, we point out possibilities for transferring our results to black holes and expanding spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09410v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/prop.202300163</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Fortsch. Phys. 71 (2023) 12, 2300163</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marco Michel, Sebastian Zell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid quantum-classical algorithm for the transverse-field Ising model in the thermodynamic limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07600v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We describe a hybrid quantum-classical approach to treat quantum many-body systems in the thermodynamic limit. This is done by combining numerical linked-cluster expansions (NLCE) with the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE). Here, the VQE algorithm is used as a cluster solver within the NLCE. We test our hybrid quantum-classical algorithm (NLCE$+$VQE) for the ferromagnetic transverse-field Ising model on the one-dimensional chain and the two-dimensional square lattice. The calculation of ground-state energies on each open cluster demands a modified Hamiltonian variational ansatz for the VQE. One major finding is convergence of NLCE$+$VQE to the conventional NLCE result in the thermodynamic limit when at least $N/2$ layers are used in the VQE ansatz for each cluster with $N$ sites. Our approach demonstrates the fruitful connection of techniques known from correlated quantum many-body systems with hybrid algorithms explored on existing quantum-computing devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07600v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.155128</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 155128 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> Sumeet, M. H\"ormann, K. P. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental charges for dual-unitary circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14148v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dual-unitary quantum circuits have recently attracted attention as an analytically tractable model of many-body quantum dynamics. Consisting of a 1+1D lattice of 2-qudit gates arranged in a 'brickwork' pattern, these models are defined by the constraint that each gate must remain unitary under swapping the roles of space and time. This dual-unitarity restricts the dynamics of local operators in these circuits: the support of any such operator must grow at the effective speed of light of the system, along one or both of the edges of a causal light cone set by the geometry of the circuit. Using this property, it is shown here that for 1+1D dual-unitary circuits the set of width-$w$ conserved densities (constructed from operators supported over $w$ consecutive sites) is in one-to-one correspondence with the set of width-$w$ solitons - operators which, up to a multiplicative phase, are simply spatially translated at the effective speed of light by the dual-unitary dynamics. A number of ways to construct these many-body solitons (explicitly in the case where the local Hilbert space dimension $d=2$) are then demonstrated: firstly, via a simple construction involving products of smaller, constituent solitons; and secondly, via a construction which cannot be understood as simply in terms of products of smaller solitons, but which does have a neat interpretation in terms of products of fermions under a Jordan-Wigner transformation. This provides partial progress towards a characterisation of the microscopic structure of complex many-body solitons (in dual-unitary circuits on qubits), whilst also establishing a link between fermionic models and dual-unitary circuits, advancing our understanding of what kinds of physics can be explored in this framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14148v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Holden-Dye, Lluis Masanes, Arijeet Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact, Average, and Broken Symmetries in a Simple Adaptive Monitored Circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17309v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Symmetry is a powerful tool for understanding phases of matter in equilibrium. Quantum circuits with measurements have recently emerged as a platform for novel states of matter intrinsically out of equilibrium. Can symmetry be used as an organizing principle for these novel states, their phases and phase transitions? In this work, we give an affirmative answer to this question in a simple adaptive monitored circuit, which hosts an ordering transition in addition to a separate entanglement transition, upon tuning a single parameter. Starting from a symmetry-breaking initial state, depending on the tuning parameter, the steady state could (i) remain symmetry-broken, (ii) exhibit the average symmetry in the ensemble of trajectories, or (iii) exhibit the exact symmetry for each trajectory. The ordering transition is mapped to the transition in a classical majority vote model, described by the Ising universality class, while the entanglement transition lies in the percolation class. Numerical simulations are further presented to support the analytical understandings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17309v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi Li, Zhu-Xi Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body computing on Field Programmable Gate Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06415v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A new implementation of many-body calculations is of paramount importance in the field of computational physics. In this study, we leverage the capabilities of Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGAs) for conducting quantum many-body calculations. Through the design of appropriate schemes for Monte Carlo and tensor network methods, we effectively utilize the parallel processing capabilities provided by FPGAs. This has resulted in a tenfold speedup compared to CPU-based computation for a Monte Carlo algorithm. By using a supercell structure and simulating the FPGA architecture on a CPU with High-Level Synthesis, we achieve $O(1)$ scaling for the time of one sweep, regardless of the overall system size. We also demonstrate, for the first time, the utilization of FPGA to accelerate a typical tensor network algorithm for many-body ground state calculations. Additionally, we show that the current FPGA computing acceleration is on par with that of multi-threaded GPU parallel processing. Our findings unambiguously highlight the significant advantages of hardware implementation and pave the way for novel approaches to many-body calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06415v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songtai Lv, Yang Liang, Yuchen Meng, Xiaochen Yao, Jincheng Xu, Yang Liu, Qibin Zheng, Haiyuan Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions in debt recycling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19104v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Debt recycling is an aggressive equity extraction strategy that potentially permits faster repayment of a mortgage. While equity progressively builds up as the mortgage is repaid monthly, mortgage holders may obtain another loan they could use to invest on a risky asset. The wealth produced by a successful investment is then used to repay the mortgage faster. The strategy is riskier than a standard repayment plan since fluctuations in the house market and investment's volatility may also lead to a fast default, as both the mortgage and the liquidity loan are secured against the same good. The general conditions of the mortgage holder and the outside market under which debt recycling may be recommended or discouraged have not been fully investigated. In this paper, to evaluate the effectiveness of traditional monthly mortgage repayment versus debt recycling strategies, we build a dynamical model of debt recycling and study the time evolution of equity and mortgage balance as a function of loan-to-value ratio, house market performance, and return of the risky investment. We find that the model has a rich behavior as a function of its main parameters, showing strongly and weakly successful phases - where the mortgage is eventually repaid faster and slower than the standard monthly repayment strategy, respectively - a default phase where the equity locked in the house vanishes before the mortgage is repaid, signalling a failure of the debt recycling strategy, and a permanent re-mortgaging phase - where further investment funds from the lender are continuously secured, but the mortgage is never fully repaid. The strategy's effectiveness is found to be highly sensitive to the initial mortgage-to-equity ratio, the monthly amount of scheduled repayments, and the economic parameters at the outset. The analytical results are corroborated with numerical simulations with excellent agreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19104v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jedc.2025.105044</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control Volume 171, February 2025, 105044</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sabrina Aufiero, Preben Forer, Pierpaolo Vivo, Fabio Caccioli, Silvia Bartolucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Transitions in Anisotropic Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02844v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Turbulence is a widely observed state of fluid flows, characterized by complex, nonlinear interactions between motions across a broad spectrum of length and time scales. While turbulence is ubiquitous, from teacups to planetary atmospheres, oceans and stars, its manifestations can vary considerably between different physical systems. For instance, three-dimensional (3D) turbulent flows display a forward energy cascade from large to small scales, while in two-dimensional (2D) turbulence, energy cascades from small to large scales. In a given physical system, a transition between such disparate regimes of turbulence can occur when a control parameter reaches a critical value. The behavior of flows close to such transition points, which separate qualitatively distinct \textit{phases} of turbulence, has been found to be unexpectedly rich. Here, we survey recent findings on such transitions in highly anisotropic turbulent fluid flows, including turbulence in thin layers and under the influence of rapid rotation. We also review recent work on transitions induced by turbulent fluctuations, such as random reversals and transitions between large-scale vortices and jets, among others. The relevance of these results and their ramifications for future investigations are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02844v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian van Kan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absorbing State Phase Transitions and Stability of Long-Range Coherence in Dissipative Quantum State Preparation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00819v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the absorbing state phase transition in a purely dissipative quantum reaction-diffusion model where the absorbing state itself has long range phase coherence. The model may also be viewed as a dissipative quantum state preparation procedure for the (generalized) W-state with errors. The 'error' Lindblad jump operators preserve the W-state as a dark state, but nonetheless act to decohere the system and induce the phase transition. We find cases where the preparation protocol is either fragile or robust against weak error quantum jump rates, and show that remnants of the coherence persist even after the phase transition to the decohering phase. Furthermore, we argue that the long range coherence of the absorbing state leads to critical behavior distinct from Directed Percolation, the typical universality class for reaction-diffusion models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00819v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Wampler, Nigel R. Cooper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong and weak symmetries and their spontaneous symmetry breaking in mixed states emerging from the quantum Ising model under multiple decoherence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12738v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Discovering and categorizing quantum orders in mixed many-body systems are currently one of the most important problems. Specific types of decoherence applied to typical quantum many-body states can induce a novel kind of mixed state accompanying characteristic symmetry orders, which has no counterparts in pure many-body states. We study phenomena generated by interplay between two types of decoherence applied to the one-dimensional transverse field Ising model (TFIM). We show that in the doubled Hilbert space formalism, the decoherence can be described by filtering operation applied to matrix product states (MPS) defined in the doubled Hilbert system. The filtering operation induces specific deformation of the MPS, which approximates the ground state of a certain parent Hamiltonian in the doubled Hilbert space. In the present case, such a parent Hamiltonian is the quantum Ashkin-Teller model, having a rich phase diagram with a critical lines and quantum phase transitions. By investigating the deformed MPS, we find various types of mixed states emergent from the ground states of the TFIM, and clarify phase transitions between them. In that study, strong and weak $Z_2$ symmetries play an important role, for which we introduce efficient order parameters, such as R\'{e}nyi-2 correlators, entanglement entropy, etc., in the doubled Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12738v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Orito, Yoshihito Kuno, Ikuo Ichinose</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
