<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Casimir effect in critical $\mathrm{O}(N)$ models from non-equilibrium Monte Carlo simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: $\mathrm{O}(N)$ vector models in three dimensions, when defined in a geometry with a compact direction and tuned to criticality, exhibit long-range fluctuations which induce a Casimir effect. The strength of the resulting interaction is encoded in the excess free-energy density, which depends on a universal coefficient: the Casimir amplitude. We present a high-precision numerical calculation of the latter, by means of a novel non-equilibrium Monte Carlo algorithm, and compare our findings with results obtained from large-$N$ expansions and from the conformal bootstrap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20403v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Bulgarelli, Michele Caselle, Alessandro Nada, Marco Panero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stochastic Stirling engine powered by an active particle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20616v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate a model of a stochastic engine operating cyclically at constant bath temperature, which consists of an overdamped Brownian harmonic oscillator that plays the role of working substance and is elastically coupled to an active particle. Stirling-like cycles are implemented by time-periodic changes of the active particle speed and the potential confining the oscillator. By analyzing its quasistatic and finite-time performance, we distinguish two regimes, which are determined by the relative magnitudes of the persistence time of active particle, the characteristic time of the elastic interaction, and the viscous relaxation time of the working substance. In the quasistatic limit, we derive analytic expressions for the average output work, the mean absorbed heat, and the efficiency, which explicitly involve the ratios of such three time-scales. For sufficiently large finite cycles, the different quantities characterizing the engine performance converge to their quasistatic values. For shorter cycles, the efficiencies are systematically lower, but with positive mean output powers that exhibit a maximum as a function of the cycle duration if the corresponding quasistatic mean work is positive. For sufficiently short cycles or if the quasistatic work is zero, the engine behaves at finite-time as a heat pump with negative power and efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20616v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erick Efrain Cote-Valencia, Juan Ruben Gomez-Solano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic Flat-Histogram Simulations of Non-Equilibrium Stochastic Processes with Continuous and Discontinuous Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As far as we know, there is no flat-histogram algorithm to sample the stationary distribution of non-equilibrium stochastic processes. The present work addresses this gap by introducing a generalization of the Wang-Landau algorithm, applied to non-equilibrium stochastic processes with local transitions. The main idea is to sample macroscopic states using a kinetic Monte Carlo algorithm to generate trial moves, which are accepted or rejected with a probability that depends inversely on the stationary distribution. The stationary distribution is refined through the simulation by a modification factor, leading to convergence toward the true stationary distribution. A visitation histogram is also accumulated, and the modification factor is updated when the histogram satisfies a flatness condition. The stationary distribution is obtained in the limit where the modification factor reaches a threshold value close to unity. To test the algorithm, we compare simulation results for several stochastic processes with theoretically known behavior. In addition, results from the kinetic flat-histogram algorithm are compared with standard exact stochastic simulations. We show that the kinetic flat-histogram algorithm can be applied to phase transitions in stochastic processes with bistability, which describe a wide range of phenomena such as epidemic spreading, population growth, chemical reactions, and consensus formation. With some adaptations, the kinetic flat-histogram algorithm can also be applied to stochastic models on lattices and complex networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20651v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. M. C. Alencar, T. F. A. Alves, G. A. Alves, F. W. S. Lima, A. Macedo-Filho, R. S. Ferreira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determination of melting temperature of hexagonal ice using Lee-Yang phase transition theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20989v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lee-Yang phase transition theory is a milestone in statistical physics. Its applications in realistic systems, however, had been substantially hindered by availability of practical schemes to calculate the Lee-Yang zeros. In this manuscript, we extend the scheme we have designed earlier [Phys. Rev. E 109, 024118 (2024)] and report simulation results for the melting temperature (T) of ice Ih under ambient pressure. The enhanced sampling technique is shown to be crucial for accessing Lee-Yang zeros accurately. The real and imaginary parts of our Lee-Yang edges demonstrate linear scaling of sizes, which can lead to a melting T of 248.15 K for the TIP4P/2005 potential in the thermodynamic limit. This result is in close quantitative agreement with previous coexistence simulations, achieved with cheaper computational costs and without prior knowledge of the phase transition. With these, we demonstrate the applicability of Lee-Yang phase transition theory in realistic molecular systems, and provide a feasible scheme for high-throughput calculations in determining the phase transition temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20989v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ling Liu, Yihua Dong, Qijun Ye, Xin-Zheng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating generalised fluids via interacting wave packets evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One-dimensional integrable and quasi-integrable systems display, on macroscopic scales, a universal form of transport known as Generalized Hydrodynamics (GHD). In its standard Euler-scale formulation, GHD mirrors the equations of a two-dimensional compressible fluid but ignores fluctuations and becomes numerically unwieldy as soon as integrability-breaking perturbations are introduced. We show that GHD can be efficiently simulated as a gas of semiclassical wave packets - a natural generalisation of hard-rod particles - whose trajectories are efficiently mapped onto those of point particles. This representation (i) provides a transparent route to incorporate integrability-breaking terms, and (ii) automatically embeds the exact fluctuating-hydrodynamics extension of GHD. The resulting framework enables fast, large-scale simulations of quasi-integrable systems even in the presence of complicated integrability-breaking perturbations. It also manifest the pivotal role of two-point correlations in systems confined by external potentials: we demonstrate that situations where local one-point observables appear thermalised can nevertheless sustain long-lived, far-from-equilibrium long-range correlations for arbitrarily long times, signaling that, differently from what previously stated, true thermalisation is not reached at diffusive time-scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21000v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Urilyon, Leonardo Biagetti, Jitendra Kethepalli, Jacopo De Nardis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional renormalization group approach to phonon modified criticality: anomalous dimension of strain and non-analytic corrections to Hooke's law</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21210v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the interplay between critical isotropic elasticity and classical Ising criticality using a functional renormalization group (FRG) approach which is implemented such that the volume is fixed during the entire renormalization group flow. For dimensions slightly smaller than four we use a simple truncation of the FRG flow equations to recover the fixed points of the constrained Ising model: the Gaussian fixed point G, the Ising fixed point I, the renormalized Ising fixed point R, and the spherical fixed point S. We show that the fixed points R and S are both characterized by a finite anomalous dimension $y_{\ast}&lt;0$ of strain fluctuations, implying that the energy dispersion of longitudinal acoustic phonons exhibits a non-analytic momentum dependence proportional to $k^{1-y_{\ast}/2}$ for small momentum $k$. We also derive and solve flow equations for the free energy at constant strain and compute stress-strain relations in the vicinity of the fixed points. As a result, we reaffirm that Ising criticality, controlled by the fixed point I, is preempted by a bulk instability. Beyond that, we find that the stress-strain relation at R and S remains linear to leading order (Hooke's law), as long as the interaction between strain and Ising fluctuations is sufficiently weak. However, the finite anomalous dimension of strain fluctuations $y_{\ast}$ gives rise to non-analytic corrections to Hooke's law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21210v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max O. Hansen, Julia von Rothkirch, Peter Kopietz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full stochastic dynamics of a tracer in a dense single-file system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tracer diffusion in single-file systems, where particles are restricted to move on a line without passing each other, has been a fertile ground to investigate anomalous diffusion and strong memory effects. While the long-time behavior of such a tracer has been well studied, with a known subdiffusive dynamics and a Gaussian description for the rescaled position, the finer details of multi-time correlations remain poorly understood. This work focuses on the limit where almost all sites of a Symmetric Exclusion Process (SEP), a paradigmatic lattice model, are occupied. It extends beyond Gaussian descriptions and single-time statistics to address the multi-time correlation functions of the tracer in the SEP. In this dense limit, we present a general relation between all $n$-time correlations of the non-Markovian tracer position process and the conditional probabilities of a single Markovian random walker. Using this relation, we derive explicit expressions for the four-time correlations and further explore important extensions: multiple tracers, non-equilibrium situations, and finite observation times. Our results underscore significant memory effects, strong temporal correlations, and the influence of initial conditions on long-time dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21446v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Poncet, Aur\'elien Grabsch, Olivier B\'enichou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermalization in open many-body systems and KMS detailed balance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20064v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starting from a microscopic description of weak system-bath interactions, we derive from first principles a quantum master equation that does not rely on the well-known rotating wave approximation. This includes generic many-body systems, with Hamiltonians with vanishingly small energy spacings that forbid that approximation. The equation satisfies a general form of detailed balance, called KMS, which ensures exact convergence to the many-body Gibbs state. Unlike the more common notion of GNS detailed balance, this notion is compatible with the absence of the rotating wave approximation. We show that the resulting Lindbladian dynamics not only reproduces the thermal equilibrium point, but also approximates the true system evolution with an error that grows at most linearly in time, giving an exponential improvement upon previous estimates. This master equation has quasi-local jump operators, can be efficiently simulated on a quantum computer, and reduces to the usual Davies dynamics in the limit. With it, we provide a rigorous model of many-body thermalization relevant to both open quantum systems and quantum algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20064v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Scandi, \'Alvaro M. Alhambra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic Timelike c-function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20459v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The integration of high-energy degrees of freedom along the renormalization group (RG) flow in Poincar\'e-invariant theories can be captured by a monotonic c-function. For such theories, holographic monotonic c-functions have been constructed using entanglement entropy. However, in theories with broken Lorentz invariance, such constructions generally fail, reflecting both the violation of the entanglement RG monotonicity and its limitations in capturing certain properties of non-relativistic RG flows. Since many quantum many-body systems lack Lorentz invariance, it is of significant importance to identify a quantity that reflects the decrease in degrees of freedom along non-relativistic RG flows. We show that the recently introduced holographic timelike entanglement entropy naturally gives rise to a new c-function applicable to all such theories. We further demonstrate the existence of this c-function in theories with Lifshitz and hyperscaling-violating fixed points, showing that, provided the null energy conditions and thermodynamic stability are satisfied, the proposed c-function exhibits the expected monotonic behavior along the RG flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20459v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios Giataganas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding the right path: statistical mechanics of connected solutions in constraint satisfaction problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We define and study a statistical mechanics ensemble that characterizes connected solutions in constraint satisfaction problems (CSPs). Built around a well-known local entropy bias, it allows us to better identify hardness transitions in problems where the energy landscape is dominated by isolated solutions. We apply this new device to the symmetric binary perceptron model (SBP), and study how its manifold of connected solutions behaves. We choose this particular problem because, while its typical solutions are isolated, it can be solved using local algorithms for a certain range of constraint density $\alpha$ and threshold $\kappa$. With this new ensemble, we unveil the presence of a cluster composed of delocalized connected solutions. In particular, we demonstrate its stability until a critical threshold $\kappa^{\rm no-mem}_{\rm loc.\, stab.}$ (dependent on $\alpha$). This transition appears as paths of solutions shatter, a phenomenon that more conventional statistical mechanics approaches fail to grasp. Finally, we compared our predictions to simulations. For this, we used a modified Monte-Carlo algorithm, designed specifically to target these delocalized solutions. We obtained, as predicted, that the algorithm finds solutions until $\kappa\approx\kappa^{\rm no-mem}_{\rm loc.\, stab.}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20954v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damien Barbier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking co-existence: zealotry vs. nonlinear social impact</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study how zealotry and nonlinear social impact affect consensus formation in the nonlinear voter model, evolutionary games, and the partisan voter model. In all three models, consensus is an absorbing state in finite populations, while co-existence is a possible outcome of the deterministic dynamics. We show that sufficiently strong zealotry -- i.e., the presence of agents who never change state -- can drive infinite populations to consensus in all three models. However, while evolutionary games and the partisan voter model permit zealotry-induced consensus for all values of their model parameters, the nonlinear voter model does not. Central to this difference is the shape of the social impact function, which quantifies how the influence of a group scales with size, and is therefore a measure of majority and minority effects. We derive general conditions relating the slope of this function at small group sizes to the local stability of consensus. Sublinear impact favours minorities and can override zealotry to prevent consensus, whereas superlinear impact promotes majorities and therefore facilitates consensus. We extend the analysis to finite populations, exploring the time-to-consensus, and the shape of quasi-stationary distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21407v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher R. Kitching, Luc\'ia S. Ramirez, Maxi San Miguel, Tobias Galla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The grammar of the Ising model: A new complexity hierarchy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.08301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.08301v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: How complex is an Ising model? Usually, this is measured by the computational complexity of its ground state energy problem. Yet, this complexity measure only distinguishes between planar and non-planar interaction graphs, and thus fails to capture properties such as the average node degree, the number of long range interactions, or the dimensionality of the lattice. Herein, we introduce a new complexity measure for Ising models and thoroughly classify Ising models with respect to it. Specifically, given an Ising model we consider the decision problem corresponding to the function graph of its Hamiltonian, and classify this problem in the Chomsky hierarchy. We prove that the language of this decision problem is (i) regular if and only if the Ising model is finite, (ii) constructive context free if and only if the Ising model is linear and its edge language is regular, (iii) constructive context sensitive if and only if the edge language of the Ising model is context sensitive, and (iv) decidable if and only if the edge language of the Ising model is decidable. We apply this theorem to show that the 1d Ising model, the Ising model on generalised ladder graphs, and the Ising model on layerwise complete graphs are constructive context free, while the 2d Ising model, the all-to-all Ising model, and the Ising model on perfect binary trees are constructive context sensitive. This work is a first step in the characterisation of physical interactions in terms of grammars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.08301v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1098/rspa.2024.0579</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. R. Soc. A. 481:20240579 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Reinhart, Gemma De les Coves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mpemba effect on non-equilibrium active Markov chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17547v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the Mpemba effect on a non-equilibrium Markov chain that mimics the run and tumble motion of an active particle in a discrete energy landscape. The broken detailed balance, rendered by the activity, gives rise to a unique anomalous relaxation in the system which is distinctly different than the typical equilibrium systems. We observe that the activity can both suppress or induce the Mpemba effect. Furthermore, we report an oscillatory Mpemba effect where the relaxation trajectories, emanating from the hot and cold initial conditions, cross each other multiple times and this occurs due to the emergence of complex eigenvalues in the relaxation spectrum due to the activity. Our work reveals a possible pathway for studying the Mpemba effect in active living systems where broken detailed balance is crucial to achieve many biological functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17547v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.111.054136</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 111, 054136 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Apurba Biswas, Arnab Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metabolic coordination and phase transitions in spatially distributed multi-cellular systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13424v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: During overflow metabolism, cells excrete glycolytic byproducts when growing under aerobic conditions in a seemingly wasteful fashion. While potentially advantageous for microbes with finite oxidative capacity, its role in higher organisms is harder to assess. Recent single-cell experiments suggest overflow metabolism arises due to imbalances in inter-cellular exchange networks. We quantitatively characterize this scenario by integrating spatial metabolic modeling with tools from statistical physics and experimental single-cell flux data. Our results provide a theoretical demonstration of how diffusion-limited exchanges shape the space of accessible multi-cellular metabolic states. Specifically, a phase transition from a balanced network of exchanges to an unbalanced, overflow regime occurs as mean glucose and oxygen uptake rates vary. Heterogeneous single-cell metabolic phenotypes occur near this transition. Time-resolved tumor-stroma co-culture data support the idea that overflow metabolism stems from failure of inter-cellular metabolic coordination. In summary, environmental control is an emergent multi-cellular property, rather than a cell-autonomous effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13424v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-025-02133-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun Phys 8, 205 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Krishnadev Narayanankutty, Jos\'e Antonio Pereiro-Morejon, Ari\'an Ferrero-Fern\'andez, Valentina Onesto, Stefania Forciniti, Loretta L. del Mercato, Roberto Mulet, Andrea De Martino, David S. Tourigny, Daniele De Martino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-dimensional Abelian and non-Abelian gauge Higgs theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05823v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gauge symmetries and Higgs mechanisms are key features of theories describing high-energy particle physics and collective phenomena in statistical and condensed-matter physics. In this review we address the collective behavior of systems of multicomponent scalar fields interacting with gauge fields, which can be already present in the underlying microscopic system or emerge only at criticality. The interplay between local gauge and global symmetries determines the phase diagram, the nature of the Higgs phases, and the nature of phase transitions between the high-temperature disordered and the low-temperature Higgs phases. However, additional crucial features determine the universal properties of the critical behavior at continuous transitions. Specifically, their nature also depends on the role played by the gauge modes at criticality. Effective (Abelian or non-Abelian) gauge Higgs field theories emerge when gauge modes develop critical correlations. On the other hand, a more standard critical behavior, which admits an effective description in terms of Landau-Ginzburg-Wilson $\Phi^4$ theories, occurs when gauge-field modes are short ranged at the transition. In the latter case, gauge fields only prevent non-gauge invariant correlation functions from becoming critical. This review covers the recent progress made in the study of Higgs systems with Abelian and non-Abelian gauge fields. We discuss the equilibrium thermodynamic properties of systems with a classical partition function, focusing mainly on three-dimensional systems, and only briefly discussing two-dimensional models. However, by using the quantum-to-classical mapping, the results on the critical behavior for classical systems in $D=d+1$ dimensions can be extended to quantum transitions in $d$ dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05823v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Bonati, Andrea Pelissetto, Ettore Vicari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal constrained control for generally damped Brownian heat engines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19124v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optimization of cyclic stochastic heat engines, a topic spanning decades of research, commonly assumes fixed control or response parameters at discrete points in the cycle-a limitation that often leads to experimentally impractical protocols. We overcome this with a general algorithm, adapted from optimal control theory, that optimizes full-cycle dynamics under realistic constraints, such as stiffness and temperature bounds, across diverse systems. Unlike geometric or mass transport methods, which rely on fixed endpoints and are unsuitable for unconstrained cycles, our approach simultaneously tunes both cycle time and control variations. Applied to a generally damped Brownian particle in a harmonic potential-an experimentally relevant case-our method is validated in the overdamped regime and extended to arbitrary damping rates. As damping decreases, maximum power vanishes and cycle time diverges; at fixed cycle times, efficiency follows a similar trend, with optimal protocols exhibiting non-monotonic complexity. Notably, optimizing temperature profiles-often overlooked-significantly enhances efficiency in intermediate damping regimes. Our work establishes the first systematic framework for optimizing cyclic stochastic processes under experimental constraints, broadening the scope of power and efficiency optimization in nonequilibrium thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19124v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monojit Chatterjee, Viktor Holubec, Rahul Marathe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective description of Taylor dispersion in strongly corrugated channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07464v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Taylor dispersion in periodic but highly corrugated channels is studied. Exact analytical expressions for the long-time diffusion constant and drift along the channel are derived to next-to-leading order in the limit of small channel period. Using these results we show how an effective model for Taylor dispersion in tortuous porous media can be framed in terms of dispersion in a uniform channel with absorption/desorption at its surface, an effective slip length for the flow at the surface and an effective, universal, diffusion constant on the surface. This work thus extends the concept of an effective slip-length for hydrodynamics flows to Taylor dispersion by those flows. The analytical results are confirmed by numerical calculations, and present a robust method to understand and upscale the transport properties of flows in porous media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07464v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Alexandre, Thomas Gu\'erin, David S. Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Two-Fluid Theory for Superfluid Hydrodynamics and the Fountain Pressure Paradox</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08826v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The two-fluid theory for superfluid hydrodynamics is derived from the fountain pressure result that condensed bosons move at constant entropy, and that therefore steady superfluid flow connects regions of equal chemical potential. The paradox of the fountain pressure equation is resolved with a quantitative prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08826v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phil Attard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent-based Monte Carlo simulations for reaction-diffusion models, population dynamics, and epidemic spreading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18145v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide an overview of Monte Carlo algorithms based on Markovian stochastic dynamics of interacting and reacting many-particle systems not in thermal equilibrium. These agent-based simulations are an effective way of introducing students to current research without requiring much prior knowledge or experience. By starting from the direct visualization of the data, students can gain immediate insight into emerging macroscopic features of a complex system and subsequently apply more sophisticated data analysis to quantitatively characterize its rich dynamical properties, both in the stationary and transient regimes. We utilize simulations of reaction-diffusion systems, stochastic models for population dynamics and epidemic spreading, to exemplify how interdisciplinary computational research can be effectively utilized in bottom-up undergraduate and graduate education through learning by doing. We also give helpful hints for the practical implementation of Monte Carlo algorithms, provide sample codes, explain some typical data analysis tools, and describe various potential error sources and pitfalls and tips for avoiding them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18145v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Swailem (Stony Brook), Ulrich Dobramysl (Oxford), Ruslan Mukhamadiarov (LMU Munich), Uwe C. T\"auber (Virginia Tech)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discontinuous shear thickening of a moderately dense inertial suspension of hydrodynamically interacting frictionless soft particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.05348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.05348v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that discontinuous shear thickening (DST) can occur even in moderately dense, inertial suspensions of hydrodynamically interacting, frictionless soft particles. Using the Lubrication-Friction Discrete Element Method, our simulations reveal that DST can emerge at lower particle densities, provided that both the inertia of the suspended particles and their softness are sufficiently pronounced. Furthermore, we show that, under these conditions, the DST behavior obtained from the simulation qualitatively agrees with that predicted by kinetic theory, even without accounting for hydrodynamic interactions. These findings expand the understanding of DST in soft particle systems and highlight the importance of particle inertia and softness in controlling rheological behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.05348v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satoshi Takada, Kazuhiro Hara, Hisao Hayakawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the choice of non-linear terms in blocking cat states by energy conservation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13699v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In [Entropy 25, 564 (2023)] I considered the problem of wavefunction ensembles for spin models. To observe magnetization at finite temperature, I had to add macroscopic nonlinear terms blocking macroscopic superpositions by energy conservation. The nonlinear terms were of the kind introduced in [W.D. Wick, arXiv:1710.03278 (2017)] to block spatial cats by energy conservation as solution to the Measurement Problem. Reviewing the theory from [W.D. Wick, arXiv:1710.03278 (2017), arXiv:1908.02352 (2019)], I derive a commutation relation that these nonlinear terms have to satisfy to be admitted and show that the terms of [W.D. Wick, arXiv:1710.03278 (2017), arXiv:2008.08663 (2020)] restricting the wavefunctions in space satisfies such relations. I generalize the terms of [Entropy 25, 564 (2023)] for non-pure spin models and check if they also satisfy the constraints, concluding with a negative answer. An experimental estimate to test the proposal of [W.D. Wick, arXiv:1710.03278 (2017)] is described at the end.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13699v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo De Carlo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative chaos and steady state of open Tavis-Cummings dimer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a coupled atom-photon system described by the Tavis-Cummings dimer (two coupled cavities) in the presence of photon loss and atomic pumping, to investigate the quantum signature of dissipative chaos. The appropriate classical limit of the model allows us to obtain a phase diagram identifying different dynamical phases, especially the onset of chaos. Both classically and quantum mechanically, we demonstrate the emergence of a steady state in the chaotic regime and analyze its properties. The interplay between quantum fluctuation and chaos leads to enhanced mixing dynamics and dephasing, resulting in the formation of an incoherent photonic fluid. The steady state exhibits an intriguing phenomenon of subsystem thermalization even outside the chaotic regime; however, its effective temperature increases with the degree of chaos. Moreover, the statistical properties of the steady state show a close connection with the random matrix theory. Finally, we discuss the experimental relevance of our findings, which can be tested in cavity and circuit quantum electrodynamics setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00776v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.111.L052204</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 111, L052204 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Debabrata Mondal, Andrey Kolovsky, S. Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Dynamics with Stochastic Non-Hermitian Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07746v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the quantum dynamics generated by a non-Hermitian Hamiltonian subject to stochastic perturbations in its anti-Hermitian part, describing fluctuating gains and losses. The dynamics averaged over the noise is described by an `anti-dephasing' master equation. We characterize the resulting state evolution and analyze its purity. The properties of such dynamics are illustrated in a stochastic dissipative qubit. Our analytical results show that adding noise allows for a rich control of the dynamics, stabilizing the lossy state and making state purification possible to a greater variety of steady states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07746v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Martinez-Azcona, Aritra Kundu, Avadh Saxena, Adolfo del Campo, Aurelia Chenu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Distillation of Coherent States with Phase-Insensitive Operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05974v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By combining multiple copies of noisy coherent states of light (or other bosonic systems), it is possible to obtain a single mode in a state with lesser noise, a process known as distillation or purification of coherent states. We investigate the distillation of coherent states from coherent thermal states under general phase-insensitive operations, and find a distillation protocol that is optimal in the asymptotic regime, i.e., when the number of input copies is much greater than 1. Remarkably, we find that in this regime, the error -- as quantified by infidelity (one minus the fidelity) of the output state with the desired coherent state -- is proportional to the inverse of the purity of coherence of the input state, a quantity obtained from the Right-Logarithmic-Derivative (RLD) Fisher information metric, hence revealing an operational interpretation of this quantity. The heart of this protocol is a phase-insensitive channel that optimally converts an input coherent thermal state with high amplitude, into an output with significantly lower amplitude and temperature. Under this channel, the purity of coherence remains asymptotically conserved. While both the input and desired output are Gaussian states, we find that the optimal protocol cannot be a Gaussian channel. Among Gaussian phase-insensitive channels, the optimal distillation protocol is a simple linear optical scheme that can be implemented with beam splitters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05974v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiv Akshar Yadavalli, Iman Marvian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin systems as quantum simulators of quantum field theories in curved spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07587v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that a quantum field theory (QFT) in general two-dimensional curved spacetimes can be realized by a system of quantum spins or qubits. We consider a spin-1/2 model on a one-dimensional ring with spatially and temporally varying exchange couplings and magnetic fields. This model reduces to a QFT of Majorana fermions in the continuum limit. From this correspondence, we establish a dictionary for translating between the spacetime-dependent parameters of the spin model and the general metric on which the QFT is defined. After addressing the general case, we consider the Friedmann-Lema\^{\i}tre-Robertson-Walker (FLRW) metric as a simple example. According to the dictionary, the QFT of Majorana fermions on the FLRW metric corresponds to the Ising model with a time-dependent transverse magnetic field. We demonstrate that the production of Majorana particles in the expanding universe can be simulated with the transverse-field Ising model by increasing the strength of the magnetic field. Furthermore, we examine the Unruh effect through the spin system by using our prescription and show the direct relation between the entanglement (or modular) Hamiltonian in the spin system and the Rindler Hamiltonian. This approach provides an experimentally viable system for probing various phenomena in QFT within curved spacetime, while also opening the door to uncovering nontrivial phenomena in spin systems inspired by curved spacetime physics. It offers fresh perspectives on both QFT in curved spacetimes and quantum many-body spin systems, revealing profound connections between these fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07587v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunichiro Kinoshita, Keiju Murata, Daisuke Yamamoto, Ryosuke Yoshii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On computational complexity of unitary and state design properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23353v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate unitary and state $t$-designs from a computational complexity perspective. First, we address the problems of computing frame potentials that characterize (approximate) $t$-designs. We present a quantum algorithm for computing frame potentials and establish the following: (1) exact computation can be achieved by a single query to a $\# \textsf{P}$-oracle and is $\# \textsf{P}$-hard; (2) for state vectors, deciding whether the frame potential is larger than or smaller than certain values is $\textsf{BQP}$-complete, provided the promise gap between the two values is inverse-polynomial in the number of qubits; and (3) for both state vectors and unitaries, this promise problem is $\textsf{PP}$-complete if the promise gap is exponentially small. Second, we address the promise problem of deciding whether or not a given set is a good approximation to a design. Given a certain promise gap that could be constant, we show that this problem is $\textsf{PP}$-hard, highlighting the inherent computational difficulty of determining properties of unitary and state designs. We further identify the implications of our results across diverse areas, including variational methods for constructing designs, diagnosing quantum chaos through out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs), and exploring emergent designs in Hamiltonian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23353v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshifumi Nakata, Yuki Takeuchi, Martin Kliesch, Andrew Darmawan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-File Diffusion of Active Brownian Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08988v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Single-file diffusion (SFD) is a key mechanism underlying transport phenomena in confined physical and biological systems. In a typical SFD process, microscopic particles are restricted to moving in a narrow channel where they cannot pass one another, resulting in constrained motion and anomalous long-time diffusion. In this study, we use Brownian dynamics simulations and analytical theory to investigate the SFD of athermal active Brownian particles (ABPs), a minimal model of active colloids. Building on prior work (Phys. Rev. E 108, 064601 (2023)), where the kinetic temperature, pressure, and compressibility of the single-file ABP system were derived, we develop an accurate analytical expression for the mean square displacement (MSD) of a tagged particle. We find that the MSD exhibits ballistic behavior at short times, governed by the reduced kinetic temperature of the system. At long times, the characteristic subdiffusive scaling of SFD, $\langle (\Delta x)^2 \rangle \sim t^{1/2}$, is preserved. However, self-propulsion introduces significant changes to the 1D mobility, which we directly relate to the system's compressibility. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the generalized 1D mobility, originally proposed by Kollmann for equilibrium systems (Phys. Rev. Lett. 90, 180602 (2003)), can be extended to active systems with minimal modification. These findings provide a framework for understanding particle transport in active systems and for tuning transport properties at the microscale, particularly in geometries where motion is highly restricted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08988v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0248772</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 162, 164902 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Akintunde, P. Bayati, H. Row, S. A. Mallory</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions and remnants of fractionalization at finite temperature in the triangular lattice quantum loop model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01503v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The quantum loop and dimer models are archetypal correlated systems with local constraints. With natural foundations in statistical mechanics, they are of direct relevance to various important physical concepts and systems, such as topological order, lattice gauge theories, geometric frustrations, or more recently Rydberg arrays quantum simulators. However, how the thermal fluctuations interact with constraints has not been explored in the important class of non-bipartite geometries. Here we study, via unbiased quantum Monte Carlo simulations and field theoretical analysis, the finite-temperature phase diagram of the quantum loop model on the triangular lattice. We discover that the recently identified, "hidden" vison plaquette (VP) quantum crystal [1] experiences a finite-temperature continuous transition, which smoothly connects to the (2+1)d Cubic* quantum critical point separating the VP and $\mathbb{Z}_{2}$ quantum spin liquid phases. This finite-temperature phase transition acquires a unique property of ``remnants of fractionalization" at finite temperature, in that, both the cubic order parameter -- the plaquette loop resonance -- and its constituent -- the vison field -- exhibit independent criticality signatures. This phase transition is connected to a 3-state Potts transition between the lattice nematic phase and the high-temperature disordered phase. We discuss the relevance of our results for current experiments on quantum simulation platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01503v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxue Ran, Sylvain Capponi, Junchen Rong, Fabien Alet, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1d Ising model with $1/r^{1.99}$ interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12243v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the 1d Ising model with long-range interactions decaying as $1/r^{1+s}$. The critical model corresponds to a family of 1d conformal field theories (CFTs) whose data depends nontrivially on $s$ in the range $1/2\leq s\leq 1$. The model is known to be described by a generalized free field with quartic interaction, which is weakly coupled near $s=1/2$ but strongly coupled near the short-range crossover at $s=1$. We propose a dual description which becomes weakly coupled at $s=1$. At $s=1$, our model becomes an exactly solvable conformal boundary condition for the 2d free scalar. We perform a number of consistency checks of our proposal and calculate the perturbative CFT data around $s=1$ analytically using both 1) our proposed field theory and 2) the analytic conformal bootstrap. Our results show complete agreement between the two methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12243v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.201602</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 201602 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dario Benedetti, Edoardo Lauria, Dalimil Maz\'a\v{c}, Philine van Vliet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why do financial prices exhibit Brownian motion despite predictable order flow?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17906v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In financial market microstructure, there are two enigmatic empirical laws: (i) the market-order flow has predictable persistence due to metaorder splitters by institutional investors, well formulated as the Lillo-Mike-Farmer model. However, this phenomenon seems paradoxical given the diffusive and unpredictable price dynamics; (ii) the price impact $I(Q)$ of a large metaorder $Q$ follows the square-root law, $I(Q)\propto \sqrt{Q}$. Here we theoretically reveal why price dynamics follows Brownian motion despite predictable order flow by unifying these enigmas. We generalize the Lillo-Mike-Farmer model to nonlinear price-impact dynamics, which is mapped to an exactly solvable L\'evy-walk model. Our exact solution shows that the price dynamics remains diffusive under the square-root law, even under persistent order flow. This work illustrates the crucial role of the square-root law in mitigating large price movements by large metaorders, thereby leading to the Brownian price dynamics, consistently with the efficient market hypothesis over long timescales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17906v4</guid>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Sato, Kiyoshi Kanazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive-Scale Simulations of 2D Ising and Blume-Capel Models on Rack-Scale Multi-GPU Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18624v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present high-performance implementations of the two-dimensional Ising and Blume-Capel models for large-scale, multi-GPU simulations. Our approach takes full advantage of the NVIDIA GB200 NVL72 system, which features up to $72$ GPUs interconnected via high-bandwidth NVLink, enabling direct GPU-to-GPU memory access across multiple nodes. By utilizing Fabric Memory and an optimized Monte Carlo kernel for the Ising model, our implementation supports simulations of systems with linear sizes up to $L=2^{23}$, corresponding to approximately $70$ trillion spins. This allows for a peak processing rate of nearly $1.15 \times 10^5$ lattice updates per nanosecond-setting a new performance benchmark for Ising model simulations. Additionally, we introduce a custom protocol for computing correlation functions, which strikes an optimal balance between computational efficiency and statistical accuracy. This protocol enables large-scale simulations without incurring prohibitive runtime costs. Benchmark results show near-perfect strong and weak scaling up to $64$ GPUs, demonstrating the effectiveness of our approach for large-scale statistical physics simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18624v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauro Bisson, Massimo Bernaschi, Massimiliano Fatica, Nikolaos G. Fytas, Isidoro Gonz\'alez-Adalid Pemart\'in, V\'ictor Mart\'in-Mayor, Alexandros Vasilopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
