<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 04:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multicomponent Linear Transport in the Absence of Local Equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The linear laws of transport phenomena are central in our description of irreversible processes in systems across the physical sciences. Linear irreversible thermodynamics allows for the identification of the underlying forces driving transport and the structure of the relevant transport coefficients for systems that are locally in equilibrium. Increasingly, linear relations are found to describe transport in systems in which a local equilibrium hypothesis is unlikely to hold. Here, we derive a mechanical theory of multicomponent transport without appealing to equilibrium notions. Our theory for the Onsager transport tensor highlights the general breakdown of the familiar Onsager reciprocal relations and Einstein relations when a local equilibrium is absent. The procedure outlined is applied to a variety of systems, including passive systems, mixtures with nonreciprocal interactions, electrolytes under an electric field, and active systems, and can be straightforwardly used to understand other transport processes. The framework further provides a basis to extend numerical approaches for computing the transport coefficients of nonequilibrium systems, as is demonstrated for a system with nonreciprocal interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23906v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Jen Chiu, Eric M. Weiner, Ahmad K. Omar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bose-Einstein Condensation, Fluctuations and Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The realisation of Bose-Einstein condensation under grand-canonical conditions has provided the experimental evidence for the simultaneous occurrence of macroscopic fluctuations and phase coherence of the condensate. The observation of these two features, against a consolidated tradition which wants the fluctuations to be pathological (grand-canonical catastrophe) and incompatible with spontaneous symmetry braking, calls for a comprehensive rethinking of the approach to the problem. In this paper we consider the uniform ideal gas in a box and we present an alternative conceptual framework. We show that the usually-employed Bogoliubov quasi-average construction fails to reproduce the broken-symmetry state. The observed features are accounted for by a different pattern of spontaneous symmetry breaking, characterised by condensation of fluctuations and long-range correlations of the order parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24228v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Crisanti, A. Sarracino, M. Zannetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinning algorithms for the Monte Carlo simulation of kinetic Ising models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The thinning method for numerical generation of the nonhomogeneous Poisson process (NHPP) arrival times has been adapted to accelerate Monte Carlo simulations of the kinetic Ising models (KIMs) with the Glauber spin-flip dynamics. The performance of the suggested algorithms has been illustrated by simulation of the decay of metastable states in stationary KIMs and of hysteresis in KIMs in a periodic external field. The thinning has been implemented by means of piecewise constant majorizing functions which exceed or are equal to NHPP rate. It has been shown that in favorable cases the use of thinning makes possible the simulations of hysteresis at frequencies in tens nanohertz and the decay of metastable states with lifetimes by many orders exceeding those in previous simulations. Good agreement of simulated results with low-temperature analytic theories has been established. Though the algorithm acceleration has been shown to enhance with lowering temperature, the hysteresis has been simulated at moderately low temperatures of practical interest estimated to cover the range from below the room temperature up to temperatures used in hyperthermia applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24414v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Tokar, H. Dreyss\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-Passage-Time Asymmetry for Biased Run-and-Tumble Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24483v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore first-passage phenomenology for biased active processes with a renewal-type structure, focusing in particular on paradigmatic run-and-tumble models in both discrete and continuous state spaces. In general, we show there is no symmetry between distributions of first-passage times to symmetric barriers positioned in and against the bias direction; however, we give conditions for such a duality to be restored asymptotically (in the limit of a large barrier distance) and highlight connections to the Gallavotti-Cohen fluctuation relation and the method of images. Our general trajectory arguments are supported by exact analytical calculations of first-passage-time distributions for asymmetric run-and-tumble processes escaping from an interval of arbitrary width, and these calculations are confirmed with high accuracy via extensive numerics. Furthermore, we quantify the degree of violation of first-passage duality using Kullback-Leibler divergence and signal-to-noise ratios associated with the first-passage times to the two barriers. We reveal an intriguing dependence of such measures of first-passage asymmetry on the underlying tumbling dynamics which may inspire inference techniques based on first-passage-time statistics in active systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24483v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonathan Sarmiento, Benjamin Walter, Debraj Das, Samvit Mahapatra, \'Edgar Rold\'an, Rosemary J. Harris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed-form survival probabilities for biased random walks at arbitrary step number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a closed-form expression for the survival probability of a biased random walker to first reach a target site on a 1D lattice. The expression holds for any step number $N$ and is computationally faster than non-closed-form results in the literature. Because our result is exact even in the intermediate step number range, it serves as a tool to study convergence to the large $N$ limit. We also obtain a closed-form expression for the probability of last passage. In contrast to predictions of the large $N$ approximation, the new expression reveals a critical value of the bias beyond which the tail of the last-passage probability decays monotonically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24814v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debendro Mookerjee, Sarah Kostinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Gaussian Network Model: a non-equilibrium description of protein fluctuations and allosteric behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the link between structure and function in proteins is fundamental in molecular biology and proteomics. A central question in this context is whether allostery - where the binding of a molecule at one site affects the activity of a distant site - emerges as a further manifestation of the intricate interplay between structure, function, and intrinsic dynamics. This study explores how allosteric regulation is modified when intrinsic protein dynamics operate under out-of-equilibrium conditions. To this purpose, we introduce a simple nonequilibrium model of protein dynamics, inspired by active matter systems, by generalizing the widely employed Gaussian Network Model (GNM) to incorporate non-thermal effects. Our approach underscores the advantage of framing allostery as a causal process by using, as a benchmark system, the second PDZ domain of the human phosphatase hPT1E that mediates protein-protein interactions. We employ causal indicators, such as response functions and transfer entropy, to identify the network of PDZ2 residues through which the allosteric signal propagates across the protein structure. These indicators reveal specific regions that align well with experimental observations. Furthermore, our results suggest that deviations from purely thermal fluctuations can significantly influence allosteric communication by introducing distinct timescales and memory effects. This influence is particularly relevant when the allosteric response unfolds on timescales incompatible with relaxation to equilibrium. Accordingly, non-thermal fluctuations may become essential for accurately describing protein responses to ligand binding and developing a comprehensive understanding of allosteric regulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24855v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Costantini, Lorenzo Caprini, Umberto Marini Bettolo Marconi, Fabio Cecconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roughening and dynamics of an electric flux string in a (2+1)D lattice gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23853v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the roughening transition in the pure $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory in (2+1) dimensions. Using numerical simulations with matrix product states, we explore the static and dynamical properties of an electric flux string between two static charges as the coupling is varied and approaches the deconfinement phase transition from the confined phase. Within the roughening region, we obtain the universal L\"uscher correction to the confining potential and observe the expected restoration of rotational symmetry. Our simulations of the out-of-equilibrium evolution of a string reveal that the growth of the entanglement entropy of the state and the string width exhibit qualitatively different behavior in the roughening region compared to the deeply confined one. In particular, we find that the rate of entropy growth is consistent with an effective description of the string excitations by a bosonic model in the roughening phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23853v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Di Marcantonio, Sunny Pradhan, Sofia Vallecorsa, Mari Carmen Ba\~nuls, Enrique Rico Ortega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical Dynamics of Random Surfaces and Multifractal Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23928v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The critical dynamics of conformal field theories on random surfaces is investigated beyond the dynamics of the overall area and the genus. It is found that the evolution of the order parameter in physical time is a multifractal random walk. Accordingly, the higher moments of time variations of the order parameter exhibit multifractal scaling. The series of Hurst exponents is computed and illustrated with the examples of the Ising-, 3-state-Potts-, and general minimal models on a random surface. Models are identified that can replicate the observed multifractal scaling in financial markets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23928v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christof Schmidhuber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Line and Planar Defects with Zero Formation Free Energy: Applications of the Phase Rule toward Ripening-Immune Microstructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24092v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Extended one- and two-dimensional defects in crystalline materials are usually metastable. The thermodynamic ground state of the material is presumed to be defect-free. Here, we investigate the conditions under which extended defects, such as grain boundaries, can exist in a multicomponent alloy when the latter reaches the thermodynamic ground state allowed by the Gibbs phase rule. We treat all extended defects as low-dimensional phases on the same footing as the conventional bulk phases. Thermodynamic analysis shows that, in the ground state, the formation free energies of all extended defects must be zero, and the system must follow a generalized phase rule. The latter predicts that only a finite number of symmetry-related defect types can coexist in the material in the ground state. Guided by the phase rule, we discuss finite-size polycrystalline and/or polyphase microstructures that are fully immune to coarsening and their possible transformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24092v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ju Li, Yuri Mishin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Phase Transitions of Matter Induced in Optically Driven Cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24318v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optical cavities have been widely applied to manipulate the properties of solid state materials inside it. We propose that in systems embedded within optical cavities driven by incident pump light, the pump induces generic phase transitions into new non-equilibrium steady states. This effect arises from the ponderomotive potential, the effective static potential exerted by the pump on the low energy degrees of freedom, which exhibits a universal step-like structure that pushes the matter degrees of freedom in the direction that red-shifts the cavity photon modes. For a two dimensional electron liquid in a driven cavity, this step-like potential pushes the electron density to jump to a smaller value so that a hybrid cavity photon mode is red shifted to slightly below the pump frequency. Similarly, for a disordered superconductor in such a driven cavity, this potential acts on the superconducting order parameter and causes a first order phase transition to a new steady state with a smaller gap. By realistic electromagnetic modeling of the cavity, we construct the non-equilibrium phase diagrams for experimentally relevant devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24318v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsan Huang, Zhiyuan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two failure modes of deep transformers and how to avoid them: a unified theory of signal propagation at initialisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24333v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Finding the right initialisation for neural networks is crucial to ensure smooth training and good performance. In transformers, the wrong initialisation can lead to one of two failure modes of self-attention layers: rank collapse, where all tokens collapse into similar representations, and entropy collapse, where highly concentrated attention scores lead to training instability. While the right initialisation has been extensively studied in feed-forward networks, an exact description of signal propagation through a full transformer block has so far been lacking. Here, we provide an analytical theory of signal propagation through vanilla transformer blocks with self-attention layers, layer normalisation, skip connections and ReLU MLP. To treat the self-attention layer, we draw on a formal parallel with the Random Energy Model from statistical physics. We identify and characterise two regimes governed by the variance of the query and key initialisations: a low-variance regime, where we recover the known rank collapse behaviour; and a previously unexplored high-variance regime, where signal is preserved but \textit{entropy collapse} occurs. In the low-variance regime, we calculate the critical strength for the residual connection to ensure signal propagation. Our theory yields trainability diagrams that identify the correct choice of initialisation hyper-parameters for a given architecture. Experiments with BERT-style models trained on TinyStories validate our predictions. Our theoretical framework gives a unified perspective on the two failure modes of self-attention and gives quantitative predictions on the scale of both weights and residual connections that guarantees smooth training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24333v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Giorlandino, Sebastian Goldt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex wave functions, CPT and quantum field theory for classical generalized Ising models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24392v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quantum or quantum field theory concept of a complex wave function is useful for understanding the information transport in classical statistical generalized Ising models.
  We relate complex conjugation to the discrete transformations charge conjugation ($C$), parity ($P$) and time reversal ($T$).
  A subclass of generalized Ising models are probabilistic cellular automata (PCA) with deterministic updating and probabilistic initial conditions.
  Two-dimensional PCA correspond to discretized quantum field theories for Majorana--Weyl, Weyl or Dirac fermions.
  Momentum and energy are conserved statistical observables.
  For PCA describing free massless fermions we investigate the vacuum and field operators for particle excitations.
  These automata admit probabilistic boundary conditions that correspond to thermal equilibrium with the quantum Fermi--Dirac distribution.
  PCA with updating sequences of propagation and interaction steps can realize a rich variety of discrete quantum field theories for fermions with interactions.
  For information theory the quantum formalism for PCA sheds new light on deterministic computing or signal processing with probabilistic input.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24392v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christof Wetterich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disordering a permutation symmetric system: revivals, thermalization and chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study explores the effects of introducing a symmetry breaking disorder on the dynamics of a system invariant under particle permutation. The disorder forces quantum states, confined to the $N+1$ dimensional completely symmetric space to penetrate the exponentially large $2^N$ dimensional Hilbert space of $N$ particles. In particular, we focus on the quantum kicked top as a Floquet system of $N$ qubits, and use linear entropy, measuring single qubit entanglement, to investigate the changes in the time scales and values of saturation when disorder is introduced. In the near-integrable regime of the kicked top, we study the robustness of quantum revivals to disorder. We also find that a classical calculation yields the quantum single qubit entanglement to remarkable accuracy in the disorder free limit. The disorder, on the other hand, is modeled in the form of noise which again fits well with the numerical calculations. We measure the extent to which the dynamics is retained within the symmetric subspace and its spreading to the full Hilbert space using different quantities. We show that increasing disorder drives the system to a chaotic phase in full Hilbert space, as also supported by the spectral statistics. We find that there is robustness to disorder in the system, and this is a function of how chaotic the kicked top is.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24453v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manju C, Uma Divakaran, Arul Lakshminarayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical demand in a stochastic model of flows in supply networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24813v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Supply networks are essential for modern production, yet their critical properties remain understudied. We present a stochastic model with random production capacities to analyze material flow to a root node, focusing on topology and buffer stocks. The critical demand, where unsatisfied demand diverges, is examined mostly through numerical simulations. Without stocks, minimal production dictates behavior, making topology irrelevant. With stocks, memory effects arise, making topology crucial. Increased local connectivity is beneficial: firms should favor broad, short supply chains over long, narrow ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24813v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 217401 (Published 30 May, 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yannick Feld, Marc Barthelemy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical mechanics of extensive-width Bayesian neural networks near interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24849v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For three decades statistical mechanics has been providing a framework to analyse neural networks. However, the theoretically tractable models, e.g., perceptrons, random features models and kernel machines, or multi-index models and committee machines with few neurons, remained simple compared to those used in applications. In this paper we help reducing the gap between practical networks and their theoretical understanding through a statistical physics analysis of the supervised learning of a two-layer fully connected network with generic weight distribution and activation function, whose hidden layer is large but remains proportional to the inputs dimension. This makes it more realistic than infinitely wide networks where no feature learning occurs, but also more expressive than narrow ones or with fixed inner weights. We focus on the Bayes-optimal learning in the teacher-student scenario, i.e., with a dataset generated by another network with the same architecture. We operate around interpolation, where the number of trainable parameters and of data are comparable and feature learning emerges. Our analysis uncovers a rich phenomenology with various learning transitions as the number of data increases. In particular, the more strongly the features (i.e., hidden neurons of the target) contribute to the observed responses, the less data is needed to learn them. Moreover, when the data is scarce, the model only learns non-linear combinations of the teacher weights, rather than "specialising" by aligning its weights with the teacher's. Specialisation occurs only when enough data becomes available, but it can be hard to find for practical training algorithms, possibly due to statistical-to-computational~gaps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24849v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Barbier, Francesco Camilli, Minh-Toan Nguyen, Mauro Pastore, Rudy Skerk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Journey from the Wilson exact RG towards the Wegner-Morris Fokker-Planck RG and the Carosso field-coarsening via Langevin stochastic processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09506v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Within the Wilson RG of 'incomplete integration' as a function of the effective RG-time $t$, the non-linear differential RG-flow for the energy $E_t[\phi(.)]$ translates for the probability distribution $P_t[\phi(.)] \sim e^{- E_t[\phi(.)]} $ into the linear Fokker-Planck RG-flow associated to independent non-identical Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes for the Fourier modes. The corresponding Langevin stochastic differential equations for the real-space field $\phi_t(\vec x)$ have been recently interpreted by Carosso as genuine infinitesimal coarsening-transformations that are the analog of spin-blocking, and whose irreversible character is essential to overcome the paradox of the naive description of the Wegner-Morris Continuity-Equation for the RG-flow as a meaningless infinitesimal change of variables in the partition function integral. This interpretation suggests to consider new RG-schemes, in particular the Carosso RG where the Langevin SDE corresponds to the stochastic heat equation also known as the Edwards-Wilkinson dynamics. After a pedestrian self-contained introduction to this stochastic formulation of RG-flows, we focus on the case where the field theory is defined on the large volume $L^d$ with periodic boundary conditions, in order to distinguish between extensive and intensives observables while keeping the translation-invariance. Since the empirical magnetization $m_e \equiv \frac{1}{L^d} \int_{L^d} d^d \vec x \ \phi(\vec x) $ is an intensive variable corresponding to the zero-momentum Fourier coefficient of the field, its probability distribution $p_L(m_e)$ can be obtained from the gradual integration over all the other Fourier coefficients associated to non-vanishing-momenta via an appropriate adaptation of the Carosso stochastic RG, in order to obtain the large deviation properties with respect to the volume $L^d$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09506v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1742-5468/add512</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Stat. Mech. (2025) 053210</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cecile Monthus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement-invisible quantum correlations in scrambling dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24212v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Scrambling unitary dynamics in a quantum system transmutes local quantum information into a non-local web of correlations which manifests itself in a complex spatio-temporal pattern of entanglement. In such a context, we show there can exist three distinct dynamical phases characterised by qualitatively different forms of quantum correlations between two disjoint subsystems of the system. Transitions between these phases are driven by the relative sizes of the subsystems and the degree scrambling that the dynamics effects. Besides a phase which has no quantum correlations as manifested by vanishing entanglement between the parts and a phase which has non-trivial quantum correlations quantified by a finite entanglement monotone, we reveal a new phase transition within the entangled phase which separates phases wherein the quantum correlations are invisible or visible to measurements on one of the subsystems. This is encoded in the qualitatively different properties of the ensemble of states on one of the subsystems conditioned on the various measurement outcomes on the other subsystem. This provides a new characterisation of entanglement phases in terms of their response to measurements instead of the more ubiquitous measurement-induced entanglement transitions. Our results have implications for the kind of tasks that can be performed using measurement feedback within the framework of quantum interactive dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24212v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.L180301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, L180301 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alan Sherry, Sthitadhi Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision bounds for multiple currents in open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09088v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Thermodynamic (TUR) and kinetic (KUR) uncertainty relations are fundamental bounds constraining the fluctuations of current observables in classical, non-equilibrium systems. Several works have verified, however, violations of these classical bounds in open quantum systems, motivating the derivation of new quantum TURs and KURs that account for the role of quantum coherence. Here, we go one step further by deriving multidimensional KUR and TUR for multiple observables in open quantum systems undergoing Markovian dynamics. Our derivation exploits a multi-parameter metrology approach, in which the Fisher information matrix plays a central role. Crucially, our bounds are tighter than previously derived quantum TURs and KURs for single observables, precisely because they incorporate correlations between multiple observables. We also find an intriguing quantum signature of correlations that is captured by the off-diagonal element of the Fisher information matrix, which vanishes for classical stochastic dynamics. By considering two examples, namely a coherently driven qubit system and the three-level maser, we demonstrate that the multidimensional quantum KUR bound can even be saturated when the observables are perfectly correlated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09088v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saulo V. Moreira, Marco Radaelli, Alessandro Candeloro, Felix C. Binder, Mark T. Mitchison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable amplitude of Sondheimer oscillations in thin cadmium crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11586v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Decades ago, Sondheimer discovered that the electric conductivity of metallic crystals hosting ballistic electrons oscillates with magnetic field. These oscillations, periodic in magnetic field with the period proportional to the sample thickness, have been understood in a semi-classical framework. Here, we present a study of longitudinal and transverse conductivity in cadmium single crystals with thickness varying between 12.6 to 475 $\mu$m. When the magnetic field is sufficiently large or the sample sufficiently thick, the amplitude of oscillation falls off as $B^{-4}$ as previously reported. In contrast, the ten first oscillations follow a $B^{-2.5}e^{-B/B_0}$ field dependence and their amplitude is set by the quantum of conductance, the sample thickness, the magnetic length and the Fermi surface geometry. This expression is in disagreement with what was predicted in semi-classical scenarios, which neglect Landau quantization. We argue that the classical/quantum crossover occurs at accessible magnetic fields for states whose Fermi wave-vector is almost parallel to the magnetic field. As a consequence, the intersection between the lowest Landau tube and flat toroids on the Fermi surface induced by confinement give rise to oscillations with a periodicity identical to the semi-classical one. A rigorous theoretical account of our data is missing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11586v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodong Guo, Xiaokang Li, Lingxiao Zhao, Zengwei Zhu, Kamran Behnia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trends and Reversion in Financial Markets on Time Scales from Minutes to Decades</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16772v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We empirically analyze the reversion of financial market trends with time horizons ranging from minutes to decades. The analysis covers equities, interest rates, currencies and commodities and combines 14 years of futures tick data, 30 years of daily futures prices, 330 years of monthly asset prices, and yearly financial data since medieval times.
  Across asset classes, we find that markets are in a trending regime on time scales that range from a few hours to a few years, while they are in a reversion regime on shorter and longer time scales. In the trending regime, weak trends tend to persist, which can be explained by herding behavior of investors. However, in this regime trends tend to revert before they become strong enough to be statistically significant, which can be interpreted as a return of asset prices to their intrinsic value. In the reversion regime, we find the opposite pattern: weak trends tend to revert, while those trends that become statistically significant tend to persist.
  Our results provide a set of empirical tests of theoretical models of financial markets. We interpret them in the light of a recently proposed lattice gas model, where the lattice represents the social network of traders, the gas molecules represent the shares of financial assets, and efficient markets correspond to the critical point. If this model is accurate, the lattice gas must be near this critical point on time scales from 1 hour to a few days, with a correlation time of a few years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16772v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara A. Safari, Christof Schmidhuber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stretching Response of a Polymer Chain with Deformable Bonds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08602v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The stretching response of polymer chains fundamentally determines the mechanical properties of polymer networks. In this Letter, we develop a statistical mechanics model that incorporates both bond stretching and bond angle deformation, enabling accurate predictions of chain behavior up to large forces. We further propose a semianalytical deformable freely rotating chain (dFRC) model, which represents the chain as a freely rotating chain with effective bond stretch and bond angle that depend on the chain stretch. Using physical parameters without fitting, both the statistical and dFRC models achieve excellent agreement with experimental data for carbon chains across all force regimes. Additionally, the dFRC model provides a direct estimate of the bond force, which is important to predict chain scission. By capturing key bond deformations while remaining computationally efficient, our work lays the foundation for future modeling of polymer network elasticity and failure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08602v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.218101</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jie Zhu, Laurence Brassart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antifragility and response to damage in the synchronization of oscillators on networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15148v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a mathematical framework to assess the impact of damage, defined as the reduction of weight in a specific link, on identical oscillator systems governed by the Kuramoto model and coupled through weighted networks. We analyze how weight modifications in a single link affect the system when its global function is to achieve the synchronization of coupled oscillators starting from random initial phases. We introduce different measures that allow the identification of cases where damage enhances synchronization (antifragile response), deteriorates it (fragile response), or has no significant impact. Using numerical solutions of the Kuramoto model, we investigate the effects of damage on network links where antifragility emerges. Our analysis includes lollipop graphs of varying sizes and a comprehensive evaluation and all the edges of 109 non-isomorphic graphs with six nodes. The approach is general and can be applied to study antifragility in other oscillator systems with different coupling mechanisms, offering a pathway for the quantitative exploration of antifragility in diverse complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15148v3</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/add974</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 58, 225002 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Polo-Gonz\'alez, A. P. Riascos, L. K. Eraso-Hernandez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A theory for diffusion-controlled reactions within nonequilibrium steady states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22623v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study diffusion-controlled processes in nonequilibrium steady states, where standard rate theory assumptions break down. Using transition path theory, we generalize the relations between reactive probability fluxes and measures of the rate of the reaction. Stochastic thermodynamics analysis reveals how work constrains the enhancement of rates relative to their equilibrium values. An analytically solvable ion pairing model under a strong electric field illustrates and validates our approach and theory. These findings provide deeper insights into diffusion-controlled reaction dynamics beyond equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22623v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokjin Moon, David T. Limmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
