<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 04:04:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the Pure States of the Replica Symmetry Breaking ansatz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the concept of Pure State of the Replica Symmetry Breaking ansatz in finite and infinite spin systems without averaging on the disorder, nor using replicas. Consider a system of n spins $\sigma\in\Omega^{n}$ with the usual set $\Omega=\left\{ -1,1\right\}$ of inner states and let $G:\,\Omega^{n}\rightarrow\left[0,1\right]$ a Gibbs measure on it of Hamiltonian $\mathcal{H}$ (also non random). We interpret the pure states of a model $\left(\Omega^{n},\mu\right)$ as disjoint subsets $\Omega^{n}$ such that the conditional measures behaves like product measures as in usual mean field approximations. Starting from such definition we try to reinterpret the RSB scheme and define an approximated probability measure. We then apply our results to the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model to obtain the Parisi formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02990v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Franchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure Fluctuation Effects on Canonical-Nonlinear Thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When we consider classical discrete systems under constant composition, their stable configuration in thermodynamic equilibrium can be typically obtained through the well-known canonica average phi. In configurational thermodynamics, phi as a map from many-body interatomic interaction to equilibrium configuration generally exhibits complicated nonlinearity, strongly depending on their underlying lattice. The connection between nonlinearity in phi (canonical nonlinearity) and the lattice has recently been amply investigated in terms of configurational geometry, leading to establishing its stochastic-thermodynamic treatment. The present work provides natural extention of the proposed treatment, explicitly including the effect of spatial fluctuation of the equilibrium configuration on thermodynamic property of the nonlinearity. We find that the fluctuation affects the upper-bound for the averaged nonlinearity disparity in multiple configurations, as an explicit and additional contribution from stochastic mutual information between focused coordination and its fluctuation, and an implicit contribution from changes in covariance matrix for density of states due to the fluctuation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03005v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koretaka Yuge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic systems with Bose-Hubbard interactions: Effects of bias on particles on a 1D lattice and random comb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Driven non-equilibrium lattice models have wide-ranging applications in contexts such as mass transport, traffic flow, and transport in biological systems. In this work, we investigate the steady-state properties of a one-dimensional lattice system that allows multiple particle occupancy on each site. The particles undergo stochastic nearest-neighbor jumps influenced by both a directional bias and on-site repulsive interactions. With periodic boundary conditions, we observe a non-monotonic dependence of inter-site correlation functions on the interaction strength. At large interaction strengths, the particle current exhibits a periodic dependence on density, accompanied by the formation of ordered stacks of particles. In contrast, with open boundary conditions, the system displays step-like density profiles reminiscent of those in tilted Bose-Hubbard systems, and a regime with a macroscopic number of empty sites followed by a steep parameter-dependent increase in density. Our results highlight how the interplay between drive, interaction, and boundary conditions leads to distinctive signatures on the current and density profiles in the steady state in different regimes.} {We also study the problem on a random comb, a simple model of a disordered system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03344v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swastik Majumder, Mustansir Barma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heating suppression via two-rate random and quasiperiodic drive protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a random and quasiperiodically driven one-dimensional non-integrable PXP spin chain in a magnetic field for two distinct drive protocols. Each of these protocols involves square pulses with two driving frequencies which are integer multiples of each other. For the first class of protocols, the duration of the pulse is changed randomly by an amplitude $dT$ while for the second class we use a random/quasiperiodic dipolar drive, where the quasiperiodicity is implemented using the Thue-Morse (TM) or Fibonacci sequences. For both protocols, we identify parameter regimes for which the thermalization of the driven chain is drastically slowed down due to proximity to a two-rate drive induced exact dynamical freezing. We also study the properties of these driven system moving slightly away from the freezing limit. For the first type of protocols, we show the existence of special value of $dT$ for which the thermalization rate remains small and provide an analytic explanation for such slow thermalization. For the second class of protocols, in contrast to random/quasiperiodic drives involving a single frequency studied earlier, we find that the TM quasiperiodic drive leads to a distinctly slower thermalization than that for drive protocols which are either periodic or follow a random or quasiperiodic Fibonacci sequence. We provide a qualitative semi-analytic understanding of these phenomena either using an exact calculation for small system sizes or carrying out a perturbative analysis in the large drive-amplitude limit. Our analysis brings out the central role of such two-frequency protocols in the reduction of heating in driven quantum systems. We discuss experiments which can test our theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02783v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krishanu Ghosh, Sayan Choudhury, Diptiman Sen, K. Sengupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement-Induced Entanglement in Conformal Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02788v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Local measurements can radically reshape patterns of many-body entanglement, especially in long-range entangled quantum-critical states. Yet, analytical results addressing the effects of measurements on many-body states remain scarce, and measurements are often approximated as forcing specific measurement outcomes. We study measurement-induced entanglement (MIE) in Tomonaga-Luttinger liquids, a broad family of 1+1d quantum critical states described at low energies by compact free boson conformal field theories (CFT). Measuring the local charge operator, we show that the MIE is entirely universal, conformally invariant, and depends on the operator content of the CFT. Using a replica-trick to address the randomness of the measurement outcomes, we compute the MIE exactly for Tomonaga-Luttinger liquids, in very good agreement with matrix-product state calculations. We show that the MIE for physical quantum measurements is fundamentally different from the entanglement induced by forcing measurement outcomes, and has a natural interpretation in terms of Born averaging over conformally-invariant boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02788v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kabir Khanna, Romain Vasseur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocal Model B: The role of mobilities and nonreciprocal interfacial forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02814v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a non-reciprocal version of Model B, as the continuum theory for non-reciprocal particle mixtures. In contrast to non-reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard models, it is important in this context to consider the dependence of mobility coefficients on the local concentrations. We show that a homogeneous state that is linearly stable for one form of the mobility can be unstable for a different form of mobility, an effect that would be impossible in equilibrium and implies a crucial role for mobilities in non-reciprocal mixtures. For unstable homogeneous states we study the spinodal dynamics governing the onset of phase separation. We find, again in contrast to non-reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard models, that exceptional point transitions between static and oscillatory instabilities are generically avoided by first order transitions where the spinodal lengthscale changes discontinuously. At these transitions we find intricate spinodal dynamics with two competing lengthscales, one governing a static instability and the other an oscillatory instability, i.e. one that generates travelling waves. We demonstrate that, depending on interaction strengths, more complex transitions can occur in the spinodal dynamics, including coexistence of three lengthscales and first order transition lines, terminated by critical points, between distinct static instabilities. Finally, we explore the effects of additional non-reciprocity in the interfacial chemical potentials, which would generically be expected when obtaining Model B by coarse graining from a non-reciprocal particle model. We show that interfacial non-reciprocity can increase the region in the spinodal phase diagram where oscillatory instabilities occur, but only up to a certain boundary that we establish analytically and demonstrate numerically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02814v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bibhut Sahoo, Rituparno Mandal, Peter Sollich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrable multispecies totally asymmetric stochastic interacting particle systems with homogeneous rates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03157v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study one dimensional stochastic particle systems with exclusion interaction that each site can be occupied by at most one particle, and homogeneous jumping rates. Alimohammadi and Ahmadi previously classified 28 Yang-Baxter integrable two-particle interaction rules for the two species models with homogeneous rates. In this work, we show that 7 of these 28 cases can be naturally extended to integrable models with an arbitrary number of species $N \geq 2$. Moreover, we discover new integrable models with one or two parameters that generalize these 7 cases. For 8 of the remaining 21 cases, we propose an alternative extension scheme that yields integrable $N$ species models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03157v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eunghyun Lee, Temirlan Raimbekov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic thermodynamics of computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.05669</link>
      <description>arXiv:1905.05669v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the major resource requirements of computers - ranging from biological cells to human brains to high-performance (engineered) computers - is the energy used to run them. Those costs of performing a computation have long been a focus of research in physics, going back to the early work of Landauer. One of the most prominent aspects of computers is that they are inherently nonequilibrium systems. However, the early research was done when nonequilibrium statistical physics was in its infancy, which meant the work was formulated in terms of equilibrium statistical physics. Since then there have been major breakthroughs in nonequilibrium statistical physics, which are allowing us to investigate the myriad aspects of the relationship between statistical physics and computation, extending well beyond the issue of how much work is required to erase a bit. In this paper I review some of this recent work on the `stochastic thermodynamics of computation'. After reviewing the salient parts of information theory, computer science theory, and stochastic thermodynamics, I summarize what has been learned about the entropic costs of performing a broad range of computations, extending from bit erasure to loop-free circuits to logically reversible circuits to information ratchets to Turing machines. These results reveal new, challenging engineering problems for how to design computers to have minimal thermodynamic costs. They also allow us to start to combine computer science theory and stochastic thermodynamics at a foundational level, thereby expanding both.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1905.05669v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/ab0850</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Invited article for special issue, "Shannon's information theory: 70 years on", Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, 2019</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David H. Wolpert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion cascade in a model of interacting random walkers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05222v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the relaxation of finite-wavevector density waves in a facilitated classical lattice gas. Linear hydrodynamics predicts that such perturbations should relax exponentially, but nonlinear effects were predicted to cause subexponential relaxation via nonperturbative long-time tails. We present a detailed numerical study of this effect. While our results clearly indicate the importance of nonlinear effects, we find that the wavevector-dependence of the late-time relaxation is clearly inconsistent with theoretical predictions. We discuss manifestations of hydrodynamic nonlinearities in mesoscopic samples and at short times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05222v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Raj, Paolo Glorioso, Sarang Gopalakrishnan, Vadim Oganesyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic 1D search-and-capture as a G/M/c queueing model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21883v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the accumulation of resources within a target due to the interplay between continual delivery, driven by 1D stochastic search processes, and sequential consumption. The assumption of sequential consumption is key because it changes the commonly used $G/M/\infty$ queue to a $G/M/c$ queue. Combining the theory of $G/M/c$ queues with the theory of first-passage times, we derive general conditions for the search process to ensure that the number of resources within the queue converges to a steady state and compute explicit expressions for the mean and variance of the number of resources within the queue at steady state. We then compare the performance of the $G/M/c$ queue with that of the $G/M/\infty$ queue for an increasing number of servers. We extend the model to consider two competing targets and show that, under specific scenarios, an additional target is beneficial to the original target. Finally, we study the effects of multiple searchers. Using renewal theory, we numerically compute the inter-arrival time density for $M$ searchers in the Laplace space, which allows us to exploit the explicit expressions for the steady-state statistics of the number of resources within $G/M/1$ and $G/M/\infty$ queues, and compare their behaviour with different numbers of searchers. Overall, the $G/M/c$ queue shows a tighter dependence on the configuration of the search process than the $G/M/\infty$ queue does.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21883v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Giral-Barajas, Paul C Bressloff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-Affected Dynamical Quantum Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03005v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the effects of uncorrelated noise on dynamical quantum phase transitions (DQPTs) in fermionic two-band models following a quantum ramp across critical points. We consider a generalized Loschmidt echo for the noise-averaged density matrix $\bar\rho$, which is a mixed state in general, as well as the pure state Loschmidt echo calculated for each noise realization with the average performed over the corresponding return rates. $\bar\rho$ can be obtained from a master equation and we show that for two-band models noise destroys its coherences which typically drives $\bar\rho$ towards the completely mixed state which is an attractive fixed point. DQPTs are thus always smoothed out for finite noise. For single noise realizations, on the other hand, we find that DQPTs under certain conditions are always present irrespective of the noise level. This leads to remarkable stable though slightly broadened DQPT-like features in the averaged return rate. We illustrate our results for the XY model by considering a noisy ramp as well as noise in the energy levels of the final Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03005v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Jafari, Alireza Akbari, Mehdi Biderang, Jesko Sirker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Waves without Spin-Waves: A Case for Soliton Propagation in Starling Flocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19665v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Collective turns in starling flocks propagate linearly with negligible attenuation, indicating the existence of an underdamped sector in the dispersion relation. Beside granting linear propagation of the phase perturbations, the real part of the frequency should also yield a spin-wave form of the unperturbed correlation function. However, new high-resolution experiments on real flocks show that underdamped traveling waves coexist with an overdamped Lorentzian correlation. Theory and experiments are reconciled once we add to the dynamics a Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19665v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Cavagna, Guido Cimino, Javier Crist\'in, Matteo Fiorini, Irene Giardina, Angelo Giustiniani, Tom\'as S. Grigera, Stefania Melillo, Roberto A. Palombella, Leonardo Parisi, Antonio Ponno, Mattia Scandolo, Zachary S. Stamler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chaos in Nonequilibrium Two-Temperature $(T_x, T_y)$ Nos\'e-Hoover Cell Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10863v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit a two-temperature Nos\'e-Hoover wanderer particle embedded in a two-dimensional periodic 2x2 cell with four smooth repulsive corners at $(x,y) = (\pm 1, \pm 1)$ to explore chaos with anisotropic thermostatting. The model employs separate thermostats in the x and y directions, enabling controlled deviations from equilibrium. By integrating the full six-dimensional equations of motion and computing the complete Lyapunov spectrum, we confirm chaos and quantify phase-space contraction with high numerical precision. The total contraction rate, interpreted as entropy production, grows nonlinearly with the thermostat anisotropy and follows a superquadratic power law, $\Lambda\propto -\delta^{2.44}$, deviating from linear-response theory, $\Lambda\propto -\delta^{2}$. We compare this behavior to a quartic correction to the linear-response prediction and discuss both fits in light of their empirical and theoretical implications. Our results demonstrate that nonlinear dissipation scaling emerges naturally even in minimal driven systems. The approximate Kaplan-Yorke dimension reveals a fractal attractor that concentrates as $|T_x - T_y|$ increases. Momentum statistics show significant non-Gaussian behavior under strong driving. Despite its dissipative nature, the model remains strictly time-reversible, offering a pedagogically rich example of microscopic reversibility coexisting with macroscopic entropy production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10863v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hesam Arabzadeh, Carol Griswold Hoover, William Graham Hoover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A More Convex Ising Formulation of Max-3-Cut Using Higher-Order Spin Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00565v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many combinatorial optimization problems (COPs) are naturally expressed using variables that take on more than two discrete values. To solve such problems using Ising machines (IMs) - specialized analog or digital devices designed to solve COPs efficiently - these multi-valued integers must be encoded using binary spin variables. A common approach is one-hot encoding, where each variable is represented by a group of spins constrained so that exactly one spin is in the "up" state. However, this encoding introduces energy barriers: changing an integer's value requires flipping two spins and passing through an invalid intermediate state. This creates rugged energy landscapes that may hinder optimization. We propose a higher-order Ising formulation for Max-3-Cut, which is the smallest fundamental COP with multi-valued integer variables. Our formulation preserves valid configurations under single-spin updates. The resulting energy landscapes are smoother, and we show that this remains true even when the binary variables are relaxed to continuous values, making it well-suited for analog IMs as well. Benchmarking on such an IM, we find that the higher-order formulation leads to significantly faster solutions than the Ising baseline. Interestingly, we find that an empirical rescaling of some terms in the Ising formulation - a heuristic proposed in prior work - approaches the performance of the higher-order Ising formulation, underscoring the importance of empirical parameter tuning in COP encodings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00565v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robbe De Prins, Guy Van der Sande, Peter Bienstman, Thomas Van Vaerenbergh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multistep reversible excitation transfer in a multicomponent rigid solution: II. Modeling the dynamics of radiationless transfer as a time-resolved Markov chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15425v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To determine the effect of nonradiative excitation energy transfer on the fluorescence of a rigid multicomponent solution, a new analytical method was developed by treating this transfer as a time-resolved Markov chain (TRMC). In the TRMC approach, we assume that the Markov chain under consideration is governed by bivariate joint probability mass-density functions. One of the random variables is discrete and represents the state number to which the process passes at a given step, while the other random variable is continuous and determines the moment in time at which this transition occurs. In general, the time distributions of this second variable can be arbitrary, continuous or discrete, and not just exponential, as required by the method known as continuous time Markov chains (CTMC). The agreement between the basic expressions of the TRMC method and the analogous expressions of the renewal theory has been demonstrated. The correctness of the TRMC method is confirmed by the fact that the time courses of fluorescence intensities calculated by this method agree with those calculated using ordinary analytical methods. In the section on calculating the quantum yields of individual components, the suitability of a method known as discrete time Markov chains (DTMC) was found. However, we argue that the DTMC method does not refer to time and propose to rename it as time-unspecified Markov chain (TUMC). The results generated by TRMC, when integrated over time, become equivalent to those generated by TUMC. The fluorescence cases of binary and ternary solutions are discussed in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15425v5</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'ozef Ku\'sba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The generic temperature response of large biochemical networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17202v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Biological systems are remarkably susceptible to relatively small temperature changes. The most obvious example is fever, when a modest rise in body temperature of only few Kelvin has strong effects on our immune system and how it fights pathogens. Another very important example is climate change, when even smaller temperature changes lead to dramatic shifts in ecosystems. Although it is generally accepted that the main effect of an increase in temperature is the acceleration of biochemical reactions according to the Arrhenius equation, it is not clear how it affects large biochemical networks with complicated architectures. For developmental systems like fly and frog, it has been shown that the system response to temperature deviates in a characteristic manner from the linear Arrhenius plot of single reactions, but a rigorous explanation has not been given yet. Here we use a graph-theoretical interpretation of the mean first-passage times of a biochemical master equation to give a statistical description. We find that in the limit of large system size and if the network has a bias towards a target state, then the Arrhenius plot is generically quadratic, in excellent agreement with numerical simulations for large networks as well as with experimental data for developmental times in fly and frog. We also discuss under which conditions this generic response can be violated, for example for linear chains, which have only one spanning tree.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17202v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian B. Voits (Heidelberg University), Ulrich S. Schwarz (Heidelberg University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing quantum complexity via universal saturation of stabilizer entropies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04190v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nonstabilizerness or `magic' is a key resource for quantum computing and a necessary condition for quantum advantage. Non-Clifford operations turn stabilizer states into resourceful states, where the amount of nonstabilizerness is quantified by resource measures such as stabilizer R\'enyi entropies (SREs). Here, we show that SREs saturate their maximum value at a critical number of non-Clifford operations. Close to the critical point SREs show universal behavior. Remarkably, the derivative of the SRE crosses at the same point independent of the number of qubits and can be rescaled onto a single curve. We find that the critical point depends non-trivially on R\'enyi index $\alpha$. For random Clifford circuits doped with T-gates, the critical T-gate density scales independently of $\alpha$. In contrast, for random Hamiltonian evolution, the critical time scales linearly with qubit number for $\alpha&gt;1$, while is a constant for $\alpha&lt;1$. This highlights that $\alpha$-SREs reveal fundamentally different aspects of nonstabilizerness depending on $\alpha$: $\alpha$-SREs with $\alpha&lt;1$ relate to Clifford simulation complexity, while $\alpha&gt;1$ probe the distance to the closest stabilizer state and approximate state certification cost via Pauli measurements. As technical contributions, we observe that the Pauli spectrum of random evolution can be approximated by two highly concentrated peaks which allows us to compute its SRE. Further, we introduce a class of random evolution that can be expressed as random Clifford circuits and rotations, where we provide its exact SRE. Our results opens up new approaches to characterize the complexity of quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04190v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22331/q-2025-07-21-1801</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum 9, 1801 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Haug, Leandro Aolita, M. S. Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CrystalGRW: Generative Modeling of Crystal Structures with Targeted Properties via Geodesic Random Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08998v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Determining whether a candidate crystalline material is thermodynamically stable depends on identifying its true ground-state structure, a central challenge in computational materials science. We introduce CrystalGRW, a diffusion-based generative model on Riemannian manifolds that proposes novel crystal configurations and can predict stable phases validated by density functional theory. The crystal properties, such as fractional coordinates, atomic types, and lattice matrices, are represented on suitable Riemannian manifolds, ensuring that new predictions generated through the diffusion process preserve the periodicity of crystal structures. We incorporate an equivariant graph neural network to also account for rotational and translational symmetries during the generation process. CrystalGRW demonstrates the ability to generate realistic crystal structures that are close to their ground states with accuracy comparable to existing models, while also enabling conditional control, such as specifying a desired crystallographic point group. These features help accelerate materials discovery and inverse design by offering stable, symmetry-consistent crystal candidates for experimental validation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08998v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krit Tangsongcharoen, Teerachote Pakornchote, Chayanon Atthapak, Natthaphon Choomphon-anomakhun, Annop Ektarawong, Bj\"orn Alling, Christopher Sutton, Thiti Bovornratanaraks, Thiparat Chotibut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the generalized Langevin equation and the Mori projection operator technique</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20457v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In statistical physics, the Nakajima-Mori-Zwanzig projection operator formalism is used to derive an integro-differential equation for observables in a Hilbert space, the generalized Langevin equation (GLE). This technique relies on the splitting of the dynamics into a projected and an orthogonal part. However, the well-posedness of the abstract Cauchy problem for the orthogonal dynamics remains an open problem. Moreover, it is rarely discussed under which assumptions the Dyson identity, which is used to derive the GLE, holds. In this article, we address this issue for rank-one projections (Mori's projection).
  For the Mori projection, the orthogonal dynamics is obtained from the bounded perturbation theorem. The variation of constants formula for strongly continuous semigroups then yields the GLE and the second fluctuation dissipation theorem (2FDT). We show that the variation of constants can be replaced by a limiting process in order to give a general proof of the GLE and 2FDT that does not require the differentiability of the fluctuating forces.
  In addition, we offer an alternative approach that does not require the bounded perturbation theorem. Our starting point is the observation that the GLE and 2FDT uniquely determine the fluctuating forces as well as the memory kernel. Furthermore, the orbit maps for the orthogonal dynamics can be directly defined via solutions of linear Volterra equations. All desired properties of the orthogonal dynamics are then proven directly from this definition. In particular, the orthogonal dynamics is a strongly continuous semigroup generated by $\overline{\mathcal{QL}}\mathcal{Q}$, where $\mathcal{L}$ is the generator of the time evolution operator, and $\mathcal{P}=1-\mathcal{Q}$ is the Mori projection operator.
  Our results apply to general autonomous dynamical systems whose time evolution is given by a strongly continuous semigroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20457v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Widder, Johannes Zimmer, Tanja Schilling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Architecture Search for Neural Network Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00885v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Architecture design and optimization are challenging problems in the field of artificial neural networks. Working in this context, we here present SPARCS (SPectral ARchiteCture Search), a novel architecture search protocol which exploits the spectral attributes of the inter-layer transfer matrices. SPARCS allows one to explore the space of possible architectures by spanning continuous and differentiable manifolds, thus enabling for gradient-based optimization algorithms to be eventually employed. With reference to simple benchmark models, we show that the newly proposed method yields a self-emerging architecture with a minimal degree of expressivity to handle the task under investigation and with a reduced parameter count as compared to other viable alternatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00885v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Peri, Lorenzo Chicchi, Duccio Fanelli, Lorenzo Giambagli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proximate integrability and exact revivals in staggered Rydberg ladders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15230v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cold Rydberg atoms trapped in an array of optical tweezers can be manipulated using laser light. We investigate the fate of out-of-equilibrium quantum dynamics in a model of Rydberg atoms arranged in a square ladder geometry within the strong blockade regime, with a detuning profile staggered along the longer direction. As the staggering strength is tuned, the model exhibits a wide class of dynamical phenomena, ranging from quantum many-body scars, integrability-induced slow dynamics and approximate Krylov fractures. Furthermore, by leveraging the chiral nature of the spectrum, we design Floquet protocols which result in dynamical signatures reminiscent of discrete-time-crystalline order and exact Floquet-flat-bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15230v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mainak Pal, Tista Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiconservation Laws and Suppressed Transport in Weakly Interacting Localized Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03115v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The stability of localization in the presence of interactions remains an open problem, with finite-size effects posing significant challenges to numerical studies. In this work, we investigate the perturbative stability of noninteracting localization under weak interactions, which allows us to analyze much larger system sizes. Focusing on disordered Anderson and quasiperiodic Aubry-Andr\'e models in one dimension, and using the adiabatic gauge potential (AGP) at first order in perturbation theory, we compute first-order corrections to noninteracting local integrals of motion (LIOMs). We find that for at least an $O(1)$ fraction of the LIOMs, the corrections are well-controlled and converge at large system sizes, while others suffer from resonances. Additionally, we introduce and study the charge-transport capacity of this weakly interacting model. To first order, we find that the charge transport capacity remains bounded in the presence of interactions. Taken together, these results demonstrate that localization is perturbatively stable to weak interactions at first order, implying that, at the very least, localization persists for parametrically long times in the inverse interaction strength. We expect this perturbative stability to extend to all orders at sufficiently strong disorder, where the localization length is short, representing the true localized phase. Conversely, our findings suggest that the previously proposed interaction-induced avalanche instability, namely in the weakly localized regime of the Anderson and Aubry-Andr\'e models, is a more subtle phenomenon arising only at higher orders in perturbation theory or through nonperturbative effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03115v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jessica Kaijia Jiang, Federica Maria Surace, Olexei I. Motrunich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
