<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech</link>
    <description>cond-mat.stat-mech updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.stat-mech" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 04:05:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ergodic properties of occupation times in heterogeneous media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the ergodic properties of Brownian motion in heterogeneous media through the statistics of occupation times. Using the Feynman-Kac formalism, we derive analytical expressions for the distributions, moments, and ergodicity breaking parameters of occupation times in two models with spatially varying diffusion coefficient: a piecewise-constant profile and a power-law profile. In the piecewise model, the half occupation time and the occupation time within an interval follow asymmetric arcsine and half-Gaussian distributions, respectively, indicating non-ergodic behavior. For the power-law case, the corresponding distributions are the Lamperti and Mittag-Leffler. In both models, we identify a transition from non-ergodic to ergodic dynamics as the exponent vary. Numerical simulations fully corroborate the analytical results, demonstrating the effectiveness of the Feynman-Kac approach for quantifying ergodicity in heterogeneous diffusion processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11099v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vicen\c{c} M\'endez, Rosa Flaquer-Galm\'es</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling of free cumulants in closed system-bath setups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11333v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis (ETH) has been established as a cornerstone for understanding thermalization in quantum many-body systems. Recently, there has been growing interest in the full ETH, which extends the framework of the conventional ETH and postulates a smooth function to describe the multi-point correlations among matrix elements. Within this framework, free cumulants play a central role, and most previous studies have primarily focused on closed systems. In this paper, we extend the analysis to a system-bath setup, considering both an idealized case with a random-matrix bath and a more realistic scenario where the bath is modeled as a defect Ising chain. In both cases, we uncover a universal scaling of microcanonical free cumulants of system observables with respect to the interaction strength. Furthermore we establish a connection between this scaling behavior and the thermalization dynamics of the thermal free cumulants of corresponding observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11333v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Merlin F\"ullgraf, Jochen Gemmer, Jiaozi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solid-angle based nearest-neighbor algorithm adapted for systems with low coordination number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10748v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nearest-neighbor identification is central to the analysis of local structure in condensed matter systems. The solid-angle-based nearest-neighbor (SANN) algorithm is widely used offering a parameter-free and computationally efficient alternative to cutoff- or Voronoi-based methods. Unfortunately, however, in systems with low coordination numbers, SANN tends to identify many particles as neighbors that are outside the nearest neighbor shell. Here, we propose a solution to this problem. Specifically, we propose a geometric modification, the ``inscribed circle modification'', that resolves systematic overcounting in low-coordination lattices without introducing free parameters. We benchmark the modified algorithm (mSANN) against Voronoi and the original SANN algorithm in crystalline, quasicrystalline, and heterogeneous systems, and demonstrate that it provides robust and low-cost neighbor identification across both two and three dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10748v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alptu\u{g} Ulug\"ol, Frank Smallenburg, Laura Filion</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invading activity fronts stabilize excitable systems against stochastic extinction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10807v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stochastic chemical reaction or population dynamics in finite systems often terminates in an absorbing state. Yet in large spatially extended systems, the time to reach species extinction (or fixation) becomes exceedingly long. Tuning control parameters may diminish the survival probability, rendering species coexistence susceptible to stochastic extinction events. In inhomogeneous settings, where a vulnerable subsystem is diffusively coupled to an adjacent stable patch, the former is reanimated through continuous influx from the interfaces, provided the absorbing region sustains spreading activity fronts. We demonstrate this generic elimination of finite-size extinction instabilities via immigration flux in predator-prey, epidemic spreading, and cyclic competition models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10807v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenneth A. V. Distefano (Virginia Tech), Sara Shabani (Virginia Tech), Uwe C. T\"auber (Virginia Tech)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Thermodynamic Uncertainty Relation for Quantum $f-$Divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10817v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that any Petz $f$-divergence (where $f$ is operator convex) between quantum states admits a universal $\chi^2$-mixture representation: the distinguishability of $\rho$ from $\sigma$ is obtained as a positive superposition of quadratic contrasts $\chi^2_\lambda$, with nonnegative weights $w_f(\lambda)$ determined explicitly from the Stieltjes representation of the generator $f$. This identifies $\chi^2_\lambda$ as atomic building blocks for quantum $f$-divergences and yields closed-form $w_f$ for canonical choices (relative entropy/KL, Hellinger/Bures, R'{e}nyi). By mapping $\chi^2_\lambda$ into a classical Pearson $\chi^2$, we leverage the Chapman-Robbins variational representation and obtain a tight and universal quantum thermodynamic uncertainty relation: any $f$-divergence is lower bounded by a function of the statistics of quantum observables (mean and variance), reproducing previous and novel results in quantum thermodynamics as applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10817v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domingos S. P. Salazar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions in the Ising model on random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study phase transitions in the Ising model on random graphs using graph limits. This framework extends mean-field theory to heterogeneous nonlocal interactions. We show that the critical temperatures are determined by the eigenvalues of the kernel operator associated with the graph limit. Bifurcation diagrams for Erdos-Renyi, small-world, and power-law graphs illustrate the theory. In the small-world case, we identify metastable behavior in both ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10838v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Artem Alexandrov, Georgi S. Medvedev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliding of cylindrical shell into a rigid hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10976v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fitting two different materials is a versatile methodology in manufacturing complex structures. One of the canonical models for fitting is the snap-fit model, in which flexible materials and rigid structures are assembled by pushing their interlocking components together. The assembly via snap-fit is often accompanied by large deformations of flexible structures and abrupt force drops, highlighting the role of elasticity, geometry, and contact friction. Despite several model studies revealing fundamental mechanics for snap-fit, the current snap-fit design relies on prototyping and empirical rules. In this paper, we analyze a snap-fit model in which a naturally curved beam slips into a rigid hole. We construct an analytical model based on the theory of elastica with contact friction and demonstrate that its predictions are in excellent quantitative agreement with both simulations and experiments. We find three distinct sliding modes: Folding, Pinning, and Unfolding. The classification is systematically organized in a phase diagram based on the geometric parameters of the shells and the hole. Our study complements existing approaches by providing a predictive framework for contact-based structures that involve friction, elasticity, and geometry, and sheds light on a unified understanding of the interactions between an elastic and a rigid body.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10976v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukiho Matsumoto, Keisuke Yoshida, Tomohiko G. Sano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic structure of relaxor ferroelectrics from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11097v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We hybridize swap Monte Carlo and geometric relaxation to determine the intrinsic compositional structure (CS) of lead magnesium niobate (PMN) relaxor. We verify the stability of a Nb-rich sublattice in PMN, as prescribed by the prevailing random-site model. But ions in the complementary sublattice are not randomly mixed. The majority of Nb ions collapse into a dominant Nb cluster which percolates the lattice with a mesh-like geometry that prevents large space charges. Subsequent molecular dynamics simulations predict a pair distribution function agreeing with neutron scattering experiments. Analysis of dipolar structures in the Nb cluster sheds light on the unique dielectric property of PMN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11097v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Xu, Kehan Cai, Pinchen Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussianity-induced enhanced target-finding dynamics of confined colloids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The encounter of diffusing entities underlies a wide range of natural phenomena. The dynamics of these first-passage processes are strongly influenced by the geometry of the system, for example through confining boundaries. Confinement, which alters the diffusion of microscopic particles through both conservative and hydrodynamic interactions, emerges as a key ingredient for modeling realistic environments. In this Letter, we investigate the impact of confinement on the first-passage statistics of a diffusing particle. This diffusive motion is probed, with nanometric precision, by combining \textit{state-of-the-art} holographic microscopy with advanced statistical inference methods. Our experimental and numerical results provide a comprehensive understanding of this process, which is governed by the coupling between gravitational, screened electrostatic and hydrodynamic forces, as well as thermal fluctuations. We further show that confinement can either slow down or enhance the typical first-passage kinetics, depending on the experimental parameters and considered direction of space. In particular, the observed boost in wall-normal target-finding efficiency appears to be a direct consequence of the non-Gaussian displacement distribution induced by the near-surface effects, and the associated increased probability of large displacements. As the latter are rare events, our findings may be of relevance to rationalize confined chemical reactions, or biological \textit{winners-take-all} stochastic processes near boundaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11117v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guirec de Tournemire (LOMA), Nicolas Fares (LOMA), Yacine Amarouchene (LOMA), Thomas Salez (LOMA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium Thermodynamics of Associative Memory Continuous-Time Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11150v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Continuous-Time Recurrent Neural Networks (CTRNNs) have been widely used for their capacity to model complex temporal behaviour. However, their internal dynamics often remain difficult to interpret. In this paper, we propose a new class of CTRNNs based on Hopfield-like associative memories with asymmetric couplings. This model combines the expressive power of associative memories with a tractable mathematical formalism to characterize fluctuations in nonequilibrium dynamics. We show that this mathematical description allows us to directly compute the evolution of its macroscopic observables (the encoded features), as well as the instantaneous entropy and entropy dissipation of the system, thereby offering a bridge between dynamical systems descriptions of low-dimensional observables and the statistical mechanics of large nonequilibrium networks. Our results suggest that these nonequilibrium associative CTRNNs can serve as more interpretable models for complex sequence-encoding networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11150v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Published in Proceedings of ALIFE2025 conference</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Aguilera, Daniele De Martino, Ivan Garashchuk, Dmitry Sinelshchikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological states and flat bands in exactly solvable decorated Cayley trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11261v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive the full spectrum of decorated Cayley trees that constitute tree analogs of selected two-dimensional Euclidean lattices; namely of the Lieb, the double Lieb, the kagome, and the star lattice. The common feature of these Euclidean lattices is that their nearest-neighbor models give rise to flat energy bands interpretable through compact localized states. We find that the tree analogs exhibit similar flat or nearly flat energy bands at the corresponding energies. Interestingly, such flat bands in the decorated Cayley trees acquire an interpretation that is absent in their Euclidean counterparts: as edge states localized to the inner or the outer boundary of the tree branches. In particular, we establish an exact correspondence between the Lieb-Cayley tree and an ensemble of one-dimensional Su-Schrieffer-Heeger chains, which maps topological edge states on one side of the chains to flat-band states localized in the bulk of the tree, furnishing the flat energy band with a topological stability. Similar mapping to topological edge states or to states bound to edge defects in one-dimensional chains is shown for flat-band states in all the considered tree decorations. We finally show that the persistence of exact flat bands on infinite decorated trees (i.e., Bethe lattices) arises naturally from a covering interpretation of tree graphs. Our findings reveal a rich landscape of flat-band and topological phenomena in non-Euclidean systems, where geometry alone can generate and stabilize unconventional quantum states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11261v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanda P. Duss, Askar Iliasov, Tom\'a\v{s} Bzdu\v{s}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrability for the spectrum of Jordanian AdS/CFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11521v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Jordanian deformations offer rare integrable realisations of non-AdS holography, whose solvability methods differ from conventional AdS/CFT examples. Here we study the $\mathfrak{sl}(2,R)$ sector of the Jordanian deformed $AdS_5\times S^5$ string and its weak-coupling spin chain counterpart: the $\mathrm{XXX}_{-1/2}$ model with a non abelian Jordanian Drinfel'd twist. While the twist breaks the usual highest-weight structure that underlies conventional Bethe ans\"atze, we show that the complete spectrum remains solvable within the Baxter framework. We argue that the functional form of the $TQ$-relation is unchanged, yet the structure of the $Q$-functions is nontrivially modified. This allows us to obtain analytic expressions at arbitrary spin chain length $J$, which match the deformed string spectrum at the one-loop level and to subleading order in the large-$J$ expansion, despite the severely reduced symmetry. Our results provide nontrivial tests of the Jordanian AdS/CFT correspondence and lay the groundwork for implementing the Separation of Variables program in non-abelian Drinfel'd-twisted models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11521v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sibylle Driezen, Fedor Levkovich-Maslyuk, Adrien Molines</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent-state path integrals in quantum thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11547v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In these notes, we elucidate some subtle aspects of coherent-state path integrals, focusing on their application to the equilibrium thermodynamics of quantum many-particle systems. These subtleties emerge when evaluating path integrals in the continuum, either in imaginary time or in Matsubara-frequency space. Our central message is that, when handled with due care, the path integral yields results identical to those obtained from the canonical Hamiltonian approach. We illustrate this through a pedagogical treatment of several paradigmatic systems: the bosonic and fermionic harmonic oscillators, the single-site Bose-Hubbard and Hubbard models, the weakly-interacting Bose gas with contact and finite-range interactions, and the BCS superconductor with contact and finite-range interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11547v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Salasnich, Cesare Vianello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete time crystals detected by time-translation twist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a boundary condition twisted by time translation as a novel probe to characterize dynamical phases in periodically driven (Floquet) quantum systems. Inspired by twisted boundary conditions in equilibrium systems, this approach modifies the temporal evolution of the system upon completing a spatial loop, enabling the identification of distinct Floquet phases, including discrete time crystals (DTCs). By studying the spectral form factor (SFF) and its response to the twist, we uncover signatures of time-crystalline order, which exhibits periodic dependence on the twist parameter analogous to the Little-Parks effect in superconductors. We apply this framework to the kicked Ising model, demonstrating that our twist can distinguish time-crystalline phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21461v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1dc6-y1x8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 165138 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Nakai, Taozhi Guo, Shinsei Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensionality-induced dynamical phase transition in the large deviation of local time density for Brownian motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05956v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the fluctuation properties of the local time density, ${\rho _T} = \frac{1}{T}\int_0^T {\delta ( {r(t) - 1} )} dt$, spent by a $d$-dimensional Brownian particle at a spherical shell of unit radius, where $r(t)$ denotes the radial distance from the particle to the origin. In the large observation time limit, $T \to \infty$, the local time density $\rho_T$ obeys the large deviation principle, $P(\rho _T= \rho) \sim e^{-T I(\rho)}$, where the rate function $I(\rho)$ is analytic everywhere for $d\leq 4$. In contrast, for $d&gt;4$, $I(\rho)$ becomes nonanalytic at a specific point $\rho=\rho_c^{(d)}$, where $\rho_c^{(d)}=d(d-4)/(2d-4)$ depends solely on dimensionality. The singularity signals the occurrence of a first-order dynamical phase transition in dimensions higher than four. Such a transition is accompanied by temporal phase separations in the large deviations of Brownian trajectories. Finally, we validate our theoretical results using a rare-event simulation approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05956v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/mcr3-5cz2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review E 112, 054121 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ruofei Yan, Hanshuang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the symmetry-resolved entanglement for non-invertible symmetries in $1{+}1$d conformal field theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02315v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, a framework for computing the symmetry-resolved entanglement entropy for non-invertible symmetries in $1{+}1$d conformal field theories has been proposed by Saura-Bastida, Das, Sierra and Molina-Vilaplana [Phys. Rev. D109, 105026]. We revisit their theoretical setup, paying particular attention to possible contributions from the conformal boundary conditions imposed at the entangling surface -- a potential subtlety that was not addressed in the original proposal. We find that the presence of boundaries modifies the construction of projectors onto irreducible sectors, compared to what can be expected from a pure bulk approach. This is a direct consequence of the fusion algebra of non-invertible symmetries being different in the presence or absence of boundaries on which defects can end. We apply our formalism to the case of the Fibonacci category symmetry in the three-state Potts and tricritical Ising model and the Rep($S_3$) fusion category symmetry in the $SU(2)_4$ Wess-Zumino-Witten conformal field theory. We numerically corroborate our findings by simulating critical anyonic chains with these symmetries as a finite lattice substitute for the expected entanglement Hamiltonian. Our predictions for the symmetry-resolved entanglement for non-invertible symmetries seem to disagree with the recent work by Saura-Bastida et al.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02315v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/lr47-yv3j</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 025004 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jared Heymann, Thomas Quella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Purely quantum memory in closed systems observed via imperfect measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13689v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The detection and quantification of non-Markovianity, a.k.a. memory, in quantum systems is a central problem in the theory of open quantum systems. There memory is as a result of the interaction between the system and its environment. Little is known, however, about memory effects induced by imperfect measurements on closed systems, where an entanglement with the environment is not possible. We investigate the emergence and characteristics of memory in closed systems observed via imperfect stroboscopic quantum measurements yielding coarse-grained outcomes. We consider ideal and two kinds of imperfect measurements: von Neumann measurements--the analogue of classical lumping--which destroy any coherence in the system, and genuinely quantum-lumping L\"uders measurements preserving certain quantum correlations. Whereas the conditions for Markov dynamics under von Neumann lumping are the same as for classical dynamics, quantum-lumping requires stronger conditions, i.e. the absence of any detectable coherence. We introduce the concept of purely quantum memory having no classical counterpart. We illustrate our results with a quantum walk on a lattice and discuss their implications for dissipative dynamics and decoherence effects induced by more realistic measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13689v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Tabanera-Bravo, Alja\v{z} Godec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonization and Kramers-Wannier dualities in general dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20167v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is well known that the noninteracting Majorana chain is dual to the one-dimensional transverse-field Ising model, either through the Jordan-Wigner transformation or by gauging fermion parity. In this correspondence, the minimal translation of the Majorana chain maps to the celebrated Kramers-Wannier (KW) duality of the spin model, with the critical point mapped to the self-dual point. In this work, we generalize this mapping to two and higher dimensions by constructing a unitary equivalence between the parity-gauged fermionic system and a spin system defined on arbitrary polyhedral decompositions of space. Imposing the flatness condition on the gauge field yields a bosonization duality between the original (ungauged) fermionic system and a gauged spin system obeying a Gauss law. The dependence of the Gauss law in the spin system on the Kasteleyn orientation (and the discrete spin structure) of the fermionic system is made explicit. Applying this bosonization to one or two copies of Majorana fermions on translationally invariant lattices, we derive higher-dimensional analogs of KW (self-)dualities in spin systems arising from fermionic minimal translations. The KW (self-)dualities are non-invertible due to projections onto eigenspaces of higher-form symmetries in the associated symmetry operators. The bosonization framework we present is intuitive, general, and systematic, encompassing other known exact bosonization methods while offering a novel approach to establish new connections between fermionic and spin systems in arbitrary dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20167v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Su, Ivar Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-organization, Memory and Learning: From Driven Disordered Systems to Living Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25367v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Disordered systems subject to a fluctuating environment can self-organize into a complex history-dependent response, retaining a memory of the driving. In sheared amorphous solids, self-organization is established by the emergence of a persistent system of mechanical instabilities that can repeatedly be triggered by the driving, leading to a state of high mechanical reversibility. As a result of self-organization, the response of the system becomes correlated with the dynamics of its environment, which can be viewed as a sensing mechanism of the system's environment. Such phenomena emerge across a wide variety of soft matter systems, suggesting that they are generic and hence may depend very little on the underlying specifics. We review self-organization in driven amorphous solids, concluding with a discussion of what self-organization in driven disordered systems can teach us about how simple organisms sense and adapt to their changing environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25367v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhittin Mungan, Eric Clement, Damien Vandembroucq, Srikanth Sastry</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
