<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 05:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Definability and Scott rank in separable Metric structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a notion of Scott rank for separable metric structures based on the definability of the (metric closures of) automorphism orbits in continuous infinitary logic. This is a continuous analogue of work of Montalb\'an for countable structures. In the process, we prove some results concerning definability, type omitting, and back-and-forth for metric structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01017v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Bejarano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No cardinal correct inner model elementarily embeds into the universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An elementary embedding $j:M\rightarrow N$ between two inner models of ZFC is cardinal preserving if $M$ and $N$ correctly compute the class of cardinals. We look at the case $N=V$ and show that there is no nontrivial cardinal preserving elementary embedding from $M$ into $V$, answering a question of Caicedo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01046v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Goldberg, Sebastiano Thei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Friedman's Property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define forcing orders which add witnesses to the failure of various forms of Friedman's Property. These posets behave similarly to the forcing order adding a nonreflecting stationary set but have the advantage of allowing the construction of master conditions and thus the preservation of various large cardinal properties. We apply these new techniques to separate various instances of variants of Friedman's Problem, both between different instances at one cardinal as well as equal instances at different cardinals and en passant obtain some new results regarding the differences between ${&lt;}\,\kappa$- and $\kappa$-strategic closure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01478v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannes Jakob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propositional calculus with multiple negations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this document, we will build a logical calculus that is a generalization of classical propositional logic but contains a finite multiplicity of negations weaker than classical negation. In this way, we can introduce contradictions in this new system without it becoming inconsistent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01627v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Daniel Ram\'irez Corea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cantor-Schr\"oder-Bernstein theorem for a class of countable linear orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02297v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The shuffle of a non-empty countable set $ S $ of linear orders is the (unique up to isomorphism) linear order $ \Xi(S) $ obtained by fixing a coloring function $ \chi: \mathbb{Q} \to S $ having fibers dense in $ \mathbb{Q} $ and replacing each rational $ q $ in $ (\mathbb{Q}, &lt;) $ with an isomorphic copy of $ \chi(q) $. We prove that any two countable shuffles that embed as convex subsets into each other are order isomorphic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02297v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suyash Srivastava, Mihir Mittal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Erd\H{o}s-Rado Classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.01513</link>
      <description>arXiv:1810.01513v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We amalgamate two generalizations of Ramsey's Theorem--Ramsey classes and the Erd\H{o}s-Rado Theorem--into the notion of a combinatorial Erd\H{o}s-Rado class. These classes are closely related to Erd\H{o}s-Rado classes, which are those from which we can build generalized indiscernibles and blueprints in nonelementary classes, especially Abstract Elementary Classes. We give several examples and some applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1810.01513v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Boney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Testable and Progressive Axiom Set for 2-Dimensional Euclidean Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11333v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper shows that the 4 axioms in the original Euclidean axiom set can be modernized as 6 axioms. The new axiom set introduces each axiom progressively, with no new concept in any of the axioms so that each axiom is testable. One of the new axiom states that Euclidean, spherical, and hyperbolic spaces are all strictly monotonic, which seems to be implied in all existing axiom sets for Euclidean geometry.
  A new implicit measure called local right ratio is introduced to replace parallel postulate, Riemann curvature tensor, or Gaussian curvature, to determine if the surface is locally flat, smooth, and curved at each point. Euclidean is shown to be the only surface to have constant right ratios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11333v4</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengpu Wang, Alice Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive properties of I2-embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00376v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We contribute to the study of generalizations of the Perfect Set Property and the Baire Property to subsets of spaces of higher cardinalities, like the power set $P(\lambda)$ of a singular cardinal $\lambda$ of countable cofinality or products $\prod_{i&lt;\omega}\lambda_i$ for a strictly increasing sequence $\langle\lambda_i ~ \vert ~ i&lt;\omega\rangle$ of cardinals. We consider the question under which large cardinal hypotheses classes of definable subsets of these spaces possess such regularity properties, focusing on rank-into-rank axioms and classes of sets definable by $\Sigma_1$-formulas with parameters from various collections of sets. We prove that $\omega$-many measurable cardinals, while sufficient to prove the Perfect Set Property of all $\Sigma_1$-definable sets with parameters in $V_\lambda\cup\{V_\lambda\}$, are not enough to prove it if there is a cofinal sequence in $\lambda$ in the parameters. For this conclusion, the existence of an I2-embedding is enough, but there are parameters in $V_{\lambda+1}$ for which I2 is still not enough. The situation is similar for the Baire Property: under I2 all sets that are $\Sigma_1$-definable using elements of $V_\lambda$ and a cofinal sequence as parameters have the Baire property, but I2 is not enough for some parameter in $V_{\lambda+1}$. Finally, the existence of an I0-embedding implies that all sets that are $\Sigma^1_n$-definable with parameters in $V_{\lambda+1}$ have the Baire property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00376v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincenzo Dimonte, Martina Iannella, Philipp L\"ucke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A non-de Finetti theorem for countable Euclidean spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22930v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The classical de Finetti Theorem classifies the $\mathrm{Sym}(\mathbb N)$-invariant probability measures on $[0,1]^{\mathbb N}$. More precisely it states that those invariant measures are combinations of measures of the form $\nu^{\otimes\mathbb N}$ where $\nu$ is a measure on $[0,1]$. Recently, Jahel--Tsankov generalized this theorem showing that under conditions on $M$, the group $\operatorname{Aut}(M)$ is de Finetti, i.e. $\operatorname{Aut}(M)$-invariant measures on $[0,1]^M$ are mixtures of measures of the form $\nu^{\otimes M}$ where $\nu$ is a measure on $[0,1]$. In this note, we give an example of a non-de Finetti non-Archimedean group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22930v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin Jahel, Pierre Perruchaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
