<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 04:00:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Soluble Lie rings of finite Morley rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07783v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We do two things. 1. As a corollary to a stronger linearisation result (Theorem A), we prove the finite Morley rank version of the Lie-Kolchin-Malcev theorem on Lie algebras (Corollary A2). 2. We classify Lie ring actions on modules of characteristic not 2, 3 and Morley rank 2 (Theorem B).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07783v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrien Deloro, Jules Tindzogho Ntsiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Around Paradox with Grounded Deduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: How can we reason around logical paradoxes without falling into them? This paper introduces grounded deduction or GD, a Kripke-inspired approach to first-order logic and arithmetic that is neither classical nor intuitionistic, but nevertheless appears both pragmatically usable and intuitively justifiable. GD permits the direct expression of unrestricted recursive definitions - including paradoxical ones such as 'L := not L' - while adding dynamic typing premises to certain inference rules so that such paradoxes do not lead to inconsistency. This paper constitutes a preliminary development and investigation of grounded deduction, to be extended with further elaboration and deeper analysis of its intriguing properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08243v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bryan Ford</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The definable content of homological invariants I: $\mathrm{Ext}$ &amp; $\mathrm{lim}^1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.08782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2008.08782v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This is the first installment in a series of papers in which we illustrate how classical invariants of homological algebra and algebraic topology can be enriched with additional descriptive set-theoretic information. To effect this enrichment, we show that many of these invariants can be naturally regarded as functors to the category, introduced herein, of groups with a Polish cover. The resulting definable invariants provide far stronger means of classification.
  In the present work we focus on the first derived functors of $\mathrm{Hom}(-,-)$ and $\mathrm{lim}(-)$. The resulting definable $\mathrm{Ext}(B,F)$ for pairs of countable abelian groups $B,F$ and definable $\mathrm{lim}^{1}(\boldsymbol{A})$ for towers $\boldsymbol{A}$ of Polish abelian groups substantially refine their classical counterparts. We show, for example, that the definable $\textrm{Ext}(-,\mathbb{Z})$ is a fully faithful contravariant functor from the category of finite rank torsion-free abelian groups $\Lambda$ with no free summands; this contrasts with the fact that there are uncountably many non-isomorphic such groups $\Lambda$ with isomorphic classical invariants $\textrm{Ext}(\Lambda,\mathbb{Z}) $. To facilitate our analysis, we introduce a general Ulam stability framework for groups with a Polish cover and we prove several rigidity results for non-Archimedean abelian groups with a Polish cover. A special case of our main result answers a question of Kanovei and Reeken regarding quotients of the $p$-adic groups. Finally, using cocycle superrigidity methods for profinite actions of property (T) groups, we obtain a hierarchy of complexity degrees for the problem $\mathcal{R}(\mathrm{Aut}(\Lambda)\curvearrowright\mathrm{Ext}(\Lambda,\mathbb{Z}))$ of classifying all group extensions of $\Lambda$ by $\mathbb{Z}$ up to base-free isomorphism, when $\Lambda =\mathbb{Z}[1/p]^{d}$ for prime numbers $p$ and $ d\geq 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2008.08782v5</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Bergfalk, Martino Lupini, Aristotelis Panagiotopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modal definability in Kripke's theory of truth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17091v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In Outline of a Theory of Truth, Kripke introduces some of the central concepts of the logical study of truth and paradox. He informally defines some of these -- such as groundedness and paradoxicality -- using modal locutions. We introduce a modal language for regimenting these informal definitions. Though groundedness and paradoxicality are expressible in the modal language, we prove that intrinsicality -- which Kripke emphasizes but does not define modally -- is not. We characterize the modally definable relations and completely axiomatize the modal semantics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17091v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Walsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Proof-theoretic Validity to Base-extension Semantics for Intuitionistic Propositional Logic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.05344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.05344v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Proof-theoretic semantics (P-tS) is the approach to meaning in logic based on 'proof' (as opposed to 'truth'). There are two major approaches to P-tS: proof-theoretic validity (P-tV) and base-extension semantics (B-eS). The former is a semantics of arguments, and the latter is a semantics of logical constants. This paper demonstrates that the B-eS for intuitionistic propositional logic (IPL) encapsulates the declarative content of a version of P-tV based on the elimination rules. This explicates how the B-eS for IPL works, and shows the completeness of this version of P-tV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.05344v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander V. Gheorghiu, David J. Pym</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extension property for partial automorphisms of the $n$-partite and semigeneric tournaments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12153v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a proof of the extension property for partial automorphisms (EPPA) for classes of finite $n$-partite tournaments for $n \in \{2,3,\ldots,\omega\}$, and for the class of finite semigeneric tournaments. We also prove that the generic $\omega$-partite tournament and the generic semigeneric tournament have ample generics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12153v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Hubi\v{c}ka, Colin Jahel, Mat\v{e}j Kone\v{c}n\'y, Marcin Sabok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multisorted Boolean Clones Determined by Binary Relations up to Minion Homomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16513v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We describe the ordering of a class of clones by minion homomorphisms, also known as minor preserving maps or height 1 clone homomorphisms. The class consists of all clones on finite sets determined by binary relations whose projections to both coordinates have at most two elements. This class can be alternatively described up to minion homomorphisms as the class of multisorted Boolean clones determined by binary relations. We also introduce and apply the concept of a minion core which provides canonical representatives for equivalence classes of clones, more generally minions, on finite sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16513v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Libor Barto, Maryia Kapytka</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
