<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Logics of False Belief and Radical Ignorance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the literature, the question about how to axiomatize the transitive logic of false belief is thought of as hard and left as an open problem. In this paper, among other contributions, we deal with this problem. In more details, although the standard doxastic operator is undefinable with the operator of false belief, the former is {\em almost definable} with the latter. On one hand, the involved almost definability schema guides us to find the desired core axioms for the transitive logic and the Euclidean logic of false belief. On the other hand, inspired by the schema and other considerations, we propose a suitable canonical relation, which can uniformly handle the completeness proof of various logics of false belief, including the transitive logic. We also extend the results to the logic of radical ignorance, due to the interdefinability of the operators of false belief and radical ignorance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07442v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-convexity, Weakly Immediate Types and $T$-$\lambda$-Spherical Completions of o-minimal Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $T$ be the theory of an o-minimal field, and $T_{\mathrm{convex}}$ the theory of its expansion by a predicate $\mathcal{O}$ for a non-trival $T$-convex valuation ring. For $\lambda$ an uncountable cardinal, say that a unary type $p(x)$ over a model of $T_{\mathrm{convex}}$ is \emph{$\lambda$-bounded weakly immediate} if its cut is defined by an empty intersection of fewer than $\lambda$ many nested valuation balls. Call an elementary extension \emph{$\lambda$-bounded wim-constructible} if it is obtained as a transfinite composition of extensions each generated by one element whose type is $\lambda$-bounded weakly immediate.
  I show that $\lambda$-bounded wim-constructible extensions do not extend the residue-field sort and that any two wim-constructible extensions can be amalgamated in an extension which is again $\lambda$-bounded wim-constructible over both.
  A consequence is that given a cardinal $\lambda$, every model of $T_{\mathrm{convex}}$ has a unique-up-to-non-unique-isomorphism $\lambda$-spherically complete $\lambda$-bounded wim-constructible extension. We call this extension the $T$-$\lambda$-spherical completion.
  In the case $T$ is power bounded, wim-constructible extensions are just the immediate extensions. I discuss the example of power bounded theories expanded by $\exp$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07646v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Freni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Definability of band structures on posets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07877v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The idempotent semigroups (bands) that give rise to partial orders by defining $a \leq b \iff a \cdot b = a$ are the "right-regular" bands (RRB), which are axiomatized by $x\cdot y \cdot x = y \cdot x$. In this work we consider the class of "associative posets", which comprises all partial orders underlying right-regular bands, and study to what extent the ordering determines the possible "compatible" band structures and their canonicity.
  We show that the class of associative posets in the signature $\{ \leq \}$ is not first-order axiomatizable. We also show that the Axiom of Choice is equivalent over $\mathit{ZF}$ to the fact that every tree with finite branches is associative. We also present an adjunction between the categories of RRBs and that of associative posets.
  We study the smaller class of "normal" posets (corresponding to right-normal bands) and give a structural characterization.
  As an application of the order-theoretic perspective on bands, we generalize results by the third author, obtaining "inner" direct product representations for RRBs having a central (commuting) element.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07877v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joel Kuperman, Alejandro Petrovich, Pedro S\'anchez Terraf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflexive graph lenses in univalent foundations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07854v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Martin-L\"of's identity types provide a generic (albeit opaque) notion of identification or "equality" between any two elements of the same type, embodied in a canonical reflexive graph structure $(=_A, \mathbf{refl})$ on any type $A$. The miracle of Voevodsky's univalence principle is that it ensures, for essentially any naturally occurring structure in mathematics, that this the resultant notion of identification is equivalent to the type of isomorphisms in the category of such structures. Characterisations of this kind are not automatic and must be established one-by-one; to this end, several authors have employed reflexive graphs and displayed reflexive graphs to organise the characterisation of identity types.
  We contribute reflexive graph lenses, a new family of intermediate abstractions lying between families of reflexive graphs and displayed reflexive graphs that simplifies the characterisation of identity types for complex structures. Every reflexive graph lens gives rise to a (more complicated) displayed reflexive graph, and our experience suggests that many naturally occurring displayed reflexive graphs arise in this way. Evidence for the utility of reflexive graph lenses is given by means of several case studies, including the theory of reflexive graphs itself as well as that of polynomial type operators. Finally, we exhibit an equivalence between the type of reflexive graph fibrations and the type of univalent reflexive graph lenses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07854v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Sterling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Games characterizing certain families of functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.05458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.05458v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We obtain several game characterizations of Baire 1 functions between Polish spaces X, Y which extends the recent result of V. Kiss. Then we propose similar characterizations for equi-Bare 1 families of functions. Also, using related ideas, we give game characterizations of Baire measurable and Lebesgue measurable functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.05458v4</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00153-024-00922-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Archive for Mathematical Logic 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marek Balcerzak, Tomasz Natkaniec, Piotr Szuca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sup Connective in IMALL: A Categorical Semantics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.02142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.02142v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore a proof language for intuitionistic multiplicative additive linear logic, incorporating the sup connective that introduces additive pairs with a probabilistic elimination, and sum and scalar products within the proof-terms. We provide an abstract characterization of the language, revealing that any symmetric monoidal closed category with biproducts and a monomorphism from the semiring of scalars to the semiring Hom(I,I) is suitable for the job. Leveraging the binary biproducts, we define a weighted codiagonal map at the heart of the sup connective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.02142v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro D\'iaz-Caro, Octavio Malherbe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Optimal Choice of Hypothesis Is the Weakest, Not the Shortest</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.12987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.12987v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: If $A$ and $B$ are sets such that $A \subset B$, generalisation may be understood as the inference from $A$ of a hypothesis sufficient to construct $B$. One might infer any number of hypotheses from $A$, yet only some of those may generalise to $B$. How can one know which are likely to generalise? One strategy is to choose the shortest, equating the ability to compress information with the ability to generalise (a proxy for intelligence). We examine this in the context of a mathematical formalism of enactive cognition. We show that compression is neither necessary nor sufficient to maximise performance (measured in terms of the probability of a hypothesis generalising). We formulate a proxy unrelated to length or simplicity, called weakness. We show that if tasks are uniformly distributed, then there is no choice of proxy that performs at least as well as weakness maximisation in all tasks while performing strictly better in at least one. In experiments comparing maximum weakness and minimum description length in the context of binary arithmetic, the former generalised at between $1.1$ and $5$ times the rate of the latter. We argue this demonstrates that weakness is a far better proxy, and explains why Deepmind's Apperception Engine is able to generalise effectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.12987v4</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-33469-6_5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Artificial General Intelligence. 2023. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 13921. Springer. pp. 42-51</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael Timothy Bennett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational Dualism and Objective Superintelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.00843v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The concept of intelligent software is flawed. The behaviour of software depends upon the hardware that interprets it. This undermines claims regarding the behaviour of theorised, software superintelligence. Here we characterise this problem as ``computational dualism'', where instead of mental and physical substance, we have software and hardware. We argue that to make objective claims regarding performance we must avoid computational dualism. We propose using an alternative based upon pancomputationalism, which defines all aspects of the environment as nothing more than relations between otherwise irreducible states. We formalise systems as behaviour (inputs and outputs, with policy being a causal intermediary), and cognition as embodied, embedded, extended and enactive. The result is cognition formalised as a part of the environment, rather than as a disembodied policy interacting with the environment though an interpreter. This allows us to make objective claims regarding intelligence, which we argue is the ability to ``generalise'', identify causes and adapt. We then propose objective upper bounds for intelligent behaviour.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.00843v3</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Timothy Bennett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The homeomorphisms of the Sierpi\'nski carpet are not classifiable by countable structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01472v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the homeomorphisms of the Sierpi\'nski carpet are not classifiable, up to conjugacy, using isomorphism types of countable structures as invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01472v2</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhruv Kulshreshtha, Aristotelis Panagiotopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
