<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 04:00:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Weak A2 spaces, the Kastanas game and strategically Ramsey sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of a weak A2 space (or wA2-space), which generalises spaces satisfying Todor\v{c}evi\'c's axioms A1-A4 and countable vector spaces. We show that in any Polish weak A2 space, analytic sets are Kastanas Ramsey, and discuss the relationship between Kastanas Ramseys sets in the projective hierarchy. We also show that in all spaces satisfying A1-A4, every subset of $\cal{R}$ is Kastanas Ramsey iff Ramsey, generalising the recent result by Cano and Di Prisco. Finally, we show that in the setting of Gowers wA2-spaces, Kastanas Ramsey sets and strategically Ramsey sets coincide, providing a connection between the recent studies on topological Ramsey spaces and countable vector spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00200v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clement Yung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of balanced residuated partially ordered monoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A residuated poset is a structure $\langle A,\le,\cdot,\backslash,/,1 \rangle$ where $\langle A,\le \rangle$ is a poset and $\langle A,\cdot,1 \rangle$ is a monoid such that the residuation law $x\cdot y\le z\iff x\le z/y\iff y\le x\backslash z$ holds. A residuated poset is balanced if it satisfies the identity $x\backslash x \approx x/x$. By generalizing the well-known construction of Plonka sums, we show that a specific class of balanced residuated posets can be decomposed into such a sum indexed by the set of positive idempotent elements. Conversely, given a semilattice directed system of residuated posets equipped with two families of maps (instead of one, as in the usual case), we construct a residuated poset based on the disjoint union of their domains. We apply this approach to provide a structural description of some varieties of residuated lattices and relation algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00604v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-68279-7_6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Bonzio, Jos\'e Gil-F\'erez, Peter Jipsen, Adam P\v{r}enosil, Melissa Sugimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to higher walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The following is an introduction to the study of higher walks, by which we mean a family of higher-dimensional extensions of Todorcevic's method of walks on the ordinals. After a brief review of this method, including, for example, definitions of the classical functions $\mathrm{Tr}$ and $\rho_2$ induced by a choice of $C$-sequence, we record a shortlist of desiderata for such extensions, along with $(n+1)$-dimensional functions $\mathrm{Tr}_n$ and $\rho_2^n$ (induced by a choice of higher-dimensional $C$-sequence) which we show to satisfy the bulk of them. Much of the interest of these higher walks functions lies in their affinity, as in the classical $n=1$ case, for the ordinals $\omega_n$ (we show, for example, that $\rho^n_2$ determines both $n$-dimensional linear orderings and $n$-coherent families on $\omega_n$, and that higher walks define nontrivial elements of the $n^{\mathrm{th}}$ cohomology groups of $\omega_n$), and in the questions that they thereby raise both about the combinatorics of the latter and about higher-dimensional infinitary combinatorics more generally; we collect the most prominent of these questions in our conclusion. These objects are also, though, of a sufficient combinatorial richness to be of interest in their own right, as we have underscored via an extended study of the first genuine novelty among them, the function $\mathrm{Tr}_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00607v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Bergfalk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Borel monadic theory of order is decidable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00887v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The monadic theory of $(\mathbb R,\le)$ with quantification restricted to Borel sets, or even to $\sigma$-combinations of analytic sets, is decidable. The Boolean combinations of $F_\sigma$-sets form an elementary substructure of the Borel sets. Under determinacy hypotheses, the proof extends to larger classes of sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00887v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sven Manthe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Complexity of Proper Homotopy Equivalence of Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the proper homotopy equivalence relation for locally finite graphs is Borel complete. Furthermore, among the infinite graphs, there is a comeager equivalence class. As corollaries, we obtain the analogous results for the homeomorphism relation of noncompact surfaces with pants decompositions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00901v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Hoganson, Jenna Zomback</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shelah's Main Gap and the generalized Borel-reducibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07510v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We answer one of the main questions in generalized descriptive set theory, the Friedman-Hyttinen-Kulikov conjecture on the Borel reducibility of the Main Gap. We show a correlation between Shelah's Main Gap and generalized Borel reducibility notions of complexity. For any $\kappa$ satisfying $\kappa=\lambda^+=2^\lambda$ and $2^{\mathfrak{c}}\leq\lambda=\lambda^{\omega_1}$, we show that if $T$ is a classifiable theory and $T'$ is a non-classifiable theory, then the isomorphism of models of $T'$ is strictly above the isomorphism of models of $T$ with respect to Borel-reducibility.
  We also show that the following can be forced: for any countable first-order theory in a countable vocabulary, $T$, the isomorphism of models of $T$ is either analytic co-analytic, or analytically-complete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07510v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Moreno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Game semantics for the constructive $\mu$-calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16697v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define game semantics for the constructive $\mu$-calculus and prove its equivalence to bi-relational semantics. As an application, we use the game semantics to prove that the $\mu$-calculus collapses to modal logic over the modal logic $\mathsf{IS5}$. We then show the completeness of $\mathsf{IS5}$ extended with fixed-point operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16697v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Pacheco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of $T$-$\lambda$-spherical completions of o-minimal fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07442v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $T$ be the theory of an o-minimal field and $T_0$ a common reduct of $T$ and $T_{an}$. I adapt Mourgues' and Ressayre's constructions to deduce structure results for $T_0$-reducts of $T$-$\lambda$-spherical completion of models of $T_{\mathrm{convex}}$. These in particular entail that whenever $\mathbb{R}_L$ is a reduct of $\mathbb{R}_{an,\exp}$ defining the exponential, every elementary extension of $\mathbb{R}_L$ has an elementary truncation-closed embedding in the class-sized field $\mathbf{No}$ of surreal numbers. This partially answers a question in [3](arXiv:2002.07739). The main technical result is that certain expansion of Hahn fields by generalized power series interpreted as functions defined on the positive infinitesimal elements, have the property that truncation closed subsets generate truncation closed substructures. This leaves room for possible generalizations to the case in which $T_0$ is power bounded but not necessarily a reduct of $T_{an}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07442v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Freni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapsing Constructive and Intuitionistic Modal Logics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the constructive and intuitionistic variants of the modal logic $\mathsf{KB}$ coincide. This result contrasts with a recent result by Das and Marin, who showed that the constructive and intuitionistic variants of $\mathsf{K}$ do not prove the same diamond-free formulas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16428v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Pacheco</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
