<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Proof Complexity and Feasible Interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is a survey on propositional proof complexity aimed at introducing the basics of the field with a particular focus on a method known as feasible interpolation. This method is used to construct "hard theorems" for several proof systems for both classical and non-classical logics. Here, a "hard theorem" refers to a theorem in the logic whose shortest proofs are super-polynomially long in the length of the theorem itself. To make this survey more accessible, we only assume a basic familiarity with propositional, modal, and first-order logic, as well as a basic understanding of the key concepts in computational complexity, such as the definitions of the classes $\mathbf{NP}$ and $\mathbf{PSPACE}$. Any additional concepts will be introduced and explained as needed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03002v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amirhossein Akbar Tabatabai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Degrees of incomputability, realizability and constructive reverse mathematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.10712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2002.10712v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There is a way of assigning a realizability notion to each degree of incomputability. In our setting, we make use of Weihrauch degrees (degrees of incomputability/discontinuity of partial multi-valued functions) to obtain Lifschitz-like relative realizability predicates. In this note, we present sample examples on how to lift some separation results on Weihrauch degrees to those over intuitionistic Zermelo-Fraenkel set theory ${\bf IZF}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2002.10712v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Kihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Jordan-Chevalley decomposition beyond algebraic groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.02637v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a decomposition of definable groups in o-minimal structures generalizing the Jordan-Chevalley decomposition of linear algebraic groups. It follows that any definable linear group G is a semidirect product of its maximal normal definable torsion-free subgroup N(G) and a definable subgroup P, unique up to conjugacy, definably isomorphic to a semialgebraic group.
  Along the way, we establish two other fundamental decompositions of classical groups in arbitrary o-minimal structures: 1) a Levi decomposition and 2) a key decomposition of disconnected groups, relying on a generalization of Frattini's argument to the o-minimal setting. In o-minimal structures, together with p-groups, 0-groups play a crucial role. We give a characterization of both classes and show that definable p-groups are solvable, like finite p-groups, but they are not necessarily nilpotent. Furthermore, we prove that definable p-groups (p=0 or p prime) are definably generated by torsion elements and, in definably connected groups, 0-Sylow subgroups coincide with p-Sylow subgroups for each p prime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.02637v4</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annalisa Conversano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A classification of incompleteness statements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05973v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For which choices of $X,Y,Z\in\{\Sigma^1_1,\Pi^1_1\}$ does no sufficiently strong $X$-sound and $Y$-definable extension theory prove its own $Z$-soundness? We give a complete answer, thereby delimiting the generalizations of G\"odel's second incompleteness theorem that hold within second-order arithmetic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05973v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry Towsner, James Walsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform Lyndon interpolation for the pure logic of necessitation with a modal reduction principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the uniform Lyndon interpolation property (ULIP) of some extensions of the pure logic of necessitation $\mathbf{N}$. For any $m, n \in \mathbb{N}$, $\mathbf{N}^+\mathbf{A}_{m,n}$ is the logic obtained from $\mathbf{N}$ by adding a single axiom $\Box^n \varphi \to \Box^m \varphi$, $\Diamond$-free modal reduction principle, together with a rule $\frac{\neg \Box \varphi}{\neg \Box \Box \varphi}$, required to make the logic complete with respect to its Kripke-like semantics. We first introduce a sequent calculus $\mathbf{GN}^+\mathbf{A}_{m,n}$ for $\mathbf{N}^+\mathbf{A}_{m,n}$ and show that it enjoys cut elimination, proving Craig and Lyndon interpolation properties as a consequence. We then introduce a general method, called propositionalization, that enables one to reduce ULIP of a logic to some weaker logic. Lastly, we construct a propositionalization of $\mathbf{N}^+\mathbf{A}_{m,n}$ into classical propositional logic $\mathbf{Cl}$, proving ULIP as a corollary. We also prove ULIP of $\mathbf{NA}_{m,n} = \mathbf{N} + \Box^n \varphi \to \Box^m \varphi$ and $\mathbf{NRA}_{m,n} = \mathbf{N} + \Box^n \varphi \to \Box^m \varphi + \frac{\neg \varphi}{\neg \Box \varphi}$ in the same manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10176v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuta Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biased elementary doctrines and quotient completions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.03066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.03066v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we fill the gap between the elementary quotient completion introduced by Maietti and Rosolini and the exact completion of a category with weak finite limits, as described by Carboni and Vitale. To achieve this, we generalize Lawvere's elementary doctrines to apply to categories with weak finite products, referring to these structures as biased elementary doctrines. We present two main constructions: the first, called strictification, produces an elementary doctrine from a biased one, while the second is an extension of the elementary quotient completion that generalizes the exact completion of a category with weak finite limits, even when weak finite products are involved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.03066v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jpaa.2025.107983</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JPAA, Volume 229, Issue 6, June 2025, 107983</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cipriano Junior Cioffo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equidistribution of polynomially bounded o-minimal curves in homogeneous spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04935v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend Ratner's theorem on equidistribution of individual orbits of unipotent flows on finite volume homogeneous spaces of Lie groups to trajectories of non-contracting curves definable in polynomially bounded o-minimal structures.
  To be precise, let $\varphi:[0,\infty)\to \text{SL}(n,\mathbb R)$ be a continuous map whose coordinate functions are definable in a polynomially bounded o-minimal structure; for example, rational functions. Suppose that $\varphi$ is non-contracting; that is, for any linearly independent vectors $v_1,\ldots,v_k$ in $\mathbb R^n$, $\varphi(t).(v_1\wedge\cdots\wedge v_k)\not\to0$ as $t\to\infty$. Then, there exists a unique smallest subgroup $H_\varphi$ of $\text{SL}(n,\mathbb R)$ generated by unipotent one-parameter subgroups such that $\varphi(t)H_\varphi\to g_0H_\varphi$ in $\text{SL}(n,\mathbb R)/H_\varphi$ as $t\to\infty$ for some $g_0\in \text{SL}(n,\mathbb R)$.
  Let $G$ be a closed subgroup of $\text{SL}(n,\mathbb R)$ and $\Gamma$ be a lattice in $G$. Suppose that $\varphi([0,\infty))\subset G$. Then $H_\varphi\subset G$, and for any $x\in G/\Gamma$, the trajectory $\{\varphi(t)x:t\in [0,T]\}$ gets equidistributed with respect to the measure $g_0\mu_{Lx}$ as $T\to\infty$, where $L$ is a closed subgroup of $G$ such that $\overline{Hx}=Lx$ and $Lx$ admits a unique $L$-invariant probability measure, denoted by $\mu_{Lx}$.
  A crucial new ingredient in this work is proving that for any finite-dimensional representation $V$ of $\text{SL}(n,\mathbb R)$, there exist $T_0&gt;0$, $C&gt;0$, and $\alpha&gt;0$ such that for any $v\in G$, the map $t\mapsto \|\varphi(t)v\|$ is $(C,\alpha)$-good on $[T_0,\infty)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04935v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Bersudsky, Nimish A. Shah, Hao Xing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existential and positive games: a comonadic and axiomatic view</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01247v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A number of model-comparison games central to (finite) model theory, such as pebble and Ehrenfeucht-Fra\"{i}ss\'{e} games, can be captured as comonads on categories of relational structures. In particular, the coalgebras for these comonads encode in a syntax-free way preservation of resource-indexed logic fragments, such as first-order logic with bounded quantifier rank or a finite number of variables.
  In this paper, we extend this approach to existential and positive fragments (i.e., without universal quantifiers and without negations, respectively) of first-order and modal logic. We show, both concretely and at the axiomatic level of arboreal categories, that the preservation of existential fragments is characterised by the existence of so-called pathwise embeddings, while positive fragments are captured by a newly introduced notion of positive bisimulation. As an application, we offer a new proof of an equi-resource Lyndon positivity theorem for (multi)modal logic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01247v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samson Abramsky, Thomas Laure, Luca Reggio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
