<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 03:39:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a logic of affordances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We aim to construct a formal theory of affordances seen as ternary relations. Beginning with a characterization of affordances proposed by James J. Gibson, and utilizing the tools provided by Zdzis{\l}aw Pawlak's information systems and rough sets, we construct a mathematically precise definition of both crisp and rough affordances. Then, we analyze modal and approximation operators that enable reasoning about affordances in both scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05214v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafal Gruszczynski, Paula Mench\'on, Ivo D\"untsch, G\"unther Gediga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Descending sequences in reflection hierarchies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05263v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is no recursively enumerable sequence of sufficiently strong 2-consistent r.e. theories such that each proves the $2$-consistency of the next. Montalb\'an and Shavrukov independently asked whether this result generalizes to $0'$-recursive sequences. We consider a general version of this problem: For arbitrary $n$, for which complexity classes $\Gamma$ are there $\Gamma$-definable sequences of $n$-consistent r.e. theories each of which proves the $n$-consistency of the next? The answer to this question depends not only on $n$ and $\Gamma$ but also on the manner in which sequences are encoded in arithmetic. We provide positive answers for certain encodings and negative answers for others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05263v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateusz {\L}e{\l}yk, James Walsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hereditarily Structurally Complete Superintuitionistic Logics and Primitive Varieties of Heyting Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give an algebraic proof of the criterion for hereditary structural completeness of an intermediate logic, or, equivalently, of the primitiveness of a variety of Heyting algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05633v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Citkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A footnote to the KPT theorem in structural Ramsey theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The celebrated theorem of Kechris, Pestov and Todor\v{c}evi\'c connecting structural Ramsey theory with topological dynamics has as a consequence that the Fra\"{\i}ss\'e limit of a Ramsey class of non-trivial finite relational structures has a reduct which is a total order; this implies an earlier result of Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il, according to which the structures in such a class are rigid (have trivial automorphism groups). In this paper, we give an alternative proof of this fact. If $\mathcal{C}$ is a Fra\"{\i}ss\'e class of rigid structures over a finite relational language, then either the Fra\"{\i}ss\'e limit of $\mathcal{C}$ has a reduct which is a total order, or there is an explicit failure of the Ramsey property involving a pair $(A,B)$ of structures in $\mathcal{C}$ with $|A|=2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05684v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter J. Cameron, Siavash Lashkarighouchani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set theory, logic, and homeomorphism groups of manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05206v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the relationship between axiomatic set theory and the first-order theory of homeomorphism groups of manifolds in the language of group theory, concentrating on first-order rigidity and type versus conjugacy. We prove that under the axiom of constructibility (i.e. {V=L}), homeomorphism groups of arbitrary connected manifolds are first-order rigid, and that the conjugacy class of a homeomorphism of a manifold is determined by its type. In contradistinction, under projective determinacy (PD), we show that in all dimensions greater than one, there exist pairs of noncompact, connected manifolds whose homeomorphism groups are elementarily equivalent but which are not homeomorphic. We also show that under PD, every manifold of positive dimension admits pairs of homeomorphisms with the same type which are not conjugate to each other. Finally, we show that infinitary sentences do determine conjugacy classes of homeomorphisms and homeomorphism types of manifolds; specifically, the conjugacy class of a homeomorphism of an arbitrary manifold is determined by a single $L_{\omega_1\omega}$ sentence. Similarly, the homeomorphism type of an arbitrary connected manifold is determined by a single $L_{\omega_1\omega}$ sentence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05206v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James E. Hanson, Thomas Koberda, J. de la Nuez Gonz\'alez, Christian Rosendal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vague Knowledge: Information without Transitivity and Partitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I relax the standard assumptions of transitivity and partition structure in economic models of information to formalize vague knowledge: non-transitive indistinguishability over states. I show that vague knowledge, while failing to partition the state space, remains informative by distinguishing some states from others. Moreover, it can only be faithfully expressed through vague communication with blurred boundaries. My results provide microfoundations for the prevalence of natural language communication and qualitative reasoning in the real world, where knowledge is often vague.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05833v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>q-fin.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kerry Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some contributions to sheaf model theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18089v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper makes contributions to "pure" sheaf model theory, the part of model theory in which the models are sheaves over a complete Heyting algebra. We start by outlining the theory in a way we hope is readable for the non-specialist. We then give a careful treatment of the interpretation of terms and formulae. This allows us to prove various preservation results, including strengthenings of the results of Brunner and Miraglia. We give refinements of Miraglia's work on directed colimits and an analogue of Tarski's theorem on the preservation of $\forall_2$-sentences under unions of chains. We next show various categories whose objects are (pairs of) presheaves and sheaves with various notions of morphism are accessible in the category theoretic sense. Together these ingredients allow us ultimately to prove that these categories are encompassed in the AECats framework for independence relations developed by Kamsma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18089v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Brunner, Charles Morgan, Darllan Pinto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Syntactic Definitions of Back-and-Forth Types</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00893v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The back-and-forth relations $M\leq_\alpha N$ are central to computable structure theory and countable model theory. It is well-known that the relation $\{(M,N) : M \leq_\alpha N\}$ is (lightface) $\Pi^0_{2\alpha}$. We show that this is optimal as the set is $\mathbf{\Pi}^0_{2\alpha}$-complete. We are also interested in the one-sided relations $\{ N : M \leq_\alpha N\}$ and $\{ N : M \geq_\alpha N\}$ for a fixed $M$, measuring the $\Pi_\alpha$ and $\Sigma_\alpha$ types of $M$. We show that these sets are always $\mathbf{\Pi}^0_{\alpha + 2}$ and $\mathbf{\Pi}^0_{\alpha+3}$ respectively, and that for most $\alpha$ there are structures $M$ for which these relations are complete at that level. In particular, there are structures $M$ such that there is no $\Pi_\alpha$ (or even $\Pi_{\alpha+1})$ sentence $\varphi$ such that $N \models \varphi \Longleftrightarrow M \leq_\alpha N$.
  This is unfortunate as not all $\Pi_{\alpha+2}$ sentences are preserved under $\leq_\alpha$. We define a new hierarchy of syntactic complexity closely related to the back-and-forth game, which can both define the back-and-forth types as well as be preserved by them. These hierarchies of formulas have already been useful in certain Henkin constructions, one of which we give in this paper, and another previously used by Gonzalez and Harrison-Trainor to show that every $\Pi_\alpha$ theory of linear orders has a model with Scott rank at most $\alpha+3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00893v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiyuan Chen, David Gonzalez, Matthew Harrison-Trainor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Cut-Free Sequent Calculus for the Analysis of Finite-Trace Properties in Concurrent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03164v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We address the problem of identifying a proof-theoretic framework that enables a compositional analysis of finite-trace properties in concurrent systems, with a particular focus on those specified via prefix-closure. To this end, we investigate the interaction of a prefix-closure operator and its residual (with respect to set-theoretic inclusion) with language intersection, union, and concatenation, and introduce the variety of closure $\ell$-monoids as a minimal algebraic abstraction of finite-trace properties to be conveniently described within an analytic proof system. Closure $\ell$-monoids are division-free reducts of distributive residuated lattices equipped with a forward diamond/backward box residuated pair of unary modal operators, where the diamond is a topological closure operator satisfying $\Diamond(x \cdot y) \leq \Diamond x \cdot \Diamond y$. As a logical counterpart to these structures, we present $\mathsf{LMC}$, a Gentzen-style system based on the division-free fragment of the Distributive Full Lambek Calculus. In $\mathsf{LMC}$, structural terms are built from formulas using Belnap-style structural operators for monoid multiplication, meet, and diamond. The rules for the modalities and the structural diamond are taken from Moortgat's system $\mathsf{NL}(\Diamond)$. We show that the calculus is sound and complete with respect to the variety of closure $\ell$-monoids and that it admits cut elimination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03164v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludovico Fusco, Alessandro Aldini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
