<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ladders and Squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1984, Ditor asked two questions: (1) For each $n\in\omega$ and infinite cardinal $\kappa$, is there a join-semilattice of breadth $n+1$ and cardinality $\kappa^{+n}$ whose principal ideals have cardinality $&lt; \kappa$? (2) For each $n \in \omega$, is there a lower-finite lattice of cardinality $\aleph_{n}$ whose elements have at most $n+1$ lower covers? We show that both questions have positive answers under the axiom of constructibility, and hence consistently with $\mathsf{ZFC}$. More specifically, we derive the positive answers from assuming that $\square_\kappa$ holds for enough $\kappa$'s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00414v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Notaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another infinite natural sum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define and study an infinitary operation on countable sequences of ordinals which is strictly monotone in many significant cases and has both an order-theoretical characterization and a characterization in terms of combinatorial games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00424v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Lipparini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recursive inseparability of classical theories of a binary predicate and non-classical logics of a unary predicate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00524v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper considers algorithmic properties of classical and non-classical first-order logics and theories in bounded languages. The main idea is to prove the undecidability of various fragments of classical and non-classical first-order logics and theories indirectly, by extracting it as a consequence of the recursive inseparability of special problems associated with them. First, we propose a domino problem, which makes it possible to catch the recursive inseparability of two sets. Second, using this problem, we prove that the classical first-order logic of a binary predicate and the theory of its finite models where the predicate is symmetric and irreflexive are recursively inseparable in a language with a single binary predicate letter and three variables (without constants and equality). Third, we prove, for an infinite class of logics, that the monadic fragment of a modal predicate logic and the logic of the class of its finite Kripke frames are recursively inseparable in languages with a single unary predicate letter and two individual variables; the same result is obtained if we replace the condition of finiteness of frames with the condition of finiteness of domains allowed in frames. Forth, we expand the results to a wide class of superintuitionistic predicate logics. In particular, it is proved that the positive fragments of the intuitionistic predicate logic and the logic of the class of finite intuitionistic Kripke frames are recursively inseparable in the language with a single unary predicate letter and two individual variables. The technique used and the results obtained allow us to answer some additional questions about the decidability of special monadic fragments of some modal and superintuitionistic predicate logics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00524v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Rybakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superintuitionistic predicate logics of linear frames: undecidability with two individual variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00531v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper presents a solution to the long-standing question about the decidability of the two-variable fragment of the superintuitionistic predicate logic $\mathbf{QLC}$ defined by the class of linear Kripke frames, which is also the `superintuitionistic' fragment of the modal predicate logic $\mathbf{QS4.3}$, under the G\"odel translation. We prove that the fragment is undecidable ($\Sigma^0_1$-complete). The result remains true for the positive fragment, even with a single binary predicate letter and an infinite set of unary predicate letters. Also, we prove that the logic defined by ordinal $\omega$ as a Kripke frame is not recursively enumerable (even both $\Sigma^0_1$-hard and $\Pi^0_1$-hard) with the same restrictions on the language. The results remain true if we add also the constant domain condition. The proofs are based on two techniques: a modification of the method proposed by M.Marx and M.Reynolds, which allows us to describe tiling problems using natural numbers rather than pairs of numbers within an enumeration of Cantor's, and an idea of `double labeling' the elements from the domains, which allows us to use only two individual variables in the proof when applying the former method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00531v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Rybakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When is $A + x A =\mathbb{R}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that there is an additive $F_\sigma$ subgroup $A$ of $\mathbb{R}$ and $x \in \mathbb{R}$ such that $\mathrm{dim_H} (A) = \frac{1}{2}$ and $A + x A =\mathbb{R}$. However, if $A \subseteq \mathbb{R}$ is a subring of $\mathbb{R}$ and there is $x \in \mathbb{R}$ such that $A + x A =\mathbb{R}$, then $A =\mathbb{R}$. Moreover, assuming the continuum hypothesis (CH), there is a subgroup $A$ of $\mathbb{R}$ with $\mathrm{dim_H} (A) = 0$ such that $x \not\in \mathbb{Q}$ if and only if $A + x A =\mathbb{R}$ for all $x \in \mathbb{R}$. A key ingredient in the proof of this theorem consists of some techniques in recursion theory and algorithmic randomness. We believe it may lead to applications to other constructions of exotic sets of reals. Several other theorems on measurable, and especially Borel and analytic subgroups and subfields of the reals are presented. We also discuss some of these results in the $p$-adics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00556v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinhe Ye, Liang Yu, Xuanheng zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Rigidity and Elementary Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a method for producing elementary embeddings from homomorphisms. This method is utilized in the study of the "strongly rigid relation principle" as defined by Hamkins and Palumbo in their paper "The Rigid Relation Principle, a New Weak Choice Principle." We establish that the strongly rigid relation principle is also a weak choice principle that is independent of ZF. Finally, we characterize proto Berkeley cardinals in terms of a strong failure of the strongly rigid relation principle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00633v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marwan Salam Mohammd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinhardt Cardinals and Eventually Dominating Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a result concerning elementary embeddings of the set-theoretic universe into itself (Reinhardt embeddings) and functions on ordinals that "eventually dominate" such embeddings. We apply that result to show the existence of elementary embeddings satisfying some strict conditions and that are also reminiscent of extendibility in a more local setting. Building further on these concepts, we make precise the nature of some large cardinals whose existence under Reinhardt embeddings was proven by Gabriel Goldberg in his paper "Measurable Cardinals and Choiceless Axioms." Finally, these ideas are used to present another proof of the Kunen inconsistency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00637v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marwan Salam Mohammd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Order Logic with Fuzzy Semantics for Describing and Recognizing Nerves in Medical Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00173v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article deals with the description and recognition of fiber bundles, in particular nerves, in medical images, based on the anatomical description of the fiber trajectories. To this end, we propose a logical formalization of this anatomical knowledge. The intrinsically imprecise description of nerves, as found in anatomical textbooks, leads us to propose fuzzy semantics combined with first-order logic. We define a language representing spatial entities, relations between these entities and quantifiers. A formula in this language is then a formalization of the natural language description. The semantics are given by fuzzy representations in a concrete domain and satisfaction degrees of relations. Based on this formalization, a spatial reasoning algorithm is proposed for segmentation and recognition of nerves from anatomical and diffusion magnetic resonance images, which is illustrated on pelvic nerves in pediatric imaging, enabling surgeons to plan surgery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00173v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabelle Bloch, Enzo Bonnot, Pietro Gori, Giammarco La Barbera, Sabine Sarnacki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decomposing graphs into stable and ordered parts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Connections between structural graph theory and finite model theory recently gained a lot of attention. In this setting, many interesting question remain on the properties of hereditary dependent (NIP) classes of graphs, in particular related to first-order transductions.
  Motivated by Simon's decomposition theorem of dependent types into a stable part and a distal (order-like) part, we conjecture that every hereditary dependent class of graphs is transduction-equivalent to a hereditary dependent class of partially ordered graphs, where the cover graph of the partial order has bounded treewidth and the unordered graph is (edge) stable.
  In this paper, we consider the first non-trivial case (classes with bounded linear cliquewidth) and prove that the conjecture holds in a strong form, where the cover graph of the partial order has bounded pathwidth. Then, we extend our study to classes that admit bounded-size bounded linear cliquewidth covers, and prove that the conjecture holds for these classes, too.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00594v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hector Buffi\`ere, Patrice Ossona de Mendez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berkeley Cardinals and Vop\v{e}nka's Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10455v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce "$n$-choiceless" supercompact and extendible cardinals in Zermelo-Fraenkel set theory without the Axiom of Choice. We prove relations between these cardinals and Vop\v{e}nka's Principle similar to those of Bagaria's work in his papers "$C^{(n)}$-Cardinals" and "More on the Preservation of Large Cardinals Under Class Forcing." We use these relations to characterize Berkeley cardinals in terms of a restricted form of Vop\v{e}nka's Principle. Finally, we establish the equiconsistency of the "$n$-choiceless" extendible cardinals with their original counterparts, and study the consistency strength of other relevant theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10455v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marwan Salam Mohammd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scott Spectral Gaps are Bounded for Linear Orderings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12084v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that any $\Pi_\alpha$ sentence of the infinitary logic $L_{\omega_1 \omega}$ extending the theory of linear orderings has a model with a $\Pi_{\alpha+4}$ Scott sentence and hence of Scott rank at most $\alpha+3$. In other words, the gap between the complexity of the theory and the complexity of the simplest model is always bounded by $4$. This contrasts the situation with general structures where for any $\alpha$ there is a $\Pi_2$ sentence all of whose models have Scott rank $\alpha$. We also give new lower bounds, though there remains a small gap between our lower and upper bounds: For most (but not all) $\alpha$, we construct a $\Pi_\alpha$ sentence extending the theory of linear orderings such that no models have a $\Sigma_{\alpha+2}$ Scott sentence and hence no models have Scott rank less than or equal to $\alpha$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12084v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Gonzalez, Matthew Harrison-Trainor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Coase Theorem and Ideal Exchanges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11484v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper offers a proof of the Coase theorem by formalizing the notion of ideal exchanges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11484v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel L\"u</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
