<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 02:39:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Directed schemes of ideals and cardinal characteristics, I: the meager additive ideal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of \emph{directed scheme of ideals} to characterize peculiar ideals on the reals, which comes from a formalization of the framework of Yorioka ideals for strong measure zero sets. We prove general theorems for directed schemes and propose a directed scheme $\vec{\mathcal{M}} = \{\mathcal{M}_I \colon I\in\mathbb{I}\}$ for the ideal $\mathcal{MA}$ of meager-additive sets of reals. This directed scheme does not only helps us to understand more the combinatorics of $\mathcal{MA}$ and its cardinal characteristics, but provides us new characterizations of the additivity and cofinality numbers of the meager ideal of the reals.
  In addition, we display connections between the characteristics associated with $\mathcal{M}_I$ and other classical characteristics. Furthermore, we demonstrate the consistency of $\mathrm{cov}(\mathcal{N}\!\mathcal{A})&lt;\mathfrak{c}$ and $\mathrm{cof}(\mathcal{MA})&lt;\mathrm{non}(\mathcal{SN})$. The first one answers a question raised by the authors in~\cite{CMR2}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00235v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel A. Cardona, Diego A. Mej\'ia, Ismael E. Rivera-Madrid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolation and Amalgamation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This chapter presents a state-of-the-art survey of relationships, traditionally referred to as `bridges', between interpolation properties for propositional logics -- including superintuitionistic, modal, and substructural logics -- and amalgamation properties for corresponding classes of algebraic structures. These bridges are developed in the framework of universal algebra and illustrated with a broad range of examples from logic and algebra, demonstrating their use in establishing properties for both fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00924v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Metcalfe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entangled Suslin lines and OGA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a model of the Open Graph Axiom (OGA) in which there is a 2-entangled Suslin line $S$. Consequently, in this model, there is a 2-entangled uncountable linear order, but no such order is separable. This resolves a problem posed by Carroy, Levine, and Notaro \cite{carroy2025} and answers a question from McKenney on MathOverflow \cite{Mckenney2014}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01065v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Martinez-Ranero, Lucas Polymeris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A guide to topological reconstruction on endomorphism monoids and polymorphism clones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Various spaces of symmetries of a structure are naturally endowed with both an algebraic and a topological structure. For example, the automorphism group of a structure is, on top of being a group, a topological group when equipped with the topology of pointwise convergence. In some cases, the algebraic structure of such space alone is sufficiently rich to determine its topology (under some requirements on the topology). For automorphism groups, the problem of when this happens has been actively pursued over the last 40 years. With the exception of some early work of Lascar, the analogue of this problem for endomorphism monoids and polymorphism clones has only received attention in the past 15 years. In this guide, we survey the current state of affairs in this relatively young line of research. We moreover use this opportunity to polish several existing results and to extend them beyond what was hitherto known.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01086v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Marimon, Michael Pinsker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A consistency theorem for cardinal sequences of length $&lt; \omega_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that if $\lambda$ is a fixed uncountable cardinal and $f = \langle \ka_{\al} : \al &lt; \delta \rangle$ is a sequence of infinite cardinals where $\delta &lt; \omega_3$ and $\ka_{\al}\in \{\om,\lambda\}$ for each $\al &lt; \delta$ in such a way that $f^{-1}\{\om\}$ is $\om_2$-closed in $\delta$, then it is consistent that there is a scattered Boolean space whose cardinal sequence is $f$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01418v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Carlos Mart\'inez, Lajos Soukup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolation in Non-Classical Logics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This chapter surveys some of the main results on interpolation in several of the most prominent families of non-classical logics. Special attention is given to the distinction between the two most commonly studied variants of interpolation--namely, Craig interpolation and deductive interpolation. Our discussion focuses primarily on how these properties present in families of logical systems taken as a whole, particularly those comprising all axiomatic extensions of any of several notable non-classical logics. We consider a range of important examples: superintuitionistic and modal logics, fuzzy logics, paraconsistent logics, relevant logics, and substructural logics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01600v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wesley Fussner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchies of Beliefs and Measurable Uniformizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the Fundamental Theorem of Epistemic Game Theory to games with Baire class one payoffs and locally compact Polish strategy spaces, and under Projective Determinacy, to games with analytically measurable payoffs and arbitrary Polish strategy spaces. We show that in full generality, the statement that rationalizable strategies are consistent with rationality and common belief in rationality follows from the Axiom of Real Determinacy, has a characterization in terms of real Gale-Stewart games, fails under the Continuum Hypothesis, and in the framework of interactive epistemics is equivalent to the Measurable Uniformization Principle from the Solovay model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01862v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stuart Zoble</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model theory, differential algebra and functional transcendence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01866v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The goal of this text is to exhibit some of the ideas and methods from geometric model theory, translated to the particular context of differentially closed fields, exhibiting in a more or less self-contained way the tools needed for the recent proof of Freitag, Jaoui and Moosa on functional transcendence and their so-called C$_2$-property, which serves as a leitmotif for the presentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01866v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amador Martin-Pizarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniformity in learning structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The standard framework for studying learning problems on algebraic structures assumes that the structures in the target family are pairwise nonisomorphic. Under this assumption, the most widely investigated learning criterion--Ex-learning--becomes inherently equivalent to the well-known paradigm of Bc-learning. This paper explores what happens when the nonisomorphism requirement is removed and analyzes the extent to which these two learning criteria remain uniformly equivalent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01867v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vittorio Cipriani, Dino Rossegger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Normalization for the Safe Fragment of a Minimal Rewrite System: A Triple-Lexicographic Proof and a Conjecture on the Unprovability of Full Termination for Any Relational Operator-Only TRS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00081v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a minimal operator-only term rewriting system with seven constructors and eight reduction rules. Our main contribution is a mechanically-verified proof of strong normalization for a guarded fragment using a novel triple-lexicographic measure combining a phase bit, multiset ordering (Dershowitz-Manna), and ordinal ranking. From strong normalization, we derive a certified normalizer with proven totality and soundness. Assuming local confluence (verified through critical pair analysis), Newman's Lemma yields confluence and therefore unique normal forms for the safe fragment. We establish impossibility results showing that simpler measures, such as additive counters, polynomial interpretations, and single-bit flags, provably fail for rules with term duplication. The work demonstrates fundamental limitations in termination proving for self-referential systems. We state a conjecture: no relational operator-only TRS can have its full-system termination proved by internally definable methods. Here "relational" is equivalent to "capable of ordered computation" - systems with a recursor enabling iteration over successors, comparison, or sequential counting. Such recursors necessarily redistribute step arguments across recursive calls, defeating all additive termination measures. This structural limitation applies to any TRS expressive enough to encode ordered data. All theorems have been formally verified in a proof assistant. The formal development is available to program committee members and referees upon request for purposes of peer review.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00081v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moses Rahnama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Theory of General von Neumann Algebras II: Group Actions and Crossed Products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00224v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Expanding on previous work of the author, we initiate the model theoretic study of W$^*$-dynamical systems. We axiomatize continuous weight-preserving group actions of $G$ on von Neumann algebras for $G$ a given locally compact Hausdorff group. Since our axiomatization is of continuous actions, the ultraproduct is defined so that the ultraproduct action of $G$ is also continuous. Building on a theorem of Tomatsu, we show that continuous ultraproducts commute with crossed products. Finally, we prove a suite of results about computability of the aforementioned axiomatizations and of presentations of crossed products. In particular, we show how the crossed product construction is a useful tool for producing computable presentations, giving special attention to the group measure space construction of Murray and von Neumann. Thereby, we establish interesting connections to computable dynamics and computable measure theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00224v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jananan Arulseelan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complemented ideals of $\ell_\infty$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00230v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Answering questions raised in \cite{Leonetti, Uzcategui} we characterize ideals $\mathcal I\subseteq \mathcal P(\omega)$ such that $c_{0,\mathcal I}$ is complemented in $\ell_\infty$ as exactly those ideals for which the space $K_{\mathcal I}= \mathsf{Stone}(\mathcal P(\omega)/\mathcal I)$ is approximable, i.e., the unit ball of the space $M(K_{\mathcal I})$ of signed Radon measures on $K_\mathcal I$ is separable in the weak* topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00230v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Hru\v{s}\'ak, Luis S\'aenz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effros' theorem on transitive group actions with a glimpse into descriptive set theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00910v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The main aim of this note is to prove a version of a celebrated theorem of Effros about transitive group actions in a non-metrizable setting, these parts have been formalized and verified with Lean by Lara Toledano. We do not claim any originality since the given proof is in fact very close to one of van Mill. Our presentation is however completely self-contained and may serve as an appetizer to descriptive set theory. It also contains a few results about Suslin spaces (continuous images of separable completely metrizable spaces, which are often called analytic) which are extremely useful in measure theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00910v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jochen Wengenroth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Games with infinite past</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01001v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study multi-player games with perfect information and general payoff function, where the set of stages is the set of non-positive integers $\{\ldots,-2,-1,0\}$. We define two related equilibrium concepts: one considering only deviations at finitely many stages and another considering all deviations. We show that (i) The sets of equilibrium plays coincide for the two equilibrium concepts, provided that at least two players are active along each infinite play. (ii) In win-lose games, the game has an equilibrium if the winning sets have Borel-rank at most 2, and we provide a counter-example showing that this is no longer true for Borel-rank 3. (iii) In general non-zero-sum games, the game has an equilibrium if the payoff functions are continuous, for example, with reversed-time discounted payoffs. The challenge for all these results is that not all strategy profiles admit a consistent infinite play, hampering the use of backward induction arguments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01001v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Galit Ashkenazi-Golan, J\'anos Flesch, Eilon Solan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computable thermodynamic formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01259v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the theory of thermodynamic formalism from the perspective of computable analysis, with a special focus on the computability of equilibrium states. Specifically, we develop two complementary general approaches to verify the computability of equilibrium states for non-uniformly expanding computable dynamical systems. The first approach applies to dynamical systems whose topological pressure functions admit effective approximations and whose measure-theoretic entropy functions are upper semi-continuous. As a concrete application, we establish the computability of the equilibrium states for Misiurewicz-Thurston rational maps with \holder continuous potentials. The second approach exploits prescribed Jacobians of equilibrium states through a local analysis and applies to settings where the measure-theoretic entropy functions may lack upper semi-continuity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01259v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilia Binder, Qiandu He, Zhiqiang Li, Xianghui Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the linear complexity of subsets of $\mathbb{F}_p^n$ bounded $\textrm{VC}_2$-dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02001v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Previous work of the second author and Wolf showed that given a set $A\subseteq \mathbb{F}_p^n$ of bounded $\textrm{VC}_2$-dimension, there is a high rank quadratic factor $\mathcal{B}$ of bounded complexity such that $A$ is approximately equal to a union of atoms of $\mathcal{B}$. That proof yielded bounds of tower type on the linear and quadratic complexities. It was later shown by the same authors that the quadratic complexity can be improved to logarithmic, however that proof provided no improvement on the linear component. In this paper we prove that the bound on the linear complexity can be improved to a triple exponential in the case of linear rank functions, and a quadruple exponential for polynomial rank functions of higher degree.
  Our strategy is based on the one developed by Gishboliner, Wigderson, and Shapira to prove the analogous result in the hypergraph setting. Step 1 is to prove a``cylinder" version of the quadratic arithmetic regularity lemma, which says that given a set $A\subseteq G=\mathbb{F}_p^n$, there is a partition of $G$ into atoms of (possibly distinct) quadratic factors of high rank and bounded complexity, so that most atoms in the partition are uniform with respect to the set $A$, in the sense of a certain local $U^3$ norm. Step 2 is to show that if $A$ has bounded $\textrm{VC}_2$-dimension, then it has density near $0$ or $1$ on all atoms which are uniform in the sense of Step 1. Step 1 relies on a recent local version of the $U^3$ inverse theorem due to Prendiville, and is necessarily phrased in terms of a local $U^3$ norm implicit in that paper. On the other hand, Step 2 relies on a counting lemma for a different local $U^3$ due to Terry and Wolf, which we prove here is approximately the same as the local $U^3$ norm used in Step 1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02001v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Sheats, Caroline Terry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Encoding argumentation frameworks with set attackers to propositional logic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08370v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Argumentation frameworks ($AF$s) have been a useful tool for approximate reasoning. The encoding method is an important approach to formally model $AF$s under related semantics. The aim of this paper is to develop the encoding method from classical Dung's $AF$s ($DAF$s) to $AF$s with set attackers ($AFSA$s) including higher-level argumentation frames ($HLAF$s), Barringer's higher-order $AF$s ($BHAF$s), frameworks with sets of attacking arguments ($SETAF$s) and higher-order set $AF$s ($HSAF$s). Regarding syntactic structures, we propose the $HSAF$s where the target of an attack is either an argument or an attack and the sources are sets of arguments and attacks. Regarding semantics, we translate $HLAF$s and $SETAF$s under respective complete semantics to {\L}ukasiewicz's 3-valued propositional logic system ($PL_3^L$). Furthermore, we propose complete semantics of $BHAF$s and $HSAF$s by respectively generalizing from $HLAF$s and $SETAF$s, and then translate to the $PL_3^L$. Moreover, for numerical semantics of $AFSA$s, we propose the equational semantics and translate to fuzzy propositional logic systems ($PL_{[0,1]}$s). This paper establishes relationships of model equivalence between an $AFSA$ under a given semantics and the encoded formula in a related propositional logic system ($PLS$). By connections of $AFSA$s and $PLS$s, this paper provides the logical foundations for $AFSA$s associated with complete semantics and equational semantics. The results advance the argumentation theory by unifying $HOAF$s and $SETAF$s under logical formalisms, paving the way for automated reasoning tools in AI, decision support, and multi-agent systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08370v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuai Tang, Jiachao Wu, Ning Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the lattice of multi-sorted relational clones on a two-element set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06033v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a new approach to the description of multi-sorted clones (sets of $k$-tuples of operations of the same arity, closed under coordinatewise composition and containing all projection tuples) on a two-element domain. Leveraging the well-known Galois connection between operations and relations, we define a small class of canonical relations sufficient to describe all Boolean multi-sorted clones up to non-surjective operations. Furthermore, we introduce elementary operations on relations, which are less cumbersome than general formulas and have many useful properties. Using these tools, we provide a new and elementary proof of the famous Post's lattice theorem. We also show that every multi-sorted clone of $k$-tuples of operations decomposes into a surjective part described by canonical relations and $2k$ clones of $(k-1)$-tuples of operations. This structural understanding allows us to describe an embedding of the lattice of multi-sorted clones into a well-understood poset. In particular, we rederive - by a simpler method - a result of V. Taimanov originally from 1983, showing that every multi-sorted clone on a two-element domain is finitely generated. Finally, we also give a concise proof of the Galois connection between (surjective) multi-sorted clones and the corresponding closed sets of relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06033v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vojt\v{e}ch David, Dmitriy Zhuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structures of uninorms on bounded lattices via t-conorms, closure operators and t-subnorms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06206v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we provide some structures of uninorms on bounded lattices via t-conorms, closure operators and t-subnorms, subject to certain constraints on the closure operators and t-subnorms. Importantly, these constraints are shown to be both sufficient and necessary. That is, the proposed methods reveal clear relationships between the structure of the resulting uninorms and the properties of the underlying components. Meanwhile, we present the degenerate cases of the aforementioned results, which are constructed using special closure operators and t-subnorms. Some of these cases correspond to well-known results documented in the literature. Moreover, the dual constructions of uninorms on bounded lattices, based on t-norms, interior operators and t-superconorms, are presented simultaneously.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06206v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyu Xiu, Zhengyuan Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
