<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On pre-local tabularity above $\mathrm{S4}\times \mathrm{S4}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate pre-local tabularity in normal extensions of the logic $\mathrm{S4}\times \mathrm{S4}$. We show that there are exactly four pre-locally tabular logics in normal extensions of products of finite height, and that every non-locally tabular logic in this family is contained in one of them. We also give an axiomatic criterion of local tabularity above the logic of products with Noetherian skeletons. Then we construct examples of pre-locally tabular extensions of $\mathrm{S4}\times \mathrm{S4}$ outside this class. In particular, we describe pre-locally tabular bimodal logics with the converse and universal modalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20874v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilya B. Shapirovsky, Vladislav V. Sliusarev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Splitting Families, Reaping Families, and Families of Permutations Associated with Asymptotic Density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate several relations between cardinal characteristics of the continuum related with the asymptotic density of the natural numbers and some known cardinal invariants. Specifically, we study the cardinals of the form $\mathfrak{s}_X$, $\mathfrak{r}_X$ and $\mathfrak{dd}_{X,Y}$ introduced in arXiv:2304.09698 and arXiv:2410.21102, answering some questions raised in these papers. In particular, we prove that $\mathfrak{s}_0=$ cov$(\mathcal{M})$ and $\mathfrak{r}_0=$ non$(\mathcal{M})$. We also show that $\mathfrak{dd}_{\{r\}, \textsf{all}}=\mathfrak{dd}_{\{1/2\}, \textsf{all}}$ for all $r\in (0,1)$, and we provide a proof of Con($\mathfrak{dd}_{(0,1),\{0,1\}}^{\textsf{rel}}&lt;$ non$(\mathcal{N})$) and Con($\mathfrak{dd}_{\textsf{all},\textsf{all}}^{\textsf{rel}}&lt;$ non$(\mathcal{N})$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21059v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Valderrama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial fingerprinting for trees and formulas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To cater to the needs of (Zero Knowledge) proofs for (mathematical) proofs, we describe a method to transform formal sentences in 2x2 - matrices over multivariate polynomials with integer coefficients, such that usual proof-steps like modus-ponens or the substitution are easy to compute from the matrices corresponding to the terms or formulas used as arguments. By evaluating the polynomial variables in random elements of a suitably chosen finite field, the proof is replaced by a numeric sequence. Only the values corresponding to the axioms have to be computed from scratch. The values corresponding to derived formulas are computed from the values corresponding to their ancestors by applying the homomorphic properties. On such sequences, various Zero Knowledge methods can be applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21114v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mihai Prunescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equational theory of ordinals with addition and left multiplication by $\omega$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13661v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the equational theory of the structure $\langle \omega^{\omega}: (x,y)\mapsto x+y, x\mapsto \omega x \rangle $ is finitely axiomatizable and give a simple axiom schema when the domain is the set of transfinite ordinals. We give an algorithm that given a pair of terms $(E,F)$ decides in linear time with respect of their common length whether or not $E=F$ is a consequence of the axioms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13661v4</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Choffrut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental sequences based on localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15953v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Building on Buchholz' assignment for ordinals below Bachmann-Howard ordinal, see Buchholz 2003, we introduce systems of fundamental sequences for two kinds of relativized $\vartheta$-function-based notation systems of strength $\Pi^1_1{\operatorname{-CA}_0}$ and prove Bachmann property for these systems, which is essential for monotonicity properties of subrecursive hierarchies defined on the basis of fundamental sequences. The central notion of our construction is the notion of localization, which was introduced in Wilken 2007.
  The first kind of stepwise defined $\vartheta$-functions over ordinal addition as basic function fits the framework of the ordinal arithmetical toolkit developed in Wilken 2007, whereas the second kind of $\vartheta$-functions is defined simultaneously and will allow for further generalization to larger proof-theoretic ordinals, see Weiermann and Wilken 2011.
  The systems of fundamental sequences given here enable the investigation of fundamental sequences and independence phenomena also in the context of patterns of resemblance, an approach to ordinal notations that is both semantic and combinatorial and was first introduced by Carlson 2001 and further analyzed in Wilken 2006, 2007, and Carlson and Wilken 2012.
  Our exposition is put into the context of the abstract approach to fundamental sequences developed by Buchholz, Cichon, and Weiermann 1994. The results of this paper will be applied in the theory of Goodstein sequences, extending results of Fern\`andez-Duque and Weiermann 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15953v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gunnar Wilken</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Proof Theory: Semi-analytic Rules and Uniform Interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.06258</link>
      <description>arXiv:1808.06258v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In \cite{Craig}, we introduced a syntactically defined and highly general class of calculi known as \emph{semi-analytic}. We then demonstrated that any sufficiently strong (modal) substructural logic with a semi-analytic calculus must satisfy the Craig interpolation property. In this paper, we show that if the calculus is also terminating in a certain formal sense, then its logic has the Uniform Interpolation Property (UIP). This result has significant applications. On the positive side, it provides a uniform and modular method for proving UIP for various logics, including $\mathsf{FL_e}$, $\mathsf{FL_{ew}}$, $\mathsf{CFL_e}$, $\mathsf{CFL_{ew}}$, and their $K$, $D$, and $T$-type modal extensions, as well as $\mathsf{CPC}$, $\mathsf{K}$, and $\mathsf{KD}$. However, its more striking consequence lies in the negative direction. It extends the negative results of \cite{Craig} to logics with CIP but without UIP. In particular, it shows that the modal logics $\mathsf{K4}$ and $\mathsf{S4}$ do not have a terminating semi-analytic calculus.
  \textbf{keywords:} Uniform interpolation, Sequent calculi, Substructural logics, Modal logics, Subexponential modalities</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1808.06258v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amirhossein Akbar Tabatabai, Raheleh Jalali</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
