<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 01:37:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A logic for instrumental obligation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops a logic based on causal inferences to formally capture the concept of instrumental obligation. We establish a causal deontic model that extends causal models with priority structures, allowing us to represent both the instrumental and deontic aspects of an obligation. In this framework, instrumental obligation is defined as a derived notion through intervention formulas of causal reasoning, where an action is considered obligatory if it is the best way to achieve the goal. We provide a sound and complete axiomatic system and show that the logic is NP-complete. The concept of instrumental permission is also taken into account in the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06824v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialiang Yan, Qingyu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On definable groups in dp-minimal topological fields equipped with a generic derivation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $T$ be a complete, model-complete, geometric dp-minimal $\mathcal{L}$-theory of topological fields of characteristic $0$ and let $T(\partial)$ be the theory of expansions of models of $T$ by a derivation $\partial$. We assume that $T(\partial)$ has a model-companion $T_{\partial}$. Let $\Gamma$ be a finite-dimensional $\mathcal{L}_\partial$-definable group in a model of $T_\partial$. Then we show that $\Gamma$ densely and definably embeds in an $\mathcal{L}$-definable group $G$.
  Further, using a $C^1$-cell decomposition result, we show that $\Gamma$ densely and definably embeds in a definable $D$-group, generalizing the classical construction of Buium of algebraic $D$-groups and extending for that class of fields, results obtained in arXiv:2208.08293, arXiv:2305.16747.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07044v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fran\c{c}oise Point</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A few notes about infinite trees in a descriptive set-theoretic setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07111v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Goy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All Borel Group Extensions of Finite-Dimensional Real Space Are Trivial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07216v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For $N \geq 2$, we study the structure of definable abelian group extensions of the additive group $(\mathbb{R}^N,+)$ by countable abelian (Borel) groups $G$. Given an extension $H$ of $(\mathbb{R}^N,+)$ by $G$, we measure the definability of $H$ by investigating its complexity as a Borel set. We do this by combining homological algebra and descriptive set theory, and hence study the Borel complexity of those functions inducing $H$, the abelian cocycles. We prove that, for every $N \geq 2$, there are no non-trivial Borel definable abelian cocycles coding group extensions of $(\mathbb{R}^N,+)$ by a countable abelian group $G$, and hence show that no non-trivial such group extensions exist. This completes the picture first investigated by Kanovei and Reeken in 2000, who proved the case $N = 1$, and whose techniques we adapt in this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07216v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linus Richter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative Quantifier Elimination for Separable-Algebraically Maximal Kaplansky Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $C$ be the class of separable-algebraically maximal equi-characteristic Kaplansky fields of a given imperfection degree, admitting an angular component map. We prove that the common theory of the class $C$ resplendently eliminates quantifiers down to the residue field and the value group, in a three sorted language of valued fields with a symbol for an angular component map and symbols for the parameterized lambda-functions. As a consequence, we obtain that equi-characteristic NIP and NIP$_n$ henselian fields with an angular component map resplendently eliminate field quantifiers in this language. We also prove that this elimination reduces existential formulas to existential formulas without quantifiers from the home sort. Finally, we draw several conclusions following the AKE philosophy for elements of the class $C$, including the usual AKE principles for $\equiv,\equiv_{\exists},\preceq,\preceq_{\exists}$ and for relative decidability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07418v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paulo Andr\'es Soto Moreno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Lambda functions in henselian and separably tame valued fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a field extension $F/C$, the ``Lambda closure'' $\Lambda_{F}C$ of $C$ in $F$ is a subextension of $F/C$ that is minimal with respect to inclusion such that $F/\Lambda_{F}C$ is separable. The existence and uniqueness of $\Lambda_{F}C$ was proved by Deveney and Mordeson in 1977. We show that it admits a simple description in terms of given generators for $C$: we expand the language of rings by the parameterized Lambda functions, and then $\Lambda_{F}C$ is the subfield of $F$ generated over $C$ by additionally closing under these functions. We then show that, given particular generators of $C$, $\Lambda_{F}C$ is the subfield of $F$ generated iteratively by the images of the generators under Lambda functions taken with respect to $p$-independent tuples also drawn from those generators.
  We apply these results to given a ``local description'' of existentially definable sets in fields equipped with a henselian topology. Let $X(K)$ be an existentially definable set in the theory of a field $K$ equipped with a henselian topology $\tau$. We show that there is a definable injection into $X(K)$ from a Zariski-open subset $U_{1}^{\circ}$ of a set with nonempty $\tau$-interior, and that each element of $U_{1}^{\circ}$ is interalgebraic (over parameters) with its image in $X(K)$. This can be seen as a kind of {\em very weak local quantifier elimination}, and it shows that existentially definable sets are (at least generically and locally) definably pararameterized by ``big'' sets.
  In the final section we extend the theory of separably tame valued fields, developed by Kuhlmann and Pal, to include the case of infinite degree of imperfection, and to allow expansions of the residue field and value group structures. We prove an embedding theorem which allows us to deduce the usual kinds of resplendent Ax--Kochen/Ershov principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07518v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sylvy Anscombe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some variants of the periodic tiling conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06757v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The periodic tiling conjecture (PTC) asserts, for a finitely generated Abelian group $G$ and a finite subset $F$ of $G$, that if there is a set $A$ that solves the tiling equation $\mathbb{1}_F * \mathbb{1}_A = 1$, there is also a periodic solution $\mathbb{1}_{A_{\mathrm{p}}}$. This conjecture is known to hold for some groups $G$ and fail for others. In this paper we establish three variants of the PTC. The first (due to Tim Austin) replaces the constant function $1$ on the right-hand side of the tiling equation by $0$, and the indicator functions $\mathbb{1}_F$ and $\mathbb{1}_A$ by bounded integer-valued functions. The second, which applies in $G=\mathbb{Z}^2$, replaces the right-hand side of the tiling equation by an integer-valued periodic function, and the functions $\mathbb{1}_F$ and $\mathbb{1}_A$ on the left-hand side by bounded integer-valued functions. The third (which is the most difficult to establish) is similar to the second, but retains the property of both $\mathbb{1}_A$ and $\mathbb{1}_{A_{\mathrm{p}}}$ being indicator functions; in particular, we establish the PTC for multi-tilings in $G=\mathbb{Z}^2$. As a result, we obtain the decidability of constant-level integer tilings in any finitely generated Abelian group $G$ and multi-tilings in $G=\mathbb{Z}^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06757v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Greenfeld, Terence Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undecidability of Polynomial Inequalities in Subset Densities and Additive Energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07378v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many results in extremal graph theory can be formulated as certain polynomial inequalities in graph homomorphism densities. Answering fundamental questions raised by Lov{\'a}sz, Szegedy and Razborov, Hatami and Norine proved that determining the validity of an arbitrary such polynomial inequality in graph homomorphism densities is undecidable. We observe that many results in additive combinatorics can also be formulated as polynomial inequalities in subset's density and its variants. Based on techniques introduced in Hatami and Norine, together with algebraic and graph construction and Fourier analysis, we prove similarly two theorems of undecidability, thus showing that establishing such polynomial inequalities in additive combinatorics are inherently difficult in their full generality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07378v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaqiao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The initial segment condition for $\kappa^+$-supercompactness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13827v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a development of the fine structure of mice with long extenders, to the level of $\kappa^+$-supercompact cardinals $\kappa$. We do this using a hierarchy with features more analogous to those familiar in the short extender context than the hierarchies introduced by Woodin and by Neeman-Steel. In particular, the mice we consider satisfy stronger versions of the initial segment condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13827v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farmer Schlutzenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random expansions of finite structures with bounded degree</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04802v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider finite relational signatures $\tau \subseteq \sigma$, a sequence of finite base $\tau$-structures $(\mathcal{B}_n : n \in \mathbb{N})$ the cardinalities of which tend to infinity and such that, for some number $\Delta$, the degree of (the Gaifman graph of) every $\mathcal{B}_n$ is at most $\Delta$. We let $\mathbf{W}_n$ be the set of all expansions of $\mathcal{B}_n$ to $\sigma$ and we consider a probabilistic graphical model, a concept used in machine learning and artificial intelligence, to generate a probability distribution $\mathbb{P}_n$ on $\mathbf{W}_n$ for all $n$. We use a many-valued ``probability logic'' with truth values in the unit interval to express probabilities within probabilistic graphical models and to express queries on $\mathbf{W}_n$. This logic uses aggregation functions (e.g. the average) instead of quantifiers and it can express all queries (on finite structures) that can be expressed with first-order logic since the aggregation functions maximum and minimum can be used to express existential and universal quantifications, respectively. The main results concern asymptotic elimination of aggregation functions (the analogue of almost sure elimination of quantifiers for two-valued logics with quantifiers) and the asymptotic distribution of truth values of formulas, the analogue of logical convergence results for two-valued logics. The structure theory that is developed for sequences $(\mathcal{B}_n : n \in \mathbb{N})$ as above may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04802v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vera Koponen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undecidability in the Ramsey theory of polynomial equations and Hilbert's tenth problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14917v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that several sets of interest arising from the study of partition regularity and density Ramsey theory of polynomial equations over integral domains are undecidable. In particular, we show that the set of homogeneous polynomials $p \in \mathbb{Z}[x_1,\cdots,x_n]$ for which the equation $p(x_1,\cdots,x_n) = 0$ is partition regular over $\mathbb{Z}\setminus\{0\}$ is undecidable conditional on Hilbert's tenth problem for $\mathbb{Q}$. For other integral domains, we get the analogous result unconditionally. More generally, we determine the exact lightface complexity of the various sets of interest. For example, we show that the set of homogeneous polynomials $p \in \mathbb{F}_q(t)[x_1,\cdots,x_n]$ for which the equation $p(x_1,\cdots,x_n) = 0$ is partition regular over $\mathbb{F}_q(t)\setminus\{0\}$ is $\Pi_2^0$-complete.
  We also prove several other results of independent interest. These include a compactness principle and a uniformity principle for density Ramsey theory on countable cancellative left amenable semigroups, as well as the existence of the natural extension for measure preserving systems of countable cancellative left reversible semigroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14917v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sohail Farhangi, Steve Jackson, Bill Mance</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Definable expansions on countable groups and countable Borel equivalence relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04130v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define and study expansion problems on countable structures in the setting of descriptive combinatorics. We consider both expansions on countable Borel equivalence relations and on countable groups, in the Borel, measure and category settings, and establish some basic correspondences between the two notions. We also prove some general structure theorems for measure and category. We then explore in detail many examples, including finding spanning trees in graphs, finding monochromatic sets in Ramsey's Theorem, and linearizing partial orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04130v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Wolman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
