<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO</link>
    <description>math.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Necessary and Sufficient Conditions for Proving Choice in Zermelo-Fraenkel Set Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16001v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces an alternative approach to proving the existence of choice functions for specific families of sets within Zermelo-Fraenkel set theory (ZF) without assuming any form on the Axiom of Choice (AC). Traditional methods of proving choice, when it is possible without AC, are based on explicit constructing a choice function, which relies on being able to identify canonical elements within the sets. Our approach, instead, employs the axiom schema of separation. We begin by considering families of well-ordered sets, then apply the schema of separation twice to build a set of possible candidates for the choice functions, and, finally, prove that this set is non-empty. This strategy enables proving the existence of choice function in situations where canonical elements cannot be identified explicitly. We then extend our method beyond families of well-ordered sets to families of sets, over which partial orders with a least element exist. After exploring possibilities for further generalization, we establish a necessary and sufficient condition: in ZF, without assuming AC, a choice function exists for a non-empty family if and only if each set admits a partial order with a least element. Finally, we demonstrate how this approach can be used to prove the existence of choice functions for families of contractible and path-connected topological spaces, including hyper-intervals in $\mathbb{R}^n$, hyper-balls, and hyper-spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16001v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentyn Khokhlov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hensel minimality, $p$-adic exponentiation and Tate uniformization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use Hensel minimality, a non-Archimedean analog of o-minimality, to study several questions around transcendental number theory, unlikely intersections, and differential fields in a non-Archimedean setting. In particular, we focus on $p$-adic exponentiation and Tate uniformization on $\mathbb{C}_p$, which we show live in a Hensel minimal structure on $\mathbb{C}_p$. We start by constructing a large collection of derivations on Hensel minimal fields that respect definable functions, which we then apply to the $p$-adic Schanuel conjecture. We also study properties of local definability in analogy to work of Wilkie, and show that $p$-adic Schanuel implies a uniform version of itself. For Tate uniformization we show a strong closure property when blurring, and deduce that $\mathbb{C}_p$ with the blurred Tate uniformization is quasiminimal. Finally, we prove a result on $p$-adic density of likely intersections for powers of elliptic curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16433v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Eterovi\'c, Floris Vermeulen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Godel Implication on Finite Chains: Truth Tables and Catalan-Bracketing Enumerations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16135v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fully bracketed implication terms on $n$ variables are evaluated in G\"odel $m$-valued logic on a finite chain, and we enumerate truth-table rows by output value across all Catalan bracketings. Using the Catalan decomposition, we derive a finite system of generating functions for these value counts and introduce a root-split refinement that records the ordered pair of truth values at the top implication, yielding $m^2$ pair classes. We prove that the associated generating functions share a common dominant square-root singularity, which implies a universal $n^{-3/2}$ asymptotic form with exponential growth rate $(4m)^n$ and a limiting output distribution as $n\to\infty$. The root-split refinement yields matching uniform asymptotics for the pair classes and gives a transparent factorization of the original counts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16135v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volkan Yildiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pitts and Intuitionistic Multi-Succedent: Uniform Interpolation for KM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16445v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Pitts' proof-theoretic technique for uniform interpolation, which generates uniform interpolants from terminating sequent calculi, has only been applied to logics on an intuitionistic basis through single-succedent sequent calculi. We adapt the technique to the intuitionistic multi-succedent setting by focusing on the intuitionistic modal logic KM. To do this, we design a novel multi-succedent sequent calculus for this logic which terminates, eliminates cut, and provides a decidability argument for KM. Then, we adapt Pitts' technique to our calculus to construct uniform interpolants for KM, while highlighting the hurdles we overcame. Finally, by (re)proving the algebraisability of KM, we deduce the coherence of the class of KM-algebras. All our results are fully mechanised in the Rocq proof assistant, ensuring correctness and enabling effective computation of interpolants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16445v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo F\'er\'ee, Ian Shillito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensionality and randomness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06961v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Arranging the bits of a random string or real into k columns of a two-dimensional array or higher dimensional structure is typically accompanied with loss in the Kolmogorov complexity of the columns, which depends on k. We quantify and characterize this phenomenon for arrays and trees and its relationship to negligible classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06961v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Barmpalias, Xiaoyan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity of deep computations via topology of function spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.00528v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use topological methods to study complexity of deep computations and limit computations. We use topology of function spaces, specifically, the classification Rosenthal compacta, to identify new complexity classes. We use the language of model theory, specifically, the concept of \emph{independence} from Shelah's classification theory, to translate between topology and computation. We use the theory of Rosenthal compacta to characterize approximablility of deep computations, both deterministically and probabilistically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.00528v4</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Due\~nez, Jos\'e Iovino, Tonatiuh Matos-Wiederhold, Luciano Salvetti, Franklin D. Tall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scott spectral gaps for trees are bounded</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07166v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a Borel class of trees, we show that there is a tree in that class whose Scott sentence is not too much more complicated than the definition of the class. In particular, if the class is definable by a $\Pi_\alpha$ sentence, then there is a model of Scott rank at most $\alpha + 2$. This gives another proof-and one that does not require first proving Vaught's conjecture for trees-of the fact that trees are not faithfully Borel complete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07166v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Harrison-Trainor, Thomas Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
