<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.RM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM</link>
    <description>q-fin.RM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 02:06:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the evolution of data breach reporting patterns and frequency in the United States: a cross-state analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04786v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the emergence of data breaches is crucial for cyber insurance. However, analyses of data breach frequency trends in the current literature lead to contradictory conclusions. We put forward that those discrepancies may be (at least partially) due to inconsistent data collection standards, as well as reporting patterns, over time and space. We set out to carefully control both. In this paper, we conduct a joint analysis of state Attorneys General's publications on data breaches across eight states (namely, California, Delaware, Indiana, Maine, Montana, North Dakota, Oregon, and Washington), all of which are subject to established data collection standards-namely, state data breach (mandatory) notification laws. Thanks to our explicit recognition of these notification laws, we are capable of modelling frequency of breaches in a consistent and comparable way over time. Hence, we are able to isolate and capture the complexities of reporting patterns, adequately estimate IBNRs, and yield a highly reliable assessment of historical frequency trends in data breaches. Our analysis also provides a comprehensive comparison of data breach frequency across the eight U.S. states, extending knowledge on state-specific differences in cyber risk, which has not been extensively discussed in the current literature. Furthermore, we uncover novel features not previously discussed in the literature, such as differences in cyber risk frequency trends between large and small data breaches. Overall, we find that the reporting delays are lengthening. We also elicit commonalities and heterogeneities in reporting patterns across states, severity levels, and time periods. After adequately estimating IBNRs, we find that frequency is relatively stable before 2020 and increasing after 2020. This is consistent across states. Implications of our findings for cyber insurance are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04786v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Avanzi (University of Melbourne), Xingyun Tan (University of Melbourne), Greg Taylor (UNSW Sydney), Bernard Wong (UNSW Sydney)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multilevel Stochastic Approximation Algorithm for Value-at-Risk and Expected Shortfall Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01207v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a multilevel stochastic approximation (MLSA) scheme for the computation of the value-at-risk (VaR) and expected shortfall (ES) of a financial loss, which can only be computed via simulations conditional on the realization of future risk factors. Thus, the problem of estimating its VaR and ES is nested in nature and can be viewed as an instance of stochastic approximation problems with biased innovations. In this framework, for a prescribed accuracy $\varepsilon$, the optimal complexity of a nested stochastic approximation algorithm is shown to be of order $\varepsilon^{-3}$. To estimate the VaR, our MLSA algorithm attains an optimal complexity of order $\varepsilon^{-2-\delta}$, where $\delta&lt;1$ is some parameter depending on the integrability degree of the loss, while to estimate the ES, it achieves an optimal complexity of order $\varepsilon^{-2}\left|\ln{\varepsilon}\right|^2$. Numerical studies of the joint evolution of the error rate and the execution time demonstrate how our MLSA algorithm regains a significant amount of the performance lost due to the nested nature of the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01207v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>St\'ephane Cr\'epey (LPSM), Noufel Frikha (CES), Azar Louzi (LPSM, CNRS, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elicitability and identifiability of tail risk measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14136v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tail risk measures are fully determined by the distribution of the underlying loss beyond its quantile at a certain level, with Value-at-Risk and Expected Shortfall being prime examples. They are induced by law-based risk measures, called their generators, evaluated on the tail distribution. This paper establishes joint identifiability and elicitability results of tail risk measures together with the corresponding quantile, provided that their generators are identifiable and elicitable, respectively. As an example, we establish the joint identifiability and elicitability of the tail expectile together with the quantile. The corresponding consistent scores constitute a novel class of weighted scores, nesting the known class of scores of Fissler and Ziegel for the Expected Shortfall together with the quantile. For statistical purposes, our results pave the way to easier model fitting for tail risk measures via regression and the generalized method of moments, but also model comparison and model validation in terms of established backtesting procedures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14136v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Fissler, Fangda Liu, Ruodu Wang, Linxiao Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
