<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.RM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM</link>
    <description>q-fin.RM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 02:54:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A multi-view contrastive learning framework for spatial embeddings in risk modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Incorporating spatial information, particularly those influenced by climate, weather, and demographic factors, is crucial for improving underwriting precision and enhancing risk management in insurance. However, spatial data are often unstructured, high-dimensional, and difficult to integrate into predictive models. Embedding methods are needed to convert spatial data into meaningful representations for modelling tasks. We propose a novel multi-view contrastive learning framework for generating spatial embeddings that combine information from multiple spatial data sources. To train the model, we construct a spatial dataset that merges satellite imagery and OpenStreetMap features across Europe. The framework aligns these spatial views with coordinate-based encodings, producing low-dimensional embeddings that capture both spatial structure and contextual similarity. Once trained, the model generates embeddings directly from latitude-longitude pairs, enabling any dataset with coordinates to be enriched with meaningful spatial features without requiring access to the original spatial inputs. In a case study on French real estate prices, we compare models trained on raw coordinates against those using our spatial embeddings as inputs. The embeddings consistently improve predictive accuracy across generalised linear, additive, and boosting models, while providing interpretable spatial effects and demonstrating transferability to unseen regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17954v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Freek Holvoet, Christopher Blier-Wong, Katrien Antonio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random processes for long-term market simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For long term investments, model portfolios are defined at the level of indexes, a setup known as Strategic Asset Allocation (SAA). The possible outcomes at a scale of a few decades can be obtained by Monte Carlo simulations, resulting in a probability density for the possible portfolio values at the investment horizon. Such studies are critical for long term wealth plannings, for example in the financial component of social insurances or in accumulated capital for retirement. The quality of the results depends on two inputs: the process used for the simulations and its parameters. The base model is a constant drift, a constant covariance and normal innovations, as pioneered by Bachelier. Beyond this model, this document presents in details a multivariate process that incorporate the most recent advances in the models for financial time series. This includes the negative correlations of the returns at a scale of a few years, the heteroskedasticity (i.e. the volatility' dynamics), and the fat tails and asymmetry for the distributions of returns. For the parameters, the quantitative outcomes depend critically on the estimate for the drift, because this is a non random contribution acting at each time step. Replacing the point forecast by a probabilistic forecast allows us to analyze the impact of the drift values, and then to incorporate this uncertainty in the Monte Carlo simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18125v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gilles Zumbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superhedging under Proportional Transaction Costs in Continuous Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the well-studied superhedging problem under proportional transaction costs in continuous time using the recently developed tools of set-valued stochastic analysis. By relying on a simple Black-Scholes-type market model for mid-prices and using continuous trading schemes, we define a dynamic family of superhedging sets in continuous time and express them in terms of set-valued integrals. We show that these sets, defined as subsets of Lebesgue spaces at different times, form a dynamic set-valued risk measure with multi-portfolio time-consistency. Finally, we transfer the problem formulation to a path-space setting and introduce approximate versions of superhedging sets that will involve relaxing the superhedging inequality, the superhedging probability, and the solvency requirement for the superhedging strategy with a predetermined error level. In this more technical framework, we are able to relate the approximate superhedging sets at different times by means of a set-valued Bellman's principle, which we believe will pave the way for a set-valued differential structure that characterizes the superhedging sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18169v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atiqah Almuzaini, \c{C}a\u{g}{\i}n Ararat, Jin Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A calibrated model of debt recycling with interest costs and tax shields: viability under different fiscal regimes and jurisdictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Debt recycling is a leveraged equity management strategy in which homeowners use accumulated home equity to finance investments, applying the resulting returns to accelerate mortgage repayment. We propose a novel framework to model equity and mortgage dynamics in presence of mortgage interest rates, borrowing costs on equity-backed credit lines, and tax shields arising from interest deductibility. The model is calibrated on three jurisdictions -- Australia, Germany, and Switzerland -- representing diverse interest rate environments and fiscal regimes. Results demonstrate that introducing positive interest rates without tax shields contracts success regions and lengthens repayment times, while tax shields partially reverse these effects by reducing effective borrowing costs and adding equity boosts from mortgage interest deductibility. Country-specific outcomes vary systematically, and rental properties consistently outperform owner-occupied housing due to mortgage interest deductibility provisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18614v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo von der Osten, Sabrina Aufiero, Pierpaolo Vivo, Fabio Caccioli, Silvia Bartolucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set risk measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18687v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the concept of set risk measures (SRMs), which are real-valued maps defined on the space of all non-empty, closed, and bounded sets of almost surely bounded random variables. Traditional risk measures typically operate on random variables, but SRMs extend this framework to sets of random variables. We establish an axiomatic scheme for SRMs, similar to classical risk measures but adapted for set operations. The main technical contribution is an axiomatic dual representation of convex SRMs by using regular, $\tau$-additive (for nets) measures on the unit ball of the dual space of essentially bounded random variables. We explore worst-case SRMs, which evaluate risk as the supremum of individual risks within a set, and provide a collection of examples illustrating the applicability of our framework to systemic risk, optimization, and decision-making under uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18687v3</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcelo Righi, Eduardo Horta, Marlon Moresco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified GARCH-Recurrent Neural Network in Financial Volatility Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09380v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we develop a unified volatility modeling framework that embeds GARCH dynamics directly within recurrent neural networks. We propose two interpretable hybrid architectures, GARCH-GRU and GARCH-LSTM, that integrate the GARCH(1,1) volatility update into the multiplicative gating structure of GRU and LSTM cells. This unified design preserves economically meaningful GARCH parameters while enabling the networks to learn nonlinear temporal dependencies in financial time series. Comprehensive out-of-sample evaluations across major U.S. equity indices show that both models consistently outperform classical GARCH specifications, pipeline-style hybrids, and neural baselines such as the Transformer across multiple metrics (MSE, MAE, SMAPE, and out-of-sample R\textsuperscript{2}). Within this family, the GARCH-GRU achieves the strongest accuracy-efficiency tradeoff, training nearly three times faster than GARCH-LSTM while maintaining comparable or superior forecasting accuracy under normal market conditions and delivering stable and economically plausible parameter estimates. The advantages persist during extreme market turbulence. In the COVID-19 stress period, both architectures retain superior forecasting accuracy and deliver well-calibrated 99 percent Value-at-Risk forecasts, achieving lower violation ratios and competitive Pinball losses relative to all benchmarks. Overall, the findings underscore the effectiveness of embedding GARCH dynamics within recurrent neural architectures, yielding models that are accurate, efficient, interpretable, and robust for real-world risk-aware volatility forecasting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09380v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyi Wei, Steve Yang, Zhenyu Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
