<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.RM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM</link>
    <description>q-fin.RM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 04:29:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Risk Variables From ESG Raw Data Using A Hierarchical Variable Selection Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Environmental, Social, and Governance (ESG) factors aim to provide non-financial insights into corporations. In this study, we investigate whether we can extract relevant ESG variables to assess corporate risk, as measured by logarithmic volatility. We propose a novel Hierarchical Variable Selection (HVS) algorithm to identify a parsimonious set of variables from raw data that are most relevant to risk. HVS is specifically designed for ESG datasets characterized by a tree structure with significantly more variables than observations. Our findings demonstrate that HVS achieves significantly higher performance than models using pre-aggregated ESG scores. Furthermore, when compared with traditional variable selection methods, HVS achieves superior explanatory power using a more parsimonious set of ESG variables. We illustrate the methodology using company data from various sectors of the US economy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18679v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi Chen, Zachary Feinstein, Ionut Florescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting Probability Distributions of Financial Returns with Deep Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study evaluates deep neural networks for forecasting probability distributions of financial returns. 1D convolutional neural networks (CNN) and Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) architectures are used to forecast parameters of three probability distributions: Normal, Student's t, and skewed Student's t. Using custom negative log-likelihood loss functions, distribution parameters are optimized directly. The models are tested on six major equity indices (S\&amp;P 500, BOVESPA, DAX, WIG, Nikkei 225, and KOSPI) using probabilistic evaluation metrics including Log Predictive Score (LPS), Continuous Ranked Probability Score (CRPS), and Probability Integral Transform (PIT). Results show that deep learning models provide accurate distributional forecasts and perform competitively with classical GARCH models for Value-at-Risk estimation. The LSTM with skewed Student's t distribution performs best across multiple evaluation criteria, capturing both heavy tails and asymmetry in financial returns. This work shows that deep neural networks are viable alternatives to traditional econometric models for financial risk assessment and portfolio management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18921v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Micha\'nk\'ow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracing Positional Bias in Financial Decision-Making: Mechanistic Insights from Qwen2.5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The growing adoption of large language models (LLMs) in finance exposes high-stakes decision-making to subtle, underexamined positional biases. The complexity and opacity of modern model architectures compound this risk. We present the first unified framework and benchmark that not only detects and quantifies positional bias in binary financial decisions but also pinpoints its mechanistic origins within open-source Qwen2.5-instruct models (1.5B--14B). Our empirical analysis covers a novel, finance-authentic dataset revealing that positional bias is pervasive, scale-sensitive, and prone to resurfacing under nuanced prompt designs and investment scenarios, with recency and primacy effects revealing new vulnerabilities in risk-laden contexts. Through transparent mechanistic interpretability, we map how and where bias emerges and propagates within the models to deliver actionable, generalizable insights across prompt types and scales. By bridging domain-specific audit with model interpretability, our work provides a new methodological standard for both rigorous bias diagnosis and practical mitigation, establishing essential guidance for responsible and trustworthy deployment of LLMs in financial systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18427v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Dimino, Krati Saxena, Bhaskarjit Sarmah, Stefano Pasquali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Systemic Risk Bailout: A PGO Approach Based on Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.05235v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the financial system, bailout strategies play a pivotal role in mitigating substantial losses resulting from systemic risk. However, the lack of a closed-form objective function to the optimal bailout problem poses significant challenges in its resolution. This paper conceptualizes the optimal bailout (capital injection) problem as a black-box optimization task, where the black box is modeled as a fixed-point system consistent with the E-N framework for measuring systemic risk in the financial system. To address this challenge, we propose a novel framework, "Prediction-Gradient-Optimization" (PGO). Within PGO, the Prediction employs a neural network to approximate and forecast the objective function implied by the black box, which can be completed offline; For the online usage, the Gradient step derives gradient information from this approximation, and the Optimization step uses a gradient projection algorithm to solve the problem effectively. Extensive numerical experiments highlight the effectiveness of the proposed approach in managing systemic risk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.05235v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuhua Xiao, Jiali Ma, Li Xia, Shushang Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
