<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.RM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM</link>
    <description>q-fin.RM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:01:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Financial Resilience Using Backward Stochastic Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07502v3 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the resilience rate as a measure of financial resilience. It captures the expected rate at which a dynamic risk measure recovers, i.e., bounces back, when the risk-acceptance set is breached. We develop the corresponding stochastic calculus by establishing representation theorems for expected time-derivatives of solutions to backward stochastic differential equations (BSDEs) with jumps, evaluated at stopping times. These results reveal that the resilience rate can be represented as a suitable expectation of the generator of a BSDE. We analyze the main properties of the resilience rate and the formal connection of these properties to the BSDE generator. We also introduce resilience-acceptance sets and study their properties in relation to both the resilience rate and the dynamic risk measure. We illustrate our results in several canonical financial examples and highlight their implications via the notion of resilience neutrality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07502v3</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roger J. A. Laeven, Matteo Ferrari, Emanuela Rosazza Gianin, Marco Zullino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Security under Heterogeneous Cyber-Risk Profiles and Contagion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cyber risk has become a critical financial threat in today's interconnected digital economy. This paper introduces a cyber-risk management framework for networked digital systems that combines the strategic behavior of players with contagion dynamics within a security game. We address the problem of optimally allocating cybersecurity resources across a network, focusing on the heterogeneous valuations of nodes by attackers and defenders, some areas may be of high interest to the attacker, while others are prioritized by the defender. We explore how this asymmetry drives attack and defense strategies and shapes the system's overall resilience. We extend a method to determine optimal resource allocation based on simple network metrics weighted by the defender's and attacker's risk profiles. We further propose risk measures based on contagion paths and analyze how propagation dynamics influence optimal defense strategies. Numerical experiments explore risk versus cost efficient frontiers varying network topologies and risk profiles, revealing patterns of resource allocation and cyber deception effects. These findings provide actionable insights for designing resilient digital infrastructures and mitigating systemic cyber risk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16805v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisa Botteghi, Martino S. Centonze, Davide Pastorello, Daniele Tantari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Enhanced Focal Loss Function to Mitigate Class Imbalance in Auto Insurance Fraud Detection with Explainable AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02283v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Detecting fraudulent auto-insurance claims remains a challenging classification problem, largely due to the extreme imbalance between legitimate and fraudulent cases. Standard learning algorithms tend to overfit to the majority class, resulting in poor detection of economically significant minority events. This paper proposes a structured three-stage training framework that integrates a convex surrogate of focal loss for stable initialization, a controlled non-convex intermediate loss to improve feature discrimination, and the standard focal loss to refine minority-class sensitivity. We derive conditions under which the surrogate retains convexity in the prediction space and show how this facilitates more reliable optimization when combined with deep sequential models. Using a proprietary auto-insurance dataset, the proposed method improves minority-class F1-scores and AUC relative to conventional focal-loss training and resampling baselines. The approach also provides interpretable feature-attribution patterns through SHAP analysis, offering transparency for actuarial and fraud-analytics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02283v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francis Boabang, Samuel Asante Gyamerah</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
