<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.RM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM</link>
    <description>q-fin.RM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.RM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 05:01:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Risk-Sharing Rules in Network-based Decentralized Insurance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05155v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies decentralized risk-sharing on networks. In particular, we consider a model where agents are nodes in a given network structure. Agents directly connected by edges in the network are referred to as friends. We study actuarially fair risk-sharing under the assumption that only friends can share risk, and we characterize the optimal signed linear risk-sharing rule in this network setting. Subsequently, we consider a special case of this model where all the friends of an agent take on an equal share of the agent's risk, and establish a connection to the graph Laplacian. Our results are illustrated with several examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05155v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heather N. Fogarty, Sooie-Hoe Loke, Nicholas F. Marshall, Enrique A. Thomann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jointly Exchangeable Collective Risk Models: Interaction, Structure, and Limit Theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06287v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a framework for systemic risk modeling in insurance portfolios using jointly exchangeable arrays, extending classical collective risk models to account for interactions. Joint exchangeability is a more general probabilistic symmetric than de Finetti's exchangeability, characterized by the Aldous-Hoover-Kallenberg representation. We establish central limit theorems that asymptotically capture total portfolio losses, providing a theoretical foundation for approximations in large portfolios and over long time horizons. These approximations are validated through simulation-based numerical experiments. Additionally, we analyze the impact of dependence on portfolio loss distributions, with a particular focus on tail behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06287v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Gaigall, Stefan Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
