<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC</link>
    <description>cs.CC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Polynomial Hierarchy does not collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The arithmetical hierarchy (AH) is similar to the polynomial hierarchy (PH). Unlike the PH, the AH does not collapse relative to any oracle. A language in the (k + 1)-st level of the AH is computable enumerable (c.e.) relative to the kth level. So, given an oracle in the kth level of the AH, we could use a black-box search to decide whether the input word is in the language. With very large padding arguments, i.e. the paddings grow faster than any relative to the level k of the AH computable function, we would construct a language contained in the k + 1 level of PH, if we use only a finite set of input words. From the oracle in AH, we would construct an analogue oracle at the kth level of PH. For the input words of the finite set, a word is in the language of AH, if and only if it is in the language of PH. And the input word is in the oracle set of AH, if and only if it is in the oracle of PH. As in the language of AH, we must apply a black-box search in the language of PH. So, we would also have exponentially many oracle queries in the language of PH. The PH does not collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18439v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reiner Czerwinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A linear bound for the size of the finite terminal assembly of a directed non-cooperative tile assembly system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The abstract tile assembly model (aTam) is a model of DNA self-assembly. Most of the studies focus on cooperative aTam where a form of synchronization between the tiles is possible. Simulating Turing machines is achievable in this context. Few results and constructions are known for the non-cooperative case (a variant of Wang tilings where assemblies do not need to cover the whole plane and some mismatches may occur).
  Introduced by P.E. Meunier and D. Regnault, efficient paths are a non-trivial construction for non-cooperative aTam. These paths of width nlog(n) are designed with n different tile types. Assembling them relies heavily on a form of ``non-determinism''. Indeed, the set of tiles may produced different finite terminal assemblies but they all contain the same efficient path. Directed non-cooperative aTam does not allow this non-determinism as only one assembly may be produced by a tile assembly system. This variant of aTam is the only one who was shown to be decidable.
  In this paper, we show that if the terminal assembly of a directed non-cooperative tile assembly system is finite then its width and length are of linear size according to the size of the tile assembly system. This result implies that the construction of efficient paths cannot be generalized to the directed case and that some computation must rely on a competition between different paths. It also implies that the construction of a square of width n using 2n-1 tiles types is asymptotically optimal. Moreover, we hope that the techniques introduced here will lead to a better comprehension of the non-directed case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18630v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergiu Ivanov, Damien Regnault</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derandomized Non-Abelian Homomorphism Testing in Low Soundness Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18998v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a randomness-efficient homomorphism test in the low soundness regime for functions, $f: G\to \mathbb{U}_t$, from an arbitrary finite group $G$ to $t\times t$ unitary matrices. We show that if such a function passes a derandomized Blum--Luby--Rubinfeld (BLR) test (using small-bias sets), then (i) it correlates with a function arising from a genuine homomorphism, and (ii) it has a non-trivial Fourier mass on a low-dimensional irreducible representation.
  In the full randomness regime, such a test for matrix-valued functions on finite groups implicitly appears in the works of Gowers and Hatami [Sbornik: Mathematics '17], and Moore and Russell [SIAM Journal on Discrete Mathematics '15]. Thus, our work can be seen as a near-optimal derandomization of their results. Our key technical contribution is a "degree-2 expander mixing lemma'' that shows that Gowers' $\mathrm{U}^2$ norm can be efficiently estimated by restricting it to a small-bias subset. Another corollary is a "derandomized'' version of a useful lemma due to Babai, Nikolov, and Pyber [SODA'08].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18998v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tushant Mittal, Sourya Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the formalization of the notion of an interactive algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19037v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An earlier paper gives an account of a quest for a satisfactory formalization of the classical informal notion of an algorithm. In this paper, an attempt is made to generalize the results of that quest to the informal notion of an interactive algorithm. The notion of an interactive proto-algorithm is introduced. Interactive algorithms are expected to be equivalence classes of interactive proto-algorithms under an appropriate equivalence relation. As in the non-interactive case, three equivalence relations are defined. Two of them are deemed to be bounds for an appropriate equivalence relation and the third is likely an appropriate one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19037v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. A. Middelburg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set Descriptive Complexity of Solvable Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent article, we introduced and studied a precise class of dynamical systems called solvable systems. These systems present a dynamic ruled by discontinuous ordinary differential equations with solvable right-hand terms and unique evolution. They correspond to a class of systems for which a transfinite method exist to compute the solution. We also presented several examples including a nontrivial one whose solution yields, at an integer time, a real encoding of the halting set for Turing machines; therefore showcasing that the behavior of solvable systems might describe ordinal Turing computations. In the current article, we study in more depth solvable systems, using tools from descriptive set theory. By establishing a correspondence with the class of well-founded trees, we construct a coanalytic ranking over the set of solvable functions and discuss its relation with other existing rankings for differentiable functions, in particular with the Kechris-Woodin, Denjoy and Zalcwasser ranking. We prove that our ranking is unbounded below the first uncountable ordinal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19304v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gozzi Riccardo, Bournez Olivier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Computational Complexity of Formal Reasoning for Encoder-Only Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18548v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate challenges and possibilities of formal reasoning for encoder-only transformers (EOT), meaning sound and complete methods for verifying or interpreting behaviour. In detail, we condense related formal reasoning tasks in the form of a naturally occurring satisfiability problem (SAT). We find that SAT is undecidable if we consider EOT, commonly considered in the expressiveness community. Furthermore, we identify practical scenarios where SAT is decidable and establish corresponding complexity bounds. Besides trivial cases, we find that quantized EOT, namely those restricted by some fixed-width arithmetic, lead to the decidability of SAT due to their limited attention capabilities. However, the problem remains difficult, as we establish those scenarios where SAT is NEXPTIME-hard and those where we can show that it is solvable in NEXPTIME for quantized EOT. To complement our theoretical results, we put our findings and their implications in the overall perspective of formal reasoning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18548v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco S\"alzer, Eric Alsmann, Martin Lange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Bipartite Matching is in NC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we study the parallel complexity of the Euclidean minimum-weight perfect matching (EWPM) problem. Here our graph is the complete bipartite graph $G$ on two sets of points $A$ and $B$ in $\mathbb{R}^2$ and the weight of each edge is the Euclidean distance between the corresponding points. The weighted perfect matching problem on general bipartite graphs is known to be in RNC [Mulmuley, Vazirani, and Vazirani, 1987], and Quasi-NC [Fenner, Gurjar, and Thierauf, 2016]. Both of these results work only when the weights are of $O(\log n)$ bits. It is a long-standing open question to show the problem to be in NC.
  First, we show that for EWPM, a linear number of bits of approximation is required to distinguish between the minimum-weight perfect matching and other perfect matchings. Next, we show that the EWPM problem that allows up to $\frac{1}{poly(n)}$ additive error, is in NC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18833v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujoy Bhore, Sarfaraz Equbal, Rohit Gurjar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Structural Complexity Landscape of Finding Balance-Fair Shortest Paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18866v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the parameterized complexity of finding shortest s-t-paths with an additional fairness requirement. The task is to compute a shortest path in a vertex-colored graph where each color appears (roughly) equally often in the solution. We provide a complete picture of the parameterized complexity landscape of the problem with respect to structural parameters by showing a tetrachotomy including polynomial kernels, fixed-parameter tractability, XP-time algorithms (and W[1]-hardness), and para-NP-hardness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18866v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Bentert, Leon Kellerhals, Rolf Niedermeier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pessimism of the Will, Optimism of the Intellect: Fair Protocols with Malicious but Rational Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fairness is a desirable and crucial property of many protocols that handle, for instance, exchanges of message.
  It states that if at least one agent engaging in the protocol is honest, then either the protocol will unfold correctly and fulfill its intended goal for all participants, or it will fail for everyone.
  In this work, we present a game-based framework for the study of fairness protocols, that does not define a priori an attacker model.
  It is based on the notion of strong secure equilibria, and leverages the conceptual and algorithmic toolbox of game theory.
  In the case of finite games, we provide decision procedures with tight complexity bounds for determining whether a protocol is immune to nefarious attacks from a coalition of participants, and whether such a protocol could exist based on the underlying graph structure and objectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18958v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'eonard Brice, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Raskin, Mathieu Sassolas, Guillaume Scerri, Marie van den Bogaard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse High Dimensional Expanders via Local Lifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High dimensional expanders (HDXs) are a hypergraph generalization of expander graphs. They are extensively studied in the math and TCS communities due to their many applications. Like expander graphs, HDXs are especially interesting for applications when they are bounded degree, namely, if the number of edges adjacent to every vertex is bounded. However, only a handful of constructions are known to have this property, all of which rely on non-trivial algebraic techniques. In particular, no random or combinatorial construction of bounded degree HDXs is known. As a result, our understanding of these objects is limited.
  The degree of an $i$-face in an HDX is the number of $(i+1)$-faces containing it. In this work we construct HDXs whose higher dimensional faces have bounded degree. This is done by giving an elementary and deterministic algorithm that takes as input a regular $k$-dimensional HDX $X$ and outputs another $k$-dimensional HDX $\widehat{X}$ with twice as many vertices. While the degree of vertices in $\widehat{X}$ grows, the degree of the $(k-1)$-faces in $\widehat{X}$ stays the same. As a result, we obtain a new `algebra-free' construction of HDXs whose $(k-1)$-face degree is bounded.
  Our algorithm is based on a simple and natural generalization of the construction by Bilu and Linial (Combinatorica, 2006), which build expanders using lifts coming from edge signings. Our construction is based on local lifts of HDXs, where a local lift is a complex whose top-level links are lifts of links in the original complex. We demonstrate that a local lift of an HDX is an HDX in many cases.
  In addition, combining local lifts with existing bounded degree constructions creates new families of bounded degree HDXs with significantly different links than before. We use this technique to construct bounded degree high dimensional expanders with links that have arbitrarily large diameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19191v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Inbar Ben Yaacov, Yotam Dikstein, Gal Maor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Framework for Universality in Physics, Computer Science, and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06851v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Turing machines and spin models share a notion of universality according to which some simulate all others. Is there a theory of universality that captures this notion? We set up a categorical framework for universality which includes as instances universal Turing machines, universal spin models, NP completeness, top of a preorder, denseness of a subset, and more. By identifying necessary conditions for universality, we show that universal spin models cannot be finite. We also characterize when universality can be distinguished from a trivial one and use it to show that universal Turing machines are non-trivial in this sense. Our framework allows not only to compare universalities within each instance, but also instances themselves. We leverage a Fixed Point Theorem inspired by a result of Lawvere to establish that universality and negation give rise to unreachability (such as uncomputability). As such, this work sets the basis for a unified approach to universality and invites the study of further examples within the framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06851v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.32408/compositionality-6-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Compositionality 6, 3 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tom\'a\v{s} Gonda, Tobias Reinhart, Sebastian Stengele, Gemma De les Coves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumerating Minimal Defensive Alliances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11963v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the task of enumerating (and counting) locally and globally minimal defensive alliances in graphs. We consider general graphs as well as special graph classes. From an input-sensitive perspective, our presented algorithms are mostly optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11963v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhidan Feng, Henning Fernau, Kevin Mann</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
