<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC</link>
    <description>cs.CC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 02:27:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>CSPs with Few Alien Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The constraint satisfaction problem asks to decide if a set of constraints over a relational structure $\mathcal{A}$ is satisfiable (CSP$(\mathcal{A})$). We consider CSP$(\mathcal{A} \cup \mathcal{B})$ where $\mathcal{A}$ is a structure and $\mathcal{B}$ is an alien structure, and analyse its (parameterized) complexity when at most $k$ alien constraints are allowed. We establish connections and obtain transferable complexity results to several well-studied problems that previously escaped classification attempts. Our novel approach, utilizing logical and algebraic methods, yields an FPT versus pNP dichotomy for arbitrary finite structures and sharper dichotomies for Boolean structures and first-order reducts of $(\mathbb{N},=)$ (equality CSPs), together with many partial results for general $\omega$-categorical structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12909v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Jonsson, Victor Lagerkvist, George Osipov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A parametric version of the Hilbert Nullstellensatz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hilbert's Nullstellensatz is a fundamental result in algebraic geometry that gives a necessary and sufficient condition for a finite collection of multivariate polynomials to have a common zero in an algebraically closed field. Associated with this result, there is the computational problem HN of determining whether a system of polynomials with coefficients in the field of rational numbers has a common zero over the field of algebraic numbers.
  In an influential paper, Koiran showed that HN can be determined in the polynomial hierarchy assuming the Generalised Riemann Hypothesis (GRH). More precisely, he showed that HN lies in the complexity class AM under GRH. In a later work he generalised this result by showing that the problem DIM, which asks to determine the dimension of the set of solutions of a given polynomial system, also lies in AM subject to GRH.
  In this paper we study the solvability of polynomial equations over arbitrary algebraically closed fields of characteristic zero. Up to isomorphism, every such field is the algebraic closure of a field of rational functions. We thus formulate a parametric version of HN, called HNP, in which the input is a system of polynomials with coefficients in a function field $\mathbb{Q}(\mathbf{x})$ and the task is to determine whether the polynomials have a common zero in the algebraic closure $\overline{\mathbb{Q}(\mathbf{x})}$.
  We observe that Koiran's proof that DIM lies in AM can be interpreted as a randomised polynomial-time reduction of DIM to HNP, followed by an argument that HNP lies in AM. Our main contribution is a self-contained proof that HNP lies in AM that follows the same basic idea as Koiran's argument -- namely random instantiation of the parameters -- but whose justification is purely algebraic, relying on a parametric version of Hilbert's Nullstellensatz, and avoiding recourse to semi-algebraic geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13027v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rida Ait El Manssour, Nikhil Balaji, Klara Nosan, Mahsa Shirmohammadi, James Worrell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A study of distributional complexity measures for Boolean functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12995v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A number of complexity measures for Boolean functions have previously been introduced. These include (1) sensitivity, (2) block sensitivity, (3) witness complexity, (4) subcube partition complexity and (5) algorithmic complexity. Each of these is concerned with "worst-case" inputs. It has been shown that there is "asymptotic separation" between these complexity measures and very recently, due to the work of Huang, it has been established that they are all "polynomially related". In this paper, we study the notion of distributional complexity where the input bits are independent and one considers all of the above notions in expectation. We obtain a number of results concerning distributional complexity measures, among others addressing the above concepts of "asymptotic separation" and being "polynomially related" in this context. We introduce a new distributional complexity measure, local witness complexity, which only makes sense in the distributional context and we also study a new version of algorithmic complexity which involves partial information. Many interesting examples are presented including some related to percolation. The latter connects a number of the recent developments in percolation theory over the last two decades with the study of complexity measures in theoretical computer science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12995v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurin K\"ohler-Schindler, Jeffrey E. Steif</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Search Trees and the Intermezzo Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18645v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The last in-tree recognition problem asks whether a given spanning tree can be derived by connecting each vertex with its rightmost left neighbor of some search ordering. In this study, we demonstrate that the last-in-tree recognition problem for Generic Search is $\mathsf{NP}$-complete. We utilize this finding to strengthen a complexity result from order theory. Given a partial order $\pi$ and a set of triples, the $\mathsf{NP}$-complete intermezzo problem asks for a linear extension of $\pi$ where each first element of a triple is not between the other two. We show that this problem remains $\mathsf{NP}$-complete even when the Hasse diagram of the partial order forms a tree of bounded height. In contrast, we give an $\mathsf{XP}$-algorithm for the problem when parameterized by the width of the partial order. Furthermore, we show that $\unicode{x2013}$ under the assumption of the Exponential Time Hypothesis $\unicode{x2013}$ the running time of this algorithm is asymptotically optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18645v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Beisegel, Ekkehard K\"ohler, Fabienne Ratajczak, Robert Scheffler, Martin Strehler</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
