<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC</link>
    <description>cs.CC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 04:05:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Reducibility among NP-Hard graph problems and boundary classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many NP-hard graph problems become easy for some classes of graphs, such as coloring is easy for bipartite graphs, but NP-hard in general. So we can ask question like when does a hard problem become easy? What is the minimum substructure for which the problem remains hard? We use the notion of boundary classes to study such questions. In this paper, we introduce a method for transforming the boundary class of one NP-hard graph problem into a boundary class for another problem. If $\Pi$ and $\Gamma$ are two NP-hard graph problems where $\Pi$ is reducible to $\Gamma$, we transform a boundary class of $\Pi$ into a boundary class of $\Gamma$. More formally if $\Pi$ is reducible to $\Gamma$, where the reduction is bijective and it maps hereditary classes of graphs to hereditary classes of graphs, then $X$ is a boundary class of $\Pi$ if and only if the image of $X$ under the reduction is a boundary class of $\Gamma$. This gives us a relationship between boundary classes and reducibility among several NP-hard problems. To show the strength of our main result, we apply our theorem to obtain some previously unknown boundary classes for a few graph problems namely; vertex-cover, clique, traveling-salesperson, bounded-degree-spanning-tree, subgraph-isomorphism and clique-cover.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14553v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Syed Mujtaba Hassan, Shahid Hussain, Abdul Samad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depth-first search for tensor rank and border rank over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14676v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an $O^*\left(|\mathbb{F}|^{(R-n_*)\left(\sum_d n_d\right)+n_*}\right)$-time algorithm for determining whether a tensor of shape $n_0\times\dots\times n_{D-1}$ over a finite field $\mathbb{F}$ has rank $\le R$, where $n_*:=\max_d n_d$; we assume without loss of generality that $\forall d:n_d\le R$. We also extend this problem to its border rank analog, i.e., determining tensor rank over rings of the form $\mathbb{F}[x]/(x^H)$, and give an $O^*\left(|\mathbb{F}|^{H\sum_{1\le r\le R} \sum_d \min(r,n_d)}\right)$-time algorithm. Both of our algorithms use polynomial space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14676v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Approximability of Satisfiable $k$-CSPs: VI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove local and global inverse theorems for general $3$-wise correlations over pairwise-connected distributions. Let $\mu$ be a distribution over $\Sigma \times \Gamma \times \Phi$ such that the supports of $\mu_{xy}$, $\mu_{xz}$, and $\mu_{yz}$ are all connected, and let $f: \Sigma^n \to \mathbb{C}$, $g: \Gamma^n \to \mathbb{C}$, $h: \Phi^n \to \mathbb{C}$ be $1$-bounded functions satisfying \[ \left|\mathbb{E}_{(x,y,z) \sim \mu^{\otimes n}}[f(x)g(y)h(z)]\right| \geq \varepsilon. \] In this setting, our local inverse theorem asserts that there is $\delta :=\textsf{exp}(-\varepsilon^{-O_{\mu}(1)})$ such that with probability at least $\delta$, a random restriction of $f$ down to $\delta n$ coordinates $\delta$-correlates to a product function. To get a global inverse theorem, we prove a restriction inverse theorem for general product functions, stating that if a random restriction of $f$ down to $\delta n$ coordinates is $\delta$-correlated with a product function with probability at least $\delta$, then $f$ is $2^{-\textsf{poly}(\log(1/\delta))}$-correlated with a function of the form $L\cdot P$, where $L$ is a function of degree $\textsf{poly}(1/\delta)$, $\|L\|_2\leq 1$, and $P$ is a product function.
  We show applications to property testing and to additive combinatorics. In particular, we show the following result via a density increment argument. Let $\Sigma$ be a finite set and $S \subseteq \Sigma \times \Sigma \times \Sigma$ such that: (1) $(x, x, x) \in S$ for all $x \in S$, and (2) the supports of $S_{xy}$, $S_{xz}$, and $S_{yz}$ are all connected. Then, any set $A \subseteq \Sigma^n$ with $|\Sigma|^{-n}|A| \geq \Omega((\log \log \log n)^{-c})$ contains $x, y, z \in A$, not all equal, such that $(x_i,y_i,z_i) \in S$ for all $i$. This gives the first reasonable bounds for the restricted 3-AP problem over finite fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15133v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amey Bhangale, Subhash Khot, Yang P. Liu, Dor Minzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Approximability of Satisfiable $k$-CSPs: VII</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\Sigma_1,\ldots,\Sigma_k$ be finite alphabets, and let $\mu$ be a distribution over $\Sigma_1 \times \dots \times \Sigma_k$ in which the probability of each atom is at least $\alpha$. We prove that if $\mu$ does not admit Abelian embeddings, and $f_i: \Sigma_i \to \mathbb{C}$ are $1$-bounded functions (for $i=1,\ldots,k$) such that \[ \left|\mathbb{E}_{(x_1,\dots,x_k) \sim \mu^{\otimes n}}\Big[f_1(x_1) \dots f_k(x_k)\Big]\right| \geq \varepsilon, \] then there exists $L\colon \Sigma_1^n\to\mathbb{C}$ of degree at most $d$ and $\|L\|_2\leq 1$ such that $|\langle f_1, L\rangle|\geq \delta$, where $d$ and $\delta&gt;0$ depend only on $k, \alpha$ and $\varepsilon$. This answers the analytic question posed by Bhangale, Khot, and Minzer (STOC 2022). We also prove several extensions of this result that are useful in subsequent applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15136v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amey Bhangale, Subhash Khot, Yang P. Liu, Dor Minzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparsifying Suprema of Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14664v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a dimension-independent sparsification result for suprema of centered Gaussian processes: Let $T$ be any (possibly infinite) bounded set of vectors in $\mathbb{R}^n$, and let $\{{\boldsymbol{X}}_t\}_{t\in T}$ be the canonical Gaussian process on $T$. We show that there is an $O_\varepsilon(1)$-size subset $S \subseteq T$ and a set of real values $\{c_s\}_{s \in S}$ such that $\sup_{s \in S} \{{\boldsymbol{X}}_s + c_s\}$ is an $\varepsilon$-approximator of $\sup_{t \in T} {\boldsymbol{X}}_t$. Notably, the size of $S$ is completely independent of both the size of $T$ and of the ambient dimension $n$.
  We use this to show that every norm is essentially a junta when viewed as a function over Gaussian space: Given any norm $\nu(x)$ on $\mathbb{R}^n$, there is another norm $\psi(x)$ which depends only on the projection of $x$ along $O_\varepsilon(1)$ directions, for which $\psi({\boldsymbol{g}})$ is a multiplicative $(1 \pm \varepsilon)$-approximation of $\nu({\boldsymbol{g}})$ with probability $1-\varepsilon$ for ${\boldsymbol{g}} \sim N(0,I_n)$.
  We also use our sparsification result for suprema of centered Gaussian processes to give a sparsification lemma for convex sets of bounded geometric width: Any intersection of (possibly infinitely many) halfspaces in $\mathbb{R}^n$ that are at distance $O(1)$ from the origin is $\varepsilon$-close, under $N(0,I_n)$, to an intersection of only $O_\varepsilon(1)$ many halfspaces.
  We describe applications to agnostic learning and tolerant property testing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14664v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anindya De, Shivam Nadimpalli, Ryan O'Donnell, Rocco A. Servedio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ex-post Stability under Two-Sided Matching: Complexity and Characterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14821v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A probabilistic approach to the stable matching problem has been identified as an important research area with several important open problems. When considering random matchings, ex-post stability is a fundamental stability concept. A prominent open problem is characterizing ex-post stability and establishing its computational complexity. We investigate the computational complexity of testing ex-post stability. Our central result is that when either side has ties in the preferences/priorities, testing ex-post stability is NP-complete. The result even holds if both sides have dichotomous preferences. On the positive side, we give an algorithm using an integer programming approach, that can determine a decomposition with a maximum probability of being weakly stable. We also consider stronger versions of ex-post stability (in particular robust ex-post stability and ex-post strong stability) and prove that they can be tested in polynomial time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14821v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haris Aziz, Gergely Cs\'aji, P\'eter Bir\'o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasonable Bounds for Combinatorial Lines of Length Three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15137v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that any subset $A \subseteq [3]^n$ with $3^{-n}|A| \ge (\log\log\log\log n)^{-c}$ contains a combinatorial line of length $3$, i.e., $x, y, z \in A$, not all equal, with $x_i=y_i=z_i$ or $(x_i,y_i,z_i)=(0,1,2)$ for all $i = 1, 2, \dots, n$. This improves on the previous best bound of $3^{-n}|A| \ge \Omega((\log^* n)^{-1/2})$ of [D.H.J. Polymath, Ann. of Math. 2012].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15137v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amey Bhangale, Subhash Khot, Yang P. Liu, Dor Minzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Note On The Natural Range Of Unambiguous-SAT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.14779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.14779v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss the natural range of the Unambiguous-SAT problem with respect to the number of clauses. We prove that for a given Boolean formula in precise conjunctive normal form with n variables, there exist functions f(n) and g(n) such that if the number of clauses is greater than f(n) then the formula does not have a satisfying truth assignment and if the number of clauses is greater than g(n) then the formula either has a unique satisfying truth assignment or no satisfying truth assignment. The interval between functions f(n) and g(n) is the natural range of the Unambiguous-SAT problem. We also provide several counting rules and an algorithm that determine the unsatisfiability of some formulas in polynomial time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.14779v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tayfun Pay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Chromatic Number of Kneser Hypergraphs via Consensus Division</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09016v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the Consensus Division theorem implies lower bounds on the chromatic number of Kneser hypergraphs, offering a novel proof for a result of Alon, Frankl, and Lov\'{a}sz (Trans. Amer. Math. Soc., 1986) and for its generalization by K\v{r}\'{\i}\v{z} (Trans. Amer. Math. Soc., 1992). Our approach is applied to study the computational complexity of the total search problem Kneser$^p$, which given a succinct representation of a coloring of a $p$-uniform Kneser hypergraph with fewer colors than its chromatic number, asks to find a monochromatic hyperedge. We prove that for every prime $p$, the Kneser$^p$ problem with an extended access to the input coloring is efficiently reducible to a quite weak approximation of the Consensus Division problem with $p$ shares. In particular, for $p=2$, the problem is efficiently reducible to any non-trivial approximation of the Consensus Halving problem on normalized monotone functions. We further show that for every prime $p$, the Kneser$^p$ problem lies in the complexity class $\mathsf{PPA}$-$p$. As an application, we establish limitations on the complexity of the Kneser$^p$ problem, restricted to colorings with a bounded number of colors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09016v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ishay Haviv</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Low-Degree Truncation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08133v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the following basic, and very broad, statistical problem: Given a known high-dimensional distribution ${\cal D}$ over $\mathbb{R}^n$ and a collection of data points in $\mathbb{R}^n$, distinguish between the two possibilities that (i) the data was drawn from ${\cal D}$, versus (ii) the data was drawn from ${\cal D}|_S$, i.e. from ${\cal D}$ subject to truncation by an unknown truncation set $S \subseteq \mathbb{R}^n$.
  We study this problem in the setting where ${\cal D}$ is a high-dimensional i.i.d. product distribution and $S$ is an unknown degree-$d$ polynomial threshold function (one of the most well-studied types of Boolean-valued function over $\mathbb{R}^n$). Our main results are an efficient algorithm when ${\cal D}$ is a hypercontractive distribution, and a matching lower bound:
  $\bullet$ For any constant $d$, we give a polynomial-time algorithm which successfully distinguishes ${\cal D}$ from ${\cal D}|_S$ using $O(n^{d/2})$ samples (subject to mild technical conditions on ${\cal D}$ and $S$);
  $\bullet$ Even for the simplest case of ${\cal D}$ being the uniform distribution over $\{+1, -1\}^n$, we show that for any constant $d$, any distinguishing algorithm for degree-$d$ polynomial threshold functions must use $\Omega(n^{d/2})$ samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08133v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anindya De, Huan Li, Shivam Nadimpalli, Rocco A. Servedio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Tree Canonization using polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10338v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graph Isomorphism (GI) is a fundamental algorithmic problem. Amongst graph classes for which the computational complexity of GI has been resolved, trees are arguably the most fundamental. Tree Isomorphism is complete for deterministic logspace, a tiny subclass of polynomial time, by Lindell's result. Over three decades ago, he devised a deterministic logspace algorithm that computes a string which is a canon for the input tree -- two trees are isomorphic precisely when their canons are identical.
  Inspired by Miller-Reif's reduction of Tree Isomorphism to Polynomial Identity Testing, we present a new logspace algorithm for tree canonization fundamentally different from Lindell's algorithm. Our algorithm computes a univariate polynomial as canon for an input tree, based on the classical Eisenstein's criterion for the irreducibility of univariate polynomials. This can be implemented in logspace by invoking the well known Buss et al. algorithm for arithmetic formula evaluation. However, we have included in the appendix a simpler self-contained proof showing that arithmetic formula evaluation is in logspace.
  This algorithm is conceptually very simple, avoiding the delicate case analysis and complex recursion that constitute the core of Lindell's algorithm. We illustrate the adaptability of our algorithm by extending it to a couple of other classes of graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10338v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Arvind, Samir Datta, Salman Faris, Asif Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost-catalytic Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07208v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Designing algorithms for space bounded models with restoration requirements on the space used by the algorithm is an important challenge posed about the catalytic computation model introduced by Buhrman et al. (2014). Motivated by the scenarios where we do not need to restore unless is useful, we define $ACL(A)$ to be the class of languages that can be accepted by almost-catalytic Turing machines with respect to $A$ (which we call the catalytic set), that uses at most $c\log n$ work space and $n^c$ catalytic space.
  We show that if there are almost-catalytic algorithms for a problem with catalytic set as $A \subseteq \Sigma^*$ and its complement respectively, then the problem can be solved by a ZPP algorithm. Using this, we derive that to design catalytic algorithms, it suffices to design almost-catalytic algorithms where the catalytic set is the set of strings of odd weight ($PARITY$). Towards this, we consider two complexity measures of the set $A$ which are maximized for $PARITY$ - random projection complexity (${\cal R}(A)$) and the subcube partition complexity (${\cal P}(A)$).
  By making use of error-correcting codes, we show that for all $k \ge 1$, there is a language $A_k \subseteq \Sigma^*$ such that $DSPACE(n^k) \subseteq ACL(A_k)$ where for every $m \ge 1$, $\mathcal{R}(A_k \cap \{0,1\}^m) \ge \frac{m}{4}$ and $\mathcal{P}(A_k \cap \{0,1\}^m)=2^{m/4}$. This contrasts the catalytic machine model where it is unclear if it can accept all languages in $DSPACE(\log^{1+\epsilon} n)$ for any $\epsilon &gt; 0$.
  Improving the partition complexity of the catalytic set $A$ further, we show that for all $k \ge 1$, there is a $A_k \subseteq \{0,1\}^*$ such that $\mathsf{DSPACE}(\log^k n) \subseteq ACL(A_k)$ where for every $m \ge 1$, $\mathcal{R}(A_k \cap \{0,1\}^m) \ge \frac{m}{4}$ and $\mathcal{P}(A_k \cap \{0,1\}^m)=2^{m/4+\Omega(\log m)}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07208v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sagar Bisoyi, Krishnamoorthy Dinesh, Bhabya Deep Rai, Jayalal Sarma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Convex Truncation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03146v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the basic statistical problem of testing whether normally distributed $n$-dimensional data has been truncated, i.e. altered by only retaining points that lie in some unknown truncation set $S \subseteq \mathbb{R}^n$. As our main algorithmic results,
  (1) We give a computationally efficient $O(n)$-sample algorithm that can distinguish the standard normal distribution $N(0,I_n)$ from $N(0,I_n)$ conditioned on an unknown and arbitrary convex set $S$.
  (2) We give a different computationally efficient $O(n)$-sample algorithm that can distinguish $N(0,I_n)$ from $N(0,I_n)$ conditioned on an unknown and arbitrary mixture of symmetric convex sets.
  These results stand in sharp contrast with known results for learning or testing convex bodies with respect to the normal distribution or learning convex-truncated normal distributions, where state-of-the-art algorithms require essentially $n^{\sqrt{n}}$ samples. An easy argument shows that no finite number of samples suffices to distinguish $N(0,I_n)$ from an unknown and arbitrary mixture of general (not necessarily symmetric) convex sets, so no common generalization of results (1) and (2) above is possible.
  We also prove that any algorithm (computationally efficient or otherwise) that can distinguish $N(0,I_n)$ from $N(0,I_n)$ conditioned on an unknown symmetric convex set must use $\Omega(n)$ samples. This shows that the sample complexity of each of our algorithms is optimal up to a constant factor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03146v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anindya De, Shivam Nadimpalli, Rocco A. Servedio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
