<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC</link>
    <description>cs.CC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Lower Bounds for Local Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Local search is a powerful heuristic in optimization and computer science, the complexity of which has been studied in the white box and black box models. In the black box model, we are given a graph $G = (V,E)$ and oracle access to a function $f : V \to \mathbb{R}$. The local search problem is to find a vertex $v$ that is a local minimum, i.e. with $f(v) \leq f(u)$ for all $(u,v) \in E$, using as few queries to the oracle as possible.
  We show that if a graph $G$ admits a lazy, irreducible, and reversible Markov chain with stationary distribution $\pi$, then the randomized query complexity of local search on $G$ is $\Omega\left( \frac{\sqrt{n}}{t_{mix} \cdot \exp(3\sigma)}\right)$, where $t_{mix}$ is the mixing time of the chain and $\sigma = \max_{u,v \in V(G)} \frac{\pi(v)}{\pi(u)}.$ This theorem formally establishes a connection between the query complexity of local search and the mixing time of the fastest mixing Markov chain for the given graph. We also get several corollaries that lower bound the complexity as a function of the spectral gap, one of which slightly improves a result from prior work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06248v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simina Br\^anzei, Nicholas J. Recker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The metric Menger problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05630v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a generalization of the well-known disjoint paths problem which we call the metric Menger problem, denoted MM(r,k), where one is given two subsets of a graph and must decide whether they can be connected by $k$ paths of pairwise distance at least $r$. We prove that this problem is NP-complete for every $r\geq 3$ and $k\geq 2$ by giving a reduction from 3SAT. This resolves a conjecture recently stated by Georgakopoulos and Papasoglu. On the other hand, we show that the problem is in XP when parameterised by treewidth and maximum degree by observing that it is `locally checkable'. In the case $r\leq 3$, we prove that it suffices to parameterise by treewidth. We also state some open questions relating to this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05630v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'ulia Balig\'acs, Joseph MacManus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arborescences and Shortest Path Trees when Colors Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06580v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Color-constrained subgraph problems are those where we are given an edge-colored (directed or undirected) graph and the task is to find a specific type of subgraph, like a spanning tree, an arborescence, a single-source shortest path tree, a perfect matching etc., with constraints on the number of edges of each color. Some of these problems, like color-constrained spanning tree, have elegant solutions and some of them, like color-constrained perfect matching, are longstanding open questions. In this work, we study color-constrained arborescences and shortest path trees. Computing a color-constrained shortest path tree on weighted digraphs turns out to be NP-hard in general but polynomial-time solvable when all cycles have positive weight. This polynomial-time solvability is due to the fact that the solution space is essentially the set of all color-constrained arborescences of a directed acyclic subgraph of the original graph. While finding color-constrained arborescence of digraphs is NP-hard in general, we give efficient algorithms when the input graph is acyclic. Consequently, a color-constrained shortest path tree on weighted digraphs having only positive weight cycles can be efficiently computed. Our algorithms also generalize to the problem of finding a color-constrained shortest path tree with minimum total weight. En route, we sight nice connections to colored matroids and color-constrained bases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06580v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. S. Ardra, Jasine Babu, Kritika Kashyap, R. Krithika, Sreejith K. Pallathumadam, Deepak Rajendraprasad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Balanced Substructures in Bicolored Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06608v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An edge-colored graph is said to be balanced if it has an equal number of edges of each color. Given a graph $G$ whose edges are colored using two colors and a positive integer $k$, the objective in the Edge Balanced Connected Subgraph problem is to determine if $G$ has a balanced connected subgraph containing at least $k$ edges. We first show that this problem is NP-complete and remains so even if the solution is required to be a tree or a path. Then, we focus on the parameterized complexity of Edge Balanced Connected Subgraph and its variants (where the balanced subgraph is required to be a path/tree) with respect to $k$ as the parameter. Towards this, we show that if a graph has a balanced connected subgraph/tree/path of size at least $k$, then it has one of size at least $k$ and at most $f(k)$ where $f$ is a linear function. We use this result combined with dynamic programming algorithms based on color coding and representative sets to show that Edge Balanced Connected Subgraph and its variants are FPT. Further, using polynomial-time reductions to the Multilinear Monomial Detection problem, we give faster randomized FPT algorithms for the problems. In order to describe these reductions, we define a combinatorial object called relaxed-subgraph. We define this object in such a way that balanced connected subgraphs, trees and paths are relaxed-subgraphs with certain properties. This object is defined in the spirit of branching walks known for the Steiner Tree problem and may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06608v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. S. Ardra, R. Krithika, Saket Saurabh, Roohani Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$C_{2k+1}$-coloring of bounded-diameter graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06694v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a fixed graph $H$, in the graph homomorphism problem, denoted by $Hom(H)$, we are given a graph $G$ and we have to determine whether there exists an edge-preserving mapping $\varphi: V(G) \to V(H)$. Note that $Hom(C_3)$, where $C_3$ is the cycle of length $3$, is equivalent to $3$-Coloring. The question whether $3$-Coloring is polynomial-time solvable on diameter-$2$ graphs is a well-known open problem. In this paper we study the $Hom(C_{2k+1})$ problem on bounded-diameter graphs for $k\geq 2$, so we consider all other odd cycles than $C_3$. We prove that for $k\geq 2$, the $Hom(C_{2k+1})$ problem is polynomial-time solvable on diameter-$(k+1)$ graphs -- note that such a result for $k=1$ would be precisely a polynomial-time algorithm for $3$-Coloring of diameter-$2$ graphs.
  Furthermore, we give subexponential-time algorithms for diameter-$(k+2)$ and -$(k+3)$ graphs.
  We complement these results with a lower bound for diameter-$(2k+2)$ graphs -- in this class of graphs the $Hom(C_{2k+1})$ problem is NP-hard and cannot be solved in subexponential-time, unless the ETH fails.
  Finally, we consider another direction of generalizing $3$-Coloring on diameter-$2$ graphs. We consider other target graphs $H$ than odd cycles but we restrict ourselves to diameter $2$. We show that if $H$ is triangle-free, then $Hom(H)$ is polynomial-time solvable on diameter-$2$ graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06694v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marta Piecyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separation of PSPACE and EXP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.14316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.14316v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article shows that PSPACE not equal EXP. A simple but novel proof technique has been used to separate these two classes. Whether an arbitrary Turing machine accepts an input when the running time is limited has been computed in this paper. Then, the limit goes to infinity. Thus, methods of the recursion theory can be applied to problems of computational complexity theory without violating the relativization barrier.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.14316v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reiner Czerwinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear average-case complexity of algorithmic problems in groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.05232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.05232v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The worst-case complexity of group-theoretic algorithms has been studied for a long time. Generic-case complexity, or complexity on random inputs, was introduced and studied relatively recently. In this paper, we address the average-case time complexity of the word problem in several classes of groups and show that it is often the case that the average-case complexity is linear with respect to the length of an input word. The classes of groups that we consider include groups of matrices over rationals (in particular, polycyclic groups), some classes of solvable groups, as well as free products. Along the way, we improve several bounds for the worst-case complexity of the word problem in groups of matrices, in particular in nilpotent groups. For free products, we also address the average-case complexity of the subgroup membership problem and show that it is often linear, too. Finally, we discuss complexity of the identity problem that has not been considered before.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.05232v5</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Olshanskii, Vladimir Shpilrain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational Complexity Evaluation of Neural Network Applications in Signal Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.12191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.12191v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we provide a systematic approach for assessing and comparing the computational complexity of neural network layers in digital signal processing. We provide and link four software-to-hardware complexity measures, defining how the different complexity metrics relate to the layers' hyper-parameters. This paper explains how to compute these four metrics for feed-forward and recurrent layers, and defines in which case we ought to use a particular metric depending on whether we characterize a more soft- or hardware-oriented application. One of the four metrics, called `the number of additions and bit shifts (NABS)', is newly introduced for heterogeneous quantization. NABS characterizes the impact of not only the bitwidth used in the operation but also the type of quantization used in the arithmetical operations. We intend this work to serve as a baseline for the different levels (purposes) of complexity estimation related to the neural networks' application in real-time digital signal processing, aiming at unifying the computational complexity estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.12191v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Freire, Sasipim Srivallapanondh, Antonio Napoli, Jaroslaw E. Prilepsky, Sergei K. Turitsyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Event Learning and Gentle Random Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.09155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.09155v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the expected disturbance caused to a quantum system by a sequence of randomly ordered two-outcome projective measurements is upper bounded by the square root of the probability that at least one measurement in the sequence accepts. We call this bound the Gentle Random Measurement Lemma.
  We then consider problems in which we are given sample access to an unknown state $\rho$ and asked to estimate properties of the accepting probabilities $\text{Tr}[M_i \rho]$ of a set of measurements $\{M_1, M_2, \ldots , M_m\}$. We call these types of problems Quantum Event Learning Problems. Using the gentle random measurement lemma, we show randomly ordering projective measurements solves the Quantum OR problem, answering an open question of Aaronson. We also give a Quantum OR protocol which works on non-projective measurements but which requires a more complicated type of measurement, which we call a Blended Measurement. Given additional guarantees on the set of measurements $\{M_1, \ldots, M_m\}$, we show the Quantum OR protocols developed in this paper can also be used to find a measurement $M_i$ such that $\text{Tr}[M_i \rho]$ is large. We also give a blended measurement based protocol for estimating the average accepting probability of a set of measurements on an unknown state.
  Finally we consider the Threshold Search Problem described by O'Donnell and B\u{a}descu. By building on our Quantum Event Finding result we show that randomly ordered (or blended) measurements can be used to solve this problem using $O(\log^2(m) / \epsilon^2)$ copies of $\rho$. Consequently, we obtain an algorithm for Shadow Tomography which requires $\tilde{O}(\log^2(m)\log(d)/\epsilon^4)$ samples, matching the current best known sample complexity. This algorithm does not require injected noise in the quantum measurements, but does require measurements to be made in a random order and so is no longer online.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.09155v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Bene Watts, John Bostanci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transition in the computational complexity of the shortest common superstring and genome assembly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.09986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.09986v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Genome assembly, the process of reconstructing a long genetic sequence by aligning and merging short fragments, or reads, is known to be NP-hard, either as a version of the shortest common superstring problem or in a Hamiltonian-cycle formulation. That is, the computing time is believed to grow exponentially with the the problem size in the worst case. Despite this fact, high-throughput technologies and modern algorithms currently allow bioinformaticians to handle datasets of billions of reads. Using methods from statistical mechanics, we address this conundrum by demonstrating the existence of a phase transition in the computational complexity of the problem and showing that practical instances always fall in the 'easy' phase (solvable by polynomial-time algorithms). In addition, we propose a Markov-chain Monte Carlo method that outperforms common deterministic algorithms in the hard regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.09986v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.109.014133</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 109, 014133 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>L. A. Fernandez, V. Martin-Mayor, D. Yllanes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Assembly of Patterns in the abstract Tile Assembly Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16284v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the abstract Tile Assembly Model, self-assembling systems consisting of tiles of different colors can form structures on which colored patterns are ``painted.'' We explore the complexity, in terms of the numbers of unique tile types required, of assembling various patterns. We first demonstrate how to efficiently self-assemble a set of simple patterns, then show tight bounds on the tile type complexity of self-assembling 2-colored patterns on the surfaces of square assemblies. Finally, we demonstrate an exponential gap in tile type complexity of self-assembling an infinite series of patterns between systems restricted to one plane versus those allowed two planes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16284v2</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phillip Drake, Matthew J. Patitz, Scott M. Summers, Tyler Tracy</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
