<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC</link>
    <description>cs.CC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 04:01:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp Online Hardness for Large Balanced Independent Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20785v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the algorithmic problem of finding large $\gamma$-balanced independent sets in dense random bipartite graphs; an independent set is $\gamma$-balanced if a $\gamma$ proportion of its vertices lie on one side of the bipartition. In the sparse regime, Perkins and Wang established tight bounds within the low-degree polynomial (LDP) framework, showing a factor-$1/(1-\gamma)$ statistical-computational gap via the Overlap Gap Property (OGP) framework tailored for stable algorithms. However, these techniques do not appear to extend to the dense setting. For the related large independent set problem in dense random graph, the best known algorithm is an online greedy procedure that is inherently unstable, and LDP algorithms are conjectured to fail even in the "easy" regime where greedy succeeds. We show that the largest $\gamma$-balanced independent set in dense random bipartite graphs has size $\alpha:=\frac{\log_b n}{\gamma(1-\gamma)}$ whp, where $n$ is the size of each bipartition, $p$ is the edge probability, and $b=1/(1-p)$. We design an online algorithm that achieves $(1-\epsilon)(1-\gamma)\alpha$ whp for any $\epsilon&gt;0$. We complement this with a sharp lower bound, showing that no online algorithm can achieve $(1+\epsilon)(1-\gamma)\alpha$ with nonnegligible probability. Our results suggest that the same factor-$1/(1-\gamma)$ gap is also present in the dense setting, supporting its conjectured universality. While the classical greedy procedure on $G(n,p)$ is straightforward, our algorithm is more intricate: it proceeds in two stages, incorporating a stopping time and suitable truncation to ensure that $\gamma$-balancedness-a global constraint-is met despite operating with limited information. Our lower bound utilizes the OGP framework; we build on a recent refinement of this framework for online models and extend it to the bipartite setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20785v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Dhawan, Eren C. K{\i}z{\i}lda\u{g}, Neeladri Maitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QIP $ \subseteq $ AM(2QCFA)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21020v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The class of languages having polynomial-time classical or quantum interactive proof systems ($\mathsf{IP}$ or $\mathsf{QIP}$, respectively) is identical to $\mathsf{PSPACE}$. We show that $\mathsf{PSPACE}$ (and so $\mathsf{QIP}$) is subset of $\mathsf{AM(2QCFA)}$, the class of languages having Arthur-Merlin proof systems where the verifiers are two-way finite automata with quantum and classical states (2QCFAs) communicating with the provers classically. Our protocols use only rational-valued quantum transitions and run in double-exponential expected time. Moreover, the member strings are accepted with probability 1 (i.e., perfect-completeness).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21020v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abuzer Yakary{\i}lmaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power of Counting by Nonuniform Families of Polynomial-Size Finite Automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.18965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.18965v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Lately, there have been intensive studies on strengths and limitations of nonuniform families of promise decision problems solvable by various types of polynomial-size finite automata families, where "polynomial-size" refers to the polynomially-bounded state complexity of a finite automata family. In this line of study, we further expand the scope of these studies to families of partial counting and gap functions, defined in terms of nonuniform families of polynomial-size nondeterministic finite automata, and their relevant families of promise decision problems. Counting functions have an ability of counting the number of accepting computation paths produced by nondeterministic finite automata. With no unproven hardness assumption, we show numerous separations and collapses of complexity classes of those partial counting and gap function families and their induced promise decision problem families. We also investigate their relationships to pushdown automata families of polynomial stack-state complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.18965v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoyuki Yamakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the complexity of constrained reconfiguration and motion planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13032v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Coordinating the motion of multiple agents in constrained environments is a fundamental challenge in robotics, motion planning, and scheduling. A motivating example involves $n$ robotic arms, each represented as a line segment. The objective is to rotate each arm to its vertical orientation, one at a time (clockwise or counterclockwise), without collisions nor rotating any arm more than once. This scenario is an example of the more general $k$-Compatible Ordering problem, where $n$ agents, each capable of $k$ state-changing actions, must transition to specific target states under constraints encoded as a set $\mathcal{G}$ of $k$ pairs of directed graphs.
  We show that $k$-Compatible Ordering is $\mathsf{NP}$-complete, even when $\mathcal{G}$ is planar, degenerate, or acyclic. On the positive side, we provide polynomial-time algorithms for cases such as when $k = 1$ or $\mathcal{G}$ has bounded treewidth. We also introduce generalized variants supporting multiple state-changing actions per agent, broadening the applicability of our framework. These results extend to a wide range of scheduling, reconfiguration, and motion planning applications in constrained environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13032v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Bousquet, Remy El Sabeh, Amer E. Mouawad, Naomi Nishimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prover-Adversary games for systems over (non-deterministic) branching programs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16014v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce Pudlak-Buss style Prover-Adversary games to characterise proof systems reasoning over deterministic branching programs (BPs) and non-deterministic branching programs (NBPs). Our starting points are the proof systems eLDT and eLNDT, for BPs and NBPs respectively, previously introduced by Buss, Das and Knop. We prove polynomial equivalences between these proof systems and the corresponding games we introduce. This crucially requires access to a form of negation of branching programs which, for NBPs, requires us to formalise a non-uniform version of the Immerman-Szelepcsenyi theorem that coNL = NL. Thanks to the techniques developed, we further obtain a proof complexity theoretic version of Immerman-Szelepcsenyi, showing that eLNDT is polynomially equivalent to systems over boundedly alternating branching programs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16014v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anupam Das, Avgerinos Delkos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Characterization of Basic Feasible Functionals Through Higher-Order Rewriting and Tuple Interpretations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12385v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The class of type-two basic feasible functionals ($\mathtt{BFF}_2$) is the analogue of $\mathtt{FP}$ (polynomial time functions) for type-2 functionals, that is, functionals that can take (first-order) functions as arguments. $\mathtt{BFF}_2$ can be defined through Oracle Turing machines with running time bounded by second-order polynomials. On the other hand, higher-order term rewriting provides an elegant formalism for expressing higher-order computation. We address the problem of characterizing $\mathtt{BFF}_2$ by higher-order term rewriting. Various kinds of interpretations for first-order term rewriting have been introduced in the literature for proving termination and characterizing first-order complexity classes. In this paper, we consider a recently introduced notion of cost-size interpretations for higher-order term rewriting and see second order rewriting as ways of computing type-2 functionals. We then prove that the class of functionals represented by higher-order terms admitting polynomially bounded cost-size interpretations exactly corresponds to $\mathtt{BFF}_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12385v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Baillot, Ugo Dal Lago, Cynthia Kop, Deivid Vale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum circuit lower bounds in the magic hierarchy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19966v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the magic hierarchy, a quantum circuit model that alternates between arbitrary-sized Clifford circuits and constant-depth circuits with two-qubit gates ($\textsf{QNC}^0$). This model unifies existing circuit models, such as $\textsf{QAC}^0_f$ and models with adaptive intermediate measurements. Despite its generality, we are able to prove nontrivial lower bounds.
  We prove new lower bounds in the first level of the hierarchy, showing that certain explicit quantum states cannot be approximately prepared by circuits consisting of a Clifford circuit followed by $\textsf{QNC}^0$. These states include ground states of some topologically ordered Hamiltonians and nonstabilizer quantum codes. Our techniques exploit the rigid structure of stabilizer codes and introduce an infectiousness property: if even a single state in a high distance code can be approximately prepared by one of these circuits, then the entire subspace must lie close to a perturbed stabilizer code. We also show that proving state preparation lower bounds beyond a certain level of the hierarchy would imply classical circuit lower bounds beyond the reach of current techniques in complexity theory.
  More broadly, our techniques go beyond lightcone-based methods and highlight how the magic hierarchy provides a natural framework for connecting circuit complexity, condensed matter, and Hamiltonian complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19966v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalie Parham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Sparsification for 1-in-3-SAT via Polynomial Freiman-Ruzsa</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17878v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new notion of sparsification, called \emph{strong sparsification}, in which constraints are not removed but variables can be merged. As our main result, we present a strong sparsification algorithm for 1-in-3-SAT. The correctness of the algorithm relies on establishing a sub-quadratic bound on the size of certain sets of vectors in $\mathbb{F}_2^d$. This result, obtained using the recent \emph{Polynomial Freiman-Ruzsa Theorem} (Gowers, Green, Manners and Tao, Ann. Math. 2025), could be of independent interest. As an application, we improve the state-of-the-art algorithm for approximating linearly-ordered colourings of 3-uniform hypergraphs (H{\aa}stad, Martinsson, Nakajima and{\v{Z}}ivn{\'{y}}, APPROX 2024).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17878v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Bedert, Tamio-Vesa Nakajima, Karolina Okrasa, Stanislav \v{Z}ivn\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
