<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC</link>
    <description>cs.CC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 01:43:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Efficiently Batching Unambiguous Interactive Proofs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that if a language $L$ admits a public-coin unambiguous interactive proof (UIP) with round complexity $\ell$, where $a$ bits are communicated per round, then the batch language $L^{\otimes k}$, i.e. the set of $k$-tuples of statements all belonging to $L$, has an unambiguous interactive proof with round complexity $\ell\cdot\mathsf{polylog}(k)$, per-round communication of $a\cdot \ell\cdot\mathsf{polylog}(k) + \mathsf{poly}(\ell)$ bits, assuming the verifier in the $\mathsf{UIP}$ has depth bounded by $\mathsf{polylog}(k)$. Prior to this work, the best known batch $\mathsf{UIP}$ for $L^{\otimes{k}}$ required communication complexity at least $(\mathsf{poly}(a)\cdot k^{\epsilon} + k) \cdot \ell^{1/\epsilon}$ for any arbitrarily small constant $\epsilon&gt;0$ (Reingold-Rothblum-Rothblum, STOC 2016).
  As a corollary of our result, we obtain a doubly efficient proof system, that is, a proof system whose proving overhead is polynomial in the time of the underlying computation, for any language computable in polynomial space and in time at most $n^{O\left(\sqrt{\frac{\log n}{\log\log n}}\right)}$. This expands the state of the art of doubly efficient proof systems: prior to our work, such systems were known for languages computable in polynomial space and in time $n^{({\log n})^\delta}$ for a small $\delta&gt;0$ significantly smaller than $1/2$ (Reingold-Rothblum-Rothblum, STOC 2016).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19075v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bonnie Berger, Rohan Goyal, Matthew M. Hong, Yael Tauman Kalai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity of Unambiguous Problems in $\Sigma^P_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19084v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The complexity class $\bf{\Sigma^P_2}$ comprises problems based on polynomial-time checkable binary relations $\phi(x,y)$ in which we ask whether there exists $x$ such that for all $y$, $\phi(x,y)$ holds. We let $\bf{U\Sigma^P_2}$ denote the subclass of unambiguous problems in $\bf{\Sigma^P_2}$, namely those whose yes-instances correspond with a unique choice of $x$. $\bf{U\Sigma^P_2}$ is unlikely to have complete problems, but we identify various syntactic subclasses associated with general properties of $\phi$ that guarantee uniqueness. We use these to classify the complexity of problems arising in social choice and game theory, such as existence of (1) a dominating strategy in a game, (2) a Condorcet winner, (3) a strongly popular partition in hedonic games, and (4) a winner (source) in a tournament. We classify these problems, showing the first is $\bf{\Delta^P_2}$-complete, the second and third are complete for a class we term $\bf{PCW}$ (Polynomial Condorcet Winner), and the fourth for a class we term $\bf{PTW}$ (Polynomial Tournament Winner). We define another unambiguous class, $\bf{PMA}$ (Polynomial Majority Argument), seemingly incomparable to $\bf{PTW}$ and $\bf{PCW}$. We show that with randomization, $\bf{PCW}$ and $\bf{PTW}$ coincide with $\bf{\Delta^P_2}$, and $\bf{PMA}$ is contained in $\bf{\Delta^P_2}$. Specifically, we prove: $\bf{\Delta^P_2} \subseteq \bf{PCW} \subseteq \bf{PTW} \subseteq \bf{S^P_2}$, and $\bf{coNP} \subseteq \bf{PMA} \subseteq \bf{S^P_2}$ (and it is known that $\bf{S^P_2}\subseteq \bf{ZPP^{NP}} \subseteq \bf{\Sigma^P_2} \cap \bf{\Pi^P_2}$). We demonstrate that unambiguity can substantially reduce computational complexity by considering ambiguous variants of our problems, and showing they are $\bf{\Sigma^P_2}$-complete. Finally, we study the unambiguous problem of finding a weakly dominant strategy in a game, which seems not to lie in $\bf{\Sigma^P_2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19084v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matan Gilboa, Paul W. Goldberg, Elias Koutsoupias, Noam Nisan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Problems from Optimization and Computational Algebra Equivalent to Hilbert's Nullstellensatz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient algorithms for many problems in optimization and computational algebra often arise from casting them as systems of polynomial equations. Blum, Shub, and Smale formalized this as Hilbert's Nullstellensatz Problem $HN_R$: given multivariate polynomials over a ring $R$, decide whether they have a common solution in $R$. We can also view $HN_R$ as a complexity class by taking the downward closure of the problem $HN_R$ under polynomial-time many-one reductions. In this work, we show that many important problems from optimization and algebra are complete or hard for this class.
  We first consider the Affine Polynomial Projection Problem: given polynomials $f,g$, does an affine projection of the variables transform $f$ into $g$? We show that this problem is at least as hard as $HN_F$ for any field $F$. Then we consider the Sparse Shift Problem: given a polynomial, can its number of monomials be reduced by an affine shift of the variables? Prior $HN_R$-hardness for this problem was known for non-field integral domains $R$, which we extend to fields.
  For the special case of the real field, HN captures the existential theory of the reals and its complement captures the universal theory of the reals. We prove that the problems of deciding real stability, convexity, and hyperbolicity of a given polynomial are all complete for the universal theory of the reals, thereby pinning down their exact complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19704v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Bl\"aser, Sagnik Dutta, Gorav Jindal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Query-Efficient Zeroth-Order Algorithms for Nonconvex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19165v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Zeroth-order optimization (ZO) has been a powerful framework for solving black-box problems, which estimates gradients using zeroth-order data to update variables iteratively. The practical applicability of ZO critically depends on the efficiency of single-step gradient estimation and the overall query complexity. However, existing ZO algorithms cannot achieve efficiency on both simultaneously. In this work, we consider a general constrained optimization model with black-box objective and constraint functions. To solve it, we propose novel algorithms that can achieve the state-of-the-art overall query complexity bound of $\mathcal{O}(d/\epsilon^4)$ to find an $\epsilon$-stationary solution ($d$ is the dimension of variable space), while reducing the queries for estimating a single-step gradient from $\mathcal{O}(d)$ to $\mathcal{O}(1)$. Specifically, we integrate block updates with gradient descent ascent and a block gradient estimator, which leads to two algorithms, ZOB-GDA and ZOB-SGDA, respectively. Instead of constructing full gradients, they estimate only partial gradients along random blocks of dimensions, where the adjustable block sizes enable high single-step efficiency without sacrificing convergence guarantees. Our theoretical results establish the finite-sample convergence of the proposed algorithms for nonconvex optimization. Finally, numerical experiments on a practical problem demonstrate that our algorithms require over ten times fewer queries than existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19165v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiyang Jin, Yuke Zhou, Yujie Tang, Jie Song, Siyang Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Minimal Achievable Quotas in Multiwinner Voting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19620v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Justified representation (JR) and extended justified representation (EJR) are well-established proportionality axioms in approval-based multiwinner voting. Both axioms are always satisfiable, but they rely on a fixed quota (typically Hare or Droop), with the Droop quota being the smallest one that guarantees existence across all instances. With this observation in mind, we take a first step beyond the fixed-quota paradigm and introduce proportionality notions where the quota is instance-dependent. We demonstrate that all commonly studied voting rules can have an additive distance to the optimum of $\frac{k^2}{(k+1)^2}$. Moreover, we look into the computational aspects of our instance-dependent quota and prove that determining the optimal value of $\alpha$ for a given approval profile satisfying $\alpha$-JR is NP-complete. To address this, we introduce an integer linear programming (ILP) formulation for computing committees that satisfy $\alpha$-JR, and we provide positive results in the voter interval (VI) and candidate interval (CI) domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19620v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Becker, Fabian Frank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simplified version of the quantum OTOC$^{(2)}$ problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19751v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This note presents a simplified version of the OTOC$^{(2)}$ problem that was recently experimentally implemented by Google Quantum AI and collaborators. We present a formulation of the problem for growing input size and hope this spurs further theoretical work on the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19751v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robbie King, Robin Kothari, Ryan Babbush, Sergio Boixo, Kostyantyn Kechedzhi, Thomas E. O'Brien, Vadim Smelyanskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parameterized Spanning Tree Congestion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08314v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study the Spanning Tree Congestion problem, where we are given a graph $G=(V,E)$ and are asked to find a spanning tree $T$ of minimum maximum congestion. Here, the congestion of an edge $e\in T$ is the number of edges $uv\in E$ such that the (unique) path from $u$ to $v$ in $T$ traverses $e$. We consider this well-studied NP-hard problem from the point of view of (structural) parameterized complexity and obtain the following results.
  We resolve a natural open problem by showing that Spanning Tree Congestion is not FPT parameterized by treewidth (under standard assumptions). More strongly, we present a generic reduction which applies to (almost) any parameter of the form ``vertex-deletion distance to class $\mathcal{C}$'', thus obtaining W[1]-hardness for parameters more restricted than treewidth, including tree-depth plus feedback vertex set, or incomparable to treewidth, such as twin cover. Via a slight tweak of the same reduction we also show that the problem is NP-complete on graphs of modular-width $4$.
  Even though it is known that Spanning Tree Congestion remains NP-hard on instances with only one vertex of unbounded degree, it is currently open whether the problem remains hard on bounded-degree graphs. We resolve this question by showing NP-hardness on graphs of maximum degree 8.
  Complementing the problem's W[1]-hardness for treewidth...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08314v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Lampis, Valia Mitsou, Edouard Nemery, Yota Otachi, Manolis Vasilakis, Daniel Vaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Criterion for Post-Selected Quantum Advantage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02369v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Assuming the polynomial hierarchy is infinite, we prove a sufficient condition for determining if uniform and polynomial size quantum circuits over a non-universal gate set are not efficiently classically simulable in the weak multiplicative sense. Our criterion exploits the fact that subgroups of $\mathrm{SL}(2;\mathbb{C})$ are essentially either discrete or dense in $\mathrm{SL}(2;\mathbb{C})$. Using our criterion, we give a new proof that both instantaneous quantum polynomial (IQP) circuits and conjugated Clifford circuits (CCCs) afford a quantum advantage. We also prove that both commuting CCCs and CCCs over various fragments of the Clifford group afford a quantum advantage, which settles two questions of Bouland, Fitzsimons, and Koh. Our results imply that circuits over just $(U^\dagger \otimes U^\dagger) \mathrm{CZ} (U \otimes U)$ afford a quantum advantage for almost all $U \in \mathrm{U}(2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02369v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaitanya Karamchedu, Matthew Fox, Daniel Gottesman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An unconditional lower bound for the active-set method in convex quadratic maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16648v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that the active-set method needs an exponential number of iterations in the worst-case to maximize a convex quadratic function subject to linear constraints, regardless of the pivot rule used. This substantially improves over the best previously known lower bound [IPCO 2025], which needs objective functions of polynomial degrees $\omega(\log d)$ in dimension $d$, to a bound using a convex polynomial of degree 2. In particular, our result firmly resolves the open question [IPCO 2025] of whether a constant degree suffices, and it represents significant progress towards linear objectives, where the active-set method coincides with the simplex method and a lower bound for all pivot rules would constitute a major breakthrough.
  Our result is based on a novel extended formulation, recursively constructed using deformed products. Its key feature is that it projects onto a polygonal approximation of a parabola while preserving all of its exponentially many vertices. We define a quadratic objective that forces the active-set method to follow the parabolic boundary of this projection, without allowing any shortcuts along chords corresponding to edges of its full-dimensional preimage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16648v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleon Bach, Yann Disser, Sophie Huiberts, Nils Mosis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better Bounds for Semi-Streaming Single-Source Shortest Paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17841v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the semi-streaming model, an algorithm must process any $n$-vertex graph by making one or few passes over a stream of its edges, use $O(n \cdot \text{polylog }n)$ words of space, and at the end of the last pass, output a solution to the problem at hand. Approximating (single-source) shortest paths on undirected graphs is a longstanding open question in this model. In this work, we make progress on this question from both upper and lower bound fronts:
  We present a simple randomized algorithm that for any $\epsilon &gt; 0$, with high probability computes $(1+\epsilon)$-approximate shortest paths from a given source vertex in \[
  O\left(\frac{1}{\epsilon} \cdot n \log^3 n \right)~\text{space} \quad \text{and} \quad O\left(\frac{1}{\epsilon} \cdot \left(\frac{\log n}{\log\log n} \right) ^2\right) ~\text{passes}.
  \] The algorithm can also be derandomized and made to work on dynamic streams at a cost of some extra $\text{poly}(\log n, 1/\epsilon)$ factors only in the space. Previously, the best known algorithms for this problem required $1/\epsilon \cdot \log^{c}(n)$ passes, for an unspecified large constant $c$.
  We prove that any semi-streaming algorithm that with large constant probability outputs any constant approximation to shortest paths from a given source vertex (even to a single fixed target vertex and only the distance, not necessarily the path) requires \[ \Omega\left(\frac{\log n}{\log\log n}\right) ~\text{passes}. \] We emphasize that our lower bound holds for any constant-factor approximation of shortest paths. Previously, only constant-pass lower bounds were known and only for small approximation ratios below two.
  Our results collectively reduce the gap in the pass complexity of approximating single-source shortest paths in the semi-streaming model from $\text{polylog } n$ vs $\omega(1)$ to only a quadratic gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17841v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sepehr Assadi, Gary Hoppenworth, Janani Sundaresan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
