<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC</link>
    <description>cs.CC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>New Planar Algorithms and a Full Complexity Classification of the Eight-Vertex Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a complete complexity classification theorem for the planar eight-vertex model. For every parameter setting in ${\mathbb C}$ for the eight-vertex model, the partition function is either (1) computable in P-time for every graph, or (2) \#P-hard for general graphs but computable in P-time for planar graphs, or (3) \#P-hard even for planar graphs. The classification has an explicit criterion. In (2), we discover new P-time computable eight-vertex models on planar graphs beyond Kasteleyn's algorithm for counting planar perfect matchings. They are obtained by a combinatorial transformation to the planar {\sc Even Coloring} problem followed by a holographic transformation to the tractable cases in the planar six-vertex model. In the process, we also encounter non-local connections between the planar eight vertex model and the bipartite Ising model, conformal lattice interpolation and M\"{o}bius transformation from complex analysis. The proof also makes use of cyclotomic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11292v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Austen Fan, Jin-Yi Cai, Shuai Shao, Zhuxiao Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Note on the Complexity of Directed Clique</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11773v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a directed graph $G$, and a linear order $\ll$ on the vertices of $G$,
  we define backedge graph $G^\ll$ to be the undirected graph on the same vertex set with edge $\{u,w\}$ in $G^\ll$ if and only if $(u,w)$ is an arc in $G$ and $w \ll u$.
  The directed clique number of a directed graph $G$ is defined as the minimum size of the maximum clique in the backedge graph $G^\ll$ taken over all linear orders $\ll$ on the vertices of $G$.
  A natural computational problem is to decide for a given directed graph $G$ and a positive integer $t$, if the directed clique number of $G$ is at most $t$.
  This problem has polynomial algorithm for $t=1$ and is known to be \NP-complete for every fixed $t\ge3$, even for tournaments.
  In this note we prove that this problem is $\Sigma^\mathsf{P}_{2}$-complete when $t$ is given on the input.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11773v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grzegorz Gutowski, Miko{\l}aj Rams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Bilinear Complexity: What Works and What Breaks with Many Modes?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The complexity of bilinear maps (equivalently, of $3$-mode tensors) has been studied extensively, most notably in the context of matrix multiplication. While circuit complexity and tensor rank coincide asymptotically for $3$-mode tensors, this correspondence breaks down for $d \geq 4$ modes. As a result, the complexity of $d$-mode tensors for larger fixed $d$ remains poorly understood, despite its relevance, e.g., in fine-grained complexity. Our paper explores this intermediate regime. First, we give a "graph-theoretic" proof of Strassen's $2\omega/3$ bound on the asymptotic rank exponent of $3$-mode tensors. Our proof directly generalizes to an upper bound of $(d-1)\omega/3$ for $d$-mode tensors. Using refined techniques available only for $d\geq 4$ modes, we improve this bound beyond the current state of the art for $\omega$. We also obtain a bound of $d/2+1$ on the asymptotic exponent of circuit complexity of generic $d$-mode tensors and optimized bounds for $d \in \{4,5\}$. To the best of our knowledge, asymptotic circuit complexity (rather than rank) of tensors has not been studied before. To obtain a robust theory, we first ask whether low complexity of $T$ and $U$ imply low complexity of their Kronecker product $T \otimes U$. While this crucially holds for rank (and thus for circuit complexity in $3$ modes), we show that assumptions from fine-grained complexity rule out such a submultiplicativity for the circuit complexity of tensors with many modes. In particular, assuming the Hyperclique Conjecture, this failure occurs already for $d=8$ modes. Nevertheless, we can salvage a restricted notion of submultiplicativity. From a technical perspective, our proofs heavily make use of the graph tensors $T_H$, as employed by Christandl and Zuiddam ({\em Comput.~Complexity}~28~(2019)~27--56) and [...]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11975v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cornelius Brand, Radu Curticapean, Petteri Kaski, Baitian Li, Ian Orzel, Tim Seppelt, Jiaheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Block Stacking, Airplane Refueling, and Robust Appointment Scheduling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11366v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: How can a stack of identical blocks be arranged to extend beyond the edge of a table as far as possible? We consider a generalization of this classic puzzle to blocks that differ in width and mass. Despite the seemingly simple premise, we demonstrate that it is unlikely that one can efficiently determine a stack configuration of maximum overhang. Formally, we prove that the Block-Stacking Problem is NP-hard, partially answering an open question from the literature. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the restriction to stacks without counterweights has a surprising connection to the Airplane Refueling Problem, another famous puzzle, and to Robust Appointment Scheduling, a problem of practical relevance. In addition to revealing a remarkable relation to the real-world challenge of devising schedules under uncertainty, their equivalence unveils a polynomial-time approximation scheme, that is, a $(1+\epsilon)$-approximation algorithm, for Block Stacking without counterbalancing and a $(2+\epsilon)$-approximation algorithm for the general case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11366v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Gmeiner, Andreas S. Schulz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gray Codes With Constant Delay and Constant Auxiliary Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give the first two algorithms to enumerate all binary words of $\{0,1\}^\ell$ (like Gray codes) while ensuring that the delay and the auxiliary space is independent from $\ell$, i.e., constant time for each word, and constant memory in addition to the $\ell$ bits storing the current word. Our algorithms are given in two new computational models: tape machines and deque machines. We also study more restricted models, queue machines and stack machines, and show that they cannot enumerate all binary words with constant auxiliary space, even with unrestricted delay.
  A tape machine is a Turing machine that stores the current binary word on a single working tape of length $\ell$. The machine has a single head and must edit its tape to reach all possible words of $\{0,1\}^{\ell}$ , and output them (in unit time, by entering special output states), with no duplicates. We construct a tape machine that achieves this task with constant delay between consecutive outputs, which implies that the machine implements a so-called skew-tolerant quasi-Gray code. We then construct a more involved tape machine that implements a Gray code.
  A deque machine stores the current binary word on a double-ended queue of length $\ell$, and stores a constant-size internal state. It works as a tape machine, except that it modifies the content of the deque by performing push and pop operations on the endpoints. We construct deque machines that enumerate all words of $\{0,1\}^\ell$ with constant-delay. The main technical challenge in this model is to correctly detect when enumeration has finished.
  Our work on deque machine is also motivated by other contexts in which endpoint modifications occur naturally. In particular, our result is a first step towards enumerating walks in directed graphs with constant delay and constant auxiliary space, addressing a core task in modern graph database query processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11791v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Amarilli, Claire David, Nadime Francis, Victor Marsault, Mika\"el Monet, Yann Strozecki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keeping a Secret Requires a Good Memory: Space Lower-Bounds for Private Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12209v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the computational cost of differential privacy in terms of memory efficiency. While the trade-off between accuracy and differential privacy is well-understood, the inherent cost of privacy regarding memory use remains largely unexplored. This paper establishes for the first time an unconditional space lower bound for user-level differential privacy by introducing a novel proof technique based on a multi-player communication game.
  Central to our approach, this game formally links the hardness of low-memory private algorithms to the necessity of ``contribution capping'' -- tracking and limiting the users who disproportionately impact the dataset. We demonstrate that winning this communication game requires transmitting information proportional to the number of over-active users, which translates directly to memory lower bounds.
  We apply this framework, as an example, to the fundamental problem of estimating the number of distinct elements in a stream and we prove that any private algorithm requires almost $\widetilde{\Omega}(T^{1/3})$ space to achieve certain error rates in a promise variant of the problem. This resolves an open problem in the literature (by Jain et al. NeurIPS 2023 and Cummings et al. ICML 2025) and establishes the first exponential separation between the space complexity of private algorithms and their non-private $\widetilde{O}(1)$ counterparts for a natural statistical estimation task. Furthermore, we show that this communication-theoretic technique generalizes to broad classes of problems, yielding lower bounds for private medians, quantiles, and max-select.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12209v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Epasto, Xin Lyu, Pasin Manurangsi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On $NP \cap coNP$ proof complexity generators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20221v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by the theory of proof complexity generators we consider the following $\Sigma^p_2$ search problem $\mbox{DD}_P$ determined by a propositional proof system $P$: given a $P$-proof $\pi$ of a disjunction $\bigvee_i \alpha_i$, no two $\alpha_i$ having an atom in common, find $i$ such that $\alpha_i \in \mbox{TAUT}$. We formulate a hypothesis (ST) that for some strong proof system $P$ the problem $\mbox{DD}_P$ is not solvable in the student-teacher model with a p-time student and a constant number of rounds. The hypothesis follows from the existence of hard one-way permutations. We prove, using a model-theoretic assumption, that (ST) implies $NP \neq coNP$. The assumption concerns the existence of extensions of models of a bounded arithmetic theory and it is open at present if it holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20221v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Krajicek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Depth-Three Circuits for Inner Product</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.04446v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that Inner Product in $2n$ variables, $\mathbf{IP}_n(x, y) = x_1y_1 \oplus \ldots \oplus x_ny_n$, can be computed by depth-3 bottom fan-in 2 circuits of size $\mathsf{poly}(n)\cdot (9/5)^n$, matching the lower bound of G\"o\"os, Guan, and Mosnoi (Inform. Comput.'24). Our construction is obtained via the following steps.
  - We provide a general template for constructing optimal depth-3 circuits with bottom fan-in $k$ for an arbitrary function $f$. We do this in two steps. First, we partition $f^{-1}(1)$ into orbits of its automorphism group. Second, for each orbit, we construct one $k$-CNF that (a) accepts the largest number of inputs from that orbit and (b) rejects all inputs rejected by $f$.
  - We instantiate the template for $\mathbf{IP}_n$ and $k = 2$. Guided by the intuition (which we call modularity principle) that optimal 2-CNFs can be constructed by taking the conjunction of variable-disjoint copies of smaller $2$-CNFs, we use computer search to identify a small set of building block 2-CNFs over at most 4 variables.
  - We again use computer search to discover appropriate combinations (disjoint conjunctions) of building blocks to arrive at optimal 2-CNFs and analyze them using techniques from analytic combinatorics.
  We believe that the approach outlined in this paper can be applied to a wide range of functions to determine their depth-3 complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.04446v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohit Gurumukhani, Daniel Kleber, Ramamohan Paturi, Christopher Rosin, Navid Talebanfard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Shallow-depth Toffoli and Qudit Quantum Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18104v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The relevance of shallow-depth quantum circuits has recently increased, mainly due to their applicability to near-term devices. In this context, one of the main goals of quantum circuit complexity is to find problems that can be solved by quantum shallow circuits but require more computational resources classically.
  Our first contribution in this work is to prove new separations between classical and quantum constant-depth circuits. Firstly, we show a separation between constant-depth quantum circuits with quantum advice $\mathsf{QNC}^0/\mathsf{qpoly}$, and $\mathsf{AC}^0[p]$, which is the class of classical constant-depth circuits with unbounded-fan in and $\mathsf{MOD}_{p}$ gates. Additionally, we show a separation between $\mathsf{QAC}^0$, the circuit class containing Toffoli gates with unbounded control, and $\mathsf{AC}^0[p]$, when $\mathsf{QAC}^0$ is augmented with additional mid-circuit measurements and classical fanout. This establishes the first such separation for a shallow-depth quantum class that does not involve quantum fanout gates, while relying solely on finite quantum gate sets. Equivalently, this yields a separation between $\mathsf{AC}^0[p]$ and $[\mathsf{QNC}^0, \mathsf{AC}^0]^2$, i.e., shallow quantum circuits interleaved with simple classical computation.
  Secondly, we consider $\mathsf{QNC}^0$ circuits with infinite-size gate sets. We show that these circuits, along with quantum prime modular gates or classical prime modular gates in combination with classical fanout, can implement threshold gates, showing that $\mathsf{QNC}^0[p]=\mathsf{QTC}^0$. Finally, we also show that in the infinite-size gate set case, these quantum circuit classes for higher-dimensional Hilbert spaces do not offer any advantage to standard qubit implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18104v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Bredariol Grilo, Elham Kashefi, Damian Markham, Michael de Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Compute a Moving Sum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00537v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Windowed recurrences are sliding window calculations where a function is applied iteratively across the window of data, and are ubiquitous throughout the natural, social, and computational sciences. In this monograph we explore the computational aspects of these calculations, including sequential and parallel computation, and develop the theory underlying the algorithms and their applicability. We introduce an efficient new sequential algorithm with low latency, and develop new techniques to derive and analyze the complexity and domain of validity of existing sequential algorithms. For parallel computation we derive new parallel and vector algorithms by relating windowed recurrences to the algebraic construction of semidirect products, and to algorithms for exponentiation in semigroups. In the middle chapters of the monograph we further develop the theory of semi-associativity and the algebraic conditions for representing function composition and function application by data. This systematizes the techniques used by practitioners to parallelize recurrence calculations. We end the monograph with an extensive gallery of examples of interest to specialists in many fields. Throughout the monograph new algorithms are described with pseudo-code transcribed from functioning source code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00537v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David K. Maslen, Daniel N. Rockmore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refining the Complexity Landscape of Speed Scaling: Hardness and Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17663v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the computational complexity of scheduling jobs on a single speed-scalable processor with the objective of capturing the trade-off between the (weighted) flow time and the energy consumption. This trade-off has been extensively explored in the literature through a number of problem formulations that differ in the specific job characteristics and the precise objective function. Nevertheless, the computational complexity of four important problem variants has remained unresolved and was explicitly identified as an open question in prior work. In this paper, we settle the complexity of these variants.
  More specifically, we prove that the problem of minimizing the objective of total (weighted) flow time plus energy is NP-hard for the cases of (i) unit-weight jobs with arbitrary sizes, and (ii)~arbitrary-weight jobs with unit sizes. These results extend to the objective of minimizing the total (weighted) flow time subject to an energy budget and hold even when the schedule is required to adhere to a given priority ordering.
  In contrast, we show that when a completion-time ordering is provided, the same problem variants become polynomial-time solvable. The latter result highlights the subtle differences between priority and completion orderings for the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17663v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonios Antoniadis, Denise Graafsma, Ruben Hoeksma, Maria Vlasiou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
