<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR</link>
    <description>cs.IR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Time Series Analysis of Key Societal Events as Reflected in Complex Social Media Data Streams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07090v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Social media platforms hold valuable insights, yet extracting essential information can be challenging. Traditional top-down approaches often struggle to capture critical signals in rapidly changing events. As global events evolve swiftly, social media narratives, including instances of disinformation, become significant sources of insights. To address the need for an inductive strategy, we explore a niche social media platform GAB and an established messaging service Telegram, to develop methodologies applicable on a broader scale. This study investigates narrative evolution on these platforms using quantitative corpus-based discourse analysis techniques. Our approach is a novel mode to study multiple social media domains to distil key information which may be obscured otherwise, allowing for useful and actionable insights. The paper details the technical and methodological aspects of gathering and preprocessing GAB and Telegram data for a keyness (Log Ratio) metric analysis, identifying crucial nouns and verbs for deeper exploration. Empirically, this approach is applied to a case study of a well defined event that had global impact: the 2023 Wagner mutiny. The main findings are: (1) the time line can be deconstructed to provide useful data features allowing for improved interpretation; (2) a methodology is applied which provides a basis for generalization. The key contribution is an approach, that in some cases, provides the ability to capture the dynamic narrative shifts over time with elevated confidence. The approach can augment near-real-time assessment of key social movements, allowing for informed governance choices. This research is important because it lays out a useful methodology for time series relevant info-culling, which can enable proactive modes for positive social engagement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07090v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andy Skumanich, Han Kyul Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-supervised Contrastive Learning for Implicit Collaborative Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07265v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Contrastive learning-based recommendation algorithms have significantly advanced the field of self-supervised recommendation, particularly with BPR as a representative ranking prediction task that dominates implicit collaborative filtering. However, the presence of false-positive and false-negative examples in recommendation systems hampers accurate preference learning. In this study, we propose a simple self-supervised contrastive learning framework that leverages positive feature augmentation and negative label augmentation to improve the self-supervisory signal. Theoretical analysis demonstrates that our learning method is equivalent to maximizing the likelihood estimation with latent variables representing user interest centers. Additionally, we establish an efficient negative label augmentation technique that samples unlabeled examples with a probability linearly dependent on their relative ranking positions, enabling efficient augmentation in constant time complexity. Through validation on multiple datasets, we illustrate the significant improvements our method achieves over the widely used BPR optimization objective while maintaining comparable runtime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07265v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shipeng Song, Bin Liu, Fei Teng, Tianrui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LIST: Learning to Index Spatio-Textual Data for Embedding based Spatial Keyword Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the proliferation of spatio-textual data, Top-k KNN spatial keyword queries (TkQs), which return a list of objects based on a ranking function that evaluates both spatial and textual relevance, have found many real-life applications. Existing geo-textual indexes for TkQs use traditional retrieval models like BM25 to compute text relevance and usually exploit a simple linear function to compute spatial relevance, but its effectiveness is limited. To improve effectiveness, several deep learning models have recently been proposed, but they suffer severe efficiency issues. To the best of our knowledge, there are no efficient indexes specifically designed to accelerate the top-k search process for these deep learning models.
  To tackle these issues, we propose a novel technique, which Learns to Index the Spatio-Textual data for answering embedding based spatial keyword queries (called LIST). LIST is featured with two novel components. Firstly, we propose a lightweight and effective relevance model that is capable of learning both textual and spatial relevance. Secondly, we introduce a novel machine learning based Approximate Nearest Neighbor Search (ANNS) index, which utilizes a new learning-to-cluster technique to group relevant queries and objects together while separating irrelevant queries and objects. Two key challenges in building an effective and efficient index are the absence of high-quality labels and unbalanced clustering results. We develop a novel pseudo-label generation technique to address the two challenges. Experimental results show that LIST significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods on effectiveness, with improvements up to 19.21% and 12.79% in terms of NDCG@1 and Recall@10, and is three orders of magnitude faster than the most effective baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07331v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqi Yin, Shanshan Feng, Shang Liu, Gao Cong, Yew Soon Ong, Bin Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Graph Foundation Models for Personalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the realm of personalization, integrating diverse information sources such as consumption signals and content-based representations is becoming increasingly critical to build state-of-the-art solutions. In this regard, two of the biggest trends in research around this subject are Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) and Foundation Models (FMs). While GNNs emerged as a popular solution in industry for powering personalization at scale, FMs have only recently caught attention for their promising performance in personalization tasks like ranking and retrieval. In this paper, we present a graph-based foundation modeling approach tailored to personalization. Central to this approach is a Heterogeneous GNN (HGNN) designed to capture multi-hop content and consumption relationships across a range of recommendable item types. To ensure the generality required from a Foundation Model, we employ a Large Language Model (LLM) text-based featurization of nodes that accommodates all item types, and construct the graph using co-interaction signals, which inherently transcend content specificity. To facilitate practical generalization, we further couple the HGNN with an adaptation mechanism based on a two-tower (2T) architecture, which also operates agnostically to content type. This multi-stage approach ensures high scalability; while the HGNN produces general purpose embeddings, the 2T component models in a continuous space the sheer size of user-item interaction data. Our comprehensive approach has been rigorously tested and proven effective in delivering recommendations across a diverse array of products within a real-world, industrial audio streaming platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07478v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Damianou, Francesco Fabbri, Paul Gigioli, Marco De Nadai, Alice Wang, Enrico Palumbo, Mounia Lalmas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The future of document indexing: GPT and Donut revolutionize table of content processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Industrial projects rely heavily on lengthy, complex specification documents, making tedious manual extraction of structured information a major bottleneck. This paper introduces an innovative approach to automate this process, leveraging the capabilities of two cutting-edge AI models: Donut, a model that extracts information directly from scanned documents without OCR, and OpenAI GPT-3.5 Turbo, a robust large language model. The proposed methodology is initiated by acquiring the table of contents (ToCs) from construction specification documents and subsequently structuring the ToCs text into JSON data. Remarkable accuracy is achieved, with Donut reaching 85% and GPT-3.5 Turbo reaching 89% in effectively organizing the ToCs. This landmark achievement represents a significant leap forward in document indexing, demonstrating the immense potential of AI to automate information extraction tasks across diverse document types, boosting efficiency and liberating critical resources in various industries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07553v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Degaga Wolde Feyisa, Haylemicheal Berihun, Amanuel Zewdu, Mahsa Najimoghadam, Marzieh Zare</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proactive Recommendation with Iterative Preference Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07571v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recommender systems mainly tailor personalized recommendations according to user interests learned from user feedback. However, such recommender systems passively cater to user interests and even reinforce existing interests in the feedback loop, leading to problems like filter bubbles and opinion polarization. To counteract this, proactive recommendation actively steers users towards developing new interests in a target item or topic by strategically modulating recommendation sequences. Existing work for proactive recommendation faces significant hurdles: 1) overlooking the user feedback in the guidance process; 2) lacking explicit modeling of the guiding objective; and 3) insufficient flexibility for integration into existing industrial recommender systems. To address these issues, we introduce an Iterative Preference Guidance (IPG) framework. IPG performs proactive recommendation in a flexible post-processing manner by ranking items according to their IPG scores that consider both interaction probability and guiding value. These scores are explicitly estimated with iteratively updated user representation that considers the most recent user interactions. Extensive experiments validate that IPG can effectively guide user interests toward target interests with a reasonable trade-off in recommender accuracy. The code is available at https://github.com/GabyUSTC/IPG-Rec.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07571v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3589335.3651548</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shuxian Bi, Wenjie Wang, Hang Pan, Fuli Feng, Xiangnan He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empowering Sequential Recommendation from Collaborative Signals and Semantic Relatedness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07623v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sequential recommender systems (SRS) could capture dynamic user preferences by modeling historical behaviors ordered in time. Despite effectiveness, focusing only on the \textit{collaborative signals} from behaviors does not fully grasp user interests. It is also significant to model the \textit{semantic relatedness} reflected in content features, e.g., images and text. Towards that end, in this paper, we aim to enhance the SRS tasks by effectively unifying collaborative signals and semantic relatedness together. Notably, we empirically point out that it is nontrivial to achieve such a goal due to semantic gap issues. Thus, we propose an end-to-end two-stream architecture for sequential recommendation, named TSSR, to learn user preferences from ID-based and content-based sequence. Specifically, we first present novel hierarchical contrasting module, including coarse user-grained and fine item-grained terms, to align the representations of inter-modality. Furthermore, we also design a two-stream architecture to learn the dependence of intra-modality sequence and the complex interactions of inter-modality sequence, which can yield more expressive capacity in understanding user interests. We conduct extensive experiments on five public datasets. The experimental results show that the TSSR could yield superior performance than competitive baselines. We also make our experimental codes publicly available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/TSSR-2A27/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07623v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyue Cheng, Hao Zhang, Qi Liu, Fajie Yuan, Zhi Li, Zhenya Huang, Enhong Chen, Jun Zhou, Longfei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Adversarial Attacks on Sequence-to-Sequence Relevance Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern sequence-to-sequence relevance models like monoT5 can effectively capture complex textual interactions between queries and documents through cross-encoding. However, the use of natural language tokens in prompts, such as Query, Document, and Relevant for monoT5, opens an attack vector for malicious documents to manipulate their relevance score through prompt injection, e.g., by adding target words such as true. Since such possibilities have not yet been considered in retrieval evaluation, we analyze the impact of query-independent prompt injection via manually constructed templates and LLM-based rewriting of documents on several existing relevance models. Our experiments on the TREC Deep Learning track show that adversarial documents can easily manipulate different sequence-to-sequence relevance models, while BM25 (as a typical lexical model) is not affected. Remarkably, the attacks also affect encoder-only relevance models (which do not rely on natural language prompt tokens), albeit to a lesser extent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07654v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Parry, Maik Fr\"obe, Sean MacAvaney, Martin Potthast, Matthias Hagen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESERE: The 1st Workshop on Decentralised Search and Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07732v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The DESERE Workshop, our First Workshop on Decentralised Search and Recommendation, offers a platform for researchers to explore and share innovative ideas on decentralised web services, mainly focusing on three major topics: (i) societal impact of decentralised systems: their effect on privacy, policy, and regulation; (ii) decentralising applications: algorithmic and performance challenges that arise from decentralisation; and (iii) infrastructure to support decentralised systems and services: peer-to-peer networks, routing, and performance evaluation tools</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07732v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Ragab, Yury Savateev, Wenjie Wang, Reza Moosaei, Thanassis Tiropanis, Alexandra Poulovassilis, Adriane Chapman, Helen Oliver, George Roussos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Position Bias Estimation with Item Embedding for Sparse Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.13931v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Estimating position bias is a well-known challenge in Learning to Rank (L2R). Click data in e-commerce applications, such as targeted advertisements and search engines, provides implicit but abundant feedback to improve personalized rankings. However, click data inherently includes various biases like position bias. Based on the position-based click model, Result Randomization and Regression Expectation-Maximization algorithm (REM) have been proposed to estimate position bias, but they require various paired observations of (item, position). In real-world scenarios of advertising, marketers frequently display advertisements in a fixed pre-determined order, which creates difficulties in estimation due to the limited availability of various pairs in the training data, resulting in a sparse dataset. We propose a variant of the REM that utilizes item embeddings to alleviate the sparsity of (item, position). Using a public dataset and internal carousel advertisement click dataset, we empirically show that item embedding with Latent Semantic Indexing (LSI) and Variational Auto-Encoder (VAE) improves the accuracy of position bias estimation and the estimated position bias enhances Learning to Rank performance. We also show that LSI is more effective as an embedding creation method for position bias estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.13931v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shion Ishikawa, Yun Ching Liu, Young-Joo Chung, Yu Hirate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating the Post-API Dilemma Search Engine Results Pages Present a Biased View of Social Media Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15479v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent decisions to discontinue access to social media APIs are having detrimental effects on Internet research and the field of computational social science as a whole. This lack of access to data has been dubbed the Post-API era of Internet research. Fortunately, popular search engines have the means to crawl, capture, and surface social media data on their Search Engine Results Pages (SERP) if provided the proper search query, and may provide a solution to this dilemma. In the present work we ask: does SERP provide a complete and unbiased sample of social media data? Is SERP a viable alternative to direct API-access? To answer these questions, we perform a comparative analysis between (Google) SERP results and nonsampled data from Reddit and Twitter/X. We find that SERP results are highly biased in favor of popular posts; against political, pornographic, and vulgar posts; are more positive in their sentiment; and have large topical gaps. Overall, we conclude that SERP is not a viable alternative to social media API access.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15479v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amrit Poudel, Tim Weninger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MetaSplit: Meta-Split Network for Limited-Stock Product Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06747v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Compared to business-to-consumer (B2C) e-commerce systems, consumer-to-consumer (C2C) e-commerce platforms usually encounter the limited-stock problem, that is, a product can only be sold one time in a C2C system. This poses several unique challenges for click-through rate (CTR) prediction. Due to limited user interactions for each product (i.e. item), the corresponding item embedding in the CTR model may not easily converge. This makes the conventional sequence modeling based approaches cannot effectively utilize user history information since historical user behaviors contain a mixture of items with different volume of stocks. Particularly, the attention mechanism in a sequence model tends to assign higher score to products with more accumulated user interactions, making limited-stock products being ignored and contribute less to the final output. To this end, we propose the Meta-Split Network (MSNet) to split user history sequence regarding to the volume of stock for each product, and adopt differentiated modeling approaches for different sequences. As for the limited-stock products, a meta-learning approach is applied to address the problem of inconvergence, which is achieved by designing meta scaling and shifting networks with ID and side information. In addition, traditional approach can hardly update item embedding once the product is consumed. Thereby, we propose an auxiliary loss that makes the parameters updatable even when the product is no longer in distribution. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first solution addressing the recommendation of limited-stock product. Experimental results on the production dataset and online A/B testing demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06747v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhao Wu, Jialiang Zhou, Ailong He, Shuguang Han, Jufeng Chen, Bo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-View Variational Autoencoder for Missing Value Imputation in Untargeted Metabolomics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07990v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Background: Missing data is a common challenge in mass spectrometry-based metabolomics, which can lead to biased and incomplete analyses. The integration of whole-genome sequencing (WGS) data with metabolomics data has emerged as a promising approach to enhance the accuracy of data imputation in metabolomics studies. Method: In this study, we propose a novel method that leverages the information from WGS data and reference metabolites to impute unknown metabolites. Our approach utilizes a multi-view variational autoencoder to jointly model the burden score, polygenetic risk score (PGS), and linkage disequilibrium (LD) pruned single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) for feature extraction and missing metabolomics data imputation. By learning the latent representations of both omics data, our method can effectively impute missing metabolomics values based on genomic information. Results: We evaluate the performance of our method on empirical metabolomics datasets with missing values and demonstrate its superiority compared to conventional imputation techniques. Using 35 template metabolites derived burden scores, PGS and LD-pruned SNPs, the proposed methods achieved R^2-scores &gt; 0.01 for 71.55% of metabolites. Conclusion: The integration of WGS data in metabolomics imputation not only improves data completeness but also enhances downstream analyses, paving the way for more comprehensive and accurate investigations of metabolic pathways and disease associations. Our findings offer valuable insights into the potential benefits of utilizing WGS data for metabolomics data imputation and underscore the importance of leveraging multi-modal data integration in precision medicine research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07990v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Zhao, Kuan-Jui Su, Chong Wu, Xuewei Cao, Qiuying Sha, Wu Li, Zhe Luo, Tian Qin, Chuan Qiu, Lan Juan Zhao, Anqi Liu, Lindong Jiang, Xiao Zhang, Hui Shen, Weihua Zhou, Hong-Wen Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-context Learning with Retrieved Demonstrations for Language Models: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11624v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Language models, especially pre-trained large language models, have showcased remarkable abilities as few-shot in-context learners (ICL), adept at adapting to new tasks with just a few demonstrations in the input context. However, the model's ability to perform ICL is sensitive to the choice of the few-shot demonstrations. Instead of using a fixed set of demonstrations, one recent development is to retrieve demonstrations tailored to each input query. The implementation of demonstration retrieval is relatively straightforward, leveraging existing databases and retrieval systems. This not only improves the efficiency and scalability of the learning process but also has been shown to reduce biases inherent in manual example selection. In light of the encouraging results and growing research in ICL with retrieved demonstrations, we conduct an extensive review of studies in this area. In this survey, we discuss and compare different design choices for retrieval models, retrieval training procedures, and inference algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11624v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Man Luo, Xin Xu, Yue Liu, Panupong Pasupat, Mehran Kazemi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
