<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR</link>
    <description>cs.IR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Semantic Tokenization for Deep CTR Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Incorporating item content information into click-through rate (CTR) prediction models remains a challenge, especially with the time and space constraints of industrial scenarios. The content-encoding paradigm, which integrates user and item encoders directly into CTR models, prioritizes space over time. In contrast, the embedding-based paradigm transforms item and user semantics into latent embeddings and then caches them, prioritizes space over time. In this paper, we introduce a new semantic-token paradigm and propose a discrete semantic tokenization approach, namely UIST, for user and item representation. UIST facilitates swift training and inference while maintaining a conservative memory footprint. Specifically, UIST quantizes dense embedding vectors into discrete tokens with shorter lengths and employs a hierarchical mixture inference module to weigh the contribution of each user--item token pair. Our experimental results on news recommendation showcase the effectiveness and efficiency (about 200-fold space compression) of UIST for CTR prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08206v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qijiong Liu, Hengchang Hu, Jiahao Wu, Jieming Zhu, Min-Yen Kan, Xiao-Ming Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Unified Modeling for Positive and Negative Preferences in Sign-Aware Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, sign-aware graph recommendation has drawn much attention as it will learn users' negative preferences besides positive ones from both positive and negative interactions (i.e., links in a graph) with items. To accommodate the different semantics of negative and positive links, existing works utilize two independent encoders to model users' positive and negative preferences, respectively. However, these approaches cannot learn the negative preferences from high-order heterogeneous interactions between users and items formed by multiple links with different signs, resulting in inaccurate and incomplete negative user preferences. To cope with these intractable issues, we propose a novel \textbf{L}ight \textbf{S}igned \textbf{G}raph Convolution Network specifically for \textbf{Rec}ommendation (\textbf{LSGRec}), which adopts a unified modeling approach to simultaneously model high-order users' positive and negative preferences on a signed user-item interaction graph. Specifically, for the negative preferences within high-order heterogeneous interactions, first-order negative preferences are captured by the negative links, while high-order negative preferences are propagated along positive edges. Then, recommendation results are generated based on positive preferences and optimized with negative ones. Finally, we train representations of users and items through different auxiliary tasks. Extensive experiments on three real-world datasets demonstrate that our method outperforms existing baselines regarding performance and computational efficiency. Our code is available at \url{https://anonymous.4open.science/r/LSGRec-BB95}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08246v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuting Liu, Yizhou Dang, Yuliang Liang, Qiang Liu, Guibing Guo, Jianzhe Zhao, Xingwei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NLQxform-UI: A Natural Language Interface for Querying DBLP Interactively</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08475v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, the DBLP computer science bibliography has been prominently used for searching scholarly information, such as publications, scholars, and venues. However, its current search service lacks the capability to handle complex queries, which limits the usability of DBLP. In this paper, we present NLQxform-UI, a web-based natural language interface that enables users to query DBLP directly with complex natural language questions. NLQxform-UI automatically translates given questions into SPARQL queries and executes the queries over the DBLP knowledge graph to retrieve answers. The querying process is presented to users in an interactive manner, which improves the transparency of the system and helps examine the returned answers. Also, intermediate results in the querying process can be previewed and manually altered to improve the accuracy of the system. NLQxform-UI has been completely open-sourced: https://github.com/ruijie-wang-uzh/NLQxform-UI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08475v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruijie Wang, Zhiruo Zhang, Luca Rossetto, Florian Ruosch, Abraham Bernstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ILCiteR: Evidence-grounded Interpretable Local Citation Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Existing Machine Learning approaches for local citation recommendation directly map or translate a query, which is typically a claim or an entity mention, to citation-worthy research papers. Within such a formulation, it is challenging to pinpoint why one should cite a specific research paper for a particular query, leading to limited recommendation interpretability. To alleviate this, we introduce the evidence-grounded local citation recommendation task, where the target latent space comprises evidence spans for recommending specific papers. Using a distantly-supervised evidence retrieval and multi-step re-ranking framework, our proposed system, ILCiteR, recommends papers to cite for a query grounded on similar evidence spans extracted from the existing research literature. Unlike past formulations that simply output recommendations, ILCiteR retrieves ranked lists of evidence span and recommended paper pairs. Secondly, previously proposed neural models for citation recommendation require expensive training on massive labeled data, ideally after every significant update to the pool of candidate papers. In contrast, ILCiteR relies solely on distant supervision from a dynamic evidence database and pre-trained Transformer-based Language Models without any model training. We contribute a novel dataset for the evidence-grounded local citation recommendation task and demonstrate the efficacy of our proposed conditional neural rank-ensembling approach for re-ranking evidence spans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08737v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayar Ghosh Roy, Jiawei Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge Conflicts for LLMs: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This survey provides an in-depth analysis of knowledge conflicts for large language models (LLMs), highlighting the complex challenges they encounter when blending contextual and parametric knowledge. Our focus is on three categories of knowledge conflicts: context-memory, inter-context, and intra-memory conflict. These conflicts can significantly impact the trustworthiness and performance of LLMs, especially in real-world applications where noise and misinformation are common. By categorizing these conflicts, exploring the causes, examining the behaviors of LLMs under such conflicts, and reviewing available solutions, this survey aims to shed light on strategies for improving the robustness of LLMs, thereby serving as a valuable resource for advancing research in this evolving area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08319v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongwu Xu, Zehan Qi, Cunxiang Wang, Hongru Wang, Yue Zhang, Wei Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPT-4V(ision) is a Generalist Web Agent, if Grounded</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01614v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent development on large multimodal models (LMMs), especially GPT-4V(ision) and Gemini, has been quickly expanding the capability boundaries of multimodal models beyond traditional tasks like image captioning and visual question answering. In this work, we explore the potential of LMMs like GPT-4V as a generalist web agent that can follow natural language instructions to complete tasks on any given website. We propose SEEACT, a generalist web agent that harnesses the power of LMMs for integrated visual understanding and acting on the web. We evaluate on the recent MIND2WEB benchmark. In addition to standard offline evaluation on cached websites, we enable a new online evaluation setting by developing a tool that allows running web agents on live websites. We show that GPT-4V presents a great potential for web agents -- it can successfully complete 51.1 of the tasks on live websites if we manually ground its textual plans into actions on the websites. This substantially outperforms text-only LLMs like GPT-4 or smaller models (FLAN-T5 and BLIP-2) specifically fine-tuned for web agents. However, grounding still remains a major challenge. Existing LMM grounding strategies like set-of-mark prompting turns out to be not effective for web agents, and the best grounding strategy we develop in this paper leverages both the HTML structure and visuals. Yet, there is still a substantial gap with oracle grounding, leaving ample room for further improvement. All code, data, and evaluation tools are available at https://github.com/OSU-NLP-Group/SeeAct.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01614v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyuan Zheng, Boyu Gou, Jihyung Kil, Huan Sun, Yu Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MetaSplit: Meta-Split Network for Limited-Stock Product Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06747v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Compared to business-to-consumer (B2C) e-commerce systems, consumer-to-consumer (C2C) e-commerce platforms usually encounter the limited-stock problem, that is, a product can only be sold one time in a C2C system. This poses several unique challenges for click-through rate (CTR) prediction. Due to limited user interactions for each product (i.e. item), the corresponding item embedding in the CTR model may not easily converge. This makes the conventional sequence modeling based approaches cannot effectively utilize user history information since historical user behaviors contain a mixture of items with different volume of stocks. Particularly, the attention mechanism in a sequence model tends to assign higher score to products with more accumulated user interactions, making limited-stock products being ignored and contribute less to the final output. To this end, we propose the Meta-Split Network (MSNet) to split user history sequence regarding to the volume of stock for each product, and adopt differentiated modeling approaches for different sequences. As for the limited-stock products, a meta-learning approach is applied to address the problem of inconvergence, which is achieved by designing meta scaling and shifting networks with ID and side information. In addition, traditional approach can hardly update item embedding once the product is consumed. Thereby, we propose an auxiliary loss that makes the parameters updatable even when the product is no longer in distribution. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first solution addressing the recommendation of limited-stock product. Experimental results on the production dataset and online A/B testing demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06747v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhao Wu, Jialiang Zhou, Ailong He, Shuguang Han, Jufeng Chen, Bo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of ChatGPT Fake Science with the xFakeSci Learning Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11767v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: ChatGPT and generative AI tools are becoming the new reality. This work is motivated by the premise that ``ChatGPT content may exhibit a distinctive behavior that can be separated from scientific articles''. In this study, we demonstrate how we tested this premise in two phases and prove its validity. Subsequently, we introduce xFakeSci, a novel learning algorithm, that is capable of distinguishing ChatGPT-generated articles from publications produced by scientists. The algorithm is trained using network models driven from multiple types of data sources, such as ChatGPT-generated documents achieved by means of prompt-engineering, and PubMed articles. To mitigate over-fitting issues, we incorporate a calibration step that is built upon data-driven heuristics, including ratios. We evaluate the algorithm across multiple datasets covering publication periods and diseases (cancer, depression, and Alzheimer's). Further, we show how the algorithm is benchmarked against the state-of-the-art (SOTA) algorithms. While the xFakeSci algorithm achieve F1 score ranging from 80% - 94%, SOTA algorithms score F1 values between 38% - 52%. We attribute the noticeable difference to the introduction of calibration and a proximity distance heuristic, which we underscore this promising performance. Indeed, the prediction of fake science generated by ChatGPT presents a considerable challenge. Nonetheless, the introduction of xFakeSci algorithm is a significant step on the way to combating fake science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11767v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Abdeen Hamed, Xindong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
