<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR</link>
    <description>cs.IR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 02:44:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>PRAGyan -- Connecting the Dots in Tweets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As social media platforms grow, understanding the underlying reasons behind events and statements becomes crucial for businesses, policymakers, and researchers. This research explores the integration of Knowledge Graphs (KGs) with Large Language Models (LLMs) to perform causal analysis of tweets dataset. The LLM aided analysis techniques often lack depth in uncovering the causes driving observed effects. By leveraging KGs and LLMs, which encode rich semantic relationships and temporal information, this study aims to uncover the complex interplay of factors influencing causal dynamics and compare the results obtained using GPT-3.5 Turbo. We employ a Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) model, utilizing a KG stored in a Neo4j (a.k.a PRAGyan) data format, to retrieve relevant context for causal reasoning. Our approach demonstrates that the KG-enhanced LLM RAG can provide improved results when compared to the baseline LLM (GPT-3.5 Turbo) model as the source corpus increases in size. Our qualitative analysis highlights the advantages of combining KGs with LLMs for improved interpretability and actionable insights, facilitating informed decision-making across various domains. Whereas, quantitative analysis using metrics such as BLEU and cosine similarity show that our approach outperforms the baseline by 10\%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13909v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Ravi, Gouri Ginde, Jon Rokne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge Distillation Approaches for Accurate and Efficient Recommender System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite its breakthrough in classification problems, Knowledge distillation (KD) to recommendation models and ranking problems has not been studied well in the previous literature. This dissertation is devoted to developing knowledge distillation methods for recommender systems to fully improve the performance of a compact model. We propose novel distillation methods designed for recommender systems. The proposed methods are categorized according to their knowledge sources as follows: (1) Latent knowledge: we propose two methods that transfer latent knowledge of user/item representation. They effectively transfer knowledge of niche tastes with a balanced distillation strategy that prevents the KD process from being biased towards a small number of large preference groups. Also, we propose a new method that transfers user/item relations in the representation space. The proposed method selectively transfers essential relations considering the limited capacity of the compact model. (2) Ranking knowledge: we propose three methods that transfer ranking knowledge from the recommendation results. They formulate the KD process as a ranking matching problem and transfer the knowledge via a listwise learning strategy. Further, we present a new learning framework that compresses the ranking knowledge of heterogeneous recommendation models. The proposed framework is developed to ease the computational burdens of model ensemble which is a dominant solution for many recommendation applications. We validate the benefit of our proposed methods and frameworks through extensive experiments. To summarize, this dissertation sheds light on knowledge distillation approaches for a better accuracy-efficiency trade-off of the recommendation models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13952v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>SeongKu Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Reading Comprehension with Encoder-Decoder Models Enhanced by Direct Preference Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extractive question answering over clinical text is a crucial need to help deal with the deluge of clinical text generated in hospitals. While encoder models (e.g., BERT) have been popular for this reading comprehension task, recently encoder-decoder models (e.g., T5) are on the rise. There is also the emergence of preference optimization techniques to align decoder-only LLMs with human preferences. In this paper, we combine encoder-decoder models with the direct preference optimization (DPO) method to improve over prior state of the art for the RadQA radiology question answering task by 12-15 F1 points. To the best of our knowledge, this effort is the first to show that DPO method also works for reading comprehension via novel heuristics to generate preference data without human inputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14000v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Sultan Al Nahian, Ramakanth Kavuluru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>User-Creator Feature Dynamics in Recommender Systems with Dual Influence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14094v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recommender systems present relevant contents to users and help content creators reach their target audience. The dual nature of these systems influences both users and creators: users' preferences are affected by the items they are recommended, while creators are incentivized to alter their contents such that it is recommended more frequently. We define a model, called user-creator feature dynamics, to capture the dual influences of recommender systems. We prove that a recommender system with dual influence is guaranteed to polarize, causing diversity loss in the system. We then investigate, both theoretically and empirically, approaches for mitigating polarization and promoting diversity in recommender systems. Unexpectedly, we find that common diversity-promoting approaches do not work in the presence of dual influence, while relevancy-optimizing methods like top-$k$ recommendation can prevent polarization and improve diversity of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14094v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Lin, Kun Jin, Andrew Estornell, Xiaoying Zhang, Yiling Chen, Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L^2CL: Embarrassingly Simple Layer-to-Layer Contrastive Learning for Graph Collaborative Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graph neural networks (GNNs) have recently emerged as an effective approach to model neighborhood signals in collaborative filtering. Towards this research line, graph contrastive learning (GCL) demonstrates robust capabilities to address the supervision label shortage issue through generating massive self-supervised signals. Despite its effectiveness, GCL for recommendation suffers seriously from two main challenges: i) GCL relies on graph augmentation to generate semantically different views for contrasting, which could potentially disrupt key information and introduce unwanted noise; ii) current works for GCL primarily focus on contrasting representations using sophisticated networks architecture (usually deep) to capture high-order interactions, which leads to increased computational complexity and suboptimal training efficiency. To this end, we propose L2CL, a principled Layer-to-Layer Contrastive Learning framework that contrasts representations from different layers. By aligning the semantic similarities between different layers, L2CL enables the learning of complex structural relationships and gets rid of the noise perturbation in stochastic data augmentation. Surprisingly, we find that L2CL, using only one-hop contrastive learning paradigm, is able to capture intrinsic semantic structures and improve the quality of node representation, leading to a simple yet effective architecture. We also provide theoretical guarantees for L2CL in minimizing task-irrelevant information. Extensive experiments on five real-world datasets demonstrate the superiority of our model over various state-of-the-art collaborative filtering methods. Our code is available at https://github.com/downeykking/L2CL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14266v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinzhou Jin, Jintang Li, Liang Chen, Chenyun Yu, Yuanzhen Xie, Tao Xie, Chengxiang Zhuo, Zang Li, Zibin Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Retrieval in Sponsored Search by Leveraging Query Context Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14346v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurately retrieving relevant bid keywords for user queries is critical in Sponsored Search but remains challenging, particularly for short, ambiguous queries. Existing dense and generative retrieval models often fail to capture nuanced user intent in these cases. To address this, we propose an approach to enhance query understanding by augmenting queries with rich contextual signals derived from web search results and large language models, stored in an online cache. Specifically, we use web search titles and snippets to ground queries in real-world information and utilize GPT-4 to generate query rewrites and explanations that clarify user intent. These signals are efficiently integrated through a Fusion-in-Decoder based Unity architecture, enabling both dense and generative retrieval with serving costs on par with traditional context-free models. To address scenarios where context is unavailable in the cache, we introduce context glancing, a curriculum learning strategy that improves model robustness and performance even without contextual signals during inference. Extensive offline experiments demonstrate that our context-aware approach substantially outperforms context-free models. Furthermore, online A/B testing on a prominent search engine across 160+ countries shows significant improvements in user engagement and revenue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14346v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Kumar Mohankumar, Gururaj K, Gagan Madan, Amit Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HeCiX: Integrating Knowledge Graphs and Large Language Models for Biomedical Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14030v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite advancements in drug development strategies, 90% of clinical trials fail. This suggests overlooked aspects in target validation and drug optimization. In order to address this, we introduce HeCiX-KG, Hetionet-Clinicaltrials neXus Knowledge Graph, a novel fusion of data from ClinicalTrials.gov and Hetionet in a single knowledge graph. HeCiX-KG combines data on previously conducted clinical trials from ClinicalTrials.gov, and domain expertise on diseases and genes from Hetionet. This offers a thorough resource for clinical researchers. Further, we introduce HeCiX, a system that uses LangChain to integrate HeCiX-KG with GPT-4, and increase its usability. HeCiX shows high performance during evaluation against a range of clinically relevant issues, proving this model to be promising for enhancing the effectiveness of clinical research. Thus, this approach provides a more holistic view of clinical trials and existing biological data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14030v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prerana Sanjay Kulkarni, Muskaan Jain, Disha Sheshanarayana, Srinivasan Parthiban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DisenSemi: Semi-supervised Graph Classification via Disentangled Representation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14081v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graph classification is a critical task in numerous multimedia applications, where graphs are employed to represent diverse types of multimedia data, including images, videos, and social networks. Nevertheless, in real-world scenarios, labeled graph data can be limited or scarce. To address this issue, we focus on the problem of semi-supervised graph classification, which involves both supervised and unsupervised models learning from labeled and unlabeled data. In contrast to recent approaches that transfer the entire knowledge from the unsupervised model to the supervised one, we argue that an effective transfer should only retain the relevant semantics that align well with the supervised task. In this paper, we propose a novel framework named DisenSemi, which learns disentangled representation for semi-supervised graph classification. Specifically, a disentangled graph encoder is proposed to generate factor-wise graph representations for both supervised and unsupervised models. Then we train two models via supervised objective and mutual information (MI)-based constraints respectively. To ensure the meaningful transfer of knowledge from the unsupervised encoder to the supervised one, we further define an MI-based disentangled consistency regularization between two models and identify the corresponding rationale that aligns well with the current graph classification task. Experimental results on a range of publicly accessible datasets reveal the effectiveness of our DisenSemi.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14081v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Wang, Xiao Luo, Chong Chen, Xian-Sheng Hua, Ming Zhang, Wei Ju</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guitar Chord Diagram Suggestion for Western Popular Music</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14260v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chord diagrams are used by guitar players to show where and how to play a chord on the fretboard. They are useful to beginners learning chords or for sharing the hand positions required to play a song.However, the diagrams presented on guitar learning toolsare usually selected from an existing databaseand rarely represent the actual positions used by performers.In this paper, we propose a tool which suggests a chord diagram for achord label,taking into account the diagram of the previous chord.Based on statistical analysis of the DadaGP and mySongBook datasets, we show that some chord diagrams are over-represented in western popular musicand that some chords can be played in more than 20 different ways.We argue that taking context into account can improve the variety and the quality of chord diagram suggestion, and compare this approach with a model taking only the current chord label into account.We show that adding previous context improves the F1-score on this task by up to 27% and reduces the propensity of the model to suggest standard open chords.We also define the notion of texture in the context of chord diagrams andshow through a variety of metrics that our model improves textureconsistencywith the previous diagram.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14260v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sound and Music Computing Conference, Jul 2024, Porto, Portugal</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre d'Hooge (LaBRI, SCRIME), Louis Bigo (LaBRI, SCRIME), Ken D\'eguernel, Nicolas Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Misinformation Detection using Large Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The increasing proliferation of misinformation and its alarming impact have motivated both industry and academia to develop approaches for misinformation detection and fact checking. Recent advances on large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable performance in various tasks, but whether and how LLMs could help with misinformation detection remains relatively underexplored. Most of existing state-of-the-art approaches either do not consider evidence and solely focus on claim related features or assume the evidence to be provided. Few approaches consider evidence retrieval as part of the misinformation detection but rely on fine-tuning models. In this paper, we investigate the potential of LLMs for misinformation detection in a zero-shot setting. We incorporate an evidence retrieval component into the process as it is crucial to gather pertinent information from various sources to detect the veracity of claims. To this end, we propose a novel re-ranking approach for multimodal evidence retrieval using both LLMs and large vision-language models (LVLM). The retrieved evidence samples (images and texts) serve as the input for an LVLM-based approach for multimodal fact verification (LVLM4FV). To enable a fair evaluation, we address the issue of incomplete ground truth for evidence samples in an existing evidence retrieval dataset by annotating a more complete set of evidence samples for both image and text retrieval. Our experimental results on two datasets demonstrate the superiority of the proposed approach in both evidence retrieval and fact verification tasks and also better generalization capability across dataset compared to the supervised baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14321v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahar Tahmasebi, Eric M\"uller-Budack, Ralph Ewerth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PolySinger: Singing-Voice to Singing-Voice Translation from English to Japanese</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14399v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The speech domain prevails in the spotlight for several natural language processing (NLP) tasks while the singing domain remains less explored. The culmination of NLP is the speech-to-speech translation (S2ST) task, referring to translation and synthesis of human speech. A disparity between S2ST and the possible adaptation to the singing domain, which we describe as singing-voice to singing-voice translation (SV2SVT), is becoming prominent as the former is progressing ever faster, while the latter is at a standstill. Singing-voice synthesis systems are overcoming the barrier of multi-lingual synthesis, despite limited attention has been paid to multi-lingual songwriting and song translation. This paper endeavors to determine what is required for successful SV2SVT and proposes PolySinger (Polyglot Singer): the first system for SV2SVT, performing lyrics translation from English to Japanese. A cascaded approach is proposed to establish a framework with a high degree of control which can potentially diminish the disparity between SV2SVT and S2ST. The performance of PolySinger is evaluated by a mean opinion score test with native Japanese speakers. Results and in-depth discussions with test subjects suggest a solid foundation for SV2SVT, but several shortcomings must be overcome, which are discussed for the future of SV2SVT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14399v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silas Antonisen, Iv\'an L\'opez-Espejo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChatQA 2: Bridging the Gap to Proprietary LLMs in Long Context and RAG Capabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14482v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we introduce ChatQA 2, a Llama3-based model designed to bridge the gap between open-access LLMs and leading proprietary models (e.g., GPT-4-Turbo) in long-context understanding and retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) capabilities. These two capabilities are essential for LLMs to process large volumes of information that cannot fit into a single prompt and are complementary to each other, depending on the downstream tasks and computational budgets. We present a detailed continued training recipe to extend the context window of Llama3-70B-base from 8K to 128K tokens, along with a three-stage instruction tuning process to enhance the model's instruction-following, RAG performance, and long-context understanding capabilities. Our results demonstrate that the Llama3-ChatQA-2-70B model achieves accuracy comparable to GPT-4-Turbo-2024-0409 on many long-context understanding tasks and surpasses it on the RAG benchmark. Interestingly, we find that the state-of-the-art long-context retriever can alleviate the top-k context fragmentation issue in RAG, further improving RAG-based results for long-context understanding tasks. We also provide extensive comparisons between RAG and long-context solutions using state-of-the-art long-context LLMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14482v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Xu, Wei Ping, Xianchao Wu, Zihan Liu, Mohammad Shoeybi, Bryan Catanzaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Recommendation with Controllable Diversification: Representation Degeneration and Diversity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.11986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.11986v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sequential recommendation (SR) models the dynamic user preferences and generates the next-item prediction as the affinity between the sequence and items, in a joint latent space with low dimensions (i.e., the sequence and item embedding space). Both sequence and item representations suffer from the representation degeneration issue due to the user/item long-tail distributions, where tail users/ items are indistinguishably distributed as a narrow cone in the latent space. We argue that the representation degeneration issue is the root cause of insufficient recommendation diversity in existing SR methods, impairing the user potential exploration and further worsening the echo chamber issue.
  In this work, we first disclose the connection between the representation degeneration and recommendation diversity, in which severer representation degeneration indicates lower recommendation diversity. We then propose a novel Singular sPectrum sMoothing regularization for Recommendation (SPMRec), which acts as a controllable surrogate to alleviate the degeneration and achieve the balance between recommendation diversity and performance. The proposed smoothing regularization alleviates the degeneration by maximizing the area under the singular value curve, which is also the diversity surrogate. We conduct experiments on four benchmark datasets to demonstrate the superiority of SPMRec, and show that the proposed singular spectrum smoothing can control the balance of recommendation performance and diversity simultaneously.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.11986v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziwei Fan, Zhiwei Liu, Hao Peng, Philip S. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transparent and Scrutable Recommendations Using Natural Language User Profiles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05810v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent state-of-the-art recommender systems predominantly rely on either implicit or explicit feedback from users to suggest new items. While effective in recommending novel options, many recommender systems often use uninterpretable embeddings to represent user preferences. This lack of transparency not only limits user understanding of why certain items are suggested but also reduces the user's ability to scrutinize and modify their preferences, thereby affecting their ability to receive a list of preferred recommendations. Given the recent advances in Large Language Models (LLMs), we investigate how a properly crafted prompt can be used to summarize a user's preferences from past reviews and recommend items based only on language-based preferences. In particular, we study how LLMs can be prompted to generate a natural language (NL) user profile that holistically describe a user's preferences. These NL profiles can then be leveraged to fine-tune a LLM using only NL profiles to make transparent and scrutable recommendations. Furthermore, we validate the scrutability of our user profile-based recommender by investigating the impact on recommendation changes after editing NL user profiles. According to our evaluations of the model's rating prediction performance on two benchmarking rating prediction datasets, we observe that this novel approach maintains a performance level on par with established recommender systems in a warm-start setting. With a systematic analysis into the effect of updating user profiles and system prompts, we show the advantage of our approach in easier adjustment of user preferences and a greater autonomy over users' received recommendations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05810v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jerome Ramos, Hossen A. Rahmani, Xi Wang, Xiao Fu, Aldo Lipani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Retrieval Algorithms in Ad and Content Recommendation Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01712v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This survey examines the most effective retrieval algorithms utilized in ad recommendation and content recommendation systems. Ad targeting algorithms rely on detailed user profiles and behavioral data to deliver personalized advertisements, thereby driving revenue through targeted placements. Conversely, organic retrieval systems aim to improve user experience by recommending content that matches user preferences. This paper compares these two applications and explains the most effective methods employed in each.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01712v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhao, Fang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DCNv3: Towards Next Generation Deep Cross Network for CTR Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13349v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deep &amp; Cross Network and its derivative models have become an important paradigm in click-through rate (CTR) prediction due to their effective balance between computational cost and performance. However, these models face four major limitations: (1) while most models claim to capture high-order feature interactions, they often do so implicitly and non-interpretably through deep neural networks (DNN), which limits the trustworthiness of the model's predictions; (2) the performance of existing explicit feature interaction methods is often weaker than that of implicit DNN, undermining their necessity; (3) many models fail to adaptively filter noise while enhancing the order of feature interactions; (4) the fusion methods of most models cannot provide suitable supervision signals for their different interaction methods.
  To address the identified limitations, this paper proposes the next generation Deep Cross Network (DCNv3) and Shallow &amp; Deep Cross Network (SDCNv3). These models ensure interpretability in feature interaction modeling while exponentially increasing the order of feature interactions to achieve genuine Deep Crossing rather than just Deep &amp; Cross. Additionally, we employ a Self-Mask operation to filter noise and reduce the number of parameters in the cross network by half. In the fusion layer, we use a simple yet effective loss weight calculation method called Tri-BCE to provide appropriate supervision signals. Comprehensive experiments on six datasets demonstrate the effectiveness, efficiency, and interpretability of DCNv3 and SDCNv3. The code, running logs, and detailed hyperparameter configurations are available at: https://anonymous.4open.science/r/DCNv3-E352.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13349v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Honghao Li, Yiwen Zhang, Yi Zhang, Hanwei Li, Lei Sang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
