<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR</link>
    <description>cs.IR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 04:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>DELM: a Python toolkit for Data Extraction with Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have become powerful tools for annotating unstructured data. However, most existing workflows rely on ad hoc scripts, making reproducibility, robustness, and systematic evaluation difficult. To address these challenges, we introduce DELM (Data Extraction with Language Models), an open-source Python toolkit designed for rapid experimental iteration of LLM-based data extraction pipelines and for quantifying the trade-offs between them. DELM minimizes boilerplate code and offers a modular framework with structured outputs, built-in validation, flexible data-loading and scoring strategies, and efficient batch processing. It also includes robust support for working with LLM APIs, featuring retry logic, result caching, detailed cost tracking, and comprehensive configuration management. We showcase DELM's capabilities through two case studies: one featuring a novel prompt optimization algorithm, and another illustrating how DELM quantifies trade-offs between cost and coverage when selecting keywords to decide which paragraphs to pass to an LLM. DELM is available at \href{https://github.com/Center-for-Applied-AI/delm}{\texttt{github.com/Center-for-Applied-AI/delm}}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20617v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Fithian, Kirill Skobelev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provenance Analysis of Archaeological Artifacts via Multimodal RAG Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present a retrieval-augmented generation (RAG)-based system for provenance analysis of archaeological artifacts, designed to support expert reasoning by integrating multimodal retrieval and large vision-language models (VLMs). The system constructs a dual-modal knowledge base from reference texts and images, enabling raw visual, edge-enhanced, and semantic retrieval to identify stylistically similar objects. Retrieved candidates are synthesized by the VLM to generate structured inferences, including chronological, geographical, and cultural attributions, alongside interpretive justifications. We evaluate the system on a set of Eastern Eurasian Bronze Age artifacts from the British Museum. Expert evaluation demonstrates that the system produces meaningful and interpretable outputs, offering scholars concrete starting points for analysis and significantly alleviating the cognitive burden of navigating vast comparative corpora.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20769v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuo Zhang, Yuechun Sun, Ruiliang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Consistency of Learning Methods for Information Retrieval Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A range of approaches have been proposed for estimating the accuracy or robustness of the measured performance of IR methods. One is to use bootstrapping of test sets, which, as we confirm, provides an estimate of variation in performance. For IR methods that rely on a seed, such as those that involve machine learning, another approach is to use a random set of seeds to examine performance variation. Using three different IR tasks we have used such randomness to examine a range of traditional statistical learning models and transformer-based learning models. While the statistical models are stable, the transformer models show huge variation as seeds are changed. In 9 of 11 cases the F1-scores (in the range 0.0--1.0) had a standard deviation of over 0.075; while 7 of 11 precision values (also in the range 0.0--1.0) had a standard deviation of over 0.125. This is in a context where differences of less than 0.02 have been used as evidence of method improvement. Our findings highlight the vulnerability of transformer models to training instabilities and moreover raise questions about the reliability of previous results, thus underscoring the need for rigorous evaluation practices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20804v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng Yuan, Justin Zobel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RecIS: Sparse to Dense, A Unified Training Framework for Recommendation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose RecIS, a unified Sparse-Dense training framework designed to achieve two primary goals: 1. Unified Framework To create a Unified sparse-dense training framework based on the PyTorch ecosystem that meets the training needs of industrial-grade recommendation models that integrated with large models. 2.System Optimization To optimize the sparse component, offering superior efficiency over the TensorFlow-based recommendation models. The dense component, meanwhile, leverages existing optimization technologies within the PyTorch ecosystem. Currently, RecIS is being used in Alibaba for numerous large-model enhanced recommendation training tasks, and some traditional sparse models have also begun training in it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20883v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua Zong, Qingtao Zeng, Zhengxiong Zhou, Zhihua Han, Zhensong Yan, Mingjie Liu, Hechen Sun, Jiawei Liu, Yiwen Hu, Qi Wang, YiHan Xian, Wenjie Guo, Houyuan Xiang, Zhiyuan Zeng, Xiangrong Sheng, Bencheng Yan, Nan Hu, Yuheng Huang, Jinqing Lian, Ziru Xu, Yan Zhang, Ju Huang, Siran Yang, Huimin Yi, Jiamang Wang, Pengjie Wang, Han Zhu, Jian Wu, Dan Ou, Jian Xu, Haihong Tang, Yuning Jiang, Bo Zheng, Lin Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FORGE: Forming Semantic Identifiers for Generative Retrieval in Industrial Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Semantic identifiers (SIDs) have gained increasing attention in generative retrieval (GR) due to their meaningful semantic discriminability. However, current research on SIDs faces three main challenges: (1) the absence of large-scale public datasets with multimodal features, (2) limited investigation into optimization strategies for SID generation, which typically rely on costly GR training for evaluation, and (3) slow online convergence in industrial deployment. To address these challenges, we propose FORGE, a comprehensive benchmark for FOrming semantic identifieR in Generative rEtrieval with industrial datasets. Specifically, FORGE is equipped with a dataset comprising 14 billion user interactions and multimodal features of 250 million items sampled from Taobao, one of the biggest e-commerce platforms in China. Leveraging this dataset, FORGE explores several optimizations to enhance the SID construction and validates their effectiveness via offline experiments across different settings and tasks. Further online analysis conducted on our platform, which serves over 300 million users daily, reveals a 0.35% increase in transaction count, highlighting the practical impact of our method. Regarding the expensive SID validation accompanied by the full training of GRs, we propose two novel metrics of SID that correlate positively with recommendation performance, enabling convenient evaluations without any GR training. For real-world applications, FORGE introduces an offline pretraining schema that reduces online convergence by half. The code and data are available at https://github.com/selous123/al_sid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20904v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kairui Fu, Tao Zhang, Shuwen Xiao, Ziyang Wang, Xinming Zhang, Chenchi Zhang, Yuliang Yan, Junjun Zheng, Yu Li, Zhihong Chen, Jian Wu, Xiangheng Kong, Shengyu Zhang, Kun Kuang, Yuning Jiang, Bo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markup Language Modeling for Web Document Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Web information extraction (WIE) is an important part of many e-commerce systems, supporting tasks like customer analysis and product recommendation. In this work, we look at the problem of building up-to-date product databases by extracting detailed information from shopping review websites. We fine-tuned MarkupLM on product data gathered from review sites of different sizes and then developed a variant we call MarkupLM++, which extends predictions to internal nodes of the DOM tree. Our experiments show that using larger and more diverse training sets improves extraction accuracy overall. We also find that including internal nodes helps with some product attributes, although it leads to a slight drop in overall performance. The final model reached a precision of 0.906, recall of 0.724, and an F1 score of 0.805.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20940v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Su Liu, Bin Bi, Jan Bakus, Paritosh Kumar Velalam, Vijay Yella, Vinod Hegde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rejuvenating Cross-Entropy Loss in Knowledge Distillation for Recommender Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20989v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper analyzes Cross-Entropy (CE) loss in knowledge distillation (KD) for recommender systems. KD for recommender systems targets at distilling rankings, especially among items most likely to be preferred, and can only be computed on a small subset of items. Considering these features, we reveal the connection between CE loss and NDCG in the field of KD. We prove that when performing KD on an item subset, minimizing CE loss maximizes the lower bound of NDCG, only if an assumption of closure is satisfied. It requires that the item subset consists of the student's top items. However, this contradicts our goal of distilling rankings of the teacher's top items. We empirically demonstrate the vast gap between these two kinds of top items. To bridge the gap between our goal and theoretical support, we propose Rejuvenated Cross-Entropy for Knowledge Distillation (RCE-KD). It splits the top items given by the teacher into two subsets based on whether they are highly ranked by the student. For the subset that defies the condition, a sampling strategy is devised to use teacher-student collaboration to approximate our assumption of closure. We also combine the losses on the two subsets adaptively. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our method. Our code is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/RCE-KD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20989v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhangchi Zhu, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IntSR: An Integrated Generative Framework for Search and Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21179v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generative recommendation has emerged as a promising paradigm, demonstrating remarkable results in both academic benchmarks and industrial applications. However, existing systems predominantly focus on unifying retrieval and ranking while neglecting the integration of search and recommendation (S&amp;R) tasks. What makes search and recommendation different is how queries are formed: search uses explicit user requests, while recommendation relies on implicit user interests. As for retrieval versus ranking, the distinction comes down to whether the queries are the target items themselves. Recognizing the query as central element, we propose IntSR, an integrated generative framework for S&amp;R. IntSR integrates these disparate tasks using distinct query modalities. It also addresses the increased computational complexity associated with integrated S&amp;R behaviors and the erroneous pattern learning introduced by a dynamically changing corpus. IntSR has been successfully deployed across various scenarios in Amap, leading to substantial improvements in digital asset's GMV(+3.02%), POI recommendation's CTR(+2.76%), and travel mode suggestion's ACC(+5.13%).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21179v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huimin Yan, Longfei Xu, Junjie Sun, Ni Ou, Wei Luo, Xing Tan, Ran Cheng, Kaikui Liu, Xiangxiang Chu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Recommendation Agent with Active User Commands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditional recommender systems rely on passive feedback mechanisms that limit users to simple choices such as like and dislike. However, these coarse-grained signals fail to capture users' nuanced behavior motivations and intentions. In turn, current systems cannot also distinguish which specific item attributes drive user satisfaction or dissatisfaction, resulting in inaccurate preference modeling. These fundamental limitations create a persistent gap between user intentions and system interpretations, ultimately undermining user satisfaction and harming system effectiveness.
  To address these limitations, we introduce the Interactive Recommendation Feed (IRF), a pioneering paradigm that enables natural language commands within mainstream recommendation feeds. Unlike traditional systems that confine users to passive implicit behavioral influence, IRF empowers active explicit control over recommendation policies through real-time linguistic commands. To support this paradigm, we develop RecBot, a dual-agent architecture where a Parser Agent transforms linguistic expressions into structured preferences and a Planner Agent dynamically orchestrates adaptive tool chains for on-the-fly policy adjustment. To enable practical deployment, we employ simulation-augmented knowledge distillation to achieve efficient performance while maintaining strong reasoning capabilities. Through extensive offline and long-term online experiments, RecBot shows significant improvements in both user satisfaction and business outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21317v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiakai Tang, Yujie Luo, Xunke Xi, Fei Sun, Xueyang Feng, Sunhao Dai, Chao Yi, Dian Chen, Zhujin Gao, Yang Li, Xu Chen, Wen Chen, Jian Wu, Yuning Jiang, Bo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic ReAct: Scalable Tool Selection for Large-Scale MCP Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20386v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present Dynamic ReAct, a novel approach for enabling ReAct agents to ef- ficiently operate with extensive Model Control Protocol (MCP) tool sets that exceed the contextual memory limitations of large language models. Our approach addresses the fundamental challenge of tool selection in environments containing hundreds or thousands of available tools, where loading all tools simultaneously is computationally infeasible. We propose and evaluate five distinct architectures that progressively refine the tool selection process, culminating in a search-and-load mechanism that achieves intelligent tool selection with minimal computational overhead. Our experimental results demonstrate that the proposed approach reduces tool loading by up to 50% while maintaining task completion accuracy, advancing the path towards truly general-purpose AI agents capable of dynamically adapting to diverse task environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20386v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nishant Gaurav, Adit Akarsh, Ankit Ranjan, Manoj Bajaj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SwasthLLM: a Unified Cross-Lingual, Multi-Task, and Meta-Learning Zero-Shot Framework for Medical Diagnosis Using Contrastive Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20567v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In multilingual healthcare environments, automatic disease diagnosis from clinical text remains a challenging task due to the scarcity of annotated medical data in low-resource languages and the linguistic variability across populations. This paper proposes SwasthLLM, a unified, zero-shot, cross-lingual, and multi-task learning framework for medical diagnosis that operates effectively across English, Hindi, and Bengali without requiring language-specific fine-tuning. At its core, SwasthLLM leverages the multilingual XLM-RoBERTa encoder augmented with a language-aware attention mechanism and a disease classification head, enabling the model to extract medically relevant information regardless of the language structure. To align semantic representations across languages, a Siamese contrastive learning module is introduced, ensuring that equivalent medical texts in different languages produce similar embeddings. Further, a translation consistency module and a contrastive projection head reinforce language-invariant representation learning. SwasthLLM is trained using a multi-task learning strategy, jointly optimizing disease classification, translation alignment, and contrastive learning objectives. Additionally, we employ Model-Agnostic Meta-Learning (MAML) to equip the model with rapid adaptation capabilities for unseen languages or tasks with minimal data. Our phased training pipeline emphasizes robust representation alignment before task-specific fine-tuning. Extensive evaluation shows that SwasthLLM achieves high diagnostic performance, with a test accuracy of 97.22% and an F1-score of 97.17% in supervised settings. Crucially, in zero-shot scenarios, it attains 92.78% accuracy on Hindi and 73.33% accuracy on Bengali medical text, demonstrating strong generalization in low-resource contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20567v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayan Sar, Pranav Singh Puri, Sumit Aich, Tanupriya Choudhury, Abhijit Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Reasoning Chains through Depth-Specialized Mixture-of-Experts in Transformer Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20577v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Contemporary transformer architectures apply identical processing depth to all inputs, creating inefficiencies and limiting reasoning quality. Simple factual queries are subjected to the same multilayered computation as complex logical problems, wasting resources while constraining deep inference. To overcome this, we came up with a concept of Dynamic Reasoning Chains through Depth Specialised Mixture of Experts (DS-MoE), a modular framework that extends the Mixture of Experts paradigm from width-based to depth specialised computation. DS-MoE introduces expert modules optimised for distinct reasoning depths, shallow pattern recognition, compositional reasoning, logical inference, memory integration, and meta-cognitive supervision. A learned routing network dynamically assembles custom reasoning chains, activating only the necessary experts to match input complexity. The dataset on which we trained and evaluated DS-MoE is on The Pile, an 800GB corpus covering diverse domains such as scientific papers, legal texts, programming code, and web content, enabling systematic assessment across reasoning depths. Experimental results demonstrate that DS-MoE achieves up to 16 per cent computational savings and 35 per cent faster inference compared to uniform-depth transformers, while delivering 2.8 per cent higher accuracy on complex multi-step reasoning benchmarks. Furthermore, routing decisions yield interpretable reasoning chains, enhancing transparency and scalability. These findings establish DS-MoE as a significant advancement in adaptive neural architectures, demonstrating that depth-specialised modular processing can simultaneously improve efficiency, reasoning quality, and interpretability in large-scale language models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20577v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sampurna Roy, Ayan Sar, Anurag Kaushish, Kanav Gupta, Tanupriya Choudhury, Abhijit Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Resolution Transformers: A Wavelet-Inspired Architecture for Multi-Scale Language Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20581v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Transformer architectures have achieved state-of-the-art performance across natural language tasks, yet they fundamentally misrepresent the hierarchical nature of human language by processing text as flat token sequences. This results in quadratic computational cost, weak computational cost, weak compositional generalization, and inadequate discourse-level modeling. We propose Hierarchical Resolution Transformer (HRT), a novel wavelet-inspired neural architecture that processes language simultaneously across multiple resolutions, from characters to discourse-level units. HRT constructs a multi-resolution attention, enabling bottom-up composition and top-down contextualization. By employing exponential sequence reduction across scales, HRT achieves O(nlogn) complexity, offering significant efficiency improvements over standard transformers. We evaluated HRT on a diverse suite of benchmarks, including GLUE, SuperGLUE, Long Range Arena, and WikiText-103, and results demonstrated that HRT outperforms standard transformer baselines by an average of +3.8% on GLUE, +4.5% on SuperGLUE, and +6.1% on Long Range Arena, while reducing memory usage by 42% and inference latency by 37% compared to BERT and GPT style models of similar parameter count. Ablation studies confirm the effectiveness of cross-resolution attention and scale-specialized modules, showing that each contributes independently to both efficiency and accuracy. Our findings establish HRT as the first architecture to align computational structure with the hierarchical organization of human language, demonstrating that multi-scale, wavelet-inspired processing yields both theoretical efficiency gains and practical improvements in language understanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20581v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayan Sar, Sampurna Roy, Kanav Gupta, Anurag Kaushish, Tanupriya Choudhury, Abhijit Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Few-Shot and Training-Free Review Generation via Conversational Prompting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Personalized review generation helps businesses understand user preferences, yet most existing approaches assume extensive review histories of the target user or require additional model training. Real-world applications often face few-shot and training-free situations, where only a few user reviews are available and fine-tuning is infeasible. It is well known that large language models (LLMs) can address such low-resource settings, but their effectiveness depends on prompt engineering. In this paper, we propose Conversational Prompting, a lightweight method that reformulates user reviews as multi-turn conversations. Its simple variant, Simple Conversational Prompting (SCP), relies solely on the user's own reviews, while the contrastive variant, Contrastive Conversational Prompting (CCP), inserts reviews from other users or LLMs as incorrect replies and then asks the model to correct them, encouraging the model to produce text in the user's style. Experiments on eight product domains and five LLMs showed that the conventional non-conversational prompt often produced reviews similar to those written by random users, based on text-based metrics such as ROUGE-L and BERTScore, and application-oriented tasks like user identity matching and sentiment analysis. In contrast, both SCP and CCP produced reviews much closer to those of the target user, even when each user had only two reviews. CCP brings further improvements when high-quality negative examples are available, whereas SCP remains competitive when such data cannot be collected. These results suggest that conversational prompting offers a practical solution for review generation under few-shot and training-free constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20805v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Genki Kusano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BESPOKE: Benchmark for Search-Augmented Large Language Model Personalization via Diagnostic Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21106v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Search-augmented large language models (LLMs) have advanced information-seeking tasks by integrating retrieval into generation, reducing users' cognitive burden compared to traditional search systems. Yet they remain insufficient for fully addressing diverse user needs, which requires recognizing how the same query can reflect different intents across users and delivering information in preferred forms. While recent systems such as ChatGPT and Gemini attempt personalization by leveraging user histories, systematic evaluation of such personalization is under-explored. To address this gap, we propose BESPOKE, the realistic benchmark for evaluating personalization in search-augmented LLMs. BESPOKE is designed to be both realistic, by collecting authentic chat and search histories directly from humans, and diagnostic, by pairing responses with fine-grained preference scores and feedback. The benchmark is constructed through long-term, deeply engaged human annotation, where human annotators contributed their own histories, authored queries with detailed information needs, and evaluated responses with scores and diagnostic feedback. Leveraging BESPOKE, we conduct systematic analyses that reveal key requirements for effective personalization in information-seeking tasks, providing a foundation for fine-grained evaluation of personalized search-augmented LLMs. Our code and data are available at https://augustinlib.github.io/BESPOKE/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21106v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyunseo Kim, Sangam Lee, Kwangwook Seo, Dongha Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrieval over Classification: Integrating Relation Semantics for Multimodal Relation Extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21151v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Relation extraction (RE) aims to identify semantic relations between entities in unstructured text. Although recent work extends traditional RE to multimodal scenarios, most approaches still adopt classification-based paradigms with fused multimodal features, representing relations as discrete labels. This paradigm has two significant limitations: (1) it overlooks structural constraints like entity types and positional cues, and (2) it lacks semantic expressiveness for fine-grained relation understanding. We propose \underline{R}etrieval \underline{O}ver \underline{C}lassification (ROC), a novel framework that reformulates multimodal RE as a retrieval task driven by relation semantics. ROC integrates entity type and positional information through a multimodal encoder, expands relation labels into natural language descriptions using a large language model, and aligns entity-relation pairs via semantic similarity-based contrastive learning. Experiments show that our method achieves state-of-the-art performance on the benchmark datasets MNRE and MORE and exhibits stronger robustness and interpretability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21151v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Hei, Tingjing Liao, Yingxin Pei, Yiyang Qi, Jiaqi Wang, Ruiting Li, Feiliang Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adoption, usability and perceived clinical value of a UK AI clinical reference platform (iatroX): a mixed-methods formative evaluation of real-world usage and a 1,223-respondent user survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Clinicians face growing information overload from biomedical literature and guidelines, hindering evidence-based care. Retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) with large language models may provide fast, provenance-linked answers, but requires real-world evaluation. We describe iatroX, a UK-centred RAG-based clinical reference platform, and report early adoption, usability, and perceived clinical value from a formative implementation evaluation. Methods comprised a retrospective analysis of usage across web, iOS, and Android over 16 weeks (8 April-31 July 2025) and an in-product intercept survey. Usage metrics were drawn from web and app analytics with bot filtering. A client-side script randomized single-item prompts to approx. 10% of web sessions from a predefined battery assessing usefulness, reliability, and adoption intent. Proportions were summarized with Wilson 95% confidence intervals; free-text comments underwent thematic content analysis. iatroX reached 19,269 unique web users, 202,660 engagement events, and approx. 40,000 clinical queries. Mobile uptake included 1,960 iOS downloads and Android growth (peak &gt;750 daily active users). The survey yielded 1,223 item-level responses: perceived usefulness 86.2% (95% CI 74.8-93.9%; 50/58); would use again 93.3% (95% CI 68.1-99.8%; 14/15); recommend to a colleague 88.4% (95% CI 75.1-95.9%; 38/43); perceived accuracy 75.0% (95% CI 58.8-87.3%; 30/40); reliability 79.4% (95% CI 62.1-91.3%; 27/34). Themes highlighted speed, guideline-linked answers, and UK specificity. Early real-world use suggests iatroX can mitigate information overload and support timely answers for UK clinicians. Limitations include small per-item samples and early-adopter bias; future work will include accuracy audits and prospective studies on workflow and care quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21188v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kolawole Tytler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SGMem: Sentence Graph Memory for Long-Term Conversational Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21212v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Long-term conversational agents require effective memory management to handle dialogue histories that exceed the context window of large language models (LLMs). Existing methods based on fact extraction or summarization reduce redundancy but struggle to organize and retrieve relevant information across different granularities of dialogue and generated memory. We introduce SGMem (Sentence Graph Memory), which represents dialogue as sentence-level graphs within chunked units, capturing associations across turn-, round-, and session-level contexts. By combining retrieved raw dialogue with generated memory such as summaries, facts and insights, SGMem supplies LLMs with coherent and relevant context for response generation. Experiments on LongMemEval and LoCoMo show that SGMem consistently improves accuracy and outperforms strong baselines in long-term conversational question answering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21212v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaxiong Wu, Yongyue Zhang, Sheng Liang, Yong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Query-Centric Graph Retrieval Augmented Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21237v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graph-based retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) enriches large language models (LLMs) with external knowledge for long-context understanding and multi-hop reasoning, but existing methods face a granularity dilemma: fine-grained entity-level graphs incur high token costs and lose context, while coarse document-level graphs fail to capture nuanced relations. We introduce QCG-RAG, a query-centric graph RAG framework that enables query-granular indexing and multi-hop chunk retrieval. Our query-centric approach leverages Doc2Query and Doc2Query{-}{-} to construct query-centric graphs with controllable granularity, improving graph quality and interpretability. A tailored multi-hop retrieval mechanism then selects relevant chunks via the generated queries. Experiments on LiHuaWorld and MultiHop-RAG show that QCG-RAG consistently outperforms prior chunk-based and graph-based RAG methods in question answering accuracy, establishing a new paradigm for multi-hop reasoning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21237v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaxiong Wu, Jianyuan Bo, Yongyue Zhang, Sheng Liang, Yong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Audio Fingerprinting Techniques for Real-Time Scalable Speech Retrieval and Speech Clusterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21876v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Audio fingerprinting techniques have seen great advances in recent years, enabling accurate and fast audio retrieval even in conditions when the queried audio sample has been highly deteriorated or recorded in noisy conditions. Expectedly, most of the existing work is centered around music, with popular music identification services such as Apple's Shazam or Google's Now Playing designed for individual audio recognition on mobile devices. However, the spectral content of speech differs from that of music, necessitating modifications to current audio fingerprinting approaches. This paper offers fresh insights into adapting existing techniques to address the specialized challenge of speech retrieval in telecommunications and cloud communications platforms. The focus is on achieving rapid and accurate audio retrieval in batch processing instead of facilitating single requests, typically on a centralized server. Moreover, the paper demonstrates how this approach can be utilized to support audio clustering based on speech transcripts without undergoing actual speech-to-text conversion. This optimization enables significantly faster processing without the need for GPU computing, a requirement for real-time operation that is typically associated with state-of-the-art speech-to-text tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21876v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/MIPRO60963.2024.10569239</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kemal Altwlkany, Sead Delali\'c, Adis Alihod\v{z}i\'c, Elmedin Selmanovi\'c, Damir Hasi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Laws for Online Advertisement Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13322v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The scaling law is a notable property of neural network models and has significantly propelled the development of large language models. Scaling laws hold great promise in guiding model design and resource allocation. Recent research increasingly shows that scaling laws are not limited to NLP tasks or Transformer architectures; they also apply to domains such as recommendation. However, there is still a lack of literature on scaling law research in online advertisement retrieval systems. This may be because 1) identifying the scaling law for resource cost and online revenue is often expensive in both time and training resources for industrial applications, and 2) varying settings for different systems prevent the scaling law from being applied across various scenarios. To address these issues, we propose a lightweight paradigm to identify online scaling laws of retrieval models, incorporating a novel offline metric and an offline simulation algorithm. We prove that under mild assumptions, the correlation between the novel metric and online revenue asymptotically approaches 1 and empirically validates its effectiveness. The simulation algorithm can estimate the machine cost offline. Based on the lightweight paradigm, we can identify online scaling laws for retrieval models almost exclusively through offline experiments, and quickly estimate machine costs and revenues for given model configurations. We further validate the existence of scaling laws across mainstream model architectures (e.g., Transformer, MLP, and DSSM) in our real-world advertising system. With the identified scaling laws, we demonstrate practical applications for ROI-constrained model designing and multi-scenario resource allocation in the online advertising system. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to study identification and application of online scaling laws for online advertisement retrieval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13322v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunli Wang, Zhen Zhang, Zixuan Yang, Tianyu Xu, Zhiqiang Wang, Yu Li, Rufan Zhou, Zhiqiang Liu, Yanjie Zhu, Jian Yang, Shiyang Wen, Peng Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cascade! Human in the loop shortcomings can increase the risk of failures in recommender systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20099v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recommender systems are among the most commonly deployed systems today. Systems design approaches to AI-powered recommender systems have done well to urge recommender system developers to follow more intentional data collection, curation, and management procedures. So too has the "human-in-the-loop" paradigm been widely adopted, primarily to address the issue of accountability. However, in this paper, we take the position that human oversight in recommender system design also entails novel risks that have yet to be fully described. These risks are "codetermined" by the information context in which such systems are often deployed. Furthermore, new knowledge of the shortcomings of "human-in-the-loop" practices to deliver meaningful oversight of other AI systems suggest that they may also be inadequate for achieving socially responsible recommendations. We review how the limitations of human oversight may increase the chances of a specific kind of failure: a "cascade" or "compound" failure. We then briefly explore how the unique dynamics of three common deployment contexts can make humans in the loop more likely to fail in their oversight duties. We then conclude with two recommendations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20099v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wm. Matthew Kennedy, Nishanshi Shukla, Cigdem Patlak, Blake Chambers, Theodora Skeadas,  Tuesday, Kingsley Owadara, Aayush Dhanotiya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Taxonomy of Negation for NLP and Neural Retrievers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22337v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding and solving complex reasoning tasks is vital for addressing the information needs of a user. Although dense neural models learn contextualised embeddings, they still underperform on queries containing negation. To understand this phenomenon, we study negation in both traditional neural information retrieval and LLM-based models. We (1) introduce a taxonomy of negation that derives from philosophical, linguistic, and logical definitions; (2) generate two benchmark datasets that can be used to evaluate the performance of neural information retrieval models and to fine-tune models for a more robust performance on negation; and (3) propose a logic-based classification mechanism that can be used to analyze the performance of retrieval models on existing datasets. Our taxonomy produces a balanced data distribution over negation types, providing a better training setup that leads to faster convergence on the NevIR dataset. Moreover, we propose a classification schema that reveals the coverage of negation types in existing datasets, offering insights into the factors that might affect the generalization of fine-tuned models on negation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22337v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roxana Petcu, Samarth Bhargav, Maarten de Rijke, Evangelos Kanoulas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal-Counterfactual RAG: The Integration of Causal-Counterfactual Reasoning into RAG</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14435v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have transformed natural language processing (NLP), enabling diverse applications by integrating large-scale pre-trained knowledge. However, their static knowledge limits dynamic reasoning over external information, especially in knowledge-intensive domains. Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) addresses this challenge by combining retrieval mechanisms with generative modeling to improve contextual understanding. Traditional RAG systems suffer from disrupted contextual integrity due to text chunking and over-reliance on semantic similarity for retrieval, often resulting in shallow and less accurate responses. We propose Causal-Counterfactual RAG, a novel framework that integrates explicit causal graphs representing cause-effect relationships into the retrieval process and incorporates counterfactual reasoning grounded on the causal structure. Unlike conventional methods, our framework evaluates not only direct causal evidence but also the counterfactuality of associated causes, combining results from both to generate more robust, accurate, and interpretable answers. By leveraging causal pathways and associated hypothetical scenarios, Causal-Counterfactual RAG preserves contextual coherence, reduces hallucination, and enhances reasoning fidelity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14435v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harshad Khadilkar, Abhay Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
