<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR</link>
    <description>cs.IR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Vector embedding of multi-modal texts: a tool for discovery?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08216v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computer science texts are particularly rich in both narrative content and illustrative charts, algorithms, images, annotated diagrams, etc. This study explores the extent to which vector-based multimodal retrieval, powered by vision-language models (VLMs), can improve discovery across multi-modal (text and images) content. Using over 3,600 digitized textbook pages largely from computer science textbooks and a Vision Language Model (VLM), we generate multi-vector representations capturing both textual and visual semantics. These embeddings are stored in a vector database. We issue a benchmark of 75 natural language queries and compare retrieval performance to ground truth and across four similarity (distance) measures. The study is intended to expose both the strengths and weakenesses of such an approach. We find that cosine similarity most effectively retrieves semantically and visually relevant pages. We further discuss the practicality of using a vector database and multi-modal embedding for operational information retrieval. Our paper is intended to offer design insights for discovery over digital libraries.
  Keywords: Vector embedding, multi-modal document retrieval, vector database benchmark, digital library discovery</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08216v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beth Plale, Sai Navya Jyesta, Sachith Withana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soundtracks of Our Lives: How Age Influences Musical Preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The majority of research in recommender systems, be it algorithmic improvements, context-awareness, explainability, or other areas, evaluates these systems on datasets that capture user interaction over a relatively limited time span. However, recommender systems can very well be used continuously for extended time. Similarly so, user behavior may evolve over that extended time. Although media studies and psychology offer a wealth of research on the evolution of user preferences and behavior as individuals age, there has been scant research in this regard within the realm of user modeling and recommender systems. In this study, we investigate the evolution of user preferences and behavior using the LFM-2b dataset, which, to our knowledge, is the only dataset that encompasses a sufficiently extensive time frame to permit real longitudinal studies and includes age information about its users. We identify specific usage and taste preferences directly related to the age of the user, i.e., while younger users tend to listen broadly to contemporary popular music, older users have more elaborate and personalized listening habits. The findings yield important insights that open new directions for research in recommender systems, providing guidance for future efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08337v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3708319.3733673</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Arsen Matej Golubovikj, Bruce Ferwerda, Alan Said, Marko Tal\v{c}i\v{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning Foundations for Deep Research Systems: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06733v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep research systems, agentic AI that solve complex, multi-step tasks by coordinating reasoning, search across the open web and user files, and tool use, are moving toward hierarchical deployments with a Planner, Coordinator, and Executors. In practice, training entire stacks end-to-end remains impractical, so most work trains a single planner connected to core tools such as search, browsing, and code. While SFT imparts protocol fidelity, it suffers from imitation and exposure biases and underuses environment feedback. Preference alignment methods such as DPO are schema and proxy-dependent, off-policy, and weak for long-horizon credit assignment and multi-objective trade-offs. A further limitation of SFT and DPO is their reliance on human defined decision points and subskills through schema design and labeled comparisons. Reinforcement learning aligns with closed-loop, tool-interaction research by optimizing trajectory-level policies, enabling exploration, recovery behaviors, and principled credit assignment, and it reduces dependence on such human priors and rater biases.
  This survey is, to our knowledge, the first dedicated to the RL foundations of deep research systems. It systematizes work after DeepSeek-R1 along three axes: (i) data synthesis and curation; (ii) RL methods for agentic research covering stability, sample efficiency, long context handling, reward and credit design, multi-objective optimization, and multimodal integration; and (iii) agentic RL training systems and frameworks. We also cover agent architecture and coordination, as well as evaluation and benchmarks, including recent QA, VQA, long-form synthesis, and domain-grounded, tool-interaction tasks. We distill recurring patterns, surface infrastructure bottlenecks, and offer practical guidance for training robust, transparent deep research agents with RL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06733v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenjun Li, Zhi Chen, Jingru Lin, Hannan Cao, Wei Han, Sheng Liang, Zhi Zhang, Kuicai Dong, Dexun Li, Chen Zhang, Yong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Range Retrieval with Graph-Based Indices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13245v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Retrieving points based on proximity in a high-dimensional vector space is a crucial step in information retrieval applications. The approximate nearest neighbor search (ANNS) problem, which identifies the $k$ nearest neighbors for a query, has been extensively studied in recent years. However, comparatively little attention has been paid to the related problem of finding all points within a given distance of a query, the range retrieval problem, despite its applications in areas such as duplicate detection, plagiarism checking, and facial recognition. In this paper, we present new techniques for range retrieval on graph-based vector indices, which are known to achieve excellent performance on ANNS queries. Since a range query may have anywhere from no matching results to thousands of matching results in the database, we introduce a set of range retrieval algorithms based on modifications of the standard graph search that adapt to terminate quickly on queries in the former group, and to put more resources into finding results for the latter group. Due to the lack of existing benchmarks for range retrieval, we also undertake a comprehensive study of range characteristics of existing embedding datasets, and select a suitable range retrieval radius for eight existing datasets with up to 1 billion points in addition to one existing benchmark. We test our algorithms on these datasets, and find up to 100x improvement in query throughput over a standard graph search and the FAISS-IVF range search algorithm. We also find up to 10x improvement over a previously suggested modification of the standard beam search, and strong performance up to 1 billion data points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13245v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Magdalen Dobson Manohar, Taekseung Kim, Guy E. Blelloch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold-Start Recommendation with Knowledge-Guided Retrieval-Augmented Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20773v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cold-start items remain a persistent challenge in recommender systems due to their lack of historical user interactions, which collaborative models rely on. While recent zero-shot methods leverage large language models (LLMs) to address this, they often struggle with sparse metadata and hallucinated or incomplete knowledge. We propose ColdRAG, a retrieval-augmented generation approach that builds a domain-specific knowledge graph dynamically to enhance LLM-based recommendation in cold-start scenarios, without requiring task-specific fine-tuning. ColdRAG begins by converting structured item attributes into rich natural-language profiles, from which it extracts entities and relationships to construct a unified knowledge graph capturing item semantics. Given a user's interaction history, it scores edges in the graph using an LLM, retrieves candidate items with supporting evidence, and prompts the LLM to rank them. By enabling multi-hop reasoning over this graph, ColdRAG grounds recommendations in verifiable evidence, reducing hallucinations and strengthening semantic connections. Experiments on three public benchmarks demonstrate that ColdRAG surpasses existing zero-shot baselines in both Recall and NDCG. This framework offers a practical solution to cold-start recommendation by combining knowledge-graph reasoning with retrieval-augmented LLM generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20773v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wooseong Yang, Weizhi Zhang, Yuqing Liu, Yuwei Han, Yu Wang, Junhyun Lee, Philip S. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LESER: Learning to Expand via Search Engine-feedback Reinforcement in e-Commerce</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05570v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: User queries in e-commerce search are often vague, short, and underspecified, making it difficult for retrieval systems to match them accurately against structured product catalogs. This challenge is amplified by the one-to-many nature of user intent, where a single query can imply diverse and competing needs. Existing methods, including neural query expansion and prompting-based LLM approaches, fall short in real-world settings: they struggle to capture nuanced user intent, often generate outputs that violate platform constraints, and rely on workflows that are difficult to scale in production. We propose Learning to Expand via Search Engine-feedback Reinforcement (LESER), a novel framework that fine-tunes a context-aware LLM using real-time search engine feedback as supervision. LESER formulates query expansion as a retrieval optimization task and leverages Group Relative Policy Optimization to learn directly from relevance and coverage metrics. LESER is trained to reason over search results and produce high quality query expansions that align with platform rules and retrieval objectives. We evaluate LESER on large-scale, real-world e-commerce datasets, demonstrating substantial improvements in both offline and online settings. Our results show that LESER not only enhances semantic coverage and retrieval relevance but also delivers measurable gains in user engagement, making it a practical and scalable solution for modern search systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05570v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yipeng Zhang, Bowen Liu, Xiaoshuang Zhang, Aritra Mandal, Canran Xu, Zhe Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniSearch: Rethinking Search System with a Unified Generative Architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06887v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modern search systems play a crucial role in facilitating information acquisition. Traditional search engines typically rely on a cascaded architecture, where results are retrieved through recall, pre-ranking, and ranking stages. The complexity of designing and maintaining multiple modules makes it difficult to achieve holistic performance gains. Recent advances in generative recommendation have motivated the exploration of unified generative search as an alternative. However, existing approaches are not genuinely end-to-end: they typically train an item encoder to tokenize candidates first and then optimize a generator separately, leading to objective inconsistency and limited generalization. To address these limitations, we propose UniSearch, a unified generative search framework for Kuaishou Search. UniSearch replaces the cascaded pipeline with an end-to-end architecture that integrates a Search Generator and a Video Encoder. The Generator produces semantic identifiers of relevant items given a user query, while the Video Encoder learns latent item embeddings and provides their tokenized representations. A unified training framework jointly optimizes both components, enabling mutual enhancement and improving representation quality and generation accuracy. Furthermore, we introduce Search Preference Optimization (SPO), which leverages a reward model and real user feedback to better align generation with user preferences. Extensive experiments on industrial-scale datasets, together with online A/B testing in both short-video and live search scenarios, demonstrate the strong effectiveness and deployment potential of UniSearch. Notably, its deployment in live search yields the largest single-experiment improvement in recent years of our product's history, highlighting its practical value for real-world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06887v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahui Chen, Xiaoze Jiang, Zhibo Wang, Quanzhi Zhu, Junyao Zhao, Feng Hu, Kang Pan, Ao Xie, Maohua Pei, Zhiheng Qin, Hongjing Zhang, Zhixin Zhai, Xiaobo Guo, Runbin Zhou, Kefeng Wang, Mingyang Geng, Cheng Chen, Jingshan Lv, Yupeng Huang, Xiao Liang, Han Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whose Name Comes Up? Auditing LLM-Based Scholar Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00074v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper evaluates the performance of six open-weight LLMs (llama3-8b, llama3.1-8b, gemma2-9b, mixtral-8x7b, llama3-70b, llama3.1-70b) in recommending experts in physics across five tasks: top-k experts by field, influential scientists by discipline, epoch, seniority, and scholar counterparts. The evaluation examines consistency, factuality, and biases related to gender, ethnicity, academic popularity, and scholar similarity. Using ground-truth data from the American Physical Society and OpenAlex, we establish scholarly benchmarks by comparing model outputs to real-world academic records. Our analysis reveals inconsistencies and biases across all models. mixtral-8x7b produces the most stable outputs, while llama3.1-70b shows the highest variability. Many models exhibit duplication, and some, particularly gemma2-9b and llama3.1-8b, struggle with formatting errors. LLMs generally recommend real scientists, but accuracy drops in field-, epoch-, and seniority-specific queries, consistently favoring senior scholars. Representation biases persist, replicating gender imbalances (reflecting male predominance), under-representing Asian scientists, and over-representing White scholars. Despite some diversity in institutional and collaboration networks, models favor highly cited and productive scholars, reinforcing the rich-getricher effect while offering limited geographical representation. These findings highlight the need to improve LLMs for more reliable and equitable scholarly recommendations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00074v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Barolo, Chiara Valentin, Fariba Karimi, Luis Gal\'arraga, Gonzalo G. M\'endez, Lisette Esp\'in-Noboa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arce: Augmented Roberta with Contextualized Elucidations for Ner in Automated Rule Checking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07286v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurate information extraction from specialized texts is a critical challenge, particularly for named entity recognition (NER) in the architecture, engineering, and construction (AEC) domain to support automated rule checking (ARC). The performance of standard pre-trained models is often constrained by the domain gap, as they struggle to interpret the specialized terminology and complex relational contexts inherent in AEC texts. Although this issue can be mitigated by further pre-training on large, human-curated domain corpora, as exemplified by methods like ARCBERT, this approach is both labor-intensive and cost-prohibitive. Consequently, leveraging large language models (LLMs) for automated knowledge generation has emerged as a promising alternative. However, the optimal strategy for generating knowledge that can genuinely enhance smaller, efficient models remains an open question. To address this, we propose ARCE (augmented RoBERTa with contextualized elucidations), a novel approach that systematically explores and optimizes this generation process. ARCE employs an LLM to first generate a corpus of simple, direct explanations, which we term Cote, and then uses this corpus to incrementally pre-train a RoBERTa model prior to its fine-tuning on the downstream task. Our extensive experiments show that ARCE establishes a new state-of-the-art on a benchmark AEC dataset, achieving a Macro-F1 score of 77.20%. This result also reveals a key finding: simple, explanation-based knowledge proves surprisingly more effective than complex, role-based rationales for this task. The code is publicly available at:https://github.com/nxcc-lab/ARCE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07286v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Chen, Jinbao Tian, Yankui Li, Yuqi Lu, Zhou Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All for law and law for all: Adaptive RAG Pipeline for Legal Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13107v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has transformed how we approach text generation tasks by grounding Large Language Model (LLM) outputs in retrieved knowledge. This capability is especially critical in the legal domain. In this work, we introduce a novel end-to-end RAG pipeline that improves upon previous baselines using three targeted enhancements: (i) a context-aware query translator that disentangles document references from natural-language questions and adapts retrieval depth and response style based on expertise and specificity, (ii) open-source retrieval strategies using SBERT and GTE embeddings that achieve substantial performance gains while remaining cost-efficient, and (iii) a comprehensive evaluation and generation framework that combines RAGAS, BERTScore-F1, and ROUGE-Recall to assess semantic alignment and faithfulness across models and prompt designs. Our results show that carefully designed open-source pipelines can rival proprietary approaches in retrieval quality, while a custom legal-grounded prompt consistently produces more faithful and contextually relevant answers than baseline prompting. Taken together, these contributions demonstrate the potential of task-aware, component-level tuning to deliver legally grounded, reproducible, and cost-effective RAG systems for legal research assistance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13107v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Figarri Keisha, Prince Singh,  Pallavi, Dion Fernandes, Aravindh Manivannan, Ilham Wicaksono, Faisal Ahmad, Wiem Ben Rim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SciNLP: A Domain-Specific Benchmark for Full-Text Scientific Entity and Relation Extraction in NLP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07801v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Structured information extraction from scientific literature is crucial for capturing core concepts and emerging trends in specialized fields. While existing datasets aid model development, most focus on specific publication sections due to domain complexity and the high cost of annotating scientific texts. To address this limitation, we introduce SciNLP - a specialized benchmark for full-text entity and relation extraction in the Natural Language Processing (NLP) domain. The dataset comprises 60 manually annotated full-text NLP publications, covering 7,072 entities and 1,826 relations. Compared to existing research, SciNLP is the first dataset providing full-text annotations of entities and their relationships in the NLP domain. To validate the effectiveness of SciNLP, we conducted comparative experiments with similar datasets and evaluated the performance of state-of-the-art supervised models on this dataset. Results reveal varying extraction capabilities of existing models across academic texts of different lengths. Cross-comparisons with existing datasets show that SciNLP achieves significant performance improvements on certain baseline models. Using models trained on SciNLP, we implemented automatic construction of a fine-grained knowledge graph for the NLP domain. Our KG has an average node degree of 3.2 per entity, indicating rich semantic topological information that enhances downstream applications. The dataset is publicly available at https://github.com/AKADDC/SciNLP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07801v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Decheng Duan, Yingyi Zhang, Jitong Peng, Chengzhi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
