<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR</link>
    <description>cs.IR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 05:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>GPR: Towards a Generative Pre-trained One-Model Paradigm for Large-Scale Advertising Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As an intelligent infrastructure connecting users with commercial content, advertising recommendation systems play a central role in information flow and value creation within the digital economy. However, existing multi-stage advertising recommendation systems suffer from objective misalignment and error propagation, making it difficult to achieve global optimality, while unified generative recommendation models still struggle to meet the demands of practical industrial applications. To address these issues, we propose GPR (Generative Pre-trained Recommender), the first one-model framework that redefines advertising recommendation as an end-to-end generative task, replacing the traditional cascading paradigm with a unified generative approach. To realize GPR, we introduce three key innovations spanning unified representation, network architecture, and training strategy. First, we design a unified input schema and tokenization method tailored to advertising scenarios, mapping both ads and organic content into a shared multi-level semantic ID space, thereby enhancing semantic alignment and modeling consistency across heterogeneous data. Second, we develop the Heterogeneous Hierarchical Decoder (HHD), a dual-decoder architecture that decouples user intent modeling from ad generation, achieving a balance between training efficiency and inference flexibility while maintaining strong modeling capacity. Finally, we propose a multi-stage joint training strategy that integrates Multi-Token Prediction (MTP), Value-Aware Fine-Tuning and the Hierarchy Enhanced Policy Optimization (HEPO) algorithm, forming a complete generative recommendation pipeline that unifies interest modeling, value alignment, and policy optimization. GPR has been fully deployed in the Tencent Weixin Channels advertising system, delivering significant improvements in key business metrics including GMV and CTCVR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10138v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Zhang, Yi Li, Yue Liu, Changping Wang, Yuan Wang, Yuling Xiong, Xun Liu, Haiyang Wu, Qian Li, Enming Zhang, Jiawei Sun, Xin Xu, Zishuai Zhang, Ruoran Liu, Suyuan Huang, Zhaoxin Zhang, Zhengkai Guo, Shuojin Yang, Meng-Hao Guo, Huan Yu, Jie Jiang, Shi-Min Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Waste It: Guiding Generative Recommenders with Structured Human Priors via Multi-head Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimizing recommender systems for objectives beyond accuracy, such as diversity, novelty, and personalization, is crucial for long-term user satisfaction. To this end, industrial practitioners have accumulated vast amounts of structured domain knowledge, which we term human priors (e.g., item taxonomies, temporal patterns). This knowledge is typically applied through post-hoc adjustments during ranking or post-ranking. However, this approach remains decoupled from the core model learning, which is particularly undesirable as the industry shifts to end-to-end generative recommendation foundation models. On the other hand, many methods targeting these beyond-accuracy objectives often require architecture-specific modifications and discard these valuable human priors by learning user intent in a fully unsupervised manner.
  Instead of discarding the human priors accumulated over years of practice, we introduce a backbone-agnostic framework that seamlessly integrates these human priors directly into the end-to-end training of generative recommenders. With lightweight, prior-conditioned adapter heads inspired by efficient LLM decoding strategies, our approach guides the model to disentangle user intent along human-understandable axes (e.g., interaction types, long- vs. short-term interests). We also introduce a hierarchical composition strategy for modeling complex interactions across different prior types. Extensive experiments on three large-scale datasets demonstrate that our method significantly enhances both accuracy and beyond-accuracy objectives. We also show that human priors allow the backbone model to more effectively leverage longer context lengths and larger model sizes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10492v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunkai Zhang (Ryan), Qiang Zhang (Ryan),  Feng (Ryan),  Lin, Ruizhong Qiu, Hanchao Yu, Jason Liu, Yinglong Xia, Zhuoran Yu, Zeyu Zheng, Diji Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fixed-Persona SLMs with Modular Memory: Scalable NPC Dialogue on Consumer Hardware</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10277v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in generating human-like text, yet their applicability to dialogue systems in computer games remains limited. This limitation arises from their substantial hardware requirements, latency constraints, and the necessity to maintain clearly defined knowledge boundaries within a game setting. In this paper, we propose a modular NPC dialogue system that leverages Small Language Models (SLMs), fine-tuned to encode specific NPC personas and integrated with runtime-swappable memory modules. These memory modules preserve character-specific conversational context and world knowledge, enabling expressive interactions and long-term memory without retraining or model reloading during gameplay. We comprehensively evaluate our system using three open-source SLMs: DistilGPT-2, TinyLlama-1.1B-Chat, and Mistral-7B-Instruct, trained on synthetic persona-aligned data and benchmarked on consumer-grade hardware. While our approach is motivated by applications in gaming, its modular design and persona-driven memory architecture hold significant potential for broader adoption in domains requiring expressive, scalable, and memory-rich conversational agents, such as virtual assistants, customer support bots, or interactive educational systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10277v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Braas, Lukas Esterle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BroadGen: A Framework for Generating Effective and Efficient Advertiser Broad Match Keyphrase Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19164v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the domain of sponsored search advertising, the focus of Keyphrase recommendation has largely been on exact match types, which pose issues such as high management expenses, limited targeting scope, and evolving search query patterns. Alternatives like Broad match types can alleviate certain drawbacks of exact matches but present challenges like poor targeting accuracy and minimal supervisory signals owing to limited advertiser usage. This research defines the criteria for an ideal broad match, emphasizing on both efficiency and effectiveness, ensuring that a significant portion of matched queries are relevant. We propose BroadGen, an innovative framework that recommends efficient and effective broad match keyphrases by utilizing historical search query data. Additionally, we demonstrate that BroadGen, through token correspondence modeling, maintains better query stability over time. BroadGen's capabilities allow it to serve daily, millions of sellers at eBay with over 2.5 billion items.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19164v5</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashirbad Mishra, Jinyu Zhao, Soumik Dey, Hansi Wu, Binbin Li, Kamesh Madduri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrieval-Augmented Generation for Reliable Interpretation of Radio Regulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09651v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study question answering in the domain of radio regulations, a legally sensitive and high-stakes area. We propose a telecom-specific Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) pipeline and introduce, to our knowledge, the first multiple-choice evaluation set for this domain, constructed from authoritative sources using automated filtering and human validation. To assess retrieval quality, we define a domain-specific retrieval metric, under which our retriever achieves approximately 97% accuracy. Beyond retrieval, our approach consistently improves generation accuracy across all tested models. In particular, while naively inserting documents without structured retrieval yields only marginal gains for GPT-4o (less than 1%), applying our pipeline results in nearly a 12% relative improvement. These findings demonstrate that carefully targeted grounding provides a simple yet strong baseline and an effective domain-specific solution for regulatory question answering. All code and evaluation scripts, along with our derived question-answer dataset, are available at https://github.com/Zakaria010/Radio-RAG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09651v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zakaria El Kassimi, Fares Fourati, Mohamed-Slim Alouini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search Is Not Retrieval: Decoupling Semantic Matching from Contextual Assembly in RAG</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04939v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Retrieval systems are essential to contemporary AI pipelines, although most confuse two separate processes: finding relevant information and giving enough context for reasoning. We introduce the Search-Is-Not-Retrieve (SINR) framework, a dual-layer architecture that distinguishes between fine-grained search representations and coarse-grained retrieval contexts. SINR enhances the composability, scalability, and context fidelity of retrieval systems by directly connecting small, semantically accurate search chunks to larger, contextually complete retrieve chunks, all without incurring extra processing costs. This design changes retrieval from a passive step to an active one, making the system architecture more like how people process information. We discuss the SINR framework's conceptual foundation, formal structure, implementation issues, and qualitative outcomes. This provides a practical foundation for the next generation of AI systems that use retrieval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04939v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harshit Nainwani, Hediyeh Baban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DatAasee -- A Metadata-Lake as Metadata Catalog for a Virtual Data-Lake</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05512v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Metadata management for distributed data sources is a long-standing but ever-growing problem. To counter this challenge in a research-data and library-oriented setting, this work constructs a data architecture, derived from the data-lake: the metadata-lake. A proof-of-concept implementation of this proposed metadata aggregator is presented, too, and also evaluated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05512v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Himpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Captions Speak Louder than Images: Generalizing Foundation Models for E-commerce from High-quality Multimodal Instruction Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17337v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Leveraging multimodal data to drive breakthroughs in e-commerce applications through Multimodal Foundation Models (MFMs) is gaining increasing attention from the research community. However, there are significant challenges that hinder the optimal use of multimodal e-commerce data by foundation models: (1) the scarcity of large-scale, high-quality multimodal benchmark datasets; and (2) the lack of effective multimodal information integration methods. To address these challenges, in this paper, we introduce MMECInstruct, the first-ever, large-scale, and high-quality multimodal instruction dataset for e-commerce. We also develop CASLIE, a simple, lightweight, yet effective framework for integrating multimodal information for e-commerce. Leveraging MMECInstruct, we fine-tune a series of e-commerce MFMs within CASLIE, denoted as CASLIE models. Our comprehensive evaluation demonstrates that CASLIE models substantially outperform 5 categories of advanced baseline models in the in-domain evaluation. Moreover, CASLIE models show strong generalizability to out-of-domain settings. MMECInstruct and CASLIE models are publicly accessible through https://ninglab.github.io/CASLIE/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17337v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyi Ling, Hanwen Du, Bo Peng, Zhihui Zhu, Xia Ning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMTEB: Massive Multilingual Text Embedding Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13595v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Text embeddings are typically evaluated on a limited set of tasks, which are constrained by language, domain, and task diversity. To address these limitations and provide a more comprehensive evaluation, we introduce the Massive Multilingual Text Embedding Benchmark (MMTEB) - a large-scale, community-driven expansion of MTEB, covering over 500 quality-controlled evaluation tasks across 250+ languages. MMTEB includes a diverse set of challenging, novel tasks such as instruction following, long-document retrieval, and code retrieval, representing the largest multilingual collection of evaluation tasks for embedding models to date. Using this collection, we develop several highly multilingual benchmarks, which we use to evaluate a representative set of models. We find that while large language models (LLMs) with billions of parameters can achieve state-of-the-art performance on certain language subsets and task categories, the best-performing publicly available model is multilingual-e5-large-instruct with only 560 million parameters. To facilitate accessibility and reduce computational cost, we introduce a novel downsampling method based on inter-task correlation, ensuring a diverse selection while preserving relative model rankings. Furthermore, we optimize tasks such as retrieval by sampling hard negatives, creating smaller but effective splits. These optimizations allow us to introduce benchmarks that drastically reduce computational demands. For instance, our newly introduced zero-shot English benchmark maintains a ranking order similar to the full-scale version but at a fraction of the computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13595v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenneth Enevoldsen, Isaac Chung, Imene Kerboua, M\'arton Kardos, Ashwin Mathur, David Stap, Jay Gala, Wissam Siblini, Dominik Krzemi\'nski, Genta Indra Winata, Saba Sturua, Saiteja Utpala, Mathieu Ciancone, Marion Schaeffer, Gabriel Sequeira, Diganta Misra, Shreeya Dhakal, Jonathan Rystr{\o}m, Roman Solomatin, \"Omer \c{C}a\u{g}atan, Akash Kundu, Martin Bernstorff, Shitao Xiao, Akshita Sukhlecha, Bhavish Pahwa, Rafa{\l} Po\'swiata, Kranthi Kiran GV, Shawon Ashraf, Daniel Auras, Bj\"orn Pl\"uster, Jan Philipp Harries, Lo\"ic Magne, Isabelle Mohr, Mariya Hendriksen, Dawei Zhu, Hippolyte Gisserot-Boukhlef, Tom Aarsen, Jan Kostkan, Konrad Wojtasik, Taemin Lee, Marek \v{S}uppa, Crystina Zhang, Roberta Rocca, Mohammed Hamdy, Andrianos Michail, John Yang, Manuel Faysse, Aleksei Vatolin, Nandan Thakur, Manan Dey, Dipam Vasani, Pranjal Chitale, Simone Tedeschi, Nguyen Tai, Artem Snegirev, Michael G\"unther, Mengzhou Xia, Weijia Shi, Xing Han L\`u, Jordan Clive, Gayatri Krishnakumar, Anna Maksimova, Silvan Wehrli, Maria Tikhonova, Henil Panchal, Aleksandr Abramov, Malte Ostendorff, Zheng Liu, Simon Clematide, Lester James Miranda, Alena Fenogenova, Guangyu Song, Ruqiya Bin Safi, Wen-Ding Li, Alessia Borghini, Federico Cassano, Hongjin Su, Jimmy Lin, Howard Yen, Lasse Hansen, Sara Hooker, Chenghao Xiao, Vaibhav Adlakha, Orion Weller, Siva Reddy, Niklas Muennighoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LoVR: A Benchmark for Long Video Retrieval in Multimodal Contexts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13928v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Long videos contain a vast amount of information, making video-text retrieval an essential and challenging task in multimodal learning. However, existing benchmarks suffer from limited video duration, low-quality captions, and coarse annotation granularity, which hinder the evaluation of advanced video-text retrieval methods. To address these limitations, we introduce LoVR, a benchmark specifically designed for long video-text retrieval. LoVR contains 467 long videos and over 40,804 fine-grained clips with high-quality captions. To overcome the issue of poor machine-generated annotations, we propose an efficient caption generation framework that integrates VLM automatic generation, caption quality scoring, and dynamic refinement. This pipeline improves annotation accuracy while maintaining scalability. Furthermore, we introduce a semantic fusion method to generate coherent full-video captions without losing important contextual information. Our benchmark introduces longer videos, more detailed captions, and a larger-scale dataset, presenting new challenges for video understanding and retrieval. Extensive experiments on various advanced embedding models demonstrate that LoVR is a challenging benchmark, revealing the limitations of current approaches and providing valuable insights for future research. We release the code and dataset link at https://github.com/TechNomad-ds/LoVR-benchmark</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13928v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qifeng Cai, Hao Liang, Hejun Dong, Meiyi Qiang, Ruichuan An, Zhaoyang Han, Zhengzhou Zhu, Bin Cui, Wentao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Do Open-Source LLMs Struggle with Data Analysis? A Systematic Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19794v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) hold promise in automating data analysis tasks, yet open-source models face significant limitations in these kinds of reasoning-intensive scenarios. In this work, we investigate strategies to enhance the data analysis capabilities of open-source LLMs. By curating a seed dataset of diverse, realistic scenarios, we evaluate model behavior across three core dimensions: data understanding, code generation, and strategic planning. Our analysis reveals three key findings: (1) Strategic planning quality serves as the primary determinant of model performance; (2) Interaction design and task complexity significantly influence reasoning capabilities; (3) Data quality demonstrates a greater impact than diversity in achieving optimal performance. We leverage these insights to develop a data synthesis methodology, demonstrating significant improvements in open-source LLMs' analytical reasoning capabilities. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/DataMind.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19794v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuqi Zhu, Yi Zhong, Jintian Zhang, Ziheng Zhang, Shuofei Qiao, Yujie Luo, Lun Du, Da Zheng, Ningyu Zhang, Huajun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planning Agents on an Ego-Trip: Leveraging Hybrid Ego-Graph Ensembles for Improved Tool Retrieval in Enterprise Task Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05888v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Effective tool pre-selection via retrieval is essential for AI agents to select from a vast array of tools when identifying and planning actions in the context of complex user queries. Despite its central role in planning, this aspect remains underexplored in the literature. Traditional approaches rely primarily on similarities between user queries and tool descriptions, which significantly limits retrieval accuracy, specifically when handling multi-step user requests. To address these limitations, we propose a Knowledge Graph (KG)-based tool retrieval framework that captures the semantic relationships between tools and their functional dependencies. Our retrieval algorithm leverages ensembles of 1-hop ego tool graphs to model direct and indirect connections between tools, enabling more comprehensive and contextual tool selection for multi-step tasks. We evaluate our approach on a synthetically generated internal dataset across six defined user classes, extending previous work on coherent dialogue synthesis and tool retrieval benchmarks. Results demonstrate that our tool graph-based method achieves 91.85% tool coverage on the micro-average CompleteRecall metric, compared to 89.26% for re-ranked semantic-lexical hybrid retrieval, the strongest non-KG baseline in our experiments. These findings support our hypothesis that the structural information modeled in the graph provides complementary signals to pure similarity matching, particularly for queries requiring sequential tool composition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05888v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Bansal, Sai Shruthi Sistla, Aarti Arikatala, Sebastian Schreiber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking Forward and Backward: Multi-Objective Reinforcement Learning for Retrieval-Augmented Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09109v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) has proven to be effective in mitigating hallucinations in large language models, yet its effectiveness remains limited in complex, multi-step reasoning scenarios. Recent efforts have incorporated search-based interactions into RAG, enabling iterative reasoning with real-time retrieval. Most approaches rely on outcome-based supervision, offering no explicit guidance for intermediate steps. This often leads to reward hacking and degraded response quality. We propose Bi-RAR, a novel retrieval-augmented reasoning framework that evaluates each intermediate step jointly in both forward and backward directions. To assess the information completeness of each step, we introduce a bidirectional information distance grounded in Kolmogorov complexity, approximated via language model generation probabilities. This quantification measures both how far the current reasoning is from the answer and how well it addresses the question. To optimize reasoning under these bidirectional signals, we adopt a multi-objective reinforcement learning framework with a cascading reward structure that emphasizes early trajectory alignment. Empirical results on seven question answering benchmarks demonstrate that Bi-RAR surpasses previous methods and enables efficient interaction and reasoning with the search engine during training and inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09109v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenda Wei, Yu-An Liu, Ruqing Zhang, Jiafeng Guo, Lixin Su, Shuaiqiang Wang, Dawei Yin, Maarten de Rijke, Xueqi Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
