<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR</link>
    <description>cs.IR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-based Semantic Search for Conversational Queries in E-commerce</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conversational user queries are increasingly challenging traditional e-commerce platforms, whose search systems are typically optimized for keyword-based queries. We present an LLM-based semantic search framework that effectively captures user intent from conversational queries by combining domain-specific embeddings with structured filters. To address the challenge of limited labeled data, we generate synthetic data using LLMs to guide the fine-tuning of two models: an embedding model that positions semantically similar products close together in the representation space, and a generative model for converting natural language queries into structured constraints. By combining similarity-based retrieval with constraint-based filtering, our framework achieves strong precision and recall across various settings compared to baseline approaches on a real-world dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16492v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emad Siddiqui, Venkatesh Terikuti, Xuan Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRISM: Purified Representation and Integrated Semantic Modeling for Generative Sequential Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generative Sequential Recommendation (GSR) has emerged as a promising paradigm, reframing recommendation as an autoregressive sequence generation task over discrete Semantic IDs (SIDs), typically derived via codebook-based quantization. Despite its great potential in unifying retrieval and ranking, existing GSR frameworks still face two critical limitations: (1) impure and unstable semantic tokenization, where quantization methods struggle with interaction noise and codebook collapse, resulting in SIDs with ambiguous discrimination; and (2) lossy and weakly structured generation, where reliance solely on coarse-grained discrete tokens inevitably introduces information loss and neglects items' hierarchical logic. To address these issues, we propose a novel generative recommendation framework, PRISM, with Purified Representation and Integrated Semantic Modeling. Specifically, to ensure high-quality tokenization, we design a Purified Semantic Quantizer that constructs a robust codebook via adaptive collaborative denoising and hierarchical semantic anchoring mechanisms. To compensate for information loss during quantization, we further propose an Integrated Semantic Recommender, which incorporates a dynamic semantic integration mechanism to integrate fine-grained semantics and enforces logical validity through a semantic structure alignment objective. PRISM consistently outperforms state-of-the-art baselines across four real-world datasets, demonstrating substantial performance gains, particularly in high-sparsity scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16556v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dengzhao Fang, Jingtong Gao, Yu Li, Xiangyu Zhao, Yi Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-powered Real-time Patent Citation Recommendation for Financial Technologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16775v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rapid financial innovation has been accompanied by a sharp increase in patenting activity, making timely and comprehensive prior-art discovery more difficult. This problem is especially evident in financial technologies, where innovations develop quickly, patent collections grow continuously, and citation recommendation systems must be updated as new applications arrive. Existing patent retrieval and citation recommendation methods typically rely on static indexes or periodic retraining, which limits their ability to operate effectively in such dynamic settings. In this study, we propose a real-time patent citation recommendation framework designed for large and fast-changing financial patent corpora. Using a dataset of 428,843 financial patents granted by the China National Intellectual Property Administration (CNIPA) between 2000 and 2024, we build a three-stage recommendation pipeline. The pipeline uses large language model (LLM) embeddings to represent the semantic content of patent abstracts, applies efficient approximate nearest-neighbor search to construct a manageable candidate set, and ranks candidates by semantic similarity to produce top-k citation recommendations. In addition to improving recommendation accuracy, the proposed framework directly addresses the dynamic nature of patent systems. By using an incremental indexing strategy based on hierarchical navigable small-world (HNSW) graphs, newly issued patents can be added without rebuilding the entire index. A rolling day-by-day update experiment shows that incremental updating improves recall while substantially reducing computational cost compared with rebuild-based indexing. The proposed method also consistently outperforms traditional text-based baselines and alternative nearest-neighbor retrieval approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16775v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianang Deng, Yu Deng, Tianchen Gao, Yonghong Hu, Rui Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PI2I: A Personalized Item-Based Collaborative Filtering Retrieval Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficiently selecting relevant content from vast candidate pools is a critical challenge in modern recommender systems. Traditional methods, such as item-to-item collaborative filtering (CF) and two-tower models, often fall short in capturing the complex user-item interactions due to uniform truncation strategies and overdue user-item crossing. To address these limitations, we propose Personalized Item-to-Item (PI2I), a novel two-stage retrieval framework that enhances the personalization capabilities of CF. In the first Indexer Building Stage (IBS), we optimize the retrieval pool by relaxing truncation thresholds to maximize Hit Rate, thereby temporarily retaining more items users might be interested in. In the second Personalized Retrieval Stage (PRS), we introduce an interactive scoring model to overcome the limitations of inner product calculations, allowing for richer modeling of intricate user-item interactions. Additionally, we construct negative samples based on the trigger-target (item-to-item) relationship, ensuring consistency between offline training and online inference. Offline experiments on large-scale real-world datasets demonstrate that PI2I outperforms traditional CF methods and rivals Two-Tower models. Deployed in the "Guess You Like" section on Taobao, PI2I achieved a 1.05% increase in online transaction rates. In addition, we have released a large-scale recommendation dataset collected from Taobao, containing 130 million real-world user interactions used in the experiments of this paper. The dataset is publicly available at https://huggingface.co/datasets/PI2I/PI2I, which could serve as a valuable benchmark for the research community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16815v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaoqing Wang, Yingcai Ma, Kairui Fu, Ziyang Wang, Dunxian Huang, Yuliang Yan, Jian Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating the Shift: A Comparative Analysis of Web Search and Generative AI Response Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16858v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rise of generative AI as a primary information source presents a paradigm shift from traditional web search. This paper presents a large-scale empirical study quantifying the fundamental differences between the results returned by Google Search and leading generative AI services. We analyze multiple dimensions, demonstrating that AI-generated answers and web search results diverge significantly in their consulted source domains, the typology of these domains (e.g., earned media vs. owned, social), query intent and the freshness of the information provided. We then investigate the role of LLM pre-training as a key factor shaping these differences, analyzing how this intrinsic knowledge base interacts with and influences real-time web search when enabled. Our findings reveal the distinct mechanics of these two information ecosystems, leading to critical observations on the emergent field of Answer Engine Optimization (AEO) and its contrast with traditional Search Engine Optimization (SEO).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16858v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahe Chen, Xiaoxuan Wang, Kaiwen Chen, Nick Koudas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Atom to Community: Structured and Evolving Agent Memory for User Behavior Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: User behavior modeling lies at the heart of personalized applications like recommender systems. With LLM-based agents, user preference representation has evolved from latent embeddings to semantic memory. While existing memory mechanisms show promise in textual dialogues, modeling non-textual behaviors remains challenging, as preferences must be inferred from implicit signals like clicks without ground truth supervision. Current approaches rely on a single unstructured summary, updated through simple overwriting. However, this is suboptimal: users exhibit multi-faceted interests that get conflated, preferences evolve yet naive overwriting causes forgetting, and sparse individual interactions necessitate collaborative signals. We present STEAM (\textit{\textbf{ST}ructured and \textbf{E}volving \textbf{A}gent \textbf{M}emory}), a novel framework that reimagines how agent memory is organized and updated. STEAM decomposes preferences into atomic memory units, each capturing a distinct interest dimension with explicit links to observed behaviors. To exploit collaborative patterns, STEAM organizes similar memories across users into communities and generates prototype memories for signal propagation. The framework further incorporates adaptive evolution mechanisms, including consolidation for refining memories and formation for capturing emerging interests. Experiments on three real-world datasets demonstrate that STEAM substantially outperforms state-of-the-art baselines in recommendation accuracy, simulation fidelity, and diversity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16872v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxin Liao, Le Wu, Min Hou, Yu Wang, Han Wu, Meng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explaining Group Recommendations via Counterfactuals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Group recommender systems help users make collective choices but often lack transparency, leaving group members uncertain about why items are suggested. Existing explanation methods focus on individuals, offering limited support for groups where multiple preferences interact. In this paper, we propose a framework for group counterfactual explanations, which reveal how removing specific past interactions would change a group recommendation. We formalize this concept, introduce utility and fairness measures tailored to groups, and design heuristic algorithms, such as Pareto-based filtering and grow-and-prune strategies, for efficient explanation discovery. Experiments on MovieLens and Amazon datasets show clear trade-offs: low-cost methods produce larger, less fair explanations, while other approaches yield concise and balanced results at higher cost. Furthermore, the Pareto-filtering heuristic demonstrates significant efficiency improvements in sparse settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16882v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Stratigi, Nikos Bikakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Segregation Before Polarization: How Recommendation Strategies Shape Echo Chamber Pathways</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16457v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Social media platforms facilitate echo chambers through feedback loops between user preferences and recommendation algorithms. While algorithmic homogeneity is well-documented, the distinct evolutionary pathways driven by content-based versus link-based recommendations remain unclear. Using an extended dynamic Bounded Confidence Model (BCM), we show that content-based algorithms--unlike their link-based counterparts--steer social networks toward a segregation-before-polarization (SbP) pathway. Along this trajectory, structural segregation precedes opinion divergence, accelerating individual isolation while delaying but ultimately intensifying collective polarization. Furthermore, we reveal a paradox in information sharing: Reposting increases the number of connections in the network, yet it simultaneously reinforces echo chambers because it amplifies small, latent opinion differences that would otherwise remain inconsequential. These findings suggest that mitigating polarization requires stage-dependent algorithmic interventions, shifting from content-centric to structure-centric strategies as networks evolve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16457v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junning Zhao, Kazutoshi Sasahara, Yu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better Generalizing to Unseen Concepts: An Evaluation Framework and An LLM-Based Auto-Labeled Pipeline for Biomedical Concept Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16711v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generalization to unseen concepts is a central challenge due to the scarcity of human annotations in Mention-agnostic Biomedical Concept Recognition (MA-BCR). This work makes two key contributions to systematically address this issue. First, we propose an evaluation framework built on hierarchical concept indices and novel metrics to measure generalization. Second, we explore LLM-based Auto-Labeled Data (ALD) as a scalable resource, creating a task-specific pipeline for its generation. Our research unequivocally shows that while LLM-generated ALD cannot fully substitute for manual annotations, it is a valuable resource for improving generalization, successfully providing models with the broader coverage and structural knowledge needed to approach recognizing unseen concepts. Code and datasets are available at https://github.com/bio-ie-tool/hi-ald.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16711v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shanshan Liu, Noriki Nishida, Fei Cheng, Narumi Tokunaga, Rumana Ferdous Munne, Yuki Yamagata, Kouji Kozaki, Takehito Utsuro, Yuji Matsumoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empowering Medical Equipment Sustainability in Low-Resource Settings: An AI-Powered Diagnostic and Support Platform for Biomedical Technicians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In low- and middle-income countries (LMICs), a significant proportion of medical diagnostic equipment remains underutilized or non-functional due to a lack of timely maintenance, limited access to technical expertise, and minimal support from manufacturers, particularly for devices acquired through third-party vendors or donations. This challenge contributes to increased equipment downtime, delayed diagnoses, and compromised patient care. This research explores the development and validation of an AI-powered support platform designed to assist biomedical technicians in diagnosing and repairing medical devices in real-time. The system integrates a large language model (LLM) with a user-friendly web interface, enabling imaging technologists/radiographers and biomedical technicians to input error codes or device symptoms and receive accurate, step-by-step troubleshooting guidance. The platform also includes a global peer-to-peer discussion forum to support knowledge exchange and provide additional context for rare or undocumented issues. A proof of concept was developed using the Philips HDI 5000 ultrasound machine, achieving 100% precision in error code interpretation and 80% accuracy in suggesting corrective actions. This study demonstrates the feasibility and potential of AI-driven systems to support medical device maintenance, with the aim of reducing equipment downtime to improve healthcare delivery in resource-constrained environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16967v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernes Lorier Atabonfack, Ahmed Tahiru Issah, Mohammed Hardi Abdul Baaki, Clemence Ingabire, Tolulope Olusuyi, Maruf Adewole, Udunna C. Anazodo, Timothy X Brown</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entire Chain Uplift Modeling with Context-Enhanced Learning for Intelligent Marketing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03379v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Uplift modeling, vital in online marketing, seeks to accurately measure the impact of various strategies, such as coupons or discounts, on different users by predicting the Individual Treatment Effect (ITE). In an e-commerce setting, user behavior follows a defined sequential chain, including impression, click, and conversion. Marketing strategies exert varied uplift effects at each stage within this chain, impacting metrics like click-through and conversion rate. Despite its utility, existing research has neglected to consider the inter-task across all stages impacts within a specific treatment and has insufficiently utilized the treatment information, potentially introducing substantial bias into subsequent marketing decisions. We identify these two issues as the chain-bias problem and the treatment-unadaptive problem. This paper introduces the Entire Chain UPlift method with context-enhanced learning (ECUP), devised to tackle these issues. ECUP consists of two primary components: 1) the Entire Chain-Enhanced Network, which utilizes user behavior patterns to estimate ITE throughout the entire chain space, models the various impacts of treatments on each task, and integrates task prior information to enhance context awareness across all stages, capturing the impact of treatment on different tasks, and 2) the Treatment-Enhanced Network, which facilitates fine-grained treatment modeling through bit-level feature interactions, thereby enabling adaptive feature adjustment. Extensive experiments on public and industrial datasets validate ECUPs effectiveness. Moreover, ECUP has been deployed on the Meituan food delivery platform, serving millions of daily active users, with the related dataset released for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03379v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinqiu Huang, Shuli Wang, Min Gao, Xue Wei, Changhao Li, Chuan Luo, Yinhua Zhu, Xiong Xiao, Yi Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking Scaling Law in Industrial Recommendation Systems with a Three-step Paradigm based Large User Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08309v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advancements in autoregressive Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved significant milestones, largely attributed to their scalability, often referred to as the "scaling law". Inspired by these achievements, there has been a growing interest in adapting LLMs for Recommendation Systems (RecSys) by reformulating RecSys tasks into generative problems. However, these End-to-End Generative Recommendation (E2E-GR) methods tend to prioritize idealized goals, often at the expense of the practical advantages offered by traditional Deep Learning based Recommendation Models (DLRMs) in terms of in features, architecture, and practices. This disparity between idealized goals and practical needs introduces several challenges and limitations, locking the scaling law in industrial RecSys. In this paper, we introduce a large user model (LUM) that addresses these limitations through a three-step paradigm, designed to meet the stringent requirements of industrial settings while unlocking the potential for scalable recommendations. Our extensive experimental evaluations demonstrate that LUM outperforms both state-of-the-art DLRMs and E2E-GR approaches. Notably, LUM exhibits excellent scalability, with performance improvements observed as the model scales up to 7 billion parameters. Additionally, we have successfully deployed LUM in an industrial application, where it achieved significant gains in an A/B test, further validating its effectiveness and practicality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08309v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bencheng Yan, Shilei Liu, Zhiyuan Zeng, Zihao Wang, Yizhen Zhang, Yujin Yuan, Langming Liu, Jiaqi Liu, Di Wang, Wenbo Su, Wang Pengjie, Jian Xu, Bo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPRINT: Scalable and Predictive Intent Refinement for LLM-Enhanced Session-based Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00570v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have enhanced conventional recommendation models via user profiling, which generates representative textual profiles from users' historical interactions. However, their direct application to session-based recommendation (SBR) remains challenging due to severe session context scarcity and poor scalability. In this paper, we propose SPRINT, a scalable SBR framework that incorporates reliable and informative intents while ensuring high efficiency in both training and inference. SPRINT constrains LLM-based profiling with a global intent pool and validates inferred intents based on recommendation performance to mitigate noise and hallucinations under limited context. To ensure scalability, LLMs are selectively invoked only for uncertain sessions during training, while a lightweight intent predictor generalizes intent prediction to all sessions without LLM dependency at inference time. Experiments on real-world datasets show that SPRINT consistently outperforms state-of-the-art methods while providing more explainable recommendations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00570v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gyuseok Lee, Wonbin Kweon, Zhenrui Yue, Yaokun Liu, Yifan Liu, Susik Yoon, Dong Wang, SeongKu Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REG4Rec: Reasoning-Enhanced Generative Model for Large-Scale Recommendation Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15308v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sequential recommendation aims to predict a user's next action in large-scale recommender systems. While traditional methods often suffer from insufficient information interaction, recent generative recommendation models partially address this issue by directly generating item predictions. To better capture user intents, recent studies have introduced a reasoning process into generative recommendation, significantly improving recommendation performance. However, these approaches are constrained by the singularity of item semantic representations, facing challenges such as limited diversity in reasoning pathways and insufficient reliability in the reasoning process. To tackle these issues, we introduce REG4Rec, a reasoning-enhanced generative model that constructs multiple dynamic semantic reasoning paths alongside a self-reflection process, ensuring high-confidence recommendations. Specifically, REG4Rec utilizes an MoE-based parallel quantization codebook (MPQ) to generate multiple unordered semantic tokens for each item, thereby constructing a larger-scale diverse reasoning space. Furthermore, to enhance the reliability of reasoning, we propose a training reasoning enhancement stage, which includes Preference Alignment for Reasoning (PARS) and a Multi-Step Reward Augmentation (MSRA) strategy. PARS uses reward functions tailored for recommendation to enhance reasoning and reflection, while MSRA introduces future multi-step actions to improve overall generalization. During inference, Consistency-Oriented Self-Reflection for Pruning (CORP) is proposed to discard inconsistent reasoning paths, preventing the propagation of erroneous reasoning. Lastly, we develop an efficient offline training strategy for large-scale recommendation. Experiments on real-world datasets and online evaluations show that REG4Rec delivers outstanding performance and substantial practical value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15308v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haibo Xing, Hao Deng, Yucheng Mao, Lingyu Mu, Jinxin Hu, Yi Xu, Hao Zhang, Jiahao Wang, Shizhun Wang, Yu Zhang, Xiaoyi Zeng, Jing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster and Memory-Efficient Training of Sequential Recommendation Models for Large Catalogs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09682v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sequential recommendations (SR) with transformer-based architectures are widely adopted in real-world applications, where SR models require frequent retraining to adapt to ever-changing user preferences. However, training transformer-based SR models often encounters a high computational cost associated with scoring extensive item catalogs, often exceeding thousands of items. This occurs mainly due to the use of cross-entropy loss, where peak memory scales proportionally to catalog size, batch size, and sequence length. Recognizing this, practitioners in the field of recommendation systems typically address memory consumption by integrating the cross-entropy (CE) loss with negative sampling, thereby reducing the explicit memory demands of the final layer. However, a small number of negative samples would degrade model performance, and as we demonstrate in our work, increasing the number of negative samples and the batch size further improves the model's performance, but rapidly starts to exceed industrial GPUs' size (~40Gb).
  In this work, we introduce the CCE- method, which offers a GPU-efficient implementation of the CE loss with negative sampling. Our method accelerates training by up to two times while reducing memory consumption by more than 10 times. Leveraging the memory savings afforded by using CCE- for model training, it becomes feasible to enhance its accuracy on datasets with a large item catalog compared to those trained with original PyTorch-implemented loss functions. Finally, we perform an analysis of key memory-related hyperparameters and highlight the necessity of a delicate balance among these factors. We demonstrate that scaling both the number of negative samples and batch size leads to better results rather than maximizing only one of them. To facilitate further adoption of CCE-, we release a Triton kernel that efficiently implements the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09682v5</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxim Zhelnin, Dmitry Redko, Daniil Volkov, Anna Volodkevich, Petr Sokerin, Valeriy Shevchenko, Egor Shvetsov, Alexey Vasilev, Darya Denisova, Ruslan Izmailov, Alexey Zaytsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topic-Specific Classifiers are Better Relevance Judges than Prompted LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04633v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The unjudged document problem, where systems that did not contribute to the original judgement pool may retrieve documents without a relevance judgement, is a key obstacle to the reuseability of test collections in information retrieval. While the de facto standard to deal with the problem is to treat unjudged documents as non-relevant, many alternatives have been proposed, such as the use of large language models (LLMs) as a relevance judge (LLM-as-a-judge). However, this has been criticized, among other things, as circular, since the same LLM can be used as the ranker and the judge. We propose to train topic-specific relevance classifiers instead: By finetuning monoT5 with independent LoRA weight adaptation on the judgments of a single assessor for a single topic's pool, we align it to that assessor's notion of relevance for the topic. The system rankings obtained through our classifier's relevance judgments achieve a Spearmans' $\rho$ correlation of $&gt;0.94$ with ground truth system rankings. As little as 128 initial human judgments per topic suffice to improve the comparability of models, compared to treating unjudged documents as non-relevant, while achieving more reliability than existing LLM-as-a-judge approaches. Topic-specific relevance classifiers are thus a lightweight and straightforward way to tackle the unjudged document problem, while maintaining human judgments as the gold standard for retrieval evaluation. Code, models, and data are made openly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04633v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Gienapp, Martin Potthast, Andrew Yates, Harrisen Scells, Eugene Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SciNUP: Natural Language User Interest Profiles for Scientific Literature Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21352v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The use of natural language (NL) user profiles in recommender systems offers greater transparency and user control compared to traditional representations. However, there is scarcity of large-scale, publicly available test collections for evaluating NL profile-based recommendation. To address this gap, we introduce SciNUP, a novel synthetic dataset for scholarly recommendation that leverages authors' publication histories to generate NL profiles and corresponding ground truth items. We use this dataset to conduct a comparison of baseline methods, ranging from sparse and dense retrieval approaches to state-of-the-art LLM-based rerankers. Our results show that while baseline methods achieve comparable performance, they often retrieve different items, indicating complementary behaviors. At the same time, considerable headroom for improvement remains, highlighting the need for effective NL-based recommendation approaches. The SciNUP dataset thus serves as a valuable resource for fostering future research and development in this area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21352v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariam Arustashvili, Krisztian Balog</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM Reasoning for Cold-Start Item Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18261v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown significant potential for improving recommendation systems through their inherent reasoning capabilities and extensive knowledge base. Yet, existing studies predominantly address warm-start scenarios with abundant user-item interaction data, leaving the more challenging cold-start scenarios, where sparse interactions hinder traditional collaborative filtering methods, underexplored. To address this limitation, we propose novel reasoning strategies designed for cold-start item recommendations within the Netflix domain. Our method utilizes the advanced reasoning capabilities of LLMs to effectively infer user preferences, particularly for newly introduced or rarely interacted items. We systematically evaluate supervised fine-tuning, reinforcement learning-based fine-tuning, and hybrid approaches that combine both methods to optimize recommendation performance. Extensive experiments on real-world data demonstrate significant improvements in both methodological efficacy and practical performance in cold-start recommendation contexts. Remarkably, our reasoning-based fine-tuned models outperform Netflix's production ranking model by up to 8% in certain cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18261v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3774904.3792872</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Li, Yu Wang, Jin Wang, Ying Li, Joydeep Ghosh, Anne Cocos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCoTER: Structured Chain-of-Thought Transfer for Enhanced Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19514v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Harnessing the reasoning power of Large Language Models (LLMs) for recommender systems is hindered by two fundamental challenges. First, current approaches lack a mechanism for automated, data-driven discovery of effective reasoning patterns, relying instead on brittle manual templates or unstable zero-shot prompting. Second, they employ structure-collapsing integration: direct prompting incurs prohibitive online inference costs, while feature extraction collapses reasoning chains into single vectors, discarding stepwise logic. To address these challenges, we propose SCoTER (Structured Chain-of-Thought Transfer for Enhanced Recommendation), a unified framework that treats pattern discovery and structure-aware transfer as a jointly optimized problem. Specifically, SCoTER operationalizes this through two synergistic components: a GVM pipeline for automated pattern discovery and a structure-preserving integration architecture that transfers stepwise logic to efficient models. Formally, we provide information-theoretic justification proving that structure-preserving transfer achieves tighter performance bounds than structure-agnostic alternatives. Empirically, experiments on four benchmarks demonstrate improvements of 3.75\%-11.59\% over a strong TIGER backbone. Moreover, in production deployment on the Tencent Advertising Platform, SCoTER achieved a 2.14\% lift in Gross Merchandise Value (GMV) while eliminating online LLM inference costs. Overall, SCoTER establishes a principled and production-validated blueprint for transferring structured LLM reasoning to large-scale recommender systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19514v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Jiang, Yang Wu, Qian Li, Yuling Xiong, Hongbo Tang, Xun Liu, Jun Zhang, Huan Yu, Hailong Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HyFormer: Revisiting the Roles of Sequence Modeling and Feature Interaction in CTR Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12681v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Industrial large-scale recommendation models (LRMs) face the challenge of jointly modeling long-range user behavior sequences and heterogeneous non-sequential features under strict efficiency constraints. However, most existing architectures employ a decoupled pipeline: long sequences are first compressed with a query-token based sequence compressor like LONGER, followed by fusion with dense features through token-mixing modules like RankMixer, which thereby limits both the representation capacity and the interaction flexibility. This paper presents HyFormer, a unified hybrid transformer architecture that tightly integrates long-sequence modeling and feature interaction into a single backbone. From the perspective of sequence modeling, we revisit and redesign query tokens in LRMs, and frame the LRM modeling task as an alternating optimization process that integrates two core components: Query Decoding which expands non-sequential features into Global Tokens and performs long sequence decoding over layer-wise key-value representations of long behavioral sequences; and Query Boosting which enhances cross-query and cross-sequence heterogeneous interactions via efficient token mixing. The two complementary mechanisms are performed iteratively to refine semantic representations across layers. Extensive experiments on billion-scale industrial datasets demonstrate that HyFormer consistently outperforms strong LONGER and RankMixer baselines under comparable parameter and FLOPs budgets, while exhibiting superior scaling behavior with increasing parameters and FLOPs. Large-scale online A/B tests in high-traffic production systems further validate its effectiveness, showing significant gains over deployed state-of-the-art models. These results highlight the practicality and scalability of HyFormer as a unified modeling framework for industrial LRMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12681v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunwen Huang, Shiyong Hong, Xijun Xiao, Jinqiu Jin, Xuanyuan Luo, Zhe Wang, Zheng Chai, Shikang Wu, Yuchao Zheng, Jingjian Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertical Semi-Federated Learning for Efficient Online Advertising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.15635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.15635v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Traditional vertical federated learning schema suffers from two main issues: 1) restricted applicable scope to overlapped samples and 2) high system challenge of real-time federated serving, which limits its application to advertising systems. To this end, we advocate a new practical learning setting, Semi-VFL (Vertical Semi-Federated Learning), for real-world industrial applications, where the learned model retains sufficient advantages of federated learning while supporting independent local serving. To achieve this goal, we propose the carefully designed Joint Privileged Learning framework (JPL) to i) alleviate the absence of the passive party's feature with federated equivalence imitation and ii) adapt to the heterogeneous full sample space with cross-branch rank alignment. Extensive experiments conducted on real-world advertising datasets validate the effectiveness of our method over baseline methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.15635v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenjie Li, Shu-Tao Xia, Jiangke Fan, Teng Zhang, Xingxing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Multimodal Interleaved Document Representation for Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02729v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Information Retrieval (IR) methods aim to identify documents relevant to a query, which have been widely applied in various natural language tasks. However, existing approaches typically consider only the textual content within documents, overlooking the fact that documents can contain multiple modalities, including images and tables. Also, they often segment each long document into multiple discrete passages for embedding, which prevents them from capturing the overall document context and interactions between paragraphs. To address these two challenges, we propose a method that holistically embeds documents interleaved with multiple modalities by leveraging the capability of recent vision-language models that enable the processing and integration of text, images, and tables into a unified format and representation. Moreover, to mitigate the information loss from segmenting documents into passages, instead of representing and retrieving passages individually, we further merge the representations of segmented passages into one single document representation, while we additionally introduce a reranking strategy to decouple and identify the relevant passage within the document if necessary. Then, through extensive experiments on diverse IR scenarios considering both the textual and multimodal queries, we show that our approach substantially outperforms relevant baselines, thanks to the consideration of the multimodal information within documents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02729v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaewoo Lee, Joonho Ko, Jinheon Baek, Soyeong Jeong, Sung Ju Hwang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ProveRAG: Provenance-Driven Vulnerability Analysis with Automated Retrieval-Augmented LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17406v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In cybersecurity, security analysts constantly face the challenge of mitigating newly discovered vulnerabilities in real-time, with over 300,000 vulnerabilities identified since 1999. The sheer volume of known vulnerabilities complicates the detection of patterns for unknown threats. While LLMs can assist, they often hallucinate and lack alignment with recent threats. Over 40,000 vulnerabilities have been identified in 2024 alone, which are introduced after most popular LLMs' (e.g., GPT-5) training data cutoff. This raises a major challenge of leveraging LLMs in cybersecurity, where accuracy and up-to-date information are paramount. Therefore, we aim to improve the adaptation of LLMs in vulnerability analysis by mimicking how an analyst performs such tasks. We propose ProveRAG, an LLM-powered system designed to assist in rapidly analyzing vulnerabilities with automated retrieval augmentation of web data while self-evaluating its responses with verifiable evidence. ProveRAG incorporates a self-critique mechanism to help alleviate the omission and hallucination common in the output of LLMs applied in cybersecurity applications. The system cross-references data from verifiable sources (NVD and CWE), giving analysts confidence in the actionable insights provided. Our results indicate that ProveRAG excels in delivering verifiable evidence to the user with over 99% and 97% accuracy in exploitation and mitigation strategies, respectively. ProveRAG guides analysts to secure their systems more effectively by overcoming temporal and context-window limitations while also documenting the process for future audits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17406v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ACCESS.2025.3638251</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Access, vol. 13, pp. 212815-212826, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Reza Fayyazi, Stella Hoyos Trueba, Michael Zuzak, Shanchieh Jay Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multi-Stage Hybrid Framework for Automated Interpretation of Multi-View Engineering Drawings Using Vision Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21862v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Engineering drawings are fundamental to manufacturing communication, serving as the primary medium for conveying design intent, tolerances, and production details. However, interpreting complex multi-view drawings with dense annotations remains challenging using manual methods, generic optical character recognition (OCR) systems, or traditional deep learning approaches, due to varied layouts, orientations, and mixed symbolic-textual content. To address these challenges, this paper proposes a three-stage hybrid framework for the automated interpretation of 2D multi-view engineering drawings using modern detection and vision language models (VLMs). In the first stage, YOLOv11-det performs layout segmentation to localize key regions such as views, title blocks, and notes. The second stage uses YOLOv11-obb for orientation-aware, fine-grained detection of annotations, including measures, GD&amp;T symbols, and surface roughness indicators. The third stage employs two Donut-based, OCR-free VLMs for semantic content parsing: the Alphabetical VLM extracts textual and categorical information from title blocks and notes, while the Numerical VLM interprets quantitative data such as measures, GD&amp;T frames, and surface roughness. Two specialized datasets were developed to ensure robustness and generalization: 1,000 drawings for layout detection and 1,406 for annotation-level training. The Alphabetical VLM achieved an overall F1 score of 0.672, while the Numerical VLM reached 0.963, demonstrating strong performance in textual and quantitative interpretation, respectively. The unified JSON output enables seamless integration with CAD and manufacturing databases, providing a scalable solution for intelligent engineering drawing analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21862v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Tayyab Khan, Zane Yong, Lequn Chen, Wenhe Feng, Nicholas Yew Jin Tan, Seung Ki Moon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GTR-Mamba: Geometry-to-Tangent Routing Mamba for Hyperbolic POI Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22942v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Next Point-of-Interest (POI) recommendation is a critical task in modern Location-Based Social Networks (LBSNs), aiming to model the complex decision-making process of human mobility to provide personalized recommendations for a user's next check-in location. Existing hyperbolic POI recommendation models, predominantly based on rotations and graph representations, have been extensively investigated. Although hyperbolic geometry has proven superior in representing hierarchical data with low distortion, current hyperbolic sequence models typically rely on performing recurrence via expensive M\"obius operations directly on the manifold. This incurs prohibitive computational costs and numerical instability, rendering them ill-suited for trajectory modeling. To resolve this conflict between geometric representational power and sequential efficiency, we propose GTR-Mamba, a novel framework featuring Geometry-to-Tangent Routing. GTR-Mamba strategically routes complex state transitions to the computationally efficient Euclidean tangent space. Crucially, instead of a static approximation, we introduce a Parallel Transport (PT) mechanism that dynamically aligns tangent spaces along the trajectory. This ensures geometric consistency across recursive updates, effectively bridging the gap between the curved manifold and linear tangent operations. This process is orchestrated by an exogenous spatio-temporal channel, which explicitly modulates the SSM discretization parameters. Extensive experiments on three real-world datasets demonstrate that GTR-Mamba consistently outperforms state-of-the-art baselines in next POI recommendation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22942v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoxuan Li, Jieyuan Pei, Tangwei Ye, Zhongyuan Lai, Zihan Liu, Fengyuan Xu, Qi Zhang, Liang Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
