<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT</link>
    <description>math.RT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 04:00:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Characteristic tilting modules and Ringel duality in the Noetherian world</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00729v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The foundations of Ringel duality for split quasi-hereditary algebras over commutative Noetherian rings are strengthened. Several descriptions and properties of the smallest resolving subcategory containing all standard modules over split quasi-hereditary algebras over commutative Noetherian rings are provided.
  In particular, given two split quasi-hereditary algebras $A$ and $B$, we prove that any exact equivalence between the smallest resolving subcategory containing all standard modules over $A$ and the smallest resolving subcategory containing all standard modules over $B$ lifts to a Morita equivalence between $A$ and $B$ which preserves the quasi-hereditary structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00729v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiago Cruz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite generation properties of the pro-$p$ Iwahori-Hecke $\operatorname{Ext}$-algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pro-$p$ Iwahori-Hecke $\operatorname{Ext}$-algebra $E^\ast$ is a graded algebra that has been introduced and studied by Ollivier-Schneider, with the long-term goal of investigating the category of smooth mod-$p$ representations of $p$-adic reductive groups and its derived category. Its $0$th graded piece is the pro-$p$ Iwahori-Hecke algebra studied by Vign\'eras and others.
  In the present article, we first show that the $\operatorname{Ext}$-algebra $E^\ast$ associated with the group $\operatorname{SL}_2(\mathfrak{F})$, $\operatorname{PGL}_2(\mathfrak{F})$ or $\operatorname{GL}_2(\mathfrak{F})$, where $\mathfrak{F}$ is an unramified extension of $\mathbb{Q}_p$ with $p \neq 2,3$, is finitely generated as a (non-commutative) algebra.
  We then specialize to the case of the group $\operatorname{SL}_2(\mathbb{Q}_p)$, with $p \neq 2,3$, and we show that in this case the natural multiplication map from the tensor algebra $T^\ast_{E^0} E^1$ to $E^\ast$ is surjective and that its kernel is finitely generated as a two-sided ideal. Using this fact as main input, we then show that $E^\ast$ is finitely presented as an algebra. We actually compute an explicit presentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00916v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Bodon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative cluster tilting theory and $\tau$-tilting theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal C$ be a Krull-Schmidt triangulated category with shift functor $[1]$ and $\mathcal R$ be a rigid subcategory of $\mathcal C$. We are concerned with the mutation of two-term weak $\mathcal R[1]$-cluster tilting subcategories. We show that any almost complete two-term weak $\mathcal R[1]$-cluster tilting subcategory has exactly two completions. Then we apply the results on relative cluster tilting subcategories to the domain of $\tau$-tilting theory in functor categories and abelian categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01152v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Liu, Jixing Pan, Panyue Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Murnaghan-Type Representations for the Positive Elliptic Hall Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct a new family of graded representations $\widetilde{W}_{\lambda}$ for the positive elliptic Hall algebra $\mathcal{E}^{+}$ indexed by Young diagrams $\lambda$ which generalize the standard $\mathcal{E}^{+}$ action on symmetric functions. These representations have homogeneous bases of eigenvectors for the action of the Macdonald element $P_{0,1} \in \mathcal{E}^{+}$ with distinct $\mathbb{Q}(q,t)$-rational spectrum generalizing the symmetric Macdonald functions. The analysis of the structure of these representations exhibits interesting combinatorics arising from the stable limits of periodic standard Young tableaux. We find an explicit combinatorial rule for the action of the multiplication operators $e_r[X]^{\bullet}$ generalizing the Pieri rule for symmetric Macdonald functions. We will also naturally obtain a family of interesting $(q,t)$ product-series identities which come from keeping track of certain combinatorial statistics associated to periodic standard Young tableaux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00756v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milo Bechtloff Weising</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost Symmetric Schur Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01049v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce and study a generalization $s_{(\mu|\lambda)}$ of the Schur functions called the almost symmetric Schur functions. These functions simultaneously generalize the finite variable key polynomials and the infinite variable Schur functions. They form a homogeneous basis for the space of almost symmetric functions and are defined using a family of recurrences involving the isobaric divided difference operators and limits of Weyl symmetrization operators. The $s_{(\mu|\lambda)}$ are the $q=t=0$ specialization of the stable limit non-symmetric Macdonald functions $\widetilde{E}_{(\mu|\lambda)}$ defined by the author in previous work. We find a combinatorial formula for these functions simultaneously generalizing well known formulas for the Schur functions and the key polynomials. Further, we prove positivity results for the coefficients of the almost symmetric Schur functions expanded into the monomial basis and into the monomial-Schur basis of the space of almost symmetric functions. The latter positivity result follows after realizing the almost symmetric Schur functions $s_{(\mu|\lambda)}$ as limits of characters of representations of parabolic subgroups in type $GL.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01049v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milo Bechtloff Weising</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Co-rank $1$ Arithmetic Siegel--Weil I: Local non-Archimedean</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the first in a sequence of four papers, where we prove the arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula in co-rank $1$ for Kudla--Rapoport special cycles on exotic smooth integral models of unitary Shimura varieties of arbitrarily large even arithmetic dimension. Our arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula implies that degrees of Kudla--Rapoport arithmetic special $1$-cycles are encoded in the first derivatives of unitary Eisenstein series Fourier coefficients.
  The crucial input is a new local limiting method at all places. In this paper, we formulate and prove the key local theorems at all non-Archimedean places. On the analytic side, the limit relates local Whittaker functions on different groups. On the geometric side at nonsplit non-Archimedean places, the limit relates degrees of $0$-cycles on Rapoport--Zink spaces and local contributions to heights of $1$-cycles in mixed characteristic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01426v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan C. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Co-rank $1$ Arithmetic Siegel--Weil II: Local Archimedean</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the second in a sequence of four papers, where we prove the arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula in co-rank $1$ for Kudla--Rapoport special cycles on exotic smooth integral models of unitary Shimura varieties of arbitrarily large even arithmetic dimension. Our arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula implies that degrees of Kudla--Rapoport arithmetic special $1$-cycles are encoded in the first derivatives of unitary Eisenstein series Fourier coefficients.
  In this paper, we formulate and prove the key Archimedean local theorem. In the case of purely Archimedean intersection numbers, we also prove an Archimedean local arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula, relating Green currents of arbitrary degree and off-central derivatives of local Whittaker functions. The crucial input is a new limiting method, which is structurally parallel to our strategy at non-Archimedean places.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01427v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan C. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Co-rank $1$ Arithmetic Siegel--Weil III: Geometric local-to-global</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01428v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the third in a sequence of four papers, where we prove the arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula in co-rank $1$ for Kudla--Rapoport special cycles on exotic smooth integral models of unitary Shimura varieties of arbitrarily large even arithmetic dimension. Our arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula implies that degrees of Kudla--Rapoport arithmetic special $1$-cycles are encoded in the first derivatives of unitary Eisenstein series Fourier coefficients.
  In this paper, we finish the reduction process from global arithmetic intersection numbers for special cycles to the local geometric quantities in our companion papers.
  Building on our previous companion papers, we also propose a construction for arithmetic special cycle classes associated to possibly singular matrices of arbitrary co-rank.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01428v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan C. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Co-rank $1$ Arithmetic Siegel--Weil IV: Analytic local-to-global</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01429v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the fourth in a sequence of four papers, where we prove the arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula in co-rank $1$ for Kudla--Rapoport special cycles on exotic smooth integral models of unitary Shimura varieties of arbitrarily large even arithmetic dimension. Our arithmetic Siegel--Weil formula implies that degrees of Kudla--Rapoport arithmetic special $1$-cycles are encoded in the first derivatives of unitary Eisenstein series Fourier coefficients.
  In this paper, we pin down precise normalizations for some $U(m,m)$ Siegel Eisenstein series, give local Siegel--Weil special value formulas with explicit constants, and record a geometric Siegel--Weil result for degrees of complex $0$-cycles. Using this, we complete the proof of our arithmetic Siegel--Weil results by patching together the local main theorems from our companion papers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01429v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan C. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knot theory and cluster algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.14740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.14740v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a connection between knot theory and cluster algebras via representation theory. To every knot diagram (or link diagram), we associate a cluster algebra by constructing a quiver with potential. The rank of the cluster algebra is $2n$, where $n$ is the number of crossing points in the knot diagram. We then construct $2n$ indecomposable modules $T(i)$ over the Jacobian algebra of the quiver with potential. For each $T(i)$, we show that the submodule lattice is isomorphic to the corresponding lattice of Kauffman states. We then give a realization of the Alexander polynomial of the knot as a specialization of the $F$-polynomial of $T(i)$, for every $i$. Furthermore, we conjecture that the collection of the $T(i)$ forms a cluster in the cluster algebra whose quiver is isomorphic to the opposite of the initial quiver, and that the resulting cluster automorphism is of order two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.14740v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V\'eronique Bazier-Matte, Ralf Schiffler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cellular pavings of fibers of convolution morphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14218v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article proves, in the case of split groups over arbitrary fields, that all fibers of convolution morphisms attached to parahoric affine flag varieties are paved by products of affine lines and affine lines minus a point. This applies in particular to the affine Grassmannian and to the convolution morphisms in the context of the geometric Satake correspondence. The second part of the article extends these results over $\mathbb Z$. Those in turn relate to the recent work of Cass-van den Hove-Scholbach on the geometric Satake equivalence for integral motives, and provide some alternative proofs for some of their results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14218v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas J. Haines</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the potential automorphy and the local-global compatibility for the monodromy operators at $p \neq l$ over CM fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01551v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a CM field. In this paper, we prove the local-global compatibility for cohomological cuspidal automorphic representations of $\mathrm{GL}_n(\mathbb{A}_F)$ at $p \neq l$ by using certain potential automorphy theorems in some cases including higher dimensional cases. Moreover, we also prove the Ramanujan conjecture for cohomological cuspidal automorphic representations of $\mathrm{GL}_2(\mathbb{A}_F )$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01551v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kojiro Matsumoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
