<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT</link>
    <description>math.RT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 03:19:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Frobenius extensions and the exotic nilCoxeter algebra for $G(m,m,3)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a previous paper of the first author, the type A affine Cartan matrix was q-deformed to produce a deformation of the reflection representation of the affine Weyl group. This deformation plays a role in the quantum geometric Satake equivalence. In this paper we introduce the study of q-deformed divided difference operators.
  When q is specialized to a primitive 2m-th root of unity, this affine reflection representation factors through a quotient, the complex reflection group $G(m,m,n)$. The divided difference operators now generate a finite-dimensional algebra we call the exotic nilCoxeter algebra. This algebra is new and has surprising features. In addition to the usual braid relations, we prove a new relation called the roundabout relation.
  A classic result of Demazure, for Weyl groups, states that the polynomial ring of the reflection representation is a Frobenius extension over its subring of invariant polynomials, and describes how the Frobenius trace can be constructed within the nilCoxeter algebra. We study the analogous Frobenius extension for $G(m,m,n)$, and identify the Frobenius trace within the exotic nilCoxeter algebra for $G(m,m,3)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18678v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Elias, Daniel Juteau, Benjamin Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A closed formula in the deformed affine nilHecke algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is a q-deformation of the reflection representation of the affine symmetric group, which arises in the quantum geometric Satake equivalence, and in the study of the complex reflection groups $G(m,m,n)$. Demazure operators (often called divided difference operators) act on the polynomial ring of this deformed representation. When $n=3$ we prove an explicit closed formula for the scalar one obtains when applying a degree $-k$ Demazure operator to a monomial of degree $k$. We also prove a simpler formula for the scalar obtained after specializing q to a root of unity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18679v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Elias, Daniel Juteau, Benjamin Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calabi-Yau completions for roots of dualizing dg bimodules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Roots of shifted Serre functors appear naturally in representation theory and algebraic geometry. We give an analogue of Keller's Calabi-Yau completion for roots of shifted inverse dualizing bimodules over dg categories. Given a positive integer $a$, we introduce the notion of the $a$-th root pair on smooth dg categories and define its Calabi-Yau completion. We prove that the Calabi-Yau completion has the Calabi-Yau property when the $a$-th root pair has certain invariance under an action of the cyclic group of order $a$, and observe that it is only twisted Calabi-Yau in general. Next, we establish a bijection between Adams graded Calabi-Yau dg categories of Gorenstein parameter $a$ and $a$-th root pairs on a dg category with the cyclic invariance. Applying this bijection, we prove that a certain operation on dg categories, called the $a$-Segre product, allows us to reproduce Calabi-Yau dg categories. Furthermore, we discuss the cluster category of these Calabi-Yau completions, and prove that it is a $\mathbb{Z}/a\mathbb{Z}$-quotient of the usual cluster category, which thereby establishes the $a$-th root versions of cluster categories. In the appendix, we give a generalization of Beilinson's theorem on tilting bundles on projective spaces to the setting of Adams graded dg categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18753v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norihiro Hanihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On character values of $GL_n(\mathbb F_q)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we use vertex operator techniques to compute character values on unipotent classes of $\GL_n(\mathbb F_q)$. By realizing the Grothendieck ring $R_G=\bigoplus_{n\geq0}^\infty R(\GL_n(\mathbb F_q))$ as Fock spaces, we formulate the Murnanghan-Nakayama rule of $\GL_n(\mathbb F_q)$ between Schur functions colored by an orbit $\phi$ of linear characters of $\overline{\mathbb F}_q$ under the Frobenius automorphism on and modified Hall-Littlewood functions colored by $f_1=t-1$, which provides detailed information on the character table of $\GL_n(\mathbb F_q)$. As applications, we use vertex algebraic methods to determine the Steinberg characters of $\GL_n(\mathbb F_q)$, which were previously determined by Curtis-Lehrer-Tits via geometry of homology groups of spherical buildings and Springer-Zelevinsky utilizing Hopf algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18793v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naihuan Jing, Yu Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Archimedean period relations for Rankin-Selberg convolutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18805v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate and prove the archimedean period relations for Rankin-Selberg convolutions of $\text{GL}(n)\times \text{GL}(n)$ and $\text{GL}(n)\times \text{GL}(n-1)$, for all generic cohomological representations. As a consequence, we prove the non-vanishing of the archimedean modular symbols. This extends the earlier results in [LLS24] for essentially tempered representations of $\text{GL}(n)\times\text{GL}(n-1)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18805v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yubo Jin, Dongwen Liu, Binyong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operator K-Theory and Tempiric Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: David Vogan proved that if $G$ is a real reductive group, and if $K$ is a maximal compact subgroup of $G$, then every irreducible representation of $K$ is included as a minimal $K$-type in precisely one tempered, irreducible unitary representation of $G$ with real infinitesimal character, and that moreover it is included there with multiplicity one and is the unique minimal $K$-type in that representation. We shall prove that the Connes-Kasparov isomorphism in operator $K$-theory is equivalent to a $K$-theoretic version of Vogan's result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18924v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Bradd, Nigel Higson, Robert Yuncken</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the minimal parabolic induction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19008v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by Beilinson-Bernstein's proof of the Jantzen conjectures, we define the minimal parabolic induction functor for Kac-Moody algebras, and establish some basic properties. As applications of the formal theory, we examine first extension groups between simple highest weight modules in the category of weight modules, and analyze the annihilators of some simple highest weight modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19008v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher hereditary algebras arising from some toric singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19040v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study graded and ungraded singularity categories of some commutative Gorenstein toric singularities, namely, Veronese subrings of polynomial rings, and Segre products of some copies of polynomial rings. We show that the graded singularity category has a tilting object whose endomorphism ring is higher representation infinite. Moreover, we construct the tilting object so that the endomorphism ring has a strict root pair of its higher Auslander-Reiten translation, which allows us to give equivalences between singularity categories and (folded) cluster categories in a such a way that their cluster tilting objects correspond to each other. Our distinguished form of tilting objects also allows us to construct (twisted) Calabi-Yau algebras as the Calabi-Yau completions of the root pairs. We give an explicit description of these twisted Calabi-Yau algebras as well as the higher representation infinite algebras in terms of quivers and relations. Along the way, we prove that certain idempotent quotients of higher representation infinite algebras remain higher representation infinite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19040v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norihiro Hanihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflexive modules and Auslander-type conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the category $\mathop{\mathrm{ref}}\Lambda$ of reflexive modules over a two-sided Noetherian ring $\Lambda$. We show that the category $\mathop{\mathrm{ref}}\Lambda$ is quasi-abelian if and only if $\Lambda$ satisfies certain Auslander-type condition on the minimal injective resolution of the ring itself. Furthermore, we establish a Morita theorem which characterizes the category of reflexive modules among quasi-abelian categories in terms of generator-cogenerators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19625v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norihiro Hanihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Casimir Radial Parts via Matsuki Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use Matsuki's decomposition for symmetric pairs $(G, H)$ of (not necessarily compact) reductive Lie groups to construct the radial parts for invariant differential operators acting on matrix-spherical functions. As an application, we employ this machinery to formulate an alternative, mathematically rigorous approach to obtaining radial parts of Casimir operators that appear in the theory of conformal blocks, which avoids poorly defined analytical continuations from the compact quotient cases. To exemplify how this works, after reviewing the presentation of conformal 4-point correlation functions via matrix-spherical functions for the corresponding symmetric pair, we for the first time provide a complete analysis of the Casimir radial part decomposition in the case of Lorentzian signature. As another example, we revisit the Casimir reduction in the case of conformal blocks for two scalar defects of equal dimension. We argue that Matsuki's decomposition thus provides a proper mathematical framework for analysing the correspondence between Casimir equations and the Calogero-Sutherland-type models, first discovered by one of the authors and Schomerus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19681v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Schl\"osser, Mikhail Isachenkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coxeter groups preserving orthants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short, elementary note we prove that if a faithful reflection representation of a Coxeter group preserves an orthant, then that Coxeter group is a product of symmetric groups acting on its natural permutation representation. We also prove an affine analogue of this statement, where an orthant is preserved modulo an invariant sublattice. As a consequence, the existence of two different versions of the quantum geometric Satake equivalence is a purely type A phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19749v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Elias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong factorization of ultradifferentiable vectors associated with compact Lie group representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18698v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show a strong factorization theorem of Dixmier-Malliavin type for ultradifferentiable vectors associated with equicontinuous compact Lie group representations on sequentially complete locally convex Hausdorff spaces. In particular, this solves [Conjecture 6.4; J. Funct. Anal. 262 (2012), 667-681] for analytic vectors in the case of compact Lie groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18698v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Debrouwere, Michiel Huttener, Jasson Vindas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Splitting the difference: Computations of the Reynolds operator in classical invariant theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18841v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: If $G$ is a linearly reductive group acting rationally on a polynomial ring $S$, then the inclusion $S^{G} \hookrightarrow S$ possesses a unique $G$-equivariant splitting, called the Reynolds operator. We describe algorithms for computing the Reynolds operator for the classical actions as in Weyl's book. The groups are the general linear group, the special linear group, the orthogonal group, and the symplectic group, with their classical representations: direct sums of copies of the standard representation and copies of the dual representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18841v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aryaman Maithani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On some Grothendieck expansions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The complete flag variety admits a natural action by both the orthogonal group and the symplectic group. Wyser and Yong defined orthogonal Grothendieck polynomials $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{O}}_z$ and symplectic Grothendieck polynomials $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{Sp}}_z$ as the $K$-theory classes of the corresponding orbit closures. There is an explicit formula to expand $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{Sp}}_z$ as a nonnegative sum of Grothendieck polynomials $\mathfrak{G}^{(\beta)}_w$, which represent the $K$-theory classes of Schubert varieties. Although the constructions of $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{Sp}}_z$ and $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{O}}_z$ are similar, finding the $\mathfrak{G}^{(\beta)}$-expansion of $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{O}}_z$ or even computing $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{O}}_z$ is much harder. If $z$ is vexillary then $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{O}}_z$ has a nonnegative $\mathfrak{G}^{(\beta)}$-expansion, but the associated coefficients are mostly unknown. This paper derives several new formulas for $\mathfrak{G}^{\mathsf{O}}_z$ and its $\mathfrak{G}^{(\beta)}$-expansion when $z$ is vexillary. Among other applications, we prove that the latter expansion has a nontrivial stability property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18963v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Marberg, Jiayi Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Quantum K-theory of Quiver Varieties at Roots of Unity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\Psi(\mathbb{z},\mathbb{a},q)$ be the fundamental solution matrix of the quantum difference equation in the equivariant quantum K-theory for Nakajima variety $X$. In this work, we prove that the operator $$ \Psi(\mathbb{z},\mathbb{a},q) \Psi\left(\mathbb{z}^p,\mathbb{a}^p,q^{p^2}\right)^{-1} $$ has no poles at the primitive complex $p$-th roots of unity $\zeta_p$ in the curve counting parameter $q$. As a byproduct, we show that the eigenvalues of the iterated product of the operators ${\bf M}_{\mathcal{L}}$ from the quantum difference equation on $X$ $$ {\bf M}_{\mathcal{L}} (\mathbb{z},\mathbb{a},q) {\bf M}_{\mathcal{L}} (\mathbb{z} q^{\mathcal{L}},\mathbb{a},q) \cdots {\bf M}_{\mathcal{L}} (\mathbb{z} q^{(p-1)\mathcal{L}},\mathbb{a},q) $$ evaluated at $\zeta_p$ are described by the Bethe equations for $X$ in which all variables are substituted by their $p$-th powers.
  Finally, upon a reduction of the quantum difference equation on $X$ to the quantum differential equation over the field with finite characteristic, the above iterated product transforms into a Grothendiek-Katz $p$-curvature of the corresponding differential connection whereas ${\bf M}_{\mathcal{L}} (\mathbb{z}^p,\mathbb{a}^p,q^p)$ becomes a certain Frobenius twist of that connection. In this way, we are reproducing, in part, the statement of a theorem by Etingof and Varchenko.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19383v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Koroteev, Andrey Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Berezinian for quantum affine superalgebra $U_q(\widehat{gl}_{M|N})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19385v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the quantum Berezinian for the quantum affine superalgebra $\mathrm{U}_q(\widehat{\gl}_{M|N})$ and show that the coefficients of the quantum Berezinian belong to the center of $\mathrm{U}_q(\widehat{\gl}_{M|N})$. We also construct another family of central elements which can be expressed in the quantum Berezinian by a Liouville-type theorem. Moreover, we prove analogues of the Jacobi identities, the Schur complementary theorem, the Sylvester theorem and the MacMahon Master theorem for the generator matrices of $\mathrm{U}_q(\widehat{\gl}_{M|N})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19385v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naihuan Jing, Li Zheng, Jian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Symmetry of Odd Leech Lattice CFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19430v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the Mathieu groups $M_{24}$ and $M_{23}$ in the isometry group of the odd Leech lattice do not lift to subgroups of the automorphism group of its lattice vertex operator (super)algebra. In other words, the subgroups $2^{24}.M_{24}$ and $2^{23}.M_{23}$ of the automorphism group of the odd Leech lattice vertex operator algebra are non-split extensions. Our method can also confirm a similar result for the Conway group $\mathrm{Co}_0$ and the Leech lattice, which was already shown in [Griess 1973]. This study is motivated by the moonshine-type observation on the $\mathcal{N}=2$ extremal elliptic genus of central charge 24 by [Benjamin, Dyer, Fitzpatrick, Kachru arXiv:1507.00004]. We also investigate weight-1 and weight-$\frac{3}{2}$ currents invariant under the subgroup $2^{24}.M_{24}$ or $2^{23}.M_{23}$ of the automorphism group of the odd Leech lattice vertex operator algebra, and revisit an $\mathcal{N}=2$ superconformal algebra in it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19430v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaki Okada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum K-theory and Integrability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19570v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, we explore some recent advancements in enumerative algebraic geometry, focusing particularly on the role of quantum K-theory of quiver varieties as viewed through the lens of integrable systems. We highlight a number of conjectures and open questions. This is a contribution to the proceedings of the GLSM@30 conference, which was held in May 2023 at the Simons Center for Geometry and Physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19570v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0217751X24460102</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Peter Koroteev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Branes and Representations of DAHA $C^\vee C_1$: affine braid group action on category</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19647v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the representation theory of the spherical double affine Hecke algebra (DAHA) of $C^\vee C_1$, using brane quantization. By showing a one-to-one correspondence between Lagrangian $A$-branes with compact support and finite-dimensional representations of the spherical DAHA, we provide evidence of derived equivalence between the $A$-brane category of $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})$-character variety of a four-punctured sphere and the representation category of DAHA of $C^\vee C_1$. The $D_4$ root system plays an essential role in understanding both the geometry and representation theory. In particular, this $A$-model approach reveals the action of an affine braid group of type $D_4$ on the category. As a by-product, our geometric investigation offers detailed information about the low-energy dynamics of the SU(2) $N_f=4$ Seiberg-Witten theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19647v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junkang Huang, Satoshi Nawata, Yutai Zhang, Shutong Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The branching models of Kwon and Sundaram via flagged hives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19721v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a bijection between the branching models of Kwon and Sundaram, conjectured previously by Lenart-Lecouvey. To do so, we use a symmetry of Littlewood-Richardson coefficients in terms of the hive model. Along the way, we obtain a new branching model in terms of flagged hives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19721v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sathish Kumar, Jacinta Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak lumping of left-invariant random walks on left cosets of finite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19742v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a finite group and let $H$ be a subgroup of $G$. The left-invariant random walk driven by a probability measure $w$ on $G$ is the Markov chain in which from any state $x \in G$, the probability of stepping to $xg \in G$ is $w(g)$. The initial state is chosen randomly according to a given distribution. The walk is said to lump weakly on left cosets if the induced process on $G/H$ is a time-homogeneous Markov chain. We characterise all the initial distributions and weights $w$ such that the walk is irreducible and lumps weakly on left cosets, and determine all the possible transition matrices of the induced Markov chain. In the case where $H$ is abelian we refine our main results to give a necessary and sufficient condition for weak lumping by an explicit system of linear equations on $w$, organized by the double cosets $HxH$. As an application we consider shuffles of a deck of $n$ cards such that repeated observations of the top card form a Markov chain. Such shuffles include the random-to-top shuffle, and also, when the deck is started in a uniform random order, the top-to-random shuffle. We give a further family of examples in which our full theory of weak lumping is needed to verify that the top card sequence is Markov.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19742v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward Crane, \'Alvaro Guti\'errez, Erin Russell, Mark Wildon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalised Temperley-Lieb algebras of type $G(r,p,n)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.09377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.09377v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In an earlier work, we defined a ``generalised Temperley-Lieb algebra'' $TL_{r,1,n}$ corresponding to the imprimitive reflection group $G(r,1,n)$ as a quotient of the cyclotomic Hecke algebra. In this work we introduce the generalised Temperley-Lieb algebra $TL_{r,p,n}$ which corresponds to the complex reflection group $G(r,p,n)$. Our definition identifies $TL_{r,p,n}$ as the fixed-point subalgebra of $TL_{r,1,n}$ under a certain automorphism $\sigma$. We prove the cellularity of $TL_{r,p,n}$ by proving that $\sigma$ induces a special shift automorphism with respect to the cellular structure of $TL_{r,1,n}$. We also give a description of the cell modules of $TL_{r,p,n}$ and their decomposition numbers, and finally we point to how our algebras might be categorified and could lead to a diagrammatic theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.09377v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gus Lehrer, Mengfan Lyu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremal weight crystals over affine Lie algebras of infinite rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.05188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.05188v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explain extremal weight crystals over affine Lie algebras of infinite rank using combinatorial models: a spinor model due to Kwon, and an infinite rank analogue of Kashiwara-Nakashima tableaux due to Lecouvey. In particular, we show that Lecouvey's tableau model is isomorphic to an extremal weight crystal of level zero. Using these combinatorial models, we explain an algebra structure of the Grothendieck ring for a category consisting of some extremal weight crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.05188v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10468-024-10302-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Taehyeok Heo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The correspondence between silting objects and $t$-structures for non-positive dg algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17597v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a bijective correspondence between isomorphism classes of basic silting objects of $\mathsf{per}(A)$ and algebraic $t$-structures of $\mathsf{D}_{\rm fd}(A)$ for locally finite non-positive dg algebra $A$ over a field $k$ (more generally, we work in the setting of ST-pair inside an algebraic triangulated category). For a non-positive (topologically) homologically smooth dg $k$-algebra $A$ whose zeroth cohomology is finite-dimensional, or for a non-positive proper dg $k$-algebra $A$, the one-to-one correspondence between isomorphism classes of basic silting objects of $\mathsf{per}(A)$ and algebraic $t$-structures on $\mathsf{D}_{\rm fd}(A)$ was already known. The main result of this paper generalizes the above two results to locally finite non-positive dg $k$-algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17597v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riku Fushimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$(k, a)$-generalized Fourier transform with negative $a$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01345v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $ (k, a) $-generalized Fourier transform $ \mathscr{F}_{k, a} $ introduced by Ben Sa\"id--Kobayashi--{\O}rsted is a deformation family of the classical Fourier transform with a Dunkl parameter $ k $ and a parameter $ a &gt; 0 $ that interpolates minimal representations of two different simple Lie groups. In the present paper, we focus on the case $ a &lt; 0 $. As a main result, we find a unitary transform that intertwines the known case $ a &gt; 0 $ and the new case $ a &lt; 0 $.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01345v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuro Hikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohen-Montgomery duality for bimodules and singular equivalences of Morita type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03280v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a group and $\Bbbk$ a commutative ring. All categories and functors are assumed to be $\Bbbk$-linear. We define a $G$-invariant bimodule ${}_SM_R$ over $G$-categories $R, S$ and a $G$-graded bimodule ${}_BN_A$ over $G$-graded categories $A, B$, and introduce the orbit bimodule $M/G$ and the smash product bimodule $N\# G$. We will show that these constructions are inverses to each other. This will be applied to Morita equivalences, stable equivalences of Morita type, singular equivalences of Morita type, and singular equivalences of Morita type with level to show that the orbit (resp. smash product) bimodule construction transforms an equivalent pair of $G$-categories (resp. $G$-graded categories) of each type to an equivalent pair of $G$-graded categories (resp. $G$-categories) of the same type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03280v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hideto Asashiba, Shengyong Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endoscopic character identities for depth-zero supercuspidal representations of $\mathrm{SL}_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20183v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the depth-zero supercuspidal $L$-packets of $\mathrm{SL}_2$. With the aid of the classical character formulas of Sally-Shalika, we prove the endoscopic character identities. We comment on the truth-status of Theorem 15.2 in the 2011 article by Adler, DeBacker, Sally and Spice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20183v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anne-Marie Aubert, Roger Plymen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreducible representations of certain nilpotent groups of finite rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00398v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the paper we study irreducible representations of some nilpotent groups of finite abelian total rank. The main result of the paper states that if a torsion-free minimax group $G$ of nilpotency class 2 admits a faithful irreducible representation $\varphi $ over a finitely generated field $k$ such that $chark \notin Sp(G)$ then there exist a subgroup $N$ and an irreducible primitive representation $\psi $ of the subgroup $N$ over $k$ such that the representation $\varphi $ is induced from $\psi $ and the quotient group $N/Ker\psi $ is finitely generated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00398v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatolii V. Tushev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine highest weight structures on module categories over quiver Hecke algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the category of finitely generated graded modules over the quiver Hecke algebra of arbitrary type admits numerous stratifications in the sense of Kleshchev. A direct consequence is that the full subcategory corresponding to the quantum unipotent subgroup associated with any Weyl group element is an affine highest weight category. Our results significantly generalize earlier works by Kato, Brundan, Kleshchev, McNamara and Muth. The key ingredient is a realization of standard modules via determinantial modules. We utilize the technique of R-matrices to study these standard modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12903v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruto Murata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projective representation theory for compact quantum groups and the quantum Baum-Connes assembly map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.04365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.04365v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the theory of projective representations for a compact quantum group $\mathbb{G}$, i.e. actions of $\mathbb{G}$ on $\mathcal{B}(H)$ for some Hilbert space $H$. We show that any such projective representation is inner, and is hence induced by an $\Omega$-twisted representation for some unitary measurable $2$-cocycle $\Omega$ on $\mathbb{G}$. We show that a projective representation is continuous, i.e. restricts to an action on the compact operators $\mathcal{K}(H)$, if and only if the associated $2$-cocycle is regular, and that this condition is automatically satisfied if $\mathbb{G}$ is of Kac type. This allows in particular to characterise the torsion of projective type of $\widehat{\mathbb{G}}$ in terms of the projective representation theory of $\mathbb{G}$. For a given regular unitary $2$-cocycle $\Omega$, we then study $\Omega$-twisted actions on C$^*$-algebras. We define deformed crossed products with respect to $\Omega$, obtaining a twisted version of the Baaj-Skandalis duality and a quantum version of the Packer-Raeburn's trick. As an application, we provide a twisted version of the Green-Julg isomorphism and obtain the quantum Baum-Connes assembly map for permutation torsion-free discrete quantum groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.04365v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4171/JNCG/596</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Noncommut. Geom. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kenny De Commer, Rub\'en Martos, Ryszard Nest</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A super Littlewood--Richardson type rule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.09633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.09633v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a super version of the Littlewood--Richardson rule for super Schur functions over signed alphabets. We give in particular combinatorial interpretations of the super Littlewood--Richardson coefficients using the properties of super Young tableaux, which have found rich applications in representation theory, algebraic combinatorics, and mathematical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.09633v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nohra Hage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost flat highest weights and application to Wilson loops on compact surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11286v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive new formulas for the expectation and variance of Wilson loops for any contractible simple loop on a compact orientable surface of genus $1$ and higher, in the model of two-dimensional Yang--Mills theory with structure group $\mathrm{U}(N)$. They are written in terms of a Gaussian measure on the dual of $\mathrm{U}(N)$ introduced recently by the author and M. Ma\"ida \cite{LM3}. From these formulas, we prove a quantitative result on the convergence of the expectation and variance as $N$ tends to infinity, refining a result of the author and A. Dahlqvist \cite{DL}. We finally derive the large $g$ limit of the Wilson loop expectation and variance, by analogy with the study of integrals on moduli spaces of compact hyperbolic surfaces. Surprisingly, the variance does not vanish in this regime, but there are no nontrivial fluctuations of any order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11286v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibaut Lemoine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal graph series, chromatic functions, and their index theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09985v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present paper, we introduce the concept of universal graph series. We then present four invariants of graphs and discuss some of their properties. In particular, one of these invariants is a generalization of the chromatic symmetric function and a complete invariant for graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09985v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsuyoshi Miezaki, Akihiro Munemasa, Yusaku Nishimura, Tadashi Sakuma, Shuhei Tsujie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence classes of lower and upper descent weak Bruhat intervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08413v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathrm{Int}(n)$ denote the set of nonempty left weak Bruhat intervals in the symmetric group $\mathfrak{S}_n$. We investigate the equivalence relation $\overset{D}{\simeq}$ on $\mathrm{Int}(n)$, where $I \overset{D}{\simeq} J$ if and only if there exists a descent-preserving poset isomorphism between $I$ and $J$. For each equivalence class $C$ of $(\mathrm{Int}(n), \overset{D}{\simeq})$, a partial order $\preceq$ is defined by $[\sigma, \rho]_L \preceq [\sigma', \rho']_L$ if and only if $\sigma \preceq_R \sigma'$. Kim-Lee-Oh (2023) showed that the poset $(C, \preceq)$ is isomorphic to a right weak Bruhat interval.
  In this paper, we focus on lower and upper descent weak Bruhat intervals, specifically those of the form $[w_0(S), \sigma]_L$ or $[\sigma, w_1(S)]_L$, where $w_0(S)$ is the longest element in the parabolic subgroup $\mathfrak{S}_S$ of $\mathfrak{S}_n$, generated by $\{s_i \mid i \in S\}$ for a subset $S \subseteq [n-1]$, and $w_1(S)$ is the longest element among the minimal-length representatives of left $\mathfrak{S}_{[n-1] \setminus S}$-cosets in $\mathfrak{S}_n$. We begin by providing a poset-theoretic characterization of the equivalence relation $\overset{D}{\simeq}$. Using this characterization, the minimal and maximal elements within an equivalence class $C$ are identified when $C$ is a lower or upper descent interval. Under an additional condition, a detailed description of the structure of $(C, \preceq)$ is provided. Furthermore, for the equivalence class containing $[w_0(S), \sigma]_L$, an injective hull of ${\sf B}([w_0(S), \sigma]_L)$ is given, and for the equivalence class containing $[\sigma, w_1(S)]_L$, a projective cover of ${\sf B}([\sigma, w_1(S)]_L)$ is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08413v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung-Il Choi, Sun-Young Nam, Young-Tak Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
