<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT</link>
    <description>math.RT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 01:44:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Monotonicity of inverse Kazhdan-Lusztig polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For arbitrary Coxeter systems, we prove that inverse Kazhdan-Lusztig polynomials satisfy a monotonicity property. This follows from the validity of Soergel's conjecture and the existence of injective morphisms between Rouquier complexes in the mixed perverse Hecke category. The monotonicity property is generalised to parabolic Kazhdan-Lusztig polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11200v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Baine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derived Satake morphisms for $p$-small weights in characteristic $p$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a finite unramified extension of $\mathbb{Q}_p$ with ring of integers $\mathcal{O}_F$, and let $\mathbf{G}$ denote a split, connected reductive group over $\mathcal{O}_F$. We fix a Borel subgroup $\mathbf{B} = \mathbf{T}\mathbf{U}$ with maximal torus $\mathbf{T}$ and unipotent radical $\mathbf{U}$, and let $L(\lambda)$ denote an irreducible representation of $G_0 := \mathbf{G}(\mathcal{O}_F)$ with coefficients in a sufficiently large field of characteristic $p$. Set $G := \mathbf{G}(F)$, etc.
  Assuming $\lambda$ is a $p$-small and sufficiently regular character and that $p - 1$ is greater than the Coxeter number of $\mathbf{G}$, we show that the complex $L(U,\textrm{c-ind}_{G_0}^{G}(L(\lambda)))$ splits as the orthogonal direct sum of its cohomology objects in the derived category of smooth $T$-representations in characteristic $p$. (Here $L(U, -)$ denotes Heyer's left adjoint of parabolic induction, from the derived category of smooth $G$-representations to the derived category of smooth $T$-representations.) Consequently, this gives rise to a collection of morphisms of graded spherical Hecke algebras $$\displaystyle{\bigoplus_{i \in \mathbb{Z}}\textrm{Ext}_{G}^{i}\left(\textrm{c-ind}_{G_0}^{G}(L(\lambda)),~\textrm{c-ind}_{G_0}^{G}(L(\lambda))\right) \longrightarrow \bigoplus_{i \in \mathbb{Z}}\textrm{Ext}_{T}^{i}\left(\textrm{c-ind}_{T_0}^{T}(L^n(U_0,L(\lambda))),~\textrm{c-ind}_{T_0}^{T}(L^n(U_0,L(\lambda)))\right)}$$ indexed by $n=-[F:\mathbb{Q}_p]\dim(\mathbf{U}), \ldots, 0$, which we refer to as derived Satake morphisms. For $\lambda=0$ and $n=0$, this recovers the graded mod $p$ Satake homomorphism constructed by Ronchetti.
  We also give some partial results for general standard parabolic subgroups $\mathbf{P} = \mathbf{M}\mathbf{N} \subset \mathbf{G}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11269v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karol Koziol, C\'edric P\'epin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representation-finite tensor product algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we complete the classification of representation-finite tensor product algebras in terms of quiver with relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11363v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functors on the category of finite sets revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11623v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the structure of the category of representations of $\mathbf{FA}$, the category of finite sets and all maps, mostly working over a field of characteristic zero. This category is not semi-simple and exhibits interesting features.
  We first construct the simple representations, recovering the classification given by Wiltshire-Gordon. The construction given here also yields explicit descriptions of the indecomposable projectives.
  These results are used to give a convenient set of projective generators of the category of representations of $\mathbf{FA}$ and hence a Morita equivalence result. This is used to explain how to calculate the multiplicities of the composition factors of an arbitrary object, based only on its underlying $\mathbf{FB}$-representation, where $\mathbf{FB}$ is the category of finite sets and bijections.
  This is applied to show how to calculate the morphism spaces between projectives in our chosen set of generators, as well as for a closely related family of objects (the significance of which can be shown by relative nonhomogeneous Koszul duality theory).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11623v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geoffrey Powell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filtering the linearization of the category of surjections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A filtration of the morphisms of the $k$-linearization $k \mathbf{FS}$ of the category $\mathbf{FS}$ of finite sets and surjections is constructed using a natural $k \mathbf{FI}^{op}$-module structure induced by restriction, where $\mathbf{FI}$ is the category of finite sets and injections. This yields the `primitive' subcategory $ k \mathbf{FS}^0 \subset k \mathbf{FS}$ that is of independent interest.
  Working over a field of characteristic zero, the subquotients of this filtration are identified as bimodules over $k \mathbf{FB}$, where $\mathbf{FB}$ is the category of finite sets and bijections, also exhibiting and exploiting additional structure. In particular, this describes the underlying $k \mathbf{FB}$-bimodule of $k \mathbf{FS}^0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11627v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geoffrey Powell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing component groups of stabilizers of nilpotent orbit representatives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The theory of nilpotent orbits of simple Lie algebras has seen tremendous developments over the past decades. In this context an important role is played by the component group of the stabilizer of a nilpotent element. In this work, the aim is to show computational methods to obtain explicit generators of the component group of the centralizer of a nilpotent element in a simple Lie algebra over $\mathbb{C}$. In some cases such generators had already been determined by impressive hand calculations but these often use the specific form of the chosen representative and are thus not immediately applicable to different representatives of the same orbit. It is then interesting to show how to overcome this issue constructing specific algorithms: for the classical types there is a straightforward method that directly translates well-known theoretical constructions; for the exceptional types we devise a method using the double centralizer of an $\mathfrak{sl}_2$-triple. In particular, it gives an independent construction of the component group, that does not depend on the prior knowledge of its isomorphism type. For our purposes, we needed to construct many algorithms which have been mainly implemented in the computational algebra system GAP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11801v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Di Bella, Willem A. De Graaf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denominator conjecture for some surface cluster algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The denominator conjecture, proposed by Fomin and Zelevinsky, says that for a cluster algebra, the cluster monomials are uniquely determined by their denominator vectors with respect to an initial cluster. In this paper, for a cluster algebra from a marked surface with at least three boundary marked points, we establish this conjecture with respect to a given strong admissible tagged triangulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11826v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changjian Fu, Shengfei Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite friezes of affine type D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11232v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we study infinite friezes arising from cluster categories of affine type $D$ and determine the growth coefficients for these friezes. We prove that for each affine type $D$, the friezes given by the tubes all have the same growth behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11232v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karin Baur, L\'ea Bittmann, Emily Gunawan, Gordana Todorov, Emine Y{\i}ld{\i}r{\i}m</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wigglyhedra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11632v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by categorical representation theory, we define the wiggly complex, whose vertices are arcs wiggling around $n+2$ points on a line, and whose faces are sets of wiggly arcs which are pairwise pointed and non-crossing. The wiggly complex is a $(2n-1)$-dimensional pseudomanifold, whose facets are wiggly pseudotriangulations. We show that wiggly pseudotriangulations are in bijection with wiggly permutations, which are permutations of $[2n]$ avoiding the patterns $(2j-1) \cdots i \cdots (2j)$ for $i &lt; 2j-1$ and $(2j) \cdots k \cdots (2j-1)$ for $k &gt; 2j$. These permutations define the wiggly lattice, an induced sublattice of the weak order. We then prove that the wiggly complex is isomorphic to the boundary complex of the polar of the wigglyhedron, for which we give explicit and simple vertex and facet descriptions. Interestingly, we observe that any Cambrian associahedron is normally equivalent to a well-chosen face of the wigglyhedron. Finally, we recall the correspondence of wiggly arcs with objects in a category, and we develop categorical criteria for a subset of wiggly arcs to form a face of the wiggly complex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11632v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asilata Bapat, Vincent Pilaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli stacks of quiver bundles with applications to Higgs bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a general method for constructing moduli stacks whose points are diagrams of vector bundles over a fixed base, indexed by a fixed simplicial set -- that is, quiver bundles of a fixed shape. We discuss some constraints on the base for these moduli stacks to be algebraic and observe that a large class of interesting schemes satisfy these constraints. Using this construction, we provide an alternate construction of moduli stacks of Higgs bundles along with a proof of algebraicity following readily from the algebraicity of moduli stacks of quiver bundles. One feature of our approach is that, for each of the moduli stacks we discuss, there are algebraic moduli stacks parametrizing morphisms of the objects being classified. We discuss some potential applications of this in categorifying non-abelian Hodge theory in a sense we will make precise. We also discuss potential applications of our methods and perspectives to the subjects of quiver modifications, abstract moduli theory, and homotopy theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11958v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmud Azam, Steven Rayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sign of linear periods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.12106v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a group with subgroup $H$, and let $(\pi,V)$ be a complex representation of $G$. The natural action of the normalizer $N$ of $H$ in $G$ on the space $\mathrm{Hom}_H(\pi,\mathbb{C})$ of $H$-invariant linear forms on $V$, provides a representation $\chi_{\pi}$ of $N$ trivial on $H$, which is a character when $\mathrm{Hom}_H(\pi,\mathbb{C})$ is one dimensional. If moreover $G$ is a reductive group over a local field, and $\pi$ is smooth irreducible, it is an interesting problem to express $\chi_{\pi}$ in terms of the possibly conjectural Langlands parameter $\phi_\pi$ of $\pi$. In this paper we consider the following situation: $G=\mathrm{GL}_m(D)$ for $D$ a central division algebra of dimension $d^2$ over a local field $F$ of characteristic zero, $H$ is the centralizer of a non central element $\delta\in G$ such that $\delta^2$ is in the center of $G$, and $\pi$ has generic Jacquet-Langlands transfer to $\mathrm{GL}_{md}(F)$. In this setting the space $\mathrm{Hom}_H(\pi,\mathbb{C})$ is at most one dimensional. When $\mathrm{Hom}_H(\pi,\mathbb{C})\simeq \mathbb{C}$ and $H\neq N$, we prove that the value of the $\chi_{\pi}$ on the non trivial class of $\frac{N}{H}$ is $(-1)^m\epsilon(\phi_\pi)$ where $\epsilon(\phi_\pi)$ is the root number of $\phi_{\pi}$. Along the way we extend many useful multiplicity one results for linear and Shalika models to the case of non split $G$. When $F$ is $p$-adic we also classify standard modules with linear periods and Shalika models, which are new results even when $D=F$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.12106v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>U. K. Anandavardhanan, Hengfei Lu, Nadir Matringe, Vincent S\'echerre, Chang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomological integrality for symmetric representations of reductive groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09218v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove the integrality conjecture for quotient stacks given by a symmetric representation of a reductive group. This result will be crucial to generalise cohomological Donaldson-Thomas theory of $2$ and $3$-Calabi-Yau categories to $0$ and $(-1)$-shifted symplectic stacks respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09218v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucien Hennecart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Ginzburg-Kaplan gamma factors and Bessel-Speh functions for finite general linear groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14262v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a new construction of tensor product gamma factors for a pair of irreducible representations of $\operatorname{GL}_c\left(\mathbb{F}_q\right)$ and $\operatorname{GL}_k\left(\mathbb{F}_q\right)$. This construction is a finite field analog of a construction of doubling type due to Kaplan in the local field case and due to Ginzburg in the global case, and it only assumes that one of the representations in question is generic. We use this construction to establish a relation between special values of Bessel functions attached to Speh representations and exotic matrix Kloosterman sums. Using this relation, we establish various identities, including the multiplicativity identity of exotic matrix Kloosterman sums.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14262v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oded Carmon, Elad Zelingher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skew symplectic and orthogonal characters through lattice paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.11730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.11730v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The skew Schur functions admit many determinantal expressions. Chief among them are the (dual) Jacobi-Trudi formula and the Lascoux-Pragacz formula, which is a skew analogue of the Giambelli identity. Comparatively, the skew characters of the symplectic and orthogonal groups, also known as the skew symplectic and orthogonal Schur functions, have received less attention in this direction. We establish analogues of the dual Jacobi-Trudi and Lascoux-Pragacz formulae for these characters. Our approach is entirely combinatorial, being based on lattice path descriptions of the tableaux models of Koike and Terada. Ordinary Jacobi-Trudi formulae are then derived in an algebraic manner from their duals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.11730v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ejc.2024.104000</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Journal of Combinatorics 122 (2024), 104000</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Seamus P. Albion, Ilse Fischer, Hans H\"ongesberg, Florian Schreier-Aigner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building pretorsion theories from torsion theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00316v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Torsion theories play an important role in abelian categories and they have been widely studied in the last sixty years. In recent years, with the introduction of pretorsion theories, the definition has been extended to general (non-pointed) categories. Many examples have been investigated in several different contexts, such as topological spaces and topological groups, internal preorders, preordered groups, toposes, V-groups, crossed modules, etc. In this paper, we show that pretorsion theories naturally appear also in the "classical" framework, namely in abelian categories. We propose two ways of obtaining pretorsion theories starting from torsion theories. The first one uses "comparable" torsion theories, while the second one extends a torsion theory with a Serre subcategory. We also give a universal way of obtaining a torsion theory from a given pretorsion theory in additive categories. We conclude by providing several applications in module categories, internal groupoids, recollements and representation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00316v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Campanini, Francesca Fedele</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
