<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT</link>
    <description>math.RT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:04:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Special orthogonal, special unitary, and symplectic groups as products of Grassmannians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe a curious structure of the special orthogonal, special unitary, and symplectic groups that has not been observed, namely, they can be expressed as matrix products of their corresponding Grassmannians realized as involution matrices. We will show that $\operatorname{SO}(n)$ is a product of two real Grassmannians, $\operatorname{SU}(n)$ a product of four complex Grassmannians, and $\operatorname{Sp}(2n, \mathbb{R})$ or $\operatorname{Sp}(2n, \mathbb{C})$ a product of four symplectic Grassmannians over $\mathbb{R}$ or $\mathbb{C}$ respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18172v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lek-Heng Lim, Xiang Lu, Ke Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the (super)cocenter of Cyclotomic Sergeev algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that cyclotomic Sergeev algebra $\mathfrak{h}_n^g$ is symmetric when the level is odd and supersymmetric when the level is even. We give an integral basis for ${\rm Tr}(\mathfrak{h}_n^g)_{\overline{0}}$, and recover Ruff's result on the rank of ${\rm Z}(\mathfrak{h}_n^g)_{\bar{0}}$ when the level is odd. We obtain a generating set of ${\rm SupTr}(\mathfrak{h}_n^g)_{\overline{0}}$, which gives an upper bound of the dimension of ${\rm Z}(\mathfrak{h}_n^g)_{\bar{0}}$ when the level is even.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18260v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Li, Lei Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of irreducible $\mathfrak{u}$-diagonalizable $H_{\ell,n}$-modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a classification for the irreducible $\mathfrak{u}$-diagonalizable representations of the degenerate affine Hecke algebra of type $G(\ell,1,n)$. Precisely we show that such $H_{\ell,n}$-modules are indexed by $\ell$-skew shapes and that the representation indexed by a skew shape $D$ has a basis of eigenvectors indexed by standard Young tableaux of shape $D$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18446v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth Manosalva P</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Representations of Automorphism Groups of $\mathfrak{o}$-Modules of Type $(2,1^{n-2})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give an inductive procedure to find the representation zeta polynomial of $\mathrm{Aut}_\mathfrak{o}(\mathfrak{o}_2\oplus\mathfrak{o}_1\oplus\dots\oplus\mathfrak{o}_1)$. In particular, we show that the dimensions of the representations are given by evaluating finitely many polynomials at $q=|\mathfrak{o}_1|$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18480v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Jackson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of tame supercuspidal representations in arbitrary residue characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let F be a non-archimedean local field whose residue field has at least four elements. Let G be a connected reductive group over F that splits over a tamely ramified extension of F. We provide a construction of supercuspidal representations of G(F) that contains all the supercuspidal representations constructed by Yu in 2001, but that also works in residual characteristic two. The input for our construction is described uniformly for all residual characteristics and is analogous to Yu's input except that we do not require our characters to satisfy the genericity condition (GE2) that Yu imposes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18553v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jessica Fintzen, David Schwein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finiteness properties of generalized Montr\'eal functors with applications to mod $p$ representations of $\mathrm{GL}_n(\mathbb{Q}_p)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18396v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The second named author previously constructed a functor $\mathbb{V}^\vee\circ D^\vee_\Delta$ from the category of smooth $p$-power torsion representations of $\mathrm{GL}_n(\mathbb{Q}_p)$ to the category of inductive limits of continuous representations on finite $p$-primary abelian groups of the direct product $G_{\mathbb{Q}_p,\Delta}\times \mathbb{Q}_p^\times$ of $(n-1)$ copies of the absolute Galois group of $\mathbb{Q}_p$ and one copy of the multiplicative group $\mathbb{Q}_p^\times$. In the present work we show that this functor attaches finite dimensional representations on the Galois side to smooth $p$-power torsion representations of finite length on the automorphic side. This has some implications on the finiteness properties of Breuil's functor, too. Moreover, $\mathbb{V}^\vee\circ D^\vee_\Delta$ produces irreducible representations of $G_{\mathbb{Q}_p,\Delta}\times \mathbb{Q}_p^\times$ when applied to irreducible objects on the automorphic side and detects isomorphisms unless it vanishes. Further, we determine the kernel of $D^\vee_\Delta$ when restricted to successive extensions of subquotients of principal series. We use this to characterize representations that are parabolically induced from the product of a torus and $\mathrm{GL}_2(\mathbb{Q}_p)$. Finally, we formulate a conjecture and prove partial results on the essential image.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18396v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gergely Jakov\'ac, Gergely Z\'abr\'adi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Character factorisations, $z$-asymmetric partitions and plethysm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18520v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Verschiebung operators $\varphi_t $ are a family of endomorphisms on the ring of symmetric functions, one for each integer $t\geq2$. Their action on the Schur basis has its origins in work of Littlewood and Richardson, and is intimately related with the decomposition of a partition into its $t$-core and $t$-quotient. Namely, they showed that the action on $s_\lambda$ is zero if the $t$-core of the indexing partition is nonempty, and otherwise it factors as a product of Schur functions indexed by the $t$-quotient. Much more recently, Lecouvey and, independently, Ayyer and Kumari have provided similar formulae for the characters of the symplectic and orthogonal groups, where again the combinatorics of cores and quotients plays a fundamental role. We embed all of these character factorisations in an infinite family involving an integer $z$ and parameter $q$ using a very general symmetric function defined by Hamel and King. The proof hinges on a new characterisation of the $t$-cores and $t$-quotients of $z$-asymmetric partitions which generalise the well-known classifications for self-conjugate and doubled distinct partitions. We also explain the connection between these results, plethysms of symmetric functions and characters of the symmetric group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18520v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seamus Albion</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Newton's identities in positive characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.19850v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Newton's identities provide a way to express elementary symmetric polynomials in terms of power polynomials over fields of characteristic zero. In this article, we study the failure of this relation in positive characteristic and what can be recovered. In particular, we show how one can write the elementary symmetric polynomials as rational functions in the power polynomials over any commutative unital ring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.19850v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jalgebra.2025.01.010</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sjoerd de Vries</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
