<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT</link>
    <description>math.RT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 01:31:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On simple restricted modules of Hamiltonian superalgebras with $p$-characters of height 0</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $H(2,1;\underline{t})$ be Hamiltonian superalgebras over $\mathbb{F}$, an algebraically closed field of prime characteristic $p&gt;3$, which are non-restricted simple Lie superalgebras, generally. In this paper, we study generalized $\chi$-reduced simple modules over $H(2,1;\underline{t})$. We proved that all generalized $\chi$-reduced Kac modules of $H(2,1;\underline{t})$ are simple with $p$-characters $\chi$ of height 0. Additionally, the isomorphism classes of these simple $H(2,1;\underline{t})$-modules are classified and their dimensions are determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08329v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyi Zhang, Liangyun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hiraga-Ichino-Ikeda conjecture on formal degrees for classical groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08470v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a conjecture of Hiraga-Ichino-Ikeda relating formal degrees of square-integrable representations to adjoint gamma factors for symplectic and even orthogonal groups over characteristic zero non-Archimedean local fields. The proof is based on the twisted endoscopic characterization of the local Langlands correspondence for such groups and extends an approach already appearing in the original paper of Hiraga-Ichino-Ikeda itself inspired from earlier work of Shahidi. Namely, the argument consists in computing in two different ways a residue of certain standard intertwining operators suitably extended to a large representation realized on an explicit space of functions. This gives rise to the spectral decomposition of certain singular twisted orbital integrals. The main theorem follows from a comparison of this identity with the Plancherel formula of a symplectic or even orthogonal group. The proof can be adapted to deal with other classical groups, namely odd orthogonal and unitary groups, but the formal degree conjecture was already established in these cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08470v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rapha\"el Beuzart-Plessis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Whittaker models beyond $\mathfrak{sl}_{2}$-triples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the notion of generalized Whittaker models by allowing them to be built upon smooth irreducible representations of unipotent subgroups of a $p$-adic reductive group that are not necessarily characters, nor induced from Weil representations. This notion generalizes the usual notion of generalized Whittaker models, which include the Bessel and Fourier--Jacobi models. Using Kirillov's orbit method for unipotent groups, we define and prove basic properties of the corresponding Jacquet functors. We also provide new instances of generalized Whittaker models of multiplicity one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08523v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gyujin Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Spherical Harmonics on the Heisenberg Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\h_n$ be the $(2n+1)$-dimensional Heisenberg group. and let ${\cal L}_\alpha$ be the sublaplacian of the Lie algebra of $\h_n$ A new spherical harmonics with its orthogonal polynomial properties is presented for the group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08619v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. E. Egwe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representations of the N=1 Heisenberg-Virasoro superalgebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We first define a class of non-weight modules over the N=1 Heisenberg-Virasoro superalgebra $\mathfrak{g}$, which are reducible modules.
  Then we give all submodules of such modules, and present the corresponding irreducible quotient modules which were exactly studied in \cite{DL}. Also, we prove that those modules constitute a complete classification of $U(\mathfrak{h})$-free modules of rank $2$ over $\mathfrak{g}$, where $\mathfrak{h}=\C L_{0}\oplus\C H_{0}$ is the degree-0 part of $\mathfrak{g}$. As an application, we obtain a class of weight $\mathfrak{g}$-modules from those non-weight $\mathfrak{g}$-modules by weighting functor. Furthermore, we study the non-weight modules over the four subalgebras of $\mathfrak{g}$: (i) the Heisenberg-Virasoro algebra; (ii) the Neveu-Schwarz algebra; (iii) the Fermion-Virasoro algebra; (iv) the Heisenberg-Clifford superalgebra. As far as we know, those non-weight Heisenberg-Virasoro modules were
  constructed in \cite{HCS}, but the structure of submodules was not clear. In this paper, we determine all submodules of them, and we show the corresponding irreducible quotient modules which were exactly defined in \cite{CG}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08738v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqi Hong, Haibo Chen, Yucai Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual rigidity of the Heisenberg groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the dual rigidity of the Heisenberg groups, that is, they can be distinguished from any other 1-connected Lie groups via the unitary dual spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08904v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ingrid Beltita, Daniel Beltita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planons and their Carroll-Galilei symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08390v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of planons, particles whose mobility is restricted to a plane, through the classification of coadjoint orbits and unitary irreducible representations of the centrally extended planon group. Planons are closely related to Galilei/Bargmann symmetries and, remarkably, the often-ignored massless coadjoint orbits of the Galilei group play a central r\^ole in their description. We thereby provide a nontrivial physical interpretation of these orbits. We further construct classical and quantum dipoles as bound states of monopoles, where the restricted planar motion arises from a novel mixed Carroll-Galilei symmetry. We also argue that the simplest and already experimentally realised systems with Carroll symmetry are in crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08390v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Figueroa-O'Farrill, Simon Pekar, Alfredo P\'erez, Stefan Prohazka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rankin-Selberg integrals for $\mathrm{GSpin}$ groups with application to the global Gan-Gross-Prasad conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09066v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct Rankin-Selberg integrals using Bessel models for a product of tensor product partial $L$-functions \begin{equation*} L^S(s,\pi\times\tau_1) L^S(s,\pi\times\tau_2)\cdots L^S(s,\pi\times\tau_r) \end{equation*} where $\pi$ is an irreducible cuspidal automorphic representation of a quasi-split $\mathrm{GSpin}$ group, and $\tau_1, \cdots, \tau_r$ are irreducible unitary cuspidal automorphic representations of $\mathrm{GL}_{k_1}, \cdots, \mathrm{GL}_{k_r}$ respectively. As an application, we prove one direction of the global Gan-Gross-Prasad conjecture for generic representations of quasi-split $\mathrm{GSpin}$ groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09066v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pan Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative singularity categories III: Cluster resolutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.09733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2006.09733v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We build foundations of an approach to study canonical forms of $2$-Calabi--Yau triangulated categories with cluster-tilting objects, using dg algebras and relative singularity categories. This is motivated by cluster theory, singularity categories, Wemyss's Homological Minimal Model Program and the relations between these topics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2006.09733v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Kalck, Dong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Lie superalgebra of transpositions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01555v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the group algebra of the symmetric group as a superalgebra, and describe its Lie subsuperalgebra generated by the transpositions. The updated version corrects some of the arguments made in Sections 4.5 - 4.7. The statements of the main results are unaffected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01555v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher M. Drupieski, Jonathan R. Kujawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derived Satake morphisms for $p$-small weights in characteristic $p$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11269v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a finite unramified extension of $\mathbb{Q}_p$ with ring of integers $\mathcal{O}_F$, and let $\mathbf{G}$ denote a split, connected reductive group over $\mathcal{O}_F$. We fix a Borel subgroup $\mathbf{B} = \mathbf{T}\mathbf{U}$ with maximal torus $\mathbf{T}$ and unipotent radical $\mathbf{U}$, and let $L(\lambda)$ denote an irreducible representation of $G_0 := \mathbf{G}(\mathcal{O}_F)$ with coefficients in a sufficiently large field of characteristic $p$. Set $G := \mathbf{G}(F)$, etc.
  Assuming $\lambda$ is a $p$-small and sufficiently regular character and that $p - 1$ is greater than the Coxeter number of $\mathbf{G}$, we show that the complex $L(U,\textrm{c-ind}_{G_0}^{G}(L(\lambda)))$ splits as the orthogonal direct sum of its cohomology objects in the derived category of smooth $T$-representations in characteristic $p$. (Here $L(U, -)$ denotes Heyer's left adjoint of parabolic induction, from the derived category of smooth $G$-representations to the derived category of smooth $T$-representations.) Consequently, this gives rise to a collection of morphisms of graded spherical Hecke algebras $$\displaystyle{\bigoplus_{i \in \mathbb{Z}}\textrm{Ext}_{G}^{i}\left(\textrm{c-ind}_{G_0}^{G}(L(\lambda)),~\textrm{c-ind}_{G_0}^{G}(L(\lambda))\right) \longrightarrow \bigoplus_{i \in \mathbb{Z}}\textrm{Ext}_{T}^{i}\left(\textrm{c-ind}_{T_0}^{T}(L^n(U_0,L(\lambda))),~\textrm{c-ind}_{T_0}^{T}(L^n(U_0,L(\lambda)))\right)}$$ indexed by $n=-[F:\mathbb{Q}_p]\dim(\mathbf{U}), \ldots, 0$, which we refer to as derived Satake morphisms. For $\lambda=0$ and $n=0$, this recovers the graded mod $p$ Satake homomorphism constructed by Ronchetti.
  We also give some partial results for general standard parabolic subgroups $\mathbf{P} = \mathbf{M}\mathbf{N} \subset \mathbf{G}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11269v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karol Koziol, C\'edric P\'epin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalised tree modules: Hom-sets and indecomposability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18996v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a zero-relation algebra over a field $\mathcal K$, Crawley-Boevey introduced the concept of a tree module and provided a combinatorial description of a basis for the space of homomorphisms between two tree modules--the basis elements are called graph maps. The indecomposability of tree modules is essentially due to Gabriel. We relax a condition in the definition of a tree module to define generalised tree modules and when $\mathrm{char}(\mathcal K)\neq2$, under a certain condition, provide a combinatorial description of a finite generating set for the space of homomorphisms between two such modules--we call the generators generalised graph maps. As an application, we provide a sufficient condition for the (in)decomposability of certain generalised tree modules. We also show that all indecomposable modules over a Dynkin quiver of type $\mathbf D$ are isomorphic to generalised tree modules--this result also follows from a theorem of Ringel which states that all exceptional modules over the path algebra $\mathcal KQ$ of a finite quiver $Q$ are generalised tree modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18996v4</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annoy Sengupta, Amit Kuber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli of objects in finite length abelian categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.10543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.10543v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct moduli spaces of objects in an abelian category satisfying some finiteness hypotheses. Our approach is based on the work of Artin-Zhang and the intrinsic construction of moduli spaces for stacks developed by Alper-Halpern-Leistner-Heinloth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.10543v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andres Fernandez Herrero, Emmett Lennen, Svetlana Makarova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli spaces of quadratic differentials: Abel-Jacobi map and deformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10265v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the moduli space of framed quadratic differentials with prescribed singularities parameterized by a decorated marked surface with punctures (DMSp), where simple zeros, double poles and higher order poles respectively correspond to decorations, punctures and boundary components. We show that the fundamental group of this space equals the kernel of the Abel-Jacobi (AJ) map from the surface mapping class group of DMSp to the first homology group of the marked surface (without decorations/punctures). Moreover, a universal cover of this space is given by the space of stability conditions on the associated 3-Calabi-Yau category.
  Furthermore, when we partially compactify and orbifold this moduli space by allowing the collision of simple zeros and some of the double poles, the resulting moduli space is isomorphic to a quotient of the space of stability conditions on the deformed (with respect to those collidable double poles) 3-Calabi-Yau category.
  Finally, we show that the fundamental group of this partially compactified orbifold equals the quotient group of the kernel of the AJ map by the square of any point-pushing diffeomorphism around any collidable double pole. This construction can produces any non-exceptional spherical/Euclidean Artin braid groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10265v4</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harish-Chandra Theorem for the Multi-Parameter Quantum Groups of Okado-Yamane Type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18599v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the centre of the multi-parameter quantum group $U_{q,G}(\mathfrak{g})$ introduced by Okado and Yamane, where $\mathfrak{g}$ is a complex simple Lie algebra, and all parameters are in general position. We mainly establish the Harish-Chandra theorem, proving that the Harish-Chandra homomorphism is an isomorphism; in particular, we determine the centre $Z(U_{q,G})\cong (U^0_\flat)^W$ is isomorphic to a polynomial algebra or a quotient algebra of a polynomial algebra. The same result holds for the $(U^0_\flat)^W$ of the two-parameter quantum group $U_{r,s}(\mathfrak{g})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18599v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaixiang Chen, Naihong Hu, Hengyi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic bootstrap for RCFT: signs and bounds for quasi-characters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07170v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quasi-characters are solutions of simple modular differential equations that form an explicit basis for the space of all admissible characters that can potentially describe rational CFT. They were classified for rank-$2$ in arXiv:1810.09472 [hep-th], where it was conjectured that their $q$-series has coefficients of alternating sign that stabilise to a fixed sign at order $\frac{c}{12}$ and sometimes undergo more exotic behaviour -- where $c$ is the central charge. Here we prove some of these conjectures and estimate the growth of coefficients near the stabilisation point. We also explain what role the signs play in the construction of admissible characters from quasi-characters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07170v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpit Das, Sunil Mukhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
