<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.RT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT</link>
    <description>math.RT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.RT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 03:01:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fixed points in Gieseker spaces and blocks of Ariki-Koike algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we establish combinatorial links between the irreducible components of the fixed point locus of the Gieseker variety and the block theory of Ariki-Koike algebras. First, we describe the fixed point locus in terms of Nakajima quiver varieties over the McKay quiver of type A. We then reinterpret the dimension of an irreducible component as double the weight of a block. Cores of charged multipartitions have been defined by Fayers and further developed by Jacon and Lecouvey. In addition, we give a new way to compute the multicharge associated with the core of a charged multipartition. Finally, we also explain how the notion of core blocks, defined by Fayers, is interpreted on the geometric side using the deep connection between quiver varieties and affine Lie algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10586v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rapha\"el Paegelow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite symmetric algebras in tensor categories and Verlinde categories of algebraic groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate objects in symmetric tensor categories that have simultaneously finite symmetric and finite exterior algebra. This forces the characteristic of the base field to be $p&gt;0$, and the maximal degree of non-vanishing symmetric and exterior powers to add up to a multiple of $p$. We give a complete classification of objects in tensor categories for which this sum equals $p$. All resulting tensor categories are Verlinde categories of reductive groups and we fill in some gaps in the literature on these categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10598v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Coulembier, Pavel Etingof, Joseph Newton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a specialization of Toda eigenfunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies rational functions $\mathfrak{J}_\alpha(q)$, which depend on a positive element $\alpha$ of the root lattice of a root system. These functions arise as Shapovalov pairings of Whittaker vectors in Verma modules of highest weight $-\rho$ for quantum groups and as Hilbert series of Zastava spaces, and are related to the Toda system. They are specializations of multivariate functions more commonly studied in the literature. We investigate the denominator of these rational functions and give an explicit combinatorial formula for the numerator in type A.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10655v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Labelle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group actions on relative cluster categories and Higgs categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a finite group acting on an ice quiver with potential $(Q, F, W)$. We construct the corresponding $G$-equivariant relative cluster category and $G$-equivariant Higgs category, extending the work of Demonet. Using the orbit mutations on the set of $G$-stable cluster-tilting objects of the Higgs category and an appropriate cluster character, we can link these data to an explicit skew-symmetrizable cluster algebra with coefficients. As a specific example, this provides an additive categorification for cluster algebras with principal coefficients in the non-simply laced case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10670v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yilin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbits on a product of two flags and a line and the Bruhat Order, I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G=GL(n)$ be the $n\times n$ complex general linear group and let $\mathcal{B}_{n}$ be its flag variety. The standard Borel subgroup $B$ of upper triangular matrices acts on the product $\mathcal{B}_{n}\times \mathbb{P}^{n-1}$ with finitely many orbits. In this paper, we study the $B$-orbits on the subvarieties $\mathcal{B}_{n}\times \mathcal{O}_{i}$, where $\mathcal{O}_{i}$ is the $B$-orbit on $\mathbb{P}^{n-1}$ containing the line through the origin in the direction of the $i$-th standard basis vector of $\mathbb{C}^{n}$. For each $i=1,\dots, n$, we construct a bijection between $B$-orbits on $\mathcal{B}_{n}\times\mathcal{O}_{i}$ and certain pairs of Schubert cells in $\mathcal{B}_{n}\times\mathcal{B}_{n}$. We also show that this bijection can be used to understand the Richardson-Springer monoid action on such $B$-orbits in terms of the classical monoid action of the symmetric group on itself. We also develop combinatorial models of these orbits and use these models to compute exponential generating functions for the sequences $\{|B\backslash(\mathcal{B}_{n}\times\mathcal{O}_{i})|\}_{n\geq 1}$ and $\{|B\backslash (\mathcal{B}_{n}\times \mathbb{P}^{n-1})|\}_{n\geq 1}$. In the sequel to this paper, we use the results of this paper to construct a correspondence between $B$-orbits on $\mathcal{B}_{n}\times\mathbb{P}^{n-1}$ and a collection of $B$-orbits on the flag variety $\mathcal{B}_{n+1}$ of $GL(n+1)$ and show that this correspondence respects closures relations and preserves monoid actions. As a consequence both closure relations and monoid actions for all $B$-orbits on $\mathcal{B}_{n}\times\mathbb{P}^{n-1}$ can be understood via the Bruhat order by using our results in [CE].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10912v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Colarusso, Sam Evens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On normal forms for the similarity classes of matrices and pairs of matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10926v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We answer two questions posed 1998 in the book 'Arnolds problems'. First, over any field k there is a representative system for the similarity classes of nxn-matrices which is a finite disjoint union of affine subspaces. And second, for n&gt;1 an analogous statement fails for pairs of nxn-matrices over any algebraically closed field of characteristic 0.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10926v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Bongartz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypercubic Decomposition of Verma Supermodules and Semibricks Realizing the Khovanov Algebra of Defect One</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study some variants of Verma modules of basic Lie superalgebras obtained via changing Borel subalgebras. These allow us to demonstrate that the principal block of \(\mathfrak{gl}(1|1)\) is realized as (non-Serre) full subcategories of any atypical block of BGG category \( \mathcal{O} \) of basic Lie superalgebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10987v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunsuke Hirota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the Howe Duality conjecture for symplectic-orthogonal and unitary pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short note we expand on recent results on the degenerate principle series $I(s,\chi)$ of classical groups associated to $s\in \mathbb{C}$ and a quadratic character $\chi$. In particular, we strengthen the result for $s\in \mathbb{R}_{\ge 0}$, which allows us to give as a corollary a new proof of the Howe duality conjecture for symplectic-orthogonal and unitary pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11551v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Droschl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quiver Grassmannians for the Bott-Samelson resolution of type A Schubert varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We realise the Bott-Samelson resolutions of type A Schubert varieties as quiver Grassmannians. In order to explicitly describe this isomorphism, we introduce the notion of a \textit{geometrically compatible} decomposition for any permutation in $S_n$. For smooth type A Schubert varieties, we identify a suitable dimension vector such that the corresponding quiver Grassmannian is isomorphic to the Schubert variety. To obtain these isomorphisms, we construct a special quiver with relations and investigate two classes of quiver Grassmannians for this quiver.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11790v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Iezzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thick subcategories of derived categories of gentle algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12023v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study thick subcategories of derived categories of gentle algebras. Any thick subcategory of a derived category of a gentle algebra is generated by a set of string objects or a set of band objects. We show the thick subcategories generated by string objects are in bijection with sets of non-crossing paths on the geometric model of the derived category.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12023v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Callum Page</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A counterexample to the Jordan-H\"older property for polarizable semiorthogonal decompositions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the Jordan-H\"older property fails for polarizable semiorthogonal decompositions -- those where every factor admits a Bridgeland stability condition. Counterexamples exist among Fukaya categories of surfaces and bounded derived categories of smooth projective varieties. Furthermore, we give an example of a smooth and proper pre-triangulated dg category with positive rank Grothendieck group which does not admit a stability condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12075v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Haiden, Dongjian Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic of matrices over rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10416v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The book is devoted to investigation of arithmetic of the matrix rings over certain classes of commutative finitely generated principal ideals do- mains. We mainly concentrate on constructing of the matrix factorization theory. We reveal a close relationship between the matrix factorization and specific properties of subgroups of the complete linear group and the special normal form of matrices with respect to unilateral equivalence. The properties of matrices over rings of stable range 1.5 are thoroughly studied.
  The book is intended for experts in the ring theory and linear algebra, senior and post-graduate students.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10416v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.15407/akademperiodika.430.278</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Kyiv, Akademperiodyka, 2021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Volodymyr Shchedryk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a conjecture of Green and Liebeck concerning codes in symmetric groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10744v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $A$ and $B$ be subsets of the symmetric group $S_n$ and $r$ a positive integer. If for every $g\in S_n$, there are precisely $r$ pairs $(a,b)\in A\times B$ such that $g=ab$, then we say that $A$ divides $r S_n$; the subset $B$ is called a code with respect to $A$ and we write $r S_n=A\boldsymbol{\cdot}B$. In this paper, we resolve a conjecture by Green and Liebeck \cite[Conjecture 2.3]{Green20} about codes in $S_n$. Let $n&gt;2k$ and let $j$ be such that $2^j\leqslant k&lt;2^{j+1}$. Suppose that $X = x^{S_n}$ is a conjugacy class in $S_n$ and $Y_k$ is the subgroup $S_k\times S_{n-k}$ of $S_n$, where the factor $S_k$ permutes the subset $\{1,\ldots,k\}$ and the factor $S_{n-k}$ permutes the subset $\{k+1,\ldots,n\}$. We show that $r S_n=X\boldsymbol{\cdot}Y_k$ if and only if the cycle-type of $x$ has exactly one cycle of length $2^i$ for $0\leqslant i\leqslant j$ and all other cycles have length at least $k+1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10744v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teng Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher Rank Macdonald Polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce higher rank generalizations of Macdonald polynomials. The higher rank non-symmetric Macdonald polynomials are Laurent polynomials in several sets of variables which form weight bases for higher rank polynomial representations of double affine Hecke algebras with respect to higher rank Cherednik operators. We prove that these polynomials satisfy generalized versions of the classical Knop--Sahi relations and we give combinatorial descriptions of their weights. The higher rank symmetric Macdonald polynomials are defined as Hecke-symmetrizations of the higher rank non-symmetric Macdonald polynomials and form eigenbases for the spaces of Hecke-invariant higher rank polynomials with respect to generalized finite variable Macdonald operators. We prove that the higher rank symmetric Macdonald polynomials satisfy stability properties allowing for the construction of infinite variable limits. These higher rank symmetric Macdonald functions form eigenbases for certain representations of the (positive) elliptic Hall algebra with respect to generalized infinite variable Macdonald operators. Lastly, we show that the higher rank polynomial representations may be used to construct higher rank polynomial representations of the double Dyck path algebra. This is a copy of the author's accepted extended abstract for FPSAC2025.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10965v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milo Bechtloff Weising</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunnels Under Geometries (or Instantons Know Their Algebras)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11294v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the tight binding model with multiple degenerate vacua we might treat wave function overlaps as instanton tunnelings between different wells (vacua). An amplitude for such a tunneling process might be constructed as $\mathsf{T}_{i\to j}\sim e^{-S_{\mathrm{ inst}}}{\mathbf{v}}_j^{+}{\mathbf{v}}_i^{-}$, where there is canonical instanton action suppression, and $\mathbf{v}_i^{-}$ annihilates a particle in the $i^{\mathrm{th}}$ vacuum, whereas $\mathbf{v}_j^{+}$ creates a particle in the $j^{\mathrm{th}}$ vacuum. Adiabatic change of the wells leads to a Berry-phase evolution of the couplings, which is described by the zero-curvature Gauss-Manin connection i.e. by a quantum $R$-matrix. Zero-curvature is actually a consequence of level repulsion or topological protection, and its implication is the Yang-Baxter relation for the $R$-matrices. In the simplest case the story is pure Abelian and not very exciting. But when the model becomes more involved, incorporates supersymmetry, gauge and other symmetries, such amplitudes obtain more intricate structures. Operators $\mathbf{v}_i^{-}$, $\mathbf{v}_j^{+}$ might also evolve from ordinary Heisenberg operators into a more sophisticated algebraic object -- a ``tunneling algebra''. The result for the tunneling algebra would depend strongly on geometry of the QFT we started with, and, unfortunately, at the moment we are unable to solve the reverse engineering problem. In this note we revise few successful cases of the aforementioned correspondence: quantum algebras $U_q(\mathfrak{g})$ and affine Yangians $Y(\hat{\mathfrak{g}})$. For affine Yangians we demonstrate explicitly how instantons ``perform'' equivariant integrals over associated quiver moduli spaces appearing in the alternative geometric construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11294v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry Galakhov, Alexei Morozov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable Machine Learning for Kronecker Coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the saliency of neural networks and employ interpretable machine learning models to predict whether the Kronecker coefficients of the symmetric group are zero or not. Our models use triples of partitions as input features, as well as b-loadings derived from the principal component of an embedding that captures the differences between partitions. Across all approaches, we achieve an accuracy of approximately 83% and derive explicit formulas for a decision function in terms of b-loadings. Additionally, we develop transformer-based models for prediction, achieving the highest reported accuracy of over 99%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11774v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgi Butbaia, Kyu-Hwan Lee, Fabian Ruehle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The shift-homological spectrum and parametrising kernels of rank functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11939v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For any compactly generated triangulated category we introduce two topological spaces, the shift-spectrum and the shift-homological spectrum. We use them to parametrise a family of thick subcategories of the compact objects, which we call radical. These spaces can be viewed as non-monoidal analogues of the Balmer and homological spectra arising in tensor-triangular geometry: we prove that for monogenic tensor-triangulated categories the Balmer spectrum is a subspace of the shift-spectrum. To construct these analogues we utilise quotients of the module category, rather than the lattice theoretic methods which have been adopted in other approaches. We characterise radical thick subcategories and show in certain cases, such as the perfect derived categories of tame hereditary algebras or monogenic tensor-triangulated categories, that every thick subcategory is radical. We establish a close relationship between the shift-homological spectrum and the set of irreducible integral rank functions, and provide necessary and sufficient conditions for every radical thick subcategory to be given by an intersection of kernels of rank functions. In order to facilitate these results, we prove that both spaces we introduce may equivalently be described in terms of the Ziegler spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11939v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isaac Bird, Jordan Williamson, Alexandra Zvonareva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conjectures on the reduced Kronecker coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.14668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.14668v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate a series of conjectures on the stable tensor product of irreducible representations of symmetric groups, which are closely related to the reduced Kronecker coefficients. These conjectures are certain generalizations of Okounkov's conjecture on the log-concavity of the Littlewood--Richardson coefficients and the Schur log-concavity theorem of Lam--Postnikov--Pylyavskyy. We prove our conjectures in some special cases and discuss some implications of these conjectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.14668v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Gui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitary representations of real groups and localization theory for Hodge modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.13215v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a conjecture of Schmid and the second named author that the unitarity of a representation of a real reductive Lie group with real infinitesimal character can be read off from a canonical filtration, the Hodge filtration. Our proof rests on three main ingredients. The first is a wall crossing theory for mixed Hodge modules: the key result is that, in certain natural families, the Hodge filtration varies semi-continuously with jumps controlled by extension functors. The second ingredient is a Hodge-theoretic refinement of Beilinson-Bernstein localization: we show that the Hodge filtration of a mixed Hodge module on the flag variety satisfies the usual cohomology vanishing and global generation properties enjoyed by the underlying $\mathcal{D}$-module. The third ingredient is an explicit calculation of the Hodge filtration on a tempered Hodge module. As byproducts of our work, we obtain a version of Saito's Kodaira vanishing for twisted mixed Hodge modules, a calculation of the Hodge filtration on a certain object in category $\mathcal{O}$, and a host of new vanishing results for coherent sheaves on flag varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.13215v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dougal Davis, Kari Vilonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Starfish lemma via birational quasi-isomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00404v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study birational quasi-isomorphisms between normal Noetherian domains endowed with cluster structures of geometric type. We prove an analogue of the Starfish lemma that allows one to transfer various cluster and algebraic properties of one variety onto another. In particular, we develop tools for proving that an upper cluster algebra equals the given commutative ring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00404v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitriy Voloshyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric interactions between bricks and $\tau$-rigidity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14863v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For finite dimensional algebras over algebraically closed fields, we prove some new results on the interactions between bricks and $\tau$-rigid modules, and also on their geometric counterparts-- brick components and generically $\tau$-reduced components. First, we give a new characterization of the locally representation-directed algebras and show that these are exactly the algebras for which every brick is $\tau$-rigid (hence, all indecomposable modules are bricks). We then consider analogous phenomena using some irreducible components of module varieties: the indecomposable components, brick components, and the indecomposable generically $\tau$-reduced components. For an algebra $A$, we prove that if two of these three sets of components coincide, then every indecomposable $\tau$-rigid $A$-module is a brick. For brick-infinite algebras, we also provide a new construction that yields, in some cases, a rational ray outside of the $\tau$-tilting fan (also called $g$-vector fan). For tame and $E$-tame algebras, we obtain new results on some open conjectures on $\tau$-tilting fans and bricks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14863v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaveh Mousavand, Charles Paquette</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphic functionals for the minimal representations of groups of type $D_n$ and $E_n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19640v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a split simply-connected group of type $D$ or $E$. The minimal automorphic representation $\Pi$ of $G(\mathbb A)$ admits a realization on a space of functions $\mathcal S(X(\mathbb A))$ for a variety $X$. In this paper we write explicitly an automorphic, i.e. $G(F)$-invariant, functional on $\mathcal S(X(\mathbb A)).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19640v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nadya Gurevich, David Kazhdan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The algebra of the monoid of order-preserving functions on an $n$-set and other reduced $E$-Fountain semigroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08075v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With every reduced $E$-Fountain semigroup $S$ which satisfies the generalized right ample condition we associate a category with zero morphisms $\mathcal{C}(S)$. Under some assumptions we prove an isomorphism of $\Bbbk$-algebras $\Bbbk S\simeq\Bbbk_{0}\mathcal{C}(S)$ between the semigroup algebra and the contracted category algebra where $\Bbbk$ is any commutative unital ring. This is a simultaneous generalization of a former result of the author on reduced E-Fountain semigroups which satisfy the congruence condition, a result of Junying Guo and Xiaojiang Guo on strict right ample semigroups and a result of Benjamin Steinberg on idempotent semigroups with central idempotents. The applicability of the new isomorphism is demonstrated with two well-known monoids which are not members of the above classes. The monoid of order-preserving functions on an $n$-set and the monoid of binary relations with demonic composition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08075v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itamar Stein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hom-orthogonal modules and brick-Brauer-Thrall conjectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For finite dimensional algebras over algebraically closed fields, we study the sets of pairwise Hom-orthogonal modules and obtain new results on some open conjectures on the behaviour of bricks and several related problems, which we generally refer to as brick-Brauer-Thrall (bBT) conjectures. Using some algebraic and geometric tools, and in terms of the notion of Hom-orthogonality, we find necessary and sufficient conditions for the existence of infinite families of bricks of the same dimension. This sheds new light on the bBT conjectures and we prove some of them for new families of algebras. Our results imply some interesting algebraic and geometric characterizations of brick-finite algebras as conceptual generalizations of local algebras. We also verify the bBT conjectures for any algebra whose Auslander-Reiten quiver has a generalized standard component, which particularly extends some results of Chindris-Kinser-Weyman on the algebras with preprojective components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20877v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaveh Mousavand, Charles Paquette</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contravariant Koszul duality between non-positive and positive dg algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08842v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Koszul dual of locally finite non-positive dg algebra is locally finite positive dg algebra. However, the Koszul dual of locally finite positive dg algebra is not necessary locally finite. We characterize locally finite positive dg algebras whose Koszul dual is locally finite. Moreover, we show that the Koszul dual functor induces contravariant equivalences between the perfect derived category and the perfectly valued derived category. As an application of Koszul dualities, we establish an ST-correspondence. We also show that, under some assumption, every covariantly finite bounded heart is a length heart, and the triangulated analogy of Smal{\o}'s symmetry holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08842v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riku Fushimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Lagrangian Formulation for Higher Spin Fields with Arbitrary Index Symmetry. I. Bosonic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1110.5044</link>
      <description>arXiv:1110.5044v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a Lagrangian description of irreducible integer higher-spin representations of the Poincare group with an arbitrary Young tableaux having k rows, on a basis of the universal BRST approach. Starting with a description of bosonic mixed-symmetry higher-spin fields in a flat space of any dimension in terms of an auxiliary Fock space associated with special Poincare module, we realize a conversion of the initial operator constraint system (constructed with respect to the relations extracting irreducible Poincare-group representations) into a first-class constraint system. For this purpose, we find, for the first time, auxiliary representations of the constraint subalgebra, to be isomorphic due to Howe duality to sp(2k) algebra, and containing the subsystem of second-class constraints in terms of new oscillator variables. We propose a universal procedure of constructing unconstrained gauge-invariant Lagrangians with reducible gauge symmetries describing the dynamics of both massless and massive bosonic fields of any spin. It is shown that the space of BRST cohomologies with a vanishing ghost number is determined only by the constraints corresponding to an irreducible Poincare-group representation. As examples of the general procedure, we formulate the method of Lagrangian construction for bosonic fields subject to arbitrary Young tableaux having 3 rows and derive the gauge-invariant Lagrangian for new model of massless rank-4 tensor field with spin $(2,1,1)$ and second-stage reducible gauge symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1110.5044v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2012.04.016</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl. Phys. B 862 (2012), pp.270-326</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>I. L. Buchbinder, A. Reshetnyak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On reduced arc spaces of toric varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.10432v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An arc space of an affine cone over a projective toric variety is known to be non-reduced in general. It was demonstrated recently that the reduced scheme structure is worth studying due to various connections with representation theory and combinatorics. In this paper we develop a general machinery for the description of the reduced arc spaces of affine cones over toric varieties. We apply our techniques to a number of classical cases and explore some connections with representation theory of current algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.10432v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2140/ant.2025.19.313</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Alg. Number Th. 19 (2025) 313-363</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Dumanski, Evgeny Feigin, Ievgen Makedonskyi, Igor Makhlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hecke Actions on Loops and Periods of Iterated Shimura Integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.00143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.00143v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we show that the classical Hecke correspondences T_N, N&gt;0, act on the free abelian groups generated by the conjugacy classes of the modular group SL_2(Z) and the conjugacy classes of its profinite completion. We show that this action induces a dual action on the ring of class functions of a certain relative unipotent completion of the modular group. This ring contains all iterated integrals of modular forms that are constant on conjugacy classes. It possesses a natural mixed Hodge structure and, after tensoring with Q_ell$, a natural action of the absolute Galois group. Each Hecke operator preserves this mixed Hodge structure and commutes with the action of the absolute Galois group. Unlike in the classical case, the algebra generated by these Hecke operators is not commutative. The appendix by Pham Tiep is not included. It can be found at arXiv:2303.02807.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.00143v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Hain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perverse filtrations and Fourier transforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13160v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the interaction between Fourier-Mukai transforms and perverse filtrations for a certain class of dualizable abelian fibrations. Multiplicativity of the perverse filtration and the "Perverse $\supset$ Chern" phenomenon for these abelian fibrations are immediate consequences of our theory. We also show that our class of fibrations include families of compactified Jacobians of integral locally planar curves.
  Applications include the following: (a) we prove the motivic decomposition conjecture for this class (including compactified Jacobian fibrations), which generalizes Deninger-Murre's theorem for abelian schemes; (b) we provide a new proof of the P=W conjecture for $\mathrm{GL}_r$; (c) we prove half of the P=C conjecture concerning refined BPS invariants for the local $\mathbb{P}^2$; (d) we show that the perverse filtration for the compactified Jacobian associated with an integral locally planar curve is multiplicative, which generalizes a result of Oblomkov-Yun for homogeneous singularities.
  Our techniques combine Arinkin's autoduality for coherent categories, Ng\^o's support theorem for the decomposition theorem, Adams operations in operational K-theory, and Corti-Hanamura's theory of relative Chow motives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13160v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davesh Maulik, Junliang Shen, Qizheng Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hook-Lengths, Symplectic/Orthogonal Contents and Amdeberhan's Conjectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01973v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The symplectic/orthogonal contents of partitions are related to the dimensions of irreducible representations of symplectic/orthogonal groups. In 2012, motivated by Nekrasov--Okounkov's hook-length formula and Stanley's hook-content formula, Amdeberhan proposed several conjectures about infinite product formulas for certain generating functions of hook-lengths and symplectic/orthogonal contents. Some special cases of his conjectures were recently proved by Amdeberhan, Andrews and Ballantine. In this paper, we prove the general cases of Amdeberhan's conjectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01973v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1112/plms.70026</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chenglang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A step to compute the determinant of finite semigroups not in ECom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00083v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The purpose of this paper is to begin studying the computation of the nonzero determinant of semigroups within the class of finite semigroups that possesses a pair of non-commutative idempotents. This paper focuses on a class of these semigroups introduced as $\ll$-smooth semigroups. This computation is applicable in the context of the extension of the MacWilliams theorem for codes over semigroup algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00083v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. H. Shahzamanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli stacks of quiver bundles with applications to Higgs bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11958v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a general method for constructing moduli stacks whose points are diagrams of vector bundles over a fixed base, indexed by a fixed simplicial set -- that is, quiver bundles of a fixed shape. We discuss some constraints on the base for these moduli stacks to be Artin and observe that a large class of interesting schemes satisfy these constraints. Using this construction, we recover Nakajima quiver varieties and provide an alternate construction for moduli stacks of Higgs bundles along with a proof of algebraicity following readily from the algebraicity of moduli stacks of quiver bundles. One feature of our approach is that, for each of the moduli stacks we discuss, there are moduli stacks that are Artin, parametrizing morphisms of the objects being classified. We discuss some potential applications of this in categorifying non-abelian Hodge theory in a sense we will make precise. We also discuss potential applications of our methods and perspectives to the subjects of quiver varieties, abstract moduli theory, and homotopy theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11958v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmud Azam, Steven Rayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum supersymmetric pairs of basic types</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02874v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We formulate and classify super Satake diagrams under a mild assumption, building on arbitrary Dynkin diagrams for finite-dimensional basic Lie superalgebras. We develop a theory of quantum supersymmetric pairs associated to the super Satake diagrams. We establish the quantum Iwasawa decomposition and construct quasi $K$-matrix associated with the quantum supersymmetric pairs. We also formulate a Schur duality between an $\imath$quantum supergroup (which is a new $q$-deformation of an ortho-symplectic Lie superalgebra) and the $q$-Brauer algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02874v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaolong Shen, Weiqiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Induction for representations of coideal doubles, with an application to quantum $SL(2,\mathbb{R})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18551v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the theory of induction in the setting of doubles of coideal $*$-subalgebras of compact quantum group Hopf $*$-algebras. We then exemplify parts of this theory in the particular case of quantum $SL(2,\mathbb{R})$, and compute the decomposition of the regular representation for quantum $SL(2,\mathbb{R})$ into irreducibles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18551v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenny De Commer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The versatility of the Drinfeld double of a finite group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11978v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this survey we review different instances in which the Drinfeld double of a finite group and its representations play a role, touching upon some of Tom Koornwinder's research interests: harmonic analysis, Lie algebras, quantum groups, non-commutative geometry, and Verlinde formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11978v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanna Carnovale, Nicola Ciccoli, Elena Collacciani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenvalue systems for integer orthogonal bases of multi-matrix invariants at finite N</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13631v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multi-matrix invariants, and in particular the scalar multi-trace operators of $\mathcal{N}=4$ SYM with $U(N)$ gauge symmetry, can be described using permutation centraliser algebras (PCA), which are generalisations of the symmetric group algebras and independent of $N$. Free-field two-point functions define an $N$-dependent inner product on the PCA, and bases of operators have been constructed which are orthogonal at finite $N$. Two such bases are well-known, the restricted Schur and covariant bases, and both definitions involve representation-theoretic quantities such as Young diagram labels, multiplicity labels, branching and Clebsch-Gordan coefficients for symmetric groups. The explicit computation of these coefficients grows rapidly in complexity as the operator length increases. We develop a new method for explicitly constructing all the operators with specified Young diagram labels, based on an $N$-independent integer eigensystem formulated in the PCA. The eigensystem construction naturally leads to orthogonal basis elements which are integer linear combinations of the multi-trace operators, and the $N$-dependence of their norms are simple known dimension factors. We provide examples and give computer codes in SageMath which efficiently implement the construction for operators of classical dimension up to 14. While the restricted Schur basis relies on the Artin-Wedderburn decomposition of symmetric group algebras, the covariant basis relies on a variant which we refer to as the Kronecker decomposition. Analogous decompositions exist for any finite group algebra and the eigenvalue construction of integer orthogonal bases extends to the group algebra of any finite group with rational characters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13631v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Padellaro, Sanjaye Ramgoolam, Ryo Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
