<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV</link>
    <description>math.CV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:01:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse images of a positive closed current for a holomorphic endomorphism of a compact K\"ahler manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that for a given surjective holomorphic endomorphism $f$ of a compact K\"ahler manifold $X$ and for some integer $p$ with $1\le p\le k$, there exists a proper invariant analytic subset $E$ for $f$ such that if $S$ is smooth in a neighborhood of $E$, the sequence $d_p^{-n}(f^n)^*(S-\alpha_S)$ converges to $0$ exponentially fast in the sense of currents where $d_p$ denotes the dynamical degree of order $p$ and $\alpha_S$ is a closed smooth form in the de Rham cohomology class of $S$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00607v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taeyong Ahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex analytic solutions for the TQG model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a condition under which the thermal quasi-geostrophic (TQG) model possesses a solution that is holomorphic in time with values in the Gevrey space of complex analytic functions. This can be seen as the complex extension of the work by Levermore and Oliver (1997) for the generalized Euler equation but applied to the TQG model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00575v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prince Romeo Mensah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphisms of K3 surfaces, signatures, and isometries of lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.06698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.06698v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Every Salem numbers of degree 4,6,8,12,14 or 16 is the dynamical degree of an automorphism of a non-projective K3 surface. We define a notion of signature of an automorphism, and use it to give a necessary and sufficient condition for Salem numbers of degree 10 and 18 to be realized as the dynamical degree of such an automorphism. The first part of the paper contains results on isometries of lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.06698v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eva Bayer-Fluckiger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manifolds with trivial Chern classes II: Manifolds Isogenous to a Torus Product, coframed Manifolds and a question by Baldassarri</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.11751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.11751v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by a general question addressed by Mario Baldassarri in 1956, we discuss characterizations of the Pseudo-Abelian Varieties introduced by Roth, and we introduce a first new notion, of Manifolds Isogenous to a k-Torus Product: the latter have the last k Chern classes trivial in rational cohomology and vanishing Chern numbers. We show that in dimension 2 the latter class is the correct substitute for some incorrect assertions by Enriques, Dantoni, Roth and Baldassarri: these are the surfaces with $K_X$ nef and $c_2(X)=0 \in H^4(X, \mathbb{Z})$. We observe in the last section, using a construction by Chad Schoen, that such a simple similar picture does not hold in higher dimension. We discuss then, as a class of solutions to Baldassarri's question, manifolds isogenous to projective (respectively: K\"ahler) manifolds whose tangent bundle or whose cotangent bundle has a trivial subbundle of positive rank. We see that the class of `partially framed' projective manifolds (that is, whose tangent bundle has a trivial subbundle) consists, in the case where $K_X$ is nef, of the Pseudo-Abelian varieties of Roth; while the class of `partially co-framed' projective manifolds is not yet fully understood in spite of the new results that we are able to show here: and we formulate some open questions and conjectures. In the course of the paper we address also the case of more general compact complex Manifolds, introducing the new notions of suspensions over parallelizable Manifolds, of twisted hyperelliptic Manifolds, and we describe the known results under the K\"ahler assumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.11751v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Catanese (Universitaet Bayreuth,KIAS Seoul)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
