<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV</link>
    <description>math.CV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 04:01:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Parametric Symplectic Jet Interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a parametric jet interpolation theorem for symplectic holomorphic automorphisms of $\mathbb{C}^{2n}$ with parameters in a Stein space. Moreover, we provide an example of an unavoidable set for symplectic holomorphic maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17581v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael B. Andrist, Gaofeng Huang, Frank Kutzschebauch, Josua Schott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All Teichmuller spaces are not starlike</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is the final step in solving the problem of starlikeness of Teichmuller spaces in Bers' embedding. This step concerns the case of finite dimensional Teichmuller spaces ${\mathbf T}(g, n)$ of positive dimension (corresponding to punctured Riemann surfaces of finite conformal type $(g, n)$ with $2g - 2 + n &gt; 0$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18239v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel L. Krushkal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted Bergman Kernels on Planar Domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.00219v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Boundary Behaviour of Weighted Bergman Kernels: For a planar domain $D \subset \mathbb{C}$ and an admissible weight function $\mu$ on it, some aspects of the boundary behaviour of the corresponding weighted Bergman kernel $K_{D, \mu}$ are studied. First, under the assumption that $\mu$ extends continuously to a smooth boundary point $p$ of $D$ and is non-vanishing there, we obtain a precise relation between $K_{D, \mu}$ and the classical Bergman kernel $K_D$ near $p$. Second, when viewed as functions of such weights, the weighted Bergman kernel is shown to have a suitable additive and multiplicative property near such boundary points.
  A Study on Holomorphic Isometries of Weighted Bergman Metrics: For a domain $D \subset \mathbb{C}^n$ and an admissible weight $\mu$ on it, we consider the weighted Bergman kernel $K_{D, \mu}$ and the corresponding weighted Bergman metric on $D$. In particular, motivated by work of Mok, Ng, Chan--Yuan and Chan--Xiao--Yuan among others, we study the nature of holomorphic isometries from the disc $\mathbb{D} \subset \mathbb{C}$ with respect to the weighted Bergman metrics arising from weights of the form $\mu = K_{\mathbb{D}}^{-d}$ for some integer $d \geq 0$. These metrics provide a natural class of examples that give rise to positive conformal constants that have been considered in various recent works on isometries. Specific examples of isometries that are studied in detail include those in which the isometry takes values in $\mathbb{D}^n$ and $\mathbb{D} \times \mathbb{B}^n$ where each factor admits a weighted Bergman metric as above for possibly different non-negative integers $d$. Finally, the case of isometries between polydisks in possibly different dimensions, in which each factor has a different weighted Bergman metric as above, is also presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.00219v3</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aakanksha Jain, Kaushal Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the class of almost subadditive weight functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10933v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We answer a question from A. V. Abanin and P. T. Tien about so-called almost subadditive weight functions in the sense of Braun-Meise-Taylor. Using recent knowledge of a growth index for functions, crucially appearing in the ultraholomorphic setting, we are able to show the existence of weights such that there does not exist an equivalent almost subadditive function and hence almost subadditive weights are a proper subclass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10933v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmaa.2024.128682</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Anal. Appl. 541, no. 1, 128682, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gerhard Schindl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric structures on the quaternionic unit ball and slice regular M\"obius transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13175v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Building from ideas of hypercomplex analysis on the quaternionic unit ball, we introduce Hermitian, Riemannian and K\"ahler-like structures on the latter. These are built from the so-called regular M\"obius transformations. Such geometric structures are shown to be natural generalizations of those from the complex setup. Our structures can be considered as more natural, from the hypercomplex viewpoint, than the usual quaternionic hyperbolic geometry. Furthermore, our constructions provide solutions to problems not achieved by hyper-K\"ahler and quaternion-K\"ahler geometries when applied to the quaternionic unit ball. We prove that the Riemannian metric obtained in this work yields the same tensor previously computed by Arcozzi-Sarfatti. However, our approach is completely geometric as opposed to the function theoretic methods of Arcozzi-Sarfatti.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13175v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raul Quiroga-Barranco</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
