<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV</link>
    <description>math.CV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 01:45:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Zalcman's lemma, Pinchuk's rescaling method, and Catlin's estimates revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a renormalization lemma for certain maps defined on the unit disc of C and taking values in some metric space. We show that the classical renormalization lemmas of Zalcman and Miniowitz can be deduced from our lemma. We also use it to establish a general normality statement for the Pinchuk's scaling method in C^2 and, incidentally, reprove the Catlin's estimates for the Kobayashi metric in finite type domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17633v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fran\c{c}ois Berteloot (IMT)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An RKHS approach to the indefinite Schwarz-Pick inequality on the bidisk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17596v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this short note, we will give a generalization of the indefinite Schwarz-Pick inequality due to Seto [8]. Our approach is based on a connection between complex geometry and the geometry of reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces, which was crucially used in our previous work [6].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17596v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Kojin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant weighted Bergman metrics on domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19588v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the cases where the weighted Bergman metrics of a domain are invariant under biholomorphisms by introducing the concept of {\it invariant weight assignments}, focusing on two examples by Tian and Tsuji, respectively. Using Bergman's minimum integral method and a domain version of the Tian-Yau-Zelditch expansion for the weighted Bergman kernels and metrics, we give an alternative proof of uniform convergence of Tian's sequence of Bergman kernels and metrics on uniform squeezing domains. We also present a proof of the uniform convergence of Tsuji's dynamical kernel sequence on uniform squeezing domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19588v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sungmin Yoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corona Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.15683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.15683v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For a wide class of domains $G\subset\mathbb C^d$ including balls and polydisks we prove the density of their canonical image in the spectrum of $H^\infty(G)$. This Corona Theorem is proved first in its abstract version for certain uniform algebras. We use properties of bands of measures and idempotents corresponding to Gleason parts.
  The essential tools are properties of hyper-Stonean spaces, normal and Henkin measures and some ideas based on Hoffman - Rossi theorem. We also use our previous results on weak-star closures of reducing bands of measures. Uniform bounds for operators used to solve the Gleason problem concerning ideals of analytic functions vanishing at given points are applied for bidual algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.15683v5</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marek Kosiek, Krzysztof Rudol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-window STFT phase retrieval: lattice uniqueness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.10620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.10620v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Short-time Fourier transform (STFT) phase retrieval refers to the reconstruction of a function $f$ from its spectrogram, i.e., the magnitudes of its short-time Fourier transform $V_gf$ with window function $g$. While it is known that for appropriate windows, any function $f \in L^2(\mathbb{R})$ can be reconstructed from the full spectrogram $|V_g f(\mathbb{R}^2)|$, in practical scenarios, the reconstruction must be achieved from discrete samples, typically taken on a lattice. It turns out that the sampled problem becomes much more subtle: recent results have demonstrated that uniqueness via lattice-sampling is unachievable, irrespective of the choice of the window function or the lattice density. In the present paper, we initiate the study of multi-window STFT phase retrieval as a way to effectively bypass the discretization barriers encountered in the single-window case. By establishing a link between multi-window Gabor systems, sampling in Fock space, and phase retrieval for finite frames, we derive conditions under which square-integrable functions can be uniquely recovered from spectrogram samples on a lattice. Specifically, we provide conditions on window functions $g_1, \dots, g_4 \in L^2(\mathbb{R})$, such that every $f \in L^2(\mathbb{R})$ is determined up to a global phase from $$\left(|V_{g_1}f(A\mathbb{Z}^2)|, \, \dots, \, |V_{g_4}f(A\mathbb{Z}^2)| \right)$$ whenever $A \in \mathrm{GL}_2(\mathbb{R})$ satisfies the density condition $|\det A|^{-1} \geq 4$. For real-valued functions, a density of $|\det A|^{-1} \geq 2$ is sufficient. Corresponding results for irregular sampling are also shown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.10620v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Grohs, Lukas Liehr, Martin Rathmair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase retrieval in Fock space and perturbation of Liouville sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00385v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the determination of functions in Fock space from samples of their absolute value, known as the phase retrieval problem in Fock space. An important finding in this research field asserts that phaseless sampling on lattices of arbitrary density renders the problem unsolvable. The present study establishes solvability when using irregular sampling sets of the form $A \cup B \cup C$, where $A, B,$ and $C$ constitute perturbations of a Liouville set, i.e., a set with the property that all functions in Fock space bounded on the set are constant. The sets $A, B,$ and $C$ adhere to specific geometrical conditions of closeness and noncollinearity. We show that these conditions are sufficiently generic so as to allow the perturbations to be chosen also at random. By proving that Liouville sets occupy an intermediate position between sets of stable sampling and sets of uniqueness, we obtain the first construction of uniqueness sets for the phase retrieval problem in Fock space having a finite density. The established results apply to the Gabor phase retrieval problem in subspaces of $L^2(\mathbb{R})$, where we derive additional reductions of the size of uniqueness sets: for the class of real-valued functions, uniqueness is achieved from two perturbed lattices; for the class of even real-valued functions, a single perturbation suffices, resulting in a separated set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00385v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Grohs, Lukas Liehr, Martin Rathmair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Equations Involving the Gamma Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01658v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $V\subseteq\mathbb{C}^{2n}$ be an algebraic variety with no constant coordinates and with a dominant projection onto the first $n$ coordinates. We show that the intersection of $V$ with the graph of the $\Gamma$ function is Zariski dense in $V$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01658v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Eterovi\'c, Adele Padgett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An iterative construction of complete K\"ahler--Einstein metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12599v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend Tsuji's iterative construction of a K\"ahler--Einstein metric with negative scalar curvature to (non-compact) K\"ahler manifolds with bounded geometry, using Berndtsson's method for the compact setting. Consequently, given a holomorphic surjective map $p:X \to Y$, where $X$ is a weakly pseudoconvex K\"ahler manifold and $Y$ is a complex manifold, whose smooth fibers admit K\"ahler--Einstein metrics with negative scalar curvature and bounded geometry, we show that the fiberwise K\"ahler--Einstein metric induces a semi-positively curved metric on the relative canonical bundle $K_{X/Y}$ of $p$. Moreover, our approach can be applied to obtain the plurisubharmonic variation of cusp K\"ahler--Einstein metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12599v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quang-Tuan Dang, Tat Dat T\^o</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
