<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV</link>
    <description>math.CV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 05:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Entire solution of a partial differential equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, using Nevanlinna's value distribution theory of meromorphic functions in several complex variables, we study for the existence of entire solutions $f$ in $\mathbb{C}^2$ of the following partial differential equation \[a_1\left(\frac{\partial f(z_1,z_2)}{\partial z_1}\right)^n+a_2f^n(z_1,z_2)=p_1e^{r(z_1,z_2)}+p_2e^{s(z_1,z_2)},\] where $n$ is a positive integer such that $n\geq 3$, $a_1,a_2,p_1,p_2$ are non-zero constants and $r(z_1,z_2), s(z_1,z_2)$ are arbitrary polynomials in $\mathbb{C}^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09579v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junfeng Xu, Nabadwip Sarkar, Sujoy Majumder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Yang-Hua theorems in several complex variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate meromorphic solutions in $\mathbb{C}^m$ of the nonlinear differential equation \[\displaystyle f^n\partial_u(f)g^n\partial_u(g)=1,\]
  where $\partial_u(f)=\sum_{j=1}^mu_j\partial_j(f)$ and $\sum_{j=1}^m u_j\neq 0$. Our results extend those of Yang and Hua [{\sc C. C. Yang} and {\sc X. H. Hua}, Uniqueness and value sharing of meromorphic functions, \textit{Ann. Acad. Sci. Fenn. Math.}, \textbf{22} (1997), 395-406.] to the framework of several complex variables. Moreover, we establish new uniqueness theorems that further generalize their conclusions to higher dimensions. As an application, explicit solutions of certain nonlinear partial differential equations in several variables are derived, and their physical interpretations are summarized in tabular form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09607v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijit Banerjee, Sujoy Majumder, Debabrata Pramanik, Nabadwip Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent advances in Bergman type projections in bounded pseudoconvex and tubular domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The intention of this survey to collect in one paper many recent results and advances related with Bergman type projection acting in various spaces of analytic functions in several complex variables in the unit ball, tubular domains over symmetric cones and bounded strongly pseudoconvex domains between function spaces of different dimensions. Various new interesting extentions of old, classical results on Bergman projections will be provided in our survey. Previously all these results were given in various papers of the first author. Bergman type projections have many nice applications in complex function theory of several complex variables in tubular domains over symmetric cones and in bounded strongly pseudoconvex domains. Our results can be seen as direct extensions of previously known results provided earlier by E.Stein, D.Bekolle, D.Debertol, B.F.Sehba, W.S.Cohn, C.Nana, L.Chen, Sh.Zhang and others which relate function spaces with the same dimension. Practically all results on Bergman type projections acting between function spaces with different dimension may be valid both in context of tubular and pseudoconvex domains with similar proofs though we formulate some results only in tube or pseudoconvex domains. Some our results are new even in case of simplest unit disk and polydisk. Problems which are related with Bergman type projection acting between various analytic and measurable function spaces of different dimensions in various complicated domains in C^n are as far as we know completely new and may have various new interesting applications in compex function theory. In this paper various new interesting problems in this research area will also be formulated and posed by authors. Our results may be valid also with very similar proofs in various Siegel domains of second type, matrix domains, bounded symmetric domains and various other domains in C^n with complicated structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10270v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. F. Shamoyan, M. G. Bashmakova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphisms of the Worm Domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Diederich-Forn{\ae}ss worm domain, an important example of a smoothly bounded pseudoconvex domain without a Stein neighborhood basis, provides key counterexamples in the theory of Several Complex Variables. In this paper, we examine its automorphism group and observe that its boundary is locally spherical everywhere except at the exceptional locus and the caps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10614v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fani Xerakia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizations of infinite circle patterns and convex polyhedra in hyperbolic 3-space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09368v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since Thurston pioneered the connection between circle packing (abbr. CP) and three-dimensional geometric topology, the characterization of CPs and hyperbolic polyhedra has become increasingly profound. Some milestones have been achieved, for example, Rodin-Sullivan \cite{Rodin-Sullivan} and Schramm \cite{schramm91} proved the rigidity of infinite CPs with the intersection angle $\Theta=0$. Rivin-Hodgson \cite{RH93} fully characterized the existence and rigidity of compact convex polyhedra in $\mathbb{H}^3$. He \cite{He} proved the rigidity and uniformization theorem for infinite CPs with $0\leq\Theta\leq \pi/2$. \cite{He} also envisioned that "in a future paper, the techniques of this paper will be extended to the case when $0\leq\Theta&lt;\pi$. In particular, we will show a rigidity property for a class of infinite convex polyhedra in the 3-dimentional hyperbolic space".
  The article aims to accomplish the work claimed in \cite{He} by proving the rigidity and uniformization theorem for infinite CPs with $0\leq\Theta&lt;\pi$, as well as infinite trivalent hyperbolic polyhedra. We will pay special attention to CPs whose contact graphs are disk triangulation graphs. Such CPs are called regular because they exclude some singular configurations and correspond well to hyperbolic polyhedra. We will establish the existence and the rigidity of infinite regular CPs. Moreover, we will prove a uniformization theorem for regular CPs, which solves the classification problem for regular CPs. Thereby, the existence and rigidity of infinite convex trivalent polyhedra are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09368v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huabin Ge, Longsong Jia, Hao Yu, Puchun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-hyperbolicity of holomorphic symplectic varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.11411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.11411v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove non-hyperbolicity of primitive symplectic varieties with $b_2 \geq 5$ that satisfy the rational SYZ conjecture. If in addition $b_2 \geq 7$, we establish that the Kobayashi pseudometric vanishes identically. This in particular applies to all currently known examples of irreducible symplectic manifolds and thereby completes the results by Kamenova--Lu--Verbitsky. The key new contribution is that a projective primitive symplectic variety with a Lagrangian fibration has vanishing Kobayashi pseudometric. The proof uses ergodicity, birational contractions, and cycle spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.11411v5</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>\'Epijournal de G\'eom\'etrie Alg\'ebrique, Volume 9 (2025), Article no. 22</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ljudmila Kamenova, Christian Lehn</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
