<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV</link>
    <description>math.CV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 01:30:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Counting Zeros of Complex-Valued Harmonic Functions via Rouch\'e's Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06721v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rouch\'e's Theorem is among the most useful results in complex analysis for counting zeros of analytic functions. Rouch\'e's Theorem also admits a harmonic analogue for counting zeros of complex harmonic functions. This analogue has previously been applied to closed curves of simple forms, such as circles, to count zeros (e.g., \cite{Brilleslyper}). We apply the harmonic analogue of Rouch\'e's Theorem directly on non-circular critical curves to determine the total number of zeros of a family of complex harmonic functions given by $f(z) = z^n + az^k + b\overline{z}^k - 1 $, where $n&gt;k\geq1$ and $a,b &gt; 0$. Under explicit inequalities relating $a$ and $b$, we determine that the total number of zeros is either $n$ or $n+2k$ (counted with multiplicity). We also prove the location of the zeros of $f$ is confined to the union of two explicit annuli in the plane: an inner annulus containing $k$ zeros and an outer annulus containing the remainder. This illustrates how non-circular critical curves can serve as contours in harmonic Rouch\'e arguments for counting and localization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06721v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Japheth Carlson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zeros of Harmonic Functions whose Caustic is a Non-Singular Image of an Epicycloid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent researchers have investigated how the zeros of certain families of complex harmonic functions change with a single parameter. Many leverage the well-behaved images of the critical curve and the harmonic analogue of the Argument Principle to prove zero-counting theorems. In this paper, we investigate the zeros of a family of harmonic functions for which the image of its critical curve is a non-singular linear image of an epicycloid. By analyzing this curve and using the harmonic analogue of the Argument Principle, we obtain a detailed zero-counting theorem for our family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06724v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eli Sampson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On some new embeddings in minimal bounded homogeneous domains in $C^n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short note we consider very general bounded minimal homogeneous domains. Under certain natural additional conditions new sharp results on Bergman type analytic spaces in minimal bounded homogeneous domains are obtained. Domains we consider here are direct generalizations of the well-studied so-called bounded symmetric domains in $C^n.$ In the unit disk and in the unit ball all our results were obtained by first author. Some results were obtained previously in tubular and bounded pseudoconvex domains. Our proofs are heavily based on properties of so called r-lattices for these general domains provided in recent papers of Yamaji. Our proofs are also based on arguments provided earlier in less general domains. We partially extend an embedding result from Yamaji's paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07091v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. F. Shamoyan, N. M. Makhina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Analysis of the Generalized Gaussian Integrals and Gaussian Like Integrals of Type I and II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07939v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Gaussian integral, denoted as \( \int_{-\infty}^{\infty} e^{-x^2} dx \), plays a significant role in mathematical literature. In this paper, we explore a family of integrals related to Gaussian functions. Specifically, we introduce generalized Gaussian integrals, represented as \( \int_{0}^{\infty} e^{-x^n} dx \), and two distinct types of Gaussian-like integrals:
  1. Type I: \( \int_{0}^{\infty} e^{-f(x)^2} dx \), and 2. Type II: \( \int_{0}^{\infty} e^{-x^2} f(x) dx \),
  where f(x) is a continuous function. The study of integrals related to Gaussian-like functions has been explored in the work of Huang and Dominy \cite{Dnd}. Our approach to evaluating these integrals relies on specialized functions, including error functions, complementary error functions, imaginary error functions, and Basel functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07939v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3126/jnms.v7i2.73105</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Nepal Mathematical Society , Vol. 7, Issue 2 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Prakash Pant, Hem Lal Dhungana, Sudip Rokaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic Deformations of Compact K\"ahler Hyperbolic Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07096v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to study the deformations of compact K\"ahler hyperbolic manifolds. We propose slightly modified versions of K\"ahler hyperbolicity as a tool to provide a first step towards investigating the deformation openness of Gromov's classical notion of K\"ahler hyperbolicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07096v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdelouahab Khelifati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some equivalent definitions for weighted Korenblum and Bloch-type spaces of the upper half-plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07294v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove some equivalent characterizations of weighted Korenblum spaces and Bloch spaces in terms of symbols of bounded Hankel operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07294v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benoit F. Sehba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Complete Derivation of Complex Circle Manifold (CCM) Riemannian manifold Optimization Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07396v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: After reviewing manifold optimization techniques in applications like MIMO communication systems, phased array beamforming, radar, and control theory, we observed that the Complex Circle Manifold (CCM) is widely employed, yet its foundational relations and equations lack a rigorous, self-contained derivation in the literature. This paper provides a systematic and rigorous proof of CCM's key properties, including its tangent space and Riemannian gradient operations, with explicit connections to real-world optimization problems. Our work aims to serve as a unified reference for researchers and practitioners applying CCM Manifold Optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07396v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amirreza Tabrizi, Mohammad Hadi Mirmohammadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalences of 5-dimensional CR manifolds III: Six models and elementary normalizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1311.7522</link>
      <description>arXiv:1311.7522v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The six nondegeneracy conditions of geometric nature that are satisfied by the only six possibly existing nondegenerate general classes I, II, III-1, III-2, IV-1, IV-2 of 5-dimensional CR manifolds are shown to be readable instantaneously from their elementarily normalized respective defining graphed equations, without advanced Moser theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1311.7522v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joel Merker (LM-Orsay)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Bohr-type inequalities with two parameters for bounded analytic functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02824v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, some Bohr inequalities for analytical functions on the unit disk are generalized to the forms with two parameters. One of our results is sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02824v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianying Zhou, Qihan Wang, Boyong Long</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On embedding theorems in analytic and harmonic function spaces of several variables in some domains in $C^n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16980v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this survey we collect some recent advances concerning embedding theorems in analytic and harmonic function spaces of several variables in various domains in $C^n$. The paper is based mainly only on recent results in this research area of the first author, but some recent new interesting nice, results of other authors will also be added in this survey in addition. Some rather short, but valuable discussions of related to this area of research problems in analytic and harmonic function spaces of one and several variables will also be provided and in addition some open questions in this reseach area will also be discussed shortly and posed by us. The paper contains also various rather short but valuable interesting comments concerning this research area of analytic and harmonic function spaces of one and several variables. Some sharp embedding results presented in this survey paper extend sharp embeddings in analytic function spaces obtained in higher dimension previously by J. Ortega, J. Fabrega, W. Cima, D. Luecking, M. Abate and many others in recent decades in the unit ball and bounded strongly pseudoconvex domains with the smooth boundary for onefunctional case to similar type analytic multyfunctional Bergman type function spaces. Same type multifunctional sharp extensions of some recent embedding results of one functional analytic function spaces of B. Sehba and D. Bekolle will be provided by us in this survey for unbounded domains namely for tubular domains over symmetric cones. In this paper we collect many new sharp embeddings obtained recently by first author though some one dimensional new sharp embeddings will be also mentioned shortly at the end of paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16980v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. F. Shamoyan, M. G. Bashmakova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coefficient estimates for the class of q-starlike functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03223v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By employing the $q$-difference operator, various classes of $q$-extensions of starlike functions have emerged from many different viewpoints and perspectives. Ruscheweyh's work unified these $q$-extensions with convolution operations. Inspired by prior research, this paper delves into the class of $q$-starlike functions defined via convolution. First, we provide comprehensive analysis of its Taylor coefficients by using the Carath\'eodory-Toeplitz Theorem and its corollaries. Precise upper bounds for the initial few coefficients are obtained for real $q\in(0,1)$. Furthermore, we analyze both Hankel and Toeplitz determinants by using the foundational results. Second, we establish the upper bounds of its coefficients with the application of Parseval's theorem for $q$-starlike functions when $q$ is a complex number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03223v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Li, Ao-Li Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli of K3 families over $\mathbb{P}^1$ and complex-hyperk\"ahler metrics induced by deformed twistor cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13420v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We answer a question posed independently by Fels-Huckleberry-Wolf and Looijenga concerning the geometric meaning of small deformations of twistor cycles in the K3 period domain. These are shown to induce complex-hyperk\"ahler metrics on members of the families via Penrose's Non-linear Graviton construction. On the way to proving this result, we construct a Hausdorff fine moduli space for families of marked K3 surfaces over smooth rational curves in the K3 period domain. Over an open subset containing all twistor cycles we construct a family of such families, which is a universal small deformation for every twistor family. Whenever possible, we extend the results to higher-dimensional irreducible holomorphic-symplectic manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13420v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Greb, Martin Schwald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Database of Continued Fractions of Polynomial Type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06086v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We describe a database of 1779 continued fractions with polynomial coefficients, of which more than 1500 are new, both for interesting constants and for transcendental functions, and provide the database inside the \TeX\ source of the paper. Look in particular at the section ``Table of Contents''.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06086v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henri Cohen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant subspaces of Brownian shifts on vector-valued Hardy spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21818v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We characterize invariant subspaces of Brownian shifts on vector-valued Hardy spaces. We also solve the unitary equivalence problem for the invariant subspaces of these shifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21818v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilanjan Das, Soma Das, Jaydeb Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
