<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV</link>
    <description>math.CV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the Parameter Spaces of Harmonic Trinomial Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the parameter space of harmonic trinomial equations of the form $z^{n+m}+b\overline{z}^m+c$, where $n,m\in\mathbb{Z}^+$ are coprime and $b,c\in\mathbb{C}$. Using versions of the Bohl and Egerv\'ary theorems for harmonic trinomials, we describe the geometric curves in the parameter space that arise when considering a simple root or a multiple root, or when two distinct roots have the same modulus. In particular, we study the geometric properties of these curves, called trochoids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11296v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waldemar Barrera, Lucia Campa, Juan Pablo Navarrete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schwarz-Pick Lemma for Invariant Harmonic Functions on the Complex Unit Ball</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper establishes a sharp Schwarz-Pick type inequality for real-valued invariant harmonic functions defined on the complex unit ball $\mathbb B^n$. The proof of this main result simultaneously provides a solution to a natural extension of the Khavinson conjecture for invariant harmonic functions, demonstrating that the sharp constants for the gradient and the radial derivative coincide. As further consequences of the main theorem, we derive two corollaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11599v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kapil Jaglan, Aeryeong Seo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering Hardy spaces from optimal domains of integration operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the optimal domains for bounded Volterra integration operators $T_g$ between distinct Hardy spaces $H^p$ and $H^q$ of the unit ball. It is shown that the intersection of the optimal domains is equal to $H^p$ if $p&gt; q$, whereas if $p&lt;q$, we show that this intersection is genuinely larger. In the unit disk, this problem was recently solved for $p=q$ by Bellavita, Daskalogiannis, Nikolaidis and Stylogiannis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11955v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Setareh Eskandari, Antti Per\"al\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the Clunie--Hayman construction in an Erd\H{o}s maximum-term problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12217v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $f(z)=\sum_{n\ge0}a_n z^n$ be a transcendental entire function and write $M(r,f):=\max_{|z|=r}|f(z)|$ and $\mu(r,f):=\max_{n\ge0}|a_n|\,r^n$. A problem of Erd\H{o}s asks for the value of $$ B:=\sup_f \liminf_{r\to\infty}\frac{\mu(r,f)}{M(r,f)}. $$ In 1964, Clunie and Hayman proved that $\frac{4}{7}&lt;B&lt;\frac{2}{\pi}$. In this paper we develop a generalization of their construction via a scaling identity and obtain the explicit lower bound $$ B&gt;0.58507, $$ improving the classical constant $\frac{4}{7}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12217v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixin He, Quanyu Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moment Problems and Spectral Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11260v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nevanlinna-Pick interpolation and moment problems use the analytic structures provided by causality in order to provide rigorous bounds on smeared spectral functions. This proceedings discusses Nevanlinna-Pick interpolation and moment problems and reviews some useful results, including a simple proof that the space of causal data in Nevanlinna--Pick interpolation is convex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11260v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Abbott, William Jay, Patrick Oare</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequently hypercyclic meromorphic curves with slow growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08048v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct entire curves in projective spaces that exhibit frequent hypercyclicity under translations along countably many prescribed directions while maintaining optimal slow growth rates. Furthermore, we establish a fundamental dichotomy by proving the impossibility of such curves simultaneously preserving frequent hypercyclicity for uncountably many directions under equivalent growth constraints. This result reveals a striking contrast with classical hypercyclicity phenomena, where entire functions can achieve hypercyclicity over some uncountable direction set without growth rate compromise. Our methodology is rooted in Nevanlinna theory and guided by the Oka principle, offering new insights into the relationship between dynamical properties and growth rates of entire curves in projective spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08048v5</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhangchi Chen, Bin Guo, Song-Yan Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The asymptoticity of extremal length in Teichm\"uller space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06314v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic behavior of extremal length along Teichm\"uller rays. Specifically, we determine the limit of extremal length along a Teichm\"uller ray and obtain an explicit expression for this limit, which complements a related formula established by Cormac Walsh. Building on this result and Kerckhoff's formula, we establish a formula for the limiting Teichm\"uller distance between two points moving along arbitrary pairs of Teichm\"uller rays. Furthermore, we derive a necessary and sufficient condition for two Teichm\"uller rays to be asymptotic. Finally, by shifting the initial points of the Teichm\"uller rays along their associated Teichm\"uller geodesics, we show that the minimum of the limiting Teichm\"uller distance coincides with the detour metric between the endpoints of the rays on the horofunction boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06314v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyang Lyu, Yi Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some inequalities for the weighted log canonical thresholds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22373v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\varphi$ be a plurisubharmonic function defined in a neighborhood of the origin in $\mathbb C^n$. For each real number $t&gt;-n$, we associate to $\varphi$ the weighted log canonical threshold \[ c_t(\varphi):=\sup\Bigl\{c\geq 0:\|z\|^{2t}e^{-2c\varphi}\in L^1_{\mathrm{loc}} \text{ near }0\Bigr\}. \] In this paper, we prove a sharp slope inequality showing that all difference quotients of the function $t\mapsto c_t(\varphi)$ are uniformly controlled by the Lelong number $\nu_\varphi(0)$. Moreover, we derive explicit lower bounds for the growth of $c_t(\varphi)$ in terms of the complex Monge-Amp\`ere mass of $\varphi$ at the origin. Our arguments combine weighted integrability estimates, restrictions to complex lines, and techniques from pluripotential theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22373v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Xuan Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the numerically and cohomologically trivial automorphisms of elliptic surfaces II: $\chi(S)&gt;0$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17033v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this second part we study first the group $Aut_{\mathbb Q}(S)$ of numerically trivial automorphisms of an algebraic properly elliptic surface $S$, that is, of a minimal algebraic surface with Kodaira dimension $\kappa(S)=1$, in the case $\chi(S) \geq 1$. Our first surprising result is that, against what has been believed for over 40 years, there exist nontrivial such groups for $p_g(S) &gt;0$. Indeed, we show even that $Aut_{\mathbb Q}(S)$ is always a 2-generated finite abelian group, but there is no absolute upper bound for its cardinality. At any rate, we give explicit and essentially optimal upper bounds for $|Aut_{\mathbb Q}(S)|$ in terms of the numerical invariants of $S$, as $\chi(S)$, or the irregularity $q(S)$, or the bigenus $P_2(S)$. Moreover, we reach an almost complete description of the possible groups $Aut_{\mathbb Q}(S)$ and we give effective criteria for such surfaces to have trivial $Aut_{\mathbb Q}(S)$. Our second surprising results concern the quite elusive group $Aut_{\mathbb Z}(S)$ of cohomologically trivial automorphisms; we are able to give the explicit upper bounds for $|Aut_{\mathbb Z}(S)|$ in special cases: 9 when $p_g(S) =0$, and we achieve the sharp upper bound 3 when $S$ (i.e., the pluricanonical elliptic fibration) is isotrivial. Also in the non isotrivial case we produce subtle examples where $Aut_{\mathbb Z}(S)$ is a group of order 2 or 3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17033v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Catanese (Bayreuth University,KIAS Seoul), Wenfei Liu (Xiamen University), Matthias Sch\"utt (Hannover University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On strong Euler-homogeneity and Saito-holonomicity for complex hypersurfaces. Applications to a conjecture on free divisors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21829v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We first develop some criteria for a general divisor to be strongly Euler-homogeneous in terms of the Fitting ideals of certain modules. We also study new variants of Saito-holonomicity, generalizing Koszul-free type properties and characterizing them in terms of the same Fitting ideals.
  Thanks to these advances, we are able to make progress in the understanding of a conjecture from 2002: a free divisor satisfying the Logarithmic Comparison Theorem (LCT) must be strongly Euler-homogeneous. Previously, it was known to be true only for ambient dimension $n \leq 3$ or assuming Koszul-freeness. We prove it in the following new cases: assuming strong Euler-homogeneity outside a discrete set of points; assuming the divisor is weakly Koszul-free; for $n=4$; for linear free divisors in $n=5$.
  Finally, we refute a conjecture stating that all linear free divisors satisfy LCT, are strongly Euler-homogeneous and have $b$-functions with symmetric roots about $-1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21829v5</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1112/jlms.70451</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. London Math. Soc., 113: e70451 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abraham del Valle Rodr\'iguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
