<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 04:00:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A transformational approach to collective behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a revolutionary approach to the characterization, forecast, and control of collective systems. Collective systems are an ensemble of conservatively interacting entities. The evolution of the entities are determined by symmetries of the interaction. Collective systems take many different forms. A plasma is a collective of charged particles, a fluid is a collective of molecules, a elementary field is a collective of elementary particles, and a cosmos is a collective of celestial bodies. Our new theory builds on the canonical transformation approach to dynamics. This approach recognizes that the symmetry leads to the conservation of a real function, that is the infinitesimal generator of a Lie group. The finite generator of the canonical transformation is derived from the infinitesimal generator by the solution of the Hamilton-Jacobi equation. This generating function is also known as the action, the entropy, and the logarithmic likelihood. The new theory generalizes this generating function to the generating functional of the collective field. Finally, this paper derives the formula for the Mayer Cluster Expansion, or the S-matrix expansion of the generating functional. We call it the Heisenberg Scattering Transformation (HST). Practically, this is a localized Fourier Transformation, whose principal components give the singularity spectrums, that is the solution to the Renormalization Group Equations. Limitations on the measurement of the system (that is the Born Rule and the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle) lead to quantization of the stochastic probabilities of the collective field. How different collective systems couple together to form systems-of-systems is formalized. The details of a practical implementation of the HST will be presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08558v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael E. Glinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling of warm dense hydrogen via explicit real time electron dynamics: Electron transport properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extract electron transport properties from atomistic simulations of a two-component plasma, by mapping the long-wavelength behaviour to a two-fluid model. The mapping procedure is performed via Markov Chain Monte Carlo sampling over multiple spectra simultaneously. The free-electron dynamic structure factor and its properties have been investigated in the hydrodynamic formulation to justify its application to the long-wavelength behaviour of warm dense matter. We have applied this method to warm dense hydrogen modelled with wave packet molecular dynamics, and showed that the inferred electron transport properties are in agreement with a variety of reference calculations, except for the electron viscosity, where a substantive decrease is observed when compared to classical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08664v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pontus Svensson, Patrick Hollebon, Daniel Plummer, Sam M. Vinko, Gianluca Gregori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the electric field distribution in streamer discharges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using electric field induced second harmonic generation (E-FISH), we performed direction-resolved absolute electric field measurements on single-channel streamer discharges in 70 mbar (7 kPa) air with 0.2 mm and 2 ns resolutions. In order to obtain the absolute (local) electric field, we developed a deconvolution method taking into account the phase variations of E-FISH. The acquired field distribution shows good agreement with the simulation results under the same conditions, in direction, magnitude and in shape. This is the first time that E-FISH is applied to streamers of this size (&gt; 0.5cm radius), crossing a large gap. Achieving these high resolution electric field measurements benefits further understanding of streamer discharges and enables future use of E-FISH on cylindrically symmetric (transient) electric field distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08765v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihao Guo (Eindhoven University of Technology), Anne Limburg (Eindhoven University of Technology), Jesse Laarman (Eindhoven University of Technology), Jannis Teunissen (Centrum Wiskunde &amp; Informatica), Sander Nijdam (Eindhoven University of Technology)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of uncertainties in electron-argon collision cross sections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00467v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The predictive capability of a plasma discharge model depends on accurate representations of electron-impact collision cross sections, which determine the key reaction rates and transport properties of the plasma. Although many cross sections have been identified through experiments and quantum mechanical simulations, their uncertainties are not well-investigated. We characterize the uncertainties in electron-argon collision cross sections using a Bayesian framework. Six collision processes -- elastic momentum transfer, ionization, and four excitations -- are characterized with semi-empirical models, whose parametric uncertainties effectively capture the features important to the macroscopic properties of the plasma, namely transport properties and chemical reaction rates. The method is designed to capture the effects of systematic errors that lead to large discrepancies between some data sets. Specifically, for the purposes of Bayesian inference, each of the parametric cross section models is augmented with a Gaussian process representing systematic measurement errors as well as model inadequacies in the parametric form. The results show that the method is able to capture scatter in the data between the electron-beam experiments and ab-initio quantum simulations. The calibrated cross section models are further validated against measurements from swarm-parameter experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00467v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung Whan Chung, Todd A. Oliver, Laxminarayan L. Raja, Robert D. Moser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time evolutions of information entropies in a one-dimensional Vlasov-Poisson system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07429v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A one-dimensional Vlasov-Poisson system is considered to elucidate how the information entropies of the probability distribution functions of the electron position and velocity variables evolve in the Landau damping process. Considering the initial condition given by the Maxwellian velocity distribution with the spatial density perturbation in the form of the cosine function of the position, we derive linear and quasilinear analytical solutions that accurately describe both early and late time behaviors of the distribution function and the electric field. The validity of these solutions is confirmed by comparison with numerical simulations based on contour dynamics. Using the quasilinear analytical solution, the time evolutions of the velocity distribution function and its kurtosis indicating deviation from the Gaussian distribution are evaluated with the accuracy of the squared perturbation amplitude. We also determine the time evolutions of the information entropies of the electron position and velocity variables and their mutual information. We further consider Coulomb collisions which relax the state in the late-time limit in the collision less process to the thermal equilibrium state. In this collisional relaxation process, the mutual information of the position and velocity variables decreases to zero while the total information entropy of the phase-space distribution function increases by the decrease in the mutual information and demonstrates the validity of Boltzmann's H-theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07429v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Maekaku, H. Sugama, T. -H. Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experiment Research on Feasibility of In-Situ Plasma Cleaning in Normal-conducting Copper Cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14386v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To assess the feasibility of in-situ plasma cleaning for copper cavities, a 13.56 MHz inductively coupled plasma platform with a built-in coil was developed at Tsinghua University. Experiments were conducted using this platform to optimize plasma discharge parameters and procedures specific to copper cavities. The results indicate that the "Ar/O + Ar/H method" significantly enhances the work function of the copper surface while reducing field enhancement effects induced by surface burrs. Consequently, this study confirms that in-situ plasma cleaning effectively mitigates field emission within copper cavities, thereby enhancing the stability and acceleration gradient of the accelerator system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14386v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qianxu Xia, Lianmin Zheng, Yingchao Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applicability criteria of proper charge neutrality and special relativistic MHD models extended by two-fluid effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03317v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The applicability of relativistic magnetohydrodynamics (RMHD) and its generalization to two-fluid models (including the Hall and inertial effects) is systematically investigated by using the method of dominant balance in the two-fluid equations. Although proper charge neutrality or quasi-neutrality is the key assumption for all MHD models, this condition is difficult to be met when both relativistic and inertial effects are taken into account. The range of application for each MHD model is illustrated in the space of dimensionless scale parameters. Moreover, the number of field variables of relativistic Hall MHD (RHMHD) is shown to be greater than that of RMHD and Hall MHD. Nevertheless, the RHMHD equations may be solved at a lower computational cost than RMHD, since root-finding algorithm, which is the most time-consuming part of the RMHD code, is no longer required to compute the primitive variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03317v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuntaro Yoshino, Makoto Hirota, Yuji Hattori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the existence of traveling wave solutions for cold plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07823v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The present paper is concerned with the existence of traveling wave solutions of the asymptotic model, derived by the authors in a previous work, to approximate the unidirectional evolution of a collision-free plasma in a magnetic field. First, using bifurcation theory, we can rigorously prove the existence of periodic traveling waves of small amplitude. Furthermore, our analysis also evidences the existence of different type of traveling waves. To this end, we present a second approach based on the analysis of the differential system satisfied by the traveling-wave profiles, the existence of equilibria, and the identification of associated homo-clinic and periodic orbits around them. The study makes use of linearization techniques and numerical computations to show the existence of different types of traveling-wave solutions, with monotone and non-monotone behaviour and different regularity, as well as periodic traveling waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07823v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Alonso-Or\'an, Angel Dur\'an, Rafael Granero-Belinch\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
