<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 04:07:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Emulation Techniques for Scenario and Classical Control Design of Tokamak Plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The optimisation of scenarios and design of real-time-control in tokamaks, especially for machines still in design phase, requires a comprehensive exploration of solutions to the Grad-Shafranov (GS) equation over a high-dimensional space of plasma and coil parameters. Emulators can bypass the numerical issues in the GS equation, if a large enough library of equilibria is available. We train an ensemble of neural networks to emulate the typical shape-control targets (separatrix at midplane, X-points, divertor strike point, flux expansion, poloidal beta) as a function of plasma parameters and active coil currents for the range of plasma configurations relevant to spherical tokamaks with a super-X divertor, with percent-level accuracy. This allows a quick calculation of the classical-control shape matrices, potentially allowing real-time calculation at any point in a shot with sub-ms latency. We devise a hyperparameter sampler to select the optimal network architectures and quantify uncertainties on the model predictions. To generate the relevant training set, we devise a Markov-Chain Monte Carlo algorithm to produce large libraries of forward Grad-Shafranov solutions without the need for user intervention. The algorithm promotes equilibria with desirable properties, while avoiding parameter combinations resulting in problematic profiles or numerical issues in the integration of the GS equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18912v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Agnello, N. C. Amorisco, A. Keats, G. K. Holt, J. Buchanan, S. Pamela, C. Vincent, G. McArdle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compression and acceleration of ions by ultra-short ultra-intense azimuthally-polarized light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An efficient plasma compression scheme by azimuthally-polarized (AP) light is proposed. An AP light possesses a donut-like intensity pattern, enabling it to compress and accelerate ions toward the optical axis across a wide range of parameters. When the light intensity reaches the relativistic regime of $10^{18}$ $\mathrm{W}/\mathrm{cm}^{2}$, and the plasma density is below the critical density, protons can be compressed and accelerated by the toroidal soliton formed by the light. The expansion process of the soliton can be well described by the snow-plow model. Three-dimensional (3D) particle-in-cell (PIC) simulations show that within the soliton regime, despite the ion density surpassing ten times of the critical density, their energy is relatively low for efficient neutron production. When the light intensity increases to $10^{22}$ $\mathrm{W}/\mathrm{cm}^{2}$, and the plasma density is tens of the critical density, deuterium ions can be compressed to thousands of the critical density and meanwhile accelerated to the MeV level by a tightly-focused AP light during the hole-boring (HB) process. This process is far more dramatic compared to the soliton regime, and can produce up to $10^{4}$ neutrons in a few light cycles. Moreover, in the subsequent beam-target stage, neutron yield is assessed to reach over $10^{8}$. Finally, we present a comparison with the results by a radially-polarized (RP) light to examine the influence of light polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19133v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Da-Chao Deng, Hui-Chun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Excitation Energies in Warm Dense Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a dense plasma environment, the energy levels of an ion shift relative to the isolated ion values. This shift is reflected in the optical spectrum of the plasma and can be measured in, for example, emission experiments. In this work, we use a recently developed method of modeling electronic states in warm dense matter to predict these level energies. In this model, excited state energies are calculated directly by enforcing constrained one-electron occupation factors, thus allowing the calculation of specific transition and ionization energies. This model includes plasma effects self-consistently, so the effect of continuum lowering is included in an ab-initio sense. We use the model to calculate the K-edge and K-alpha energies of solid density magnesium, aluminum, and silicon over a range of temperatures, finding close agreement with experimental results. We also calculate the ionization potential depression (IPD) to compare to widely used models, and investigate the effects of temperature on the lowering of the continuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19420v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Q. Thelen, D. A. Rehn, C. J. Fontes, C. E. Starrett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser Interactions with Gas Jets: EMP Emission and Nozzle Damage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a theoretical model of electromagnetic pulse emission and nozzle damage from high-power laser interactions with gas jets. As hot electrons are accelerated beyond the laser channel, they produce a positively-charged plasma that expands into the ambient gas until it reaches the gas jet nozzle. A strong plasma potential leads to electrical breakdown that ionises the gas even faster than the expanding plasma ions. When contact is made between the plasma and the conducting nozzle surface, a discharge current propagates to ground and an electromagnetic pulse is radiated via an antenna emission mechanism. Damage to gas jet nozzles is caused by heating from plasma ions rather than Ohmic heating via a discharge current. Our model agrees with experimental data from experiments on proton acceleration in near-critical plasmas at the Vulcan and VEGA-3 lasers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19519v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Wykeham Bradford, Valeria Ospina-Bohorquez, Michael Ehret, Jose-Luis Henares, Pilar Puyuelo-Valdes, Tomasz Chodukowski, Tadeusz Pisarczyk, Zofia Rusiniak, Carlos Salgado-Lopez, Christos Vlachos, Massimiliano Sciscio, Martina Salvadori, George Hicks, Jean-Raphael Marques, Laurent Gremillet, Joao Jorge Santos, Fabrizio Consoli, Vladimir Tikhonchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turbulence properties and kinetic signatures of electron in Kelvin-Helmholtz waves during a geomagnetic storm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18990v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive study of Magnetospheric Multiscale (MMS) spacecraft encounter with KHI during a geomagnetic storm, focusing on elucidating key turbulence properties and reconnection signatures observed at the edges of KH vortices. The spectral slope for electric field stays approximately constant for frequencies below the ion cyclotron frequency and exhibits a break around the lower hybrid frequency, indicating wave activity. Furthermore, MMS observes a current sheet accompanied by intense electron jets and features consistent with strong guide-field asymmetric reconnection across the magnetopause. Substantial agyrotropy (by a factor of 10) in electron distribution functions is observed in the reconnecting current sheet and at the edges of KH. Our observation presents a multi-scale view into KH turbulence under strongly driven conditions and into the dynamics occurring at electron dissipation scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18990v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harsha Gurram, Jason R. Shuster, Li-Jen Chen, Matthew R. Argall, Richard E. Denton, Rachel C. Rice, Brandon L. Burkholder, Daniel J. Gershman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Needed computations and computational capabilities for stellarators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18804v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Stellarator plasmas are externally controlled to a degree unparalleled by any other fusion concept, magnetic or inertial. This control is largely through the magnetic fields produced by external coils. The development of fusion energy could be expedited by carrying out remarkably straight-forward computations to define strategies for exploiting this external control. In addition to these computations, which have a reliability limited only by competence, certain physics areas that affect the develop of stellarator power plants should have more intense study. The low cost and speed with which computations can be carried out relative to experiments has implications for the development of fusion. Computations should be used to develop a strategy that to the extent possible allows major issues to be circumvented. Required computations for this strategy are the subject of this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18804v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allen H Boozer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subspace Acceleration for a Sequence of Linear Systems and Application to Plasma Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.02156v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an acceleration method for sequences of large-scale linear systems, such as the ones arising from the numerical solution of time-dependent partial differential equations coupled with algebraic constraints. We discuss different approaches to leverage the subspace containing the history of solutions computed at previous time steps in order to generate a good initial guess for the iterative solver. In particular, we propose a novel combination of reduced-order projection with randomized linear algebra techniques, which drastically reduces the number of iterations needed for convergence. We analyze the accuracy of the initial guess produced by the reduced-order projection when the coefficients of the linear system depend analytically on time. Extending extrapolation results by Demanet and Townsend to a vector-valued setting, we show that the accuracy improves rapidly as the size of the history increases, a theoretical result confirmed by our numerical observations. In particular, we apply the developed method to the simulation of plasma turbulence in the boundary of a fusion device, showing that the time needed for solving the linear systems is significantly reduced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.02156v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Margherita Guido, Daniel Kressner, Paolo Ricci</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
