<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 04:01:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pump depletion and the Raman gap in ignition-scale plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05232v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Laser-plasma instabilities under ignition conditions for direct-drive inertial confinement fusion are studied using two-dimensional Particle-in-Cell simulations with a combination of in-plane (PP) and out-of-the-plane (SP) lasers. The results show that stimulated Raman side scattering can induce significant pump depletion and form a gap in the Raman scattered light spectra that have been observed in experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05232v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. H. Cao, M. J. Rosenberg, A. A. Solodov, H. Wen, C. Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wideband Glide-Symmetric Double-Corrugated Gap-Waveguide Traveling-Wave Tube for Millimeter Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the use of glide symmetry (GS) and electromagnetic bandgap (EBG) technology in a glide-symmetric double corrugated gap waveguide (GSDC-GW) slow wave structure (SWS) for traveling wave tube (TWT) applications. Notably, this GS structure provides the advantage of wide-band operation and the EBG eliminates the need for a conductive connection between the top and bottom waveguide plates. The TWT performance is evaluated via particle-in-cell simulations that reveal a 3-dB bandwidth of approximately 12 GHz spanning from 54.5 GHz to 66.3 GHz, accompanied by a maximum gain of 23 dB. Because of GS, the backward wave in the first spatial harmonic is not longitudinally polarized, leading to a low risk of backward wave oscillations in the TWT. This work places the GSDC-EBG structure within the arena of potential SWS topologies for TWTs operating under similar conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05238v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Saavedra-Melo, Nelson Castro, Robert Marosi, Eva Rajo-Iglesias, Filippo Capolino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Novel Stellarator Single-Stage Optimization Algorithms to Design the Columbia Stellarator Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Columbia Stellarator eXperiment (CSX), currently being designed at Columbia University, aims to test theoretical predictions related to QA plasma behavior, and to pioneer the construction of an optimized stellarator using three-dimensional, non-insulated high-temperature superconducting (NI-HTS) coils. The magnetic configuration is generated by a combination of two circular planar poloidal field (PF) coils and two 3D-shaped interlinked (IL) coils, with the possibility to add windowpane coils to enhance shaping and experimental flexibility. The PF coils and vacuum vessel are repurposed from the former Columbia Non-Neutral Torus (CNT) experiment, while the IL coils will be custom-wound in-house using NI-HTS tapes. To obtain a plasma shape that meets the physics objectives with a limited number of coils, novel single-stage optimization techniques are employed, optimizing both the plasma and coils concurrently, in particular targeting a tight aspect ratio QA plasma and minimized strain on the HTS tape. Despite the increased complexity due to the expanded degrees of freedom, these methods successfully identify optimized plasma geometries that can be realized by coils meeting engineering specifications. This paper discusses the derivation of the constraints and objectives specific to CSX, and describe how two recently developed single-stage optimization methodologies are applied to the design of CSX. A set of selected configurations for CSX is then described in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05261v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Baillod, E. J. Paul, G. Rawlinson, M. Haque, S. W. Freiberger, S. Thapa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faraday shield dissipation in the drivers of SPIDER based on electromagnetic 3D calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: SPIDER (Source for the Production of Ions of Deuterium Extracted from Rf plasma) is a full-scale prototype of the ITER NBI source. It is based on the concept of inductive coupling between radio-frequency current drive and plasma. Present three-dimensional (3D) electromagnetic calculations of stationary RF fields in SPIDER permit an evaluation of the power dissipation in its main constituents. Taking experimental plasma parameters as input, we concentrate on the power dissipation in the copper-made Faraday shield lateral wall (FSLW) of the source for discharges with and without a static magnetic filter field. In agreement with our previous results and a first comparison with calorimetry data from the FSLW cooling circuit, the FSLW cylinder alone absorbs around 50\% of the available power for the studied plasma parameters. A hypothesized improvement of transport confinement may increase significantly the efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05821v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. L\'opez-Bruna, S. Denizeau, I. Predebon, A. La Rosa, C. Poggi, P. Agostinetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of fusion reactivities using non-Maxwellian energy distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss conditions for the enhancement of fusion reactivities arising from different choices of energy distribution functions for the reactants. The key element for potential gains in fusion reactivity is identified in the functional dependence of the tunnellng coefficient upon the energy, ensuring the existence of a finite range of temperatures for which reactivity of fusion processes is boosted with respect to the Maxwellian case. This is shown, using a convenient parameterization of the tunneling coefficient dependence upon the energy, analytically in the simplified case of a bimodal Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution, and numerically for kappa-distributions. We then consider tunneling potentials progressively better approximating fusion processes, and evaluate in each case the average reactivity in the case of kappa-distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05848v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.109.025207</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review E 109, 025207 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ben I. Squarer, Carlo Presilla, Roberto Onofrio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Characteristics of the Proton Isotropy Boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04488v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using particle data from the ELFIN satellites, we present a statistical study of 284 proton isotropy boundary events on the nightside magnetosphere, characterizing their occurrence and distribution in local time, latitude (L-shell), energy, and precipitating energy flux, as a function of geomagnetic activity. For a given charged particle species and energy, its isotropy boundary (IB) is the magnetic latitude poleward of which persistently isotropic pitch-angle distributions ($J_{prec}/J_{perp}\sim 1$) are first observed to occur. This isotropization is interpreted as resulting from magnetic field-line curvature (FLC) scattering in the equatorial magnetosphere. We find that proton IBs are observed under all observed activity levels, spanning 16 to 05 MLT with $\sim$100% occurrence between 19 and 03 MLT, trending toward 60% at dawn/dusk. These results are also compared with electron IB properties observed using ELFIN, where we find similar trends across local time and activity, with the onset in $\geq$50 keV proton IB occurring on average 2 L-shells lower, and providing between 3 and 10 times as much precipitating power. Proton IBs typically span $64^\circ$-$66^\circ$ in magnetic latitude (5-6 in L-shell), corresponding to the outer edge of the ring current, tending toward lower IGRF latitudes as geomagnetic activity increases. The IBs were found to commonly occur 0.3-2.1 Re beyond the plasmapause. Proton IBs typically span $&lt;$50 keV to $\sim$1 MeV in energy, maximizing near 22 MLT, and decreasing to a typical upper limit of 300-400 keV toward dawn and dusk, with peak observed isotropic energy increasing by $\sim$500 keV during active intervals. These results suggest that FLC in the vicinity of IBs can provide a substantial depletion mechanism for energetic protons, with the total nightside precipitating power from FLC-scattering found to be on the order of 100 MW, at times $\geq$10 GW.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04488v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin Wilkins, Vassilis Angelopoulos, Anton Artemyev, Andrei Runov, Xiao-Jia Zhang, Jiang Liu, Ethan Tsai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lectures on Statistical Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Presented here is a transcription of the lecture notes from Professor Allan N. Kaufman's graduate statistical mechanics course at Berkeley from the 1972-1973 academic year. Part 1 addresses equilibrium statistical mechanics with topics: fundamentals, classical fluids and other systems, chemical equilibrium, and long-range interactions. Part 2 addresses non-equilibrium statistical mechanics with topics: fundamentals, Brownian motion, Liouville and Klimontovich equations, Landau equation, Markov processes and Fokker-Planck equation, linear response and transport theory, and an introduction to non-equilibrium quantum statistical mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04899v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allan N. Kaufman, Bruce I. Cohen, Alain J. Brizard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure and dynamics of the magnetopause and its boundary layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The magnetopause is the key region in space for the transfer of solar wind mass, momentum, and energy into the magnetosphere. During the last decade, our understanding of the structure and dynamics of Earth's magnetopause and its boundary layers has advanced considerably; thanks largely to the advent of multi-spacecraft missions such as Cluster and THEMIS. Moreover, various types of physics-based techniques have been developed for visualizing two- or three-dimensional plasma and field structures from data taken by one or more spacecraft, providing a new approach to the analysis of the spatiotemporal properties of magnetopause processes, such as magnetic reconnection and the Kelvin-Helmholtz instability (KHI). Information on the size, shape, orientation, and evolution of magnetic flux ropes or flow vortices generated by those processes can be extracted from in situ measurements. Observations show that magnetopause reconnection can be globally continuous for both southward and northward interplanetary magnetic field (IMF) conditions, but even under such circumstances, more than one X-line may exist within a certain (low-latitude or high-latitude) portion on the magnetopause and some X-lines may retreat anti-sunward. The potential global effects of such behavior are discussed. An overview is also given of the identification, excitation, evolution, and possible consequences of the magnetopause KHI: there is evidence for nonlinear KHI growth and associated vortex-induced reconnection under northward IMF. Observation-based estimates indicate that reconnection tailward of both polar cusps can be the dominant mechanism for solar wind plasma entry into the dayside magnetosphere under northward IMF. However, the mechanism by which the transferred plasma is transported into the central portion of the magnetotail, and the role of magnetopause processes in this transport remain unclear.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05262v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5047/meep.2012.00102.0071</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monogr. Environ. Earth Planets 1(2) (2012) 71-119</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Hasegawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid, strongly magnetized accretion in the zero-net-vertical-flux shearing box</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05467v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that there exist two qualitatively different turbulent states of the zero-net-vertical-flux shearing box. The first, which has been studied in detail previously, is characterized by a weakly magnetized ($\beta\sim50$) midplane with slow periodic reversals of the mean azimuthal field (dynamo cycles). The second (the "low-$\beta$ state"), which is the main subject of this paper, is characterized by a strongly magnetized $\beta\sim1$ midplane dominated by a coherent azimuthal field with much stronger turbulence and much larger accretion stress $\alpha \sim 1$. The low-$\beta$ state is realized in simulations that begin with sufficiently strong azimuthal magnetic fields. The mean azimuthal field in the low-$\beta$ state is quasi steady (no cycles) and is sustained by a dynamo mechanism that compensates for the continued loss of magnetic flux through the vertical boundaries; we attribute the dynamo to the combination of differential rotation and the Parker instability, although many of its details remain unclear. Vertical force balance in the low-$\beta$ state is dominated by the mean magnetic pressure except at the midplane, where thermal pressure support is always important (this is true even when simulations are initialized at $\beta\ll1$, provided the thermal scale-height of the disk is well-resolved). The efficient angular momentum transport in the low-$\beta$ state may resolve long-standing tension between predictions of magnetorotational turbulence (at high $\beta$) and observations; likewise, the bifurcation in accretion states we find may be important for understanding the state transitions observed in dwarf novae, X-ray binaries, and changing-look AGN. We discuss directions for future work including the implications of our results for global accretion disk simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05467v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Squire, Eliot Quataert, Philip F. Hopkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the influence of divertor baffles on nitrogen-seeded detachment in TCV with SOLPS-ITER simulations and TCV experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07292v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Plasma edge simulation with the SOLPS-ITER code are performed to study the influence of divertor baffles on nitrogen-seeded detachment in L-mode TCV discharges. Simulations of nitrogen seeding with baffles is found to yield lower target temperatures and heat fluxes than in baffle-only and seeding-only simulations. The neutral compression increases with both baffles and seeding, but due to different mechanism according to the proposed neutral transport model. The nitrogen retention, defined as the divertor-to-main chamber nitrogen density ratio, increases with the seeding rate if baffled. Baffled nitrogen retentions are lower than the unbaffled retentions at low seeding levels and are higher at high seeding levels. The baffled carbon retentions are always above the unbaffled retentions due to increased target particle flux and sputtering by baffling. Baffles also relocate more impurity radiations from the main chamber region into the divertor. The predicted trends of target parameters, radiation and neutral distributions are well supported by TCV experiments, though discrepancies in absolute values remain. The simulations generally yield a colder and denser divertor, consistent with previous SOLPS-ITER simulations of Ohmically heated L-modes in TCV. The comparison of simulation and experiment, together with the proposed neutral transport model, suggest the necessity of sufficient baffling in future TCV divertor upgrade, and a combination of baffling and seeding to facilitate the access to detachment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07292v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation times of velocity and kinetic helicity fluctuations in nonhelical hydrodynamic turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15860v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonhelical turbulence within a linear shear flow has demonstrated efficient amplification of large-scale magnetic fields in numerical simulations, but its precise mechanism remains elusive. The incoherent $\alpha$ mechanism proposes that a zero-mean fluctuating transport coefficient $\alpha$ (linked to kinetic helicity) in the shear flow is a candidate driver. Previous renovating-flow models have proposed that the correlation time of helicity fluctuations must be sufficiently extended to overcome turbulent magnetic diffusivity, yet only empirical validation of this concept has been obtained. In this study, we conduct direct numerical simulations of weakly compressible nonhelical hydrodynamic turbulence. We scrutinize the correlation times of velocity and kinetic helicity fluctuations in distinct flow configurations, including rotation, shearing, and Keplerian flows, as well as the shearing burgulence counterpart. Our findings indicate that rotation contributes to a prolonged correlation time of helicity compared to velocity, particularly notable in auto-correlations of both volume-averaged quantities and individual Fourier modes due to the formation of large-scale vortices. In contrast, moderate shear strength does not exhibit significant scale separation, with shear flows elongating vortices in the shear direction. Shearing burgulence, characterized by shorter helicity correlation times, appears less conducive to hosting the incoherent $\alpha$ effect. Notably, at modest shear rates, only Keplerian flows exhibit sufficiently coherent helicity fluctuations, in contrast to shearing flows. However, the relative strength of helicity fluctuations compared to turbulent diffusivity is significantly lower, raising doubts about the viability of the incoherent $\alpha$ effect as a potential dynamo driver in the subsonic flows examined in this study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15860v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongzhe Zhou, Naveen Jingade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation of weakly collisional plasma: continuous spectra, discrete eigenmodes, and the decay of echoes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07992v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The relaxation of a weakly collisional plasma is described by the Boltzmann-Poisson equations with the Lenard-Bernstein collision operator. We perform a perturbative analysis of these equations, and obtain exact analytic solutions, enabling definitive resolutions to long-standing controversies regarding the impact of weak collisions on continuous spectra and Landau eigenmodes. Unlike some previous studies, we retain both damping and diffusion terms in the collision operator. We find that the linear response is a temporal convolution of a continuum that depends on the continuous velocities of particles, and discrete modes that encapsulate coherent oscillations. The discrete modes are exponentially damped over time due to collective effects (Landau damping) as well as collisional dissipation. The continuum is also damped by collisions but somewhat differently. Up to a collision time, which is the inverse of the collision frequency $\nu_{\mathrm{c}}$, the continuum decay is driven by velocity diffusion and occurs super-exponentially over a timescale $\sim \nu^{-1/3}_{\mathrm{c}}$. After a collision time, however, the continuum decay is driven by the collisional damping of particle velocities and diffusion of their positions, and occurs exponentially over a timescale $\sim \nu_{\mathrm{c}}$. This hitherto unknown, slow exponential decay causes perturbations to damp the most on scales comparable to the mean free path, but very slowly on larger scales, which establishes the local thermal equilibrium, the essence of the fluid limit. The long-term decay of the response is driven by the discrete modes on scales smaller than the mean free path, but, on larger scales, is governed by the slowly decaying continuum and the least damped discrete mode. Our analysis firmly establishes a long-sought connection between the collisionless and fluid limits of weakly collisional plasmas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07992v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uddipan Banik, Amitava Bhattacharjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Alfven-Wave Dynamics and Pre-Merger Emission from Crustal Oscillations in Neutron Star Mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17026v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars have solid crusts threaded by strong magnetic fields. Perturbations in the crust can excite non-radial oscillations, which can in turn launch Alfven waves into the magnetosphere. In the case of a compact binary close to merger involving at least one neutron star, this can happen through tidal interactions causing resonant excitations that shatter the neutron star crust. We present the first numerical study that elucidates the dynamics of Alfven waves launched in a compact binary magnetosphere. We seed a magnetic field perturbation on the neutron star crust, which we then evolve in fully general-relativistic force-free electrodynamics using a GPU-based implementation. We show that Alfven waves steepen nonlinearly before reaching the orbital light cylinder, form flares, and dissipate energy in a transient current sheet. Our results predict radio and X-ray precursor emission from this process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17026v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elias R. Most, Yoonsoo Kim, Katerina Chatziioannou, Isaac Legred</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
