<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 01:38:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Intensity and Dimensionality-Dependent Dynamics of Laser-Proton Acceleration in 1D, 2D, and 3D Particle-in-Cell Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Due to the high computational cost of 3D particle-in-cell (PIC) simulations, lower-dimensional (2D or 1D) simulations are frequently used in their place. Our work shows that when modeling high-intensity laser ion acceleration, simulation dimensionality interfaces with laser intensity in the dynamics of ion acceleration at every step of the process, from laser absorption through particle acceleration. We expand on previous studies by comparing the behavior of 1D and 2D simulations (of different polarization) with 3D PIC simulations at high resolutions across five orders of magnitude of laser intensity, enabling us to study multiple regimes of laser-proton acceleration. We find that key output metrics such as maximum proton energy depend on a complex interplay of both simulation dimensionality and laser intensity regime. Differences between simulation predictions generally increase for higher laser intensity regimes, making 3D simulations especially important for quantitative predictions of next-generation laser experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10386v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lillian A. Daneshmand, Madeline Aszalos, Scott Feister, Joseph R. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Mass Diffusion on Rayleigh-Taylor Instability Under A Large Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rayleigh-Taylor instabilities (RTI) play an important role in the evolution of inertial confinement fusion (ICF) processes, while analytical prediction of the RTI growth rate often fails to reach an agreement with the experimental and simulation results. Accurate analytical prediction of RTI growth is of great significance to the success of ICF schemes. In this paper, we study the effects of mass diffusion and exponential density distribution on RTI under a large gravity, by solving the Rayleigh equation with a linear approximation to the density distribution of the mixing layer. While both effects tend to dampen the instability growth, mass diffusion dominates the damping of perturbations of larger wavenumber and exponential density distribution dominates those of smaller wavenumber, resulting in a non-monotonicity of the density suppression factor of the instability growth rate over perturbation wavenumbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10510v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Guo, D. Wu, J. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proton Radiography Inversions with Source Extraction and Comparison to Mesh Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Proton radiography is a central diagnostic technique for measuring electromagnetic (EM) fields in high-energy-density, laser-produced plasmas. In this technique, protons traverse the plasma where they accumulate small EM deflections which lead to variations in the proton fluence pattern on a detector. Path-integrated EM fields can then be extracted from the fluence image through an inversion process. In this work, experiments of laser-driven foils were conducted on the OMEGA laser and magnetic field reconstructions were performed using both "fluence-based" techniques and high-fidelity "mesh-based" methods. We implement nonzero boundary conditions into the inversion and show their importance by comparing against mesh measurements. Good agreement between the methods is found only when nonzero boundary conditions are used. We also introduce an approach to determine the unperturbed proton source profile, which is a required input in fluence reconstruction algorithms. In this approach, a fluence inversion is embedded inside of a mesh region, which provides overconstrained magnetic boundary conditions. A source profile is then iteratively optimized to satisfy the boundary information. This method substantially enhances the accuracy in recovering EM fields. Lastly, we propose a scheme to quantify uncertainty in the final inversion that is introduced through errors in the source retrieval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10879v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Griff-McMahon, V. Valenzuela-Villaseca, S. Malko, G. Fiksel, M. J. Rosenberg, D. B. Schaeffer, W. Fox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compression Acceleration of Protons and Heavier Ions at the Heliospheric Current Sheet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10445v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent observations by Parker Solar Probe (PSP) suggest that protons and heavier ions are accelerated to high energies by magnetic reconnection at the heliospheric current sheet (HCS). By solving the energetic particle transport equation in large-scale MHD simulations, we study the compression acceleration of protons and heavier ions in the reconnecting HCS. We find that the acceleration of multi-species ions results in nonthermal power-law distributions with spectral index consistent with the PSP observations. Our study shows that the high-energy cutoff of protons can reach $E_{max} \sim 0.1$ - $1$ MeV depending on the particle diffusion coefficients. We also study how the high-energy cutoff of different ion species scales with the charge-to-mass ratio $E_{max} \propto (Q/M)^\alpha$. When determining the diffusion coefficients from the quasilinear theory with a Kolmogorov magnetic power spectrum, we find that $\alpha \sim 0.4$, which is somewhat smaller than $\alpha \sim 0.7$ observed by PSP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10445v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Murtas, Xiaocan Li, Fan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plasma stratification in AC discharges in noble gases at low currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05926v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A hybrid kinetic-fluid model is used to study plasma stratification in alternating current (AC) discharges in noble gases at low plasma densities. Self-consistent coupled solutions of a nonlocal kinetic equation for electrons, a drift-diffusion equation of ions, and a Poisson equation for the electric field are obtained for a positive column and the entire discharge with near-electrode sheaths. A simplified two-level excitation-ionization model neglects the nonlinear effects due to stepwise ionization, gas heating, and Coulomb interactions among electrons. Standing striations are obtained for the reduced values of electric fields, E/p, corresponding to the inelastic energy balance of electrons in a range of driving frequencies. An analog of Novak law (striation length proportional to the excitation threshold of atoms and inversely proportional to the mean square root of the electric field), is observed in simulations, indicating the nonlocal nature of standing striations in AC discharges at low plasma densities. Stratified plasma operates in a dynamic regime for various driving frequencies. In this regime, ions respond to the time-averaged electric field, whereas electrons react to the instantaneous electric field. The disparity of time scales between ambipolar diffusion, which occurs at the ion time scale, and electron kinetics in the coordinate-energy phase space, which occurs at the free electron diffusion time scale, produces complicated fluxes in the phase space (due to electron heating, energy loss in collisions, and ionization processes) that are responsible for the stratification. Our paper emphasizes the need for the kinetic approach to analyze stratification phenomena in AC discharge of noble gases. It promotes an efficient method for the kinetic treatment of electrons that is an alternative to the commonly used PIC method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05926v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir I. Kolobov, Robert R. Arslanbekov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
