<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 03:31:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying the Growth Phase of Magnetic Reconnection using Pressure-Strain Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14139v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic reconnection often initiates abruptly and then rapidly progresses to a nonlinear quasi-steady state. While satellites frequently detect reconnection events, ascertaining whether the system has achieved steady-state or is still evolving in time remains challenging. Here, we propose that the relatively rapid opening of reconnection separatrices within the electron diffusion region (EDR) serves as an indicator of the growth phase of reconnection. The opening of the separatrices is produced by electron flows diverging away from the neutral line downstream of the X-line and flowing around a dipolarization front. This flow pattern leads to characteristic spatial structures in pressure-strain interaction that could be a useful indicator for the growth phase of a reconnection event. We employ two-dimensional particle-in-cell numerical simulations of anti-parallel magnetic reconnection to validate this prediction. We find that the signature discussed here, alongside traditional reconnection indicators, can serve as a marker of the growth phase. This signature is potentially accessible using multi-spacecraft single-point measurements, such as with NASA's Magnetospheric Multiscale (MMS) satellites in Earth's magnetotail. Applications to other settings where reconnection occurs are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14139v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Hasan Barbhuiya, Paul A. Cassak, Alex Chasapis, Michael A. Shay, Giulia Cozzani, Alessandro Retino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plasma-Metal Junction:A Junction With Negative Turn-On Voltage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unlike junctions in solid-state devices, a plasma-metal junction (pm-junction) is a junction of classical and quantum electrons. The plasma electrons are Maxwellain in nature, while metal electrons obey the Fermi-Dirac distribution. In this experiment, the current-voltage characteristics of solid-state devices that form homo or hetero-junction are compared to the pm-junction. Observation shows that the turn-on voltage for pn-junction is 0.5V and decreases to 0.24V for metal-semiconductor junction. However, the pm-junction's turn-on voltage was lowered to a negative value of -7.0V. The devices with negative turn-on voltage are suitable for high-frequency operations. Further, observations show that the current-voltage characteristics of the pm-junction depend on the metal's work function, and the turn-on voltage remains unchanged. This result validates the applicability of the energy-band model for the pm-junction. We present a perspective metal-oxide-plasma (MOP), a gaseous electronic device, as an alternative to metal-oxide-semiconductor (MOS), based on the new understanding developed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14306v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sneha Latha Kommuguri, Smrutishree Pratihary, Thangjam Rishikanta Singh, Suraj Kumar Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel understanding of the role of plasma-molecular kinetics on divertor power exhaust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: During detachment, a buffer of neutral atoms and molecules builds up between the target and the ionising plasma. Collisions between the plasma and the molecules play an important role in the detachment process. Studies of plasma-molecular kinetics indicate that the gas temperature is increased during detachment for a wide range of conditions on the MAST-U and TCV tokamaks. This is related to an increased $\mathrm{D}_2$ lifetime during detachment, leading to more plasma-molecule collisions that raise the molecular temperature. Such collisions subsequently result in significant power and momentum losses to the divertor plasma during detachment. Using a simplified inference, these losses are estimated using the rotational temperature, neutral pressure and ionisation front position. Significant power losses (about $10\%$ of $P_{SOL}$) and dominant momentum losses (majority of the upstream pressure) from plasma-molecule collisions are inferred experimentally in long-legged, strongly baffled, detached divertors (MAST-U Super-X divertor), consistent with SOLPS-ITER simulations. The vibrational distribution obtained is compared with an Eirene-like collisional-radiative model setup, indicating some qualitative agreements and disagreements, potentially highlighting model gaps.
  These interpretations highlight the importance of plasma-molecular collisions, leading to power and momentum losses during detachment. Our analysis and reduced modelling of these processes provide further insights into detachment control observations, the workings of long-legged divertors and divertor power balance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14403v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Osborne, K. Verhaegh, D. Moulton, H. Reimerdes, P. Ryan, N. Lonigro, S. Mijin, R. Osawa, K. Murray, S. Kobussen, Y. Dimizia, A. Perek, C. Theiler, R. Ducker, D. Mykytchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the critical role of the rear wall thickness of a grooved TNSA target</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cutoff energy and the divergence of the protons generated by the target normal sheath acceleration mechanism are known to be significantly influenced by micrometer and nanometer-size structures on the target front and rear surfaces. Specifically, the cutoff energy is significantly enhanced by creating a central rectangular groove on the target front surface, as shown in a recent study [Physics of Plasmas, 30(6), 063102 (2023)]. Here we report on 2D Particle-In-Cell (PIC) simulations to thoroughly explore the effect of the depth of the central rectangular groove on the energy spectra of the accelerated protons. The proton cutoff energy is found to enhance drastically as the thickness of the rear wall of the groove is reduced from a few micrometers to a few tens of nanometers, however, it drops sharply as the thickness of the rear wall is further reduced towards creating a complete hole through the target.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14412v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imran Khan, Vikrant Saxena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gyrokinetic prediction of core tungsten peaking in a WEST plasma with nitrogen impurities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tungsten peaking is predicted in the core of a WEST plasma with total-f gyrokinetic simulations, including both collisional and turbulent transport. This prediction is validated with a synthetic diagnostic of the bolometry. Although nitrogen impurities are shown to reduce the neoclassical peaking of tungsten on-axis, the overall tungsten peaking increases when nitrogen impurities are present, as they reduce the turbulence screening off-axis. This finding is important for the plasma current ramp-up phase of ITER, where light impurities seeding will be desirable to achieve low temperatures at the plasma-facing components and reduce tungsten sputtering. It provides further argument for applying early ECRH heating to maintain margins on the core power balance. The neoclassical peaking factor is cross-verified between XGC and FACIT. The heat flux at separatrix and the heat load width are modeled by XGC and compared to WEST data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14432v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Dominski, P. Maget, O. Manas, J. Morales, S. Ku, A. Scheinberg, C. S. Chang, R. Hager, M. O'Mullane, the WEST team</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray Spectroscopy of the Dwarf Nova Z Chamaeleontis in Quiescence and Outburst Using the XMM-Newton Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present X-ray spectroscopy of the SU UMa-type dwarf nova (DN) Z Cha using the EPIC and RGS instruments onboard the XMM-Newton Observatory. The quiescent system can be modeled by collisional equilibrium or nonequilibrium plasma models, yielding a kT of 8.2-13.0 keV at a luminosity of (5.0-6.0)$\times$10$^{30}$ erg/s. The spectra yield better reduced $\chi^{2}$ using partial covering absorbers of cold and photoionized nature. The ionized absorber has an equivalent N$_H$=(3.4-5.9)$\times$10$^{22}$ cm$^{-2}$ and a log($\xi$)=3.5-3.7 with (50-60)% covering fraction when VNEI model (XSPEC) is used. The line diagnosis in quiescence shows no resonance lines with only detected forbidden lines of Ne, Mg, Si. The H-like C, O, Ne, and Mg are detected. The strongest line is O VIII with (2.7-4.6)$\times$10$^{-14}$ erg/s/cm$^2$. The quiescent X-ray emitting plasma is not collisional and not in ionization equilibrium which is consistent with hot ADAF-like accretion flows. The line diagnosis in outburst shows He-like O, and Ne with intercombination lines being the strongest along with weaker resonance lines. This indicates the plasma is more collisional and denser, but yet not in a collisional equilibrium, revealing ionization timescales of (0.97-1.4)$\times$10$^{11}$ s cm$^{-3}$. The R-ratios in outburst yield electron densities of (7-90)$\times$10$^{11}$ cm$^{-3}$ and the G-ratios yield electron temperatures of (2-3)$\times$10$^{6}$ K. The outburst luminosity is (1.4-2.5)$\times$10$^{30}$ erg/s. The flow is inhomogeneous in density. All detected lines are narrow with widths limited by the resolution of RGS yielding Keplerian rotational velocities $&lt;$1000 km/s. This is too low for boundary layers, consistent with the nature of ADAF-like hot flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14526v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Solen Balman, Eric M. Schlegel, Patrick Godon, Jeremy J. Drake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effects of resistivity on oscillatory reconnection and consequences for solar flare Quasi Periodic Pulsations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14563v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quasi-periodic pulsations (QPPs) are often observed in flare emissions. While these may reveal much about the time-dependent reconnection involved in flare energy release, the underlying mechanisms are still poorly understood. In this paper, we use 2D magnetohydrodynamic simulations to investigate the magnetic reconnection in two merging flux ropes, focusing on the effects of the resistivity on the time variation of the reconnection. We consider both uniform resistivity and current-dependent anomalous resistivity profiles. Our findings reveal that resistivity plays a critical role in controlling the reconnection dynamics, including reconnection rate oscillations and the rate of decay of the reconnection rate. Resistivity also influences the oscillations in emitted gyrosynchrotron radiation. However, in contrast to this strong influence of resistivity on reconnection rates, we observed a different behaviour for the emitted waves, whose frequencies are almost independent of resistivity variations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14563v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0226068</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Luiz A. C. A. Schiavo, James Stewart, Philippa K. Browning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neoclassical transport of tungsten ion bundles in total-f neoclassical gyrokinetic simulations of a whole-volume JET-like plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13145v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The application of a bundling technique to model the diverse charge states of tungsten impurity species in total-f gyrokinetic simulations is demonstrated. The gyrokinetic bundling method strategically groups tungsten ions of similar charge, optimizing computational efficiency. The initial radial configuration of these bundles and their respective charges are derived from a coronal approximation and the quasi-neutrality of the plasma. A low-density JET H-mode like plasma is simulated using the neoclassical version of XGC across the entire plasma volume, spanning from the magnetic axis to the divertor. An accumulation of tungsten is observed at the pedestal top, as a result of low-Z tungsten ions moving inward from the scrape-off-layer (SOL) into the core region and high-Z tungsten ions moving outward from the core into the pedestal. This organization of the fluxes cannot be captured by a single tungsten-ion simulation. Large up-down poloidal asymmetries of tungsten form in the pedestal and strongly influence the direction of neoclassical fluxes. The temperature screening effect and its correlation with asymmetries is analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13145v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0144509</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Plasmas 31, 032303 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. Dominski, C. S. Chang, R. Hager, S. Ku, E. S. Yoon, V. Parail</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beam Pointing of Relativistic High-order Harmonics Genrated on a Nonuniform Pre-plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09752v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The use of tunable pre-pulse is a common technique to enhance the high-order harmonic generation from surface plasma. The shape and dynamic of the electron density, the degree of ionization and its rate, and the plasma heating are influenced by the pre-pulse properties. Non-uniform pre-pulse could cause a spatially varying density map to the pre-plasma region, which serves as the spectrally up-conversion and reflection surface. The corresponding geometrical feature and plasma nature under laser field will affect the harmonic emission properties. In this study, the variation in harmonic beam pointing due to the electron density shape was investigated. Particle-in-cell simulations demonstrated that both plasma hydrodynamics and geometrical optical effect induce the deviation of harmonic beam from specular reflection. This research contributes to the understanding of the surface plasma dynamics during high harmonic generation process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09752v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaoneng Wu, Yiming Xu, Andre Kalouguine, Jaismenn Kaur, Antoine Cavagna, Zuoye Liu, Rodrigo Lopez-Martens, Cangtao Zhou, Philippe Zeitoun, Stefan Haessler, Lu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
