<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 01:40:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Particle Injection Problem in Magnetic Reconnection and Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic reconnection and turbulence in magnetically-dominated environments have been proposed as important nonthermal particle acceleration mechanisms that generate high energy particles and associated emissions. While the acceleration to high energy that produces the power-law energy distribution has drawn strong interest, recent studies actively discuss pre-acceleration, or injection, to a sufficient energy for a sustained and prolonged Fermi-like acceleration. The injection process is important for determining the fraction of nonthermal particles and energy partition between thermal and nonthermal particles. We review recent advances in understanding the injection mechanisms responsible for populating these nonthermal power-law spectra, and conclude with an outlook for studies and applications of injection models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19938v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Guo, Omar French, Qile Zhang, Xiaocan Li, Jeongbhin Seo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First experimental demonstration of plasma shape control in a tokamak through Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, a Model Predictive Controller (MPC) is proposed to control the plasma shape in the Tokamak \`a Configuration Variable (TCV). The proposed controller relies on models obtained by coupling linearized plasma response models, derived from the \texttt{fge} code of the Matlab EQuilibrium toolbox (MEQ) suite, with a state-space description of the core TCV magnetic control system. It optimizes the reference signals fed to this inner control loop in order to achieve the desired plasma shape while also enforcing constraints on the plant outputs. To this end, a suitable Quadratic Programming (QP) problem is formulated and solved in real-time. The effectiveness of the proposed controller is illustrated through a combination of simulations and experimental results. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time that a plasma shape control solution based on MPC has been experimentally tested on a real tokamak.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20096v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adriano Mele, Maria A. Topalova, Cristian Galperti, Stefano Coda, TCV team, Eurofusion Tokamak Exploitation Team</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Machine Learning Approach to Modeling Line Emission from Helium-Containing Plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The helium I line intensity ratio (LIR) method is used to measure the electron density ($n_e$) and temperature ($T_e$) of fusion-relevant plasmas. Although the collisional-radiative model (CRM) has been used to predict $n_e$ and $T_e$, recent studies have shown that machine learning approaches can provide better measurements if a sufficient dataset for training is available. This study investigates a hybrid neural network approach that combines CRM- and experiment-based models. Although the CRM-based model alone exhibited negative transfer in most cases, the ensemble model modestly improved the prediction accuracy of $T_e$. Notably, in data-limited scenarios, the CRM-based model outperformed the others for $T_e$ prediction, highlighting its potential for applications with constrained diagnostic access.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20117v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin Kajita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tomography for Plasma Imaging: a Unifying Framework for Bayesian Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20232v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Plasma diagnostics often employ computerized tomography to estimate emissivity profiles from a finite, and often limited, number of line-integrated measurements. Decades of algorithmic refinement have brought considerable improvements, and led to a variety of employed solutions. These often feature an underlying, common structure that is rarely acknowledged or investigated. In this paper, we present a unifying perspective on sparse-view tomographic reconstructions for plasma imaging, highlighting how many inversion approaches reported in the literature can be naturally understood within a Bayesian framework. In this setting, statistical modelling of acquired data leads to a likelihood term, while the assumed properties of the profile to be reconstructed are encoded within a prior term. Together, these terms yield the posterior distribution, which models all the available information on the profile to be reconstructed. We show how credible reconstructions, uncertainty quantification and further statistical quantities of interest can be efficiently obtained from noisy tomographic data by means of a stochastic gradient flow algorithm targeting the posterior. This is demonstrated by application to soft x-ray imaging at the TCV tokamak. We validate the proposed imaging pipeline on a large dataset of generated model phantoms, showing how posterior-based inference can be leveraged to perform principled statistical analysis of quantities of interest. Finally, we address some of the inherent, and thus remaining, limitations of sparse-view tomography. All the computational routines used in this work are made available as open access code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20232v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Hamm, C. Theiler, M. Simeoni, B. P. Duval, T. Debarre, L. Simons, J. R. Queralt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MHD simulation of tilt instability during the dynamic FRC magnetic compression process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nonlinear evolution of the tilt instability in a field reversed configuration (FRC) during the dynamic magnetic compression process has been investigated using magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations with the NIMROD code [C. R. Sovinec \textit{et al.}, J. Comput. Phys. \textbf{195}, 355 (2004)]. The tilt mode induces significant deformations in the linear growth phase and results in complete confinement loss of the FRC in the nonlinear phase, with no evidence of dynamic nonlinear stabilization. The growth rate of the tilt mode increases with the compression field ramping rate and approaches an asymptotic value. Toroidal flow can reduce both the growth rate and the nonlinear saturation amplitude of the tilt mode. The stabilizing effect of the toroidal rotation is enhanced with higher compression field ramping rates due to the spontaneous toroidal field generation and increased flow shear during compression. Although the tilt mode remains unstable with a toroidal rotation Mach number close to 0.5, the onset of tilt distortion can be delayed, allowing a magnetic compression ratio up to 5.3 before the compressional heating terminates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20443v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Ma, Ping Zhu, Bo Rao, Haolong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-Loop Turbulent Helical Magnetohydrodynamics: Large-Scale Dynamo and Energy Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20578v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a two-loop field-theoretic analysis of incompressible helical magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) in fully developed stationary turbulence. A key feature of helical MHD is the appearance of an infrared-unstable ``mass-like'' term in the loop diagrams of the magnetic response function. Physically, this term corresponds to the relevant perturbation of the Joule damping, proportional to $\boldsymbol{\nabla} \times \boldsymbol{b}$ ($\boldsymbol{b} =$ magnetic field). Its presence destabilizes the trivial ground state $\langle \boldsymbol{b} \rangle = 0$ and forces us to look for a mechanism for stabilizing the system. We show that such stabilization can be achieved in two ways: (i) by introducing into induction equation an external mass-like parameter that precisely cancels these dangerous loop corrections (kinematic regime), or (ii) via spontaneous breaking of the rotational symmetry, leading to a new ground state with nonzero large-scale magnetic field (turbulent dynamo regime). For the latter case, we study the two-loop correction to the spontaneously generated magnetic field and demonstrate that Goldstone-like corrections to Alfv\'en modes along with some other anisotropic structures arise. Our results also confirm that the emergent mean magnetic field leads to a steeper slope of the magnetic energy spectrum, $-11/3 + 2\gamma_{b\star}$ (with $\gamma_{b\star} = -0.1039 - 0.4202\rho^2$, for $|\rho| \leqslant 1$ as the degree of helicity), compared to the Kolmogorov velocity spectrum of $-11/3$, thereby breaking equipartition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20578v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/xhzb-5hr4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michal Hnati\v{c}, Tom\'a\v{s} Lu\v{c}ivjansk\'y, Luk\'a\v{s} Mi\v{z}i\v{s}in, Yurii Molotkov, Andrei Ovsiannikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Escape and transport in chaotic motion of charged particles in a magnetized plasma under the influence of two and three modes of drift waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates how two- and three-wave configurations govern particle escape and transport in tokamak edge plasmas. Using a Hamiltonian model derived from drift-wave turbulence, we analyze test particle dynamics through Poincar\'e maps, fractal escape basins, and entropy metrics. Introducing a third wave increases basin entropy, enhancing particle escape rates while reducing basin boundary entropy, indicative of suppressed basin mixing. Escape time analyses reveal resonant scattering disrupts coherent transport pathways, linking fractal absorption patterns to heat load mitigation in divertors. Characteristic transport is also analyzed and regimes transition between anomalous $(\alpha &gt; 1)$ and normal diffusion $(\alpha \approx 1)$, two-wave systems sustain anomalous transport, while the third wave homogenizes fluxes through stochastic scattering. Fractal structures in escape basins and entropy-driven uncertainty quantification suggest strategies to engineer transport properties, balancing chaos and order for optimized confinement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20013v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Haerter, E. D. Leonel, R. L. Viana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-event neutron time-of-flight spectroscopy with a petawatt-laser-driven neutron source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20026v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fast neutron-induced nuclear reactions are crucial for advancing our understanding of fundamental nuclear processes, stellar nucleosynthesis, and applications, including reactor safety, medical isotope production, and materials research. With many research reactors being phased out, compact accelerator-based neutron sources are becoming increasingly important. Laser-driven neutron sources (LDNSs) offer unique advantages -- ultrashort neutron pulsees for superior energy resolution, high per-pulse flux, and a drastically reduced footprint. However, their use in single-event fast neutron spectroscopy remains unproven, requiring stable multi-shot operation and detectors capable of functioning in the extreme environment of petawatt-class laser-plasma interactions. Here, we present a proof-of-concept experiment at the DRACO~PW laser in a pitcher-catcher configuration, stably producing 6-7e7 neutrons/shot with energies above 1 MeV, over more than 200 shots delivered at a shot-per-minute rate. Neutron time-of-flight measurements were performed using a single-crystal diamond detector, which is located only 1.5 m away from the source and capable of resolving individual neutron-induced reactions. Observed reaction rates are consistent with Monte Carlo simulations inferred by real-time diagnostics of accompanying gamma, ion, and electron fluxes. With the recent advances in repetition rate, targetry, and ion acceleration efficiency, this work establishes LDNSs as a promising, scalable platform for future fast neutron-induced reaction studies, particularly for measurements involving short-lived isotopes or requiring high instantaneous neutron flux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20026v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Mill\'an-Callado, S. Scheuren, A. Alejo, J. Benlliure, R. Beyer, T. E. Cowan, B. Fern\'andez, E. Griesmayer, A. R. Junghans, J. Kohl, F. Kroll, J. Metzkes-Ng, I. Prencipe, J. M. Quesada, M. Rehwald, C. R\"odel, T. Rodr\'iguez-Gonz\'alez, U. Schramm, M. Roth, R. Stefanikova, S. Urlass, C. Weiss, K. Zeil, T. Ziegler, C. Guerrero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling Core and Edge Mechanisms of the L-mode Density Limit in DIII-D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02773v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The L-mode density limit is re-examined on the DIII-D tokamak using a negative triangularity configuration to study the underlying physics. We find the limit may not be a singular disruptive boundary but a multifaceted density saturation phenomenon governed by distinct core and edge transport mechanisms. Sustained, non-disruptive operation is achieved at densities up to 1.8 times the Greenwald limit ($n_\mathrm{G}$) until the termination of auxiliary heating. Systematic power scans reveal distinct power scalings for the core ($n_e \propto P_\mathrm{SOL}^{0.27\pm0.03}$) and edge ($n_e \propto P_\mathrm{SOL}^{0.42\pm0.04}$) density limits. The edge density saturation is triggered abruptly by the onset of a non-disruptive, high-field side radiative instability that clamps the edge density below $n_\mathrm{G}$. In contrast, the core density continues to rise until it saturates at a level featured by substantially enhanced core turbulence. Core transport evolves from a diffusive to an intermittent, avalanche-like state, as indicated by heavy-tailed probability density functions (kurtosis $\approx 6$), elevated Hurst exponents, and a $1/f$-type power spectrum. These findings demonstrate that the L-mode density limit is determined by a combination of edge radiative instabilities and core turbulent transport.This distinction provides separate targets for control strategies aimed at extending the operational space of future fusion devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02773v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Hong, P. H. Diamond, O. Sauter, J. Chen, F. Khabanov, Z. Li, D. Liu, A. Marinoni, G. R. McKee, T. L. Rhodes, F. Scotti, K. E. Thome, G. R. Tynan, M. A. Van Zeeland, Z. Yan, L. Zeng, the DIII-D NT Team</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fusion research in a Deuterium-Tritium tokamak</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11222v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent ITER re-baselining calls for new fusion-relevant research best carried out in a DT-capable tokamak device with similar technical choices. The present paper describes key issues that could be addressed in a Suitably Enhanced DT-capable Tokamak (SET), with tungsten plasma facing components, boronization systems, and 10 MW of ECRH, based on JET's characteristics and knowledgebase. We discuss hardware options, and show that fusion-relevant operational scenarios could be achieved. Notably, development, validation and testing of fusion and nuclear diagnostics, to be used in next generation devices, would require a DT-capable tokamak as described.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11222v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. R. Solano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lectures on Statistical Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04899v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Presented here is a transcription of the lecture notes from Professor Allan N. Kaufman's graduate statistical mechanics course at Berkeley from the 1972-1973 academic year. Part 1 addresses equilibrium statistical mechanics with topics: fundamentals, classical fluids and other systems, chemical equilibrium, and long-range interactions. Part 2 addresses non-equilibrium statistical mechanics with topics: fundamentals, Brownian motion, Liouville and Klimontovich equations, Landau equation, Markov processes and Fokker-Planck equation, linear response and transport theory, and an introduction to non-equilibrium quantum statistical mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04899v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/S0022377825000042</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Plasma Physics, Vol 91, No. 3, 20 June 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Allan N. Kaufman, Bruce I. Cohen, Alain J. Brizard</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
