<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 04:08:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation Studies of Resonant Excitation of Electron Bernstein Waves in Capacitive Discharges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The behavior of capacitive coupled plasma (CCP) discharges is investigated in a mildly magnetized regime, defined by the condition 1 $\leq$ $f_{ce}/f_{rf}$ $\lt$ 2, where $f_{ce}$ and $f_{rf}$ are the cyclotron and radio-frequencies (RF), respectively. This regime exhibits complex and distinctive plasma dynamics due to the interplay between RF fields and the externally applied magnetic field. Two prominent phenomena are observed in this regime. First, the plasma density profile becomes asymmetric across the discharge, deviating from the typical symmetric distribution seen in unmagnetized CCPs. Second, electron Bernstein waves (EBWs), high-frequency electrostatic waves, are excited and propagate within the bulk plasma, particularly along steep electron density gradients. As the strength of the magnetic field increases within this regime, the CCP discharge undergoes a transition from a symmetric configuration to an asymmetric one, and then returns to a symmetric profile at higher field strengths. Notably, the excitation and propagation of EBWs are strongly correlated with the presence of discharge asymmetry and localized density gradients. These waves play a significant role in energy transport and electron heating under mildly magnetized conditions. To gain deeper insight into the underlying physics, detailed numerical simulations are carried out using the particle-in-cell Monte Carlo collision (PIC-MCC) technique. These simulations capture the kinetic behavior of electrons and ions, including the collisionless effects and sheath dynamics essential to understanding the excitation of EBWs and the evolution of discharge symmetry. The study thus sheds light on the role of weak magnetic fields in shaping plasma behavior and highlights the importance of wave-particle interactions in magnetized CCPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15269v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deepak Gautam, Sarveshwar Sharma, Igor Kaganovich, Bhooshan Paradkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>THz emission from multiple ionized plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studies employing nonlinear interactions of THz pulses are nowadays a promising scientific research field. To capture these phenomena, THz pulses with energy ranging from hundreds of \muJ to the mJ level are necessary. However, techniques that provide pulses with such energy levels are still not widely established. Upscaling methods of laser-solid interaction is limited by the damage threshold of materials, while the mechanism of THz generation from high intensity laser-gas interactions is not fully understood yet. Here, we establish the photocurrent model of laser-driven plasma THz generation in the high-intensity regime by accounting for high-ionization states of the target gas. Our model shows excellent agreement with experimental observations, provides a clear explanation of phenomena in both spectral and temporal domains, and explains the high conversion efficiency from laser to THz. In the experiments, we achieved a generation of 0.2 mJ THz pulses, driven by a Ti:sapphire laser with a conversion efficiency exceeding 1 %.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15462v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucie Jurkovi\v{c}ov\'a, David \v{S}tok, Caroline Juliano, Maty\'a\v{s} Stan\v{e}k, Jaroslav Nejdl, Ond\v{r}ej Hort</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trotter-based quantum algorithm for solving transport equations with exponentially fewer time-steps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15691v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The extent to which quantum computers can simulate physical phenomena and solve the partial differential equations (PDEs) that govern them remains a central open question. In this work, one of the most fundamental PDEs is addressed: the multidimensional transport equation with space- and time-dependent coefficients. We present a quantum numerical scheme based on three steps: quantum state preparation, evolution, and measurement of relevant observables. The evolution step combines a high-order centered finite difference with a time-splitting scheme based on product formula approximations, also known as Trotterization. Novel numerical analysis is introduced to bound the different sources of error and we prove that, for the product formula approximations, vector norm analysis guarantees similar accuracy with exponentially fewer time steps than operator-norm-based approaches, thereby significantly reducing the projected computational resources. We also present efficient quantum circuits and numerical simulations that confirm the predicted vector-norm scaling. We report results on real quantum hardware for the one-dimensional convection equation, and solve a non-linear ordinary differential equation via its associated Liouville equation, a particular case of transport equations. This work provides a practical framework for efficiently simulating transport phenomena on quantum computers, with potential applications in plasma physics, molecular gas dynamics and non-linear dynamical systems, including chaotic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15691v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Zylberman, Thibault Fredon, Nuno F. Loureiro, Fabrice Debbasch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase space transport, quasilinear diffusion and locality in phase velocity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14657v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we address the motion of charged particles subjected to a discrete spectrum of electrostatic waves. We focus on situations when transport dominates, leading to significant variations in particle velocity. Nonetheless, these velocity changes remain finite due to the presence of KAM tori bounding phase space. We analyze the conditions under which transport can be modeled as a diffusion process and evaluate the relevance of the so-called quasilinear value of the diffusion coefficient. We distinguish between traditional quasilinear diffusion, when wave-particle interaction is perturbative, and the so-called chaotic regime of diffusion, when the particle motion looks erratic. In the perturbative regime, we demonstrate both numerically and theoretically that diffusion occurs only when wave-particle interaction is local in phase velocity; that is, when wave contributions from phase velocities far from the particles instantaneous velocities are negligible. Conversely, numerical results indicate that chaotic diffusion can occur even when wave-particle interaction is not local. Furthermore, in regimes when quasilinear diffusion is applicable, we introduce a simple analytical expression for the time evolution of the velocity distribution function, that accounts for phase space boundaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14657v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Didier B\'enisti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortex-magnetic competition and regime transitions in antiparallel flux tubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10648v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vortex-magnetic interactions shape magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) turbulence, influencing energy transfer in astrophysical, geophysical, and industrial systems. On the Sun, granular-scale vortex flows couple strongly with magnetic fields, channeling energy into the corona. At high Reynolds numbers, vorticity and magnetic fields are nearly frozen into the charged fluid, and MHD flows emerge from the Lorentz force mediated interactions between coherent vortex structures in matter and the field. To probe this competition in a controlled setting, we revisit the canonical problem of two antiparallel flux tubes. By varying the magnetic flux threading each tube--and thus sweeping the interaction parameter $N_i$, which gauges Lorentz-to-inertial force balance--we uncover three distinct regimes: vortex-dominated joint reconnection, instability-triggered cascade, and Lorentz-induced vortex disruption. At low $N_i$, classical vortex dynamics dominate, driving joint vortex-magnetic reconnection and amplifying magnetic energy via a dynamo effect. At moderate $N_i$, the system oscillates between vorticity-driven attraction and magnetic damping, triggering instabilities and nonlinear interactions that spawn secondary filaments and drive an energy cascade. At high $N_i$, Lorentz forces suppress vortex interactions, aligning the tubes axially while disrupting vortex cores and rapidly converting magnetic to kinetic energy. These findings reveal how the inertial-Lorentz balance governs energy transfer and coherent structure formation in MHD turbulence, offering insight into vortex-magnetic coevolution in astrophysical plasmas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10648v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiyu Shen, Rodolfo Ostilla-M\'onico, Xiaojue Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
