<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 02:49:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear Fusion Enhancement by Heavy Nuclear Catalysts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We seek to understand the effect of high electron density in the proximity of a heavy nucleus on the fusion reaction rates in a hot plasma phase. We investigate quantitatively the catalytic effect of gold ($Z=79$) ions embedded in an electron plasma created due to plasmonic focusing of high-intensity short laser pulses. Using self-consistent strong plasma screening, we find highly significant changes in the internuclear potential of light elements present nearby. For gold, we see a $14\,$keV change in the internuclear potential near the nuclear surface, independent of the long-distance thermal Debye-H\"uckel screening. The dense polarization cloud of electrons around the gold catalyst leads to a $\sim 1.5$ enhancement of proton-boron ($^{11}$B) fusion above $T=100\,$keV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07804v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Grayson, Johann Rafelski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous kinetic profile and magnetic equilibrium inference with Bayesian integrated data analysis in preparation for ITER</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07805v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate plasma state reconstruction will be crucial for the success of ITER and future fusion plants, but the harsh conditions of a burning plasma will make diagnostic operation more challenging than in current machines. Integrated data analysis (IDA) based on Bayesian inference allows for improved information gain by combining the analysis of many diagnostics into a single step using sophisticated forward models. It also provides a framework to seamlessly combine predictive modeling and data, which can be invaluable in a data-poor environment. As a step towards integrated data analysis at scale, we present a new, fast integrated analysis framework that allows for the simultaneous reconstruction of the kinetic profiles and the magnetic equilibrium with statistically relevant uncertainties included. This analysis framework allows for the systematic evaluation of models using extensive experimental data leveraging DOE supercomputing infrastructure, such as being developed through the DOE-ASCR Integrated Research Infrastructure (Smith, XLOOP). To test the performance and verify the code it was applied to an ITER-like scenario using a realistic machine geometry and diagnostic description. Using artificial data for magnetics, Thomson scattering, interferometry, and polarimetry generated from a known ground truth, the coupled equilibrium and kinetic profile reconstruction problem was solved via the Maximum a posteriori method in approximately three minutes on a multicore CPU including uncertainty quantification. The resulting equilibrium and kinetic profiles were found to be in reasonable agreement with the ground truth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07805v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. S. Denk, T. B. Amara, T. Odstrcil, L. Stagner, C. Akcay, T. Slendebroek, S. P. Smith, M. A. Van Zeeland, T. Akiyama, R. Nazikian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards the generation of petawatt near-infrared few-cycle light pulses via forward Raman amplification in plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Light amplification towards extremely high power in the infrared regime remains a significant challenge due to the lack of suitable gain media. Here we propose a new scheme to amplify a laser pulse with tunable wavelengths towards extremely high power via forward Raman amplification in plasma. Different from those previously proposed schemes based upon backward Raman or Brillouin amplification, our scheme involves a pump pulse and a seed pulse co-propagating in moderate density plasma, with the phase matching conditions for forward Raman scattering fulfilled. Due to their group velocity difference in plasma, the pump with a shorter wavelength and longer duration will chase the seed and transfer energy to the latter efficiently. Analytical models both for linear and nonlinear stages of amplification as well as particle-in-cell simulation show that by employing a 1.0 $\mathrm{\mu m}$ pump laser, a 1.8 $\mathrm{\mu m}$ seed pulse can be amplified $10^4$ times in its intensity, and then self-compressed to near-single-cycle. Our scheme shows the merits of high efficiency, high compactness, and relatively easy implementation with the co-propagating configuration, which may provide a unique route towards the petawatt few-cycle infrared laser pulses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08174v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Yu Lei, Zheng-Ming Sheng, Su-Ming Weng, Min Chen, Jie Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of initial spin orientation on the generation of polarized electron beams from laser wakefield acceleration in plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08351v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The effects of the initial spin orientation on the final electron beam polarization via laser wakefield acceleration in pre-polarized plasma are investigated theoretically and numerically. From a variation of the initial spin direction, the spin dynamics of the electron beam is found to depend on the self-injection mechanism. The effects of wakefields and laser fields are studied using test particle dynamics and particle-in-cell simulation based on the Thomas-Bargmann-Michel-Telegdi equation, respectively. Compared to the case of transverse injection, the scheme of longitudinal injection is more favorable to obtain a highly polarization electron beam.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08351v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. R. Yin, X. F. Li, Y. J. Gu, N. Cao, Q. Kong, M. Buescher, S. M. Weng, M. Chen, Z. M. Sheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Law for Discharges in Z pinch Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08570v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the snowplow model for studying discharges in Z pinch devices. In this context, to obtain a complete picture on the physics of those discharges, we replenish the term disregarded in the original formulation of the snowplow equations. This is, we now consider not only the magnetic force inward on the current sheath but we take into account also a force outward on it. Such a force results from the kinetic pressure of the gas occluded by the current sheath.
  The internal energy gained by the gas towards the end of the discharge depends on the full history of the dynamical variables of the system. In other terms, the internal energy is a functional of the dynamical variables of the system. We write down the expression for evaluating that internal energy and we present also the formula for computing the temperature of the gas.
  On this basis, we derive a scaling law that relates the temperature the gas in a Z pinch experiment would attain with the energetic and spatial wingspan of the corresponding experimental setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08570v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel C\'ardenas, Alejandro Nettle, Leandro N\'u\~nez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ion-Acoustic Waves and the Proton-Alpha Streaming Instability at Collisionless Shocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07953v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ion-acoustic waves are routinely observed at collisionless shocks and could be an important source of resistivity. The source of instability and the effects of the waves are not fully understood. We show, using Magnetospheric Multiscale (MMS) mission observations and numerical modeling, that across low Mach number shocks a large relative drift between protons and alpha particles develops, which can be unstable to the proton-alpha streaming instability. The results from linear analysis and a numerical simulation show that the resulting waves agree with the observed wave properties. The generated ion-acoustic waves are predicted to become nonlinear and form ion holes, maintained by trapped protons and alphas. The instability reduces the relative drift between protons and alphas, and heats the ions, thus providing a source of resistivity at shocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07953v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel B. Graham, Yuri V. Khotyaintsev, Ahmad Lalti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous high-yield fast neutron generation with few-cycle laser pulses at 10 Hz for applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08197v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a laser-based neutron source that produces $1.8 \times 10^5$ neutrons/s with a conversion rate of $7.8 \times 10^5$ neutrons/J. Laser pulses of 12 fs and 23 mJ were focused onto a 430-nm-thick heavy water liquid sheet at a 10 Hz repetition rate. The resulting peak intensity of $4 \times 10^{18}$ W/cm$^2$ accelerated deuterium ions from the target rear side to a kinetic energy of 1 MeV. This deuteron beam induced $^{2}$H(d,n)$^{3}$He fusion reactions in a deuterated polyethylene target, producing fast neutrons. The neutron yield was measured using two independent detection systems: the LILITH time-of-flight spectrometer, consisting of eight plastic scintillators covering nearly $180^\circ$, and a calibrated bubble detector spectrometer. The neutron yield per laser shot is 35 times higher than that recently achieved by lasers with comparable pulse energies, while the conversion rate is the highest ever achieved by continuously operating, sub-100 fs lasers. The generated neutrons are emitted from an area of 0.65 cm$^2$ corresponding to the deuteron beam spot on the catcher. Their angular distribution is peaked in forward and backward directions in agreement with the literature data on the angular distribution of $^{2}$H(d,n)$^{3}$He reaction. The system operated continuously for several hours per day with an unprecedented stability of 5%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08197v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Stuhl, P. Varmazyar, Z. Elekes, Z. Hal\'asz, T. Gilinger, M. F\"ule, M. Karnok, E. Buz\'as, A. P. Kov\'acs, B. Nagy, A. Moh\'acsi, B. B\'ir\'o, L. Csedreki, A. Fenyvesi, Zs. F\"ul\"op, Z. Korkulu, I. Kuti, J. Csontos, P. P. Geetha, Sz. T\'oth, G. Szab\'o, K. Osvay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carbon Nanotube-Based 100s TeV/m-Level Particle Accelerators Driven by High-density Electron Beams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08498v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solid-state materials, such as carbon nanotubes (CNTs), have the potential to support ultra-high accelerating fields in the TV/m range for charged particle acceleration. In this study, we explore the feasibility of using nanostructured CNTs forest to develop plasma-based accelerators at the 100s TeV-level, driven by high-density, ultra-relativistic electron beams, using fully three-dimensional particle-in-cell simulations. Two different acceleration mechanisms are proposed and investigated: the surface plasmon leakage field and the bubble wakefield. The leakage field, driven by a relatively low-density beam, can achieve an acceleration field up to TV/m, capable of accelerating both electron and positron beams. In particular, due to the direct acceleration by the driving beam, the positron acceleration is highly efficient with an average acceleration gradient of 2.3 TeV/m. In contrast, the bubble wakefield mechanism allows significantly higher acceleration fields, e.g. beyond 400 TV/m, with a much higher energy transfer efficiency of 66.7%. In principle, electrons can be accelerated to PeV energies over distances of several meters. If the beam density is sufficiently high, the CNT target will be completely blown out, where no accelerating field is generated. Its threshold has been estimated. Two major challenges in these schemes are recognised and investigated. Lever- aging the ultra-high energy and charge pumping rate of the driving beam, the nanostructured CNTs also offer significant potential for a wide range of advanced applications. This work represents a promising avenue for the development of ultra-compact, high-energy particle accelerators. We also outline conceptual experiments using currently available facilities, demonstrating that this approach is experimentally accessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08498v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bifeng Lei, Hao Zhang, Cristian Bontoiu, Alexandre Bonatto, Javier Resta-Lopez, Guoxing Xia, Bin Qiao, Carsten Welsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positive streamer discharge simulations in humid air: uncertainty in input data and sensitivity analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03861v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study how the choice of input data affects simulations of positive streamers in humid air, focusing on H2O cross sections, photoionization models, and chemistry sets. Simulations are performed in air with a mole fraction of 0%, 3% or 10% H2O using an axisymmetric fluid model. Five H2O cross section sets are considered, which lead to significant differences in the resulting electron attachment coefficient. As a result, the streamer velocity can vary by up to about 50% with 10% H2O. We compare results with three photoionization models: the Naidis model for humid air, the Aints model for humid air, and the standard Zheleznyak model for dry air. With the Naidis and in particular the Aints model, there is a significant reduction in photoionization with higher humidities. This results in higher streamer velocities and maximal electric fields, and it can also cause streamer branching in our axisymmetric simulations. Three humid air chemistry sets are considered. Differences between these sets, particularly in the formation of water clusters around positive ions, cause the streamer velocity to vary by up to about 50% with 10% H2O. A sensitivity analysis is performed to identify the most important chemical reactions in these chemistries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03861v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baohong Guo, Hemaditya Malla, Alejandro Malagon-Romero, Jannis Teunissen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wakefield regeneration in a resonantly driven plasma accelerator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14175v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Plasma wakefields offer high acceleration gradients, orders of magnitude larger than conventional RF accelerators. However, the achievable luminosity remains relatively low, typically limited by repetition rate and the charge accelerated per shot. In this work, we show that a train of drive bunches can be harnessed to accelerate multiple witness bunches in a single shot. We demonstrate that periodically loading the wakefields removes the limit on the energy transfer from the drive beam to the plasma, which allows the luminosity to be increased. Proof-of-concept simulations for the AWAKE scheme are carried out to demonstrate the technique, achieving a doubling of the accelerated charge while exploiting only a fraction of the drive train.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14175v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John P. Farmer, Giovanni Zevi Della Porta</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
