<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.plasm-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph</link>
    <description>physics.plasm-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.plasm-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 02:59:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A space-resolved visible spectrometer system using compact endoscopic optics for full vertical profile measurement of impurity line emissions in superconducting EAST tokamak</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In Experimental Advanced Superconducting Tokamak (EAST tokamak) with tungsten divertors and molybdenum first wall, lithiumization and boronization have been frequently carried out to improve the plasma performance, in particular, in long pulse discharges. A study on impurity behaviors of lithium, boron and tungsten atoms/ions in the edge plasma is then crucially important. For the purpose, a space-resolved visible spectrometer system has been newly developed to observe full vertical profiles over a length of 1.7m of impurity line emissions in wavelength range of 320-800nm. For the full vertical profile measurement compact endoscopic optics is employed with an optical fiber bundle for the system, which can be inserted into a 1.5m long extension tube called 'long nose', because the distance between the diagnostic port and plasma center is considerably long. Therefore, a quartz glass window mounted from the vacuum vessel side is designed to withstand the reverse pressure. A mechanical shutter is also designed to open at a large angle of 235 degree so that the viewing angle of nearby ports is not blocked. Two sets of the fiber bundle, 60-channel linear array and 11*10 channel planar array , with a length of 30m are attached to two sets of Czerny-Turner visible spectrometers for one-dimensional (1D) vertical profile measurement of core plasma and two-dimensional (2D) spectroscopy of divertor plasma, respectively. A complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS) detector with 2048*2048 pixels is used for the visible spectrometers. A preliminary result on the full vertical profile is obtained for BII line emission at 703.19nm in the 1D system</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18977v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Hu, Y. Cheng, L. Zhang, S. Morita, J. Ma, M. Kobayashi, C. Zhou, J. Chen, Y. Cao, F. Zhang, W. Zhang, Z. Li, D. Mitnik, S. Wang, Y. Jie, G. Zuo, J. Qian, H. Liu, G. Xu, J. Hu, K. Lu, Y. Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conceptual study on using Doppler backscattering to measure magnetic pitch angle in tokamak plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19061v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new approach to measure the magnetic pitch angle profile in tokamak plasmas with Doppler backscattering (DBS), a technique traditionally used for measuring flows and density fluctuations. The DBS signal is maximised when its probe beam's wavevector is perpendicular to the magnetic field at the cutoff location, independent of the density fluctuations. Hence, if one could isolate this effect, DBS would then yield information about the magnetic pitch angle. By varying the toroidal launch angle, the DBS beam reaches cutoff with different angles with respect to the magnetic field, but with other properties remaining similar. Hence, the toroidal launch angle which gives maximum backscattered power is thus that which is matched to the pitch angle at the cutoff location, enabling inference of the magnetic pitch angle. We performed systematic scans of the DBS toroidal launch angle for repeated DIII-D tokamak discharges. Experimental DBS data from this scan were analysed and combined with Gaussian beam-tracing simulations using the Scotty code. The pitch-angle inferred from DBS is consistent with that from magnetics-only and motional-Stark-effect-constrained (MSE) equilibrium reconstruction in the edge. In the core, the pitch angles from DBS and magnetics-only reconstructions differ by one to two degrees, while simultaneous MSE measurements were not available. The uncertainty in these measurements was under a degree; we show that this uncertainty is primarily due to the error in toroidal steering, the number of toroidally separated measurements, and shot-to-shot repeatability. We find that the error of pitch-angle measurements can be reduced by optimising the poloidal launch angle and initial beam properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19061v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>AK Yeoh, VH Hall-Chen, QT Pratt, BS Victor, J Damba, TL Rhodes, NA Crocker, KR Fong, JC Hillesheim, FI Parra, J Ruiz Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operando XPS in Reactive Plasmas: The Importance of The Wall Reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advancements in differential pumping and electron optics over the past few decades have enabled x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) measurements at (near-)ambient pressures, bridging the pressure gap for characterizing realistic sample chemistries. Recently, we demonstrated the capabilities of an ambient pressure XPS (APXPS) setup for in-situ plasma environment measurements, allowing plasma-surface interactions to be studied in operando rather than using the traditional before-and-after analysis approach. This new plasma-XPS technique facilitates the identification of reaction intermediates critical for understanding plasma-assisted surface processes relevant to semiconductor nanomanufacturing, such as physical vapor deposition, etching, atomic layer deposition, etc. In this report, we apply the plasma-XPS approach to monitor real-time surface chemical changes on a model Ag(111) single crystal exposed to oxidizing and reducing plasmas. We correlate surface-sensitive data with concurrent gas-phase XPS measurements and residual gas mass-spectra analysis of species generated during plasma exposure, highlighting the significant role of plasma-induced chamber wall reactions. Ultimately, we demonstrate that plasma-XPS provides comprehensive insights into both surface and gas-phase chemistry, establishing it as a versatile and dynamic characterization tool with broad applications in microelectronics research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19303v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Trey Diulus, Ashley R. Head, Jorge Anibal Boscoboinik, Andrei Kolmakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal neutralization of negative space charges in photon-enhanced thermionic emission devices under bidirectional discharge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18539v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we innovatively modeled photon-enhanced thermionic emission (PETE) devices, incorporating positive ion injection and bidirectional discharge's effects on the space charge barrier simultaneously. Compared to previous models, our model allows the positive ion distribution function to be compatible with scenarios in which the anode motive is either higher or lower than the cathode motive, and also adapts to significant anode discharge. Through numerical simulations and parametric analyses, we found that: (1) As the ratio of the positive ion increases, the capability for space charge neutralization becomes stronger. (2) The lower the electron affinity is, the smaller the ratio of positive ions are required. (3) When the anode temperature is higher or the anode work function is lower, the impact of reverse discharge on the net current density is more pronounced. Conversely, when the anode temperature is higher or the anode work function is greater, the ratio of positive ions required to achieve complete space charge neutralization increases. This study further elucidates the mechanisms and characteristics of space charge neutralization effects in PETE devices, providing a theoretical foundation for optimizing their design. Additionally, the accompanying theory and algorithm possess the potential to spark innovative research across diverse fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18539v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinqiao Lin, Zhiqiang Fan, Shunjie Zhang, Xiaohang Chen, Zhimin Yang, Jincan Chen, Shanhe Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Streamer-like red line diffuse auroras driven by time domain structures and ECH waves associated with a plasma injection and braking ion flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Auroral streamers are important meso-scale processes of dynamic magnetosphere-ionosphere coupling, typically studied using imagers sensitive to energetic (&gt;1 keV) electron precipitation, such as all-sky imagers (ASIs). This paper reports streamer-like red-line auroras, representing low-energy (&lt;1 keV) precipitation, observed poleward of a black aurora and an auroral torch. These red-line auroras were associated with a magnetospheric electron injection and braking ion flows. Observations were made using the THEMIS spacecraft and ground-based imagers, including the ASI, REGO, and meridian scanning photometer (MSP) at Fort Smith. We identify plasma sheet electron pitch-angle scattering by time-domain structures (TDSs) and electron cyclotron harmonics (ECH) waves as the driver of these red-line auroras, because of (1) a strong correlation (~0.9) between observed red-line intensities and precipitating fluxes; (2) consistent red-line intensities from auroral transport code forward modeling, and (3) consistent precipitation characteristic energies from MSP optical inference and quasi-linear estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18692v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangyang Shen, Xu Zhang, Jun Liang, Anton Artemyev, Vassilis Angelopoulos, Emma Spanswick, Larry Lyons, Yukitoshi Nishimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplification of turbulence through multiple planar shocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18708v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the amplification of isotropic, incompressible turbulence through multiple planar, collisional shocks, using analytical linear theory. There are two limiting cases we explore. The first assumes shocks occur rapidly in time such that the turbulence does not evolve between shocks. Whereas the second case allows enough time for turbulence to isotropize between each shock. For the latter case, through a quasi-equation-of-state, we show that the weak multi-shock limit is agnostic to the distinction between thermal and vortical turbulent pressures, like an isotropic volumetric compression. When turbulence does not return to isotropy between shocks, the generated anisotropy -- itself a function of shock strength -- can feedback on amplification by further shocks, altering choices for maximal or minimal amplification. In addition for this case, we find that amplification is sensitive to the shock ordering. We map how choices of shock strength can impact these amplification differences due to ordering, finding, for example, shock pairs which lead to identical mean post-shock fields (density, temperature, pressure) but maximally distinct turbulent amplification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18708v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael F. Zhang, Seth Davidovits, Nathaniel J. Fisch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microwave sink using plasma based localized surface plasmons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19021v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Overcoming the diffraction limit, meaning focusing waves on a sub-wavelength scale, has received considerable attention for applications involving light and acoustics. Indeed, the intense focusing achieved enhances the interactions between waves and matter, and the improved spatial resolution opens up possibilities in fields such as imaging, detection and communication. In optics, a passive sink may be obtained if the incident light couples to localized surface plasmon (LSP) resonances, resulting in Coherent Perfect Absorption condition. The presence of optical surface plasmons at metal interfaces is due to the angular frequency of metals, which lies in the optical regime due to their high density of free electrons. Plasmas, which consists of ionized gazes with a lower electron density, can support surface plasmons in the microwave regime. Hence, we demonstrate in this paper that sub-wavelength plasmas behave as a passive microwave sink by exciting LSP resonance inside the plasma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19021v1</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Fromont, J. De Rosny, R. Pascaud, N. Lebbe, O. Pascal, J. Sokoloff, L. Liard, T. Delage, A. Saucourt, M. Fink, V. Mazi\`eres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Quantum Simulation of the Fokker-Planck Equation applied to Quantum Radiation Reaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17517v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Near-future experiments with Petawatt class lasers are expected to produce a high flux of gamma-ray photons and electron-positron pairs through Strong Field Quantum Electrodynamical processes. Simulations of the expected regime of laser-matter interaction are computationally intensive due to the disparity of the spatial and temporal scales and because quantum and classical descriptions need to be accounted for simultaneously (classical for collective effects and quantum for nearly-instantaneous events of hard photon emission and pair creation). A typical configuration for experiments is a scattering of an electron and a laser beam which can be mapped to an equivalent problem with constant magnetic field. We study the stochastic cooling of an electron beam in a strong constant uniform magnetic field, both its particle distribution functions and their energy momenta. We start by obtaining approximate closed-form analytical solutions to the relevant observables. Then, we apply the quantum-hybrid Variational Quantum Imaginary Time Evolution to the Fokker-Planck equation describing this process, and compare against theory and results from Particle-In-Cell simulations and classical Partial Differential Equation solvers, showing good agreement. This work will be useful as a first step towards quantum simulation of plasma physics scenarios where diffusion processes are important, in particular in strong electromagnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17517v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Oscar Amaro, Lucas I. I\~nigo Gamiz, Marija Vranic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal optical vortex (STOV) polariton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17413v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We confirm the existence of the spatiotemporal optical vortex (STOV) polariton and the value of its tOAM, verifying our theory of transverse orbital angular momentum in a simple dispersive medium [S. W. Hancock et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 127, 193901 (2021)]. We also develop a physical picture of the polariton as a structure driven by torques induced by the ponderomotive force of the light in the presence of material dispersion. This is a new type of spatiotemporal torque unanticipated in our recent work [S. W. Hancock et al., Phys. Rev. X 14, 011031 (2024)]. These results are accomplished by high resolution particle-in-cell (PIC) simulations of STOV pulse reflection from and transmission through a fully ionized hydrogen plasma slab. The linear theory matches the PIC simulations up to near-critical plasma densities and near-relativistic field strengths. For higher intensities, optical tOAM becomes invested in collective modes of the plasma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17413v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. S. Le, S. W. Hancock, N. Tripathi, H. M. Milchberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Conductivity and Nonadiabatic Born Effective Charges of Disordered Metals, Warm Dense Matter, and Hot Dense Plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16230v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The average ionization state is a critical parameter in plasma models for charged particle transport, equation of state, and optical response. The dynamical or nonadiabatic Born effective charge (NBEC), calculated via first principles time-dependent density functional theory, provides exact ionic partitioning of bulk electron response for both metallic and insulating materials. The NBEC can be trivially transformed into a ''group conductivity," that is, the electron conductivity ascribed to a subset of ions. We show that for disordered metallic systems, such as warm dense matter (WDM) and hot dense plasma, the static limit of the NBEC is different from the average ionization state, but that the ionization state can be extracted from the group conductivity even in mixed systems. We demonstrate this approach using a set of archetypical examples, including cold and warm aluminium, low- and high- density WDM carbon, and a WDM carbon-beryllium-hydrogen mixture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16230v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vidushi Sharma, Alexander J. White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrodynamics of Vortices in Quasi-2D Scalar Bose-Einstein Condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14302v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In two spatial dimensions, vortex-vortex interactions approximately vary with the logarithm of the inter-vortex distance, making it possible to describe an ensemble of vortices as a Coulomb gas. We introduce a duality between vortices in a quasi-two-dimensional (quasi-2D) scalar Bose-Einstein condensates (BEC) and effective Maxwell's electrodynamics. Specifically, we address the general scenario of inhomogeneous, time-dependent BEC number density with dissipation or rotation. Starting from the Gross-Pitaevskii equation (GPE), which describes the mean-field dynamics of a quasi-2D scalar BEC without dissipation, we show how to map vortices in a quasi-2D scalar BEC to 2D electrodynamics beyond the point-vortex approximation, even when dissipation is present or in a rotating system. The physical meaning of this duality is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14302v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.013217</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 013217 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Seong-Ho Shinn, Adolfo del Campo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical study of solar eruption, extreme-ultraviolet wave propagation, and wave-induced prominence dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15697v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Extreme ultraviolet (EUV) waves, frequently produced by eruptions, propagate through the non-uniform magnetic field of the solar corona and interact with distant prominences, inducing their global oscillations. However, the generation, propagation, and interaction of these waves with distant prominences remain poorly understood. We aim to study the influence of an eruptive flux rope (EFR) on a distant prominence by means of extreme-resolution numerical simulations. We cover a domain of a horizontal extent of 1100 Mm, while capturing details down to 130 km using automated grid refinement. We performed a 2.5D numerical experiment using the open-source \texttt{MPI-AMRVAC 3.1} code, modeling an eruption as a 2.5D catastrophe scenario augmented with a distant dipole magnetic field to form a flux rope prominence. Our findings reveal that the EFR becomes unstable and generates a quasi-circular front. The primary front produces a slow secondary front when crossing the equipartition lines where the Alfv\'en speed is close to the sound speed. The resulting fast and slow EUV waves show different behaviors: the fast EUV wave slightly decelerates as it propagates through the corona, while the slow EUV wave forms a stationary front. The fast EUV wave interacts with the remote prominence, driving both transverse and longitudinal oscillations. Additionally, magnetic reconnection at a null point below the prominence-hosting flux rope is triggered by the fast EUV wave, affecting the flux rope magnetic field and the prominence oscillations. Our study unifies important results of the dynamics of eruptive events and their interactions with distant prominences, including details of (oscillatory) reconnection and chaotic plasmoid dynamics. We demonstrate for the first time the full consequences of remote eruptions on prominence dynamics and clarify the damping mechanisms of prominence oscillations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15697v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeriia Liakh, Rony Keppens</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
