<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR</link>
    <description>cs.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 04:00:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time Diverse Motion In-betweening with Space-time Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present a data-driven framework for generating diverse in-betweening motions for kinematic characters. Our approach injects dynamic conditions and explicit motion controls into the procedure of motion transitions. Notably, this integration enables a finer-grained spatial-temporal control by allowing users to impart additional conditions, such as duration, path, style, etc., into the in-betweening process. We demonstrate that our in-betweening approach can synthesize both locomotion and unstructured motions, enabling rich, versatile, and high-quality animation generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00270v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3677388.3696327</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Chu, Zeshi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MM-Conv: A Multi-modal Conversational Dataset for Virtual Humans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00253v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a novel dataset captured using a VR headset to record conversations between participants within a physics simulator (AI2-THOR). Our primary objective is to extend the field of co-speech gesture generation by incorporating rich contextual information within referential settings. Participants engaged in various conversational scenarios, all based on referential communication tasks. The dataset provides a rich set of multimodal recordings such as motion capture, speech, gaze, and scene graphs. This comprehensive dataset aims to enhance the understanding and development of gesture generation models in 3D scenes by providing diverse and contextually rich data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00253v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Deichler, Jim O'Regan, Jonas Beskow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flex3D: Feed-Forward 3D Generation With Flexible Reconstruction Model And Input View Curation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00890v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generating high-quality 3D content from text, single images, or sparse view images remains a challenging task with broad applications.Existing methods typically employ multi-view diffusion models to synthesize multi-view images, followed by a feed-forward process for 3D reconstruction. However, these approaches are often constrained by a small and fixed number of input views, limiting their ability to capture diverse viewpoints and, even worse, leading to suboptimal generation results if the synthesized views are of poor quality. To address these limitations, we propose Flex3D, a novel two-stage framework capable of leveraging an arbitrary number of high-quality input views. The first stage consists of a candidate view generation and curation pipeline. We employ a fine-tuned multi-view image diffusion model and a video diffusion model to generate a pool of candidate views, enabling a rich representation of the target 3D object. Subsequently, a view selection pipeline filters these views based on quality and consistency, ensuring that only the high-quality and reliable views are used for reconstruction. In the second stage, the curated views are fed into a Flexible Reconstruction Model (FlexRM), built upon a transformer architecture that can effectively process an arbitrary number of inputs. FlemRM directly outputs 3D Gaussian points leveraging a tri-plane representation, enabling efficient and detailed 3D generation. Through extensive exploration of design and training strategies, we optimize FlexRM to achieve superior performance in both reconstruction and generation tasks. Our results demonstrate that Flex3D achieves state-of-the-art performance, with a user study winning rate of over 92% in 3D generation tasks when compared to several of the latest feed-forward 3D generative models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00890v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junlin Han, Jianyuan Wang, Andrea Vedaldi, Philip Torr, Filippos Kokkinos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LFS-Aware Surface Reconstruction from Unoriented 3D Point Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13924v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel approach for generating isotropic surface triangle meshes directly from unoriented 3D point clouds, with the mesh density adapting to the estimated local feature size (LFS). Popular reconstruction pipelines first reconstruct a dense mesh from the input point cloud and then apply remeshing to obtain an isotropic mesh. The sequential pipeline makes it hard to find a lower-density mesh while preserving more details. Instead, our approach reconstructs both an implicit function and an LFS-aware mesh sizing function directly from the input point cloud, which is then used to produce the final LFS-aware mesh without remeshing. We combine local curvature radius and shape diameter to estimate the LFS directly from the input point clouds. Additionally, we propose a new mesh solver to solve an implicit function whose zero level set delineates the surface without requiring normal orientation. The added value of our approach is generating isotropic meshes directly from 3D point clouds with an LFS-aware density, thus achieving a trade-off between geometric detail and mesh complexity. Our experiments also demonstrate the robustness of our method to noise, outliers, and missing data and can preserve sharp features for CAD point clouds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13924v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TMM.2024.3453050</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rao Fu, Kai Hormann, Pierre Alliez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HUMAP: Hierarchical Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.07718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.07718v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dimensionality reduction (DR) techniques help analysts to understand patterns in high-dimensional spaces. These techniques, often represented by scatter plots, are employed in diverse science domains and facilitate similarity analysis among clusters and data samples. For datasets containing many granularities or when analysis follows the information visualization mantra, hierarchical DR techniques are the most suitable approach since they present major structures beforehand and details on demand. This work presents HUMAP, a novel hierarchical dimensionality reduction technique designed to be flexible on preserving local and global structures and preserve the mental map throughout hierarchical exploration. We provide empirical evidence of our technique's superiority compared with current hierarchical approaches and show a case study applying HUMAP for dataset labelling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.07718v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TVCG.2024.3471181</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Wilson E. Marc\'ilio-Jr, Danilo M. Eler, Fernando V. Paulovich, Rafael M. Martins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniHands: Towards Robust 4D Hand Mesh Recovery via A Versatile Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20330v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce OmniHands, a universal approach to recovering interactive hand meshes and their relative movement from monocular or multi-view inputs. Our approach addresses two major limitations of previous methods: lacking a unified solution for handling various hand image inputs and neglecting the positional relationship of two hands within images. To overcome these challenges, we develop a universal architecture with novel tokenization and contextual feature fusion strategies, capable of adapting to a variety of tasks. Specifically, we propose a Relation-aware Two-Hand Tokenization (RAT) method to embed positional relation information into the hand tokens. In this way, our network can handle both single-hand and two-hand inputs and explicitly leverage relative hand positions, facilitating the reconstruction of intricate hand interactions in real-world scenarios. As such tokenization indicates the relative relationship of two hands, it also supports more effective feature fusion. To this end, we further develop a 4D Interaction Reasoning (FIR) module to fuse hand tokens in 4D with attention and decode them into 3D hand meshes and relative temporal movements. The efficacy of our approach is validated on several benchmark datasets. The results on in-the-wild videos and real-world scenarios demonstrate the superior performances of our approach for interactive hand reconstruction. More video results can be found on the project page: https://OmniHand.github.io.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20330v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dixuan Lin, Yuxiang Zhang, Mengcheng Li, Yebin Liu, Wei Jing, Qi Yan, Qianying Wang, Hongwen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RNG: Relightable Neural Gaussians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19702v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) has shown its impressive power in novel view synthesis. However, creating relightable 3D assets, especially for objects with ill-defined shapes (e.g., fur), is still a challenging task. For these scenes, the decomposition between the light, geometry, and material is more ambiguous, as neither the surface constraints nor the analytical shading model hold. To address this issue, we propose RNG, a novel representation of relightable neural Gaussians, enabling the relighting of objects with both hard surfaces or fluffy boundaries. We avoid any assumptions in the shading model but maintain feature vectors, which can be further decoded by an MLP into colors, in each Gaussian point. Following prior work, we utilize a point light to reduce the ambiguity and introduce a shadow-aware condition to the network. We additionally propose a depth refinement network to help the shadow computation under the 3DGS framework, leading to better shadow effects under point lights. Furthermore, to avoid the blurriness brought by the alpha-blending in 3DGS, we design a hybrid forward-deferred optimization strategy. As a result, we achieve about $20\times$ faster in training and about $600\times$ faster in rendering than prior work based on neural radiance fields, with $60$ frames per second on an RTX4090.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19702v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahui Fan, Fujun Luan, Jian Yang, Milo\v{s} Ha\v{s}an, Beibei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
