<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR</link>
    <description>cs.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>MotionPersona: Characteristics-aware Locomotion Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present MotionPersona, a novel real-time character controller that allows users to characterize a character by specifying attributes such as physical traits, mental states, and demographics, and projects these properties into the generated motions for animating the character. In contrast to existing deep learning-based controllers, which typically produce homogeneous animations tailored to a single, predefined character, MotionPersona accounts for the impact of various traits on human motion as observed in the real world. To achieve this, we develop a block autoregressive motion diffusion model conditioned on SMPLX parameters, textual prompts, and user-defined locomotion control signals. We also curate a comprehensive dataset featuring a wide range of locomotion types and actor traits to enable the training of this characteristic-aware controller. Unlike prior work, MotionPersona is the first method capable of generating motion that faithfully reflects user-specified characteristics (e.g., an elderly person's shuffling gait) while responding in real time to dynamic control inputs. Additionally, we introduce a few-shot characterization technique as a complementary conditioning mechanism, enabling customization via short motion clips when language prompts fall short. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that MotionPersona outperforms existing methods in characteristics-aware locomotion control, achieving superior motion quality and diversity. Results, code, and demo can be found at: https://motionpersona25.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00173v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyi Shi, Wei Liu, Jidong Mei, Wangpok Tse, Rui Chen, Xuelin Chen, Taku Komura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power-Linear Polar Directional Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel method for directional-field design on meshes, enabling users to specify singularities at any location on a mesh. Our method uses a piecewise power-linear representation for phase and scale, offering precise control over field topology. The resulting fields are smooth and accommodate any singularity index and field symmetry. With this representation, we mitigate the artifacts caused by coarse or uneven meshes. We showcase our approach on meshes with diverse topologies and triangle qualities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00222v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiabao Brad Wang, Amir Vaxman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pro3D-Editor : A Progressive-Views Perspective for Consistent and Precise 3D Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Text-guided 3D editing aims to precisely edit semantically relevant local 3D regions, which has significant potential for various practical applications ranging from 3D games to film production. Existing methods typically follow a view-indiscriminate paradigm: editing 2D views indiscriminately and projecting them back into 3D space. However, they overlook the different cross-view interdependencies, resulting in inconsistent multi-view editing. In this study, we argue that ideal consistent 3D editing can be achieved through a \textit{progressive-views paradigm}, which propagates editing semantics from the editing-salient view to other editing-sparse views. Specifically, we propose \textit{Pro3D-Editor}, a novel framework, which mainly includes Primary-view Sampler, Key-view Render, and Full-view Refiner. Primary-view Sampler dynamically samples and edits the most editing-salient view as the primary view. Key-view Render accurately propagates editing semantics from the primary view to other key views through its Mixture-of-View-Experts Low-Rank Adaption (MoVE-LoRA). Full-view Refiner edits and refines the 3D object based on the edited multi-views. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method outperforms existing methods in editing accuracy and spatial consistency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00512v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Zheng, Mengqi Huang, Nan Chen, Zhendong Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Path Guiding with Distribution Factorization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a neural path guiding method to aid with Monte Carlo (MC) integration in rendering. Existing neural methods utilize distribution representations that are either fast or expressive, but not both. We propose a simple, but effective, representation that is sufficiently expressive and reasonably fast. Specifically, we break down the 2D distribution over the directional domain into two 1D probability distribution functions (PDF). We propose to model each 1D PDF using a neural network that estimates the distribution at a set of discrete coordinates. The PDF at an arbitrary location can then be evaluated and sampled through interpolation. To train the network, we maximize the similarity of the learned and target distributions. To reduce the variance of the gradient during optimizations and estimate the normalization factor, we propose to cache the incoming radiance using an additional network. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that our approach is better than the existing methods, particularly in challenging scenes with complex light transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00839v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Figueiredo, Qihao He, Nima Khademi Kalantari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybridizing Expressive Rendering: Stroke-Based Rendering with Classic and Neural Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-Photorealistic Rendering (NPR) has long been used to create artistic visualizations that prioritize style over realism, enabling the depiction of a wide range of aesthetic effects, from hand-drawn sketches to painterly renderings. While classical NPR methods, such as edge detection, toon shading, and geometric abstraction, have been well-established in both research and practice, with a particular focus on stroke-based rendering, the recent rise of deep learning represents a paradigm shift. We analyze the similarities and differences between classical and neural network based NPR techniques, focusing on stroke-based rendering (SBR), highlighting their strengths and limitations. We discuss trade offs in quality and artistic control between these paradigms, propose a framework where these approaches can be combined for new possibilities in expressive rendering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00870v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kapil Dev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LensCraft: Your Professional Virtual Cinematographer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Digital creators, from indie filmmakers to animation studios, face a persistent bottleneck: translating their creative vision into precise camera movements. Despite significant progress in computer vision and artificial intelligence, current automated filming systems struggle with a fundamental trade-off between mechanical execution and creative intent. Crucially, almost all previous works simplify the subject to a single point-ignoring its orientation and true volume-severely limiting spatial awareness during filming. LensCraft solves this problem by mimicking the expertise of a professional cinematographer, using a data-driven approach that combines cinematographic principles with the flexibility to adapt to dynamic scenes in real time. Our solution combines a specialized simulation framework for generating high-fidelity training data with an advanced neural model that is faithful to the script while being aware of the volume and dynamic behavior of the subject. Additionally, our approach allows for flexible control via various input modalities, including text prompts, subject trajectory and volume, key points, or a full camera trajectory, offering creators a versatile tool to guide camera movements in line with their vision. Leveraging a lightweight real time architecture, LensCraft achieves markedly lower computational complexity and faster inference while maintaining high output quality. Extensive evaluation across static and dynamic scenarios reveals unprecedented accuracy and coherence, setting a new benchmark for intelligent camera systems compared to state-of-the-art models. Extended results, the complete dataset, simulation environment, trained model weights, and source code are publicly accessible on LensCraft Webpage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00988v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahra Dehghanian, Morteza Abolghasemi, Hossein Azizinaghsh, Amir Vahedi, Hamid Beigy, Hamid R. Rabiee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TRiMM: Transformer-Based Rich Motion Matching for Real-Time multi-modal Interaction in Digital Humans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large Language Model (LLM)-driven digital humans have sparked a series of recent studies on co-speech gesture generation systems. However, existing approaches struggle with real-time synthesis and long-text comprehension. This paper introduces Transformer-Based Rich Motion Matching (TRiMM), a novel multi-modal framework for real-time 3D gesture generation. Our method incorporates three modules: 1) a cross-modal attention mechanism to achieve precise temporal alignment between speech and gestures; 2) a long-context autoregressive model with a sliding window mechanism for effective sequence modeling; 3) a large-scale gesture matching system that constructs an atomic action library and enables real-time retrieval. Additionally, we develop a lightweight pipeline implemented in the Unreal Engine for experimentation. Our approach achieves real-time inference at 120 fps and maintains a per-sentence latency of 0.15 seconds on consumer-grade GPUs (Geforce RTX3060). Extensive subjective and objective evaluations on the ZEGGS, and BEAT datasets demonstrate that our model outperforms current state-of-the-art methods. TRiMM enhances the speed of co-speech gesture generation while ensuring gesture quality, enabling LLM-driven digital humans to respond to speech in real time and synthesize corresponding gestures. Our code is available at https://github.com/teroon/TRiMM-Transformer-Based-Rich-Motion-Matching</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01077v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueqian Guo, Tianzhao Li, Xin Lyu, Jiehaolin Chen, Zhaohan Wang, Sirui Xiao, Yurun Chen, Yezi He, Helin Li, Fan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PromptVFX: Text-Driven Fields for Open-World 3D Gaussian Animation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Visual effects (VFX) are key to immersion in modern films, games, and AR/VR. Creating 3D effects requires specialized expertise and training in 3D animation software and can be time consuming. Generative solutions typically rely on computationally intense methods such as diffusion models which can be slow at 4D inference. We reformulate 3D animation as a field prediction task and introduce a text-driven framework that infers a time-varying 4D flow field acting on 3D Gaussians. By leveraging large language models (LLMs) and vision-language models (VLMs) for function generation, our approach interprets arbitrary prompts (e.g., "make the vase glow orange, then explode") and instantly updates color, opacity, and positions of 3D Gaussians in real time. This design avoids overheads such as mesh extraction, manual or physics-based simulations and allows both novice and expert users to animate volumetric scenes with minimal effort on a consumer device even in a web browser. Experimental results show that simple textual instructions suffice to generate compelling time-varying VFX, reducing the manual effort typically required for rigging or advanced modeling. We thus present a fast and accessible pathway to language-driven 3D content creation that can pave the way to democratize VFX further.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01091v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mert Kiray, Paul Uhlenbruck, Nassir Navab, Benjamin Busam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WishGI: Lightweight Static Global Illumination Baking via Spherical Harmonics Fitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Global illumination combines direct and indirect lighting to create realistic lighting effects, bringing virtual scenes closer to reality. Static global illumination is a crucial component of virtual scene rendering, leveraging precomputation and baking techniques to significantly reduce runtime computational costs. Unfortunately, many existing works prioritize visual quality by relying on extensive texture storage and massive pixel-level texture sampling, leading to large performance overhead. In this paper, we introduce an illumination reconstruction method that effectively reduces sampling in fragment shader and avoids additional render passes, making it well-suited for low-end platforms. To achieve high-quality global illumination with reduced memory usage, we adopt a spherical harmonics fitting approach for baking effective illumination information and propose an inverse probe distribution method that generates unique probe associations for each mesh. This association, which can be generated offline in the local space, ensures consistent lighting quality across all instances of the same mesh. As a consequence, our method delivers highly competitive lighting effects while using only approximately 5% of the memory required by mainstream industry techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01288v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junke Zhu, Zehan Wu, Qixing Zhang, Cheng Liao, Zhangjin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Silence is Golden: Leveraging Adversarial Examples to Nullify Audio Control in LDM-based Talking-Head Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01591v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advances in talking-head animation based on Latent Diffusion Models (LDM) enable the creation of highly realistic, synchronized videos. These fabricated videos are indistinguishable from real ones, increasing the risk of potential misuse for scams, political manipulation, and misinformation. Hence, addressing these ethical concerns has become a pressing issue in AI security. Recent proactive defense studies focused on countering LDM-based models by adding perturbations to portraits. However, these methods are ineffective at protecting reference portraits from advanced image-to-video animation. The limitations are twofold: 1) they fail to prevent images from being manipulated by audio signals, and 2) diffusion-based purification techniques can effectively eliminate protective perturbations. To address these challenges, we propose Silencer, a two-stage method designed to proactively protect the privacy of portraits. First, a nullifying loss is proposed to ignore audio control in talking-head generation. Second, we apply anti-purification loss in LDM to optimize the inverted latent feature to generate robust perturbations. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of Silencer in proactively protecting portrait privacy. We hope this work will raise awareness among the AI security community regarding critical ethical issues related to talking-head generation techniques. Code: https://github.com/yuangan/Silencer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01591v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Gan, Jiaxu Miao, Yunze Wang, Yi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image Generation from Contextually-Contradictory Prompts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Text-to-image diffusion models excel at generating high-quality, diverse images from natural language prompts. However, they often fail to produce semantically accurate results when the prompt contains concept combinations that contradict their learned priors. We define this failure mode as contextual contradiction, where one concept implicitly negates another due to entangled associations learned during training. To address this, we propose a stage-aware prompt decomposition framework that guides the denoising process using a sequence of proxy prompts. Each proxy prompt is constructed to match the semantic content expected to emerge at a specific stage of denoising, while ensuring contextual coherence. To construct these proxy prompts, we leverage a large language model (LLM) to analyze the target prompt, identify contradictions, and generate alternative expressions that preserve the original intent while resolving contextual conflicts. By aligning prompt information with the denoising progression, our method enables fine-grained semantic control and accurate image generation in the presence of contextual contradictions. Experiments across a variety of challenging prompts show substantial improvements in alignment to the textual prompt.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01929v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saar Huberman, Or Patashnik, Omer Dahary, Ron Mokady, Daniel Cohen-Or</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DragPoser: Motion Reconstruction from Variable Sparse Tracking Signals via Latent Space Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14567v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-quality motion reconstruction that follows the user's movements can be achieved by high-end mocap systems with many sensors. However, obtaining such animation quality with fewer input devices is gaining popularity as it brings mocap closer to the general public. The main challenges include the loss of end-effector accuracy in learning-based approaches, or the lack of naturalness and smoothness in IK-based solutions. In addition, such systems are often finely tuned to a specific number of trackers and are highly sensitive to missing data e.g., in scenarios where a sensor is occluded or malfunctions. In response to these challenges, we introduce DragPoser, a novel deep-learning-based motion reconstruction system that accurately represents hard and dynamic on-the-fly constraints, attaining real-time high end-effectors position accuracy. This is achieved through a pose optimization process within a structured latent space. Our system requires only one-time training on a large human motion dataset, and then constraints can be dynamically defined as losses, while the pose is iteratively refined by computing the gradients of these losses within the latent space. To further enhance our approach, we incorporate a Temporal Predictor network, which employs a Transformer architecture to directly encode temporality within the latent space. This network ensures the pose optimization is confined to the manifold of valid poses and also leverages past pose data to predict temporally coherent poses. Results demonstrate that DragPoser surpasses both IK-based and the latest data-driven methods in achieving precise end-effector positioning, while it produces natural poses and temporally coherent motion. In addition, our system showcases robustness against on-the-fly constraint modifications, and exhibits exceptional adaptability to various input configurations and changes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14567v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1111/cgf.70026</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jose Luis Ponton, Eduard Pujol, Andreas Aristidou, Carlos Andujar, Nuria Pelechano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Event-driven 3D Reconstruction: Development under Different Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19753v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Event cameras have gained increasing attention for 3D reconstruction due to their high temporal resolution, low latency, and high dynamic range. They capture per-pixel brightness changes asynchronously, allowing accurate reconstruction under fast motion and challenging lighting conditions. In this survey, we provide a comprehensive review of event-driven 3D reconstruction methods, including stereo, monocular, and multimodal systems. We further categorize recent developments based on geometric, learning-based, and hybrid approaches. Emerging trends, such as neural radiance fields and 3D Gaussian splatting with event data, are also covered. The related works are structured chronologically to illustrate the innovations and progression within the field. To support future research, we also highlight key research gaps and future research directions in dataset, experiment, evaluation, event representation, etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19753v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuanzhi Xu, Haoxian Zhou, Haodong Chen, Vera Chung, Qiang Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ART-DECO: Arbitrary Text Guidance for 3D Detailizer Construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20431v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a 3D detailizer, a neural model which can instantaneously (in &lt;1s) transform a coarse 3D shape proxy into a high-quality asset with detailed geometry and texture as guided by an input text prompt. Our model is trained using the text prompt, which defines the shape class and characterizes the appearance and fine-grained style of the generated details. The coarse 3D proxy, which can be easily varied and adjusted (e.g., via user editing), provides structure control over the final shape. Importantly, our detailizer is not optimized for a single shape; it is the result of distilling a generative model, so that it can be reused, without retraining, to generate any number of shapes, with varied structures, whose local details all share a consistent style and appearance. Our detailizer training utilizes a pretrained multi-view image diffusion model, with text conditioning, to distill the foundational knowledge therein into our detailizer via Score Distillation Sampling (SDS). To improve SDS and enable our detailizer architecture to learn generalizable features over complex structures, we train our model in two training stages to generate shapes with increasing structural complexity. Through extensive experiments, we show that our method generates shapes of superior quality and details compared to existing text-to-3D models under varied structure control. Our detailizer can refine a coarse shape in less than a second, making it possible to interactively author and adjust 3D shapes. Furthermore, the user-imposed structure control can lead to creative, and hence out-of-distribution, 3D asset generations that are beyond the current capabilities of leading text-to-3D generative models. We demonstrate an interactive 3D modeling workflow our method enables, and its strong generalizability over styles, structures, and object categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20431v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qimin Chen, Yuezhi Yang, Yifang Wang, Vladimir G. Kim, Siddhartha Chaudhuri, Hao Zhang, Zhiqin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating by Understanding: Neural Visual Generation with Logical Symbol Groundings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17451v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Making neural visual generative models controllable by logical reasoning systems is promising for improving faithfulness, transparency, and generalizability. We propose the Abductive visual Generation (AbdGen) approach to build such logic-integrated models. A vector-quantized symbol grounding mechanism and the corresponding disentanglement training method are introduced to enhance the controllability of logical symbols over generation. Furthermore, we propose two logical abduction methods to make our approach require few labeled training data and support the induction of latent logical generative rules from data. We experimentally show that our approach can be utilized to integrate various neural generative models with logical reasoning systems, by both learning from scratch or utilizing pre-trained models directly. The code is released at https://github.com/future-item/AbdGen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17451v3</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Peng, Zijie Zha, Yu Jin, Zhexu Luo, Wang-Zhou Dai, Zhong Ren, Yao-Xiang Ding, Kun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate Differential Operators for Hybrid Neural Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05984v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural fields have become widely used in various fields, from shape representation to neural rendering, and for solving partial differential equations (PDEs). With the advent of hybrid neural field representations like Instant NGP that leverage small MLPs and explicit representations, these models train quickly and can fit large scenes. Yet in many applications like rendering and simulation, hybrid neural fields can cause noticeable and unreasonable artifacts. This is because they do not yield accurate spatial derivatives needed for these downstream applications. In this work, we propose two ways to circumvent these challenges. Our first approach is a post hoc operator that uses local polynomial fitting to obtain more accurate derivatives from pre-trained hybrid neural fields. Additionally, we also propose a self-supervised fine-tuning approach that refines the hybrid neural field to yield accurate derivatives directly while preserving the initial signal. We show applications of our method to rendering, collision simulation, and solving PDEs. We observe that using our approach yields more accurate derivatives, reducing artifacts and leading to more accurate simulations in downstream applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05984v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Chetan, Guandao Yang, Zichen Wang, Steve Marschner, Bharath Hariharan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flex3D: Feed-Forward 3D Generation with Flexible Reconstruction Model and Input View Curation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00890v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Generating high-quality 3D content from text, single images, or sparse view images remains a challenging task with broad applications. Existing methods typically employ multi-view diffusion models to synthesize multi-view images, followed by a feed-forward process for 3D reconstruction. However, these approaches are often constrained by a small and fixed number of input views, limiting their ability to capture diverse viewpoints and, even worse, leading to suboptimal generation results if the synthesized views are of poor quality. To address these limitations, we propose Flex3D, a novel two-stage framework capable of leveraging an arbitrary number of high-quality input views. The first stage consists of a candidate view generation and curation pipeline. We employ a fine-tuned multi-view image diffusion model and a video diffusion model to generate a pool of candidate views, enabling a rich representation of the target 3D object. Subsequently, a view selection pipeline filters these views based on quality and consistency, ensuring that only the high-quality and reliable views are used for reconstruction. In the second stage, the curated views are fed into a Flexible Reconstruction Model (FlexRM), built upon a transformer architecture that can effectively process an arbitrary number of inputs. FlemRM directly outputs 3D Gaussian points leveraging a tri-plane representation, enabling efficient and detailed 3D generation. Through extensive exploration of design and training strategies, we optimize FlexRM to achieve superior performance in both reconstruction and generation tasks. Our results demonstrate that Flex3D achieves state-of-the-art performance, with a user study winning rate of over 92% in 3D generation tasks when compared to several of the latest feed-forward 3D generative models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00890v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junlin Han, Jianyuan Wang, Andrea Vedaldi, Philip Torr, Filippos Kokkinos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLZero: Direct Policy Inference from Language Without In-Domain Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05718v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The reward hypothesis states that all goals and purposes can be understood as the maximization of a received scalar reward signal. However, in practice, defining such a reward signal is notoriously difficult, as humans are often unable to predict the optimal behavior corresponding to a reward function. Natural language offers an intuitive alternative for instructing reinforcement learning (RL) agents, yet previous language-conditioned approaches either require costly supervision or test-time training given a language instruction. In this work, we present a new approach that uses a pretrained RL agent trained using only unlabeled, offline interactions--without task-specific supervision or labeled trajectories--to get zero-shot test-time policy inference from arbitrary natural language instructions. We introduce a framework comprising three steps: imagine, project, and imitate. First, the agent imagines a sequence of observations corresponding to the provided language description using video generative models. Next, these imagined observations are projected into the target environment domain. Finally, an agent pretrained in the target environment with unsupervised RL instantly imitates the projected observation sequence through a closed-form solution. To the best of our knowledge, our method, RLZero, is the first approach to show direct language-to-behavior generation abilities on a variety of tasks and environments without any in-domain supervision. We further show that components of RLZero can be used to generate policies zero-shot from cross-embodied videos, such as those available on YouTube, even for complex embodiments like humanoids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05718v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harshit Sikchi, Siddhant Agarwal, Pranaya Jajoo, Samyak Parajuli, Caleb Chuck, Max Rudolph, Peter Stone, Amy Zhang, Scott Niekum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllable Satellite-to-Street-View Synthesis with Precise Pose Alignment and Zero-Shot Environmental Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03498v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Generating street-view images from satellite imagery is a challenging task, particularly in maintaining accurate pose alignment and incorporating diverse environmental conditions. While diffusion models have shown promise in generative tasks, their ability to maintain strict pose alignment throughout the diffusion process is limited. In this paper, we propose a novel Iterative Homography Adjustment (IHA) scheme applied during the denoising process, which effectively addresses pose misalignment and ensures spatial consistency in the generated street-view images. Additionally, currently, available datasets for satellite-to-street-view generation are limited in their diversity of illumination and weather conditions, thereby restricting the generalizability of the generated outputs. To mitigate this, we introduce a text-guided illumination and weather-controlled sampling strategy that enables fine-grained control over the environmental factors. Extensive quantitative and qualitative evaluations demonstrate that our approach significantly improves pose accuracy and enhances the diversity and realism of generated street-view images, setting a new benchmark for satellite-to-street-view generation tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03498v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xianghui Ze, Zhenbo Song, Qiwei Wang, Jianfeng Lu, Yujiao Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LayerCraft: Enhancing Text-to-Image Generation with CoT Reasoning and Layered Object Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00010v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Text-to-image (T2I) generation has made remarkable progress, yet existing systems still lack intuitive control over spatial composition, object consistency, and multi-step editing. We present $\textbf{LayerCraft}$, a modular framework that uses large language models (LLMs) as autonomous agents to orchestrate structured, layered image generation and editing. LayerCraft supports two key capabilities: (1) $\textit{structured generation}$ from simple prompts via chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning, enabling it to decompose scenes, reason about object placement, and guide composition in a controllable, interpretable manner; and (2) $\textit{layered object integration}$, allowing users to insert and customize objects -- such as characters or props -- across diverse images or scenes while preserving identity, context, and style. The system comprises a coordinator agent, the $\textbf{ChainArchitect}$ for CoT-driven layout planning, and the $\textbf{Object Integration Network (OIN)}$ for seamless image editing using off-the-shelf T2I models without retraining. Through applications like batch collage editing and narrative scene generation, LayerCraft empowers non-experts to iteratively design, customize, and refine visual content with minimal manual effort. Code will be released at https://github.com/PeterYYZhang/LayerCraft.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00010v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuyao Zhang, Jinghao Li, Yu-Wing Tai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
