<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR</link>
    <description>cs.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 02:14:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Generating real-time detailed ground visualisations from sparse aerial point clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Building realistic wide scale outdoor 3D content with sufficient visual quality to observe at walking eye level or from driven vehicles is often carried out by large teams of artists skilled in modelling, texturing, material shading and lighting, which typically leads to both prohibitive costs and reduced accuracy honoring the variety of real world ground truth landscapes. In our proposed method, we define a process to automatically amplify real-world scanned data and render real-time in animated 3D to explore at close range with high quality for training, simulation, video game and visualisation applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18664v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Murray, Eddie Waite, Caleb Ross, Scarlet Mitchell, Alexander Bradley, Joanna Jamrozy, Kenny Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Procedural city modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a method to procedurally generate a familiar yet complex human artifact: the city. We are not trying to reproduce existing cities, but to generate artificial cities that are convincing and plausible by capturing developmental behavior. In addition, our results are meant to build upon themselves, such that they ought to look compelling at any point along the transition from village to metropolis. Our approach largely focuses upon land usage and building distribution for creating realistic city environments, whereas previous attempts at city modeling have mainly focused on populating road networks. Finally, we want our model to be self automated to the point that the only necessary input is a terrain description, but other high-level and low-level parameters can be specified to support artistic contributions. With the aid of agent based simulation we are generating a system of agents and behaviors that interact with one another through their effects upon a simulated environment. Our philosophy is that as each agent follows a simple behavioral rule set, a more complex behavior will tend to emerge out of the interactions between the agents and their differing rule sets. By confining our model to a set of simple rules for each class of agents, we hope to make our model extendible not only in regard to the types of structures that are produced, but also in describing the social and cultural influences prevalent in all cities</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18899v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>1st Midwestern Graphics Conference 2003</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Lechner, Ben Watson, Uri Wilensky, Martin Felsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TiVy: Time Series Visual Summary for Scalable Visualization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Visualizing multiple time series presents fundamental tradeoffs between scalability and visual clarity. Time series capture the behavior of many large-scale real-world processes, from stock market trends to urban activities. Users often gain insights by visualizing them as line charts, juxtaposing or superposing multiple time series to compare them and identify trends and patterns. However, existing representations struggle with scalability: when covering long time spans, leading to visual clutter from too many small multiples or overlapping lines. We propose TiVy, a new algorithm that summarizes time series using sequential patterns. It transforms the series into a set of symbolic sequences based on subsequence visual similarity using Dynamic Time Warping (DTW), then constructs a disjoint grouping of similar subsequences based on the frequent sequential patterns. The grouping result, a visual summary of time series, provides uncluttered superposition with fewer small multiples. Unlike common clustering techniques, TiVy extracts similar subsequences (of varying lengths) aligned in time. We also present an interactive time series visualization that renders large-scale time series in real-time. Our experimental evaluation shows that our algorithm (1) extracts clear and accurate patterns when visualizing time series data, (2) achieves a significant speed-up (1000X) compared to a straightforward DTW clustering. We also demonstrate the efficiency of our approach to explore hidden structures in massive time series data in two usage scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18972v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gromit Yeuk-Yin Chan, Luis Gustavo Nonato, Themis Palpanas, Cl\'audio T. Silva, Juliana Freire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion Synthesis with Sparse and Flexible Keyjoint Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15557v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Creating expressive character animations is labor-intensive, requiring intricate manual adjustment of animators across space and time. Previous works on controllable motion generation often rely on a predefined set of dense spatio-temporal specifications (e.g., dense pelvis trajectories with exact per-frame timing), limiting practicality for animators. To process high-level intent and intuitive control in diverse scenarios, we propose a practical controllable motions synthesis framework that respects sparse and flexible keyjoint signals. Our approach employs a decomposed diffusion-based motion synthesis framework that first synthesizes keyjoint movements from sparse input control signals and then synthesizes full-body motion based on the completed keyjoint trajectories. The low-dimensional keyjoint movements can easily adapt to various control signal types, such as end-effector position for diverse goal-driven motion synthesis, or incorporate functional constraints on a subset of keyjoints. Additionally, we introduce a time-agnostic control formulation, eliminating the need for frame-specific timing annotations and enhancing control flexibility. Then, the shared second stage can synthesize a natural whole-body motion that precisely satisfies the task requirement from dense keyjoint movements. We demonstrate the effectiveness of sparse and flexible keyjoint control through comprehensive experiments on diverse datasets and scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15557v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Inwoo Hwang, Jinseok Bae, Donggeun Lim, Young Min Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
