<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR</link>
    <description>cs.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 05:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Stroke Patches: Customizable Artistic Image Styling Using Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel, regression-based method for artistically styling images. Unlike recent neural style transfer or diffusion-based approaches, our method allows for explicit control over the stroke composition and level of detail in the rendered image through the use of an extensible set of stroke patches. The stroke patch sets are procedurally generated by small programs that control the shape, size, orientation, density, color, and noise level of the strokes in the individual patches. Once trained on a set of stroke patches, a U-Net based regression model can render any input image in a variety of distinct, evocative and customizable styles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03114v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>39th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2025) Creative AI Track</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ian Jaffray, John Bronskill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Vibe-Check Protocol: Quantifying Cognitive Offloading in AI Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The integration of Large Language Models (LLMs) into software engineering education has driven the emergence of ``Vibe Coding,'' a paradigm where developers articulate high-level intent through natural language and delegate implementation to AI agents. While proponents argue this approach modernizes pedagogy by emphasizing conceptual design over syntactic memorization, accumulating empirical evidence raises concerns regarding skill retention and deep conceptual understanding. This paper proposes a theoretical framework to investigate the research question: \textit{Is Vibe Coding a better way to learn software engineering?} We posit a divergence in student outcomes between those leveraging AI for acceleration versus those using it for cognitive offloading. To evaluate these educational trade-offs, we propose the \textbf{Vibe-Check Protocol (VCP)}, a systematic benchmarking framework incorporating three quantitative metrics: the \textit{Cold Start Refactor} ($M_{CSR}$) for modeling skill decay; \textit{Hallucination Trap Detection} ($M_{HT}$) based on signal detection theory to evaluate error identification; and the \textit{Explainability Gap} ($E_{gap}$) for quantifying the divergence between code complexity and conceptual comprehension. Through controlled comparisons, VCP aims to provide a quantitative basis for educators to determine the optimal pedagogical boundary: identifying contexts where Vibe Coding fosters genuine mastery and contexts where it introduces hidden technical debt and superficial competence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02410v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aizierjiang Aiersilan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The perceptual gap between video see-through displays and natural human vision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Video see-through (VST) technology aims to seamlessly blend virtual and physical worlds by reconstructing reality through cameras. While manufacturers promise perceptual fidelity, it remains unclear how close these systems are to replicating natural human vision across varying environmental conditions. In this work, we quantify the perceptual gap between the human eye and different popular VST headsets (Apple Vision Pro, Meta Quest 3, Quest Pro) using psychophysical measures of visual acuity, contrast sensitivity, and color vision. We show that despite hardware advancements, all tested VST systems fail to match the dynamic range and adaptability of the naked eye. While high-end devices approach human performance in ideal lighting, they exhibit significant degradation in low-light conditions, particularly in contrast sensitivity and acuity. Our results map the physiological limitations of digital reality reconstruction, establishing a specific perceptual gap that defines the roadmap for achieving indistinguishable VST experiences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02805v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialin Wang, Songming Ping, Kemu Xu, Yue Li, Hai-Ning Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolution deficits drive simulator sickness and compromise reading performance in virtual environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02829v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Extended reality (XR) is evolving into a general-purpose computing platform, yet its adoption for productivity is hindered by visual fatigue and simulator sickness. While these symptoms are often attributed to latency or motion conflicts, the precise impact of textual clarity on physiological comfort remains undefined. Here we show that sub-optimal effective resolution, the clarity that reaches the eye after the full display-optics-rendering pipeline, is a primary driver of simulator sickness during reading tasks in both virtual reality and video see-through environments. By systematically manipulating end-to-end effective resolution on a unified logMAR scale, we measured reading psychophysics and sickness symptoms in a controlled within-subjects study. We find that reading performance and user comfort degrade exponentially as resolution drops below 0 logMAR (normal visual acuity). Notably, our results reveal 0 logMAR as a key physiological tipping point: resolutions better than this threshold yield naked-eye-level performance with minimal sickness, whereas poorer resolutions trigger rapid, non-linear increases in nausea and oculomotor strain. These findings suggest that the cognitive and perceptual effort required to resolve blurry text directly compromises user comfort, establishing human-eye resolution as a critical baseline for the design of future ergonomic XR systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02829v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialin Wang, Xinru Cheng, Boyong Hou, Hai-Ning Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
