<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Which shapes can appear in a Curve Shortening Flow Singularity?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study possible tangles that can occur in singularities of solutions to plane Curve Shortening Flow. We exhibit solutions in which more complicated tangles with more than one self-intersection disappear into a singular point. It seems that there are many examples of this kind and that a complete classification presents a problem similar to the problem of classifying all knots in $\mathbb R^3$. As a particular example, we introduce the so-called $n$-loop curves, which generalize Matt Grayson's Figure-Eight curve, and we conjecture a generalization of the Coiculescu-Schwarz asymptotic bow-tie result, namely, a vanishing $n$-loop, when rescaled anisotropically to fit a square bounding box, converges to a "squeezed bow-tie," i.e. the curve $\{(x, y) : |x|\leq 1, y=\pm x^{n-1}\}\cup\{(\pm 1, y) : |y|\leq 1\}$. As evidence in support of the conjecture, we provide a formal asymptotic analysis on one hand, and a numerical simulation for the cases $n=3$ and $n=4$ on the other.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09876v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sigurd Angenent, Evan Patrick Davis, Ellie DeCleene, Paige Ellingson, Ziheng Feng, Edgar Gevorgyan, Aris Lemmenes, Alex Moon, Tyler Joseph Tommasi, Yamin Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\partial\bar{\partial}$-Lemma and $p$-K\"ahler structures on families of solvmanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10126v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide families of compact $(n + 1)$-dimensional complex non K\"ahler manifolds satisfying the $\partial\bar{\partial}$-Lemma, with holomoprhically trivial canonical bundle, carrying a balanced metric and with no $p$-K\"ahler structures. Such a construction extends to the completely solvable case in any dimension Nakamura's construction of low-dimensional holomorphically parallelizable solvmanifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10126v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Cattaneo, Adriano Tomassini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gap results for biharmonic submanifolds in spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10155v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we determine a larger gap of the mean curvature for a class of proper biharmonic submanifolds with parallel mean curvature vector field in Euclidean spheres. When the bounds of the gap are reached, we obtain splitting results of the submanifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10155v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Andronic, Simona Nistor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete integrability of subriemannian geodesic flows on $\mathbb{S}^7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10157v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Four subriemannian (SR) structures over the Euclidean sphere $\mathbb{S}^7$ are considered in accordance to the previous literature. The defining bracket generating distribution is chosen as the horizontal space in the Hopf fibration, the quaternionic Hopf fibration or spanned by a suitable number of canonical vector fields. In all cases the induced SR geodesic flow on $T^*\mathbb{S}^7$ is studied. Adapting a method by A. Thimm, a maximal set of functionally independent and Poisson commuting first integrals are constructed, including the corresponding SR Hamiltonian. As a result, the complete integrability in the sense of Liouville is proved for the SR geodesic flow. It is observed that these first integrals arise as the symbols of commuting second order differential operators one of them being a (not necessarily intrinsic) sublaplacian. On the way one explicitly derives the Lie algebras of all SR isometry groups intersected with $O(8)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10157v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfram Bauer, Abdellah Laaroussi, Daisuke Tarama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-Lagrangian structures and the space of rays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper focuses on local curvature invariants associated with bi-Lagrangian structures. We establish several geometric conditions that determine when the canonical connection is flat, building on our previous findings regarding divergence-free webs. Addressing questions raised by Tabachnikov, we provide complete solutions to two problems: the existence of flat bi-Lagrangian structures within the space of rays induced by a pair of hypersurfaces, and the existence of flat bi-Lagrangian structures induced by tangents to Lagrangian curves in the symplectic plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10345v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech Domitrz, Marcin Zubilewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimizing movements for forced anisotropic curvature flow of droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09902v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study forced anisotropic curvature flow of droplets on an inhomogeneous horizontal hyperplane. As in [Bellettini, Kholmatov: J. Math. Pures Appl. (2018)] we establish the existence of smooth flow, starting from a regular droplet and satisfying the prescribed anisotropic Young's law, and also the existence of a $1/2$-H\"older continuous in time minimizing movement solution starting from a set of finite perimeter. Furthermore, we investigate various properties of minimizing movements, including comparison principles, uniform boundedness and the consistency with the smooth flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09902v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shokhrukh Yu. Kholmatov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convex co-compact hyperbolic manifolds are determined by their pleating lamination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10090v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Convex co-compact 3-dimensional hyperbolic manifolds are uniquely determined by the pleating measured lamination on the boundary of their convex core.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10090v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Dular, Jean-Marc Schlenker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of singular rotationally symmetric gradient Ricci solitons in higher dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.13685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2107.13685v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By using fixed point argument we give a proof for the existence of singular rotationally symmetric steady and expanding gradient Ricci solitons in higher dimensions with metric $g=\frac{da^2}{h(a^2)}+a^2g_{S^n}$ for some function $h$ where $g_{S^n}$ is the standard metric on the unit sphere $S^n$ in $\mathbb{R}^n$ for any $n\ge 2$. More precisely for any $\lambda\ge 0$ and $c_0&gt;0$, we prove that there exist infinitely many solutions $h\in C^2((0,\infty);\mathbb{R}^+)$ for the equation $2r^2h(r)h_{rr}(r)=(n-1)h(r)(h(r)-1)+rh_r(r)(rh_r(r)-\lambda r-(n-1))$, $h(r)&gt;0$, in $(0,\infty)$ satisfying $\underset{\substack{r\to 0}}{\lim}\,r^{\sqrt{n}-1}h(r)=c_0$ and prove the higher order asymptotic behaviour of the global singular solutions near the origin. We also find conditions for the existence of unique global singular solution of such equation in terms of its asymptotic behaviour near the origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2107.13685v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kin Ming Hui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified synthetic Ricci curvature lower bounds for Riemannian and sub-Riemannian structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.07762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.07762v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in the theory of metric measures spaces on the one hand, and of sub-Riemannian ones on the other hand, suggest the possibility of a "great unification" of Riemannian and sub-Riemannian geometries in a comprehensive framework of synthetic Ricci curvature lower bounds. With the aim of achieving such a unification program, in this paper we initiate the study of gauge metric measure spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.07762v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Barilari, Andrea Mondino, Luca Rizzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature surfaces in generic conformally flat hypersurfaces arising from Poincar\'{e} metric -- Extension and Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.12128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.12128v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study generic conformally flat (analytic-)hypersurfaces in the Euclidean $4$-space $\mathbb{R}^4$. Such a local-hypersurface is obtained as an evolution of surfaces issuing from a certain surface in $\mathbb{R}^4$, and then, in consequence, the original surface is a (principal-)curvature surface of the hypersurface. The Poincar\'{e} metric ${\check g}_H$ of the upper half plane leads to a $6$-dimensional set of rational Riemannian metrics $g_0$ of $\mathbb{R}^2$: on a simply connected open set in the regular domain of $g_0$, a curvature surface $f^0$ with the metric $g_0$ is determined, which we denote by $(f^0,g_0)$. In this paper, we choose a suitable metric $g_0$ of $\mathbb{R}^2$ determined by ${\check g}_H$ to get nice curvature surfaces (but it also has degenerate and divergent points in $\mathbb{R}^2$), and clarify the structure of the curvature surfaces $(f^0,g_0)$: the curvature surfaces $(f^0,g_0)$ extend analytically to what kind of set in $\mathbb{R}^2$ beyond the regular set of $g_0$, and then the extended surface $(f^0,g_0)$ is defined on a certain open set of $\mathbb{R}^2$ and bounded in $\mathbb{R}^4$; for the extended surface $(f^0,g_0)$, we explicitly catch the set of degenerate points and the limits in $\mathbb{R}^4$ of both ends of every principal curvature line, and then the two limits of every line for one principal curvature are parallel small circles in a standard $2$-sphere $\mathbb{S}^2$. Then, every principal curvature line in the extended surface $(f^0,g_0)$ is expressed by a frame field of $\mathbb{R}^4$ induced on the surface from a hypersurface and it lies on a standard $2$-sphere $\mathbb{S}^2$ with line-dependent radius. We also provide a general method of constructing an approximation of such frame fields, and obtain the entire pictures of those lines including degenerate points of $(f^0,g_0)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.12128v4</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nozomu Matsuura, Yoshihiko Suyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure of non-classical Fuchsian Schottky groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07501v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we have initiated the non-classical structure on a type of generalized Schottky group (for instance Fuchsian Schottky groups) in the hyperbolic plane with boundary. A Schottky group is said to be non-classical if the curves used in the Schottky construction are Jordan curves. In fact, in this paper, we have provided a structure of the rank $2$ non-classical Fuchsian Schottky groups by using two suitable hyperbolic M\"obius transformations on the upper-half plane model. In particular, we have derived two non-trivial examples of non-classical Fuchsian Schottky groups in the upper-half plane with the circle at infinity as the boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07501v4</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Absos Ali Shaikh, Uddhab Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformally compact and higher conformal Yang-Mills equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.11458v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: On conformally compact manifolds we study Yang-Mills equations, their boundary conditions, formal asymptotics, and Dirichlet-to-Neumann maps. We find that smooth solutions with "magnetic" Dirichlet boundary data are obstructed by a conformally invariant, higher order boundary current. We study the asymptotics of the interior Yang-Mills energy functional and show that the obstructing current is the variation of the conformally invariant coefficient of the first log term in this expansion which is a higher derivative conformally invariant analog of the Yang-Mills energy. The invariant energy is the anomaly for the renormalized interior Yang-Mills functional and its variation gives higher conformal Yang-Mills equations. Global solutions to the magnetic boundary problem determine higher order "electric" Neumann data. This yields the Dirichlet-to-Neumann map. We also construct conformally invariant, higher transverse derivative boundary operators. Acting on interior connections, they give obstructions to solving the Yang-Mills boundary problem, determine the asymptotics of formal solutions, and yield conformally invariant tensors capturing the (non-local) electric Neumann data. We also characterize a renormalized Yang-Mills action functional that encodes global features analogously to the renormalized volume for Poincar\'e-Einstein structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.11458v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Rod Gover, Emanuele Latini, Andrew Waldron, Yongbing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantitative second order estimate for (weighted) $p$-harmonic functions in manifolds under curvature-dimension condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.07470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.07470v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We build up a quantitative second order Sobolev estimate of $ \ln w$ for positive $p$-harmonic functions $w$ in Riemannian manifolds under Ricci curvature bounded from blow and also for positive weighted $p$-harmonic functions $w$ in weighted manifolds under the Bakry-\'{E}mery curvature-dimension condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.07470v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayin Liu, Shijin Zhang, Yuan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature bound of Dyson Brownian Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00262v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that a differential structure associated with the infinite particle Dyson Brownian motion satisfies the Bakry-\'Emery nonnegative lower Ricci curvature bound $\mathsf{BE}(0, \infty)$. Various functional inequalities follow including a local spectral gap inequality, the Lipschitz Feller property, the dimension-free Harnack inequality and the evolutional variation inequality. As a consequence, the infinite Dyson Brownian motion is characterised as a gradient flow of the Boltzmann-Shannon entropy associated with $\mathsf{sine}_\beta$ point processes with respect to a certain Benamou-Brenier-like Wasserstein distance. At the end, we provide a sufficient condition for $\mathsf{BE}(K, \infty)$ beyond the Dyson model and apply it to the infinite particle model of the $\beta$-Riesz gas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00262v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
