<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 02:34:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Jacobi operator of some special minimal hypersurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08728v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we discuss stability and nondegeneracy properties of some special families of minimal hypersurfaces embedded in $\mathbb{R}^m\times \mathbb{R}^n$ with $m,n\geq 2$. These hypersurfaces are asymptotic at infinity to a fixed Lawson cone $C_{m,n}$. In the case $m+n\ge 8$, we show that such hypersurfaces are strictly stable and we provide a full classification of their bounded Jacobi fields, which in turn allows us to prove the non-degeneracy of such surfaces. In the case $m+n\le 7$, we prove that such hypersurfaces have infinite Morse index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08728v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Agudelo, Matteo Rizzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on Huisken's isoperimetric mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short note, we explain that Huisken's isoperimetric mass is always nonnegative for elementary reasons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08871v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey L. Jauregui, Dan A. Lee, Ryan Unger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computer Assisted Projective Rigidity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08405v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we provide a computer assisted proof that about two thousand surgeries far away from the ideal point in the hyperbolic Dehn filling space of the figure-eight knot complement are infinitesimally projectively rigid. We also prove that for projective deformations of the figure-eight knot complement sufficiently close to the complete hyperbolic structure, the induced map on the first cohomology of the longitude of the boundary torus is non-zero. This paper provides a complementary piece to the results of Heusener and Porti who showed that for each k in Z, there is a sufficiently large Nk for which every k/n-Dehn filling on the figure-eight knot complement for n larger than Nk is infinitesimally projectively rigid. In the process of the proof, we provide explicit representations of the figure-eight knot complement in PSO(3,1) which are rational in the real and imaginary parts of the shapes of the ideal tetrahedra used to glue the knot complement together.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08405v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Daly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obstructions to distinguished Riemannian metrics via Lorentzian geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.14701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.14701v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We approach the problem of finding obstructions to curvature distinguished Riemannian metrics by considering Lorentzian metrics to which they are dual in a suitable sense. Obstructions to the latter then yield obstructions to the former. This framework applies both locally and globally, including to compact manifolds, and is sensitive to various aspects of curvature. Here we apply it in two different ways. First, by embedding a Riemannian manifold into a Lorentzian one and utilizing Penrose's "plane wave limit," we find necessary local conditions, in terms of the Hessian of just one function, for large classes of Riemannian metrics to contain within them those that have parallel Ricci tensor, or are Ricci-flat, or are locally symmetric. Second, by considering Riemannian metrics dual to constant curvature Lorentzian metrics via a type of Wick rotation, we are able to rule out the existence of a family of compact Riemannian manifolds (in all dimensions) that deviate from constant curvature in a precise sense.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.14701v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Theor. Math. Phys., vol. 27, no. 7 (2023), 2219-2259</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Amir Babak Aazami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immortal solutions of the K\"ahler-Ricci flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04444v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We survey some recent developments on solutions of the K\"ahler-Ricci flow on compact K\"ahler manifolds which exist for all positive times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04444v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentino Tosatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypersurfaces of constant scalar curvature in hyperbolic space with prescribed asymptotic boundary at infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07656v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we study the asymptotic Plateau problem in hyperbolic space, and we prove the existence of a smooth complete hypersurface of constant scalar curvature in hyperbolic space with a prescribed asymptotic boundary at infinity. Following a pioneering work of Bo Guan and Joel Spruck, we seek the solution as a vertical graph over a bounded domain and solve the corresponding Dirichlet problem for a fully nonlinear partial differential equation by establishing the crucial second order estimates for admissible solutions.
  Our proof consists of three main ingredients: (1) a non-standard, special choice for the parameter in the auxiliary function, (2) a so-called almost-Jacobi inequality for the equation operator, and (3) a set of arguments which reduce the situation to semi-convex case and which keep the coefficient of the troublesome negative term within a suitable magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07656v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimality Conditions for Interval-Valued Optimization Problems on Riemannian Manifolds Under a Total Order Relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.09396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.09396v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article explores fundamental properties of convex interval-valued functions defined on Riemannian manifolds. The study employs generalized Hukuhara directional differentiability to derive KKT-type optimality conditions for an interval-valued optimization problem on Riemannian manifolds. Based on type of functions involved in optimization problems, we consider the following cases:
  1. objective function as well as constraints are real-valued;
  2. objective function is interval-valued, and constraints are real-valued;
  3. objective function as well as constraints are interval-valued.
  The whole theory is justified with the help of examples. The order relation that we use throughout the paper is a total order relation defined on the collection of all closed and bounded intervals in $\mathbb{R}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.09396v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hilal Ahmad Bhat, Akhlad Iqbal, Mahwash Aftab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theta bundle, Quillen connection and the Hodge theoretic projective structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05843v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There are two canonical projective structures on any compact Riemann surface of genus at least two: one coming from the uniformization theorem, and the other from Hodge theory. They produce two (different) families of projective structures over the moduli space $M_g$ of compact Riemann surfaces. A recent work of Biswas, Favale, Pirola, and Torelli shows that families of projective structures over $M_g$ admit an equivalent characterization in terms of complex connections on the dual $\mathcal{L}$ of the determinant of the Hodge line bundle over $M_g$; the same work gave the connection on $\mathcal L$ corresponding to the projective structures coming from uniformization. Here we construct the connection on $\mathcal L$ corresponding to the family of Hodge theoretic projective structures. This connection is described in three different ways: firstly as the connection induced on $\mathcal L$ by the Chern connection of the $L^2$-metric on the Hodge bundle, secondly as an appropriate root of the Quillen metric induced by the (square of the) Theta line bundle on the universal family of abelian varieties, endowed with the natural Hermitian metric given by the polarization, and finally as Quillen connection gotten using the Arakelov metric on the universal curve, modified by Faltings' delta invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05843v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Biswas, Alessandro Ghigi, Carolina Tamborini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular Nakano positivity of direct image sheaves of adjoint bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11412v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a proper K\"ahler fibration $f \colon X \to Y$ and a singular Hermitian line bundle $(L, h)$ on $X$ with semi-positive curvature. We prove that the direct image sheaf $f_{*}(\mathcal{O}_{X}(K_{X/Y}+L) \otimes \mathcal{I}(h))$, equipped with the Narasimhan-Simha metric, is singular Nakano semi-positive in the sense that the $\overline{\partial}$-equation can be solved with optimal $L^{2}$-estimate. Our proof does not rely on the theory of Griffiths positivity for the direct image sheaf.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11412v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Inayama, Shin-ichi Matsumura, Yuta Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular Solutions to the Complex Monge-Amp\`ere Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21667v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an explicit pluripotential and viscosity solution to the complex Monge-Amp\`ere equation with constant right-hand side on $\mathbb D\times\mathbb C^{n-1}\,(n\geq 2)$, which lies merely in $W^{1,2}_{loc}\cap W^{2,1}_{loc}$ and is not even Dini continuous. Additionally, we exhibit two families of explicit entire toric solutions on $\mathbb C^n$ with continuous H\"older exponent $\alpha\in(0,1)$ and $W^{2,p}_{loc}$ exponent $p\in (1,2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21667v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxiang Wang, Wenlong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
