<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Volume growth functions of complete Riemannian manifolds with positive scalar curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04121v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $M$ be an open manifold of dimension at least $3$, which admits a complete metric of positive scalar curvature. For a function $v$ with bounded growth of derivative, whether $M$ admits a metric of positive scalar curvature with volume growth of the same growth type as $v$ is unknown. We answer this question positively in the case of manifolds, which are infinite connected sums of closed manifolds that admit metrics of positive scalar curvature. To define a metric of positive scalar curvature with a certain volume growth type on $M$, we use the Gromov-Lawson construction of metrics with positive scalar curvature on connected sums and Grimaldi-Pansu's construction of metrics of bounded geometry of certain volume growth type on open manifolds. We generalize this result to manifolds, which are infinite connected sums of similar closed manifolds along lower-dimensional spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04121v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anushree Das, Soma Maity</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Research problems on relations between Nijenhuis geometry and integrable systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04276v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper surveys open problems and questions related to interplay between the theory of integrable systems with infinitely and finitely many degrees of freedom and Nijenhuis geometry.
  This text has grown out from preparatory materials for the series of research symposia and workshops on Nijenhuis geometry and integrable systems held at SMRI (Sydney) and MATRIX (Creswick) in February 2022 and at La Trobe University (Melbourne) and MATRIX in February 2024, and from the open problem sessions at these events.
  It includes both relatively simple questions to get familiar with the topic, as well as challenging problems that are of great importance for the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04276v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey V. Bolsinov, Andrey Yu. Konyaev, Vladimir S. Matveev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On relative $L^\infty$ estimate for complex Monge-Amp\`ere equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a relative $L^\infty$ estimate for a class of complex Monge-Amp\`ere type equations on K\"ahler manifolds. It provides a unified approach to Tundinger type estimate and uniform estimate. It also improves the previous results about modulus of continuity, stability estimates, and $W^{1,1}$-estimates of Green's functions. The argument is based on the PDE method developed by Guo-Phong-Tong and constructing appropriate comparison metrics from entropy bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04393v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junbang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Alexandrov-Bakelman-Pucci estimate and its applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove an Alexandrov-Bakelman-Pucci type estimate, which involves the integral of the determinant of the complex Hessian over a certain subset. It improves the classical ABP estimate adapted (by inequality $2^{2n}|\det(u_{i\bar{j}})|^2\geq |\det(\nabla^2u)|$) to complex setting. We give an application of it to derive sharp gradient estimates for complex Monge-Amp\`ere equations. The approach is based on the De Giorgi iteration method developed by Guo-Phong-Tong for equations of complex Monge-Amp\`ere type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04395v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junbang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Streets-Tian Conjecture on Lie algebras with codimension $2$ abelian ideals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04791v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Hermitian-symplectic metric is a Hermitian metric whose K\"ahler form is given by the $(1,1)$-part of a closed $2$-form. Streets-Tian Conjecture states that a compact complex manifold admitting a Hermitian-symplectic metric must be K\"ahlerian (i.e., admitting a K\"ahler metric). The conjecture is known to be true in dimension $2$ but is open in dimensions $3$ or higher in general, except in a number of special situations, such as twistor spaces (Verbitsky), Fujiki ${\mathcal C}$ spaces (Chiose), Vaisman manifolds (Angella-Otiman), etc. For Lie-complex manifolds (namely, compact quotients $G/\Gamma$ of Lie groups by discrete subgroups with left-invariant complex structures), the conjecture has also been confirmed in a number of special cases, including when $G$ is nilpotent (Enrietti-Fino-Vezzoni), when $G$ is completely solvable (Fino-Kasuya), or when $J$ is abelian (Fino-Kasuya-Vezzoni), or $G$ is almost abelian (Fino-Kasuya-Vezzoni, Fino-Paradiso), etc. In this article, we conduct a detailed case analysis and confirm Streets-Tian Conjecture for $G$ whose Lie algebra contains an abelian ideal of codimension $2$. Such Lie algebras are always solvable of step at most $3$, but are not $2$-step solvable and not completely solvable in general. Our approach is explicit in nature by describing both the Hermitian-symplectic metrics on such Lie algebras and the pathways of deforming them into K\"ahler ones, in hope of advancing our understanding of the subtlety and intricacy of this interesting conjecture in non-K\"ahler geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04791v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kexiang Cao, Fangyang Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling $f-$Biharmonic $\theta_{\alpha }-$Slant Curves in $\mathcal{S}-$ Space Forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we firstly provide a concise overview of $\mathcal{S}-$manifolds, $f$-biharmonicity and $\theta _{\alpha }$-slant curves. We then derive a key equation and analyze it in detail to establish the necessary and sufficient conditions for $\theta _{\alpha }$-slant curves to be $f$-biharmonic. Finally, we present an example to support our findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04876v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\c{S}aban G\"uven\c{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Focal surfaces and evolutes of framed curves in hyperbolic 3-space from the viewpoint of Legendrian duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A hyperbolic framed curve is a smooth curve with a moving frame in hyperbolic 3-space. It may have singularities. By using this moving frame, we can investigate the differential geometry properties of curves, even at singular points. In fact, we consider the focal surfaces and evolutes of hyperbolic framed curves by using Legendrian dualities which developed by Chen and Izumiya. The focal surfaces are the dual surfaces of tangent indicatrix of original curves. Moreover, classifications of singularities of the serval dual surfaces are shown. By this, we give the relationship among focal surfaces, evolutes and dual surfaces of evolutes. Finally, we study duality relations of singularities between focal surfaces and dual surfaces of evolutes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04888v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haibo Yu, Liang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survey on Broken Ray Transforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We survey recent developments in the theory and applications of the broken ray transforms. Furthermore, we discuss some open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04908v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham R. Jathar, Jesse Railo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Problems for Twisted Geodesic Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The article surveys inverse problems related to the twisted geodesic flows on Riemannian manifolds with boundary, focusing on the generalized ray transforms, tensor tomography, and rigidity problems. The twisted geodesic flow generalizes the usual geodesic flow, allowing to model richer dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04911v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham R. Jathar, Jesse Railo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gap phenomena under curvature restrictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04985v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the paper we discuss gap phenomena of three different types related to Ricci (and sectional) curvature. The first type is about spectral gaps. The second type is about sharp gap metric-rigidity, originally due to Anderson. The third is about sharp gap topological-rigidity. We also propose open problems along these directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04985v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shouhei Honda, Andrea Mondino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Focal surfaces of lightcone framed surfaces in the Lorentz-Minkowski 3-space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the differential geometry properties of focal surfaces of lightcone framed surfaces in Lorentz-Minkowski 3-space. In general, a mixed type surface is a connected regular surface with non-empty spacelike and timelike point sets. In order to investigate the mixed type surface with singular points, we introduce the lightcone framed surface. First, we give the lightcone frame, by which we define the lightcone framed surface. Next, we consider the differential geometry properties of lightcone framed surfaces by using the lightcone frame. At last, we give the definition of focal surfaces of lightcone framed surfaces and investigate the differential geometry properties of focal surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05048v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Xu, Liang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pullback Flow Matching on Data Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04543v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose Pullback Flow Matching (PFM), a novel framework for generative modeling on data manifolds. Unlike existing methods that assume or learn restrictive closed-form manifold mappings for training Riemannian Flow Matching (RFM) models, PFM leverages pullback geometry and isometric learning to preserve the underlying manifold's geometry while enabling efficient generation and precise interpolation in latent space. This approach not only facilitates closed-form mappings on the data manifold but also allows for designable latent spaces, using assumed metrics on both data and latent manifolds. By enhancing isometric learning through Neural ODEs and proposing a scalable training objective, we achieve a latent space more suitable for interpolation, leading to improved manifold learning and generative performance. We demonstrate PFM's effectiveness through applications in synthetic data, protein dynamics and protein sequence data, generating novel proteins with specific properties. This method shows strong potential for drug discovery and materials science, where generating novel samples with specific properties is of great interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04543v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Friso de Kruiff, Erik Bekkers, Ozan \"Oktem, Carola-Bibiane Sch\"onlieb, Willem Diepeveen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the regularity of area minimizing currents at boundaries with arbitrary multiplicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04566v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider an area-minimizing integral $m$-current $T$, within a submanifold $\Sigma \in C^{3,\kappa}$ of $\mathbb{R}^{m+n}$, with arbitrary boundary multiplicity $\partial T = Q[\![\Gamma]\!]$, where $\Gamma\subset\Sigma$ of class $C^{3,\kappa}$. We prove that the set of density $Q/2$ boundary singular points of $T$ is $\mathcal{H}^{m-3}$-rectifiable. This result generalizes Allard's boundary regularity theorem to a higher multiplicity setting.
  In particular, if $\Gamma$ is a closed manifold which lies at the boundary of a uniformly convex set $\Omega$ and $\Sigma=\mathbb{R}^{m+n}$ the whole boundary singular set is $\mathcal{H}^{m-3}$ -rectifiable.
  As a structural consequence of our regularity theory, we show that the boundary regular set, without any assumptions on the density, is open and dense in $\Gamma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04566v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Fleschler, Reinaldo Resende</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-groupoids and quiver-theoretical solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04973v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The notion of post-groups was introduced by Bai, Guo and the first two authors recently, which are the global objects corresponding to post-Lie algebras, equivalent to skew-left braces, and can be used to construct set-theoretical solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation. In this paper, first we introduce the notion of post-groupoids, which consists of a group bundle and some other structures satisfying some compatibility conditions. Post-groupoids reduce to post-groups if the underlying base is one point. An action of a group on a set gives rise to the natural example of post-groupoids. We show that a post-groupoid gives rise to a groupoid (called the Grossman-Larson groupoid), and an action on the original group bundle. Then we introduce the notion of relative Rota-Baxter operators on a groupoid with respect to an action on a group bundle. A relative Rota-Baxter operator naturally gives rise to a post-groupoid and a matched pair of groupoids. One important application of post-groupoids is that they give rise to quiver-theoretical solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation on the quiver underlying the Grossman-Larson groupoid. We also introduce the notion of a skew-left bracoid, which consists of a group bundle and a groupoid satisfying some compatibility conditions. A skew-left bracoid reduces to a skew-left brace if the underlying base is one point. We give the one-to-one correspondence between post-groupoids and skew-left bracoids. Finally, we show that post-Lie groupoids give rise to post-Lie algebroids via differentiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04973v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunhe Sheng, Rong Tang, Chenchang Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abundant Superintegrable Systems and Hessian Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05009v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that a large class of non-degenerate second-order (maximally) superintegrable systems gives rise to Hessian structures, which admit natural (Hessian) coordinates adapted to the superintegrable system. In particular, abundant superintegrable systems on Riemannian manifolds of constant sectional curvature fall into this class. We explicitly compute the natural Hessian coordinates for examples of non-degenerate second-order superintegrable systems in dimensions two and three.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05009v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Armstrong, Andreas Vollmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized Online Riemannian Optimization with Dynamic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05128v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper develops the first decentralized online Riemannian optimization algorithm on Hadamard manifolds. Our algorithm, the decentralized projected Riemannian gradient descent, iteratively performs local updates using projected Riemannian gradient descent and a consensus step via weighted Frechet mean. Theoretically, we establish linear variance reduction for the consensus step. Building on this, we prove a dynamic regret bound of order ${\cal O}(\sqrt{T(1+P_T)}/\sqrt{(1-\sigma_2(W))})$, where $T$ is the time horizon, $P_T$ represents the path variation measuring nonstationarity, and $\sigma_2(W)$ measures the network connectivity. The weighted Frechet mean in our algorithm incurs a minimization problem, which can be computationally expensive. To further alleviate this cost, we propose a simplified consensus step with a closed-form, replacing the weighted Frechet mean. We then establish linear variance reduction for this alternative and prove that the decentralized algorithm, even with this simple consensus step, achieves the same dynamic regret bound. Finally, we validate our approach with experiments on nonstationary decentralized Frechet mean computation over hyperbolic spaces and the space of symmetric positive definite matrices, demonstrating the effectiveness of our methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05128v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengchao Chen, Qiang Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the uniqueness of tangent cones to area minimizing currents at boundaries with arbitrary multiplicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider an area minimizing current $T$ in a $C^2$ submanifold $\Sigma$ of $\mathbb{R}^{m+n}$, with arbitrary integer boundary multiplicity $\partial T = Q [\![ \Gamma ]\!]$ where $\Gamma$ is a $C^2$ submanifold of $\Sigma$. We show that at every density $Q/2$ boundary point the tangent cone to $T$ is unique and there is a power rate of convergence to the unique tangent cone.
  In particular, if $\Gamma$ is a closed manifold which lies at the boundary of a uniformly convex set $\Omega$ and $\Sigma=\mathbb{R}^{m+n}$ then $T$ has a unique tangent cone at every boundary point.
  As a structural consequence of the uniqueness of the tangent cone, we obtain a decomposition theorem which is the starting point of the boundary regularity theory we develop in another paper in collaboration with Reinaldo Resende. The regularity theory we obtain generalizes Allard's boundary regularity theorem to a higher multiplicity setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05132v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Fleschler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic versus distributional lower Ricci curvature bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.03715v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compare two standard approaches to defining lower Ricci curvature bounds for Riemannian metrics of regularity below $C^2$. These are, on the one hand, the synthetic definition via weak displacement convexity of entropy functionals in the framework of optimal transport, and the distributional one based on non-negativity of the Ricci-tensor in the sense of Schwartz. It turns out that distributional bounds imply entropy bounds for metrics of class $C^1$ and that the converse holds for $C^{1,1}$-metrics under an additional convergence condition on regularisations of the metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.03715v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/prm.2023.70</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. A Royal Soc. Edinburgh, 2023:1-25</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael Kunzinger, Michael Oberguggenberger, James A. Vickers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Riemannian Bianchi identities of metric connections with skew torsion and generalized Ricci solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03986v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Curvature properties of a metric connection with totally skew-symmetric torsion are investigated. It is shown that if either the 3-form $T$ is harmonic, $dT=\delta T=0$ or the curvature of the torsion connection $R\in S^2\Lambda^2$ then the scalar curvature of a $\nabla$-Einstein manifold is determined by the norm of the torsion up to a constant. It is proved that a compact generalized gradient Ricci soliton with closed torsion is Ricci flat if and only if either the norm of the torsion or the Riemannian scalar curvature are constants. In this case the torsion 3-form is harmonic and the gradient function has to be constant.
  Necessary and sufficient conditions a metric connection with skew torsion to satisfy the Riemannian first Bianchi identity as well as the contracted Riemannian second Binachi identity are presented. It is shown that if the torsion connection satisfies the Riemannian first Bianchi identity then it satisfies the contracted Riemannian second Bianchi identity. It is also proved that a metric connection with skew torsion satisfying the curvature identity $R(X,Y,Z,V)=R(Z,Y,X,V)$ must be flat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03986v5</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Ivanov, Nikola Stanchev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Riemannian curvature identities of a $G_2$ connection with skew-symmetric torsion and generalized Ricci solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05619v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Curvature properties of the characteristic connection on an integrable $G_2$ manifold are investigated. We consider integrable $G_2$ manifold of constant type, i.e. the scalar product of the exterior derivative of the $G_2$ form with its Hodge dual is constant. We show that on an integrable $G_2$ manifold of constant type with $G_2$-instanton characteristic curvature and vanishing Ricci tensor the torsion 3-form is harmonic. Consequently, we prove that the characteristic curvature is symmetric in exchange the first and the second pair and Ricci flat if and only if the three-form torsion is parallel with respect to the Levi-Civita and to the characteristic connection simultaneously and this is equivalent to the condition that the characteristic curvature satisfies the Riemannian first Bianchi identity. We find that the Hull connection is a $G_2$-instanton exactly when the torsion is closed. We observe that any compact integrable $G_2$ manifold with closed torsion is a generalized gradient Ricci soliton and this is equivalent to a certain vector field to be parallel with respect to the characteristic connection. In particular, this vector field is an infinitesimal automorphism of the $G_2$ structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05619v4</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Ivanov, Nikola Stanchev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological rigidity of small RCD(K,N) spaces with maximal rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10189v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a polycyclic group $\Lambda$, $\text{rank} ( \Lambda )$ is defined as the number of $\mathbb{Z}$ factors in a polycyclic decomposition of $\Lambda$. For a finitely generated group $G$, $\text{rank} (G)$ is defined as the infimum of $ \text{rank} (\Lambda )$ among finite index polycyclic subgroups $\Lambda \leq G$. For a compact $\text{RCD} (K,N)$ space $(X,\mathsf{d}, \mathfrak{m})$ with $\text{diam} (X) \leq \varepsilon (K,N)$, the rank of $\pi_1(X)$ is at most $N$. In this note we show that in case of equality, $X$ is homeomorphic to an infranilmanifold, generalizing to the non-smooth setting a result by Kapovitch--Wilking. We also fill a gap in the proof that if $\pi_1(X) = \mathbb{Z}^N$, then $X$ is bi-H\"older homeomorphic to a flat torus (diffeomorphic in the smooth case).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10189v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Zamora, Xingyu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cheeger type inequalities associated with isocapacitary constants on graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12583v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce Cheeger type constants via isocapacitary constants introduced by Maz'ya to estimate first Dirichlet, Neumann and Steklov eigenvalues on a finite subgraph of a graph. Moreover, we estimate the bottom of the spectrum of the Laplace operator and the Dirichlet-to-Neumann operator for an infinite subgraph. Estimates for higher-order Steklov eigenvalues on a finite or infinite subgraph are also proved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12583v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bobo Hua, Florentin M\"unch, Tao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biharmonic functions and bi-eigenfunctions on some model spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13560v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we first give a convenient formula for bi-Laplacian on a sphere and the complete description of its eigenvalues, buckling eigenvalues, and their corresponding eigenfunctions. We then show that the radial (or rotationally symmetric) solutions for biharmonic equation on the model space $( \mathbb{R}^+\times S^{m-1}, dr^2 + \sigma^2(r)\, g^{S^{m-1}})$ can be given by an integral formula. We also prove that the model space always admits proper biharmonic functions as the products of any eigenfunctions of the factor sphere with certain radial functions. Many explicit examples of proper biharmonic functions on space forms are given. Finally, we give a complete classification of proper biharmonic functions with positive Laplacian on the punctured Euclidean space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13560v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye-Lin Ou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-existence of extremal Sasaki metrics via the Berglund-H\"ubsch transpose</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use the Berglund-H\"ubsch transpose rule from classical mirror symmetry in the context of Sasakian geometry and results on relative K-stability in the Sasaki setting developed by Boyer and van Coevering to exhibit examples of Sasaki manifolds of complexity 3 or complexity 4 that do not admit any extremal Sasaki metrics in its whole Sasaki-Reeb cone which is of Gorenstein type. Previously, examples with this feature were produced by Boyer and van Coevering for Brieskorn-Pham polynomials or their deformations. Our examples are based on the more general framework of invertible polynomials. In particular, we construct families of examples of links with the following property: if the link satisfies the Lichnerowicz obstruction of Gauntlett, Martelli, Sparks and Yau, then its Berglund-H\"ubsch dual preserves this obstruction and moreover this dual admits a perturbation in its local moduli which is obstructed to admitting extremal Sasaki metrics in its whole Sasaki-Reeb cone. In particular, we exhibit examples that have the homotopy type of a sphere or are rational homology spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09720v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaime Cuadros Valle, Ralph R. Gomez, Joe Lope Vicente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological and dynamical aspects of some spectral invariants of contact manifolds with circle action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11787v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study analytic torsion and eta like invariants on CR contact manifolds of any dimension admitting a circle transverse action, and equipped with a unitary representation. We show that, when defined using the spectrum of relevant operators arising in this geometry, the spectral series involved can been interpreted in their whole, both from a topological viewpoint, and as purely dynamical functions of the Reeb flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11787v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michel Rumin (LMO)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak quasi contact metric manifolds and new characteristics of K-contact and Sasakian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02752v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quasi contact metric manifolds (introduced by Y. Tashiro and then studied by several authors) are a natural extension of the contact metric manifolds. Weak almost contact metric manifolds, i.e., the linear complex structure on the contact distribution is replaced by a nonsingular skew-symmetric tensor, were defined by the author and R. Wolak. In this paper, we study a weak analogue of quasi contact metric manifolds. Our main results generalize some well known theorems and provide new criterions for K-contact and Sasakian manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02752v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Rovenski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted isoperimetric ratios and extension problems for fractional conformal Laplacians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.09160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.09160v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate a novel connection between the weighted isoperimetric problems and the weighted Poisson integrals of the extension problems for nonlocal elliptic operators.
  We first derive sharp inequalities for the weighted Poisson integrals associated with degenerate elliptic equations on the half-space and the unit ball, and classify their extremizers. The equations arise from the Caffarelli-Silvestre extension for the fractional Laplacian on the Euclidean space and its conformal transformation via the M\"obius transformation.
  We next interpret the above sharp inequalities in a conformal geometric viewpoint. For this aim, we formulate a variational problem involving a weighted isoperimetric ratio on a smooth metric measure space induced by a conformally compact Einstein (CCE) manifold. Then, we prove that the variational problem is closely linked to the Chang-Gonz\'alez extension for a fractional conformal Laplacian on the conformal infinity of the CCE manifold, and is reduced to the sharp inequality if the CCE manifold is either the Poincar\'e half-space or ball model. We also find a criterion that ensures the existence of a smooth extremizer of the variational problem, and present a relevant conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.09160v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sangdon Jin, Seunghyeok Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Path constrained unbalanced optimal transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15860v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dynamical formulations of optimal transport (OT) frame the task of comparing distributions as a variational problem which searches for a path between distributions minimizing a kinetic energy functional. In applications, it is frequently natural to require paths of distributions to satisfy additional conditions. Inspired by this, we introduce a model for dynamical OT which incorporates constraints on the space of admissible paths into the framework of unbalanced OT, where the source and target measures are allowed to have a different total mass. Our main results establish, for several general families of constraints, the existence of solutions to the variational problem which defines this path constrained unbalanced optimal transport framework. These results are primarily concerned with distributions defined on a Euclidean space, but we extend them to distributions defined over parallelizable Riemannian manifolds as well. We also consider metric properties of our framework, showing that, for certain types of constraints, our model defines a metric on the relevant space of distributions. This metric is shown to arise as a geodesic distance of a Riemannian metric, obtained through an analogue of Otto's submersion in the classical OT setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15860v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bauer, Nicolas Charon, Tom Needham, Mao Nishino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Neumann problem of special Lagrangian type equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06110v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the Neumann problem for special Lagrangian type equations with critical and supercritical phases. These equations naturally generalize the special Lagrangian equation and the k-Hessian equation. By establishing uniform a priori estimates up to the second order, we obtain the existence result using the continuity method. The new technical aspect is our direct proof of boundary double normal derivative estimates. In particular, we directly prove the double normal estimates for the 2-Hessian equation in dimension 3. Moreover, we solve the classical Neumann problem by proving the uniform gradient estimate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06110v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guohuan Qiu, Dekai Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness of equipotential photon surfaces in 4-dimensional static vacuum asymptotically flat spacetimes for positive, negative, and zero mass -- and a new partial proof of the Willmore inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21522v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present different proofs of the uniqueness of 4-dimensional static vacuum asymptotically flat spacetimes containing a connected equipotential photon surface or in particular a connected photon sphere. We do not assume that the equipotential photon surface is outward directed or non-degenerate and hence cover not only the positive but also the negative and the zero mass case which has not yet been treated in the literature. Our results partially reproduce and extend beyond results by Cederbaum and by Cederbaum and Galloway. In the positive and negative mass cases, we give three proofs which are based on the approaches to proving black hole uniqueness by Israel, Robinson, and Agostiniani--Mazzieri, respectively. In the zero mass case, we give four proofs. One is based on the positive mass theorem, the second one is inspired by Israel's approach and in particular leads to a new proof of the Willmore inequality in $(\mathbb{R}^3, \delta)$, under a technical assumption. The remaining two proofs are inspired by proofs of the Willmore inequality by Cederbaum and Miehe and by Agostiniani and Mazzieri, respectively. In particular, this suggests to view the Willmore inequality and its rigidity case as a zero mass version of equipotential photon surface uniqueness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21522v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carla Cederbaum, Albachiara Cogo, Axel Fehrenbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
