<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 01:40:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal limits for parabolic SL(n,C)-Higgs bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we generalize the conformal limit correspondence between Higgs bundles and holomorphic connections to the parabolic setting. Under mild genericity assumptions on the parabolic weights, we prove that the conformal limit always exists and that it defines holomorphic sections of the space of parabolic lambda-connections which preserve a natural stratification and foliate the moduli space. Along the way, we give a careful gauge theoretic construction of the moduli space of parabolic Higgs bundles with full flags which allows the eigenvalues of the residues of the Higgs field to vary. A number of new phenomena arise in the parabolic setting. In particular, in the generality we consider, unlike the nonparabolic case, the nonabelian Hodge correspondence does not define sections of the space of logarithmic lambda-connections, and the conformal limit does not define a one-parameter family in any given moduli space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16798v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian Collier, Laura Fredrickson, Richard Wentworth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hermitian, Ricci-flat toric metrics on non-compact surfaces \`a la Biquard-Gauduchon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biquard-Gauduchon have shown that conformally K\"ahler, Ricci-flat, ALF toric metrics on the complement of toric divisors are: the Taub-NUT metric with reversed orientation, in the Kerr-Taub-bolt family or in the Chen-Teo family. The same authors have also given a unified construction for the above families relying on an axi-symmetric harmonic function on $\mathbb{R}^3$. In this work, we reverse this construction and use methods from a paper of the second named author, "Uniqueness among scalar-flat K\"ahler metrics on non-compact toric 4-manifolds", to show that all conformally K\"ahler, Ricci-flat, toric metrics on the complement of toric divisors, under some mild assumptions on the associated moment polytope, are among the families above. In particular all such metrics are ALF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16843v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gon\c{c}alo Oliveira, Rosa Sena-Dias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notions of uniform manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore a definition of uniformity on noncompact manifolds that does not require a Riemannian metric, but is equivalent to bounded gemetry.
  These are unfinished research notes (and will likely never be published), but since they were cited by other people, I'm submitting this here for easier referencing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16869v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaap Eldering</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher order obstructions to Riccati-type equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop new techniques in order to deal with Riccati-type equations, subject to a further algebraic constraint, on Riemannian manifolds $(M^3,g)$. We find that the obstruction to solve the aforementioned equation has order $4$ in the metric coefficients and is fully described by an homogeneous polynomial in $\mathrm{Sym}^{16}TM$. Techniques from real algebraic geometry, reminiscent of those used for the "PositiveStellen-Satz " problem, allow determining the geometry in terms of explicit exterior differential systems. Analysis of the latter shows flatness for the metric $g$; in particular we complete the classification of asymptotically harmonic manifolds of dimension $3$, establishing those are either flat or real hyperbolic spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16915v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihun Kim, Paul-Andi Nagy, JeongHyeong Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-affinities of planar curves: towards unified description of aesthetic curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17008v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the self-affinity of planar curves. It is regarded as an important property to characterize the log-aesthetic curves which have been studied as reference curves or guidelines for designing aesthetic shapes in CAD systems. We reformulate the two different self-affinities proposed in the development of log-aesthetic curves. We give rigorous proof that one self-affinity actually characterizes log-aesthetic curves, while another one characterizes parabolas. We then propose a new self-affinity which, in equiaffine geometry, characterizes the constant curvature curves (the quadratic curves). It integrates the two self-affinities, by which constant curvature curves in similarity and equiaffine geometries are characterized in a unified manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17008v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun Kumagai, Kenji Kajiwara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The behavior of the Hermitian curvature flow with Q=0 on complex parallelizable manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17061v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the flow of Hermitian metrics governed by the second Chern-Ricci form on a compact complex manifolds. The flow belongs to the family of Hermitian curvature flows introduced by Streets and Tian and it was considered by Lee in order to study compact Hermitian manifolds with almost negative Chern bisectional curvature. We show a regularity result on compact complex parallelizable manifolds and we prove that Chern-flat metrics are dynamically stable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17061v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucio Bedulli, Luigi Vezzoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Morse Functions, Excision and Higher Torsions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17100v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Comparing invariants from both topological and geometric perspectives is a key focus in index theorem. This paper compares higher analytic and topological torsions and establishes a version of the higher Cheeger-M\"uller/Bismut-Zhang theorem. In fact, Bismut-Goette achieved this comparison assuming the existence of fiberwise Morse functions satisfying the fiberwise Thom-Smale transversality condition (TS condition). To fully generalize the theorem, we should remove this assumption. Notably, unlike fiberwise Morse functions, fiberwise generalized Morse functions (GMFs) always exist, we extend Bismut-Goette's setup by considering a fibration $ M \to S $ with a unitarily flat complex bundle $ F \to M $ and a fiberwise GMF $ f $, while retaining the TS condition.
  Compared to Bismut-Goette's work, handling birth-death points for a generalized Morse function poses a key difficulty. To address this, first, by the work of the author M.P., joint with Zhang and Zhu, we focus on a relative version of the theorem. Here, analytic and topological torsions are normalized by subtracting their corresponding torsions for trivial bundles. Next, using new techniques from by the author J.Y., we excise a small neighborhood around the locus where $f$ has birth-death points. This reduces the problem to Bismut-Goette's settings (or its version with boundaries) via a Witten-type deformation. However, new difficulties arise from very singular critical points during this deformation.To address these, we extend methods from Bismut-Lebeau, using Agmon estimates for noncompact manifolds developed by Dai and J.Y.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17100v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Puchol, Junrong Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Static vacuum 3+1 black holes that cannot be put into stationary rotation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16960v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that some of the static Myers/Korotkin-Nicolai (MKN) vacuum 3+1 static black holes cannot be put into stationary rotation. Namely, they cannot be deformed into axisymmetric stationary vacuum black holes with non-zero angular momentum. Other than axisymmetry, no assumptions are made on the possible deformations. The phenomenon occurs in particular for those MKN solutions for which the distance along the axis between the two horizon's poles is sufficiently small compared to the square root of its area. The MKN solutions, sometimes called periodic Schwarzschild, are physically regular but asymptotically Kasner.
  The static rigidity presented here appears to be the first in the literature of General Relativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16960v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Peraza, Martin Reiris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A counterexample to the log canonical Beauville--Bogomolov decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17260v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For every $d \geq 4$, we construct a $d$-dimensional, log canonical, $K$-trivial variety with the property that two general fibers of its Albanese morphism are not birational. This provides a strong counterexample to the Beauville--Bogomolov decomposition in the log canonical setting. This construction can also be adapted to construct a smooth quasi-projective variety of logarithmic Kodaira dimension 0 whose quasi-Albanese morphism has maximal variation. On the positive side, we show that the Albanese morphism for log canonical pairs with nef anti-canonical class is a locally stable family of pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17260v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Bernasconi, Stefano Filipazzi, Zsolt Patakfalvi, Nikolaos Tsakanikas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Index of Embedded Networks in the Sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.12653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.12653v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we will compute the Morse index and nullity for the stationary embedded networks in spheres. The key theorem in the computation is that the index (and nullity) for the whole network is related to the index (and nullity) of small networks and the Dirichlet-to-Neumann map defined in this paper. Finally, we will show that for all stationary triple junction networks in $\mathbb{S}^2$, there is only one eigenvalue (without multiplicity) $-1$, which is less than 0, and the corresponding eigenfunctions are locally constant. Besides, the multiplicity of eigenvalues 0 is 3 for these networks, and their eigenfunctions are generated by the rotations on the sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.12653v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jfa.2024.110525</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Gaoming Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A sharp lower bound on the mean curvature integral with critical power for integral varifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01754v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Part I Weakly differentiable functions
  Part II PDEs on varifolds
  15 Sobolev spaces ... 75
  16 Preliminaries ... 82
  17 Maximum estimates ... 86
  18 Second order flatness of Lebesgue spaces for integral varifolds with subcritical integrability of the mean curvature ... 94
  19 Second order differentiability of the support of integral varifolds with critical integrability of the mean curvature ... 100
  20 Harnack inequality ... 108
  Part III The generalised Gauss map
  21 Points of finite lower density ... 118
  22 Points of infinite density ... 130
  23 Area formula for the generalised Gauss map ... 137
  24 A sharp lower bound on the mean curvature integral with critical power for integral varifolds ... 138
  Appendix
  A Monotonicity identity ... 139
  B An observation concerning the Lusin property ... 140</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01754v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Menne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar curvature and volume entropy of hyperbolic 3-manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00138v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that any closed hyperbolic 3-manifold M admits a Riemannian metric with scalar curvature at least -6, but with volume entropy strictly larger than 2. In particular, this construction gives counterexamples to a conjecture of I. Agol, P. Storm and W. Thurston.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00138v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Demetre Kazaras, Antoine Song, Kai Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
