<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A logifold structure on measure space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper,we develop a local-to-global and measure-theoretical approach to understand datasets. The idea is to take network models with restricted domains as local charts of datasets. We develop the mathematical foundations for these structures, and show in experiments how it can be used to find fuzzy domains and to improve accuracy in data classification problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05492v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Inkee Jung, Siu-Cheong Lau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rigidity of eigenfunctions' gradient estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05517v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: On compact Riemannian manifolds with non-negative Ricci curvature and smooth (possibly empty), convex (or mean convex) boundary, if the sharp Li-Yau type gradient estimate of an Neumann (or Dirichlet) eigenfunction holds at some non-critical points of the eigenfunction; we show that the manifold is isometric to the product of one lower dimension manifold and a round circle (or a line segment).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05517v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoyi Xu, Xiaolong Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified extremal K\"{a}hler metrics and multiplier Hermitian-Einstein metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the notion of multiplier Hermitian-Einstein metric of type $\sigma$ introduced by Mabuchi, we introduce the notion of $\sigma$-extremal K\"{a}hler metrics on compact K\"{a}hler manifolds, which generalizes Calabi's extremal K\"{a}hler metrics. We characterize the existence of this metric in terms of the coercivity of a certain functional on the space of K\"{a}hler metrics to show that, on a Fano manifold, the existence of a $\sigma$-extremal K\"{a}hler metric implies the existence of a multiplier Hermitian-Einstein metric of type $\sigma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05604v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasuhiro Nakagawa, Satoshi Nakamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About generalized complex structures on $\mathbb S^6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the existence of generalized complex structures on the six-dimensional sphere $\mathbb S^6$. We work with the generalized tangent bundle $\mathbb T\mathbb S^6\to \mathbb S^6$ and define the integrability of generalized geometric structures in terms of the Dorfman bracket. Specifically, we prove that there is not a direct way to induce a generalized complex structure on $\mathbb S^6$ from its usual nearly K\"ahler structure inherited from the octonions product.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05681v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Etayo, Pablo G\'omez-Nicol\'as, Rafael Santamar\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the dimension of the singular set of perimeter minimizers in spaces with a two-sided Ricci curvature bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05775v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the Hausdorff dimension of the singular set of perimeter minimizers in non-collapsed Ricci limit spaces with a two-sided Ricci curvature bound is at most $N-5$, where $N$ is the dimension of the ambient space. The estimate is sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05775v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Cucinotta, Francesco Fiorani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the volume entropy on a harmonic manifold of hypergeometric type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Harmonic manifolds of hypergeometric type form a class of non-compact harmonic manifolds that includes rank one symmetric spaces of non-compact type and Damek-Ricci spaces. When normalizing the metric of a harmonic manifold of hypergeometric type to satisfy the Ricci curvature $\mathrm{Ric} = -(n-1)$, we show that the volume entropy of this manifold satisfies a certain inequality. Additionally, we show that manifolds yielding the upper bound of volume entropy are only real hyperbolic spaces with sectional curvature $-1$, while examples of Damek-Ricci spaces yielding the lower bound exist in only four cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05896v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyasu Satoh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse expansion of the metric at null hypersurfaces I. Uniqueness and application to Killing horizons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the first in a series of two papers where we analyze the transverse expansion of the metric on a general null hypersurface. In this paper we obtain general geometric identities relating the transverse derivatives of the ambient Ricci tensor and the transverse expansion of the metric at the null hypersurface. We also explore the case where the hypersurface exhibits a generalized symmetry generator, namely a privileged vector field in the ambient space which, at the hypersurface, is null and tangent (including the possibility of zeroes). This covers the Killing, homothetic, or conformal horizon cases, and, more generally, any situation where detailed information on the deformation tensor of the symmetry generator is available. Our approach is entirely covariant, independent on any field equations, and does not make any assumptions regarding the topology or dimension of the null hypersurface. As an application we prove that the full transverse expansion of the spacetime metric at a non-degenerate Killing horizon (also allowing for bifurcation surfaces) is uniquely determined in terms of abstract data on the horizon and the tower of derivatives of the ambient Ricci tensor at the horizon. In particular, the transverse expansion of the metric in $\Lambda$-vacuum spacetimes admitting a non-degenerate horizon is uniquely determined in terms of abstract data at the horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05377v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Mars, Gabriel S\'anchez-P\'erez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K-stable valuations and Calabi-Yau metrics on affine spherical varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: After providing an explicit K-stability condition for a $\mathbb{Q}$-Gorenstein log spherical cone, we prove the existence and uniqueness of an equivariant K-stable degeneration of the cone, and deduce uniqueness of the asymptotic cone of a given complete $K$-invariant Calabi-Yau metric in the trivial class of an affine $G$-spherical manifold, $K$ being the maximal compact subgroup of $G$.
  Next, we prove that the valuation induced by $K$-invariant Calabi-Yau metrics on affine $G$-spherical manifolds is in fact $G$-invariant. As an application, we point out an affine smoothing of a Calabi-Yau cone that does not admit any $K$-invariant Calabi-Yau metrics asymptotic to the cone. Another corollary is that on $\mathbb{C}^3$, there are no other complete Calabi-Yau metrics with maximal volume growth and spherical symmetry other than the standard flat metric and the Li-Conlon-Rochon-Sz\'ekelyhidi metrics with horospherical asymptotic cone. This answers the question whether there is a nontrivial asymptotic cone with smooth cross section on $\mathbb{C}^{3}$ raised by Conlon-Rochon when the symmetry is spherical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05833v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tran-Trung Nghiem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability and Statistical Inversion of Travel time Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12544v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the travel time tomography problem for conformal metrics on a bounded domain, which seeks to determine the conformal factor of the metric from the lengths of geodesics joining boundary points. We establish forward and inverse stability estimates for simple conformal metrics under some a priori conditions. We then apply the stability estimates to show the consistency of a Bayesian statistical inversion technique for travel time tomography with discrete, noisy measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12544v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashwin Tarikere, Hanming Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing renormalized curvature integrals on Poincar\'e-Einstein manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We describe a general procedure for computing renormalized curvature integrals on Poincar\'e-Einstein manifolds. In particular, we explain the connection between the Gauss-Bonnet-type formulas of Albin and Chang-Qing-Yang for the renormalized volume, and explicitly identify a scalar conformal invariant in the latter formula. Our approach constructs scalar conformal invariants that are divergences at any Einstein manifold; these imply that the scalar invariant in the Chang-Qing-Yang formula is not unique in dimension at least eight. Our procedure also produces explicit conformally invariant Gauss-Bonnet-type formulas for compact Einstein manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11319v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey S. Case, Ayush Khaitan, Yueh-Ju Lin, Aaron J. Tyrrell, Wei Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-positive curvature and vanishing theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03895v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider mixed curvature $\mathcal{C}_{a,b}$, which is a convex combination of Ricci curvature and holomorphic sectional curvature introduced by Chu-Lee-Tam. We prove that if a compact complex manifold M admits a K\"{a}hler metric with quasi-positive mixed curvature and $3a+2b\geq0$, then it is projective. If $a,b\geq0$, then M is rationally connected. As a corollary, the same result holds for k-Ricci curvature. We also show that any compact K\"{a}hler manifold with quasi-positive 2-scalar curvature is projective. Lastly, we generalize the result to the Hermitian case. In particular, any compact Hermitian threefold with quasi-positive real bisectional curvature have vanishing Hodge number $h^{2,0}$. Furthermore, if it is K\"{a}hlerian, it is projective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03895v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nilpotent structures of oriented neutral vector bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05003v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study nilpotent structures of an oriented vector bundle $E$ of rank $4n$ with a neutral metric $h$ and an $h$-connection $\nabla$. We define $H$-nilpotent structures of $(E, h, \nabla )$ for a Lie subgroup $H$ of $SO(2n, 2n)$ related to neutral hyperK\"{a}hler structures. We observe that there exist a complex structure $I$ and paracomplex structures $J_1$, $J_2$ of $E$ such that $h$, $\nabla$, $I$, $J_1$, $J_2$ form a neutral hyperK\"{a}hler structure of $E$ if and only if there exists an $H$-nilpotent structure of $(E, h, \nabla )$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05003v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoya Ando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compactness of Marked Length Isospectral Sets of Birkhoff Billiard Tables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05426v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that equivalence classes of marked length isospectral Birkhoff billiard tables are compact in the $C^\infty$ topology, analogous to the Laplace spectral results of Melrose, Osgood, Phillips and Sarnak. To do so, we derive a hierarchical structure for the integral invariants of Marvizi and Melrose, or equivalently the coefficients of a caustic length-Lazutkin parameter expansion, which are in turn algebraically equivalent to the Taylor coefficients of Mather's $\beta$ function (also called the mean minimal action). Under a generically satisfied noncoincidence condition, these are also Laplace spectral invariants and can be used to hear the shape of certain drumheads. As a byproduct, we obtain an independent proof of the compactness of Laplace isospectral sets for strictly convex planar billiard tables. The proof of the structure theorem uses an interpolating Hamiltonian for nearly glancing billiard orbits and some analytic number theory to compute its Taylor coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05426v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Vig</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
