<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 02:29:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Effective normalization of sub-Riemannian connections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a new normalization condition for connections on sub-Riemannian manifolds with constant symbols. The condition is formulated in terms of Cartan connections and depends only on the first degree of homogeneity of the curvature. The essential part of our result is to show how a Cartan connection can be uniquely determined by a partial connection on the horizontal bundle. Viewed from the manifold, this observation is equivalent to the following claim: a compatible partial affine connection can be uniquely extended to both a full affine connection and a grading of the tangent bundle, and our normalization ensures that the holonomy of this connection will coincide with the horizontal holonomy, i.e., related to horizontal paths only. We give several examples in which we compute the canonical connections for a class of sub-Riemannian manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00108v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erlend Grong, Jan Slovak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canonical parameters on a surface in $\mathbb R^4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00148v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present paper, we study surfaces in the four-dimensional Euclidean space $\mathbb{R}^4$. We define special principal parameters, which we call canonical, on each surface without minimal points, and prove that the surface admits (at least locally) canonical principal parameters. They can be considered as a generalization of the canonical parameters for minimal surfaces and the canonical parameters for surfaces with parallel normalized mean curvature vector field introduced before. We prove a fundamental existence and uniqueness theorem formulated in terms of canonical principal parameters, which states that the surfaces in $\mathbb{R}^4$ are determined up to a motion by four geometrically determined functions satisfying a system of partial differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00148v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ognian Kassabov, Velichka Milousheva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the Penrose cut-and-paste method: Null shells with pressure and energy flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cut-and-paste method is a procedure for constructing null thin shells by matching two regions of the same spacetime across a null hypersurface. Originally proposed by Penrose, it has so far allowed to describe purely gravitational and null-dust shells in constant-curvature backgrounds. In this paper, we extend the cut-and-paste method to null shells with arbitrary gravitational/matter content. To that aim, we first derive a locally Lipschitz continuous form of the metric of the spacetime resulting from the most general matching of two constant-curvature spacetimes with totally geodesic null boundaries, and then obtain the coordinate transformation that turns this metric into the cut-and-paste form with a Dirac-delta term. The paper includes an example of a null shell with non-trivial energy density, energy flux and pressure in Minkowski space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00231v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Manzano, Argam Ohanyan, Roland Steinbauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shrinkers of the area-preserving curve-shortening flow: Existence and saddle-point property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider homothetic evolutions of the area-preserving curve-shortening flow (APCSF), that is, classical curve shortening flow with an additional non-local forcing term. By using known results on $\lambda$-curves, we prove the existence of non-circular shrinkers for this flow. In our first main result, we present a partial classification scheme, similar to the well-known Abresch-Langer classification for shrinkers of curve-shortening flow. Finally, we also deduce a saddle-point property for all non-circular (APCSF)-shrinkers analogous to the known saddle-point property of Abresch-Langer curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00352v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita Cernomazov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Riemannian viewpoint on the Amari-Cencov $\alpha$-connections and Proudman-Johnson equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a new geometric interpretation of the Amari-Cencov $\alpha$-connections $\nabla^{(\alpha)}$ from information geometry: On the space of densities $\operatorname{Dens}_+(M)$, we show that there exist Riemannian metrics $G^\alpha$, which we call $\alpha$-Fisher-Rao metrics, whose Levi-Civita connections are $\nabla^{(\alpha)}$. With the exception of $\alpha=0$ (the Fisher-Rao metric), these metrics are non-invariant to the action of the diffeomorphism group $\operatorname{Diff}(M)$, even though the connections are invariant. This gives a new way of interpreting the geodesics of the $\nabla^{(\alpha)}$ as energy-minimizing curves. On the space of probability densities $\operatorname{Prob}(M)$, we show that the same phenomenon holds for $\alpha\in \{-1,0,1\}$ and that the $\alpha$-connections are not metric otherwise. We show that $\nabla^{(\alpha)}$-geodesics on this space can be interpreted as radial projections of straight lines on appropriate hyper-surfaces, and use this geometric picture to obtain geodesic convexity for any $\alpha\in \mathbb{R}$. In addition, we prove analogous results for appropriate metrics and connections on $\operatorname{Diff}(M)$, which, for the case $M=\mathbb{R}$, imply that the generalized Proudman-Johnson equations on the real line are the Euler-Arnold equations of non-right invariant metrics. Finally, in the finite-dimensional case, we show that $\nabla^{(\alpha)}$ can be metric or non-metric depending on the considered statistical model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00371v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bauer, Alice Le Brigant, Cy Maor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear F-manifolds, a duality and the generalized tangent bundle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00474v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A linear F-manifold is an F-manifold (E, \circ , e) defined on the total space of a vector bundle \pi : E \rightarrow M for which the multiplication and unit field are linear tensor fields. We develop a systematic treatment of linear F-manifolds. Using an additional suitable connection on M, we define a duality between linear F-manifolds (with and without Euler fields) on E and the total space E^{*} of the dual vector bundle. Our main examples of linear F-manifolds are the tangent and cotangent prolongation. Motivated by the direct sum of tangent and cotangent prolongation, we define and investigate compatibility conditions between linear F-manifolds and the geometry of the generalized tangent bundle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00474v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liana David</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-contact structures with symmetry: local normal forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00802v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A pair of transverse contact distributions on a 3-manifold will in general admit no 1-parameter families of symmetries: a flow preserving both contact distributions. Here, we will determine local normal forms for such pairs admitting symmetries. In particular, we observe that orientable Anosov flows may be globally given by the intersection of a pair of oppositely oriented contact distributions admitting, around any point, maximal local symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00802v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor Jackman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean curvature of direct image bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $E\to X$ be a vector bundle of rank $r$ over a compact complex manifold $X$ of dimension $n$. It is known that if the line bundle $O_{P(E^*)}(1)$ over the projectivized bundle $P(E^*)$ is positive, then $E\otimes \det E$ is Nakano positive by the work of Berndtsson. In this paper, we give a subharmonic analogue. Let $p:P(E^*)\to X$ be the projection and $\alpha$ be a K\"ahler form on $X$. If the line bundle $O_{P(E^*)}(1)$ admits a metric $h$ with curvature $\Theta$ positive on every fiber and $\Theta^r\wedge p^*\alpha^{n-1}&gt; 0$, then $E\otimes \det E$ carries a Hermitian metric whose mean curvature is positive.
  As an application, we show that the following subharmonic analogue of the Griffiths conjecture is true: if the line bundle $O_{P(E^*)}(1)$ admits a metric $h$ with curvature $\Theta$ positive on every fiber and $\Theta^r\wedge p^*\alpha^{n-1}&gt; 0$, then $E$ carries a Hermitian metric with positive mean curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00820v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuang-Ru Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homotopies for Lagrangian field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00133v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Consider the variational bicomplex for $\mathcal{E}$ the space of sections of a graded, affine bundle. Local functionals $\mathcal{F}$ are defined as an equivalence class of density-valued functionals, which represent Lagrangian densities. A choice of a $k$-symplectic local form $\omega$ on $\mathcal{E}$ induces a Lie$[k]$ algebra structure on (Hamiltonian) local functionals $(\mathcal{F}_{\mathrm{ham}},\{\cdot,\cdot\}_{\mathrm{ham}})$. For any $\omega$ and any choice of a cohomological vector field $Q$ compatible with $\omega$, we build an explicit $L_\infty$ algebra on a resolution of $\mathcal{F}_{\mathrm{ham}}$, which is $L_\infty$ quasi-isomorphic to a dgL$[k]$a $(\mathcal{F}_{\mathrm{ham}},d_{\mathrm{ham}},\{\cdot,\cdot\}_{\mathrm{ham}})$. In the case $k=-1$, this provides an explicit lift of the standard Batalin--Vilkovisky framework to local forms enriched by the $L_\infty$ structure, in terms of local homotopies. We further provide a multisymplectic interpretation of the resulting data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00133v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Schiavina, Jonas Schnitzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal free boundary minimal surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00337v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the nonlocal analogue of the classical free boundary minimal hypersurfaces in an open domain $\Omega$ of $\mathbb{R}^n$ as the (boundaries of) critical points of the fractional perimeter $\operatorname{Per}_s(\cdot,\,\Omega )$ with respect to inner variations leaving $\Omega$ invariant. We deduce the Euler-Lagrange equations and prove a few surprising features, such as the existence of critical points without boundary and a strong volume constraint in $\Omega$ for unbounded hypersurfaces. Moreover, we investigate stickiness properties and regularity across the boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00337v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Badran, Serena Dipierro, Enrico Valdinoci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero Probability of the Cut Locus of a Fr\'echet Mean on a Riemannian Manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00747v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the cut locus of a Fr\'echet mean of a random variable on a connected and complete Riemanian manifold has zero probability, a result known previously in special cases and conjectured in general. In application, we rule out stickiness, while providing examples of nowhere smooth Fr\'echet functions and we discuss extensions of the statement to Fr\'echet $p$-means, for $p\neq 2$, as well as to noncomplete manifolds and more general metric spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00747v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Lytchak, Stephan F. Huckemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Einstein Structure of Four-Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05335v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is known that the moduli space of Einstein structures in four dimensions is generally considered to be rigid so that Einstein metrics tend to be isolated modulo diffeomorphisms under infinitesimal Einstein deformations. We examine the rigidity of the Einstein structure by considering deformations of the round four-sphere. We show that any deviation from the standard metric of the round four-sphere (except for scaling) breaks the Einstein condition. This further supports the idea of rigidity. We analyze the Einstein structure of four-manifolds based on the irreducible decomposition of the self-dual structure of Einstein manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05335v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeongwon Ho, Kyung Kiu Kim, Hyun Seok Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllability on landmark manifolds for shapes and neural ODEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08090v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Landmark manifolds consist of a collection of distinct points, and dynamics on this manifold can be used to represent flows, such as solutions of ODEs and flows deforming a shape. We will consider landmark configurations in the Euclidean space and how such configuration can be connected through flows of vector field. For every dimension equal or larger than two, we explicitly describe two vector fields whose flows can connect any pair of landmark configuration regardless of how many points are in the configuration. This property is called the exact universal interpolation property. For the case of dimension one, we show the same result holds for landmark configurations as long as they have the same relative order. In all dimensions, we are able to achieve controllability by combining a constant vector field with a polynomial vector field of degree three.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08090v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erlend Grong, Sylvie Vega-Molino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The topological holonomy group and the complexity of horizontality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10092v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In [2], it is observed that if in the twistor space associated with an oriented vector bundle of rank $4$ over $T^2$ with a positive-definite metric and a metric connection, the horizontality has infinite complexity derived from one of the cases studied in [1], then the complexity is expressed by a dense subset of $S^2$. In the present paper, it is observed that in such a situation, the topological holonomy group is dense in $SO(3)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10092v4</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoya Ando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of the topological holonomy groups in $SO(3)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20593v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we obtain classification of the topological holonomy groups in $SO(3)$. Such a group is given by one of the following: a finite group (such groups are classified by Klein); a commutative infinite group which is generated by one or two elements, and dense in a subgroup of $SO(3)$ isomorphic to $SO(2)$; a non-commutative infinite group generated by two elements of order $2$, $\infty$ such that these rotation axes are orthogonal; a non-commutative infinite group which is dense in $SO(3)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20593v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoya Ando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surfaces in a strict Walker 3-manifold that contain non-null curves with zero torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22261v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a non-null curve $\gamma$ in a strict Walker 3-manifold, first we show that (locally) $\gamma$ lies in a flat cylinder with a null axis. Secondly, we construct an example of such a curve $\gamma$ and such a cylinder $S$ that contains $\gamma$ . In particular, the hypothesis that $S$ is totally geodesic has some consequence on the geometry of the ambient Walker 3-manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22261v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>El Hadji Baye Camara, Athoumane Niang, Ameth Ndiaye, Adama Thiandoum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental groups of open manifolds with nonnegative Ricci curvature and universal cover Euclidean volume growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23690v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we will give an positive answer to Pan-Rong's conjecture that for an open manifold with nonnegative Ricci curvature, if its universal cover has Euclidean volume growth, then its fundamental group is finitely generated. Moreover the fundamental group is virtually abelian. The same result has been given by H.Huang-X.Huang for dimension 4. In fact, we will show the fundamental group finitely generated in a more general condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23690v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lina Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
