<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-negative curvature on certain product manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G/H$ be a closed, simply connected homogeneous manifold. Suppose every stable class of real vector bundles over $G/H$ contains a homogeneous bundle. Then, for any closed, simply connected smooth manifold $M$ homotopy equivalent to $G/H$, there exists $n&gt;\mathrm{dim}(M)$ such that the product manifold $M\times S^{n}$ admits a metric with non-negative sectional curvature. Many homogeneous manifolds satisfy this assumption, including simply connected compact rank-one symmetric spaces, and among others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15194v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity and Classification of Legendrian Self-Shrinkers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we first classify Legendrian self-shrinkers in $\mathbb{R}% ^{3}$ and $\mathbb{R}^{5}$. We then proved a Legendrian rigidity theorem, which can be regarded as an analogue of the result of Li-Wang \cite{lw}. More precisely, let $F(\Sigma)\subset\mathbb{R}^{5}$ be an orientable Legendrian self-shrinker, if $\Vert A\Vert_{g}^{2}\leq2$ and the associated Legendrian immersion $\bar{F}\subset\mathbb{R}^{4}\times\mathbb{S}^{1}$ is compact, then $\bar{F}$ must be a flat minimal generalized Legendrian Clifford torus in $\mathbb{S}^{5}$, whose cone $\mathcal{C}(\bar{F}(\Sigma))$ is the Harvey-Lawson special Lagrangian cone in $\mathbb{C}^{3}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15279v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu-Cheng Chang, Chin-Tung Wu, Liuyang Zhang, Qiuxia Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry on curves which go around a Whitney umbrella</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider curves which go around Whitney umbrella. Then we consider the geodesic and the normal curvatures, ruled surfaces generated by the normal vector and normal developable surfaces with respect to the tangent and bi-tangent vectors of the curve. Then we obtain several functions which represents geometry on Whitney umbrella. Looking at the top terms of them with respect to the radius, we study geometry on Whitney umbrella.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15293v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masayuki Hara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentzian Cheeger-Gromov convergence and temporal functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15441v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Uniqueness (up to isometries) and existence of limits are analyzed in the context of Cheeger-Gromov convergence of spacetimes. To face the non-compactness of the vector isometry group in the semi-Riemanian setting, standard \em{pointed} convergence is strenghtened to \em{anchored} convergence (which requires the convergence of a timelike direction in the Lorenzian case). Then, a local isometry between the neighborhoods of the basepoints is found, and extended globally under geodesic completeness and simple connectedness. In spacetimes, by using Cauchy temporal functions as both strengthenings of the anchor and tools to ``Wick rotate'' metrics, a new notion of convergence for globally hyperbolic spacetimes (including the case of timelike boundaries) is introduced. The machinery of Riemannian Cheeger-Gromov theory becomes applicable after revisiting the tools related to time functions and studying their connections with Sormani-Vega null distance. In particular, several results with interest on its own right are obtained such as: time functions are locally Lipschitz up to rescaling, global and local characterizations of $h$-steep functions, independence of steepness and $h$-steepness for temporal functions, compatibility of both conditions for Cauchy temporal functions, and the stability of the latter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15441v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sa\'ul Burgos, Jos\'e L. Flores, Miguel S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New curvature characterization for the weighted Sasaki sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we use the shifted cones introduced by Yang and Zhang to classify Sasaki manifolds. This gives a new curvature characterization for the weighted Sasaki sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15560v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pak Tung Ho, Kuang-Ru Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Submanifolds with boundary in sub-Riemannian Heisenberg Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the notion of submanifolds with boundary with intrinsic $C^1$ regularity in sub-Riemannian Heisenberg groups and we provide some examples. Eventually, we present a Stokes' Theorem for such submanifolds involving the integration of Rumin's differential forms in Heisenberg groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15634v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Di Marco, Davide Vittone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Future stability of solutions of the Einstein-nonlinear scalar field system with decelerated expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15303v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study solutions to the Einstein equations coupled to a nonlinear scalar field with exponential potential. This system admits Friedmann-Lema\^itre-Robertson-Walker solutions undergoing decelerated expansion, with $\mathbb{T}^3$ spatial topology and scale factor $a(t) = t^p$ for $1/3 &lt; p &lt; 1$. For each $p \in (2/3,1)$, we prove that the corresponding FLRW spacetime is future-stable as a solution to the Einstein-nonlinear scalar field system. Given initial data on a spacelike hypersurface that is sufficiently close to the FLRW data, we show the resulting solution is future-causal geodesically complete, and remains close to the FLRW solution for all time. Moreover, we show the perturbed metric components and scalar field converge to spatially homogeneous functions as $t \rightarrow \infty$. A key feature of our analysis is the decomposition of the metric and scalar field perturbations into their spatial averages and oscillatory remainders with zero average.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15303v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louie Bernhardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projective rigidity of circle patterns and polyhedral surfaces in hyperbolic ends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15339v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $S$ be a closed, orientable surface of genus $g\geq 2$. We consider Delaunay circle patterns on $S$ equipped with a complex projective structure. We prove that the space of complex projective structures on $S$ equipped with a Delaunay circle pattern of prescribed combinatorics and intersection angles is a manifold of dimension $6g-6$, and that the forgetful map to the space $\cC_S$ of $\CP^1$-structures on $S$ is a Lagrangian immersion. This extends a recent result of Bonsante and Wolf for circle packings.
  This statement, and its proof, are more conveniently stated in terms of ideal polyhedral surfaces (surfaces with vertices at infinity) in hyperbolic ends, with the angles between the circles corresponding to the dihedral angles. Seen from this angle, we extend the statement to ideal polyhedral surfaces with prescribed edge lengths (or induced metrics), and to other types of polyhedral surfaces, either compact or hyperideal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15339v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Marc Schlenker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-maximal Anosov representations from surface groups to $\mathrm{SO}_0(2,3)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08118v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the representation given by a stable $\alpha_1$-cyclic parabolic $\mathrm{SO}_0(2,3)$-Higgs bundle through the non-Abelian Hodge correspondence is $\{\alpha_2\}$-almost dominated. This is a generalization of Filip's result on weight $3$ variation of Hodge structures and answers a question asked by Collier, Tholozan and Toulisse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08118v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junming Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentzian manifolds equipped with a concircularly semi-symmetric metric connection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01897v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Building upon previous works characterizing GRW space-times using concircular and torse-forming vectors, this paper investigates a Lorentzian manifold equipped with a concircularly semi-symmetric metric connection. We demonstrate that such a manifold reduces to a GRW space-time under specific conditions: when the generator of the observed connection is a unit timelike vector. Also, in that case, the mentioned connection becomes a semi-symmetric metric $P$-connection. The non-zero nature of the three curvature tensors and their corresponding Ricci tensors motivates an exploration of manifold symmetries. In this way, we derive necessary and sufficient conditions for the manifold to be Einstein and we prove that a perfect fluid space-time with a semi-symmetric metric $P$-connection is Ricci pseudo-symmetric manifold of constant type. Furthermore, we show that if this space-time satisfies the Einstein's field equations without the cosmological constant, the strong energy condition is violated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01897v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miroslav D. Maksimovi\'c, Milan Lj. Zlatanovi\'c, Milica R. Vu\v{c}urovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical Exponent Rigidity for $\Theta-$positive Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17559v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove for a $\Theta-$positive representation from a discrete subgroup $\Gamma\subset \mathsf{PSL}(2,\mathbb{R})$, the critical exponent for any $\alpha\in \Theta$ is not greater than one. When $\Gamma$ is geometrically finite, the equality holds if and only if $\Gamma$ is a lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17559v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhufeng Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formally Integrable Structures II. Division Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07511v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We formulate a division problem for a class of overdetermined systems introduced by L. H{\"o}rmander, and establish an effective divisibility criterion. In addition, we prove a coherence theorem which extends Nadel's coherence theorem from complex structures to elliptic systems of partial differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07511v3</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingchun Ji, Jun Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary Detection Algorithm Inspired by Locally Linear Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18456v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the study of high-dimensional data, it is often assumed that the data set possesses an underlying lower-dimensional structure. A practical model for this structure is an embedded compact manifold with boundary. Since the underlying manifold structure is typically unknown, identifying boundary points from the data distributed on the manifold is crucial for various applications. In this work, we propose a method for detecting boundary points inspired by the widely used locally linear embedding algorithm. We implement this method using two nearest neighborhood search schemes: the epsilon-radius ball scheme and the K-nearest neighbor scheme. This algorithm incorporates the geometric information of the data structure, particularly through its close relation with the local covariance matrix. We analyze the algorithm by exploring the spectral properties of the local covariance matrix, with the findings guiding the selection of key parameters. In the presence of high-dimensional noise, we propose a framework aimed at enhancing boundary detection in noisy data. Furthermore, we demonstrate the algorithm's performance with simulated examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18456v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Cheng Kuo, Nan Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite Ideal Polyhedra in Hyperbolic 3-Space: Existence and Rigidity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19528v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the seminal work [27], Rivin obtained a complete characterization of finite ideal polyhedra in hyperbolic 3-space by the exterior dihedral angles. Since then,the characterization of infinite hyperbolic polyhedra has become an extremely challenging open problem. By studying ideal circle patterns (ICPs), we characterize the infinite ideal polyhedra (IIP) and resolve this problem. Specifically, we establish the existence and rigidity of embedded ICPs on the plane. We further prove the uniformization theorem for the embedded ICPs, which solves the type problem of infinite ICPs. This is an analog of the uniformization theorem obtained by He and Schramm in [22, 23]. Moreover, we demonstrate that, unlike He-Schramm's work, the type theory for infinite ICPs depends not only on the structure of the cellular decomposition but also on the selection of intersection angles. In fact, we construct Example 4.13 to show the difference. Consequently, we obtain the existence and rigidity of IIP with prescribed exterior angles. Due to the example, our results on the type problem of infinite ICPs and the existence of IIP are sharp. For ICPs with arbitrary angles, our example also demonstrates that the VEL-parabolicity and ICP-parabolicity are not equivalent (while in He and Schramm's settings, VEL-parabolicity and CP-parabolicity are equivalent), indicating that our setting is extremely distinct from He and Schramm's. To prove our results, we develop a uniform Ring Lemma via the technique of pointed Gromov-Hausdorff convergence for ICPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19528v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huabin Ge, Hao Yu, Puchun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
