<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Simplicial sheaves of modules and Morita invariance of groupoid cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07285v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article we develop a unified framework for proving Morita invariance of cohomology theories associated to Lie groupoids. Our approach is to view these cohomology theories as arising from sheaves of modules on the nerve of the groupoid. We establish criteria for when such sheaves of modules give rise to Morita invariant cohomology theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07285v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Tang, Joel Villatoro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensional reduction of stable Higgs bundle and the Doubly-Coupled Vortex Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07489v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a compact Riemann surface and $\mathbb{P}^1$ be the complex projective line. In this paper, we introduce an equation which we call the doubly-coupled vortex equation on $X$. We show that the existence of a solution of the doubly-coupled is equivalent to the existence of an $SU(2)$-invariant Hermitian-Einstein metric on certain Higgs bundles over $X\times \mathbb{P}^1$. By applying the Kobayashi-Hitchin correspondence for Higgs bundles, we further show that the existence of a solution to the doubly-coupled vortex equation is equivalent to the stability of the associated Higgs quadruplet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07489v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Ono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Level sets of harmonic functions on three-dimensional manifolds with nonnegative scalar curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07608v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the level sets of harmonic functions on $(\mathbb{R}^{3}\setminus \{0\},g)$. Drawing inspiration from Miao, we adopt the method developed by Munteanu-Wang to derive a monotonic quantity associated with the level sets of harmonic functions on $(\mathbb{R}^{3}\setminus \{0\},g)$ with nonnegative scalar curvature, under certain conditions. Furthermore, we establish a rigidity result for this quantity. Additionally, we find an extra scalar-flat metric on $\mathbb{R}^{3}\setminus \{0\}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07608v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukai Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The holonomy of the Obata connection on Joyce hypercomplex manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the holonomy of the Obata connection on Joyce hypercomplex manifolds. For all such group manifolds except $\mathrm{SU}(2n+1)$, we show that the holonomy group is strictly contained in the quaternionic general linear group. The case of $\mathrm{SU}(2n+1)$ is more subtle: for every $n&gt;1$, we show that there exist infinitely many Joyce hypercomplex structures with Obata holonomy strictly contained in $\mathrm{GL}(n(n+1),\mathbb{H})$. On the other hand, Soldatenkov showed that $\mathrm{SU}(3)$ has Obata holonomy equal to $\mathrm{GL}(2,\mathbb{H})$ \cite{Sol}, and we present here a new example on $\mathrm{SU}(5)$ with holonomy equal to $\mathrm{GL}(6,\mathbb{H})$. Finally, we investigate Joyce hypercomplex manifolds whose restricted holonomy lie in $\mathrm{SL}(n, \mathbb{H})$, yielding new compact examples of twisted Calabi-Yau manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07722v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatrice Brienza, Udhav Fowdar, Giovanni Gentili, Luigi Vezzoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A local generalisation of frame bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Frame bundles equipped with a principal connection have their local structure characterised by a 1-form, called the Cartan connection 1-form, which gathers the principal connection form and the soldering form. We introduce generalised frame bundles as a smooth manifold equipped with a coframe with value in a suitable Lie algebra and which furthermore satisfies a weakened version of the Maurer-Cartan equation. From this structure it is possible to construct a Lie algebra action on the manifold. We study the question of whether it is possible to construct a Lie group action and build a base manifold over which the initial manifold is a frame bundle. We find that generalised frame bundles can have singular underlying manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07749v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\'emie Pierard de Maujouy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete characterization of anisotropic geodesics in the Euclidean space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07224v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a lower semicontinuous, 1-homogeneous positive function defined on $\mathbf{R}^n$. We provide a characterization of absolutely continuous paths that minimize the anisotropic $F$-length between two points. The characterization is achieved by establishing a connection between the minimizing paths and the geometry of the anisotropic $F$-isoperimetric set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07224v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Aldrigo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $L^p$-diameter of the space of contractible loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07270v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that the space of contractible simple loops of a given fixed area in any compact oriented surface has infinite diameter as a homogeneous space of the group of area-preserving diffeomorphisms endowed with the $L^p$-metric. As a special case, this resolves the $L^p$-metric analogue of the well-known question in symplectic topology regarding the space of equators on the two-sphere. Our methods involve a new class of functionals on a normed group, which are more general than quasi-morphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07270v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Brandenbursky, Egor Shelukhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log Calabi--Yau manifolds: holomorphic tensors, stability and universal cover</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07508v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study various geometric properties of log Calabi-Yau manifolds, i.e. log smooth pairs $(X,D)$ such that $K_X+D=0$. More specifically, we focus on the two cases where $X$ is a Fano manifold and $D$ is either smooth or has two proportional components. Despite the existence of a complete Ricci flat K\"ahler metric on $X\setminus D$ in both cases, we will show that the geometric properties of the pair $(X,D)$ are vastly different, e.g. validity of Bochner principle, local triviality of the quasi-Albanese map, polystability of $T_X(-\log D)$ and compactifiability of the universal cover of $X\setminus D$. When $D$ has two components we show that the universal cover of $X\setminus D$ is a Calabi-Yau manifold of infinite topological type, and we describe the geometry at infinity from a Riemannian point of view.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07508v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tristan C. Collins, Henri Guenancia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A gradient estimate for the linearized translator equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07629v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we develop some analytic foundations for the linearized translator equation in $\mathbb{R}^4$, i.e. in the first dimension where the Bernstein property fails. This equation governs how the (noncompact) singularity models of the mean curvature flow in $\mathbb{R}^4$ fit together in a common moduli space. Here, we prove a gradient estimate, which gives a sharp bound for $W_v$, namely for the derivative of the variation field $W$ in the tip region. This serves as a substitute for the fundamental quadratic concavity estimate from Angenent-Daskalopoulos-Sesum, which has been crucial for controlling $Y_v$, namely the derivative of the profile function $Y$ in the tip region. Moreover, together with interior estimates by virtue of the linearized translator equation our gradient estimate implies a bound for $W_\tau$ as well. Hence, our gradient estimate also serves as substitute Hamilton's Harnack inequality, which has played an important role for controlling $Y_\tau$ in the tip region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07629v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyeongsu Choi, Robert Haslhofer, Or Hershkovits</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector fields and flows on $C^\infty$-schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19064v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that a vector field on an affine $C^\infty$-scheme Spec(A) has a flow if the $C^\infty$-ring A is finitely generated. If the vector field is complete then
  the flow is the target map of a groupoid internal to the category of
  $C^\infty$-schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19064v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Lerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
