<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fredholm properties of the jacobi Operator of minimal conical hypersurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study non-degeneracy properties of $\Sigma$ via the Jacobi operator $J_\Sigma:=\Delta_\Sigma+|A_\Sigma|^2$ of a given minimal hypersurface $\Sigma$ asymptotic to a cone $C\subset \mathbb{R}^{N+1}$ of co-dimension one. Here $\Delta_{\Sigma}$ is the Laplace Beltrami operator of $\Sigma$ and $|A_{\Sigma}|$ is the norm of the second fundamental form of $\Sigma$. We also construct a right inverse of $J_{\Sigma}$, that is, we prove that the Jacobi equation $J_\Sigma\phi=f$ is solvable in $\Sigma$, at least under some suitable non-degeneracy assumptions about $\Sigma$ and about the asymptotic behavior of $f$ at infinity. We also discuss some examples where our results can be applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11804v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Ivan Agudelo Rico, Matteo Rizzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact lifts and Holder lifts to central extension of Carnot groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11897v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the existence problem of lift F of a map f between Carnot group with different smoothness, where we use central extension to define lifting. Our main result is the existence of the contact lifts of Lipschitz and Sobolev maps and the rigidity result for the contact lift of quasiconformal maps: a quasiconformal map admits a contact lift then it is bi-Lipschitz. We also show a necessary criterion for the extension of {\gamma}-Holder lift when {\gamma} &gt; n+1/n for step-n Carnot group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11897v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihan Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity of Cohomogeneity two equivariant isotopy minimization problems and minimal hypersurfaces with large first Betti number on spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the regularity of cohomogeneity two equivariant isotopy minimization problems. Based on this, we develop cohomogeneity two equivariant min-max theory for minimal hypersurfaces proposed by Pitts and Rubinstein in 1988. As an application, for $g \ge 1$ and $4 \le n+1 \le 7$, we construct minimal hypersurfaces $\Sigma_{g}^{n}$ on round spheres $\mathbb{S}^{n+1}$ with $(SO(n-1) \times \mathbb{D}_{g+1})$-symmetry. For sufficiently large $g$, $\Sigma_{g}^{n}$ is a sequence of minimal hypersurfaces with arbitrarily large Betti numbers of topological type $\#^{2g} (S^{1} \times S^{n-1})$ or $\#^{2g+2} (S^{1} \times S^{n-1})$, which converges to a union of $\mathbb{S}^{n}$ and a Clifford hypersurface $\sqrt{\frac{1}{n}}\mathbb{S}^{1} \times \sqrt{\frac{n-1}{n}} \mathbb{S}^{n-1}$ or $\sqrt{\frac{2}{n}}\mathbb{S}^{2} \times \sqrt{\frac{n-2}{n}} \mathbb{S}^{n-2}$. In particular, for dimensions $5$ and $6$, $\Sigma_{g}^{n}$ has a topological type $\#^{2g} (S^{1} \times S^{n-1})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12322v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongyeong Ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A remark on the second order estimates for the quaternionic Calabi-Yau problem on hyperk\"ahler manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the second order estimate for solutions to the quaternionic Calabi-Yau problem on hyperk\"ahler manifolds, originally established by Dinew and Sroka. In this note, we present a simplified argument to derive the estimate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12415v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Gentili, Luigi Vezzoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The geometric characteristics of SGL submanifolds in an indefinite Sasakian statistical manifold equipped with a quarter symmetric metric connection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This research paper examines the geometric structure of screen generic lightlike (SGL) submanifolds in an indefinite Sasakian statistical manifold equipped with a quarter-symmetric (QS) metric connection. The study focuses on analyzing the integrability conditions and the parallelism properties of various distributions associated with these submanifolds. It explores the characteristics of totally geodesic foliations and mixed geodesic submanifolds, providing significant insights into their geometric behavior. In addition to the theoretical development, the paper also presents an illustrative example of a contact SGL submanifold within an indefinite Sasakian statistical manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12522v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vandana Gupta,  Shagun, Jasleen Kaur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quermassintegral inequalities for horo-convex domains in the sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a new notion of convexity for subsets of the unit sphere, which closely resembles the horo-convexity for subsets of the hyperbolic space. We call this notion, accordingly, horo-convexity. For horo-convex hypersurfaces of the unit sphere, we prove the smooth convergence of the classical Guan/Li flow of inverse type and use this result to prove the full set of quermassintegral inequalities for horo-convex hypersurfaces of the unit sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12565v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shujing Pan, Julian Scheuer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A remark on Symphonic maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we are devoted to define p symphonic morphism and characterize it partially as in the case of harmonic morphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12639v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangzhi Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Theory of Almost Periodic Banach--Malcev Algebras and Applications to Moufang Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce almost periodic Banach--Malcev algebras as a non-associative extension of Bohr's classical theory. Our framework is based on the relative compactness of adjoint orbits $\{e^{t\,\mathrm{ad}(x)}(y)\}$, which yields the spectral characterization $\sigma(\mathrm{ad}(x)) \subseteq i\mathbb{R}$, uniform boundedness of orbit closures in the strong operator topology, and a continuous functional calculus for almost periodic derivations. Compact Malcev algebras -- most notably the imaginary octonions $\mathrm{Im}(\mathbb{O})$ -- provide canonical finite-dimensional examples, and their associated Moufang loops carry strictly periodic flows. We also analyze structural actions on eigenspaces of the Malcev Laplacian as a concrete case study, where the bounded defect operator $S(x,y) \in \mathcal{B}(M)$ quantifies the non-associative correction. While speculative links to non-associative gauge theory are noted, they lie beyond the established mathematical scope. The recent convergence control of the BCH series for special Banach--Malcev algebras \cite{Athmouni2025} provides analytic justification for the local Moufang structure used throughout.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12687v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marwa Ennaceur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the splitting of weak nearly ${\cal C}$-manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weak metric $f$-manifolds, i.e., the linear complex structure on the contact distribution is replaced by a nonsingular skew-symmetric tensor, defined by V. Rovenski and R. Wolak (2022), allow a new look at the theory of almost contact and metric $f$-manifolds. In this paper, we study the curvature and topology of a structure of this type, called the weak nearly ${\cal C}$-structure; specifically, we are guided by the following question: Under what conditions are weak nearly $\cal C$-manifolds locally the Riemannian products? Our theorems generalize results of H. Endo (2005), A. Nicola-G. Dileo-I. Yudin (2018) on nearly cosymplectic manifolds and V. Rovenski (2024) on weak nearly cosymplectic manifolds to the context of weak nearly ${\cal C}$-manifolds. Namely, we find conditions under which a $(2n+s)$-dimensional weak nearly ${\cal C}$-manifold becomes a Riemannian product, and characterize $(4+s)$-dimensional weak nearly ${\cal C}$-manifolds. The consequences of these theorems present new results for nearly ${\cal C}$-manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12820v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Nayak, Dhriti Sundar Patra, Vladimir Rovenski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free boundary and capillary minimal surfaces in spherical caps I: Low genus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12877v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is the first of two articles in which we investigate the geometry of free boundary and capillary minimal surfaces in balls $B_R\subset\mathbb{S}^3$. In this article, we extend our previous half-space intersection properties to warped products, and extend (non-)umbilicity of discs and annuli to capillary minimal surfaces in high codimension. We establish a dual operation relating free boundary and capillary minimal surfaces. These results are discussed in a continuous, unified framework, particularly in relation to uniqueness of minimal annuli.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12877v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keaton Naff, Jonathan J. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An asymptotic slope of the {\alpha}-K-energy for the Kahler-Yang-Mills equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12897v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For holomorphic vector bundles over compact K\"ahler manifolds, we establish a formula for the asymptotic slope of the {\alpha}-K-energy associated with the Kahler-Yang-Mills equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12897v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akito Futaki, Jianwei Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular structures and geometric holonomy in the zero divisor set of the sedenions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study left zero divisors in the 16-dimensional sedenion algebra using explicit algebraic and geometric methods. Writing a sedenion as a pair of octonions (v1, v2), we compute the determinant of left multiplication by v and show that it factors as the fourth power of the norm times a quartic polynomial D2. The factor D2 vanishes precisely when v1 and v2 have the same norm and are orthogonal as vectors in R^8, giving a concrete polynomial criterion for nontrivial zero divisors. After normalizing by the norm, the zero divisor set becomes diffeomorphic to the Stiefel manifold V2(R^8) of orthonormal 2-frames, which we interpret as a "zero divisor frame bundle". On a suitable 3-dimensional linear slice, this set is modeled by a quadratic double cone, a structure we confirm by numerical experiments and 3-dimensional visualization. Finally, we approximate the Levi-Civita connection induced from the ambient Euclidean metric and compute parallel transport along a great-circle loop in V2(R^8); projecting the holonomy to a torus of base and fiber angles produces a curve of essentially (1,1) type. These results provide an explicit determinantal invariant and a concrete geometric picture of singular structures and holonomy in the zero divisor set of the sedenions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13002v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoot Koebisu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On diameter rigidity for K\"ahler manifolds with positive holomorphic sectional curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish some diameter rigidity for K\"ahler manifolds with positive holomorphic sectional curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13097v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianchun Chu, Man-Chun Lee, Jintian Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics of the graph Laplace operator near an isolated singularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate asymptotics of the continuous graph Laplace operator on a smooth Riemannian manifold $(M,g)$ admitting an isolated singularity $x$. We show that if the curvature function $\kappa$ doesn't grow too fast near $x$, then the graph Laplace operator at $x$ converges to the weighted Laplace-Beltrami operator as the bandwidth $t\downarrow 0.$ On the other hand, we also prove that if one locally modifies a given Riemannian metric across $x$ by a non-constant \textit{purely angular }conformal factor, then $\kappa$ grows too fast and the graph Laplace operator behaves like $O(\frac{1}{\sqrt{t}})$ near $x$, as $t\downarrow 0$, given a mild condition on the angular conformal factor. We provide the Taylor expansion of the graph Laplace operator as $t\downarrow 0$ in specific cases. Numerical simulations at the end illustrate our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13314v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Susovan Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compactification of metric moduli space of $K3$ surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13315v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a conjecture of Odaka--Oshima, which says that there is an algebraic description of the Gromov--Hausdorff compactification of all unit-diameter hyperk\"ahler metrics on K3 surfaces. As a corollary, we obtain a classification of the Gromov--Hausdorff limits of those hyperk\"ahler K3 surfaces with a fixed complex structure or with a fixed polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13315v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zexuan Ouyang, Gang Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the spectrum of the magnetic Dirac operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The magnetic Dirac operator describes the relativistic motion of a charged particle in a magnetic field. Although this operator got a lot of attention in physics many of its fundamental mathematical properties remain unexplored and this article is a first step towards filling this gap. To this end we provide a number of eigenvalue estimates for the magnetic Dirac operator on closed Riemannian manifolds and explicitly compute its spectrum for specific choices of the magnetic field on the flat torus and on the three-dimensional round sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13338v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volker Branding, Nicolas Ginoux, Georges Habib</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar Curvature in Dimension 4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that every locally conformally flat metric on a closed, oriented hyperbolic 4-manifold with scalar curvature bounded below by -12 satisfies Schoen's conjecture. We also classify all closed Riemannian 4-manifolds of positive scalar curvature that arise as total spaces of fibre bundles. For a closed locally conformally flat 4-manifold with scalar curvature zero and nontrivial second homotopy group, we show that its universal Riemannian cover is homothetic to the standard product of the hyperbolic plane and the round 2-sphere. This affirmatively answers a question of N. H. Noronha.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13528v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialong Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreducible groups and ergodicity in the boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12141v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that if $G$ is a real semi-simple Lie group, and $\Gamma$ is a discrete subgroup of $G$ containing a subgroup $\Sigma$ acting ergodically (in a strong sense) on the Furstenberg boundary of $G$, then $\Gamma$ is not isomorphic to a free product of $\Sigma$ with $\Z$. Moreover, if $\Sigma$ has algebraic entries, then $\Gamma$ has algebraic entries as well. As a consequence, we show that if all irreducible discrete subgroups of $\SL_2(\R) \times \SL_2(\R)$ act ergodically on $\mathbb{S}^1\times \mathbb{S}^1 $, such groups cannot be free groups (or even Gromov hyperbolic). In the appendix, we discuss a connection between the existence of discrete irreducible groups and diophantine properties of Lie groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12141v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhadip dey, Sebastian Hurtado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli stacks of quiver connections and non-Abelian Hodge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In arXiv:2407.11958, a moduli stack parametrizing $I$--indexed diagrams of Higgs bundles over a base stack $X$ was constructed for any finite simplicial set $I$, inspiring speculations about extending the non-Abelian Hodge correspondence to these moduli stacks. In the present work, we formalize the de Rham side of this conjectural extension. We construct moduli stacks parametrizing diagrams of bundles with $\lambda$--connections over a base prestack $X$, where $\lambda$ can be a fixed number or a parameter. Taking $\lambda$ to be $1$ gives a moduli stack parametrizing diagrams of bundles with connection, while taking it to be a parameter gives a version of Simpson's non-Abelian Hodge filtration for digrams of bundles with connection. We show that when $X$ is a smooth and projective scheme over an algebraically closed field $k$ of characteristic $0$, these moduli stacks are algebraic and locally of finite presentation, and have affine diagonal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12188v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmud Azam, Steven Rayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal rational curves on equivariant compactifications of symmetric spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12237v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $G/H$ be a symmetric space of a complex linear algebraic group $G$ and let $X$ be a nonsingular equivariant compactification of $G/H$. We investigate the question: when are minimal rational curves on $X$ orbit-closures of 1-parameter subgroups of $G$? We show that this is the case if the variety of minimal rational tangents (VMRT) at a base point in $G/H \subset X$ is Gauss-nondegenerate. Our method combines algebraic geometry of minimal rational curves with differential geometry of symmetric spaces: orbits of 1-parameter subgroups arise as holomorphic geodesics of an invariant torsion-free affine connection on $G/H$. We prove furthermore that the Gauss-nondegeneracy of VMRT holds for nonsingular equivariant compactifications of simple algebraic groups regarded as symmetric spaces. In this case, we also show that the VMRT is the closure of an adjoint orbit, which generalizes a result of Brion and Fu's on wonderful compactifications to arbitrary equivariant compactifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12237v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Muk Hwang, Qifeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Classes and Supersymmetric Berezin Volumes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12269v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We argue that modular classes of Q-manifolds provide an efficient method for addressing the existence of supersymmetric Berezin volumes in the supergeometric representation theory of the $\mathcal{N}=2$ $d=1$ supertranslation algebra. We establish a cohomological coherence criterion for the existence of a Berezin volume that is invariant under both of the supercharges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12269v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew James Bruce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and nonexistence results for a nonlocal isoperimetric problem on $\mathbb{H}^n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12621v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In Euclidean space $\mathbb{R}^n$, the minimization problem of a nonlocal isoperimetric functional with a competition between perimeter and a nonlocal term derived from the negative power of the distance function, has been extensively studied. In this paper, we investigate this nonlocal isoperimetric problem in hyperbolic space $\mathbb{H}^n$, we prove that the geodesic balls are unique minimizers (up to hyperbolic isometries) for small volumes $m$ and obtain nonexistence results for large volumes $m$ under certain ranges of the exponent in the nonlocal term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12621v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haizhong Li, Bo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigen, singular, cosine-sine, and Autonne--Takagi vectors distributions of random matrix ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12766v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that some of the best-known matrix decompositions of some of the best-known random matrix ensembles give us the unique $G$-invariant uniform distributions on some of the best-known manifolds. The eigenvectors distributions of the Gaussian, Laguerre, and Jacobi ensembles are all given by the uniform distribution on the complete flag manifold. The singular vectors distributions of Ginibre ensembles are given by the uniform distribution on a product of the complete flag manifold with a Stiefel manifold. Circular ensembles split into two types: The cosine-sine vectors distributions of circular real, unitary, and quaternionic ensembles are given by the uniform distributions on products of a (partial) flag manifold with copies of the orthogonal, unitary, or compact symplectic groups. The Autonne--Takagi vectors distributions of circular orthogonal, Lagrangian, and symplectic ensembles are given by the uniform distributions on Lagrangian Grassmannians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12766v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihan Guo, Lek-Heng Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher differentiation via higher formal groupoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We solve the differentiation problem for Lie $\infty$-groups. Our approach builds on a classical version of Cartier duality which canonically identifies the Hopf algebra of point distributions supported at the identity of a Lie group with the universal enveloping algebra of its Lie algebra. Hence, for Lie $\infty$-groups, we consider simplicial coalgebras of point distributions. To do this properly, we first develop the homotopy theory of pointed formal $\infty$-groupoids within K. Behrend and E. Getzler's framework for higher geometric stacks. These objects are "higher" but not "derived", which is an important distinction for the geometric applications in mind. The second part of our construction relies on a careful analysis of J. Pridham's variation of the Dold-Kan adjunction for cosimplicial algebras. Our main result is a differentiation functor at the level of 1-categories from finite-dimensional Lie $\infty$-groups to finite-type Lie $\infty$-algebras that is homotopically well-behaved, coordinate-free, and explicit yet tractable. In particular, if $G_\bullet$ is a simplicial Lie group with Lie algebra $\mathfrak{g}_\bullet$, we prove that the differentiation of its classifying space $\overline{\mathscr{W}}_{\! \bullet}G$ is canonically isomorphic to the dg Lie algebra of normalized chains $N_\ast(\mathfrak{g}_\bullet)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12979v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher L. Rogers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apollonian random manifolds and their bass notes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13139v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the spectrum of the Laplacian on two models of random hyperbolic 3-orbifolds, related to the Apollonian group and the super Apollonian group. We determine explicit spectral gaps for these random orbifolds. Moreover, we use our model to investigate the bass note spectrum of the set of hyperbolic 3-orbifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13139v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Hide, Bram Petri, Anna Roig-Sanchis, Joe Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity of weighted manifolds via classification results for semilinear equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13181v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study model semilinear equations on complete and non-compact weighted Riemannian manifolds with non-negative Bakry-\'Emery Ricci curvature. Our main goal is to classify positive solutions of the equation at the Sobolev-critical exponent, and furthermore to prove that the existence of such solutions implies rigidity of the manifold and triviality of the weight.
  This is possible when the weighted manifold has non-negative finite dimensional Bakry-\'Emery Ricci curvature, and even under the weaker condition of non-negative infinite dimensional Bakry-\'Emery Ricci curvature, up to imposing some additional conditions in the latter case. To exhibit the sharpness of these additional conditions, we construct a non-trivial positive solution of the critical problem on a weighted manifold with positive infinite dimensional curvature.
  We also obtain a corresponding rigidity result for solutions of the Liouville equation on weighted Riemannian surfaces. Finally, we prove some non-existence theorems when the nonlinearity is sub-critical or simply under certain volume growth conditions. In particular, the latter rules out all positive solutions on shrinking gradient Ricci solitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13181v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Ciraolo, Alberto Farina, Troy Petitt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomology of Quaternionic Foliations and Orbifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.02733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.02733v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Starting with a concise review of quaternionic geometry and quaternionic K{\"a}hler manifolds, we define a transversely quaternionic K{\"a}hler foliation. Then we formulate and prove the foliated versions of the now classical results of V.Y. Kraines and A. Fujiki on the cohomology of quaternionic K{\"a}hler manifolds. Finally, as any orbifold can be realized as the leaf space of a suitably defined Riemannian foliation we reformulate our results for quaternionic orbifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.02733v4</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rouzbeh Mohseni, Robert A. Wolak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A special class of $k$-harmonic maps inducing calibrated fibrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14074v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider two special classes of $k$-harmonic maps between Riemannian manifolds which are related to calibrated geometry, satisfying a first order fully nonlinear PDE. The first is a special type of weakly conformal map $u \colon (L^k, g) \to (M^n, h)$ where $k \leq n$ and $\alpha$ is a calibration $k$-form on $M$. Away from the critical set, the image is an $\alpha$-calibrated submanifold of $M$. These were previously studied by Cheng-Karigiannis-Madnick when $\alpha$ was associated to a vector cross product, but we clarify that such a restriction is unnecessary. The second, which is new, is a special type of weakly horizontally conformal map $u \colon (M^n, h) \to (L^k, g)$ where $n \geq k$ and $\alpha$ is a calibration $(n-k)$-form on $M$. Away from the critical set, the fibres $u^{-1} \{ u(x) \}$ are $\alpha$-calibrated submanifolds of $M$.
  We also review some previously established analytic results for the first class; we exhibit some explicit noncompact examples of the second class, where $(M, h)$ are the Bryant-Salamon manifolds with exceptional holonomy; we remark on the relevance of this new PDE to the Strominger-Yau-Zaslow conjecture for mirror symmetry in terms of special Lagrangian fibrations and to the $\mathrm{G}_2$ version by Gukov-Yau-Zaslow in terms of coassociative fibrations; and we present several open questions for future study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14074v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Iliashenko, Spiro Karigiannis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rough geometric integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a notion of distributional $k$-forms on $d$-dimensional manifolds which can be integrated against suitably regular $k$-submanifolds. Our approach combines ideas from Whitney's geometric integration [Whi57] with those of sewing approaches to rough integration [Gub04, FdLP06].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16615v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ajay Chandra, Harprit Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The de Rham cohomology of a Lie group modulo a dense subgroup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07381v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $H$ be a dense subgroup of a Lie group $G$ with Lie algebra $\mathfrak g$. We show that the (diffeological) de Rham cohomology of $G/H$ equals the Lie algebra cohomology of $\mathfrak g/\mathfrak h$, where $\mathfrak h$ is the ideal $\{Z\in\mathfrak g:\exp(tZ)\in H \text{ for all } t\in\mathbf R\}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07381v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brant Clark, Francois Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Huber Theorem revisited in dimensions 2 and 4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05541v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the second Huber theorem in dimensions 2 and 4. In dimension 2, we prove a new version assuming that the Gauss curvature lies in a negative Sobolev space using Coulomb frames. In dimension $4$, given a metric having a pointwise singularity with $L^p$-bounds on the Bach tensor, we construct a conformal metric which is regular across the singularity. To do so, we introduce another Coulomb-type condition, similar to the case of Yang--Mills connections. This enables us to obtain a conformal metric satisfying an $\varepsilon$-regularity property. We obtain a generalization of the two-dimensional case that can be applied to study the singularities of Bach-flat metrics and immersions with second fundamental forms in $W^{2,\frac{4}{3}+\varepsilon}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05541v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Laurain, Dorian Martino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vaisman Solvmanifolds as Finite Quotients of Kodaira-Thurston Nilmanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03557v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that every Vaisman solvmanifold is a finite quotient of a Kodaira-Thurston manifold. More generally, we show that every aspherical compact Vaisman manifold with strongly polycyclic fundamental group is a finite quotient of a Kodaira-Thurston manifold. As consequences, we obtain that every completely solvable solvmanifold admitting a Vaisman structure is a Kodaira-Thurston manifold, that Oeljeklaus-Toma manifolds admit no Vaisman structures (not necessarily left-invariant), and that solvmanifolds does not admit LCK Einstein-Weyl structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03557v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas H. S. Gomes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An associated bundle approach to the Bures--Wasserstein geometry of fixed rank covariance matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05873v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Bures--Wasserstein geometry of covariance matrices provides a canonical distance on the statistical manifold of centred Gaussian measures and lies at the intersection of information geometry, quantum information, and optimal transport. The space of covariance matrices admits a natural stratified structure whose strata consist of fixed-rank covariance matrices. In this paper we focus on the rank-$k$ stratum $\textrm{Sym}^+(n,k)$ and revisit its geometry through the diffeomorphic associated-bundle model $\textrm{Sym}^+(n,k)\cong\textrm{St}(n,k)\times_{O(k)}\textrm{Sym}^{+}(k)$. Working in this bundle picture, we (i) prove that the fibers are totally geodesic, (ii) derive a system of differential equations for Bures--Wasserstein geodesics, and (iii) establish a one-to-one correspondence between Grassmannian logarithms and Bures--Wasserstein logarithms on $\textrm{Sym}^+(n,k)$, and hence between minimizing geodesics in the two spaces. This alternative viewpoint clarifies the role of the underlying base $\Gr(k,n)$ in the Bures--Wasserstein geometry of low-rank covariance matrices and sets the stage for further investigations into structured covariance models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05873v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Marconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stratified manifolds with corners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21775v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define categories of stratified manifolds (s-manifolds) and stratified manifolds with corners (s-manifolds with corners). An s-manifold $\bf X$ of dimension $n$ is a Hausdorff, locally compact topological space $X$ with a stratification $X=\coprod_{i\in I}X^i$ into locally closed subsets $X^i$ which are smooth manifolds of dimension $\le n$, satisfying some conditions.
  S-manifolds can be very singular, but still share many good properties with ordinary manifolds, e.g. an oriented s-manifold $\bf X$ has a fundamental class $[\bf X]_{\rm fund}$ in Steenrod homology $H_n^{St}(X,\mathbb Z)$, and transverse fibre products exist in the category of s-manifolds.
  S-manifolds are designed for applications in Symplectic Geometry. In future work we hope to show that after suitable perturbations, the moduli spaces $\mathcal M$ of $J$-holomorphic curves used to define Gromov-Witten invariants, Lagrangian Floer cohomology, Fukaya categories, and so on, can be made into s-manifolds or s-manifolds with corners, and their fundamental classes used to define Gromov-Witten invariants, Lagrangian Floer cohomology, ....</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21775v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic Joyce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral isoperimetric inequalities for a class of mixed eigenvalue problems of the Laplacian on triangles and trapezoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11135v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, under suitable geometric constraints, we have successfully obtained characterizations for the extremum values of the functional of mixed eigenvalues of the Laplacian on triangles (or trapezoids) in the Euclidean plane $\mathbb{R}^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11135v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruifeng Chen, Jing Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Polyharmonic Liouville Hierarchy on Complete Manifolds of Nonnegative Ricci Curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04141v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a complete Liouville--type hierarchy for polyharmonic functions on Riemannian manifolds with nonnegative Ricci curvature. Extending Yau's classical result for harmonic functions and our recent biharmonic Liouville theorem, we prove that on any complete manifold of nonnegative Ricci curvature, every $k$--polyharmonic function of growth $o(r^{2(k-1)})$ must in fact be $(k-1)$--polyharmonic. Iterating this procedure yields the result that all polyharmonic functions of sublinear growth are constant.The key innovation is a new $L^{2}$ estimate for the Laplacian of a polyharmonic function, obtained by induction through a delicate cutoff construction combined with a hole--filling argument. This provides the first sharp geometric extension of the Euclidean classification of polyharmonic functions to manifolds of nonnegative Ricci curvature, and completes a natural hierarchy of Yau--type Liouville theorems for iterates of the Laplacian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04141v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John E. Bravo, Jean C. Cortissoz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Liouville's theorem and the Strong Liouville Property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14443v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore Liouville's theorem and the Strong Liouville Property (SLP) for harmonic functions on Riemannian cones and surfaces. Our approach recasts the classical Liouville property in terms of the growth of radial eigenfunctions (in the case of manifolds with rotational symmetry), allowing us to recover and sharpen known results under minimal assumptions. We provide explicit estimates for the slowest-growing nonconstant harmonic functions on cones and surfaces, and construct examples where doubling fails but Liouville and SLP still hold. Finally, we prove a nonlinear Liouville theorem for $p$-subharmonic functions, $p\geq 2$, under curvature bounds, in complete Riemannian surfaces with a pole which simultaneously recover Milnor's and Cheng--Yau's theorems as particular cases. This result appears to be new and suggests a unified geometric perspective on linear and nonlinear Liouville phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14443v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John E. Bravo, Jean C. Cortissoz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K-polystability of Fano 4-folds with large Lefschetz defect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03571v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate K-polystability on smooth complex Fano 4-folds with Lefschetz defect at least 2, focusing on the case of Lefschetz defect 3 and on Casagrande-Druel Fano 4-folds with Lefschetz defect 2. We show that exactly 5 of the 19 families of Fano 4-folds with Lefschetz defect 3 are K-polystable. Moreover, among 175 families of Casagrande-Druel Fano 4-folds with Lefschetz defect 2, we prove that 5 are K-polystable, while 132 are K-unstable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03571v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleonora A. Romano, Saverio A. Secci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Young measure relaxation gaps for controllable systems with smooth state constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we tackle the problem of the existence of a gap corresponding to Young measure relaxations for state-constrained optimal control problems. We provide a counterexample proving that a gap may occur in a very regular setting, namely for a smooth controllable system state-constrained to the closed unit ball, provided that the Lagrangian density (i.e., the running cost) is non-convex in the control variables. The example is constructed in the setting of sub-Riemannian geometry with the core ingredient being an unusual admissible curve that exhibits a certain form of resistance to state-constrained approximation. Specifically, this curve cannot be approximated by neighboring admissible curves while obeying the state constraint due to the intricate nature of the dynamics near the boundary of the constraint set. This example therefore demonstrates the impossibility of Filippov-Wazewski type approximation in the presence of state constraints. Our example also presents an occupation measure relaxation gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13776v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Augier, Milan Korda, Rodolfo Rios-Zertuche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positive paths in diffeomorphism groups of manifolds with a contact distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07279v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a cooriented contact manifold $(M,\xi)$, it is possible to define a notion of positivity on the group $\mathrm{Diff}(M)$ of diffeomorphisms of $M$, by looking at paths of diffeomorphisms that are positively transverse to the contact distribution $\xi$. We show that, in contrast to the analogous notion usually considered on the group of diffeomorphisms preserving $\xi$, positivity on $\mathrm{Diff}(M)$ is completely flexible. In particular, we show that for the standard contact structure on $\mathbb{R}^{2n+1}$ any two diffeomorphisms are connected by a positive path. This result generalizes to compactly supported diffeomorphisms on a large class of contact manifolds. As an application we answer a question about Legendrians in thermodynamic phase space posed by Entov, Polterovich and Ryzhik in the context of thermodynamic processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07279v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakob Hedicke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratic flatness and Regularity for Codimension-One Varifolds with Bounded Anisotropic Mean Curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18357v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that a $ n $-dimensional unit-density varifold $ V $ in an open subset of $ \mathbf{R}^{n+1} $ with bounded anisotropic mean curvature is $ C^{1, \alpha} $-regular almost everywhere, provided $\mathcal{H}^n \llcorner {\rm spt} \| V \| $ is absolutely continuous with respect to the weight measure $ \| V \| $. This result answers a natural question arising from the work of Allard on the regularity of varifolds with bounded anisotropic mean curvature (1986). Indeed, we prove a quadratic flatness theorem for general varifolds of bounded anisotropic mean curvature, that can be combined with Allard's local anisotropic regularity theorem to infer almost everywhere regularity. The quadratic flatness theorem is of independent interest, since it provides the first result in the literature dealing with the \emph{full support} of a~varifold with bounded anisotropic mean curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18357v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Santilli, S{\l}awomir Kolasi\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Enriquez connection for higher genus polylogarithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00486v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the variation of the Enriquez connection for higher genus polylogarithms under degenerations of Riemann surfaces with marked points, and show that this connection becomes the connection constructed by the author for degenerating families of pointed Riemann surfaces. Therefore, we have an important application that the higher genus polylogarithms derived from the Enriquez connection can be described explicitly as power series in deformation parameters and their logarithms associated with the families whose coefficients are expressed by multiple zeta values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00486v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Ichikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A general comparison principle for the pluripotential complex Monge-Amp\`ere flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06412v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a comparison principle for the pluripotential complex Monge-Amp\`ere flows for the right-hand side of the form $dt \wedge d\mu$ where $d\mu$ is dominated by a Monge-Amp\`ere measure of a bounded plurisubharmonic function. As a consequence, we obtain the uniqueness of the weak solution to the pluripotential Cauchy-Dirichlet problem. We also study the long-term behavior of the solution under some assumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06412v3</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowoo Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two new universal inequalities for Neumann eigenvalues of the Laplacian on a planar convex domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18043v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish two new universal inequalities for Neumann eigenvalues of the Laplacian on a planar convex domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18043v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kei Funano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on Regularity theory for Nonlinear elliptic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03012v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this note, we present several seminal developments in the regularity theory of nonlinear (uniformly) elliptic equations, including the De Giorgi-Nash-Moser theory concerning the Hilbert 19th problem and variational equations, as well as the Krylov-Safonov and Evans-Safonov theories for fully nonlinear equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03012v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenye Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite Convergence of the Moment-SOS Hierarchy on the Product of Spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11119v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the polynomial optimization problem of minimizing a multihomogeneous polynomial over the product of spheres. This polynomial optimization problem models the tensor optimization problem of finding the best rank one approximation of an arbitrary tensor. We show that the moment-SOS hierarchy has finite convergence in this case, for a generic multihomogeneous objective function. To show finite convergence of the hierarchy, we use a result of Huang et al. [SIAM J. Optim. 34(4) (2024), pp 3399-3428], which relies on local optimality conditions. To prove that the local optimality conditions hold generically, we use techniques from differential geometry and Morse theory. This work generalizes the main result of Huang [Optim. Lett. 17(5) (2023), pp 1263-1270], which shows finite convergence for the case of a homogeneous polynomial over a single sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11119v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sami Halaseh, Victor Magron, Mateusz Skomra</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
