<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 05:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the theoretical approach to Grassmannians and Pl\"ucker coordinates for additive skew-symmetric pairwise comparisons matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Symmetry and antisymmetry are fundamental concepts in many strict sciences. Pairwise comparisons (PC) matrices are fundamental tools for representing pairwise relations in decision making. In this theoretical study, we present a novel framework that embeds additive skew-symmetric PC matrices into the Grassmannian manifold $G(2, n)$. This framework leverages Pl\"ucker coordinates to provide a rigorous geometric interpretation of their structure. Our key result demonstrates that the algebraic consistency condition $a_{ij} + a_{jk} - a_{ki} = 0$ is equivalent to the geometric consistency of $2$-planes in $G(2, n)$, satisfying the Pl\"ucker relations. This connection reveals that the algebraic properties of PC matrices can be naturally understood through their geometric representation. Additionally, we extend this framework by interpreting PC matrices as differential $2$-forms, providing a new perspective on their consistency as a closedness condition. Our framework of linear algebra, differential geometry, and algebraic geometry, placing PC matrices in a broader mathematical context. Rather than proposing a practical alternative to existing methods, our study aims to offer a theoretical foundation for future research by exploring new insights into higher-dimensional geometry and the geometric modeling of pairwise comparisons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10014v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waldemar W. Koczkodaj, Witold Pedrycz, Alexander Pigazzini, Laura P. Pigazzini, Richard Pincak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The stability for F-Yang-Mills functional on CP^n</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10205v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the critical points of $F$-Yang-Mills functional on $\mathbb{C}P^n$, which are called $F$-Yang-Mills connections. We prove that if $(2+\frac4n)F''(x)x+(n+1)F'(x)&lt;0$, then the weakly stable $F$-Yang-Mills connection on $\mathbb{C}P^n$ must be flat. Moreover, if $(2+\frac4n)F''(x)x+(n+1)F'(x)=0$, we obtain the structure of curvatures corresponding to weakly stable connections. We also show a gap theorem for $F$-Yang-Mills connections on $\mathbb{C}P^n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10205v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomogeneity two Bazaikin spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the sectional curvature of all of the cohomogeneity two Bazaikin spaces with respect to a Riemannian metric construction due to Wilking. We show that, in contrast to the cohomogeneity one and homogeneous case, for all of the cohomogeneity two examples, the set of points with strictly positive curvature does not have full measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10253v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason DeVito, Rachel Flores</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holonomy, Zeta Functions, and Cohomological Structures in Foliated Manifolds with Stratified Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09848v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper explores the interplay between holonomy, Ihara zeta functions, and cohomological structures within the framework of ratified F-completions of foliated manifolds. We develop a novel formalism for the Gamma-set, a topological multigraph that captures intersection points of foliations with stratified boundaries, and use it to define an Ihara zeta function that encodes the manifold's symmetries. By investigating the holonomy group of spinor fields in relation to the Delta-actions on the Gamma-set, we conjecture a duality between holonomy fixed points and the poles of the Ihara zeta function, extending to twisted cohomology classes. We further analyze how the twist map T impacts cohomology within stratified spaces, highlighting the role of vector bundles and the twisted cochain complex. Applications of our framework to spectral graph theory and tiling in R^n demonstrate the power of holonomy-zeta duality in geometrically rich foliated structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09848v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Zimmerman, Nehal Doiphode</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric inequalities and rigidity of gradient shrinking Ricci solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.12725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2009.12725v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we prove that the Sobolev inequality, the logarithmic Sobolev inequality, the Schr\"odinger heat kernel upper bound, the Faber-Krahn inequality, the Nash inequality and the Rozenblum-Cwikel-Lieb inequality all equivalently exist on complete gradient shrinking Ricci solitons. We also obtain some integral gap theorems for compact shrinking Ricci solitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2009.12725v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4310/AJM.250116215812</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Asian Journal of Mathematics, Vol. 28, Issue 4 (2024), pp. 549-580</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Yong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Z2 harmonic functions on $\mathbb{R}^2$ and the polynomial Pell's equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.11893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.11893v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There has been many studies on Z2 harmonic functions, differential forms or spinors recently. This paper focuses on a very special and relatively simple aspect: Z2 harmonic functions on $\mathbb{R}^2$ with point singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.11893v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weifeng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flexibility and rigidity of conformal embeddings in Lorentzian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10346v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that for any Riemannian metric $g$ on a closed orientable surface $\Sigma$ and any spacelike embedding $f:\Sigma \rightarrow M$ in a pseudo-Riemannian manifold $(M,h)$, the embedding $f$ can be $C^{0}$-approximated by a smooth conformal embedding for $g$. If in addition, $M$ is a quotient of the $(2+1)$-dimensional solid timelike cone by a cocompact lattice of $SO^{\circ}(2,1)$, we show that the set of negatively curved metrics on $\Sigma$ that admit isometric embeddings in $M$ projects into a relatively compact set in the Teichm\"uller space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10346v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/imrn/rnae284</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int. Math. Res. Not. IMRN(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alaa Boukholkhal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diameter, Area, and Mean curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04636v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we extend diameter bounds of Simon, Topping, and Wu--Zheng to submanifolds with boundary and (potentially non-compact) ambient manifolds with minor curvature restrictions. The bound is dependent on both an integral of mean curvature and the area of the manifold. We apply our diameter bounds to minimal, constant mean curvature, and prescribed mean curvature surfaces arising in min-max constructions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04636v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory R. Chambers, Jared Marx-Kuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sandwich operators and Einstein deformations of compact symmetric spaces related to Jordan algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08770v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the deformability of the symmetric Einstein metrics on the spaces $\mathrm{SU}(n)/\mathrm{SO}(n)$ and $\mathrm{SU}(2n)/\mathrm{Sp}(n)$, thereby concluding the problem to second order for all irreducible symmetric spaces. The obstruction integrals are calculated from invariant polynomials on certain Lie algebra representations. To aid the computation, we develop so-called sandwich operators for compact Lie algebras and relate them to quadratic Casimir operators. We also explain the source of the infinitesimal Einstein deformations on irreducible symmetric spaces, except for the complex Grassmannians, by exploring their relation to simple Jordan algebras. As an application we prove the nonlinear instability of most of the infinitesimally deformable irreducible compact symmetric spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08770v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stuart James Hall, Paul Schwahn, Uwe Semmelmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable degenerations of singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.10915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.10915v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For any Kawamata log terminal (klt) singularity and any minimizer of its normalized volume function, we prove that the associated graded ring is always finitely generated, as conjectured by Chi Li. As a consequence, we complete the last step of establishing the Stable Degeneration Conjecture proposed by Chi Li and the first named author for an arbitrary klt singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.10915v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyang Xu, Ziquan Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$P=W$ via $\mathcal{H}_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.05429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.05429v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{H}_2$ be the Lie algebra of polynomial Hamiltonian vector fields on the symplectic plane. Let $X$ be the moduli space of stable Higgs bundles of fixed relatively prime rank and degree, or more generally the moduli space of stable parabolic Higgs bundles of arbitrary rank and degree for a generic stability condition. Let $H^*(X)$ be the cohomology with rational coefficients. Using the operations of cup-product by tautological classes and Hecke correspondences we construct an action of $\mathcal{H}_2$ on $H^*(X)[x,y]$, where $x$ and $y$ are formal variables. We show that the perverse filtration on $H^*(X)$ coincides with the filtration canonically associated to $\mathfrak{sl}_2\subset \mathcal{H}_2$ and deduce the $P=W$ conjecture of de Cataldo-Hausel-Migliorini.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.05429v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamas Hausel, Anton Mellit, Alexandre Minets, Olivier Schiffmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
