<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence functors in graded supergeometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been recently proved that the category of N-manifolds of degree $n$, i.e., $\mathbb N$-graded supermanifolds of degree $n$ in which the parity agrees with the gradation, is equivalent to the category of purely even $n$-tuple vector superbundles with a certain action of the symmetry group $S_n$ permuting the vector bundle structures; this can be viewed as a desuperization of N-manifolds. We put this result into a much wider context of graded structures on supermanifolds and describe explicitly several canonical equivalences of the corresponding categories in a purely geometrical and constructive way; the desuperization equivalence functor is a composition of some of them. Our constructions are completely canonical, we use such tools of supergeometry as the iterated tangent functor, the parity reversion in vector superbundles, and the modern view of $n$-tuple vector bundles as a sequence of commuting Euler vector fields of the vector bundle structures in question. All this opens new horizons in the land of graded supergeometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06366v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katarzyna Grabowska, Janusz Grabowski, Miko{\l}aj Rotkiewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Minkowski-type inequalities in certain warped product spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores the stability of Minkowski-type inequalities for hypersurfaces in warped product spaces. We establish a stability estimate that bounds the norm of the traceless second fundamental form of the hypersurface in terms of the deficit in the Minkowski inequalities satisfied by the hypersurface. Additionally, we prove the stability of Minkowski inequalities in specific cases of the Reissner-Nordstr\"om Anti-de Sitter (RN-AdS) and Anti-de Sitter Schwarzschild (AdS-Schwarzschild) manifolds, which serve as examples of warped products. We also establish a new rigidity result for locally conformally flat manifolds to understand the stability of these inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06422v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prachi Sahjwani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-existence of cohomogeneity one Einstein metrics of two summands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the non-existence of cohomogeneity one Einstein metrics on a class of compact manifolds arising as double disk bundles, whose principal orbits split into two inequivalent irreducible summands. The proof uses a phase space barrier argument that yields a new obstruction to the existence of closed cohomogeneity one Einstein metrics, even when the principal orbits admit homogeneous Einstein metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06631v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanci Chi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A $G_2$-Hilbert functional in $G_2$-geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce a new functional on the space of $G_2$-structures which we call the $G_2$-Hilbert functional. It is uniquely determined by a few basic principles inspired by the Einstein-Hilbert functional in Riemannian Geometry, and it has similar variational behaviour with it. For instance, torsion-free and nearly $G_2$-structures are saddle critical points of the volume-normalized $G_2$-Hilbert functional. This allows us to uniquely distinguish two new flows of $G_2$-structures, which can be considered as analogues of the Ricci flow in $G_2$-geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06872v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panagiotis Gianniotis, George Zacharopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The basic component of the mean curvature of Riemannian foliations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a Riemannian foliation $F$ on a compact manifold $M$ with a bundle-like metric, the de Rham complex of $M$ is $C^{\infty}$-splitted as the direct sum of the basic complex and its orthogonal complement. Then the basic component $\kappa_{b}$ of the mean curvature form of $F$ is closed and defines a class $\xi(F)$ in the basic cohomology that is invariant under any change of the bundle-like metric. Moreover, any element in $\xi(F)$ can be realized as the basic component of the mean curvature of some bundle-like metric.
  It is also proved that $\xi(F)$ vanishes iff there exists some bundle-like metric on $M$ for which the leaves are minimal submanifolds. As a consequence, this tautness property is verified in any of the following cases: (a) when the Ricci curvature of the transverse Riemannian structure is positive, or (b) when $F$ is of codimension one. In particular, a compact manifold with a Riemannian foliation of codimension one has infinite fundamental group.
  A small correction of a lemma from the original manuscript is included as an addendum, written in collaboration with Ken Richardson.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06957v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jes\'us A. \'Alvarez L\'opez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On some critical Riemannian metrics and Thorpe-type conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let \((M, g)\) be a compact, closed Riemannian manifold of dimension \(n\), and let \(k\) be an integer such that \(2 \leq 2k \leq n\). Denote by \(R^k\) the \(k\)-th Thorpe tensor, defined as the \(k\)-fold exterior product of the Riemann curvature tensor \(R\). We consider the geometric functionals $
H_{2k}(g) := \int_M \operatorname{tr}(R^k) \, \mathrm{dvol}_g$ and $ G_{2k}(g) :=\int_M \|R^k\|^2 \, \mathrm{dvol}_g,$ where \(\operatorname{tr}(R^k)\) denotes the full contraction (trace) of \(R^k\). For \(k = 1\), \(H_2(g)\) coincides with the Hilbert--Einstein functional, while \(G_2(g)\) is the \(L^2\)-norm of the Riemann curvature tensor.
  We derive the first variation formulas for \(H_{2k}\) and \(G_{2k}\), and study some properties of their critical points. In particular, we prove that an Einstein metric is critical for \(G_2\) if and only if it is critical for \(H_4\). More generally, we show that a hyper-\((2k)\)-Einstein metric is critical for \(G_{2k}\) if and only if it is critical for \(H_{4k}\).
  We further introduce and study two new classes of Riemannian metrics: the \((2k)\)-Thorpe and \((2k)\)-anti-Thorpe metrics, defined via self-duality and anti-self-duality conditions on the Thorpe tensor \(R^k\), respectively. In dimension \(n = 4k\), we show that both types are critical for \(G_{2k}\). In higher dimensions (\(n &gt; 4k\)), the same duality conditions imply that $R^k$ is harmonic. Under additional positivity assumptions on the Riemann tensor, we further deduce rigidity results for such metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06990v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Larbi Labbi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A gluing formula for the $Z_2$-valued index of odd symmetric operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07094v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate Dirac-type operator $D$ on involutive manifolds with boundary with symmetry, which forces the index of $D$ to vanish. We study the secondary $Z_2$-valued index of elliptic boundary value problems for such operators. We prove a $Z_2$-valued analog of the splitting theorem: the $Z_2$-valued index of an operator on a closed manifold $M$ equals the $Z_2$-valued index of a boundary value problem on a manifold obtained by cutting $M$ along a hypersurface $N$. When $N$ divides $M$ into two disjoint submanifolds $M_1$ and $M_2$, the $Z_2$-valued index on $M$ is equal to the mod 2 reduction of the usual $Z$-valued index of the Atiyah-Patodi-Singer boundary value problem on $M_1$. This leads to a cohomological formula for the $Z_2$-valued index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07094v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxim Braverman, Ahmad Reza Haj Saeedi Sadegh, Junrong Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nakai-Moishezon criteria and the toric Thomas-Yau conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a class of Lagrangian sections $L$ contained in certain Calabi-Yau Lagrangian fibrations (mirrors of toric weak Fano manifolds). We prove that a form of the Thomas-Yau conjecture holds in this case: $L$ is Hamiltonian isotopic to a special Lagrangian section in this class if and only if a stability condition holds, in the sense of a slope inequality on objects in a set of exact triangles in the Fukaya-Seidel category. This agrees with general proposals by Li. We use the SYZ transform, the toric gamma theorem, and toric homological mirror symmetry in order to reduce the statement to one about supercritical deformed Hermitian Yang-Mills connections, known as the Nakai-Moishezon criterion. As an application, we prove that, on the mirror of a toric weak del Pezzo surface, if $L$ defines a Bridgeland stable object in the Fukaya-Seidel category in a natural sense, then it is Hamiltonian isotopic to a special Lagrangian section in the class. The converse also holds in the example given by the blowup of the projective plane at a point. This is consistent with general conjectures due to Joyce. We discuss some generalisations, including a weaker analogue of our main result for general projective toric manifolds, and a similar obstruction, related to Lagrangian multi-sections, in a special case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07228v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Stoppa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreducible Killing and conformal Killing tensors on homogeneous plane waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a classification of irreducible Killing and conformal Killing 2-tensors on homogeneous plane waves, a specific class of Lorentzian metrics on four-dimensional manifolds. Using the framework of BGG operators, we derive explicit formulae for these tensors and identify the conditions under which they exist.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07368v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Gregorovi\v{c}, Lenka Zalabov\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criteria for codimension two singularities of surfacesand their applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07716v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give simple criteria for the singularities appearing on surfaces codimension less than or equal to two. As applications, we give conditions for codimension two singularities that appear in ruled surfaces and center maps of surfaces in the Euclidean space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07716v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kentaro Saji, Runa Shimada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The capillary $L_p$-Minkowski problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is a continuation of our recent work [54] concerning the capillary Minkowski problem. We propose, in this paper, a capillary $L_p$-Minkowski problem for $p\geq 1$, which seeks to find a capillary convex body with a prescribed capillary $L_p$-surface area measure in the Euclidean half-space. This formulation provides a natural Robin boundary analogue of the classical $L_p$-Minkowski problem introduced by Lutwak [43]. For $p&gt;1$, we resolve the capillary $L_p$-Minkowski problem in the smooth category by reducing it to a Monge-Amp\`ere equation with a Robin boundary condition on the unit spherical cap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07746v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinqun Mei, Guofang Wang, Liangjun Weng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Lie systems from Goursat distributions: reductions and reconstructions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06231v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that types of bracket-generating distributions lead to new classes of Lie systems with compatible geometric structures. Specifically, the $n$-trailer system is analysed, showing that its associated distribution is related to a Lie system if $n = 0$ or $n = 1$. These systems allow symmetry reductions and the reconstruction of solutions of the original system from those of the reduced one. The reconstruction procedure is discussed and indicates potential extensions for studying broader classes of differential equations through Lie systems and new types of superposition rules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06231v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Carballal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Riemann sphere of a C*-algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06434v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given the unital C$^*$-algebra $A$, the unitary orbit of the projector $p_0=\begin{pmatrix}1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 \end{pmatrix}$ in the C$^*$-algebra $M_2(A)$ of $2\times 2$ matrices with coefficients in $A$ is called in this paper, the Riemann sphere $R$ of $A$. We show that $R$ is a homogeneous reductive C$^\infty$ manifold of the unitary group $U_2(A)\subset M_2(A)$ and carries the differential geometry deduced from this structure (including an invariant Finsler metric). Special attention is paid to the properties of geodesics and the exponential map. If the algebra $A$ is represented in a Hilbert space $H$, in terms of local charts of $R$, elements of the Riemann sphere may be identified with (graphs of) closed operators on $H$ (bounded or unbounded). In the first part of the paper, we develop several geometric aspects of $R$ including a relation between the exponential map of the reductive connection and the cross-ratio of subspaces of $H\times H$. In the last section we show some applications of the geometry of $R$, to the geometry of operators on a Hilbert space. In particular, we define the notion of bounded deformation of an unbounded operator and give some relevant examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06434v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esteban Andruchow, Gustavo Corach, L\'azaro Recht, Alejandro Varela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On global rigidity of transversely holomorphic Anosov flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study transversely holomorphic flows, i.e. those whose holonomy pseudo-group is given by biholomorphic maps. We prove that for Anosov flows on smooth compact manifolds, the strong unstable (respectively, stable) distribution is integrable to complex manifolds, on which the flow acts holomorphically. Furthermore, assuming its complex dimension to be one, it is uniquely integrable to complex affine one-dimensional manifolds, each moreover affinely diffeomorphic to $\mathbb C$, on which the flow acts affinely. In this case, the weak stable (respectively, unstable) foliation is transversely holomorphic, and even transversely projective if the flow is assumed to be topologically transitive. By combining these facts in low dimensions, our main result is as follows : if a transversely holomorphic Anosov flow on a smooth compact five-dimensional manifold is topologically transitive, then it is either $C^\infty$-orbit equivalent to the suspension of a hyperbolic automorphism of a complex torus, or, up to finite covers, $C^\infty$-orbit equivalent to the geodesic flow of a compact hyperbolic manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06572v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mounib Abouanass</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the regularity of time-delayed embeddings with self-intersections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06712v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study regularity of the time-delayed coordinate maps \[\phi_{h,k}(x) = (h(x), h(Tx), \ldots, h(T^{k-1}x))\] for a diffeomorphism $T$ of a compact manifold $M$ and smooth observables $h$ on $M$. Takens' embedding theorem shows that if $k &gt; 2\dim M$, then $\phi_{h,k}$ is an embedding for typical $h$. We consider the probabilistic case, where for a given probability measure $\mu$ on $M$ one allows self-intersections in the time-delayed embedding to occur along a zero-measure set. We show that if $k \geq \dim M$ and $k &gt; \dim_H(\text{supp} \mu)$, then for a typical observable, $\phi_{h,k}$ is injective on a full-measure set with a pointwise Lipschitz inverse. If moreover $k &gt; \dim M$, then $\phi_{h,k}$ is a local diffeomorphism at almost every point. As an application, we show that if $k &gt; \dim M$, then the Lyapunov exponents of the original system can be approximated with arbitrary precision by almost every orbit in the time-delayed model of the system. We also give almost sure pointwise bounds on the prediction error and provide a non-dynamical analogue of the main result, which can be seen as a probabilistic version of Whitney's embedding theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06712v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam \'Spiewak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal geodesics are not variational in higher dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06739v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Variationality of the equation of conformal geodesics is an important problem in geometry with applications to general relativity. Recently it was proven that, in three dimensions, this system of equations for un-parametrized curves is the Euler-Lagrange equations of a certain conformally invariant functional, while the parametrized system in three dimensions is not variational. We demonstrate that variationality fails in higher dimensions for both parametrized and un-parametrized conformal geodesics, indicating that variational principle may be the selection principle for the physical dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06739v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Kruglikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Mass Distribution of Random Holomorphic Sections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07120v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, we prove a central limit theorem for the mass distribution of random holomorphic sections associated with a sequence of positive line bundles endowed with $\mathscr{C}^3$ Hermitian metrics over a compact K\"{a}hler manifold. In addition, we show that almost every sequence of such random holomorphic sections exhibits quantum ergodicity in the sense of Zelditch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07120v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Turgay Bayraktar, Afrim Bojnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posed geometric boundary data in General Relativity, II: Dirichlet boundary data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07128v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this second work in a series, we prove the local-in-time well-posedness of the IBVP for the vacuum Einstein equations with Dirichlet boundary data on a finite timelike boundary, provided the Brown-York stress tensor of the boundary is a Lorentz metric of the same sign as the induced Lorentz metric on the boundary. This is a convexity-type assumption which is an exact analog of a similar result in the Riemannian setting. This assumption on the (extrinsic) Brown-York tensor cannot be dropped in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07128v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongshan An, Michael T. Anderson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metrics for quandles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07535v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A quandle is an algebraic system originating in knot theory, which can be regarded as a generalization of the conjugation of groups. This structure naturally defines two subgroups of its automorphism group, which are called the inner automorphism group and the displacement group, and they act on the quandle from the right. For a quandle with such groups being finitely generated, we investigate the graph structures induced from the actions, and induced metric spaces. The graph structures are defined by the notion of the Schreier graph, which is a natural generalization of the Cayley graph for a group. In particular, the metric associated with the displacement group for an important class of quandles, namely, generalized Alexander quandles, is studied in detail. We show that such a metric space is quasi-isometric to the displacement group with a word metric. Finally, we provide some examples quasi-isometric to typical metric spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07535v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Iwamoto, Ryoya Kai, Yuya Kodama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting and equidistribution of strongly reversible closed geodesics in negative curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07738v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $M$ be a pinched negatively curved Riemannian orbifold, whose fundamental group has torsion of order $2$. Generalizing results of Sarnak and Erlandsson-Souto for constant curvature oriented surfaces, and with very different techniques, we give an asymptotic counting result on the number of strongly reversible periodic orbits of the geodesic flow in $M$, and prove their equidistribution towards the Bowen-Margulis measure. The result is proved in the more general setting with weights coming from thermodynamic formalism, and also in the analogous setting of graphs of groups with $2$-torsion. We give new examples in real hyperbolic Coxeter groups, complex hyperbolic orbifolds and graphs of groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07738v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jouni Parkkonen, Fr\'ed\'eric Paulin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.07116</link>
      <description>arXiv:1710.07116v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quasifolds are singular spaces that generalize manifolds and orbifolds. They are locally modeled by manifolds modulo the smooth action of countable groups and they are typically not Hausdorff. If the countable groups happen to be all finite, then quasifolds are orbifolds and if they happen to be all equal to the identity, they are manifolds. In this article we illustrate quasifolds by describing a two-dimensional example that displays all of their main characteristics: the quasisphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1710.07116v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisa Prato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blowing up sequences of constant mean curvature tori in $\mathbb{R}^3$ to minimal surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.01574v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is motivated by the question of whether a sequence of solutions of a given integrable system can be blown up to obtain a solution of a different integrable system in the limit. We study a specific example of this phenomenon. Namely, we describe a blow-up for immersed constant mean curvature (cmc) planes of finite type with unbounded principal curvatures and derive sufficient conditions under which this blow-up converges to a minimal surface immersion. Passing to the respective Gauss-Codazzi equations, we are blowing up a sequence of solutions to the sinh-Gordon integrable system to obtain a solution to Liouville's equation, whose integrable system will turn out to be closely related to the Korteweg-de Vries integrable system. Our most important tool for this investigation is the algebraic-geometric correspondence that was established by Pinkall/Sterling and by Hitchin for cmc planes of finite type, which include all cmc tori.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.01574v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Carberry, Sebastian Klein, Martin Ulrich Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kato meets Bakry-\'Emery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.07428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.07428v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that any complete Riemannian manifold with negative part of the Ricci curvature in a suitable Dynkin class is bi-Lipschitz equivalent to a finite-dimensional $\mathrm{RCD}$ space, by building upon the transformation rule of the Bakry-\'Emery condition under time change. We apply this result to show that our previous results on the limits of closed Riemannian manifolds satisfying a uniform Kato bound carry over to limits of complete manifolds. We also obtain a weak version of the Bishop-Gromov monotonicity formula for manifolds satisfying a strong Kato bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.07428v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gilles Carron, Ilaria Mondello, David Tewodrose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Smale conjecture and min-max theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05756v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a new proof of the Smale conjecture for $\mathbb{RP}^3$ and all lens spaces using minimal surfaces and min-max theory. For $\mathbb{RP}^3$, the conjecture was first proved in 2019 by Bamler-Kleiner using Ricci flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05756v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00222-025-01334-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Ketover, Yevgeny Liokumovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature homogeneous hypersurfaces in space forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02302v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We classify curvature homogeneous hypersurfaces in S^4 and H^4. In higher dimesnsion one only has the FKM examples and an isolate one by Tsukada of a hypersurface in H^5.
  Besides some simple examples, we show that there exists an isolated hypersurface with a circle of symmetries and and a one parameter family admitting no continuous symmetries. Outside the set of minimal points, which only exists in the case of S^4, every example is locally and up to covers of this form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02302v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Bryant, Luis Florit, Wolfgang Ziller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry on deformations of S1 singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17172v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To study a one parameter deformation of an $S_1$ singularity taking into consideration its differential geometric properties, we give a form representing the deformation using only diffeomorphisms on the source and isometries of the target. Using this form, we study differential geometric properties of $S_1$ singularities and the Whitney umbrellas appearing in the deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17172v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runa Shimada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete 3-manifolds of positive scalar curvature with quadratic decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07198v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that if an orientable 3-manifold $M$ admits a complete Riemannian metric whose scalar curvature is positive and has a subquadratic decay at infinity, then it decomposes as a (possibly infinite) connected sum of spherical manifolds and $\mathbb{S}^2 \times \mathbb{S}^1$ summands. This generalises a theorem of Gromov and Wang by using a different, more topological, approach. As a result, the manifold $M$ carries a complete Riemannian metric of uniformly positive scalar curvature, which partially answers a conjecture of Gromov. More generally, the topological decomposition holds without any scalar curvature assumption under a weaker condition on the filling discs of closed curves in the universal cover based on the notion of fill radius. Moreover, the decay rate of the scalar curvature is optimal in this decomposition theorem. Indeed, the manifold $\mathbb{R}^2 \times \mathbb{S}^1$ supports a complete metric of positive scalar curvature with exactly quadratic decay, but does not admit a decomposition as a connected sum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07198v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florent Balacheff, Teo Gil Moreno de Mora Sard\`a, St\'ephane Sabourau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blowing up Chern-Ricci flat balanced metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22241v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a compact Chern-Ricci flat balanced orbifold, we show that its blow-up at a finite family of smooth points admits constant Chern scalar curvature balanced metrics, extending Arezzo-Pacard's construction to the balanced setting. Moreover, if the orbifold has isolated singularities and admits crepant resolutions, we show that they always carry Chern-Ricci flat balanced metrics, without any further hypothesis. In addition, we discuss the general constant Chern scalar curvature balanced case and discuss another version of the main Theorem assuming the existence of a special (n-2, n-2)-form. We also present several classes of examples in which our results can be applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22241v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.matpur.2025.103691</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Pures Appl. (9) 197 (2025), Paper No. 103691, 52 pp</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Elia Fusi, Federico Giusti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Born Lie algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04856v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that every Born Lie algebra can be obtained by the bicross product construction starting from two pseudo-Riemannian Lie algebras. We then obtain a classification of all Lie algebras up to dimension four and all six-dimensional nilpotent Lie algebras admitting an integrable Born structure. Finally, we study the curvature properties of the pseudo-Riemannian metrics of the integrable Born structures obtained in our classification results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04856v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.geomphys.2025.105518</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Geometry and Physics, Volume 214, August 2025, 105518</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Gil-Garc\'ia, Paula Naomi Pilatus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open orbits in causal flag manifolds, modular flows and wedge regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11635v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study open orbits of symmetric subgroups of a simple connected
  Lie group G on a causal flag manifold.
  First we show that a flag manifold M of G carries an invariant causal structure if and only if G is hermitian
  of tube type and M is the conformal completion
  of the corresponding simple euclidean Jordan algebra,
  resp., the Shilov boundary of the associated symmetric tube domain.
  We then study open orbits in M under symmetric subgroups,
  also called causal
  Makarevic spaces, from the perspective of applications in Algebraic Quantum Field Theory (AQFT). A key motivation is the geometry of corresponding modular flows.
  The open orbits are reductive causal symmetric
  spaces, which arise in two flavors:
  compactly causal and non-compactly causal ones.
  In the non-compactly causal case we determine the corresponding Euler elements
  and their positivity regions. For compactly causal spaces,
  modular flows do not always exist and we determine
  when this is the case. Then the positivity regions of the modular flows are not globally hyperbolic,
  but these spaces contain other interesting
  globally hyperbolic subsets that can be described
  in terms of the conformally flat Jordan coordinates via Cayley charts.
  We discuss the Lorentzian case, involving de Sitter
  and anti-de Sitter space in some detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11635v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karl-Hermann Neeb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\ast$-$\eta$-Ricci solitons and Einstein metrics on a weak $\beta$-Kenmotsu manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18031v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Weak almost contact manifolds (i.e., the complex structure on the contact distribution is replaced by a nonsingular skew-symmetric tensor), defined by the author and R. Wolak, allow a new look at the classical theory. An important case of these manifolds, which is locally a twisted or warped product, is a weak $\beta$-Kenmotsu manifold defined by the author and D.S. Patra. In the paper, the concept of the $\ast$-Ricci tensor is adapted to weak almost contact manifolds, the interaction of the $\ast$-$\eta$-Ricci soliton with the weak $\beta$-Kenmotsu structure is studied and new characteristics of Einstein metrics are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18031v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Rovenski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and Computation of Geodesic Distances on Reductive Homogeneous Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04878v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many geometric machine learning and image analysis applications, require a left-invariant metric on the 5D homogeneous space of 3D positions and orientations SE(3)/SO(2). This is done in Equivariant Neural Networks (G-CNNs), or in PDE-Based Group Convolutional Neural Networks (PDE-G-CNNs), where the Riemannian metric enters in multilayer perceptrons, message passing, and max-pooling over Riemannian balls.
  In PDE-G-CNNs it is proposed to take the minimum left-invariant Riemannian distance over the fiber in SE(3)/SO(2), whereas in G-CNNs and in many geometric image processing methods an efficient SO(2)-conjugation invariant section is advocated.
  The conjecture rises whether that computationally much more efficient section indeed always selects distance minimizers over the fibers. We show that this conjecture does NOT hold in general, and in the logarithmic norm approximation setting used in practice we analyze the small (and sometimes vanishing) differences. We first prove that the minimal distance section is reached by minimal horizontal geodesics with constant momentum and zero acceleration along the fibers, and we generalize this result to (reductive) homogeneous spaces with legal metrics and commutative structure groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04878v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Remco Duits, Gijs Bellaard, Barbara Tumpach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of a Novel Model Reduction Technique to the Assessment of Boundedness/Stability of Some Delay Time-Varying Vector Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11398v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Assessing the boundedness and stability of vector nonlinear systems with variable delays and coefficients remains a challenging problem with broad applications in science and engineering. Existing methods tend to produce overly conservative criteria that offer limited practical value and often fail to explicitly characterize the temporal evolution of solution norms.
  This paper presents a novel framework for evaluating the evolution of solution norms in such systems. This approach constructs scalar counterparts for the original vector equations. We prove that the solutions to these scalar nonlinear equations, which also include delays and variable coefficients, provide upper bounds for the norms of the original solutions, if the history functions for both equations are properly matched. This reduction enables the evaluation of the boundedness and stability of vector systems through the analysis of the dynamics of their scalar counterparts, which can be performed via straightforward simulations or simplified analytical reasoning.
  Consequently, we introduce new criteria for boundedness and stability and estimate the radii of the balls containing history functions that yield bounded or stable solutions for the original vector systems. Finally, we validated our inferences through representative simulations that also assessed the accuracy of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11398v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark A. Pinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remarks on the Griffiths infinitesimal invariant of algebraic curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01907v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study two canonically defined admissible normal functions on the moduli space of smooth genus 4 algebraic curves including the Ceresa normal function. In particular, we study the vanishing criteria for the Griffiths infinitesimal invariants of both normal functions over a specific family of curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01907v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haohua Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentzian-Euclidean black holes and Lorentzian to Riemannian metric transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14108v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent papers on spacetimes with a signature-changing metric, the concept of a Lorentzian-Euclidean black hole and new elements for Lorentzian-Riemannian signature change have been introduced. A Lorentzian-Euclidean black hole is a signature-changing modification of the Schwarzschild spacetime satisfying the vacuum Einstein equations in a weak sense. Here the event horizon serves as a boundary beyond which time becomes imaginary. We demonstrate that the proper time needed to reach the horizon remains finite, consistently with the classical Schwarzschild solution. About Lorentzian to Riemannian metric transitions, we stress that the hypersurface where the metric signature changes is naturally a spacelike hypersurface which can be identified with the future or past causal boundary of the Lorentzian sector. Moreover, a number of geometric interpretations appear, as the degeneracy of the metric corresponds to the collapse of the causal cones into a line, the degeneracy of the dual metric corresponds to collapsing into a hyperplane, and additional geometric structures on the transition hypersurface (Galilean and dual Galilean) might be explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14108v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rossella Bartolo, Erasmo Caponio, Anna Valeria Germinario, Miguel S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Beltrami -- de Sitter model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12364v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We combine the well-known Beltrami-Klein model of non-Euclidean geometry on a $2-$dimensional disk, where the geodesics are the chords of the disk, with the $2-$dimensional de Sitter space. The geometry of the de Sitter space is defined on the complement of the Beltrami-Klein disk in the plane, with the de Sitter metric being the unique Lorentzian Einstein metric whose light cones form cones tangent to the disk in this complement. This leads to a Beltrami-de Sitter model on the plane ${\bf R}^2$, which is endowed with the Riemannian Beltrami metric on the disk and the Lorentzian de Sitter metric outside the disk in ${\bf R}^2$.
  We explore the relevance of this model for Penrose's Conformal Cyclic Cosmology, first in the $2-$dimensional setting and subsequently in higher dimensions, including the physically significant case of four dimensions. In this context, we define a Radon-like transform between the de Sitter and Beltrami spaces, facilitating the purely geometric transformation of physical fields from the Lorentzian de Sitter space to the Riemannian Beltrami space.
  In the $2-$, and $3-$dimensional cases, we also uncover a hidden ${\bf G}_2$ symmetry associated with the de Sitter spaces in these dimensions, which is related to a certain vector distribution naturally defined by the geometry of the model. We suggest the potential for discovering similar hidden symmetries in the $n-$dimensional Beltrami-de Sitter model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12364v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawel Nurowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new energy method for shortening and straightening complete curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03395v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a novel energy method that reinterprets ``curve shortening'' as ``tangent aligning''. This conceptual shift enables the variational study of infinite-length curves evolving by the curve shortening flow, as well as higher order flows such as the elastic flow, which involves not only the curve shortening but also the curve straightening effect. For the curve shortening flow, we prove convergence to a straight line under mild assumptions on the ends of the initial curve. For the elastic flow, we establish a global well-posedness theory, and investigate the precise long-time behavior of solutions. In fact, our method applies to a more general class of geometric evolution equations including the surface diffusion flow, Chen's flow, and the free elastic flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03395v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuya Miura, Fabian Rupp</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
