<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.DG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG</link>
    <description>math.DG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.DG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Butcher series for Hamiltonian Poisson integrators through symplectic groupoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a pre-Lie formalism of Butcher trees for the approximation of Hamilton-Jacobi solutions on any symplectic groupoid $\mathcal{G} \rightrightarrows M.$ The impact of this new algebraic approach is twofold. On the geometric side, it yields algebraic operations to approximate Lagrangian bisections of $\mathcal{G}$ using the Butcher-Connes-Kreimer Hopf algebra and, in turn, aims at a better understanding of the group of Poisson diffeomorphisms of $M.$ On the computational side, we define a new class of Poisson integrators for Hamiltonian dynamics on Poisson manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05000v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrien Busnot Laurent, Oscar Cosserat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The asymptotic of the Mullins-Sekerka and the area-preserving curvature flow in the planar flat torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic behavior of flat flow solutions to the periodic and planar two-phase Mullins-Sekerka flow and area-preserving curvature flow. We show that flat flows converge to either a finite union of equally sized disjoint disks or to a finite union of disjoint strips or to the complement of these configurations exponentially fast. A key ingredient in our approach is the derivation of a sharp quantitative Alexandrov inequality for periodic smooth sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05399v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vedansh Arya, Daniele De Gennaro, Anna Kubin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Problems on Intrinsically Harmonic Forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short note we recall the definition of intrinsically harmonic forms, some known results and some open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05496v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Bande</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warped products and synthetic lower curvature bounds: an overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is a survey about the contruction of warped products between (semi-)Riemannian manifolds and metric (measure) spaces. The resulting spaces will be semi-Riemannian manifolds, metric (measure) spaces or Lorentzian metric and metric measure spaces. We present details of the contruction in each case and we will highlight important properties like fiber independence and the energy equation. Warped products behave nicely in relation with curvature lower bounds. Here we will focus on sectional and Ricci curvature lower bounds and their Lorentzian counterparts. Throughout the article we provide many examples and formulate questions and conjectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05521v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ketterer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vectorial Kato inequality for $p$-harmonic maps with optimal constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive the sharp vectorial Kato inequality for $p$-harmonic mappings. Surprisingly, the optimal constant differs from the one obtained for scalar valued $p$-harmonic functions by Chang, Chen, and Wei. As an application we demonstrate how this inequality can be used in the study of regularity of $p$-harmonic maps. Furthermore, in the case of $p$-harmonic maps from $B^3$ to $\mathbb{S}^3$, we enhance the known range of $p$ values for which regularity is achieved. Specifically, we establish that for $p \in [2, 2.642]$, minimizing $p$-harmonic maps must be regular.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05038v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Gastel, Katarzyna Mazowiecka, Micha{\l} Mi\'skiewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypersymplectic structures invariant under an effective circle action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05272v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A hypersymplectic structure on a 4-manifold is a triple of symplectic forms for which any non-zero linear combination is again symplectic. In 2006 Donaldson conjectured that on a compact 4-manifold any hypersymplectic structure can be deformed through cohomologous hypersymplectic structures to a hyperk\"ahler triple. We prove this under the assumption that the initial structure is invariant under an effective $S^1$-action. In particular we show that the underlying 4-manifold is diffeomorphic to $\mathbb{T}^4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05272v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joel Fine, Weiyong He, Chengjian Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Riemannian Metric Learning: Closer to You than You Imagine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Riemannian metric learning is an emerging field in machine learning, unlocking new ways to encode complex data structures beyond traditional distance metric learning. While classical approaches rely on global distances in Euclidean space, they often fall short in capturing intrinsic data geometry. Enter Riemannian metric learning: a powerful generalization that leverages differential geometry to model the data according to their underlying Riemannian manifold. This approach has demonstrated remarkable success across diverse domains, from causal inference and optimal transport to generative modeling and representation learning. In this review, we bridge the gap between classical metric learning and Riemannian geometry, providing a structured and accessible overview of key methods, applications, and recent advances. We argue that Riemannian metric learning is not merely a technical refinement but a fundamental shift in how we think about data representations. Thus, this review should serve as a valuable resource for researchers and practitioners interested in exploring Riemannian metric learning and convince them that it is closer to them than they might imagine-both in theory and in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05321v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Gruffaz, Josua Sassen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic Aspects of Weil Bundles over $p$-Adic Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05567v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a systematic theory of Weil bundles over \( p \)-adic analytic manifolds, forging new connections between differential calculus over non-archimedean fields and arithmetic geometry. By developing a framework for infinitesimal structures in the \( p \)-adic setting, we establish that Weil bundles \( M^A \) associated with a \( p \)-adic manifold \( M \) and a Weil algebra \( A \) inherit a canonical analytic structure. Key results include:
  \text{Lifting theorems :} for analytic functions, vector fields, and connections, enabling the transfer of geometric data from \( M \) to \( M^A \). A \text{Galois-equivariant structure :} on Weil bundles defined over number fields, linking their geometry to arithmetic symmetries.
  A \text{cohomological comparison isomorphism:} between the Weil bundle \( M^A \) and the crystalline cohomology of \( M \), unifying infinitesimal and crystalline perspectives. Applications to Diophantine geometry and \( p \)-adic Hodge theory are central to this work. We show that spaces of sections of Hodge bundles on \( M^A \) parametrize \( p \)-adic modular forms, offering a geometric interpretation of deformation-theoretic objects. Furthermore, Weil bundles are used to study infinitesimal solutions of equations on elliptic curves, revealing new structural insights into \( p \)-adic deformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05567v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Tchuiaga, C. Dor Kewir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epstein curves and holography of the Schwarzian action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the duality between Jackiw-Teitelboim gravity and Schwarzian field theory, we show identities between the Schwarzian action of a circle diffeomorphism with (1) the hyperbolic area enclosed by the Epstein curve in the hyperbolic disk $\mathbb{D}$, (2) the asymptotic excess in the isoperimetric inequality for the equidistant Epstein foliation, (3) the variation of the Loewner energy along its equipotential foliation, and (4) the asymptotic change in hyperbolic area under a conformal distortion near the circle. From these geometric interpretations, we obtain two new proofs of the non-negativity of the Schwarzian action for circle diffeomorphisms, one from the isoperimetric inequality and the other from the monotonicity of the Loewner energy. Moreover, we show that the horocycle truncation used in Epstein's construction of the Epstein curve also defines a renormalized length of hyperbolic geodesics in $\mathbb{D}$, which coincides with the log of the bi-local observable. From this, we show that the bi-local observables on the edges of any ideal triangulation of $\mathbb{D}$ determine the circle diffeomorphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05690v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franco Vargas Pallete, Yilin Wang, Catherine Wolfram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spaces of unbounded Fredholm operators: I. Homotopy equivalences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.14359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.14359v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to the space of unbounded Fredholm operators equipped with the graph topology, the subspace of operators with compact resolvent, and their subspaces consisting of self-adjoint operators. Our main results are the following: (1) Natural maps between these four spaces and classical spaces of bounded operators representing K-theory are homotopy equivalences. This provides an alternative proof of a particular case of results of Joachim. (2) The subspace of unbounded essentially positive Fredholm operators represents odd K-theory. (3) The subspace of invertible operators in each of these spaces of unbounded operators is contractible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.14359v3</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marina Prokhorova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian $S^1$-manifolds which are like a coadjoint orbit of $G_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01825v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Consider a compact symplectic manifold of dimension $2n$ with a Hamiltionan circle action. Then there are at least $n+1$ fixed points. Motivated by recent works on the case that the fixed point set consists of precisely $n+1$ isolated points, this paper studies a Hamiltonian $S^1$ action on a $10$-dimensional compact symplectic manifold with exactly 6 isolated fixed points. We study the relations of the following data: the first Chern class of the manifold,the largest weight of the action, all the weights of the action,the total Chern class of the manifold, and the integral cohomology ring of the manifold. We show how certain data can determine the others and show the similarities of these data with those of a coadjoint orbit of the exceptional Lie group $G_2$, equipped with a Hamiltonian action of a subcircle of the maximal torus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01825v4</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sections of Lagrangian fibrations on holomorphic symplectic manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07877v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $M$ be a holomorphically symplectic manifold, equipped with a Lagrangian fibration $\pi:\; M \to X$. A degenerate twistor deformation (sometimes also called ``a Tate-Shafarevich twist'') is a family of holomorphically symplectic structures on $M$ parametrized by $H^{1,1}(X)$. All members of this family are equipped with a holomorphic Lagrangian projection to $X$, and their fibers are isomorphic to the fibers of $\pi$. Assume that $M$ is a compact hyperkahler manifold of maximal holonomy, and the general fiber of the Lagrangian projection $\pi$ is primitive (that is, not divisible) in integer homology. We also assume that $\pi$ has reduced fibers in codimension 1. Then $M$ has a degenerate twistor deformation $M'$ such that the Lagrangian projection $\pi:\; M' \to X$ admits a meromorphic section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07877v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fedor Bogomolov, Ljudmila Kamenova, Misha Verbitsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Nonlinear Extension of the Variable Projection (VarPro) Method for NURBS-based Conformal Surface Flattening</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19088v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the field of computer graphics, conformal surface flattening has been widely studied for tasks such as texture mapping, geometry processing, and mesh generation. Typically, existing methods aim to flatten a given input geometry while preserving conformality as much as possible, meaning the result is only as conformal as possible. By contrast, this study focuses on surfaces that can be flattened conformally without singularities, making the process a coupled problem: the input (or target) surface must be recursively refined while its flattening is computed.
  Although the uniformization theorem or the Riemann mapping theorem guarantees the existence of a conformal flattening for any simply connected, orientable surface, those theorems permit singularities in the flattening. If singularities are not allowed, only a special class of surfaces can be conformally flattened-though many practical surfaces do fall into this class.
  To address this, we develop a NURBS-based approach in which both the input surface and its flattening are refined in tandem, ensuring mutual conformality. Because NURBS surfaces cannot represent singularities, the resulting pair of surfaces is naturally singularity-free. Our work is inspired by the form-finding method by [Miki and Mitchell 2022, 2024], which solves bilinear PDEs by iteratively refining two surfaces together. Building on their demonstration of the effectiveness of variable projection (VarPro), we adopt a similar strategy: VarPro alternates between a linear projection and a nonlinear iteration, leveraging a partially linear (separable) problem structure. However, since our conformal condition separates into two nonlinear subproblems, we introduce a nonlinear extension of VarPro. Although this significantly increases computational cost, the quality of the results is noteworthy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19088v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaaki Miki</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
