<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math-ph</link>
    <description>math-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Categories of quantum cpos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper unites two research lines. The first involves finding categorical models of quantum programming languages and their type systems. The second line concerns the program of quantization of mathematical structures, which amounts to finding noncommutative generalizations (also called quantum generalizations) of these structures. Using a quantization method called discrete quantization, which essentially amounts to the internalization of structures in a category of von Neumann algebras and quantum relations, we find a noncommutative generalization of $\omega$-complete partial orders (cpos), called quantum cpos. Cpos are central in domain theory, and are widely used to construct categorical models of programming languages. We show that quantum cpos have similar categorical properties to cpos and are therefore suitable for the construction of categorical models for quantum programming languages, which is illustrated with some examples. For this reason, quantum cpos may form the backbone of a future quantum domain theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01816v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andre Kornell, Bert Lindenhovius, Michael Mislove</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Flow for the Riemann zeros</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01828v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, with Mussardo we defined a quantum mechanical problem of a single particle scattering with impurities wherein the quantized energy levels $E_n (\sigma)$ are exactly equal to the zeros of the Riemann $\zeta (s)$ where $\sigma = \Re (s)$ in the limit $\sigma \to 1/2$. The S-matrix is based on the Euler product and is unitary by construction, thus the underlying hamiltonian is hermitian and all eigenvalues must be real. Motivated by the Hilbert-P\'olya idea we study the spectral flows for $\{ E_n (\sigma) \}$. This leads to a simple criterion for the validity of the Riemann Hypothesis. The spectral flow arguments are simple enough that we present analogous results for the Generalized and Grand Riemann Hypotheses. We also illustrate our results for a counter example where the Riemann Hypothesis is violated since there is no underlying unitary S-matrix due to the lack of an Euler product.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01828v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e LeClair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superintegrable systems associated to commutants of Cartan subalgebras in enveloping algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a classification and explicit formulas for the elements that span the centralizer of Cartan subalgebras of complex semisimple Lie algebras of non-exceptional type in their universal enveloping algebra, and show that these generate polynomial (Poisson) algebras. The precise structure for the case of rank three simple Lie algebras is provided, and the inclusion relations between the corresponding polynomial algebras illustrated. We develop the ideas of constructing algebraic superintegrable systems and their integrals from the generators of the centralizer subalgebras and their symmetry algebra. In particular, we present explicitly one example the superintegrable system corresponding to the Cartan centralizer of $\mathfrak{so}(6,\mathbb{C})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01958v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rutwig Campoamor-Stursberg, Danilo Latini, Ian Marquette, Junze Zhang, Yao-Zhong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Hamiltonian neural Koopman operator and simultaneously sustaining and discovering conservation law</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02154v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurately finding and predicting dynamics based on the observational data with noise perturbations is of paramount significance but still a major challenge presently. Here, for the Hamiltonian mechanics, we propose the Hamiltonian Neural Koopman Operator (HNKO), integrating the knowledge of mathematical physics in learning the Koopman operator, and making it automatically sustain and even discover the conservation laws. We demonstrate the outperformance of the HNKO and its extension using a number of representative physical systems even with hundreds or thousands of freedoms. Our results suggest that feeding the prior knowledge of the underlying system and the mathematical theory appropriately to the learning framework can reinforce the capability of machine learning in solving physical problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02154v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingdong Zhang, Qunxi Zhu, Wei Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated density of states for the Poisson point interactions on $\mathbf{R}^3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We determine the principal term of the asymptotics of the integrated density of states (IDS) $N(\lambda)$ for the Schr\"odinger operator with point interactions on $\mathbf{R}^3$ as $\lambda \to -\infty$, provided that the set of positions of the point obstacles is the Poisson configuration, and the interaction parameters are bounded i.i.d.\ random variables. In particular, we prove $N(\lambda) =O(|\lambda|^{-3/2})$ as $\lambda\to -\infty$. In the case that all interaction parameters are equal to a constant, we give a more detailed asymptotics of $N(\lambda)$, and verify the result by a numerical method using R.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02256v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Kaminaga, Takuya Mine, Fumihiko Nakano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Partial Differential Equations in Different Domains by Operator Learning method Based on Boundary Integral Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article explores operator learning models that can deduce solutions to partial differential equations (PDEs) on arbitrary domains without requiring retraining. We introduce two innovative models rooted in boundary integral equations (BIEs): the Boundary Integral Type Deep Operator Network (BI-DeepONet) and the Boundary Integral Trigonometric Deep Operator Neural Network (BI-TDONet), which are crafted to address PDEs across diverse domains. Once fully trained, these BIE-based models adeptly predict the solutions of PDEs in any domain without the need for additional training. BI-TDONet notably enhances its performance by employing the singular value decomposition (SVD) of bounded linear operators, allowing for the efficient distribution of input functions across its modules. Furthermore, to tackle the issue of function sampling values that do not effectively capture oscillatory and impulse signal characteristics, trigonometric coefficients are utilized as both inputs and outputs in BI-TDONet. Our numerical experiments robustly support and confirm the efficacy of this theoretical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02298v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Meng, Yutong Lu, Ying Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Around the codifferential of products of p-forms and generalized interior products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Identities pertaining to the de Rham codifferential {\delta} in differential geometry are scattered in the literature. This article gathers such formulas involving usual differential operators (Lie derivative, Schouten-Nijenhuis bracket, ...), while adding a few new ones using a natural extension of the interior product, to provide a compact handy summary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02476v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Huguet, J. Queva, J. Renaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Free-fermion Formulation of Two-dimensional Ising Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00232v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ising model is a famous toy model in condensed matter and statistical physics. In this work we present a free-fermion formulation of the two-dimensional classical Ising models on the honeycomb, triangular and Kagom\'e lattices. Each Ising model is studied in the case of a zero field and the case of an imaginary field i({\pi}/2)k_BT. We employ the decorated lattice technique, star-triangle transformation and weak-graph expansion method to exactly map each Ising model in both cases into an eight-vertex model on the square lattice. The resulting vertex weights are shown to satisfy the free-fermion condition. In the zero field case, each Ising model is an even free-fermion model. In the case of the imaginary field, the Ising model on the honeycomb lattice is an even free-fermion model while those on the triangular and Kagom\'e lattices are odd free-fermion models. The exact solution of the Kagom\'e lattice Ising model in the imaginary field i({\pi}/2)k_BT is obtained, which has not been reported in previous works. The frustrated Ising models on the triangular and Kagom\'e lattices in the imaginary field still exhibit a non-zero residual entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00232v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>De-Zhang Li, Xin Wang, Xiao-Bao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schr\"{o}dinger Bridge with Quadratic State Cost is Exactly Solvable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Schr\"odinger bridge is a diffusion process that steers a given distribution to another in a prescribed time while minimizing the effort to do so. It can be seen as the stochastic dynamical version of the optimal mass transport, and has growing applications in generative diffusion models and stochastic optimal control. In this work, we propose a regularized variant of the Schr\"odinger bridge with a quadratic state cost-to-go that incentivizes the optimal sample paths to stay close to a nominal level. Unlike the conventional Schr\"odinger bridge, the regularization induces a state-dependent rate of killing and creation of probability mass, and its solution requires determining the Markov kernel of a reaction-diffusion partial differential equation. We derive this Markov kernel in closed form. Our solution recovers the heat kernel in the vanishing regularization (i.e., diffusion without reaction) limit, thereby recovering the solution of the conventional Schr\"odinger bridge. Our results enable the use of dynamic Sinkhorn recursion for computing the Schr\"odinger bridge with a quadratic state cost-to-go, which would otherwise be challenging to use in this setting. We deduce properties of the new kernel and explain its connections with certain exactly solvable models in quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00503v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis M. H. Teter, Wenqing Wang, Abhishek Halder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pivoting through the chiral-clock family</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01680v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Onsager algebra, invented to solve the two-dimensional Ising model, can be used to construct conserved charges for a family of integrable $N$-state chiral clock models. We show how it naturally gives rise to a "pivot" procedure for this family of chiral Hamiltonians. These Hamiltonians have an anti-unitary CPT symmetry that when combined with the usual $\mathbb{Z}_N$ clock symmetry gives a non-abelian dihedral symmetry group $D_{2N}$. We show that this symmetry gives rise to symmetry-protected topological (SPT) order in this family for all even $N$, and representation-SPT (RSPT) physics for all odd $N$. The simplest such example is a next-nearest-neighbour chain generalising the spin-1/2 cluster model, an SPT phase of matter. We derive a matrix-product state representation of its fixed-point ground state along with the ensuing entanglement spectrum and symmetry fractionalisation. We analyse a rich phase diagram combining this model with the Onsager-integrable chiral Potts chain, and find trivial, symmetry-breaking and (R)SPT orders, as well as extended gapless regions. For odd $N$, the phase transitions are "unnecessarily" critical from the SPT point of view.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01680v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick G. Jones, Abhishodh Prakash, Paul Fendley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bit by Bit: Gravity Through the Lens of Quantum Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01695v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This dissertation reviews several recent advances at the intersection of quantum information and holography. In holography, properties of quantum systems admit a gravitational interpretation via the AdS/CFT correspondence. For holographic states, boundary entanglement entropy is dual to bulk geodesic areas, known as Ryu-Takayanagi surfaces. Furthermore, the viability to possess a holographic dual at all is constrained by entanglement structure. Accordingly, entanglement enables a coarse classification of states in a Hilbert space. Similarly, state transformation under operator groups also provides a classification on the Hilbert space. Stabilizer states, for example, are invariant under large sets of operations and consequently can be simulated on a classical computer. Cayley graphs offer a useful representation for a group of operators, where vertices represent group elements and edges represent generators. The orbit of a state under action of the group can also be represented as a "reachability graph", a quotient of the group Cayley graph. Reachability graphs can be dressed to encode entanglement information, making them a useful tool for studying entanglement dynamics. Quotienting a reachability graph by group elements that fix a state computable, e.g. entanglement entropy, builds a "contracted graph". Contracted graphs explicitly bound state parameter evolution in quantum circuits. In this thesis, an upper bound on entanglement entropy evolution in Clifford circuits is presented. Another important property of quantum systems is magic, which quantifies the difficulty of simulating a quantum state. Magic and entanglement play complementary roles when describing emergent phenomena in AdS/CFT. This work describes the interplay of entanglement and magic, offering holographic consequences for magic as cosmic brane back-reaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01695v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ASU Electronic Theses and Dissertations, May 2, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>William Munizzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The density conjecture for activated random walk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01731v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the late 1990s, Dickman, Mu\~noz, Vespignani, and Zapperi explained the self-organized criticality observed by Bak, Tang, and Wiesenfeld as an external force pushing a hidden parameter toward the critical value of a traditional absorbing-state phase transition. As evidence, they observed empirically that for various sandpile models the particle density in a finite box under driven-dissipative dynamics converges to the critical density of an infinite-volume version of the model. We give the first proof of this well-known density conjecture in any setting by establishing it for activated random walk in one dimension. We prove that two other natural versions of the model have the same critical value, further establishing activated random walk as a universal model of self-organized criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01731v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Hoffman, Tobias Johnson, Matthew Junge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homoclinic Solution to Zero of a Non-autonomous, Nonlinear, Second Order Differential Equation with Quadratic Growth on the Derivative</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01772v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work aims to obtain a positive, smooth, even, and homoclinic to zero (i.e zero at infinity) solution to a non-autonomous, second-order, nonlinear differential equation involving quadratic growth on the derivative. We apply Galerkin's method combined with Strauss' approximation on the term involving the first derivative to obtain weak solutions. We also study the regularity of the solutions and the dependence on their existence with a parameter</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01772v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo dos Santos Corr\^ea Junior, Luiz Fernando de Oliveira Faria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projective and Carrollian geometry at time/space-like infinity on projectively compact Ricci flat Einstein manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01800v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article we discuss how to construct canonical \emph{strong} Carrollian geometries at time/space like infinity of projectively compact Ricci flat Einstein manifolds $(M,g)$ and discuss the links between the underlying projective structure of the metric $g$. The obtained Carrollian geometries are determined by the data of the projective compactification. The key idea to achieve this is to consider a new type of Cartan geometry based on a non-effective homogeneous model for projective geometry. We prove that this structure is a general feature of projectively compact Ricci flat Einstein manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01800v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Borthwick, Yannick Herfray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Common Solution Space of General Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01998v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review the solution space for the field equations of Einstein's General Relativity for various static, spherically symmetric spacetimes. We consider the vacuum case, represented by the Schwarzschild black hole; the de Sitter-Schwarzschild geometry, which includes a cosmological constant; the Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m geometry, which accounts for the presence of charge. Additionally we consider the homogenenous and anisotropic locally rotational Bianchi II spacetime in the vacuum. Our analysis reveals that the field equations for these scenarios share a common three-dimensional group of point transformations, with the generators being the elements of the $D\otimes_{s}T_{2}$ Lie algebra, known as the semidirect product of dilations and translations in the plane. Due to this algebraic property the field equations for the aforementioned gravitational models can be expressed in the equivalent form of the null geodesic equations for conformally flat geometries. Consequently, the solution space for the field equations is common, and it is the solution space for the free particle in a flat space. This appoach open new directions on the construction of analytic solutions in gravitational physics and cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01998v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andronikos Paliathanasis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogeneous nucleation for two-dimensional Kawasaki dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the third in a series of three papers in which we study a lattice gas subject to Kawasaki dynamics at inverse temperature $\beta&gt;0$ in a large finite box $\Lambda_\beta \subset \mathbb{Z}^2$ whose volume depends on $\beta$. Each pair of neighbouring particles has a negative binding energy $-U&lt;0$, while each particle has a positive activation energy $\Delta&gt;0$. The initial configuration is drawn from the grand-canonical ensemble restricted to the set of configurations where all the droplets are subcritical. Our goal is to describe, in the metastable regime $\Delta \in (U,2U)$ and in the limit as $\beta\to\infty$, how and when the system nucleates, i.e., creates a critical droplet somewhere in $\Lambda_\beta$ that subsequently grows by absorbing particles from the surrounding gas.
  In the first paper we showed that subcritical droplets behave as quasi-random walks. In the second paper we used the results in the first paper to analyse how subcritical droplets form and dissolve on multiple space-time scales when the volume is moderately large, namely, $|\Lambda_\beta| = \mathrm{e}^{\theta\beta}$ with $\Delta &lt; \theta &lt; 2\Delta-U$. In the present paper we consider the setting where the volume is very large, namely, $|\Lambda_\beta| = \mathrm{e}^{\Theta\beta}$ with $\Delta &lt; \Theta &lt; \Gamma-(2\Delta-U)$, where $\Gamma$ is the energy of the critical droplet in the local model with fixed volume, and use the results in the first two papers to identify the nucleation time and the tube of typical trajectories towards nucleation. We will see that in a very large volume critical droplets appear more or less independently in boxes of moderate volume, a phenomenon referred to as homogeneous nucleation. One of the key ingredients in the proof is an estimate showing that no information can travel between these boxes on relevant time scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02099v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Baldassarri, Alexandre Gaudilli\`ere, Frank den Hollander, Francesca Romana Nardi, Enzo Olivieri, Elisabetta Scoppola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the non-uniqueness of the energy-momentum and spin currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The macroscopic energy-momentum and spin densities of relativistic spin hydrodynamics are obtained from the ensemble average of their respective microscopic definitions (quantum operators). These microscopic definitions suffer from ambiguities, meaning that, one may obtain different forms of symmetric energy-momentum tensor and spin tensor through pseudogauge transformations (or in other words Belinfante improvement procedure). However, this ambiguity can be removed if we obtain these currents using Noether's second theorem instead of widely used Noether's first theorem. In this article, we use Noether's second theorem to derive (symmetric) energy-momentum tensor and (antisymmetric) spin tensor without the need of pseudogauge transformations for free Dirac massive particles with spin one-half.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02127v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajeev Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication Complexity of Graph Isomorphism, Coloring, and Distance Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02199v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quantum information, nonlocal games are particularly useful for differentiating classical, quantum, and non-signalling correlations. An example of differentiation is given by the principle of no-collapse of communication complexity, which is often interpreted as necessary for a feasible physical theory. It is satisfied by quantum correlations but violated by some non-signalling ones.
  In this work, we investigate this principle in the context of three nonlocal games related to graph theory, starting from the well-known graph isomorphism and graph coloring games, and introducing a new game, the vertex distance game, with a parameter $D\in\mathbb N$, that generalizes the former two to some extent. For these three games, we prove that perfect non-signalling strategies collapse communication complexity under favorable conditions. We also define a refinement of fractional isomorphism of graphs, namely D-fractional isomorphisms, and we show that this characterizes perfect non-signalling strategies for the vertex distance game. Surprisingly, we observe that non-signalling strategies provide a finer distinction for the new game compared to classical and quantum strategies since the parameter D is visible only in the non-signalling setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02199v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Botteron, Moritz Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The geometric Toda equations for noncompact symmetric spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02323v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper has two purposes. The first is to classify all those versions of the Toda equations which govern the existence of $\tau$-primitive harmonic maps from a surface into a homogeneous space $G/T$ for which $G$ is a noncomplex noncompact simple real Lie group and $T$ is a maximal compact torus, i.e., a maximal torus inside a maximal compact subgroup $H &lt; G$. Here $\tau$ is the Coxeter automorphism which Drinfel'd &amp; Sokolov assigned to each affine Dynkin diagram. This allows $\tau$ to be either an inner or an outer automorphism. We show that, up to equivalence, the real forms $G&lt;G^\mathbb{C}$ which are compatible with $\tau$ can be classified using a simple labelling of the corresponding affine diagram.
  The second purpose is to establish when stability criteria can be used to prove the existence of solutions. We interpret the Toda equations over a compact Riemann surface $\Sigma$ as equations for a metric on a holomorphic principal $T^\mathbb{C}$-bundle $Q^\mathbb{C}$ over $\Sigma$. The corresponding Chern connection, when combined with a holomorphic field $\varphi$, produces a $G$-connection which is flat precisely when the Toda equations hold. We call the pair $(Q^\mathbb{C},\varphi)$ a Toda pair. We classify those real forms of the Toda equations for which the Toda pair is a principal pair (in the sense of Bradlow et al.) and we call these totally noncompact Toda pairs. Using the stability theory for principal pairs we prove that for totally noncompact cyclic Toda pairs $(Q^\mathbb{C},\varphi)$ the corresponding Toda equations always admit solutions. Every solution to the geometric Toda equations has a corresponding $G$-Higgs bundle. We explain how to construct this $G$-Higgs bundle directly from the Toda pair and show that Baraglia's cyclic Higgs bundles arise from a very special case of totally noncompact cyclic Toda pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02323v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian McIntosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral representation in Klein space: simplifying celestial leaf amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the spectral representation in Klein space which is the split $(2,2)$ signature flat spacetime. The Klein space can be foliated into Lorentzian $\mathrm{AdS}_3 /\mathbb{Z}$ slices, and its identity resolution has both continuous and discrete parts. We calculate the identity resolution, and the plancherel measure in these slices. Using the foliation of Klein space into the slices, and the identity resolution, and the plancherel measure in each slices, we compute the spectral representation of the massive bulk-to-bulk propagator in Klein space. It can be expressed as the sum of product of two massive (or tachyonic) conformal primary wavefunctions, with both continuous and discrete parts, and sharing a common boundary coordinate. An interesting point in Klein space is that since the identity resolution has both discrete and continuous parts, a new type of conformal primary wavefunction naturally arises for the massive (or tachyonic) case. For the conformal primary wavefunctions, both the discrete and continuous parts involve integrating over the common boundary coordinate and the real (or imaginary) mass. In the discrete part, the conformal dimension is summed, whereas in the continuous part, it is integrated. The spectral representation in Klein space is a computational tool to derive conformal block expansions for celestial amplitude in Klein space and its building blocks called celestial leaf amplitudes, by integrating the particle interaction vertex over a single slice of foliation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02342v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarthak Duary, Sourav Maji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Braided scalar quantum field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02372v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We formulate scalar field theories in a curved braided $L_\infty$-algebra formalism and analyse their correlation functions using Batalin-Vilkovisky quantization. We perform detailed calculations in cubic braided scalar field theory up to two-loop order and three-point multiplicity. The divergent tadpole contributions are eliminated by a suitable choice of central curvature for the $L_\infty$-structure, and we confirm the absence of UV/IR mixing. The calculations of higher loop and higher multiplicity correlators in homological perturbation theory are facilitated by the introduction of a novel diagrammatic calculus. We derive an algebraic version of the Schwinger-Dyson equations based on the homological perturbation lemma, and use them to prove the braided Wick theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02372v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Djorjde Bogdanovi\'c, Marija Dimitrijevi\'c \'Ciri\'c, Voja Radovanovi\'c, Richard J. Szabo, Guillaume Trojani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence, Uniqueness and Asymptotic Dynamics of Nonlinear Schr\"odinger Equations With Quasi-Periodic Initial Data: II. The Derivative NLS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02512v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the second part of a two-paper series studying the nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with quasi-periodic initial data. In this paper, we focus on the quasi-periodic Cauchy problem for the derivative nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation. Under the assumption that the Fourier coefficients of the initial data obey an exponential upper bound, we establish local existence of a solution that retains quasi-periodicity in space with a slightly weaker Fourier decay. Moreover, the solution is shown to be unique within this class of quasi-periodic functions. Also, we prove that, for the derivative nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation in a weakly nonlinear setting, within the time scale, as the small parameter of nonlinearity tends to zero, the nonlinear solution converges asymptotically to the linear solution in the sense of both sup-norm and analytic Sobolev-norm.
  The proof proceeds via a consideration of an associated infinite system of coupled ordinary differential equations for the Fourier coefficients and an explicit combinatorial analysis for the Picard iteration with the help of Feynman diagrams and the power of $\ast^{[\cdot]}$ labelling the complex conjugate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02512v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Damanik (Rice University), Yong Li (Jilin University), Fei Xu (Jilin University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jacobi Group Symmetry of Hamilton's Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.10766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.10766v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the diffeomorphisms of an extended phase space with time, energy, momentum and position degrees of freedom that leave invariant the symplectic 2-form and and a degenerate orthogonal metric dt^2 locally satisfy Hamilton's equations up to the usual canonical transformations on the position-momentum subspace.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.10766v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen G. Low, Rutwig Campoamor-Stursberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic quantization of two-dimensional $P(\Phi)$ Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.04137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.04137v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a simple and self-contained construction of of the $P(\Phi)$ Euclidean Quantum Field Theory in the plane and verify the Osterwalder-Schrader axioms: translational and rotational invariance, reflection positivity and regularity. In the intermediate steps of the construction we study measures on spheres. In order to control the infinite volume limit we use the parabolic stochastic quantization equation and the energy method. To prove the translational and rotational invariance of the limit measure we take advantage of the fact that the symmetry groups of the plane and the sphere have the same dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.04137v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00023-024-01447-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pawe{\l} Duch, Wojciech Dybalski, Azam Jahandideh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embezzlement of entanglement, quantum fields, and the classification of von Neumann algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07299v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the quantum information theoretic task of embezzlement of entanglement in the setting of von Neumann algebras. Given a shared entangled resource state, this task asks to produce arbitrary entangled states using local operations without communication while perturbing the resource arbitrarily little. We quantify the performance of a given resource state by the worst-case error. States for which the latter vanishes are 'embezzling states' as they allow to embezzle arbitrary entangled states with arbitrarily small error. The best and worst performance among all states defines two algebraic invariants for von Neumann algebras. The first invariant takes only two values. Either it vanishes and embezzling states exist, which can only happen in type III, or no state allows for nontrivial embezzlement. In the case of factors not of finite type I, the second invariant equals the diameter of the state space. This provides a quantitative operational interpretation of Connes' classification of type III factors within quantum information theory. Type III$_1$ factors are 'universal embezzlers' where every state is embezzling. Our findings have implications for relativistic quantum field theory, where type III algebras naturally appear. For instance, they explain the maximal violation of Bell inequalities in the vacuum. Our results follow from a one-to-one correspondence between embezzling states and invariant probability measures on the flow of weights. We also establish that universally embezzling ITPFI factors are of type III$_1$ by elementary arguments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07299v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lauritz van Luijk, Alexander Stottmeister, Reinhard F. Werner, Henrik Wilming</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong ill-posedness in $L^{\infty}$ of the 2d Boussinesq equations in vorticity form and application to the 3d axisymmetric Euler Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16167v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the strong ill-posedness in the sense of Hadamard of the two-dimensional Boussinesq equations in $W^{1, \infty}(\mathbb{R}^2)$ without boundary, extending to the case of systems the method that Shikh Khalil \&amp; Elgindi arXiv:2207.04556v1 developed for scalar equations. We provide a large class of initial data with velocity and density of small $W^{1, \infty}(\mathbb{R}^2)$ size, for which the horizontal density gradient has a strong $L^{\infty}(\mathbb{R}^2)$-norm inflation in infinitesimal time, while the vorticity and the vertical density gradient remain bounded. Furthermore, exploiting the three-dimensional version of Elgindi's decomposition of the Biot-Savart law, we apply the method to the three-dimensional axisymmetric Euler equations with swirl and away from the vertical axis, showing that a large class of initial data with velocity field uniformly bounded in $W^{1, \infty}(\mathbb{R}^2)$ provides a solution whose swirl component has a strong $W^{1, \infty}(\mathbb{R}^2)$-norm inflation in infinitesimal time, while the potential vorticity remains bounded at least for small times. Finally, the $W^{1,\infty}$-norm inflation of the swirl (and the $L^{\infty}$-norm inflation of the vorticity field) is quantified from below by an explicit lower bound which depends on time, the size of the data and it is valid for small times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16167v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberta Bianchini, Lars Eric Hientzsch, Felice Iandoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Droplet dynamics in a two-dimensional rarefied gas under Kawasaki dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.14099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.14099v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This is the second in a series of three papers in which we study a lattice gas subject to Kawasaki conservative dynamics at inverse temperature $\beta&gt;0$ in a large finite box $\Lambda_\beta \subset\mathbb Z^2$ whose volume depends on $\beta$. Each pair of neighbouring particles has a negative binding energy $-U&lt;0$, while each particle has a positive activation energy $\Delta&gt;0$. The initial configuration is drawn from the grand-canonical ensemble restricted to the set of configurations where all the droplets are subcritical. Our goal is to describe, in the metastable regime $\Delta\in(U,2U)$ and in the limit as $\beta\to\infty$, how and when the system nucleates.
  In the first paper we showed that subcritical droplets behave as quasi-random walks. In the present paper we use the results in the first paper to analyse how subcritical droplets form and dissolve on multiple space-time scales when the volume is moderately large, i.e., $|\Lambda_\beta|=\mathrm e^{\Theta\beta}$ with $\Delta&lt;\Theta&lt;2\Delta-U$. In the third paper we consider the setting where the volume is very large, namely, $|\Lambda_\beta|=\mathrm e^{\Theta\beta}$ with $\Delta&lt;\Theta&lt;\Gamma-(2\Delta-U)$, where $\Gamma$ is the energy of the critical droplet in the local model with fixed volume, and use the results in the first two papers to identify the nucleation time. We will see that in a very large volume critical droplets appear more or less independently in boxes of moderate volume, a phenomenon referred to as homogeneous nucleation.
  Since Kawasaki dynamics is conservative, i.e., particles are preserved, we need to control non-local effects in the way droplets are formed and dissolved. This is done via a deductive approach: the tube of typical trajectories leading to nucleation is described via a series of events on which the evolution of the gas consists of droplets wandering around on multiple space-time scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.14099v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Baldassarri, Alexandre Gaudilli\`ere, Frank den Hollander, Francesca Romana Nardi, Enzo Olivieri, Elisabetta Scoppola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new quantum computational set-up for algebraic topology via simplicial sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11304v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, a quantum computational framework for algebraic topology based on simplicial set theory is presented. This extends previous work, which was limited to simplicial complexes and aimed mostly to topological data analysis. The proposed set--up applies to any parafinite simplicial set and proceeds by associating with it a finite dimensional simplicial Hilbert space, whose simplicial operator structure is studied in some depth. It is shown in particular how the problem of determining the simplicial set's homology can be solved within the simplicial Hilbert framework. Further, the conditions under which simplicial set theoretic algorithms can be implemented in a quantum computational setting with finite resources are examined. Finally a quantum algorithmic scheme capable to compute the simplicial homology spaces and Betti numbers of a simplicial set combining a number of basic quantum algorithms is outlined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11304v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Zucchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry Connections for 2d $(2,2)$ Theories, Monopole Spectral Data &amp; (Generalised) Cohomology Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08454v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study Berry connections for supersymmetric ground states of 2d $\mathcal{N}=(2,2)$ GLSMs quantised on a circle, which are generalised periodic monopoles. Periodic monopole solutions may be encoded into difference modules, as shown by Mochizuki, or into an alternative algebraic construction given in terms of vector bundles endowed with filtrations. By studying the ground states in terms of a one-parameter family of supercharges, we relate these two different kinds of spectral data to the physics of the GLSMs. From the difference modules we derive novel difference equations for brane amplitudes, which in the conformal limit yield novel difference equations for hemisphere or vortex partition functions. When the GLSM flows to a nonlinear sigma model with K\"ahler target $X$, we show that the two kinds of spectral data are related to different (generalised) cohomology theories: the difference modules are related to the equivariant quantum cohomology of $X$, whereas the vector bundles with filtrations are related to its equivariant K-theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08454v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea E. V. Ferrari, Daniel Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The harmonic oscillator on the Moyal-Groenewold plane: an approach via Lie groups and twisted Weyl tuples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.06143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.06143v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the functional calculus of the harmonic oscillator on each Moyal-Groenewold plane, the noncommutative phase space which is a fundamental object in quantum mechanics. Specifically, we show that the harmonic oscillator admits a bounded $\mathrm{H}^\infty(\Sigma_\omega)$ functional calculus for any angle $0 &lt; \omega &lt; \frac{\pi}{2}$ and even a bounded H\"ormander functional calculus on the associated noncommutative $\mathrm{L}^p$-spaces, where $\Sigma_\omega=\{ z \in \mathbb{C}^*: |\arg z| &lt;\omega \}$. To achieve these results, we develop a connection with the theory of 2-step nilpotent Lie groups by introducing a notion of twisted Weyl tuple and connecting it to some semigroups of operators previously investigated by Robinson via group representations. Along the way, we demonstrate that $\mathrm{L}^p$-square-max decompositions lead to new insights between noncommutative ergodic theory and $R$-boundedness, and we prove a twisted transference principle, which is of independent interest. Our approach accommodate the presence of a constant magnetic field and they are indeed new even in the framework of magnetic Weyl calculus on classical $\mathrm{L}^p$-spaces. Our results contribute to the understanding of functional calculi on noncommutative spaces and have implications for the maximal regularity of the most basic evolution equations associated to the harmonic oscillator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.06143v4</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Arhancet, Lukas Hagedorn, Christoph Kriegler, Pierre Portal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization of K\"ahler Manifolds via Brane Quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14574v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In their physical proposal for quantization [20], Gukov-Witten suggested that, given a symplectic manifold $M$ with a complexification $X$, the A-model morphism spaces $\operatorname{Hom}(\mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}}, \mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}})$ and $\operatorname{Hom}(\mathcal{B}, \mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}})$ should recover holomorphic deformation quantization of $X$ and geometric quantization of $M$ respectively, where $\mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}}$ is a canonical coisotropic A-brane on $X$ and $\mathcal{B}$ is a Lagrangian A-brane supported on $M$.
  Assuming $M$ is spin and K\"ahler with a prequantum line bundle $L$, Chan-Leung-Li [10] constructed a subsheaf $\mathcal{O}_{\operatorname{qu}}^{(k)}$ of smooth functions on $M$ with a non-formal star product and a left $\mathcal{O}_{\operatorname{qu}}^{(k)}$-module structure on the sheaf of holomorphic sections of $L^{\otimes k} \otimes \sqrt{K}$.
  In this paper, we give a careful treatment of the relation between (holomorphic) deformation quantizations of $M$ and $X$. As a result, Chan-Leung-Li's work [10] provides a mathematical realization of the action of $\operatorname{Hom}(\mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}}, \mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}})$ on $\operatorname{Hom}(\mathcal{B}, \mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}})$. By Fedosov's gluing arguments, we also construct a $\mathcal{O}_{\operatorname{qu}}^{(k)}$-$\overline{\mathcal{O}}_{\operatorname{qu}}^{(k)}$-bimodule structure on the sheaf of smooth sections of $L^{\otimes 2k}$ to realize the actions of $\operatorname{Hom}(\mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}}, \mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}})$ and $\operatorname{Hom}(\overline{\mathcal{B}}_{\operatorname{cc}}, \overline{\mathcal{B}}_{\operatorname{cc}})$ on $\operatorname{Hom}(\overline{\mathcal{B}}_{\operatorname{cc}}, \mathcal{B}_{\operatorname{cc}})$, which is related to the analytic geometric Langlands program.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14574v3</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>YuTung Yau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracy-Widom distribution in four-dimensional super-Yang-Mills theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13050v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Various observables in different four-dimensional superconformal Yang-Mills theories can be computed exactly as Fredholm determinants of truncated Bessel operators. We exploit this relation to determine their dependence on the 't Hooft coupling constant. Unlike the weak coupling expansion, which has a finite radius of convergence, the strong coupling expansion is factorially divergent, necessitating the inclusion of nonperturbative, exponentially small corrections. We develop a method to systematically compute these corrections and discuss the resurgent properties of the resulting transseries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13050v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zoltan Bajnok, Bercel Boldis, Gregory P. Korchemsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Solutions in Polynomial Affine Gravity with Torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11703v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Polynomial Affine Gravity is an alternative gravitational model, where the interactions are mediated solely by the affine connection, instead of the metric tensor. In this paper, we explore the space of solutions to the field equations when the torsion fields are turned on, in a homogeneous and isotropic (cosmological) scenario. We explore various metric structures that emerge in the space of solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11703v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Castillo-Felisola, Bastian Grez, Gonzalo J. Olmo, Oscar Orellana, Jos\'e Perdiguero G\'arate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Virasoro fusion and modular kernels at any irrational central charge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09325v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a series representation for the Virasoro fusion and modular kernels at any irrational central charge. Two distinct, yet closely related formulas are needed for the cases $c\in \mathbb C \backslash (-\infty,1]$ and $c &lt;1$. We also conjecture that the formulas have a well-defined limit as the central charge approaches rational values. Our proposal for $c &lt;1$ agrees numerically with the fusion transformation of the four-point spherical conformal blocks, whereas our proposal for $c\in \mathbb C \backslash (-\infty,1]$ agrees numerically with Ponsot and Teschner's integral formula for the fusion kernel. The case of the modular kernel is studied as a special case of the fusion kernel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09325v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Roussillon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative phase mixing for Hamiltonians with trapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17153v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove quantitative decay estimates of macroscopic quantities generated by the solutions to linear transport equations driven by a general family of Hamiltonians. The associated particle trajectories are all trapped in a compact region of phase-space and feature a non-degenerate elliptic stagnation point. The analysis covers a large class of Hamiltonians generated by the radially symmetric compactly supported equilibria of the gravitational Vlasov-Poisson system. Working in radial symmetry, our analysis features both the 1+2-dimensional case and the harder 1+1-dimensional case, where all the particles have the same value of the modulus of angular momentum. The latter case is also of importance in both the plasma physics case and two dimensional incompressible fluid flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17153v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahir Had\v{z}i\'c, Gerhard Rein, Matthew Schrecker, Christopher Straub</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
