<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math-ph</link>
    <description>math-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 05:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the eigenvectors of the 5D discrete Fourier transform number operator in Newtonian basis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00148v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A simple analytic approach to the evaluation of the eigenvalues and eigenvectors f_n of the 5D discrete number operator N_5 is formulated. This approach is essentially based on the symmetry of the intertwining operators with respect to the discrete reflection operator. A procedure for the sparsealization of the intertwining operators has been developed, which made it possible to establish a discrete analog of the well-known continuous case formula. A discrete analog for the eigenvectors f_n of another continuous case formula is constructed in the Newtonian basis polynomials, times the lowest eigenvector f_0.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00148v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natig Atakishiyev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized finite and affine $W$-algebras in type $A$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a new family of affine $W$-algebras $W^k(\lambda,\mu)$ parameterized by partitions $\lambda$ and $\mu$ associated with the centralizers of nilpotent elements in $\mathfrak{gl}_N$. The new family unifies a few known classes of $W$-algebras. In particular, for the column-partition $\lambda$ we recover the affine $W$-algebras $W^k(\mathfrak{gl}_N,f)$ of Kac, Roan and Wakimoto, associated with nilpotent elements $f\in\mathfrak{gl}_N$ of type $\mu$. Our construction is based on a version of the BRST complex of the quantum Drinfeld-Sokolov reduction. We show that the application of the Zhu functor to the vertex algebras $W^k(\lambda,\mu)$ yields a family of generalized finite $W$-algebras $U(\lambda,\mu)$ which we also describe independently as associative algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00271v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dong Jun Choi, Alexander Molev, Uhi Rinn Suh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on: "Comment on "Nonperturbative calculation of Born-Infeld effects on the Schr\"odinger spectrum of the hydrogen atom"" by M. N. Smolyakov</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This reply to Dr. Smolyakov's comment [2] on our PRL paper [1] was solicited by PRL on Nov. 17, 2021 and submitted to PRL on Nov. 30, 2021. Regretfully, the editors of PRL decided not to publish Dr. Smolyakov's comment; hence, not our reply to it. However, since Dr. Smolyakov made his comment publicly available at the arXiv.org in June 2022 (of which we learned only on Dec. 26, 2024), we have decided to make our reply to his comment publicly available as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00613v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. K. Carley, M. K. -H. Kiessling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trading linearity for ellipticity: a nonsmooth approach to Einstein's theory of gravity and the Lorentzian splitting theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00702v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While Einstein's theory of gravity is formulated in a smooth setting, the celebrated singularity theorems of Hawking and Penrose describe many physical situations in which this smoothness must eventually break down. In positive-definite signature, there is a highly successful theory of metric and metric-measure geometry which includes Riemannian manifolds as a special case, but permits the extraction of nonsmooth limits under dimension and curvature bounds analogous to the energy conditions from relativity: here sectional curvature is reformulated through triangle comparison, while Ricci curvature is reformulated using entropic convexity along geodesics of probability measures.
  This lecture highlights recent progress in the development of an analogous theory in Lorentzian signature, whose ultimate goal is to provide a nonsmooth theory of gravity. In particular, we foreshadow a low-regularity splitting theorem obtained by sacrificing linearity of the d'Alembertian to recover ellipticity. We exploit a negative homogeneity $p$-d'Alembert operator for this purpose. The same technique yields a simplified proof of Eschenberg (1988), Galloway (1989), and Newman's (1990) confirmation of Yau's (1982) conjecture, bringing both Lorentzian splitting results into a framework closer to the Cheeger--Gromoll (1971) splitting theorem from Riemannian geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00702v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert J. McCann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lieb--Thirring inequalities for large quantum systems with inverse nearest-neighbor interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00866v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove an analogue of the Lieb--Thirring inequality for many-body quantum systems with the kinetic operator $\sum_i (-\Delta_i)^s$ and the interaction potential of the form $\sum_i \delta_i^{-2s}$ where $\delta_i$ is the nearest-neighbor distance to the point $x_i$. Our result extends the standard Lieb--Thirring inequality for fermions and applies to quantum systems without the anti-symmetry assumption on the wave functions. Additionally, we derive similar results for the Hardy--Lieb--Thirring inequality and obtain the asymptotic behavior of the optimal constants in the strong coupling limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00866v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. K. Duong, Phan Th\`anh Nam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics for the magnetic Dirichlet-to-Neumann eigenvalues in general domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by a paper by T. Chakradhar, K. Gittins, G. Habib and N. Peyerimhoff, we analyze their conjecture that the ground state energy of the magnetic Dirichlet-to-Neumann operator tends to infinity as the magnetic field tends to infinity. More precisely, we prove refined conjectures for general two dimensional domains, based on the analysis in the case of the half-plane and the disk by two of us (B.H. and F.N.). We also extend our analysis to the three dimensional case, and explore a connection with the eigenvalue asymptotics of the magnetic Robin Laplacian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00947v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernard Helffer, Ayman Kachmar, Francois Nicoleau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nearsightedness in Materials with Indirect Band Gap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nearsightedness property in the linear tight binding model at zero Fermi-temperature. We focus on the decay property of the density matrix for materials with indirect band gaps. By representing the density matrix in reciprocal space, we establish a qualitatively sharp estimate for the exponential decay rate in homogeneous systems. An extending result under perturbations is also derived. This work refines the estimates presented in (Ortner, Thomas &amp; Chen 2020), particularly for systems with small band gaps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01188v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huajie Chen, Juerong Feng, Christoph Ortner, Jack Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic Solutions of the Haydys-Witten Equations and Symplectic Khovanov Homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An influential conjecture by Witten states that there is an instanton Floer homology of four-manifolds with corners that in certain situations is isomorphic to Khovanov homology of a given knot $K$. The Floer chain complex is generated by Nahm pole solutions of the Kapustin-Witten equations on $\mathbb{R}^3 \times \mathbb{R}^+_y$ with an additional monopole-like singular behaviour along the knot $K$ inside the three-dimensional boundary at $y=0$. The Floer differential is given by counting solutions of the Haydys-Witten equations that interpolate between Kapustin-Witten solutions along an additional flow direction $\mathbb{R}_s$. This article investigates solutions of a decoupled version of the Kapustin-Witten and Haydys-Witten equations on $\mathbb{R}_s \times \mathbb{R}^3 \times \mathbb{R}^+_y$, which in contrast to the full equations exhibit a Hermitian Yang-Mills structure and can be viewed as a lift of the extended Bogomolny equations (EBE) from three to five dimensions. Inspired by Gaiotto-Witten's approach of adiabatically braiding EBE-solutions to obtain generators of the Floer homology, we propose that there is an equivalence between adiabatic solutions of the decoupled Haydys-Witten equations and non-vertical paths in the moduli space of EBE-solutions fibered over the space of monopole positions. Moreover, we argue that the Grothendieck-Springer resolution of the Lie algebra of the gauge group provides a finite-dimensional model of this moduli space of monopole solutions. These considerations suggest an intriguing similarity between Haydys-Witten instanton Floer homology and symplectic Khovanov homology and provide a novel approach towards a proof of Witten's gauge-theoretic interpretations of Khovanov homology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01365v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Bleher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commutator Estimates and Quantitative Local Weyl's Law for Sch\"odinger Operators with Non-Smooth Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01381v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze semi-classical Schr\"odinger operators with potentials of class $C^{1,1/2}$ and establish commutator estimates for the associated projection operators in Schatten norms. These are then applied to prove quantitative versions of the local and phase space Weyl laws in $L^p$ spaces. We study both non-interacting, and interacting particle systems. In particular, we are able to treat the case of the minimizers of the Hartree energy in the case of repulsive singular pair interactions such as the Coulomb potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01381v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esteban C\'ardenas, Laurent Lafleche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Riemann-Hilbert problems, Fredholm determinants, explicit combinatorial expansions, and connection formulas for the general $q$-Painlev\'e III$_3$ tau functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01419v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We reformulate the $q$-difference linear system corresponding to the $q$-Painlev\'e equation of type $A_7^{(1)'}$ as a Riemann-Hilbert problem on a circle. Then, we consider the Fredholm determinant built from the jump of this Riemann-Hilbert problem and prove that it satisfies bilinear relations equivalent to $P(A_7^{(1)'})$. We also find the minor expansion of this Fredholm determinant in explicit factorized form and prove that it coincides with the Fourier series in $q$-deformed conformal blocks, or partition functions of the pure $5d$ $\mathcal{N}=1$ $SU(2)$ gauge theory, including the cases with the Chern-Simons term. Finally, we solve the connection problem for these isomonodromic tau functions, finding in this way their global behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01419v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavlo Gavrylenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Average mutual information for random fermionic Gaussian quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20244v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Studying the typical entanglement entropy of a bipartite system when averaging over different ensembles of pure quantum states has been instrumental in different areas of physics, ranging from many-body quantum chaos to black hole evaporation. We extend such analysis to open quantum systems and mixed states, where we compute the typical mutual information in a bipartite system averaged over the ensemble of mixed Gaussian states with a fixed spectrum. Tools from random matrix theory and determinantal point processes allow us to compute arbitrary k-point correlation functions of the singular values of the corresponding complex structure in a subsystem for a given spectrum in the full system. In particular, we evaluate the average von Neumann entropy in a subsystem based on the level density and the average mutual information. Those results are given for finite system size as well as in the thermodynamic limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20244v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Hackl, Mario Kieburg, Joel Maldonado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Yang-Mills-Dirac Quantum Field Theory Emerging From a Dirac Operator on a Configuration Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00005v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starting with a Dirac operator on a configuration space of $SU(2)$ gauge connections we consider its fluctuations with inner automorphisms. We show that a certain type of twisted inner fluctuations leads to a Dirac operator whose square gives the Hamiltonian of Yang-Mills quantum field theory coupled to a fermionic sector that consist of one-form fermions. We then show that if a metric exists on the underlying three-dimensional manifold then there exists a change of basis of the configuration space for which the transformed fermionic sector consists of fermions that are no-longer one-forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00005v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Aastrup, Jesper M. Grimstrup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry of meromorphic differentials produced by involution identity, and relation to integer partitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that meromorphic differentials $\omega^{(0)}_n(z_1,...,z_n)$ which are recursively generated by an involution identity are symmetric in all their arguments $z_1,...,z_n$ -- provided that an intriguing combinatorial identity between integer partitions into given number of parts is true.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00082v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Hock (Heidelberg), Raimar Wulkenhaar (M\"unster)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moments and saddles of heavy CFT correlators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00092v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the operator product expansion (OPE) of identical scalars in a conformal four-point correlator as a Stieltjes moment problem, and use Riemann-Liouville type fractional differential operators to transform the correlation function into a classical moment-generating function. We use crossing symmetry to derive leading and subleading relations between moments in $\Delta$ and $J_2 = \ell(\ell+d-2)$ in the ``heavy" limit of large external scaling dimension, and combine them with constraints from unitarity to derive two-sided bounds on moment sequences in $\Delta$ and the covariance between $\Delta$ and $J_2$. The moment sequences which saturate these bounds produce ``saddle point" solutions to the crossing equations which we identify as particular limits of correlators in a generalized free field (GFF) theory. This motivates us to study perturbations of heavy GFF four-point correlators by way of saddle point analysis, and we show that saddles in the OPE arise from contributions of fixed-length operator families encoded by a decomposition into deformed higher-spin conformal blocks. To apply our techniques, we consider holographic correlators of four identical single scalar fields perturbed by a bulk interaction, and use their first few moments to derive Gaussian weight-interpolating functions that predict the OPE coefficients of interacting double-twist operators in the heavy limit. We further compute tree-level perturbations on saddles in 1/2 BPS Wilson line defect correlators in planar $\mathcal{N} = 4$ SYM, making predictions about deformations of families of long operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00092v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Poland, Gordon Rogelberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced-order Bopp-Podolsky model on the null-plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00133v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the null-plane dynamics for a reduced-order version of the higher-derivatives Bopp-Podoslky generalized electrodynamics model. By introducing an auxiliary vector field, we achieve a simpler equivalent version with lower derivatives. The massive and massless modes for the Podolsky gauge field get split into two sectors. We describe the model in terms of light-front coordinates and, by choosing $x^+$ as a natural evolution parameter, proceed to its null-plane dynamics analysis obtaining the whole constraints structure and canonical field equations. After a convenient constraints redefinition, we calculate the Dirac brackets corresponding to the second-class sector. Gauge invariance is preserved and, after elimination of second-class constraints, we obtain a consistent Abelian first-class theory for the reduced-order Bopp-Podolsky model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00133v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario C. Bertin, Ronaldo Thibes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full symmetric Toda system and vector fields on the group $SO_n(\R)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00137v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we discuss the relation between the functions that give first integrals of full symmetric Toda system (an important Hamilton system on the space of traceless real symmetric matrices) and the vector fields on the group of orthogonal matrices: it is known that this system is equivalent to an ordinary differential equation on the orthogonal group, and we extend this observation further to its first integrals. As a by-product we describe a representation of the Lie algebra of $B^+(\R)$-invariant functions on the dual space of Lie algebra $\mathfrak{sl}_n(\R)$ (under the canonical Poisson structure) by vector fields on $SO_n(\R)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00137v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. B. Chernyakov, G. I. Sharygin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metriplectic 4-bracket algorithm for constructing thermodynamically consistent dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A unified thermodynamic algorithm (UTA) is presented for constructing thermodynamically consistent dynamical systems, i.e., systems that have Hamiltonian and dissipative parts that conserve energy while producing entropy. The algorithm is based on the metriplectic 4-bracket given in Morrison and Updike [Phys.\ Rev.\ E 109, 045202 (2024)]. A feature of the UTA is the force-flux relation $\mathbf{J}^\alpha = - L^{\alpha\beta}\, \nabla(\delta H / \delta \xi^\beta)$ for phenomenological coefficients $L^{\alpha\beta}$, Hamiltonian $H$ and dynamical variables $\xi^\beta$. The algorithm is applied to the Navier-Stokes-Fourier, the Cahn-Hilliard-Navier-Stokes, and and Brenner-Navier-Stokes-Fourier systems, and significant generalizations of these systems are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00159v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azeddine Zaidni, Philip J. Morrison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superdiffusive Central Limit Theorem for the Stochastic Burgers Equation at the critical dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00344v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Stochastic Burgers Equation (SBE) is a singular, non-linear Stochastic Partial Differential Equation (SPDE) that describes, on mesoscopic scales, the fluctuations of stochastic driven diffusive systems with a conserved scalar quantity. In space dimension d = 2, the SBE is critical, being formally scale invariant under diffusive scaling. As such, it falls outside of the domain of applicability of the theories of Regularity Structures and paracontrolled calculus. In apparent contrast with the formal scale invariance, we fully prove the conjecture first appeared in [H. van Beijeren, R. Kutner, &amp; H. Spohn, Phys. Rev. Lett., 1986] according to which the 2d-SBE is logarithmically superdiffusive, i.e. its diffusion coefficient diverges like $(\log t)^{2/3}$ as $t\to\infty$, thus removing subleading diverging multiplicative corrections in [D. De Gaspari &amp; L. Haunschmid-Sibitz, Electron. J. Probab., 2024] and in [H.-T. Yau, Ann. of Math., 2004] for 2d-ASEP. We precisely identify the constant prefactor of the logarithm and show it is proportional to $\lambda^{4/3}$, for $\lambda&gt;0$ the coupling constant, which, intriguingly, turns out to be exactly the same as for the one-dimensional Stochastic Burgers/KPZ equation. More importantly, we prove that, under super-diffusive space-time rescaling, the SBE has an explicit Gaussian fixed point in the Renormalization Group sense, by deriving a superdiffusive central limit-type theorem for its solution.
  This is the first scaling limit result for a critical singular SPDE, beyond the weak coupling regime, and is obtained via a refined control, on all length-scales, of the resolvent of the generator of the SBE. We believe our methods are well-suited to study other out-of-equilibrium driven diffusive systems at the critical dimension, such as 2d-ASEP, which, we conjecture, have the same large-scale Fixed Point as SBE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00344v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Cannizzaro, Quentin Moulard, Fabio Toninelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gaudin model for the general linear Lie superalgebra and the completeness of the Bethe ansatz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathfrak{B}_{m|n}(\underline{\boldsymbol{z}})$ be the Gaudin algebra of the general linear Lie superalgebra $\mathfrak{gl}_{m|n}$ with respect to a sequence $\underline{\boldsymbol{z}} \in \mathbb{C}^\ell$ of pairwise distinct complex numbers, and let $M$ be any $\ell$-fold tensor product of irreducible polynomial modules over $\mathfrak{gl}_{m|n}$. We show that the singular space $M^{\rm sing}$ of $M$ is a cyclic $\mathfrak{B}_{m|n}(\underline{\boldsymbol{z}})$-module and the Gaudin algebra $\mathfrak{B}_{m|n}(\underline{\boldsymbol{z}})_{M^{\rm sing}}$ of $M^{\rm sing}$ is a Frobenius algebra. We also show that $\mathfrak{B}_{m|n}(\underline{\boldsymbol{z}})_{M^{\rm sing}}$ is diagonalizable with a simple spectrum for a generic $\underline{\boldsymbol{z}}$ and give a description of an eigenbasis and its corresponding eigenvalues in terms of the Fuchsian differential operators with polynomial kernels. This may be interpreted as the completeness of a reformulation of the Bethe ansatz for $\mathfrak{B}_{m|n}(\underline{\boldsymbol{z}})_{M^{\rm sing}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00401v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wan Keng Cheong, Ngau Lam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large time analysis of the rate function associated to the Boltzmann equation: dynamical phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00402v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyse the large time behaviour of the rate function that describes the probability of large fluctuations of an underlying microscopic model associated to the homogeneous Boltzmann equation, such as the Kac walk. We consider in particular the asymptotic of the number of collisions, per particle and per unit of time, and show it exhibits a phase transition in the joint limit in which the number of particles N and the time interval [0,T] diverge. More precisely, due to the existence of Lu-Wennberg solutions, the corresponding limiting rate function vanishes for subtypical values of the number of collisions. We also analyse the second order large deviations showing that the probability of subtypical fluctuations is exponentially small in N, independently on T. As a key point, we establish the controllability of the homogeneous Boltzmann equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00402v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giada Basile, Dario Benedetto, Lorenzo Bertini, Daniel Heydecker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast mixing of weakly interacting fermionic systems at any temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the mixing time of a recently proposed efficiently implementable Lindbladian designed to prepare the Gibbs states in the setting of weakly interacting fermionic systems. We show that at any temperature, the Lindbladian spectral gap for even parity observables is lower bounded by a constant that is independent of the system size, when the interaction strength (e.g., the on-site interaction strength for the Fermi-Hubbard model) is below a constant threshold, which is also independent of the system size. This leads to a mixing time estimate that is at most linear in the system size, thus showing that the corresponding Gibbs states can be prepared efficiently on quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00443v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Tong, Yongtao Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analogue black string in a quantum harmonic oscillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00478v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a scalar particle without self-interaction or backreaction from the space-time background, the dynamics are governed by the Klein-Gordon equation. In this work, we write the exact solution of this equation in the background of a chargeless, static black string in terms of the biconfluent Heun function. In this curious system, we are able to explore what happens if we have negative values for the masses. The eigenvalue problem provides complex energy values for the particle, which may indicate the presence of quasinormal modes. We show a simple quantum system that can imitate the particle in the black string background, whose solutions are also applications of the biconfluent Heun function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00478v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matheus E. Pereira, Alexandre G. M. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-Quenched Invariance Principle for the Random Lorentz Gas -- Beyond the Boltzmann-Grad Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00519v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By synchronously coupling multiple Lorentz trajectories exploring the same environment consisting of randomly placed scatterers in R^3 we upgrade the annealed invariance principle proved in [C. Lutsko, B. T\'oth, Commun. Math. Phys. 379 589-632 (2020)] to quenched setting (that is, valid for almost all realizations of the environment) along sufficiently fast extractor sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00519v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B\'alint T\'oth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting Parallelism for Fast Feynman Diagrammatics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Diagrammatic expansions are a paradigmatic and powerful tool of quantum many-body theory. Their evaluation to high order, e.g., by the Diagrammatic Monte Carlo technique, can provide unbiased results in strongly correlated and challenging regimes. However, calculating a factorial number of terms to acceptable precision remains very costly even for state-of-the-art methods. We achieve a dramatic acceleration of evaluating Feynman's diagrammatic series by use of specialised hardware architecture within the recently introduced combinatorial summation (CoS) framework. We present how exploiting the massive parallelism and concurrency available from GPUs leads to orders of magnitude improvement in computation time even on consumer-grade hardware. This provides a platform for making probes of novel phenomena of strong correlations much more accessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00675v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Sturt, Evgeny Kozik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In Search of a Hidden Curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00716v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Three enumeration problems are discussed in these lectures. One is a detailed account on simple Hurwitz numbers, explaining how the problem was solved by discovering a key curve. This key ignites the generating functions of Hurwitz numbers and drives them into polynomials. The unexpected polynomiality then brings us simple proofs of the Witten-Kontsevich theorem and the $\lambda_g$-theorem of Faber-Pandharipande. An analogous problem associated with Catalan numbers is also presented, which has a simpler feature in terms of analysis. The third enumeration problem is a quest of identifying a hidden curve behind the Ap\'ery sequence, which remains to be discovered.
  It is examined how a counting problem leads to a \emph{spectral curve} through a differential equation, of Picard-Fuchs type but can be nonlinear. The counting problem is a geometric question associated with the \emph{genus $0$, one marked point} case. Going from the $(0,1)$-case to arbitrary $(g,n)$-case is explained as a process of \emph{quantization} of the spectral curve.
  This perspective of quantization is discussed in a geometric setting, when the differential equations have holomorphic coefficients, in terms of Higgs bundles, opers, and Gaiotto's conformal limit construction. In this context, however, there are no counting problems behind the scene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00716v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motohico Mulase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Classification of Pathological Misner-Type Spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00841v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the Misner space, incorporating Kip Thorne's "moving wall" model, and pseudo-Schwarzschild spacetime, exploring their geometric structures, geodesics, and causal properties. We propose that pseudo-Schwarzschild spacetime serves as a non-flat generalization of Misner space. We then introduce the pseudo-Reissner-Nordstr\"om spacetime, a novel chronology-violating model that extends the previous two frameworks and unifies the geodesic structures of all three spacetimes. We suggest that these spacetimes constitute a causality-violating family, interconnected through common fundamental causal features$-$geodesics, Cauchy and chronology horizons, and acausal regions$-$leading a conjecture that they are isocausal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00841v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. E. Rieger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fisher Information in Kinetic Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00925v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: These notes review the theory of Fisher information, especially its use in kinetic theory of gases and plasmas. The recent monotonicity theorem by Guillen--Silvestre for the Landau--Coulomb equation is put in perspective and generalised. Following my joint work with Imbert and Silvestre, it is proven that Fisher information is decaying along the spatially homogeneous Boltzmann equation, for all relevant interactions, and from this the once longstanding problem of regularity estimates for very singular collision kernels (very soft potentials) is solved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00925v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Villani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reductions and degenerate limits of Yang-Baxter maps with $3\times 3$ Lax matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01210v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We generalise a family of quadrirational parametric Yang-Baxter maps with $3\times 3$ Lax matrices by introducing additional essential parameters. These maps preserve a prescribed Poisson structure which originates from the Sklyanin bracket. We investigate various low-dimensional reductions of this family, as well as degenerate limits with respect to the parameters that were introduced. As a result, we derive several birational Yang-Baxter maps, and we discuss some of their integrability properties. This work is part of a more general classification of Yang-Baxter maps admitting a strong $3\times 3$ Lax matrix with a linear dependence on the spectral parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01210v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Adamopoulou, T. E. Kouloukas, G. Papamikos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The clock advance description of the Epidemic Type Aftershock Sequence (ETAS) model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01233v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this short paper we propose to extend the ETAS model to micro-seismic events. For that we interpret the triggered events in an ETAS model as individual local clock advances of an independent background process. The solution of the ETAS model thus becomes the sum of an infinite Markov chain of independent time adjusted background processses. This allows the incorporation of events at all scales. No artificial small magnitude cutoff is needed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01233v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Holschneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signs of high order derivatives for the theta and Epstein zeta functions and application</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01265v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the 1950s, 1960s and 1988, number theorists Rankin \cite{Ran1953}, Cassels \cite{Cas1959}, Ennola \cite{Enn1964a}, Diananda \cite{Dia1964}, and Montgomery \cite{Mon1988} derived the signs of first order derivatives of Epstein zeta and theta functions, respectively. In this note, we shall derive the signs of higher order derivatives of such functions. Application to lattice minimization problems will be given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01265v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deng Kaixin, Luo Senping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical networks and data analysis in phylogenetics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A classic problem in data analysis is studying the systems of subsets defined by either a similarity or a dissimilarity function on $X$ which is either observed directly or derived from a data set. For an electrical network there are two functions on the set of the nodes defined by the resistance matrix and the response matrix either of which defines the network completely. We argue that these functions should be viewed as a similarity and a dissimilarity function on the set of the nodes moreover they are related via the covariance mapping also known as the Farris transform or the Gromov product. We will explore the properties of electrical networks from this point of view. It has been known for a while that the resistance matrix defines a metric on the nodes of the electrical networks. Moreover for a circular electrical network this metric obeys the Kalmanson property as it was shown recently. We will call such a metric an electrical Kalmanson metric. The main results of this paper is a complete description of the electrical Kalmanson metrics in the set of all Kalmanson metrics in terms of the geometry of the positive Isotropic Grassmannian whose connection to the theory of electrical networks was discovered earlier. One important area of applications where Kalmanson metrics are actively used is the theory of phylogenetic networks which are a generalization of phylogenetic trees. Our results allow us to use in phylogenetics the powerful methods of reconstruction of the minimal graphs of electrical networks and possibly open the door into data analysis for the methods of the theory of cluster algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01383v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Gorbounov, A. Kazakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Time Quantum Gibbs Sampling for Fermi-Hubbard Model at any Temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01412v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, there have been several advancements in quantum algorithms for Gibbs sampling. These algorithms simulate the dynamics generated by an artificial Lindbladian, which is meticulously constructed to obey a detailed-balance condition with the Gibbs state of interest, ensuring it is a stationary point of the evolution, while simultaneously having efficiently implementable time steps. The overall complexity then depends primarily on the mixing time of the Lindbladian, which can vary drastically, but which has been previously bounded in the regime of high enough temperatures [Rouz\'e {\it et al.}~arXiv:2403.12691 and arXiv:2411.04885].
  In this work, we calculate the spectral gap of the Lindbladian for free fermions using third quantisation, and then prove a constant gap of the perturbed Lindbladian corresponding to interacting fermions up to some maximal coupling strength. This is achieved by using theorems about stability of the gap for lattice fermions. Our methods apply at any constant temperature and independently of the system size. The gap then provides an upper bound on the mixing time, and hence on the overall complexity of the quantum algorithm, proving that the purified Gibbs state of weakly interacting (quasi-)local fermionic systems of any dimension can be prepared in $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}} (n^3 \operatorname{polylog}(1/\epsilon))$ time on $\mathcal{O}(n)$ qubits, where $n$ denotes the size of the system and $\epsilon$ the desired accuracy. We provide exact numerical simulations for small system sizes supporting the theory and also identify different suitable jump operators and filter functions for the sought-after regime of intermediate coupling in the Fermi-Hubbard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01412v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\v{S}t\v{e}p\'an \v{S}m\'id, Richard Meister, Mario Berta, Roberto Bondesan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biorthogonal polynomials related to quantum transport theory of disordered wires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03720v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the Plancherel-Rotach type asymptotics of the biorthogonal polynomials associated to the biorthogonal ensemble with the joint probability density function \begin{equation*}
  \frac{1}{C} \prod_{1 \leq i &lt; j \leq n} (\lambda_j -\lambda_i)(f(\lambda_j) - f(\lambda_i)) \prod^n_{j = 1} W^{(n)}_{\alpha}(\lambda_j) d\lambda_j, \end{equation*} where \begin{align*} f(x) = {}&amp; \sinh^2(\sqrt{x}), &amp; W^{(n)}_{\alpha}(x) = {}&amp; x^{\alpha} h(x) e^{-nV(x)}. \end{align*} In the special case that the potential function $V$ is linear, this biorthogonal ensemble arises in the quantum transport theory of disordered wires. We analyze the asymptotic problem via $2$-component vector-valued Riemann-Hilbert problems, and solve it under the one-cut regular with a hard edge condition. We use the asymptotics of biorthogonal polynomials to establish sine universality for the correlation kernel in the bulk, and provide a central limit theorem with a specific variance for holomorphic linear statistics.
  As an application of our theories, we establish the Ohm's law (1.12) and universal conductance fluctuation (1.13) for the disordered wire model, thereby rigorously confirming predictions from experimental physics [Washburn-Webb86].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03720v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dong Wang, Dong Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long persistence of localization in a disordered anharmonic chain beyond the atomic limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11243v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish rigorous bounds on the decorrelation time and thermal transport in the disordered Klein-Gordon chain with a quartic on-site potential, governed by a parameter $\lambda$. At $\lambda = 0$, the chain is harmonic, and any form of transport is fully suppressed by Anderson localization. For the anharmonic system, at $\lambda &gt; 0$, our results show that decorrelation and transport can occur only on time scales that grow faster than any polynomial in $1/\lambda$ as $\lambda \to 0$. From a technical perspective, the main novelty of our work is that we don't restrict ourselves to the atomic limit. Instead, we develop perturbation theory around the harmonic system with a fixed harmonic interaction between nearby oscillators. This allows us to compare our mathematical results with previous numerical work and contribute to resolving an ongoing debate, as detailed in a companion paper arXiv:2308.10572.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11243v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech De Roeck, Fran\c{c}ois Huveneers, Oskar A. Pro\'sniak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out-of-time-ordered correlators of mean-field bosons via Bogoliubov theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01736v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum many-body chaos concerns the scrambling of quantum information among large numbers of degrees of freedom. It rests on the prediction that out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs) of the form $\langle [A(t),B]^2\rangle$ can be connected to classical symplectic dynamics. We rigorously prove a variant of this correspondence principle for mean-field bosons. We show that the $N\to\infty$ limit of the OTOC $\langle [A(t),B]^2\rangle$ is explicitly given by a suitable symplectic Bogoliubov dynamics. In practical terms, we describe the dynamical build-up of many-body entanglement between a particle and the whole system by an explicit nonlinear PDE on $L^2(\mathbb{R}^3) \oplus L^2(\mathbb{R}^3)$. For higher-order correlators, we obtain an out-of-time-ordered analog of the Wick rule. The proof uses Bogoliubov theory. Our finding spotlights a new problem in nonlinear dispersive PDE with implications for quantum many-body chaos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01736v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius Lemm, Simone Rademacher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pauli Hamiltonians with an Aharonov-Bohm Flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11971v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a two-dimensional Pauli operator describing a charged quantum particle with spin $1/2$ moving on a plane in presence of an orthogonal Aharonov-Bohm magnetic flux. We classify all the admissible self-adjont realizations and give a complete picture of their spectral and scattering properties. Symmetries of the resulting Hamiltonians are also discussed, as well as their connection with the Dirac operator perturbed by an Aharonov-Bohm singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11971v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4171/JST/496</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Spectral Theory 14(3), 1147-1193 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>William Borrelli, Michele Correggi, Davide Fermi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bessel kernel determinants and integrable equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11213v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive differential equations for multiplicative statistics of the Bessel determinantal point process depending on two parameters. In particular, we prove that such statistics are solutions to an integrable nonlinear partial differential equation describing isospectral deformations of a Sturm-Liouville equation. We also derive identities relating solutions to the integrable partial differential equation and to the Sturm-Liouville equation which imply an analogue for Painlev\'e V of Amir-Corwin-Quastel "integro-differential Painlev\'e II equation". This equation reduces, in a degenerate limit, to the system of coupled Painlev\'e V equations derived by Charlier and Doeraene for the generating function of the Bessel process, and to the Painlev\'e V equation derived by Tracy and Widom for the gap probability of the Bessel process. Finally, we study an initial value problem for the integrable partial differential equation. The approach is based on Its-Izergin-Korepin-Slavnov theory of integrable operators and their associated Riemann-Hilbert problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11213v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00023-024-01527-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Annales Henri Poincar\'e, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Ruzza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum inverse scattering for the 20-vertex model up to Dynkin automorphism: crossing probabilities, 3D Poisson structure, triangular height functions, weak integrability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11066v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We initiate a novel application of the quantum-inverse scattering method for the 20-vertex model, building upon seminal work from Faddeev and Takhtajan on the study of Hamiltonian systems, with applications to crossing probabilities, 3D Poisson structure, triangular height functions, and integrability. In comparison to a previous work of the author in late $2023$ which characterized integrability of a Hamiltonian flow for the 6-vertex model from integrability of inhomogeneous limit shapes, formalized in a work of Keating, Reshetikhin and Sridhar, notions similar to those of integrability can be realized for the 20-vertex model by studying new classes of higher-dimensional L-operators. In comparison to two-dimensional L-operators expressed in terms of Pauli basis elements, three-dimensional L-operators provided by Boos and colleagues have algebraic, combinatorial, and geometric, qualities, all of which impact leading order approximations of correlations, products of L-operators, the transfer matrix, and the quantum monodromy matrix in finite volume. In comparison to the inhomogeneous 6-vertex model, the 20-vertex model does not enjoy as strong of an integrability property through the existence of suitable action-angle variables, which is of interest to further explore, possibly from information on limit shapes given solutions to the three-dimensional Euler-Lagrange equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11066v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pete Rigas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative Equilibria for Scaling Symmetries and Central Configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15191v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore scaling symmetries within the framework of symplectic geometry. We focus on the action $\Phi$ of the multiplicative group $G = \mathbb{R}^+$ on exact symplectic manifolds $(M, \omega,\theta)$, with $\omega = -d\theta$, where $ \theta $ is a given primitive one-form. Extending established results in symplectic geometry and Hamiltonian dynamics, we introduce conformally symplectic maps, conformally Hamiltonian systems, conformally symplectic group actions, and the notion of conformal invariance. This framework allows us to generalize the momentum map to the conformal momentum map, which is crucial for understanding scaling symmetries. Additionally, we provide a generalized Hamiltonian Noether's theorem for these symmetries.
  We introduce the (conformal) augmented Hamiltonian $H_{\xi}$ and prove that the relative equilibria of scaling symmetries are solutions to equations involving $ H _{ \xi } $ and the primitive one-form $\theta$. We derive their main properties, emphasizing the differences from relative equilibria in traditional symplectic actions.
  For cotangent bundles, we define a scaled cotangent lifted action and derive explicit formulas for the conformal momentum map. We also provide a general definition of central configurations for Hamiltonian systems on cotangent bundles that admit scaling symmetries. Applying these results to simple mechanical systems, we introduce the augmented potential $U_{\xi}$ and show that the relative equilibria of scaling symmetries are solutions to an equation involving $ U _{ \xi } $ and the Lagrangian one-form $\theta_L$.
  Finally, we apply our general theory to the Newtonian $n$-body problem, recovering the classical equations for central configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15191v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Rastelli, Manuele Santoprete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equilibrium of Charges and Differential Equations Solved by Polynomials II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01494v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We continue study of equilibrium of two species of 2d coulomb charges (or point vortices in 2d ideal fluid) started in [20]. Although for two species of vortices with circulation ratio -1 the relationship between the equilibria and the factorization/Darboux transformation of the Schrodinger operator was established a long ago, the question about similar relationship for the ratio -2 remained unanswered. Here we present the answer: One has to consider Darboux-type transformations of third order differential operators rather than second order Schrodinger operators. Furthermore, we show that such transformations can also generate equilibrium configurations where an additional charge of a third specie is present. Relationship with integrable hierarchies is briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01494v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Loutsenko, Oksana Yermolayeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A family of instanton-invariants for four-manifolds and their relation to Khovanov homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13285v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article reviews Witten's gauge-theoretic approach to Khovanov homology from the perspective of Haydys-Witten instanton Floer theory. Expanding on Witten's arguments, we introduce a one-parameter family of instanton Floer homology groups $HF_{\theta}(W^4)$, which, based on physical arguments, are expected to be topological invariants of the four-manifold $W^4$. In analogy to the original Yang-Mills instanton Floer theory, these groups are defined by the solutions of the $\theta$-Kapustin-Witten equations on $W^4$ modulo instanton solutions of the Haydys-Witten equations that interpolate between them on the five-dimensional cylinder $\mathbb{R}_s \times W^4$. The relation to knot invariants arises when the four-manifold is the geometric blowup $W^4 = [X^3 \times \mathbb{R}^+, K]$ along a knot $K \subset X^3 \times \{0\}$ embedded in its three-dimensional boundary. The boundaries and corners of this manifold require the specification of boundary conditions that preserve the topological invariance of the construction and are fundamentally linked to various dimensional reductions of the Haydys-Witten equations. We provide a comprehensive discussion of these dimensional reductions and relate them to well-known gauge-theoretic equations in lower dimensions, including the $\theta$-Kapustin-Witten equations, twisted extended Bogomolny equations, and twisted octonionic Nahm equations. Along the way, we record novel results on the elliptic regularity of the Haydys-Witten equations with twisted Nahm pole boundary conditions. The upshot of the article is a tentative definition of Haydys-Witten Floer theory and a precise restatement of Witten's conjecture: an equality between the Haydys-Witten Floer homology $HF^\bullet_{\pi/2}([S^3 \times \mathbb{R}^+, K])$ and Khovanov homology $Kh^\bullet(K)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13285v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Bleher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximation of Schr\"odinger operators with point interactions on bounded domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16056v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider Schr\"odinger operators on a bounded domain $\Omega\subset \mathbb{R}^3$, with homogeneous Robin or Dirichlet boundary conditions on $\partial\Omega$ and a point (zero-range) interaction placed at an interior point of $\Omega$. We show that, under suitable spectral assumptions, and by means of an extension-restriction procedure which exploit the already known result on the entire space, the singular interaction is approximated by rescaled sequences of regular potentials. The result is missing in the literature, and we also take the opportunity to point out some general issues in the approximation of point interactions and the role of zero energy resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16056v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Noja, Raffaele Scandone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge symmetry and partially Lagrangian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19447v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the classical field theory whose equations of motion follow from the least action principle, but the class of admissible trajectories is restricted by differential equations. The key element of the proposed construction is the complete gauge symmetry of these additional equations. The unfree variation of the trajectories reduces to the infinitesimal gauge symmetry transformation of the equations restricting the trajectories. We explicitly derive the equations that follow from the requirement that this gauge variation of the action vanishes. The system of equations for conditional extrema is not Lagrangian as such, but it admits an equivalent Hamiltonian formulation with a non-canonical Poisson bracket. The bracket is degenerate, in general. Alternatively, the equations restricting dynamics could be added to the action with Lagrange multipliers with unrestricted variation of the original variables. In this case, we would arrive at the Lagrangian equations for original variables involving Lagrange multipliers and for Lagrange multipliers themselves. In general, these two methods are not equivalent because the multipliers can bring extra degrees of freedom compared to the case of equations derived by unfree variation of the action. We illustrate the general method with two examples. The first example is the particle in a central field with varying trajectories restricted by the equation of conservation of angular momentum. The phase space gets one more dimension, and there is an extra conserved quantity $K$ which is responsible for the precession of trajectories. $K=0$ corresponds to the trajectories of usual Lagrangian dynamics. The second example is the linearized gravity with Einstein-Hilbert action and the class of varying fields is restricted by linearized Nordstr\"om equation. This conditional extrema problem is shown to lead to the linearized Cotton gravity equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19447v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Lyakhovich, Nikita Sinelnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum tunneling and its absence in deep wells and strong magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present new results on quantum tunneling between deep potential wells, in the presence of a strong constant magnetic field. We construct a family of double well potentials containing examples for which the low-energy eigenvalue splitting vanishes, and hence quantum tunneling is eliminated. Further, by deforming within this family, the magnetic ground state can be made to transition from symmetric to anti-symmetric. However, for typical double wells in a certain regime, tunneling is not suppressed, and we provide a lower bound for the eigenvalue splitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21100v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles L. Fefferman, Jacob Shapiro, Michael I. Weinstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real Forms of Holomorphic Hamiltonian Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.10417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2009.10417v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By complexifying a Hamiltonian system one obtains dynamics on a holomorphic symplectic manifold. To invert this construction we present a theory of real forms which not only recovers the original system but also yields different real Hamiltonian systems which share the same complexification. This provides a notion of real forms for holomorphic Hamiltonian systems analogous to that of real forms for complex Lie algebras. Our main result is that the complexification of any analytic mechanical system on a Grassmannian admits a real form on a compact symplectic manifold. This produces a `unitary trick' for Hamiltonian systems which curiously requires an essential use of hyperk\"ahler geometry. We demonstrate this result by finding compact real forms for the simple pendulum, the spherical pendulum, and the rigid body.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2009.10417v4</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3842/SIGMA.2024.114</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIGMA 20 (2024), 114, 24 pages</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Philip Arathoon, Marine Fontaine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smoothing Properties of a Linearization of the Three Waves Collision Operator in the bosonic Boltzmann-Nordheim Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.03633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.03633v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the kinetic theory of a three-dimensional fluid of weakly interacting bosons in a non-equilibrium state which includes both normal fluid and a condensate. More precisely, we look at the previously postulated nonlinear Boltzmann-Nordheim equations for such systems, in a spatially homogeneous state which has an isotropic momentum distribution, and we linearize the equation around an equilibrium state which has a condensate. We study the most singular part of the linearized operator coming from the three waves collision operator for supercritical initial data. The operator has two types of singularities, one of which is similar to the marginally smoothing operator defined by the symbol $\ln(1+p^2)$. Our main result in this context is that for initial data in a certain Banach space of functions satisfying a H\"{older} type condition, at least for some finite time, evolution determined by the linearized operator improves the H\"{o}lder regularity. The main difficulty in this problem arises from the combination of a point singularity and a line singularity present in the linear operator, and we have to use certain fine-tuned function spaces in order to carry out our analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.03633v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jogia Bandyopadhyay, Jani Lukkarinen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental emulator of pulse dynamics in fractional nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a nonlinear optical platform to emulate a nonlinear \textit{L\'{e}vy waveguide} that supports the pulse propagation governed by a generalized fractional nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation (FNLSE). Our approach distinguishes between intra-cavity and extra-cavity regimes, exploring the interplay between the effective fractional group-velocity dispersion (FGVD) and Kerr nonlinearity. In the intra-cavity configuration, we observe stable \textit{fractional solitons} enabled by an engineered combination of the fractional and regular dispersions in the fiber cavity. The soliton pulses exhibit their specific characteristics, \textit{viz.}, "heavy tails" and a "spectral valley" in the temporal and frequency domain, respectively, highlighting the effective nonlocality introduced by FGVD. Further investigation in the extra-cavity regime reveals the generation of spectral valleys with multiple lobes, offering potential applications to the design of high-dimensional data encoding. To elucidate the spectral valleys arising from the interplay of FGVD and nonlinearity, we have developed an innovative "force" model supported by comprehensive numerical analysis. These findings open new avenues for experimental studies of spectral-temporal dynamics in fractional nonlinear systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15150v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilong Liu, Yingwen Zhang, St\'ephane Virally, Ebrahim Karimi, Boris A. Malomed, Denis V. Seletskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardy-Sobolev interpolation inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11249v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive a family of interpolation estimates which improve Hardy's inequality and cover the Sobolev critical exponent. We also determine all optimizers among radial functions in the endpoint case and discuss open questions on nonrestricted optimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11249v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00526-024-02800-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Calc. Var. Partial Differential Equations 63 (2024), Art. 184</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Charlotte Dietze, Phan Th\`anh Nam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charged massless scalar fields in a charged $C$-metric black hole: Exact solutions, Hawking radiation, and scattering of scalar waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12454v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study Hawking radiation and wave scattering of charged scalar fields in a charged $C$-metric black hole background. The conformally invariant wave equation for charged scalar fields can be separated into radial and angular parts, each with five singularities. We first show that the radial and angular equations can be respectively transformed into the general Heun equation, and then we explore exact solutions of the radial Heun equation in terms of the local Heun functions and connection coefficients. Exact behaviors of the asymptotic wave functions are determined without approximations. We further apply the exact results to derive Hawking radiation, quasinormal modes and superradiance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12454v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.124065</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ming Chen, Gabriele Tartaglino-Mazzucchelli, Yao-Zhong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Deviations of the $\Phi^4_3$ Measure via Stochastic Quantisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00975v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $\Phi^4_3$ measure is one of the easiest non-trivial examples of a Euclidean quantum field theory (EQFT) whose rigorous construction in the 1970's has been one of the celebrated achievements of constructive quantum field theory. In recent years, progress in the field of singular stochastic PDEs, initiated by the theory of regularity structures, has allowed for a new construction of the $\Phi^4_3$ EQFT as the invariant measure of a previously ill-posed Langevin dynamics, a strategy originally proposed by Parisi and Wu ('81) under the name stochastic quantisation. We apply the same methodology to obtain a large deviation principle (LDP) for the family of periodic $\Phi^4_3$ measures at varying temperature. In addition, we show that the rate functional of the LDP and the $\Phi^4_3$ action functional coincide up to a constant. We wish to highlight that while our main result had previously been obtained by Barashkov (2022), the main focus of this work is on the approach through the stochastic quantisation equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00975v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Klose, Avi Mayorcas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic continuations and numerical evaluation of the Appell $F_1$, $F_3$, Lauricella $F_D^{(3)}$ and Lauricella-Saran $F_S^{(3)}$ and their Application to Feynman Integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02237v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present our investigation of the study of two variable hypergeometric series, namely Appell $F_{1}$ and $F_{3}$ series, and obtain a comprehensive list of its analytic continuations enough to cover the whole real $(x,y)$ plane, except on their singular loci. We also derive analytic continuations of their 3-variable generalization, the Lauricella $F_{D}^{(3)}$ series and the Lauricella-Saran $F_{S}^{(3)}$ series, leveraging the analytic continuations of $F_{1}$ and $F_{3}$, which ensures that the whole real $(x,y,z)$ space is covered, except on the singular loci of these functions. While these studies are motivated by the frequent occurrence of these multivariable hypergeometric functions in Feynman integral evaluation, they can also be used whenever they appear in other branches of mathematical physics. To facilitate their practical use, we provide four packages: $\texttt{AppellF1.wl}$, $\texttt{AppellF3.wl}$, $\texttt{LauricellaFD.wl}$, and $\texttt{LauricellaSaranFS.wl}$ in $\textit{MATHEMATICA}$. These packages are applicable for generic as well as non-generic values of parameters, keeping in mind their utilities in the evaluation of the Feynman integrals. We explicitly present various physical applications of these packages in the context of Feynman integral evaluation and compare the results using other packages such as $\texttt{FIESTA}$. Upon applying the appropriate conventions for numerical evaluation, we find that the results obtained from our packages are consistent. Various $\textit{Mathematica}$ notebooks demonstrating different numerical results are also provided along with this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02237v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cpc.2024.109386</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Comput.Phys.Commun. 306 (2025) 109386</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Souvik Bera, Tanay Pathak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A misleading naming convention: de Sitter `tachyonic' scalar fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17539v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the concept of de Sitter (dS) 'tachyonic' scalar fields, characterized by discrete negative squared mass values, and assess their physical significance through a rigorous Wigner-inspired group-theoretical analysis. This perspective demonstrates that such fields, often misinterpreted as inherently unstable due to their mass parameter, are best understood within the framework of unitary irreducible representations (UIRs) of the dS group. The discrete mass spectrum arises naturally in this representation framework, offering profound insights into the interplay between dS relativity and quantum field theory. Contrary to their misleading nomenclature, we argue that the 'mass' parameter associated with these fields lacks intrinsic physical relevance, challenging traditional assumptions that link it to physical instability. Instead, any perceived instability originates from mismanagement of the system's inherent gauge invariance rather than the fields themselves. A proper treatment of this gauge symmetry, particularly through the Gupta-Bleuler formalism, restores the expected characteristics of these fields as free quantum entities in a highly symmetric spacetime. This study seeks to dispel misconceptions surrounding dS 'tachyonic' fields, underscoring the importance of precise terminology and robust theoretical tools in addressing their unique properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17539v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Pierre Gazeau, Hamed Pejhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representing arbitrary ground states of toric code by a restricted Boltzmann machine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01451v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically analyze the representability of toric code ground states by Restricted Boltzmann Machine with only local connections between hidden and visible neurons. This analysis is pivotal for evaluating the model's capability to represent diverse ground states, thus enhancing our understanding of its strengths and weaknesses. Subsequently, we modify the Restricted Boltzmann Machine to accommodate arbitrary ground states by introducing essential non-local connections efficiently. The new model is not only analytically solvable but also demonstrates efficient and accurate performance when solved using machine learning techniques. Then we generalize our the model from $Z_2$ to $Z_n$ toric code and discuss future directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01451v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.045101</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 045101 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Penghua Chen, Bowen Yan, Shawn X. Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative Lightcones from Quantum SO(2,1) Conformal Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12459v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Five new families of noncommutative lightcones in 2+1 dimensions are presented as the quantizations of the inequivalent Poisson homogeneous structures that emerge when the lightcone is constructed as a homogeneous space of the SO(2,1) conformal group. Each of these noncommutative lightcones maintains covariance under the action of the respective quantum deformation of the SO(2,1) conformal group. We discuss the role played by SO(2,1) automorphisms in the classification of inequivalent Poisson homogeneous lightcones, as well as the geometric aspects of this construction. The localization properties of the novel quantum lightcones are analyzed and shown to be deeply connected with the geometric features of the Poisson homogeneous spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12459v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad9a49</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quant. Grav. 42 (2024) 2, 025005</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Martina Adamo, Angel Ballesteros, Flavio Mercati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal quantum mechanics of causal diamonds: Time evolution, thermality, and instability via path integral functionals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18177v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An observer with a finite lifetime $\mathcal{T}$ perceives the Minkowski vacuum as a thermal state at temperature $T_D = 2 \hbar/(\pi \mathcal{T})$, as a result of being constrained to a double-coned-shaped region known as a causal diamond. In this paper, we explore the emergence of thermality in causal diamonds due to the role played by the symmetries of conformal quantum mechanics (CQM) as a (0+1)-dimensional conformal field theory, within the de Alfaro-Fubini-Furlan model and generalizations. In this context, the hyperbolic operator $S$ of the SO(2,1) symmetry of CQM: (i) is the generator of the time evolution of a diamond observer; (ii) its dynamical behavior leads to the predicted thermal nature; and (iii) its associated quantum instability has a Lyapunov exponent $\lambda_L = \pi T_D/\hbar$, which is half the upper saturation bound of the information scrambling rate. Our approach is based on a comprehensive framework of path-integral representations of the CQM generators in canonical and microcanonical forms, supplemented by semiclassical arguments. The properties of the operator $S$ are studied with emphasis on an operator duality with the corresponding elliptic operator $R$, using a representation in terms of an effective scale-invariant inverse square potential combined with inverted and ordinary harmonic oscillator potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18177v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.124043</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 124043 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>H. E. Camblong, A. Chakraborty, P. Lopez-Duque, C. R. Ord\'o\~nez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal quantum mechanics of causal diamonds: Quantum instability and semiclassical approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18191v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Causal diamonds are known to have thermal behavior that can be probed by finite-lifetime observers equipped with energy-scaled detectors. This thermality can be attributed to the time evolution of observers within the causal diamond, governed by one of the conformal quantum mechanics (CQM) symmetry generators: the noncompact hyperbolic operator $S$. In this paper, we show that the unbounded nature of $S$ endows it with a quantum instability, which is a generalization of a similar property exhibited by the inverted harmonic oscillator potential. Our analysis is semiclassical, including a detailed phase-space study of the classical dynamics of $S$ and its dual operator $R$, and a general semiclassical framework yielding basic instability and thermality properties that play a crucial role in the quantum behavior of the theory. For an observer with a finite lifetime $\mathcal{T}$, the detected temperature
  $T_D = 2 \hbar/(\pi \mathcal{T})$ is associated with a Lyapunov exponent $\lambda_L = \pi T_D/\hbar$, which is half the upper saturation bound of the information scrambling rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18191v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. E. Camblong, A. Chakraborty, P. Lopez-Duque, C. Ord\'o\~nez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-time Asymptotics for the Ablowitz-Ladik system with present of solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21526v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the soliton resolution and Painlev\'e asymptotics for the focusing Ablowitz-Ladik system with the initial data in a discrete weighted $\ell^2$ space. First, we establish the global well-posedness of this initial-value problem, which is further reformulated as a Riemann-Hilbert problem with higher-order poles. Using Fredholm theory, the Riemann-Hilbert problem with the jump contour consisting of three circles centered around the origin is uniquely solved. Then, by performing a $\bar\partial$-nonlinear steepest descent method to the Riemann-Hilbert problem, we obtain the asymptotic approximation to the solution of the focusing Ablowitz-Ladik system for large time in different space-time regions of the $(n,t)$-half plane. In the sectors $\{(n,t): n /(2t) &lt;-M_0 \}$ and $\{(n,t): n /(2t) &gt;M_0 \}$, where $M_0$ is a positive constant, the leading order asymptotics is dominated by the solitons; while in the sector $\{(n,t): |n /(2t) -1 &lt;M_0^{-1} \}$, the long-time asymptotics is influenced by both the solitons and the oscillations; In the two transition zones $\{(n,t): |n /(2t)+1|t^{2/3} &lt;C \}$ and $\{(n,t): |n /(2t)-1|t^{2/3} &lt;C \}$ with $C$ being a positive constant, we find the Painlev\'e-type asymptotics which can be expressed in terms of the solution of the second Painlev\'e transcendents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21526v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meisen Chen, Engui Fan, Zhaoyu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the crystal limit of the q-difference sixth Painlev\'e equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07963v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the Riemann-Hilbert correspondence associated with the $q$-difference sixth Painlev\'e equation in the crystal limit, i.e. $q\rightarrow 0$, and show two main results. First, the limit of this generically highly transcendental mapping is shown to exist. Second, we show that the limiting map is bi-rational and describe it explicitly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07963v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nalini Joshi, Pieter Roffelsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic classification of Hietarinta's solutions of Yang-Baxter equations~:~invertible $4\times 4$ operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05375v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In order to examine the simulation of integrable quantum systems using quantum computers, it is crucial to first classify Yang-Baxter operators. Hietarinta was among the first to classify constant Yang-Baxter solutions for a two-dimensional local Hilbert space (qubit representation). Including the one produced by the permutation operator, he was able to construct eleven families of invertible solutions. These techniques are effective for 4 by 4 solutions, but they become difficult to use for representations with more dimensions. To get over this limitation, we use algebraic ans\"{a}tze to generate the constant Yang-Baxter solutions in a representation independent way. We employ four distinct algebraic structures that, depending on the qubit representation, replicate 10 of the 11 Hietarinta families. Among the techniques are partition algebras, Clifford algebras, Temperley-Lieb algebras, and a collection of commuting operators. Using these techniques, we do not obtain the $(2,2)$ Hietarinta class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05375v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)067</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2024, 67 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Somnath Maity, Vivek Kumar Singh, Pramod Padmanabhan, Vladimir Korepin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality for Diagonal Eigenvector Overlaps of non-Hermitian Random Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16144v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the universality of the joint distribution of an eigenvalue and the corresponding diagonal eigenvector overlap, in the bulk and at the edge, for eigenvalues of complex matrices and real eigenvalues of real matrices. As part of the proof we obtain a bound for the least non-zero singular value of $X-z$ when $z$ is an edge eigenvalue and a bound for the inner product between left and right singular vectors of $X-z$ when $|z|=1+O(N^{-1/2})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16144v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Osman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The two-loop Amplituhedron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11501v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The loop-Amplituhedron $\mathcal{A}^{(L)}_{n}$ is a semialgebraic set in the product of Grassmannians $\mathrm{Gr}_{\mathbb{R}}(2,4)^L$. Recently, many aspects of this geometry for the case of $L=1$ have been elucidated, such as its algebraic and face stratification, its residual arrangement and the existence and uniqueness of the adjoint. This paper extends this analysis to the simplest higher loop case given by the two-loop four-point Amplituhedron $\mathcal{A}^{(2)}_4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11501v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Dian, Elia Mazzucchelli, Felix Tellander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal coarse geometry of spin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07912v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The prospect of realizing highly entangled states on quantum processors with fundamentally different hardware geometries raises the question: to what extent does a state of a quantum spin system have an intrinsic geometry? In this paper, we propose that both states and dynamics of a spin system have a canonically associated coarse geometry, in the sense of Roe, on the set of sites in the thermodynamic limit. For a state $\phi$ on an (abstract) spin system with an infinite collection of sites $X$, we define a universal coarse structure $\mathcal{E}_{\phi}$ on the set $X$ with the property that a state has decay of correlations with respect to a coarse structure $\mathcal{E}$ on $X$ if and only if $\mathcal{E}_{\phi}\subseteq \mathcal{E}$. We show that under mild assumptions, the coarsely connected completion $(\mathcal{E}_{\phi})_{con}$ is stable under quasi-local perturbations of the state $\phi$. We also develop in parallel a dynamical coarse structure for arbitrary quantum channels, and prove a similar stability result. We show that several order parameters of a state only depend on the coarse structure of an underlying spatial metric, and we establish a basic compatibility between the dynamical coarse structure associated to a quantum circuit $\alpha$ and the coarse structure of the state $\psi\circ \alpha$ where $\psi$ is any product state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07912v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Elokl, Corey Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Itinerant Ferromagnetism from One-Dimensional Mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03638v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a universal kinetic mechanism for a half-metallic ferromagnet -- a metallic state with full spin polarization -- arising from strong on-site Coulomb repulsions between particles that exhibit constrained one-dimensional (1D) dynamics. We illustrate the mechanism in the context of a solvable model on a Lieb lattice in which doped electrons have 1D mobility. Such 1D motion is shown to induce only multi-spin ring exchanges of even parity, which mediate ferromagnetism and result in a unique half-metallic ground state. In contrast to the Nagaoka mechanism of ferromagnetism, this result pertains to any doped electron density in the {\it thermodynamic} limit. We explore various microscopic routes to such (approximate) 1D dynamics, highlighting two examples: doped holes in the strong-coupling limit of the Emery model and vacancies in a two-dimensional Wigner crystal. Finally, we demonstrate an intriguing exact equivalence between the bosonic and fermionic versions of these models, which implies a novel mechanism for the conjectured Bose metallic phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03638v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyung-Su Kim, Veit Elser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical measure of the propagation between two topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11928v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the propagation of initial condition in the presence of two topological insulators without magnetic field where the interface is a smooth connected not compact curve without boundaries. The solution is governed by an adiabatic modulation of a Dirac operator with a variable mass. We determine the evolution of the semiclassical measure of the solution with a two-scale Wigner measure method by reducing the Dirac operator to a normal form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11928v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Eric Vacelet</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
