<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math-ph</link>
    <description>math-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Limit shapes for Domain-Wall (colored) vertex models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study partition functions with domain-wall like boundary conditions for path models issued from colored vertex models. These models display an arctic phenomenon, as attested by numerical simulations. We show that the colored vertex model is equivalent to a certain single-color ``colorblind" vertex model. In a special case of the weights for the colorblind touching paths, we derive the arctic curve using a bijective sliding map to non-intersecting paths, for which arctic curves were previously derived using the tangent method. The resulting arctic curves are only piecewise analytic, as in the known non-free fermion cases of Six vertex model with domain-wall boundaries and its relatives. We also prove a shear phenomenon, that some portions of the arctic curve are sheared versions of the analytic continuation of other portions, as already observed in the uniformly weighted Six and Twenty vertex models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25442v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philippe Di Francesco, David Keating</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hadamard parametrix on half-Minkowski with Robin boundary conditions: Fundamental solutions and Hadamard states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the problem of constructing fundamental solutions and Hadamard states for a Klein-Gordon field in half-Minkowski spacetime with Robin boundary conditions in $d \geq 2$ spacetime dimensions. First, using a generalisation of the Robin-to-Dirichlet map exploited by Bondurant and Fulling [J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. {\bf 38} 7 (2005)] in dimension $2$, we obtain a representation for the advanced and retarded Green operators in terms of a convolution with the kernel of the inverse Robin-to-Dirichlet map. This allows us to prove the uniqueness and support properties of the Green operators. Second, we obtain a local representation for the Hadamard parametrix that provides the correct local definition of Hadamard states in $d \geq 2$ dimensions, capturing `reflected' singularities from the spacetime boundary. We show that our fundamental solutions abide by this local parametrix representation. Finally, we prove the equivalence of our local Hadamard condition and the global Hadamard condition with a wave-front set described in terms of generalized broken bi-characteristics, obtaining a Radzikowski-like theorem in half-Minkowski spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26035v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Costeri, C. Dappiaggi, B. A. Ju\'arez-Aubry, R. D. Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-Hamiltonian Structures and Equivalent Representations of the Pais-Uhlenbeck Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26477v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a complete classification of all the ways the Pais-Uhlenbeck osicllator might be embedded in two dimensional space. We discuss the Bi-Hamiltonian structures of this model, and examine how alternative Hamiltonian structures might be generated from the dynamical Lie symmetries of the theory. We then examine how the Bi-Hamiltonian strucutre may be exploited to evade the problem of unbounded Hamiltonians that is usually associated with Higher Time Derivative Theories. The effect of interactions on this Bi-Hamiltonian structure is also considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26477v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bethan Turner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularities at the vertex of connected angular inhomogeneities under thermal and elastic loading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26609v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the singularities at the vertex of multiply connected angular inhomogeneities for heat conduction and elastic deformation. With the aid of Eshelby's equivalent inclusion method (EIM), each inhomogeneity is simulated as an equivalent inclusion, exhibiting the same material properties as the matrix but containing a continuously distributed eigen-field with potential singularities at the vertices and edge lines. Specifically, the eigen-temperature-gradient (ETG) and eigenstrain are utilized to simulate material mismatch of thermal conductivity and stiffness, respectively. Using the separation of variables, the eigen-fields can be formulated in terms of distance to vertices and opening angles, and disturbed thermal/elastic fields are evaluated by domain integrals of Green's function multiplied by eigen-fields, which form Fredholm's integral equation of the second kind. The boundary value problem is reduced to solve for eigenvalues, which are used to determine the order of singularity. The present solution is versatile - by placing two identical inhomogeneities together, it recovers the classic solutions for a single wedge in a bimaterial media or infinite domain. The general and analytical formulae take full consideration of interactions of multiple inhomogeneities and reveal the effects of opening angles and material properties on the thermal and elastic singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26609v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanpeng Yang, Huiming Yin, Chunlin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferromagnetic domain walls under spin-orbit torque</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22241v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Domain walls in antiferromagnets under a spin-polarized current present rich dynamics that is not observed in ferromagnets, and it is tunable by the current polarization. Precessional dynamics is obtained for perpendicular spin polarization, in agreement with expectations in older works. Propagating walls are obtained for an in-plane polarization. We obtain the velocity as a function of current by a perturbation method for low velocities, and the wall profile is found to lack a definite parity. For high velocities, the main features of the wall profile are obtained by a direct solution of an equation that is valid in a limiting case. We discuss the magnetization of the dynamical walls and find that this can become large, providing a potential method for observations. Oscillatory motion of domain walls is obtained for spin polarization that has both perpendicular and in-plane components, and an analytical description is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22241v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Theodorou, Stavros Komineas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological non-Abelian Gauge Structures in Cayley-Schreier Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, novel crystalline constructions known as Cayley-Schreier lattices have been suggested as a platform for realizing arbitrary gauge fields in synthetic crystals with real hopping amplitudes. We show that Cayley-Schreier lattices can naturally give rise to implementable lattice systems that incorporate non-Abelian gauge structures transforming into a space-group symmetry. We show that the symmetry sectors can, moreover, be interpreted as blocks of spin models that can effectively realize a wealth of different topological invariants in a single setup. We underpin these general results with concrete models and show how they can be implemented in current experimental platforms. Our work sets the stage for a systematic investigation of topological insulators and metals with non-Abelian gauge structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25316v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zolt\'an Guba, Robert-Jan Slager, Lavi K. Upreti, Tom\'a\v{s} Bzdu\v{s}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Wigner theorem for non-invertible symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25327v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish the conditions under which a conservation law associated with a non-invertible operator may be realized as a symmetry in quantum mechanics. As illustrated by Wigner, all symmetries forming a group structure (and hence invertible) must be either unitary or antiunitary. Relinquishing this assumption of invertibility, we demonstrate that the fundamental invariance of quantum transition probabilities under the application of symmetries mandates that all non-invertible symmetries may only correspond to {\it projective} unitary or antiunitary transformations, i.e., {\it partial isometries}. This extends the notion of physical states beyond conventional rays in Hilbert space to equivalence classes in an {\it extended, gauged Hilbert space}, thereby broadening the traditional understanding of symmetry transformations in quantum theory. We discuss consequences of this result and explicitly illustrate how, in simple model systems, whether symmetries be invertible or non-invertible may be inextricably related to the particular boundary conditions that are being used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25327v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerardo Ortiz, Chinmay Giridhar, Philipp Vojta, Andriy H. Nevidomskyy, Zohar Nussinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalization of Chern-Simons Wilson Loops via Flux Quantization in Cohomotopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25336v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the practice of physics model building, the process of renormalization, resummation, and anomaly cancellation is to incrementally repair initially ill-defined Lagrangian quantum field theories. Impressive as this is, one would rather have concisely defined complete theories to begin with, and understand these choices as emergent from fundamental principles. As an instructive example, we recall renormalization choices for Wilson loop observables in abelian Chern-Simons theory. Then we show that these emerge in a novel non-Lagrangian topological completion of 5D Maxwell-Chern-Simons QFT, by means of proper flux quantization in 2-Cohomotopy. This result is a modest cousin, with applications to topologically ordered quantum materials, of the more ambitious flux quantization of 11D supergravity in 4-Cohomotopy ("Hypothesis H").</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25336v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hisham Sati, Urs Schreiber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast quantum computation with all-to-all Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25345v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: All-to-all interactions arise naturally in many areas of theoretical physics and across diverse experimental quantum platforms, motivating a systematic study of their information-processing power. Assuming each pair of qubits interacts with $\mathrm{O}(1)$ strength, time-dependent all-to-all Hamiltonians can simulate arbitrary all-to-all quantum circuits, performing quantum computation in time proportional to the circuit depth. We show that this naive correspondence is far from optimal: all-to-all Hamiltonians can process information on much shorter timescales.
  First, we prove that any two-qubit gate can be simulated by all-to-all Hamiltonians on $N$ qubits in time $\mathrm{O}(1/N)$ (up to factor $N^{\delta}$ with an arbitrarily small constant $\delta&gt;0$), with polynomially small error $1/\mathrm{poly}(N)$. Immediate consequences include: 1) Certain $\mathrm{O}(N)$-qubit unitaries and entangled states, such as the multiply-controlled Toffoli gate and the GHZ and W states, can be generated in $\mathrm{O}(1/N)$ time; 2) Trading space for time, any quantum circuit can be simulated in arbitrarily short time; 3) Information could propagate in a fast way that saturates known Lieb-Robinson bounds in strongly power-law interacting systems.
  Our second main result proves that any depth-$D$ quantum circuit can be simulated by a randomized Hamiltonian protocol in time $T=\mathrm{O}(D/\sqrt{N})$, with constant space overhead and polynomially small error.
  The techniques underlying our results depart fundamentally from the existing literature on parallelizing commuting gates: We rely crucially on non-commuting Hamiltonians and draw on diverse physical ideas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25345v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nijenhuis operators on Banach fibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25405v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the infinite-dimensional Banach setting, we consider general smooth Banach fibrations $\tau:M\to M_0$ and `$(1,1)$-tensors' $N:TM\to TM$ that are projectable (in the obvious sense) onto Nijenhuis operators $N_0:TM_0\to TM_0$ on $M_0$. We prove that the vanishing of the Nijenhuis torsion of $N_0$ is equivalent to the fact that the Nijenhuis torsion of $N$ takes only vertical values, i.e., values in $ker(T\tau)$. Consequences for almost complex structures on (real) Banach manifolds are also derived. As canonical examples, we define tangent lifts $d_T(N_0):TT M_0\to TT M_0$ of Nijenhuis operators $N_0$ in the Banach category, and prove that they are automatically projectable for the canonical fibrations $\tau_{M_0}:TM_0\to M_0$. Finally, we comment on the projectability in the case of Banach homogeneous manifolds $\tau:G\to G/K$, studied recently by some authors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25405v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katarzyna Grabowska, Janusz Grabowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic Monge-Amp\`ere Equation on a Cylinder: Well-Posedness and Stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper develops a rigorous analytic framework for the hyperbolic Monge-Amp\`ere equation on strip-like domains, which model wrinkled patterns in thin elastic sheets. Our work addresses the rigid side of the classical rigidity-flexibility dichotomy by defining this regime not by high smoothness, but by the more fundamental property of partial convexity. The hodograph transformation is the natural tool for this setting, as its validity is predicated on partial convexity. It converts the nonlinear Monge-Amp\`ere equation into a linear damped wave equation, allowing us to formulate a well-posed Cauchy-Goursat problem. A key challenge is the corner singularity that arises where characteristic and non-characteristic boundary data meet. To resolve this, we develop a parametrix-corrector decomposition that captures the solution's inherent singular behavior. This method recasts the problem as a singular Volterra integral equation, for which we prove the existence and uniqueness of a new class of hodograph weak solutions. Finally, we derive energy estimates to establish the quantitative stability of these rigid solutions under perturbations of the underlying curvature function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25553v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Deliyianni, Shankar C. Venkataramani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-Range Bosonic Systems at Thermal Equilibrium: Computational Complexity and Clustering of Correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Long-range systems, characterized by couplings that decay as a power law $r^{-\alpha}$, are of fundamental importance and attract widespread interest across diverse physical phenomena. Among these, bosonic systems are particularly significant due to their theoretical importance and experimental relevance. In this Letter, we propose a classical algorithm with a quasipolynomial runtime to efficiently approximate the partition function of long-range bosonic systems at high temperatures. For finite-range systems, the complexity improves to almost polynomial time. We also present a rigorous proof for the power-law decay of correlation functions. This property, known as clustering of correlation, is well-established for finite-range spin models. However, in sharp contrast, has remained largely unexplored for long-range bosonic systems. The results presented here address two long-standing gaps concerning the computational complexity and correlation clustering in such systems. The methodology we introduce provides new tools for future studies of challenging problems in statistical and quantum many-body physics concerning bosonic system and computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25572v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin-Hai Tong, Tomotaka Kuwahara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Stochastic-Dissipative St\"{o}rmer Problem-Trajectories and Radiation Patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a generalization of the classical nonrelativistic St\"{o}rmer problem, describing the motion of charged particles in a purely magnetic dipole field, by taking into account the effects of the dissipation, assumed to be of friction type, proportional to the velocity of the particle, and of the presence of stochastic forces. In the presence of dissipative/stochastic effects, the motion of the particle in the magnetic dipole field can be described by a generalized Langevin type equation, which generalizes the standard Lorentz force equation. We perform a detailed numerical analysis of the dynamical behavior of the particles in a magnetic dipolar field in the presence of dissipative and stochastic forces, as well as of the electromagnetic radiation patterns emitted during the motion. The effects of the dissipation coefficient and of the stochastic force on the particle motion and on the emitted electromagnetic power are investigated, and thus a full description of the spectrum of the magnetic dipole type electromagnetic radiation and of the physical properties of the motion is also obtained. The power spectral density of the emitted electromagnetic power is also obtained for each case, and, for all considered St\"{o}rmer type models, it shows the presence of peaks in the radiation spectrum, corresponding to certain intervals of the frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25888v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiberiu Harko, Gabriela Raluca Mocanu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Solutions to the Quantum Schr\"odinger Bridge Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25980v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Quantum Schr\"odinger Bridge Problem (QSBP) describes the evolution of a stochastic process between two arbitrary probability distributions, where the dynamics are governed by the Schr\"odinger equation rather than by the traditional real-valued wave equation. Although the QSBP is known in the mathematical literature, we formulate it here from a Lagrangian perspective and derive its main features in a way that is particularly suited to generative modeling. We show that the resulting evolution equations involve the so-called Bohm (quantum) potential, representing a notion of non-locality in the stochastic process. This distinguishes the QSBP from classical stochastic dynamics and reflects a key characteristic typical of quantum mechanical systems. In this work, we derive exact closed-form solutions for the QSBP between Gaussian distributions. Our derivation is based on solving the Fokker-Planck Equation (FPE) and the Hamilton-Jacobi Equation (HJE) arising from the Lagrangian formulation of dynamical Optimal Transport. We find that, similar to the classical Schr\"odinger Bridge Problem, the solution to the QSBP between Gaussians is again a Gaussian process; however, the evolution of the covariance differs due to quantum effects. Leveraging these explicit solutions, we present a modified algorithm based on a Gaussian Mixture Model framework, and demonstrate its effectiveness across several experimental settings, including single-cell evolution data, image generation, molecular translation and applications in Mean-Field Games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25980v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mykola Bordyuh, Djork-Arn\'e Clevert, Marco Bertolini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the propagation of mountain waves: linear theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26125v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive and establish a solution concept for the linear mountain wave problem in two dimensions. After linearizing the governing equations and a change of variables, the problem can be stated as a Dirichlet boundary value problem for a Helmholtz equation in terms of the vertical wind profile in the upper half-plane, with altitude-dependent potential (the Scorer parameter). To single out the correct solution, we have to make use of a radiation condition which is, due to the different physical situation, different from the classical Sommerfeld radiation condition for electromagnetic or acoustic waves. We rigorously develop a transform method and construct the physically correct solution, following Lyra's monotonicity criterion for mountain waves. In this procedure, we clearly recognize the two typical types of mountain waves: vertically propagating waves and trapped lee waves. This paper is the first rigorous work on Helmholtz-like equations in the upper half-plane subject to such a non-classical radiation condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26125v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Constantin, J\"org Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLT for LES of real valued random centrosymmetric matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26141v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the fluctuations of the eigenvalues of real valued large centrosymmetric random matrices via its linear eigenvalue statistic. This is essentially a central limit theorem (CLT) for sums of dependent random variables. The dependence among them leads to behavior that differs from the classical CLT. The main contribution of this article is finding the expression of the variance of the limiting Gaussian distribution. The crux of the proof lies in combinatorial arguments that involve counting overlapping loops in complete undirected weighted graphs with growing degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26141v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indrajit Jana, Sunita Rani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concavity of spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26196v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by recent breathtaking progress in the synthetic study of Lorentzian geometry, we investigate the local concavity of time separation functions on Finsler spacetimes as a Lorentzian counterpart to Busemann's convexity in metric geometry. We show that a Berwald spacetime is locally concave if and only if its flag curvature is nonnegative in timelike directions. We also give another characterization of nonnegative flag curvature by the convexity of future (or past) capsules, inspired by Krist\'aly--Kozma's result in the positive definite case. These characterizations are new even for Lorentzian manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26196v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Beran, Darius Er\"os, Shin-ichi Ohta, Felix Rott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competition of small targets in planar domains: from Dirichlet to Robin and Steklov boundary condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26367v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider steady-state diffusion in a bounded planar domain with multiple small targets on a smooth boundary. Using the method of matched asymptotic expansions, we investigate the competition of these targets for a diffusing particle and the crucial role of surface reactions on the targets. We start from the classical problem of splitting probabilities for perfectly reactive targets with Dirichlet boundary condition and improve some earlier results. We discuss how this approach can be generalized to partially reactive targets characterized by a Robin boundary condition. In particular, we show how partial reactivity reduces the effective size of the target. In addition, we consider more intricate surface reactions modeled by mixed Steklov-Neumann or Steklov-Neumann-Dirichlet problems. We provide the first derivation of the asymptotic behavior of the eigenvalues and eigenfunctions for these spectral problems in the small-target limit. Finally, we show how our asymptotic approach can be extended to interior targets in the bulk and to exterior problems where diffusion occurs in an unbounded planar domain outside a compact set. Direct applications of these results to diffusion-controlled reactions are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26367v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis S. Grebenkov, Michael J. Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effective Reactivity for Capturing Brownian Motion by Partially Reactive Patches on a Spherical Surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26381v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the trapping of diffusing ligands, modeled as Brownian particles, by a sphere that has $N$ partially reactive boundary patches, each of small area, on an otherwise reflecting boundary. For such a structured target, the partial reactivity of each boundary patch is characterized by a Robin boundary condition, with a local boundary reactivity $\kappa_i$ for $i=1,\ldots,N$. For any spatial arrangement of well-separated patches on the surface of the sphere, the method of matched asymptotic expansions is used to derive explicit results for the capacitance $C_{\rm T}$ of the structured target, which is valid for any $\kappa_i&gt;0$. This target capacitance $C_{\rm T}$ is defined in terms of a Green's matrix, which depends on the spatial configuration of patches, the local reactive capacitance $C_i(\kappa_i)$ of each patch and another coefficient that depends on the local geometry near a patch. The analytical dependence of $C_{i}(\kappa_i)$ on $\kappa_i$ is uncovered via a spectral expansion over Steklov eigenfunctions. For circular patches, the latter are readily computed numerically and provide an accurate fully explicit sigmoidal approximation for $C_{i}(\kappa_i)$. In the homogenization limit of $N\gg 1$ identical uniformly-spaced patches with $\kappa_i=\kappa$, we derive an explicit scaling law for the effective capacitance and the effective reactivity of the structured target that is valid in the limit of small patch area fraction. From a comparison with numerical simulations, we show that this scaling law provides a highly accurate approximation over the full range $\kappa&gt;0$, even when there is only a moderately large number of reactive patches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26381v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis S. Grebenkov, Michael J. Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine Gauge Theory: A Diffeomorphism Invariant Gauge Theory of Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper is a comprehensive investigation of the Affine Gauge Theory (AGT) as a gauge theory of gravity having the same mathematical structure as gauge theories of the other fundamental forces of nature. This mathematical structure consists of a principal fiber bundle over the spacetime manifold that is endowed with an affine connection. The relationship between AGT and various formulations of teleparallel theories of gravity, which are alternatives to General Relativity, are examined. Here, it is argued that the Affine Bundle is the most natural principal fibre bundle for a gauge theory of gravity. AGT is also shown to be strictly diffeomorphism invariant. In particular, an explicit proof of diffeomorphism invariance in AGT is given - showing that AGT possesses the important symmetry of General Relativity, as would be expected from a theory of gravity. Lastly, the claim that AGT is background independent, as General Relativity is, from varying degrees of strictness in the definition of background independence is closely examined. Reasons for why a background independent theory is preferred are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26410v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kurniawan Tjandra, Kuldip Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the dependence of the nonlinear Schrodinger flow upon the power of the nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26414v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove continuity properties for the flow map associated to the defocusing energy-subcritical power-like nonlinear Schr{\"o}dinger equation, when the power varies. We show local in time continuity in the energy space for any power, and global in time continuity for sufficiently large powers. When the linear dispersive rate is counterbalanced by a time-dependent rescaling, we show a uniform in time continuity of the squared modulus of this rescaled function, in Kantorovich distance, for any power, including long range cases in terms of scattering. The most difficult result addresses the convergence of suitably renormalized solutions to the solution of the logarithmic Schr{\"o}dinger equation, when the power goes to zero, uniformly in time, in Kantorovich distance. The proof relies on estimates for perturbed porous medium equations, involving the harmonic Fokker-Planck operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26414v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'emi Carles (IRMAR), Quentin Chauleur (LPP), Guillaume Ferriere (LPP)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural and Compositional Complexities of Hierarchical Self-Assembly: a Hypergraph Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26449v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Programmable self-assembly enables the construction of complex molecular, supramolecular, and crystalline architectures from well-designed building blocks. Here we introduce a hypergraph-based framework, termed Blocks \&amp; Bonds (B\&amp;B), that extends classical chemical graph theory to encode directed multi-colored interactions, internal symmetries of building blocs, and hierarchical organization. Within this framework, we develop a universal script, Structure Code, for encoding complex hypergraph organization. In the spirit of Kolmogorov's approach, we define Structural Complexity as the minimal information required to encode a self-assembled structure. It is complemented by Compositional Complexity, capturing the diversity of building blocks. The two measures are related through Complexity Inequality, stating that structural complexity cannot exceed compositional complexity for programmable assembly, and identify cases where violations signal emergent complexity. Applications to molecular systems (ethylene glycol, glucose) and programmable DNA-origami lattices demonstrate how B\&amp;B hypergraphs and the structure code naturally capture modularity, stereochemistry, and crystallographic order while enabling significant compression of structural information. This approach provides a unified and scalable language for classifying complexity across scales, bridging information theory with the design of programmable matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26449v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexei V. Tkachenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On uniqueness of radial potentials for given Dirichlet spectra with distinct angular momenta</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26485v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider an inverse spectral problem for radial Schr\" odinger operators with singular potentials. First, we show that the knowledge of the Dirichlet spectra for infinitely many angular momenta~$\ell$ satisfying a M\"untz-type condition uniquely determines the potential. Then, in a neighborhood of the zero potential, we prove that the potential is uniquely determined by two Dirichlet spectra associated with distinct angular momenta in the cases \((\ell_1,\ell_2) = (0,1)\) and \((0,2)\). Our approach relies on an explicit analysis of the corresponding singular differential equation, combined with the classical Kneser--Sommerfeld formula. These results confirm, in the linearized setting and in these configurations, a conjecture originally formulated by Rundell and Sacks (2001).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26485v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damien Gobin, Beno\^it Gr\'ebert, Bernard Helffer, Fran\c{c}ois Nicoleau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Fermat's principle and Snell's law for cone structures and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26492v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fermat's principle is fully generalized to the case where a smooth interface separates two cone structures -- Lorentz-Finsler lightcones -- representing wave propagation in a potentially inhomogeneous, anisotropic, time-dependent and discontinuous medium. The interface, wave source and receiver are assumed to be a hypersurface, a submanifold and a curve in the spacetime, respectively, of any causal character. For a trajectory to fullfil Fermat's principle -- i.e., to be a critical point of the arrival time functional -- its direction must change at the interface, obeying a precise condition that generalizes Snell's law of refraction when the wave crosses the interface, or the law of reflection when it remains in a single medium. Both laws are analyzed in detail to establish the conditions ensuring the existence and uniqueness of refracted and reflected trajectories, and to determine whether they actually minimize the arrival time. Applications to Zermelo's navigation problem and the determination of geodesics in discretized spacetimes are also emphasized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26492v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel \'Angel Javaloyes, Steen Markvorsen, Enrique Pend\'as-Recondo, Miguel S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A family of instanton-invariants for four-manifolds and their relation to Khovanov homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13285v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article provides a review of the gauge-theoretic approach to Khovanov homology, framed in terms of a generalisation of Witten's original proposal. Concretely, the physical arguments underlying Witten's insights suggest that there is a one-parameter family of Haydys-Witten instanton Floer homology groups $HF_{\theta}(W^4)$ for four-manifolds. At the heart of the proposal is a systematic investigation of the dimensional reductions of the Haydys-Witten equations. It is shown that on the five-dimensional cylinder $M^5=\mathbb{R}_s\times W^4$ with nowhere-vanishing vector field $v=\cos\theta\, \partial_s+\sin\theta\, w$, the Haydys-Witten equations provide flow equations for the $\theta$-Kapustin-Witten equations on $W^4$. Similar reductions to lower dimensions include the twisted extended Bogomolny equations on three-manifolds and the twisted octonionic Nahm equations on one-manifolds, whose solutions provide natural boundary conditions along the boundary and corners of $W^4$. These reductions determine the indicial roots of the Haydys-Witten and $\theta$-Kapustin-Witten equations with twisted Nahm-pole boundary conditions, which are required to establish elliptic regularity. Motivated by these insights, the groups $HF_{\theta}(W^4)$ are defined in analogy with Yang-Mills instanton Floer theory: solutions of the $\theta$-Kapustin-Witten equations on $W^4$ modulo Haydys-Witten instantons on the cylinder $\mathbb{R}_s\times W^4$ interpolating between them. The relation to knot invariants observed by Witten arises when the four-manifold is the geometric blow-up $W^4=[X^3\times\mathbb{R}^+,K]$ along a knot $K\subset X^3\times{0}$ in its three-dimensional boundary. This yields a precise restatement of Witten's conjecture as the equality between $HF^\bullet_{\pi/2}([S^3\times\mathbb{R}^+,K])$ and Khovanov homology $Kh^\bullet(K)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13285v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Bleher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the generalized Langevin equation and the Mori projection operator technique</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20457v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In statistical physics, the Nakajima-Mori-Zwanzig projection operator formalism is used to derive an integro-differential equation for observables in a Hilbert space, the generalized Langevin equation (GLE). This technique relies on the splitting of the dynamics into a projected and an orthogonal part. However, the well-posedness of the abstract Cauchy problem for the orthogonal dynamics remains an open problem. Moreover, it is rarely discussed under which assumptions the Dyson identity, which is used to derive the GLE, holds. In this article, we address this issue for rank-one projections (Mori's projection). For the Mori projection, the orthogonal dynamics is obtained from the bounded perturbation theorem. The variation of constants formula for strongly continuous semigroups then yields the GLE and the second fluctuation dissipation theorem (2FDT). We show that the variation of constants can be replaced by a limiting process in order to give a general proof of the GLE and 2FDT that does not require the differentiability of the fluctuating forces. In addition, we offer an alternative approach that does not require the bounded perturbation theorem. Our starting point is the observation that the GLE and 2FDT uniquely determine the fluctuating forces as well as the memory kernel. Furthermore, the orbit maps for the orthogonal dynamics can be directly defined via solutions of linear Volterra equations. All desired properties of the orthogonal dynamics are then proven directly from this definition. In particular, the orthogonal dynamics is a strongly continuous semigroup generated by $\overline{\mathcal{QL}}\mathcal{Q}=\mathcal{QLQ}$, where $\mathcal{L}$ is the generator of the time evolution operator, and $\mathcal{P}=1-\mathcal{Q}$ is the Mori projection operator. Our results apply to general autonomous dynamical systems whose time evolution is given by a strongly continuous semigroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20457v5</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/ae02cc</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Widder, Johannes Zimmer, Tanja Schilling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the periodic Fredkin chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18291v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Fredkin chain is a spin-$1/2$ model with interaction of three nearest neighbors. In the case of periodic boundary conditions, the ground state is degenerate and can be described in terms of equivalence classes of Dyck paths. We introduce two operators commuting with the Hamiltonian which play the roles of lowering and raising operators when acting on the ground states. These operators generate the $B$- or $C$-type Lie algebras, depending on whether the number of sites $N$ is odd or even, respectively, with rank $n=\lceil N/2\rceil$. The third component of the total spin operator can be represented as a sum of the Cartan subalgebra elements and some central element. In the $C$-type Lie algebra case (even number of sites), this representation coincides with a similar formula previously conjectured for spin-$1$ operators, in the context of the periodic Motzkin chain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18291v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei G. Pronko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is a Dissipative System Always a Gradient System or a Gradient Like System?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14409v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We find that to the dynamics of a given dissipative system a $p=1$ differential form can be associated with a general decomposition into a potential term and a non-potential residual part. If the residual part is absent the form is closed and the system is gradient system or gradient like. If it is non-closed, in the differential form approach, it remains non-closed under a variable change of coordinates, i.e., the system is not a gradient one or a gradient like in any coordinate system. On the other hand, there are claims that a potential should always exists, i.e., the class of dissipative systems and the the class of gradient systems should coincide. We fix this conundrum by introducing a generalized change of coordinates that aims a transformation to a gradient system or a gradient like system. The condition of being closed in the new coordinates of a certain, through the generalized change of coordinates defined differential form, results in a nonlinear differential equation together with a consistency condition. We give examples of physical systems where an analytical solution for the transformation can be found, and hitherto, the potential, but even when the potential is not accessible analytically, we find that it always exist, and therefore we give in principle an affirmative answer to the defining question of this work. Our findings removes loopholes in the question if a potential may exist but it is not known.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14409v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Rangel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An easier way to compute 2-cocycles coming from a reduction for semidirect products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16169v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For Hamiltonian actions of semidirect products $G=F \ltimes H$, we study 2-cocycles arising from residual Hamiltonian actions of $F$ on Hamiltonian reductions for $H$. The motivation comes from the study of Teichmuller spaces for surfaces with boundary, which carry Hamiltonian actions of the Virasoro algebra. In this paper, we give a general setup for the problem, and we suggest an easier way to obtain the Gelfand-Fuchs 2-cocycles for Hamiltonian actions on Teichmuller spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16169v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viacheslav Goncharov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationary solutions to the stochastic Burgers equation on the line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.07464</link>
      <description>arXiv:1910.07464v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider invariant measures for the stochastic Burgers equation on $\mathbb{R}$, forced by the derivative of a spacetime-homogeneous Gaussian noise that is white in time and smooth in space. An invariant measure is indecomposable, or extremal, if it cannot be represented as a convex combination of other invariant measures. We show that for each $a\in\mathbb{R}$, there is a unique indecomposable law of a spacetime-stationary solution with mean $a$, in a suitable function space. We also show that solutions starting from spatially-decaying perturbations of mean-$a$ periodic functions converge in law to the extremal space-time stationary solution with mean $a$ as time goes to infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1910.07464v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-021-04025-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Comm. Math. Phys. volume 382 (2021), 875--949</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Dunlap, Cole Graham, Lenya Ryzhik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental speed limits on entanglement dynamics of bipartite quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.07415v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The speed limits on entanglement are defined as the maximal rate at which entanglement can be generated or degraded in a physical process. We derive the speed limits on entanglement, using the relative entropy of entanglement and trace-distance entanglement, for unitary as well as for arbitrary quantum dynamics, where we assume that the dynamics of the closest separable state can be approximately described by the closest separable dynamics of the actual dynamics of the system. For unitary dynamics of isolated bipartite systems which are described by pure states, the rate of entanglement production is bounded by the product of fluctuations of the system's driving Hamiltonian and the surprisal operator, with an additional term reflecting the time-dependent nature of the closest separable state. Removing restrictions on the purity of the input and on the unitarity of the evolution, the two terms in the bound get suitably altered.
  Furthermore, we find a lower bound on the time required to generate or degrade a certain amount of entanglement by arbitrary quantum dynamics. We demonstrate the tightness of our speed limits on entanglement by considering quantum processes of practical interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.07415v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.052420</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.A 110 (2024) 5, 052420</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vivek Pandey, Swapnil Bhowmick, Brij Mohan,  Sohail, Ujjwal Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generally covariant geometric momentum and geometric potential for a Dirac fermion on a two-dimensional hypersurface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15982v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Geometric momentum is the appropriate momentum for a particle constrained to move on a curved surface, which depends on the extrinsic curvature and leads to observable effects, and curvature-induced quantum potentials appear for a nonrelativistic free particle on the surface. In the context of multi-component quantum states, the geometric momentum should be rewritten as a generally covariant geometric momentum, which contains an additional term defined as the gauge potential. For a Dirac fermion constrained on a two-dimensional hypersurface, we derive the generally covariant geometric momentum, and demonstrate that no curvature-induced geometric potentials arise on a pseudosphere or a helical surface. The dynamical quantization conditions are verified to be effective in dealing with constrained systems on hypersurfaces, enabling the derivation of both the generally convariant geometric momentum and the geometric potential for a spin particle constrained on parametrically defined surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15982v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/ae08f5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Scr. 100, 105301 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Z. Li, L. Q. Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mining higher-order triadic interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14997v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Complex systems often involve higher-order interactions which require us to go beyond their description in terms of pairwise networks. Triadic interactions are a fundamental type of higher-order interaction that occurs when one node regulates the interaction between two other nodes. Triadic interactions are found in a large variety of biological systems, from neuron-glia interactions to gene-regulation and ecosystems. However, triadic interactions have so far been mostly neglected. In this article, we propose {the Triadic Perceptron Model (TPM)} that demonstrates that triadic interactions can modulate the mutual information between the dynamical state of two linked nodes. Leveraging this result, we formulate the Triadic Interaction Mining (TRIM) algorithm to extract triadic interactions from node metadata, and we apply this framework to gene expression data, finding new candidates for triadic interactions relevant for Acute Myeloid Leukemia. Our work reveals important aspects of higher-order triadic interactions that are often ignored, yet can transform our understanding of complex systems and be applied to a large variety of systems ranging from biology to climate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14997v4</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marta Niedostatek, Anthony Baptista, Jun Yamamoto, Jurgen Kurths, Ruben Sanchez Garcia, Ben MacArthur, Ginestra Bianconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-uniqueness of phase transitions for graphical representations of the Ising model on tree-like graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22061v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the graphical representations of the Ising model on tree-like graphs. We construct a class of graphs on which the loop $\mathrm{O}(1)$ model and the single random current exhibit a non-unique phase transition with respect to the inverse temperature, highlighting the non-monotonicity of both models. It follows from the construction that there exist infinite graphs $\mathbb{G}\subseteq \mathbb{G}'$ such that the uniform even subgraph of $\mathbb{G}'$ percolates and the uniform even subgraph of $\mathbb{G}$ does not. We also show that on the wired $d$-regular tree, the phase transitions of the loop $\mathrm{O}(1)$, the single random current, and the random-cluster models are all unique and coincide.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22061v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ALEA, Lat. Am. J. Probab. Math. Stat. 22, 889-904, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ulrik Thinggaard Hansen, Frederik Ravn Klausen, Peter Wildemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of blowup solutions for Liouville systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07467v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the following Liouville system defined on a flat torus \begin{equation} \left\{ \begin{array}{lr} -\Delta u_i=\sum_{j=1}^n a_{ij}\rho_j\Big(\frac{h_j e^{u_j}}{\int_\Omega h_j e^{u_j}}-1\Big),\nonumber u_j\in H_{per}^1(\Omega)\mbox{ for }i\in I=\{1,\cdots,n\}\nonumber, \end{array} \right. \end{equation} where $h_j\in C^3(\Omega)$, $h_j&gt;0$, $\rho_j&gt;0$ and $u=(u_1,..,u_n)$ is doubly periodic on $\partial\Omega$. The matrix $A=(a_{ij})_{n\times n}$ satisfies certain properties. One central problem about Liouville systems is whether multi-bubble solutions do exist. In this work we present a comprehensive construction of multi-bubble solutions in the most general setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07467v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zetao Cheng, Haoyu Li, Lei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skew Pl\"ucker Relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08293v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Schur functions satisfy the relative Pl\"ucker relations which describe the projective embedding of the flag varieties and the Hirota bilinear equations for the modified KP hierarchies. These relative Pl\"ucker relations are generalized to the skew Schur functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08293v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3842/SIGMA.2025.080</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIGMA 21 (2025), 080, 19 pages</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kazuya Aokage, Eriko Shinkawa, Hiro-Fumi Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elias' Encoding from Lagrangians and Renormalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23447v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present paper we give a derivation of Elias' Omega code from physics principles by combining a constrained variational formulation of prefix coding with a renormalization flow on codeword distributions.
  Starting from a Lagrangian that minimizes average codelength under the Kraft-McMillan constraint, we show that the implied distribution is a fixed point of a coarse-graining map, yielding the canonical iterated log-sum length, asymptotically up to an additive constant.
  This establishes completeness and asymptotic optimality, and connects universal integer coding with coarse-grained entropy, uncertainty-type bounds, and entropy relations familiar from statistical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23447v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kolpakov, Aidan Rocke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a 5D UV completion of Argyres-Douglas theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05610v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss a novel UV completion of a class of Argyres-Douglas (AD) theories in the $\Omega$-background by its embedding into the renormalisation group flow from five dimensional $\mathcal{N}=1$ superconformal field theories (SCFT) on $S^1$. This is obtained via analysing these theories in the light of ($q$-)Painlev\'e/gauge theory correspondence, which allows to compute the five dimensional BPS partition functions as an expansion in the Wilson loop vev with integer $q$-polynomials coefficients. These are derived formulating the gauge theory on a blown-up geometry and using a five-dimensional lift of (topological) operator/state correspondence. We discuss in detail the phase diagram of the four dimensional limits, pinpointing the special AD loci. Explicit computations are reported for $\tilde E_1$ SCFT and its limit to H$_0=(A_1,A_2)$ AD theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05610v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Bonelli, Pavlo Gavrylenko, Ideal Majtara, Alessandro Tanzini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Asymptotic Analysis of Some PDE and Steklov Eigenvalue Problems with Partially Reactive Patches in 3-D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.17394v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider steady-state diffusion in a three-dimensional bounded domain with a smooth reflecting boundary that is partially covered by small partially reactive patches. By using the method of matched asymptotic expansions, we investigate the competition of these patches for a diffusing particle and the crucial role of surface reactions on these targets. After a brief overview of former contributions to this field, we first illustrate our approach by considering the classical problems of the mean first-reaction time (MFRT) and the splitting probability for partially reactive patches characterized by a Robin boundary condition. For a spherical domain, we derive a three-term asymptotic expansion for the MFRT and splitting probabilities in the small-patch limit. This expansion is valid for arbitrary reactivities, and also accounts for the effect of the spatial configuration of patches on the boundary. Secondly, we consider more intricate surface reactions modeled by mixed Steklov-Neumann or Steklov-Neumann-Dirichlet problems. We provide the first derivation of the asymptotic behavior of the eigenvalues and eigenfunctions for these spectral problems in the small-patch limit for a spherical domain. Extensions of these asymptotic results to arbitrary domains and their physical applications are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.17394v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis S. Grebenkov, Michael J. Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual Symmetries and Algebraic Structures in the Kerr-Schild Double Copy I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24112v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Kerr-Schild double copy is celebrated for producing exact gravitational spacetimes from gauge fields, yet the preservation of symmetry content gone largely unexplored. We investigate the fate of residual symmetries in the Kerr-Schild double copy, focusing on the Schwarzschild solution. On the gauge theory side, we derive the residual transformations that preserve the Abelian and non-Abelian Kerr-Schild ansatz\"e, finding they both form an infinite-dimensional Lie algebra parameterized by arbitrary null functions. On the gravity side, we analyze the resulting residual diffeomorphisms of the Kerr-Schild Schwarzschild metric. Restricting our focus to the Killing vector class of solutions, we find that the only surviving diffeomorphisms are the finite-dimensional global isometries of Schwarzschild, reducing the residual gauge algebra to the Poincar\'e subalgebra containing exclusively time translations and spatial rotations. This finding confirms a fundamental structural mismatch: the infinite-dimensional algebra of the gauge side admits no analogous structure in this gravitational sector. We formalize this by showing that the BRST operator for the residual symmetry is trivialized under the Killing condition, establishing the consistency of this algebraic reduction within a quantum field theoretic framework. This paper is the first of a two-part series. In Part II, we complete this analysis by examining the more complex proper conformal Killing vector class of solutions and formulating a unified BRST framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24112v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brandon Holton</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
