<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 04:01:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Coarsely separation of groups and spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by a classical theorem of topological dimension theory, we prove that every geodesic metric space of asymptotic dimension $n$ containing a bi-infinite geodesic can be coarsely separated by a subset $S$ of asymptotic dimension equal to or smaller than $n-1$.\\ We define asymptotic Cantor manifolds, and we prove that every finitely generated group contains such a manifold. We also state some questions related to them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15892v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panagiotis Tselekidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crossed modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is an overview of the idea of a crossed module. For a group, the triple that consists of the group, its group of automorphisms, and the canonical homomorphism from the group to its group of automorphisms constitutes a crossed module. Crossed modules arise from the identities among the relations of the presentation of a group, from the extension problem for groups and, more generally, in low dimensional topology. Also, the (successful) attempt to extend the idea of a normal extension of commutative fields to the realm of non-commutative algebras leads to crossed modules. Crossed modules appear implicitly in a forgotten paper by A. Turing which in principle settles the extension problem for groups. Crossed modules make perfect sense for Lie algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15900v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1090/noti2831</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Notices Amer. Math. Soc. 70 (2023), 1802-1813</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Huebschmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Dehn functions for family of polycyclic groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this note, we initiate the concept of Dehn functions for a family of finite groups. We investigate the Dehn function for some specific families of finite polycyclic groups. We also consider related notions of spherical Dehn function and mean Dehn function for family of finite simple cyclic groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16096v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krishnendu Gongopadhyay, Lokenath Kundu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orders and Fibering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16102v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2018, Kielak gave a virtual fibering criterion for RFRS groups. In this paper, we present a simpler proof of this.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16102v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Okun, Kevin Schreve</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Le Conte de la Mesure sur les Complexes Cubiques CAT(0)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16360v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the topic of probability measures on CAT(0) cube complexes and prove that an amenable group acting on a CAT(0) cube complex, regardless of dimension, necessarily preserves an interval in the Roller compactification. In the finite dimensional case, we prove that there must be an orbit of cardinality $2^N$, where $N$ is bounded by the dimension. This is a slight extension of the author's previous Tits' Alternative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16360v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Talia Fern\'os</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On maximal subgroups of ample groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16364v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper is concerned with maximal subgroups of the ample (better known as topological full) groups of homeomorphisms of totally disconnected compact metrizable topological spaces. We describe all maximal subgroups that are stabilizers of finite sets. Under certain assumptions on the ample group (including minimality), we describe all maximal subgroups that are stabilizers of closed sets or stabilizers of partitions into clopen sets. In particular, our results apply to the ample groups associated with Cantor minimal systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16364v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rostislav Grigorchuk, Yaroslav Vorobets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted conjugacy in dihedral Artin groups I: Torus Knot groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we provide an alternative solution to a result by Juh\'{a}sz that the twisted conjugacy problem for odd dihedral Artin groups is solvable, that is, groups with presentation $G(m) = \langle a,b \; | \; _{m}(a,b) = {}_{m}(b,a) \rangle$, where $m\geq 3$ is odd, and $_{m}(a,b)$ is the word $abab \dots$ of length $m$, is solvable. Our solution provides an implementable linear time algorithm, by considering an alternative group presentation to that of a torus knot group, and working with geodesic normal forms. An application of this result is that the conjugacy problem is solvable in extensions of odd dihedral Artin groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16671v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gemma Crowe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of primitive elements under group actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate group actions in which certain primitive elements fix a point, while not all group elements possess this property when acting upon some space. Using similar dynamical tools, we introduce the notion of Nielsen girth and prove the existence of groups with infinite girth but having finite Nielsen girth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16769v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pratyush Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hausdorff dimension of the generalized Brunner-Sidki-Vieira Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the Hausdorff dimension of the closure of the generalized Brunner-Sidki-Vieira group acting on the $m$-adic tree for $m\ge 2$, providing the first examples of self-similar topologically finitely generated closed subgroups of transcendental Hausdorff dimension in the group of $m$-adic automorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16876v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Fari\~na-Asategui, Mikel E. Garciarena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On quasi-homomorphism rigidity for lattices in simple algebraic groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16500v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Property $(TTT)$ was introduced by Ozawa as a strengthening of Kazhdan's property $(T)$ and Burger and Monod's property $(TT)$. In this paper, we improve Ozawa's result by showing that any simple algebraic group of rank $\geq 2$ over a local field has property $(TTT)$. We also show that lattices in a second countable locally compact group inherits property $(TTT)$. Finally, we study to what extent Lie groups with infinite center fail to have properties $(TT)$ and $(TTT)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16500v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Dumas (UCBL, ICJ, EDPA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locally-primitive block designs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16822v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A locally-primitive design is a block design $(\mathcal{P},\mathcal{B})$ which admits an automorphism group $G$ with primitive local actions. It is proved that $G$ is primitive on the points $\mathcal{P}$, and either $G$ is an almost simple group, or $G$ acting on $\mathcal{P}$ is an affine group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16822v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianfu Chen, Peice Hua, Cai Heng Li, Yanni Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thompson's group $F$, tangles, and link homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend a construction of Jones to associate $(n, n)$-tangles with elements of Thompson's group $F$ and prove that it is asymptotically faithful as $n \to\infty$. Using this construction we show that the oriented Thompson group $\vec F$ admits a lax group action on a category of Khovanov's chain complexes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16838v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vyacheslav Krushkal, Louisa Liles, Yangxiao Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ideals of equations for elements in a free group and context-free languages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.10276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.10276v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a finitely generated free group, and let $H\le F$ be a finitely generated subgroup. An equation for an element $g\in F$ with coefficients in $H$ is an element $w(x)\in H*\langle x \rangle$ such that $w(g)=1$ in $F$; the degree of the equation is the number of occurrences of $x$ and $x^{-1}$ in the cyclic reduction of $w(x)$. Given an element $g\in F$, we consider the ideal $\mathfrak{I}_g\subseteq H*\langle x \rangle$ of equations for $g$ with coefficients in $H$; we study the structure of $\mathfrak{I}_g$ using context-free languages.
  We describe a new algorithm that determines whether $\mathfrak{I}_g$ is trivial or not; the algorithm runs in polynomial time. We also describe a polynomial-time algorithm that, given $d\in\mathbb{N}$, decides whether or not the subset $\mathfrak{I}_{g,d}\subseteq\mathfrak{I}_g$ of all degree-$d$ equations is empty. We provide a polynomial-time algorithm that computes the minimum degree $d_{\min}$ of a non-trivial equation in $\mathfrak{I}_g$. We provide a sharp upper bound on $d_{\min}$. Finally, we study the growth of the number of (cyclically reduced) equations in $\mathfrak{I}_g$ and in $\mathfrak{I}_{g,d}$ as a function of their length. We prove that this growth is either polynomial or exponential, and we provide a polynomial-time algorithm that computes the type of growth (including the degree of the growth if it's polynomial).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.10276v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Ascari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotypic equivalence of Abelian p-groups with separable reduced parts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that two elementarily equivalent Abelian p-groups with separable reduced parts are isotypically equivalent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11261v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Bunina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the stable cohomology of the IA-automorphism groups of free groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.13458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.13458v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Borel's stability and vanishing theorem gives the stable cohomology of $\mathrm{GL}(n,\mathbb{Z})$ with coefficients in algebraic $\mathrm{GL}(n,\mathbb{Z})$-representations. By combining the Borel theorem with the Hochschild-Serre spectral sequence, we compute the twisted first cohomology of the automorphism group $\mathrm{Aut}(F_n)$ of the free group $F_n$ of rank $n$. We also study the stable rational cohomology of the IA-automorphism group $\mathrm{IA}_n$ of $F_n$. We propose a conjectural algebraic structure of the stable rational cohomology of $\mathrm{IA}_n$, and consider some relations to known results and conjectures. We also consider a conjectural structure of the stable rational cohomology of the Torelli groups of surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.13458v5</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuo Habiro, Mai Katada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On 3-generated axial algebras of Jordan type half</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10680v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axial algebras of Jordan type $\eta$ are a special type of commutative non-associative algebras. They are generated by idempotents whose adjoint operators have the minimal polynomial dividing $(x-1)x(x-\eta)$, where $\eta$ is a fixed value that is not equal to $0$ or $1$. These algebras have restrictive multiplication rules that generalize the Peirce decomposition for idempotents in Jordan algebras.
  A universal $3$-generated algebra of Jordan type $\frac{1}{2}$ as an algebra with $4$ parameters was constructed by I. Gorshkov and A. Staroletov. Depending on the value of the parameter, the universal algebra may contain a non-trivial form radical. In this paper, we describe all semisimple $3$-generated algebras of Jordan type $\frac{1}{2}$ over a quadratically closed field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10680v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravil Bildanov, Ilya Gorshkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
