<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 05:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the $\mathbb{A}^1$-invariance of $\mathrm{K}_2$ of Chevalley groups of simply-laced type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study the $\mathbb{A}^1$-invariance of the unstable functor $\mathrm{K}_2(\Phi, R)$ in the case when $\Phi$ is an irreducible root system of type $\mathsf{ADE}$ containing $\mathsf{A}_4$ and not of type $\mathsf{E}_8$. We show that in the geometric case, i. e. when $R$ is a regular ring containing a field $k$ one has $\mathrm{K}_2(\Phi, R[t]) = \mathrm{K}_2(\Phi, R)$, which allows one to interpret the unstable $\mathrm{K}_2$ groups as $\mathbb{A}^1$-fundamental groups of Chevalley--Demazure group schemes in the $\mathbb{A}^1$-homotopy category. We also prove a variant of "early stability" theorem which allows one to find a generating set of $\mathrm{K}_2(\Phi, A[X_1, \ldots X_n])$ in the case when $A$ is a Dedekind domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06944v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Sinchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Completeness Condition for Dirichlet-Selberg domains in the symmetric space $SL(n,\mathbb{R})/SO(n,\mathbb{R})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a geometric algorithm related to the $SL(n,\mathbb{R})$-action on the symmetric space $SL(n,\mathbb{R})/SO(n)$. As a required condition of Poincar\'e's Fundamental Polyhedron Theorem, a step of the algorithm checks whether a certain constructed manifold is complete. We prove that such completeness condition is always satisfied in specific cases, analogous to a known result in hyperbolic spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06987v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukun Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elasticity of free type III actions of free groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07047v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that measure-class-preserving non-amenable treeable equivalence relations of type III, meaning not preserving any equivalent $\sigma$-finite measure, are induced by free actions of non-abelian free groups of any given number of generators, including infinitely generated free groups, with the additional property that no ends of the induced Schreier graph are vanishing. This is done using a characterization of type III due to Hopf for transformations and Dang-Ngoc-Nghiem in general. This highlights the difference between the type III setting and the measure-preserving setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07047v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Poulin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual Finiteness of $A_{2,3,2n}$ Triangle Artin Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07063v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that triangle Artin groups of the type $A_{2,3,2n}$ are residually finite for all $n\geq4$. This requires splitting these triangle Artin groups as graphs of groups and then proving that each of these graphs of groups has finite stature with respect to its vertex groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07063v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Greyson Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Krull-Schmidt Theorem for small profinite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that every small profinite group can be decomposed into a direct product of indecomposable profinite groups, and that such a decomposition is unique up to order and isomorphisms of the components. We also investigate the cancellation property of some free pro-$\mathcal{C}$ groups, and give a new criterion for a profinite group to be small.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07699v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamar Bar-On, Nikolay Nikolov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exotic aspherical 4-manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19400v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct closed, aspherical, smooth 4-manifolds that are homeomorphic but not diffeomorphic. These provide counterexamples to a smooth analog of the Borel conjecture in dimension four. Our technique is to apply the `reflection group trick' of the first author to pairs of exotic 4-manifolds with boundary constructed by the second author and Piccirillo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19400v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Davis, Kyle Hayden, Jingyin Huang, Daniel Ruberman, Nathan Sunukjian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebra, group, and Hopf Rota-Baxter operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07158v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We know definition of Rota--Baxter operators on different algebraic systems. For examples, on groups, on algebras, on Hopf algebras. On some algebraic systems it is possible to define different types of Rota--Baxter operators. For example, on group algebra it is possible to define Rota--Baxter operator as on associative algebra, group Rota--Baxter operator and Rota--Baxter operator as on a Hopf algebra. We are investigating the following question: What are connections between these operators? We are studying these questions for the Sweedler algebra $H_4$, that is 4-dimension non--cocommutative Hopf algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07158v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeriy G. Bardakov, Igor M. Nikonov, Viktor N. Zhelaybin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic $2-$valued group structures on $\mathbb P^1$, Kontsevich-type polynomials, and multiplication formulas, I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The theory of a two-valued algebraic group structure on a complex plane and complex projective line is developed. In this theory, depending on the choice of the neutral element, the local multiplication law is given by the Buchstaber polynomial or the generalized Kontsevich polynomial. One of the most exciting results of our studies is a simple construction of a two-valued algebraic group on $\mathbb C$ different from known coset-construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07330v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Buchstaber, Ilia Gaiur, Vladimir Rubtsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit Profile for Projections of Random Walks on Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.12859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.12859v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Establishing cutoff, an abrupt transition from "not mixed" to "well mixed", is a classical topic in the theory of mixing times for Markov chains. Interest has grown recently in determining not only the existence of cutoff and the order of its mixing time and window, but the exact shape, or profile, of the convergence inside the window. Classical techniques, such as coupling or $\ell_2$-bounds, are typically too crude to establish this and there has been a push to develop general techniques.
  We build upon this work, extending from conjugacy-invariant random walks on groups to certain projections. We exemplify our method by analysing the $k$-particle interchange process on the complete $n$-graph with $k \asymp n$. This is a projection of the random-transposition card shuffle, which corresponds to $k = n$, analysed by Teyssier.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.12859v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1214/24-EJP1207</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Electron. J. Probab. 29: 1-22 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Evita Nestoridi, Sam Olesker-Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomized Geodesic Flow on Hyperbolic Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14350v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by Gromov's geodesic flow problem on hyperbolic groups $G$, we develop in this paper an analog using random walks. This leads to a notion of a harmonic analog $\Theta$ of the Bowen-Margulis-Sullivan measure on $\partial^2 G$. We provide three different but related constructions of $\Theta$: 1) by moving the base-point along a quasigeodesic ray 2) by moving the base-point along random walk trajectories 3) directly as a push-forward under the boundary map to $\partial^2 G$ of a measure inherited from studying all bi-infinite random walk trajectories (with no restriction on base-point) on $G^{\mathbb{Z}}$.
  Of these, the third construction is the most involved and needs new techniques. It relies on developing a framework where we can treat bi-infinite random walk trajectories as analogs of bi-infinite geodesics on complete simply connected negatively curved manifolds. Geodesic flow on a hyperbolic group is typically not well-defined due to non-uniqueness of geodesics. We circumvent this problem in the random walk setup by considering \emph{all} trajectories. We thus get a well-defined \emph{discrete flow} given by the $\mathbb{Z}-$shift on bi-infinite random walk trajectories. The $\mathbb{Z}-$shift is the random analog of the time one map of the geodesic flow. As an analog of ergodicity of the geodesic flow on a closed negatively curved manifold, we establish ergodicity of the $G$-action on $(\partial^2G, \Theta)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14350v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luzie Kupffer, Mahan Mj, Chiranjib Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
