<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 01:49:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A step to compute the determinant of finite semigroups not in ECom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00083v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The purpose of this paper is to begin studying the computation of the nonzero determinant of semigroups within the class of finite semigroups that possesses a pair of non-commutative idempotents. This paper focuses on a class of these semigroups introduced as $\ll$-smooth semigroups. This computation is applicable in the context of the extension of the MacWilliams theorem for codes over semigroup algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00083v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. H. Shahzamanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Groups elementarily equivalent to metabelian Baumslag$-$Solitar groups and regular bi-interpretability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that metabelian Baumslag$-$Solitar group $BS(1,k)$, $k&gt;1$, is (strongly) regularly bi-interpretable with the ring of integers $\mathbb{Z}$, and describe in algebraic terms all groups that are elementarily equivalent to $BS(1,k)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00642v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evelina Daniyarova, Alexei Myasnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pushforward measures on homogeneous spaces of non-unimodular groups and properties of modular functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper shows that a formula for the pushforward measures on the fiber bundle $ G \to G / H $ of homogeneous space of locally compact groups $ G $ and $ H $ can be written down by using the modular functions. As a result, we obtain the equality \begin{align} \frac{ \Delta_G ( h ) }{ \Delta_{ G / N } ( h N ) } = \frac{ \Delta_H ( h ) }{ \Delta_{ H / N } ( h N ) } \end{align} on the modular functions for any closed subgroups $ N $ and $ H $ of a locally compact group $ G $ with $ N \lhd G $ and $ N \subset H \subset G $ and any $ h \in H $.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00670v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Satomi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on words having same image on finite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The question of whether two words in a free group that induce the same measure on every finite group as word maps are automorphic remains open. In this work, we study words whose images as word maps on every finite group are identical. We establish that two words in $F_2$, where one of the words is $x^n$ or $[x,y]^n$ for $n \in \Z$, having same image on every finite group, are endomorphic to each other. Furthermore, we demonstrate that if the word map corresponding to a word $w_1 \in F_n$ has the same image as a test word $w_2 \in F_n$ on every finite group, then this is sufficient to ensure that $w_1$ and $w_2$ induce the same measure on every finite group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00789v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shrinit Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Profinite rigidity of affine Coxeter groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that the irreducible affine Coxeter groups are first-order rigid and deduce from this that they are profinitely rigid in the absolute sense. We then show that the first-order theory of any irreducible affine Coxeter group does not have a prime model. Finally, we prove that universal Coxeter groups of finite rank are homogeneous, and that the same applies to every hyperbolic (in the sense of Gromov) one-ended right-angled Coxeter group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01141v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Paolini, Rizos Sklinos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Around first-order rigidity of Coxeter groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By the work of Sela, for any free group $F$, the Coxeter group $W_ 3 = \mathbb{Z}/2\mathbb{Z} \ast \mathbb{Z}/2\mathbb{Z} \ast \mathbb{Z}/2\mathbb{Z}$ is elementarily equivalent to $W_3 \ast F$, and so Coxeter groups are not closed under elementary equivalence among finitely generated groups. In this paper we show that if we restrict to models which are generated by finitely many torsion elements (finitely torsion-generated), then we can recover striking rigidity results. Our main result is that if $(W, S)$ is a Coxeter system whose irreducible components are either spherical, or affine or (Gromov) hyperbolic, and $G$ is finitely torsion-generated and elementarily equivalent to $W$, then $G$ is itself a Coxeter group. This combines results of the second author et al. from [MPS22, PS23] with the following main hyperbolic result: if $W$ is a Coxeter hyperbolic group and $G$ is $\mathrm{AE}$-equivalent to $W$ and finitely torsion-generated, then $G$ belongs to a finite collection of Coxeter groups (modulo isomorphism). Furthermore, we show that there are two hyperbolic Coxeter groups $W$ and $W'$ which are non-isomorphic but $\mathrm{AE}$-equivalent. We also show that, on other hand, if we restrict to certain specific classes of Coxeter groups then we can recover the strongest possible form of first-order rigidity, which we call first-order torsion-rigidity, namely the Coxeter group $W$ is the only finitely torsion-generated model of its theory. Crucially, we show that this form of rigidity holds for the following classes of Coxeter groups: even hyperbolic Coxeter groups and free products of one-ended or finite hyperbolic Coxeter groups. We conjecture that the same kind of phenomena occur for the whole class of Coxeter groups. In this direction, we prove that if $W$ and $W'$ are even Coxeter groups which are elementarily equivalent, then they are isomorphic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01164v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Andr\'e, Gianluca Paolini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coloured shuffle compatibility, Hadamard products, and ask zeta functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01387v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We devise an explicit method for computing combinatorial formulae for Hadamard products of certain rational generating functions. The latter arise naturally when studying so-called ask zeta functions of direct sums of modules of matrices or class- and orbit-counting zeta functions of direct products of nilpotent groups. Our method relies on shuffle compatibility of coloured permutation statistics and coloured quasisymmetric functions, extending recent work of Gessel and Zhuang.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01387v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angela Carnevale, Vassilis Dionyssis Moustakas, Tobias Rossmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morse boundaries of 3-manifold groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.08368v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We classify the homeomorphism types of the Morse boundaries of all 3-manifold groups into 9 different possible homeomorphism types, and show how the Morse boundary depends on the geometric decomposition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.08368v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefanie Zbinden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Right-angled Artin groups and the cohomology basis graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05495v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be a finite graph and let $A(\Gamma)$ be the corresponding right-angled Artin group. From an arbitrary basis $\mathcal B$ of $H^1(A(\Gamma),\mathbb F)$ over an arbitrary field, we construct a natural graph $\Gamma_{\mathcal B}$ from the cup product, called the \emph{cohomology basis graph}. We show that $\Gamma_{\mathcal B}$ always contains $\Gamma$ as a subgraph. This provides an effective way to reconstruct the defining graph $\Gamma$ from the cohomology of $A(\Gamma)$, to characterize the planarity of the defining graph from the algebra of $A(\Gamma)$, and to recover many other natural graph-theoretic invariants. We also investigate the behavior of the cohomology basis graph under passage to elementary subminors, and show that it is not well-behaved under edge contraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05495v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ram\'on Flores, Delaram Kahrobaei, Thomas Koberda, Corentin Le Coz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariable generation of finite simple groups and rational homology of coset posets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.16319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that every finite simple group is generated invariably by a Sylow subgroup and a cyclic group. It follows that that the order complex of the coset poset of an arbitrary finite group has nontrivial reduced rational homology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.16319v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert M. Guralnick, John Shareshian, Russ Woodroofe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp relations between volume growth, isoperimetry and escape probability in vertex-transitive graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2001.01467v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove sharp bounds on the probability that the simple random walk on a vertex-transitive graph escapes the ball of radius $r$ before returning to its starting point. In particular, this shows that if the ball of radius $r$ has size slightly greater than quadratic in $r$ then this probability is bounded from below. On the other hand, we show that if the ball of radius $r$ has volume slightly less than cubic in $r$ then this probability decays logarithmically for all larger balls. These results represent a finitary refinement of Varopoulos's theorem that a random walk on a vertex-transitive graph is recurrent if and only if the graph has at most quadratic volume growth. They also imply the existence of a gap at $0$ for escape probabilities: there exists a universal constant $c&gt;0$ such that the random walk on an arbitrary vertex-transitive graph is either recurrent or has a probability of at least $c$ of escaping to infinity. We also prove versions of these results for finite graphs, in particular confirming and strengthening a conjecture of Benjamini and Kozma from 2002. Amongst other things, we also generalise our results to give a sharp finitary version of the characterisation of $p$-parabolic vertex-transitive graphs, prove a number of sharp isoperimetric inequalities for vertex-transitive graphs, and prove a locality result for the escape probability of the random walk on a vertex-transitive graph that can be seen as an analogue of Schramm's locality conjecture for the critical percolation probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2001.01467v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romain Tessera, Matthew Tointon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Manhattan curve, ergodic theory of topological flows and rigidity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.13451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.13451v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For every non-elementary hyperbolic group, we introduce the Manhattan curve associated to any pair of left-invariant hyperbolic metrics which are quasi-isometric to a word metric. It is convex; we show that it is continuously differentiable and moreover is a straight line if and only if the corresponding two metrics are roughly similar, i.e., they are within bounded distance after multiplying by a positive constant. Further, we prove that the Manhattan curve associated to two strongly hyperbolic metrics is twice continuously differentiable. The proof is based on the ergodic theory of topological flows associated to general hyperbolic groups and analyzing the multifractal structure of Patterson-Sullivan measures. We exhibit some explicit examples including a hyperbolic triangle group and compute the exact value of the mean distortion for pairs of word metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.13451v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Cantrell, Ryokichi Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping class groups are quasicubical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.10681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.10681v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is proved that the mapping class group of any closed surface with finitely many marked points is quasiisometric to a CAT(0) cube complex. We provide two distinct proofs, one tailored to mapping class groups, and one applying to a larger class of groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.10681v3</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry Petyt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic models for CAT(0) spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.14127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.14127v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce two new tools for studying CAT(0) spaces: \emph{curtains}, versions of cubical hyperplanes; and the \emph{curtain model}, a counterpart of the curve graph. These tools shed new light on CAT(0) spaces, allowing us to prove a dichotomy of a rank-rigidity flavour, establish Ivanov-style rigidity theorems for isometries of the curtain model, find isometry-invariant copies of its Gromov boundary in the visual boundary of the underlying CAT(0) space, and characterise rank-one isometries both in terms of their action on the curtain model and in terms of curtains. Finally, we show that the curtain model is universal for WPD actions over all groups acting properly on the CAT(0) space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.14127v4</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry Petyt, Davide Spriano, Abdul Zalloum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inductive Freeness of Ziegler's Canonical Multiderivations for Restrictions of Reflection Arrangements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.00436v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal A$ be a free hyperplane arrangement. In 1989, Ziegler showed that the restriction $\mathcal A"$ of $\mathcal A$ to any hyperplane endowed with the natural multiplicity $\kappa$ is then a free multiarrangement. In 2024, the first two authors proved an analogue of Ziegler's theorem for the stronger notion of inductive freeness: if $\mathcal A$ is inductively free, then so is the free multiarrangement $(\mathcal A'',\kappa)$. In 2018, all reflection arrangements which admit inductively free Ziegler restrictions were classified by the first two authors. The aim of this paper is an extension of this classification to all restrictions of reflection arrangements utilizing the aforementioned fundamental result from the 2024 paper of the first two authors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.00436v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Torsten Hoge, Gerhard Roehrle, Sven Wiesner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The diameter of random Schreier graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16733v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a combinatorial proof of the following theorem. Let $G$ be any finite group acting transitively on a set of cardinality $n$. If $S \subseteq G$ is a random set of size $k$, with $k \geq (\log n)^{1+\varepsilon}$ for some $\varepsilon &gt;0$, then the diameter of the corresponding Schreier graph is $O(\log_k n)$ with high probability. Except for the implicit constant, this result is the best possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16733v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Dona, Luca Sabatini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
