<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 04:03:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Realizability of the Poisson Boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14029v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that for any countable group $ G $ equipped with a probability measure $ \mu $, there exists a randomized stopping time $ \tau $ such that $ (G, \mu _{\tau} )$ admits a strictly larger space of bounded harmonic functions than $ (G,\mu) $, unless this space is trivial for all measures on $ G $. In particular, we exhibit an irreducible probability measure on the free group $F_2$ such that the Poisson boundary is strictly larger than the geometric boundary equipped with the hitting measure, resolving a longstanding open problem. As another consequence, there is never a nontrivial universal topological realization of the Poisson boundary for any countable group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14029v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunal Chawla, Joshua Frisch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Universal Inverse Monoids with the $F$-Inverse Property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14047v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An inverse monoid $M$ is called $F$-inverse if each $\sigma$-class of $M$, where $\sigma$ is the minimum group congruence of $M$, has a maximum element with respect to the natural order of $M$. Upon Kinyon's observation made in 2018 that $F$-inverse monoids form a variety in the enriched signature involving an additional unary operation mapping each element of $M$ to the maximum element of its $\sigma$-class, a separate theory of $F$-inverse monoids is developing in recent years, greatly aided by a recent solution to the long-standing problem of Henckell and Rhodes on finite $F$-inverse covers of finite inverse monoids. In particular, a description of the universal object $F(G,X)$ in the class of $X$-generated $F$-inverse monoids with a prescribed maximum group image was provided recently. In this paper we introduce yet another object $M_F(G,X)$, the one that is universal for inverse monoids (so, not in the enriched signature) that are $X$-generated with maximum group image a quotient of $G$ and which happen to be $F$-inverse. We obtain presentations and geometric models based on Cayley graphs of groups for such inverse monoids. As an application, we are able to characterise all one-relator special inverse monoids $\mathrm{Inv}\langle{X}\,|\,{w=1}\rangle$ with a cyclically reduced relator word $w$ enjoying the $F$-inverse property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14047v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Dolinka, Ganna Kudryavtseva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partial Group Symmetry in Figures I: Semidirect Products and the Six Coins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct a partial group \(\mathcal{P}(F)\) that represents the "partial symmetry" inherent in a subset \(F\) of \(d\)-dimensional Euclidean space. In cases where \(F\) is not connected, \(\mathcal{P}(F)\) captures more detailed information than the conventional symmetry group \(G(F)\). To establish a stronger connection between \(\mathcal{P}(F)\) and \(F\), we introduce a novel definition of partial group action. Furthermore, to characterize \(\mathcal{P}(F)\) in specific cases, we define partial group actions on other partial groups and present a construction of the corresponding semidirect product.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14304v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Hayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rota-Baxter operators on compact simple Lie groups and algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Rota-Baxter operator on a Lie group $ G $ is a smooth map $ B : G \to G $ such that $ B(g)B(h) = B(gB(g)hB(g)^{-1}) $ for all $ g, h \in G $. This concept was introduced in 2021 by Guo, Lang and Sheng as a Lie group analogue of Rota-Baxter operators of weight 1 on Lie algebras. We show that the only Rota-Baxter operators on compact simple Lie groups are the trivial map and the inverse map. A similar description for Rota-Baxter operators of weight 1 on compact simple Lie algebras is provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14324v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saveliy V. Skresanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hermitian Cubic norm structures and groups of relative rank one</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14509v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hermitian cubic norm structures were recently introduced in order to study the class of skew-dimension one structurable algebras (which are typically only defined over fields of characteristic different from $2$ and $3$) over arbitrary rings and fields. Here, we generalize the quartic norm for these algebras and show that elements for which the quartic norm is invertible are conjugate invertible. This leads to the notion of a division hermitian cubic norm structure, defined as one in which the quartic norm is anisotropic. We classify such structures in terms of the Tits index of an associated (rank one) adjoint simple linear algebraic group and show that any adjoint linear algebraic group with such a Tits index defines a corresponding hermitian cubic norm structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14509v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michiel Smet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual fibring of Poincar\'e-duality groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that a RFRS Poincar\'e-duality group $G$ admits a virtual epimorphism to the integers whose kernel is itself a Poincar\'e-duality group over every field if and only if the $L^2$-homology of $G$ vanishes and so do the positive-characteristic variants thereof.
  Our investigations yield a more general relationship between cohomology at infinity of groups that algebraically fibre and their fibres. In particular, we show that if the fundamental group of an aspherical manifold of dimension at least three algebraically fibres, then the fibre is one ended.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14666v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam P. Fisher, Giovanni Italiano, Dawid Kielak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Geometry and Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14060v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Linear Geometry studies geometric properties which can be expressed via the notion of a line. All information about lines is encoded in a ternary relation called a line relation. A set endowed with a line relation is called a liner. So, Linear Geometry studies liners. Imposing some additional axioms on a liner, we obtain some special classes of liners: regular, projective, affine, proaffine, etc. Linear Geometry includes Affine and Projective Geometries and is a part of Incidence Geometry. The aim of this book is to present a self-contained logical development of Linear Geometry, starting with some intuitive acceptable geometric axioms and ending with algebraic structures that necessarily arise from studying the structure of geometric objects that satisfy those simple and intuitive geometric axioms. We shall meet many quite exotic algebraic structures that arise this way: magmas, loops, ternary-ring, quasi-fields, alternative rings, procorps, profields, etc. We strongly prefer (synthetic) geometric proofs and use tools of analytic geometry only when no purely geometric proof is available. Liner Geometry has been developed by many great mathematicians since times of Antiquity (Thales, Euclides, Proclus, Pappus), through Renaissance (Descartes, Desargues), Early Modernity (Playfair, Gauss, Lobachevski, Bolyai, Poncelet, Steiner, M\"obius), Late Modernity Times (Steinitz, Klein, Hilbert, Moufang, Hessenberg, Jordan, Beltrami, Fano, Gallucci, Veblen, Wedderburn, Lenz, Barlotti) till our contempories (Hartshorne, Hall, Buekenhout, Gleason, Kantor, Doyen, Hubault, Dembowski, Klingenberg, Grundh\"ofer).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14060v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taras Banakh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A group-theoretic approach to Shannon capacity of graphs and a limit theorem from lattice packings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14654v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a group-theoretic approach to the Shannon capacity problem. Using this approach we extend and recover, in a structured and unified manner, various families of previously known lower bounds on the Shannon capacity. Bohman (2003) proved that, in the limit $p\to\infty$, the Shannon capacity of cycle graphs $\Theta(C_p)$ converges to the fractional clique covering number, that is, $\lim_{p \to \infty} p/2 - \Theta(C_p) = 0$. We strengthen this result by proving that the same is true for all fraction graphs: $\lim_{p/q \to \infty} p/q - \Theta(E_{p/q}) = 0$. Here the fraction graph $E_{p/q}$ is the graph with vertex set $\mathbb{Z}/p\mathbb{Z}$ in which two distinct vertices are adjacent if and only if their distance mod $p$ is strictly less than $q$. We obtain the limit via the group-theoretic approach. In particular, the independent sets we construct in powers of fraction graphs are subgroups (and, in fact, lattices). Our approach circumvents known barriers for structured ("linear") constructions of independent sets of Calderbank-Frankl-Graham-Li-Shepp (1993) and Guruswami-Riazanov (2021).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14654v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pjotr Buys, Sven Polak, Jeroen Zuiddam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Busemann-Selberg Functions and Completeness for Dirichlet-Selberg domains in $SL(n,\mathbb{R})/SO(n,\mathbb{R})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06987v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a general completeness criterion for Dirichlet-Selberg domains in the symmetric space $SL(n,\mathbb{R})/SO(n)$. By introducing and analyzing Busemann-Selberg functions - which extend classical Busemann functions and capture asymptotic behavior toward the Satake boundary - we show that every gluing manifold or orbifold produced by Dirichlet-Selberg domain is complete. This result parallels the well-known hyperbolic case and ensures that the key completeness condition in Poincar\'e's Algorithm always holds in specific cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06987v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukun Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compactifications of pseudofinite and pseudo-amenable groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08440v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We first give simplified and corrected accounts of some results in \cite{PiRCP} on compactifications of pseudofinite groups. For instance, we use a classical theorem of Turing \cite{Turing} to give a simplified proof that any definable compactification of a pseudofinite group has an abelian connected component. We then discuss the relationship between Turing's work, the Jordan-Schur Theorem, and a (relatively) more recent result of Kazhdan \cite{Kazh} on approximate homomorphisms, and we use this to widen our scope from finite groups to amenable groups. In particular, we develop a suitable continuous logic framework for dealing with definable homomorphisms from pseudo-amenable groups to compact Lie groups. Together with the stabilizer theorems of \cite{HruAG,MOS}, we obtain a uniform (but non-quantitative) analogue of Bogolyubov's Lemma for sets of positive measure in discrete amenable groups. We conclude with brief remarks on the case of amenable topological groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08440v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Conant, Ehud Hrushovski, Anand Pillay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bieri-Neumann-Strebel sets of quasi-projective groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06250v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a smooth complex quasi-projective variety and $\Gamma=\pi_1(X)$. Let $\chi \colon \Gamma \to \mathbb{R}$ be an additive character. We prove that the ray $[\chi]$ does not belong to the BNS set $\Sigma(\Gamma)$ if and only if it comes as a pullback along an algebraic fibration $f \colon X \to \mathcal{C}$ over a quasi-projective hyperbolic orbicurve $\mathcal{C}$. We also prove that if $\pi_1(X)$ admits a solvable quotient which is not virtually nilpotent, there exists a finite \'etale cover $X_1 \to X$ and a fibration $f \colon X_1 \to \mathcal{C}$ over a quasi-projective hyperbolic orbicurve $\mathcal{C}$. Both of these results were proved by Delzant in the case when $X$ is a compact K\"ahler manifold. We deduce that $\Gamma$ is virtually solvable if and only if it is virtually nilpotent, generalising the theorems of Delzant and Arapura-Nori. As a byproduct, we prove a version of Simpson's Lefschetz Theorem for the integral leaves of logarithmic $1$-forms that do not extend to any partial compactification. We give two applications of our results. First, we strengthen the recent theorem of Cadorel-Deng-Yamanoi on virtual nilpotency of fundamental groups of quasi-projective $h$-special and weakly special manifolds. Second, we prove the sharpness of Suciu's tropical bound for the fundamental groups of smooth quasi-projective varieties and answer a question of Suciu on the topology of hyperplane arrangements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06250v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasily Rogov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable functions and F{\o}lner's Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13766v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that if $G$ is an amenable group and $A\subseteq G$ has positive upper Banach density, then there is an identity neighborhood $B$ in the Bohr topology on $G$ that is almost contained in $AA^{-1}$ in the sense that $B\backslash AA^{-1}$ has upper Banach density $0$. This generalizes the abelian case (due to F{\o}lner) and the countable case (due to Beiglb\"{o}ck, Bergelson, and Fish). The proof is indirectly based on local stable group theory in continuous logic. The main ingredients are Grothendieck's double-limit characterization of relatively weakly compact sets in spaces of continuous functions, along with results of Ellis and Nerurkar on the topological dynamics of weakly almost periodic flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13766v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Conant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Periodic colorings and orientations in infinite graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01951v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the existence of periodic colorings and orientations in locally finite graphs. A coloring or orientation of a graph $G$ is periodic if the resulting colored or oriented graph is quasi-transitive, meaning that $V(G)$ has finitely many orbits under the action of the group of automorphisms of $G$ preserving the coloring or the orientation. When such a periodic coloring or orientation of $G$ exists, $G$ itself must be quasi-transitive and it is natural to investigate when quasi-transitive graphs have such periodic colorings or orientations. We provide examples of Cayley graphs with no periodic orientation or non-trivial coloring, and examples of quasi-transitive graphs of treewidth 2 without periodic orientation or proper coloring. On the other hand we show that every quasi-transitive graph $G$ of bounded pathwidth has a periodic proper coloring with $\chi(G)$ colors and a periodic orientation. We relate these problems with techniques and questions from symbolic dynamics and distributed computing and conclude with a number of open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01951v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tara Abrishami, Louis Esperet, Ugo Giocanti, Matthias Hamann, Paul Knappe, R\"ognvaldur G. M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commensurability Among Deligne-Mostow Monodromy Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09682v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper gives the commensurability classification of Deligne--Mostow ball quotients and shows that the 104 Deligne--Mostow lattices form 38 commensurability classes. First, we find commensurability relations among Deligne--Mostow monodromy groups, which are not necessarily discrete. This generalizes previous work by Sauter and Deligne--Mostow in dimension two. In this part, we consider certain projective surfaces with two fibrations over the projective line, which induce two sets of Deligne--Mostow data. Correspondences between moduli spaces provide a geometric realization of commensurability relations. Secondly, we obtain commensurability invariants from conformal classes of Hermitian forms and toroidal boundary divisors. This completes the commensurability classification of Deligne--Mostow lattices and provides an alternative approach to the results of Kappes--M{\"o}ller and McMullen on non-arithmetic Deligne--Mostow lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09682v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenglong Yu, Zhiwei Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generalized character related to the local structure and representation theory of a finite group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03976v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the generalized character $\Psi_{1,p,G}$ of a finite group $G$ which vanishes on all $p$-singular elements of $G$ and whose value at each $p$-regular $y \in G$ is the number of $p$-elements of $C_{G}(y)$. We conjecture that this is always a character, and may be afforded by a projective $RG$-module, where $R$ is an appropriate complete discrete valuation ring whose residue field has characteristic $p$. We examine a number of case where this is the case, and consider consequences for the representation theory and character theory of $G$ when this conjecture is known to hold. In particular, we prove, among other things, that the conjecture is valid for all primes $p$ in the case that $G \cong {\rm PSL}(2,q)$ or ${\rm SL}(2,q)$ for every prime power $q$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03976v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geoffrey R. Robinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting totally real units and eigenvalue patterns in $\rm{SL}_n(\mathbb Z)$ and $\rm{Sp}_{2n}(\mathbb Z)$ in thin tubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13288v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For a vector $v=(v_1,\dots ,v_n)$ with $v_1&gt;\cdots&gt;v_n$ and $\sum v_i=0$, we study the "directional entropy" of two arithmetic objects: (1) the logarithmic embeddings of degree-$n$ totally real units, and (2) the logarithmic eigenvalue data of $\operatorname{SL}_n(\mathbb Z)$. In each case, the entropy in the direction of $v$ is $\mathsf E_n(v)= \rho_{\operatorname{SL}_n}(v)=\sum_{i=1}^{n-1}(n-i)\,v_i,$ the value of the half-sum of positive roots of $\operatorname{SL}_n(\mathbb R)$ evaluated at $v$. More precisely, the number of objects lying in a thin tube around the ray $\mathbb R_+v$ and of norm at most $T$ grows on the order of $ \exp\!\bigl(\rho_{\operatorname{SL}_n}(v)\,T\bigr)$ as $T\to \infty$.
  Because each eigenvalue data determines an $\operatorname{SL}_n(\mathbb R)$-conjugacy class, this implies a lower bound of order $\exp\!\bigl(\rho_{\operatorname{SL}_n}(v)T\bigr)$ for the number of $\operatorname{SL}_n(\mathbb Z)$-conjugacy classes with a prescribed eigenvalue data; we also obtain an upper bound of order $\exp\!\bigl(2\rho_{\operatorname{SL}_n}(v)T\bigr)$.
  A parallel argument for the symplectic lattice $\operatorname{Sp}_{2n}(\mathbb Z)$, taken in the symmetric direction $v=(v_1,\dots ,v_n,-v_n,\dots ,-v_1),\quad v_1&gt;\cdots&gt;v_n&gt;0,$ shows that $\mathsf E_{2n}^{\operatorname{Sp}}(v)=\rho_{\operatorname{Sp}_{2n}}(v)=\sum_{i=1}^n(n+1-i)v_i,$ the half-sum of positive roots of $\operatorname{Sp}_{2n}(\mathbb R)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13288v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hee Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strict comparison for twisted group C*-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18569v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that any reduced twisted group C*-algebra of a selfless group with the rapid decay property is selfless. As an application, we show that twisted group C*-algebras of acylindrically hyperbolic groups (possibly with nontrivial finite radical) and rapid decay are pure, and hence have strict comparison.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18569v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sven Raum, Hannes Thiel, Eduard Vilalta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two axes in non-commutative algebras with a Frobenius form</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11303v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Throughout this paper $A$ is a commutative non-associative algebra over a field $\mathbb{F}$ of characteristic not $2.$ In addition $A$ posses a Frobenius form. We obtain detailed information about the multiplication in $A$ given two axes of type half in $A.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11303v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoav Segev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
