<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 01:53:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous cochains on Furstenberg boundaries and injectivity of the comparison map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05333v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Monod proved that any continuous cohomology of a semisimple Lie group $G$ can be represented by a measurable cocycle on the associated Furstenberg boundary, which we upgraded to an alternating cocycle. In the current paper we improve that result by showing that we can actually take a representing cocycle which is continuous on an explicit subset of generic tuples. We give an analogous result in the case of bounded cohomology. Finally, we exploit this characterization to prove the injectivity of the comparison map in degree $3$ for $\mathrm{Isom}^\circ(\mathbb{H}_{\mathbb{C}}^n)$, when $n \geq 2$, and in degree $4$ for $\mathrm{Isom}^\circ(\mathbb{H}^n_{\mathbb{R}})$, when $n \geq 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05333v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michelle Bucher, Alessio Savini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metric criteria for fixed price of countable groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish general criteria for a countable group $\Gamma$ to have fixed price 1 depending on a choice of left-invariant proper metric on $\Gamma$. We apply this criterion to show that if $\Gamma_1,\Gamma_2$ are two countable groups satisfying a certain growth condition then $\Gamma_1\times \Gamma_2$ has fixed price 1. For example, $\Gamma\times \Gamma$ has fixed price 1 for any countable group $\Gamma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05459v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erin Bevilacqua, Lewis Bowen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary actions of CAT(0) spaces: topological freeness and applications to $C^*$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05669v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study topological dynamics on the visual boundary and several combinatorial boundaries associated to $\operatorname{CAT}(0)$ spaces. Through verifying the freeness of Myrberg points on the boundaries, we prove that a large class of these boundary actions are topologically free strong boundary actions. These include certain visual boundary actions obtained from proper isometric actions of groups on proper $\operatorname{CAT}(0)$ spaces with rank-one elements, horofunction boundary actions from actions of irreducible finitely generated infinite non-affine Coxeter groups on the Caylay graphs, and Roller-type boundary actions from certain group actions on irreducible $\operatorname{CAT}(0)$ cube complexes. This in particular leads to a new proof of Kar-Sageev's topological freeness result for Roller boundary actions of $\operatorname{CAT}(0)$ cube complexes and generalizes Klisee's topological freeness result on horofunction boundaries from hyperbolic and right angled Coxeter groups to the general case. As applications to $C^*$-algebras, our work yields new examples of $C^*$-selfless groups and of exact, purely infinite, simple reduced crossed product $C^\ast$-algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05669v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Ma, Daxun Wang, Wenyuan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exposure Orders in Free Group Algebras: Minimal Schreier Transversals, Free Bases, and Gr\"obner Bases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider the free group algebra $K\left[F\right]$, where $F$ is a free group and $K$ a field. A well-order $\prec$ on $F$ is called an exposure order if words are greater than their proper prefixes. We show that every one-sided ideal $I$ in $K\left[F\right]$ admits a Schreier transversal, a basis, and a Gr\"obner basis -- each minimal in a natural sense with respect to $\prec$. When $I$ is finitely generated and $\prec$ is computable, we provide an algorithm for computing these minimal structures from a finite generating set. This extends the foundational works of Lewin and Rosenmann, which relied on the shortlex order, to both a broader class of orders on $F$ and to infinitely generated ideals, while retaining algorithmic capabilities for such orders in case $I$ is finitely generated.
  General exposure orders lack a form of compatibility with products which we call suffix-invariance, that shortlex enjoys, and which prior Gr\"obner basis constructions in $K\left[F\right]$ relied on. In its absence, reductions may strictly increase the support of elements, requiring nontrivial conceptual adaptations to definitions and algorithms. These adaptations clarify the notion of minimality underlying prior constructions and demonstrate that algorithmic Gr\"obner theory in $K\left[F\right]$ does not fundamentally require suffix-invariance, although its presence -- as in shortlex -- results in a simpler theory.
  Our framework further illuminates the flexibility of exposure orders: with a suitable choice of $\prec$, any Schreier transversal for $I$ can be realized as minimal, and any basis for $I$ arising from the constructions of Lewin or Rosenmann can likewise be realized as its minimal basis, unifying both approaches under a single framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05906v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matan Seidel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphically Equivalent Elements of Finite Abelian Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a finite abelian group $G$ and elements $x, y \in G$, we prove that there exists $\phi \in \text{Aut}(G)$ such that $\phi(x) = y$ if and only if $G/\langle x \rangle \cong G/\langle y \rangle$. This result leads to our development of the two fastest known algorithms to determine if two elements of a finite abelian group are automorphic images of one another. The second algorithm also computes $G/\langle x \rangle$ in a near-linear time algorithm for groups, most feasible when the group has exponent at most $10^{20}$. We conculde with an algorithm that computes the automorphic orbits of finite abelian groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06013v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Agarwal, Rachel Chen, Rohan Garg, Jared Kettinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Conjugacy Problem for ascending HNN-extensions of free groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.04357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.04357v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give an algorithm to solve the Conjugacy Problem for ascending HNN-extensions of free groups. To do this, we give algorithms to solve certain problems on dynamics of free group endomorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.04357v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan D. Logan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identities of triangular Boolean matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16113v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a combinatorial characterization of the identities holding in the semiring of all upper triangular Boolean $n\times n$-matrices and apply the characterization to computational complexity of identity checking, finite axiomatizability of equational theories, and algebraic descriptions of certain classes of recognizable languages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16113v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail V. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homology and K-theory for self-similar actions of groups and groupoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02359v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nekrashevych associated to each self-similar group action an ample groupoid and a $\mathrm{C}^\ast$-algebra. We perform complete computations of the homology of the groupoid and the K-theory of the $\mathrm{C}^\ast$-algebra for a myriad of examples, including the Grigorchuk group, the Grigorchuk--Erschler group, Gupta--Sidki groups, and self-similar actions of free abelian groups and lamplighter groups. The key development is the construction, for arbitrary self-similar group actions, of long exact sequences which compute the homology and K-theory in terms of the homology of the group and K-theory of the group $\mathrm{C}^\ast$-algebra via the transfer map and the virtual endomorphism. Results are proved more generally for self-similar groupoids. As a consequence of our results and recent results of X.~Li, we are able to show that R\"over's simple group containing the Grigorchuk group and Thompson's group $V$ is rationally acyclic but has nontrivial Schur multiplier. We prove many more R\"over--Nekrashevych groups of self-similar groups are rationally acyclic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02359v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alistair Miller, Benjamin Steinberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Description of the structure of DG--algebras via characters on a groupoid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21784v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a description of graded derivations in group algebras. Using this result for arbitrary graduation of the group algebra, we describe all possible structures of DG algebras. The corresponding examples are given. The description is given in terms of characters on a groupoid analogous to the groupoid of inner action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21784v5</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.46298/cm.15775</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Andronick Arutyunov, Oleg Muravev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
