<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 04:00:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A marking graph for finite-type Artin groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Clean markings on surfaces were a key component in Masur and Minsky's hierarchy machinery, which proved to be a powerful tool in the study of mapping class groups. We construct a marking graph for irreducible finite-type Artin groups which is quasi-isometric to the group modulo its center, i.e., an element of $A_{\Gamma}/Z(A_{\Gamma})$ is determined up to finite error by its action on one of our markings. To construct this graph, we construct suitable collections of transverse parabolic subgroups which extend the maximal simplices of the complex of irreducible parabolic subgroups to analogues of clean markings, and we define natural analogues of elementary moves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10394v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaitlin Ragosta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-orientable regular hypermaps of arbitrary hyperbolic type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10434v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the consequences of residual finiteness of triangle groups is that for any given hyperbolic triple $(\ell,m,n)$ there exist infinitely many regular hypermaps of type $(\ell,m,n)$ on compact orientable surfaces. The same conclusion also follows from a classification of those finite quotients of hyperbolic triangle groups that are isomorphic to linear fractional groups over finite fields. A non-orientable analogue of this, that is, existence of regular hypermaps of a given hyperbolic type on {\em non-orientable} compact surfaces, appears to have been proved only for {\em maps}, which arise when one of the parameters $\ell,m,n$ is equal to $2$.
  In this paper we establish a non-orientable version of the above statement in full generality by proving the following much stronger assertion: for every hyperbolic triple $(\ell,m,n)$ there exists an infinite set of primes $p$ of positive Dirichlet density, such that (i) there exists a regular hypermap $\mathcal{H}$ of type $(\ell,m,n)$ on a compact non-orientable surface such that the automorphism group of $\mathcal{H}$ is isomorphic to $\PSL(2,p)$, and, moreover, (ii) the carrier compact surface of {\em every} regular hypermap of type $(\ell,m,n)$ with rotation group isomorphic to $\PSL(2,p)$ is necessarily non-orientable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10434v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gareth A. Jones, Martin Ma\v{c}aj, Jozef \v{S}ir\'a\v{n}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Product Of Exponentials (POE) Splines on Lie-Groups: Limitations, Extensions, and Application to SO(3) and SE(3)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10513v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Existing methods for constructing splines and Bezier curves on a Lie group G involve repeated products of exponentials deduced from local geodesics, w.r.t. a Riemannian metric, or rely on general polynomials. Moreover, each of these local curves is supposed to start at the identity of $G$. Both assumptions may not reflect the actual curve to be interpolated. This paper pursues a different approach to construct splines on $G$. Local curves are expressed as solutions of the Poisson equation on G. Therewith, the local interpolations satisfies the boundary conditions while respecting the geometry of $G$. A $k$th-order approximation of the solutions gives rise to a $k$th-order product of exponential (POE) spline. Algorithms for constructing 3rd- and 4th-order splines are derived from closed form expressions for the approximate solutions. Additionally, spline algorithms are introduced that allow prescribing a vector field the curve must follow at the interpolation points. It is shown that the established algorithms, where $k$th-order POE-splines are constructed by concatenating local curves starting at the identity, cannot exactly reconstruct a $k$th-order motion. To tackle this issue, the formulations are extended by allowing for local curves between arbitrary points, rather than curves emanating from the identity. This gives rise to a global $k$th-order spline with arbitrary initial conditions. Several examples are presented, in particular the shape reconstruction of slender rods modeled as geometrically non-linear Cosserat rods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10513v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/nme.70088</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Mueller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Gelfand Pairs of the Dihedral and Dicyclic Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A strong Gelfand pair $(G, H)$ is a finite group $G$ and a subgroup $H$ where every irreducible character of $H$ induces to a multiplicity-free character of $G$. We determine the strong Gelfand pairs of the dihedral groups $D_{2n}$ and the dicyclic groups $Dic_{4n}$ for all $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10756v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph E. Marrow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Degenerate Whittaker space for some induced representations of ${\rm GL}_4(\mathfrak{o}_2)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10796v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathfrak{o}_l$ be a finite principal ideal local ring of length $l$. The degenerate Whittaker space associated with a representation of ${\rm GL}_{2n}(\mathfrak{o}_l)$ is a representation of ${\rm GL}_n(\mathfrak{o}_l)$. For strongly cuspidal representations of ${\rm GL}_{2n}(\mathfrak{o}_l)$ the structure of degenerate Whittaker space is described by Prasad's conjecture, which has been proven for ${\rm GL}_4(\mathfrak{o}_2)$. In this paper, we describe the degenerate Whittaker space for certain induced representations of ${\rm GL}_4(\mathfrak{o}_2)$, specifically those induced from subgroups analogous to the maximal parabolic subgroups of ${\rm GL}_4(\mathbb{F}_q)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10796v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankita Parashar, Shiv Prakash Patel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An integral formula for Lie groups, and the Mathieu conjecture reduced to Abelian non-Lie conjectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11622v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an explicit integration formula for the Haar integral on a compact connected Lie group. This formula relies on a known decomposition of a compact connected simple Lie group into symplectic leaves, when one views the group as a Poisson Lie group. In this setting the Haar integral is constructed using the Kostant harmonic volume form on the corresponding flag manifold, and explicit coordinates are known for these invariant differential forms. The formula obtained is related to one found by Reshetikhin-Yakimov.
  Using our integration formula, we reduce the Mathieu conjecture to two stronger conjectures about Laurent polynomials in several complex variables with polynomial coefficients in several real variable polynomials. In these stronger conjectures there is no reference to Lie group theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11622v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael M\"uger, Lars Tuset</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly chiral rational homology spheres with hyperbolic fundamental groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05604v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For each $m\geq0$ and any prime $p\equiv3\ \mathrm{(mod \ 4)}$, we construct strongly chiral rational homology $(4m+3)$-spheres, which have real hyperbolic fundamental groups and only non-zero integral intermediate homology groups isomorphic to $\mathbb{Z}_{2p}$ in degrees $1,2m+1$ and $4m+1$. This gives group theoretic analogues in high dimensions of the existence of strongly chiral hyperbolic rational homology $3$-spheres, as well as of the existence of strongly chiral hyperbolic manifolds of any dimension that are not rational homology spheres, which was shown by Weinberger. One of our tools will be $r$-spins. We thus investigate the relationship between the sets of degrees of self-maps of a given manifold and its $r$-spins, and give classes of manifolds for which the sets are equal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05604v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoforos Neofytidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correction to: An algebraic model for finite loop spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07292v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We correct here two errors in our earlier paper "An algebraic model for finite loop spaces" [arXiv:1212.2033]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07292v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carles Broto, Ran Levi, Bob Oliver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Dedekind Skew Braces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23550v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Skew braces play a central role in the theory of set-theoretic non-degenerate solutions of the Yang--Baxter equation, since their algebraic properties significantly affect the behaviour of the corresponding solutions (see for example [Ballester-Bolinches et al., Adv. Math. 455 (2024), 109880]). Recently, the study of nilpotency-like conditions for the solutions of the Yang--Baxter equation has drawn attention to skew braces of abelian type in which every substructure is an ideal (so-called, Dedekind skew braces); see for example [Ballester-Bolinches et al., Result Math. 80 (2025), Article Number 21].
  The aim of this paper is not only to show that the hypothesis the skew brace is of abelian type can be neglected in essentially all the known results in this context, but also to extend this theory to skew braces whose additive or multiplicative groups are locally cyclic (and more in general of finite rank).
  Our main results -- which are in fact much more general than stated here -- are as follows:
  (1) Every finite Dedekind skew brace is centrally nilpotent.
  (2) Every hypermultipermutational Dedekind skew brace with torsion-free additive group is trivial.
  (3) Characterization of a skew brace whose additive or multiplicative group is locally cyclic
  (4) If a set-theoretic non-degenerate solution of the Yang--Baxter equation has a Dedekind structure skew brace and fixes the diagonal elements, then such a solution must be the twist solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23550v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Caranti, I. Del Corso, M. Di Matteo, M. Ferrara, M. Trombetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dilations of non-Markovian dynamical systems on graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07511v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To generalise evolution families we consider systems of contractions $\{\varphi(u, v)\}_{(u, v) \in E}$ defined on the edges of a graph $\mathcal{G} = (\Omega, E)$. In this setup the Markov property, or \emph{divisibility}, can be modelled via $\varphi(u, v)\varphi(v, w) = \varphi(u, w)$ for edges $(u, v), (v, w), (u, w) \in E$. We obtain results in three settings: 1) contractive Banach space operators; 2) positive unital maps on $C^{\ast}$-algebras; and 3) CPTP-maps on trace class operators on a Hilbert space. In the discrete setting we are able to dilate possibly indivisible families of contractions to divisible families of operators with 'nice' properties (viz. surjective isometries resp. $C^{\ast}$-algebraic automorphisms resp. unitary representations). In the special case of linearly ordered graphs equipped with the order topology, we establish sufficient conditions for strongly continuous dilations of possibly indivisible families in the Banach space and $C^{\ast}$-algebra contexts. To achieve these results we work with string-rewriting systems, and make use of and extend dilation theorems of Stroescu [43], Kraus [23, 24], and vom Ende--Dirr [49].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07511v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raj Dahya</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
