<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 01:48:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Limits over orbit categories of locally finite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We correct an error in the paper [BLO3], and take the opportunity to examine in more detail the derived functors of inverse limits over orbit categories of (infinite) locally finite groups. The main results show how to reduce this in many cases to limits over orbit categories of finite groups, but we also look at generalizations of the Lyndon-Hochschild-Serre spectral sequence for higher limits over orbit categories for an extension of locally finite groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02488v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bob Oliver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing the Zariski closure of a finitely generated rational matrix group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe an algorithm for determining the algebraic subgroup of GL(n,C)
  that is defined as the closure of the group generated by a finite number of
  elements of GL(n,C). The algorithm avoids the use of Groebner bases
  and can therefore be used on non-trivial examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02577v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Willem A. de Graaf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential map of germs of vector fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce an exponential map of the algebra of germs of vector fields into the group of germs of diffeomorphisms at zero. It is shown that this mapping is not a bijection. A brief review of the key results of the analytic iteration problem is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02117v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Kaptsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph and wreath products of cellular automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.10186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.10186v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the set of subgroups of the automorphism group of a two-sided full shift is closed under countable graph products. We introduce the notion of a group action without $A$-cancellation (for an abelian group $A$), and show that when $A$ is a finite abelian group and $G$ is a group of cellular automata whose action does not have $A$-cancellation, the wreath product $A \wr G$ embeds in the automorphism group of a full shift. We show that all free abelian groups and free groups admit such cellular automata actions. In the one-sided case, we prove variants of these results with reasonable alphabet blow-ups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.10186v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ville Salo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marked length spectrum rigidity in groups with contracting elements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10165v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a study of the well-known marked length spectrum rigidity problem in the coarse-geometric setting. For any two (possibly non-proper) group actions $G\curvearrowright X_1$ and $G\curvearrowright X_2$ with contracting property, we prove that if the two actions have the same marked length spectrum, then the orbit map $Go_1\to Go_2$ must be a rough isometry. In the special case of cusp-uniform actions, the rough isometry can be extended to the entire space. This generalizes the existing results in hyperbolic groups and relatively hyperbolic groups. In addition, we prove a finer marked length spectrum rigidity from confined subgroups and further, geometrically dense subgroups. Our proof is based on the Extension Lemma and uses purely elementary metric geometry. This study produces new results and recovers existing ones for many more interesting groups through a unified and elementary approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10165v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1112/jlms.70146</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. London Math. Soc. 111 (2025), no.4, e70146</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Renxing Wan, Xiaoyu Xu, Wenyuan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the singularities of the exponential function of a semidirect product</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15053v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the Fr\'echet--Lie groups of the form $C^{\infty}(M)\rtimes \mathbb{R}$ resulting from smooth flows on compact manifolds $M$ fail to be locally exponential in several cases: when at least one non-periodic orbit is locally closed, or when the flow restricts to a linear one on an orbit closure diffeomorphic to a torus. As an application, we prove that the Bondi--Metzner--Sachs group of symmetries of an asymptotically flat spacetime is not locally exponential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15053v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandru Chirvasitu, Rafael Dahmen, Karl-Hermann Neeb, Alexander Schmeding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure of an exotic $2$-local subgroup in $E_7(q)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20281v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be the finite simple group of Lie type $G = E_7(q)$, where $q$ is an odd prime power. Then $G$ is an index $2$ subgroup of the adjoint group $G_{\operatorname{ad}}$, which is also denoted by $G_{\operatorname{ad}} = \operatorname{Inndiag}(G)$ and known as the group of inner-diagonal automorphisms. It was proven by Cohen--Liebeck--Saxl--Seitz (1992) that there is an elementary abelian $2$-subgroup $E$ of order $4$ in $G_{\operatorname{ad}}$, such that $N_{G_{\operatorname{ad}}}(E)/C_{G_{ad}}(E) \cong \operatorname{Sym}_3$, and $C_{G_{\operatorname{ad}}}(E) = E \times \operatorname{Inndiag}(D_4(q))$. Furthermore, such an $E$ is unique up to conjugacy in $G_{\operatorname{ad}}$.
  It is known that $N_G(E)$ is always a maximal subgroup of $G$, and $N_{G_{\operatorname{ad}}}(E)$ is a maximal subgroup of $G_{\operatorname{ad}}$ unless $N_{G_{\operatorname{ad}}}(E) \leq G$. In this note, we describe the structure of $N_{G}(E)$. It turns out that $N_G(E) = N_{G_{\operatorname{ad}}}(E)$ if and only if $q \equiv \pm 1 \mod{8}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20281v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikko Korhonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abstract 3D-rotation groups and recognition of icosahedral modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12411v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce an abstract notion of a 3D-rotation module for a group $G$ that does not require the module to carry a vector space structure, a priori nor a posteriori. We prove that, under an expected irreducibility-like assumption, the only finite $G$ with such a module are those already known from the classical setting: $\operatorname{Alt}(4)$, $\operatorname{Sym}(4)$, and $\operatorname{Alt}(5)$. Our main result then studies the module structure when $G = \operatorname{Alt}(5)$ and shows that, under certain natural restrictions, it is fully determined and generalizes that of the classical icosahedral module.
  We include an application to the recently introduced setting of modules with an additive dimension, a general setting allowing for simultaneous treatment of classical representation theory of finite groups as well as representations within various well-behaved model-theoretic settings such as the $o$-minimal and finite Morley rank ones. Leveraging our recognition result for icosahedral modules, we classify the faithful $\operatorname{Alt}(5)$-modules with additive dimension that are dim-connected of dimension $3$ and without $2$-torsion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12411v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lauren McEnerney, Joshua Wiscons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Normalizer-Solubilizer Conjecture_V2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11486v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a finite group and $x$ be an element of $G$. Define $\textrm{Sol}_G(x)$ as the set of all $y\in G$ such that $\langle x, y\rangle$ is soluble. We provide an equivalent condition for the normalizer-solubilizer conjecture, namely $|\mathcal{N}_G(\langle x\rangle)| \mid |\textrm{Sol}_G(x)|$. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the conjecture holds in the special case where $\mathcal{N}_G(\langle x \rangle)$, the normalizer of $\langle x \rangle$, is a Frobenius group with kernel $\mathcal{C}_G(x)$, the centralizer of $x$. Finally, we will classify all finite simple groups $G$ that contain an element $x$ for which $\textrm{Sol}_G(x)$ is a maximal subgroup of order $pq$, where $p$ and $q$ are prime numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11486v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamid Mousavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representation Independent Decompositions of Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04660v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Constructing complex computation from simpler building blocks is a defining problem of computer science. In algebraic automata theory, we represent computing devices as semigroups. Accordingly, we use mathematical tools like products and homomorphisms to understand computation through hierarchical decompositions. To address the shortcomings of some of the existing decomposition methods, we generalize semigroup representations to semigroupoids by introducing types. On the abstraction level of category theory, we describe a flexible, iterative and representation independent algorithm. Moving from the specific state transition model to the abstract composition of arrows unifies seemingly different decomposition methods and clarifies the three algorithmic stages: collapse, copy and compress. We collapse some dynamics through a morphism to the top level; copy the forgotten details into the bottom level; and finally we apply compression there. The hierarchical connections are solely for locating the repeating patterns in the compression. These theoretical findings pave the way for more precise computer algebra tools and allow for understanding computation with other algebraic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04660v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Attila Egri-Nagy, Chrystopher L. Nehaniv</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded displacement permutations on tree-like spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21496v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is shown that if a metric space exhibits certain finiteness and tree-like properties, then elements of its group of bounded displacement which are infinitely divisible are also torsion. This extends a result of N. M. Suchkov, A. A. Shlepkin, and D. A. Taysnyov.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21496v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel M. Corson</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
