<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On $A$-Groups with the Same Index Set as a Nilpotent Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15250v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a finite group and $N(G)$ be the set of conjugacy class sizes of $G$. For a prime $p$, let $|G||_p$ be the highest $p$-power dividing some element of $N(G)$. and define $|G|| = {\Pi}_{p\in {\pi}(G)}|G||_p$. $G$ is said to be an $A$-group if all its Sylow subgroups are abelian. We prove that if $G$ is an $A$-group such that $N(G)$ contains $|G||_p$ for every $p\in {\pi}(G)$ as well as $|G||$, then $G$ must be abelian. This result gives a positive answer to a question posed by Camina and Camina in 2006.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15250v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Zhou, Ilya Gorshkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conjugate reversibility in complex special linear groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15336v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce and study conjugate reversibility (or $c$-reversibility) in the complex special linear group $\SL(n,\C)$ where an element is conjugate to the inverse of its complex conjugate. We prove that in $\SL(n, \C)$, every $c$-reversible element is strongly $c$-reversible. We provide a complete classification of $c$-reversible elements based on their conjugacy invariants. This leads to an algebraic characterization of projective transformations. As a special case, a finer classification in $\SL(4, \C)$ is obtained in terms of trace conditions and resultant computations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15336v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krishnendu Gongopadhyay, Rahul Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Profinite rigidity of crystallographic groups arising from Lie theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that every finite direct product of crystallographic groups arising from an irreducible root system (in the sense of Lie theory) is profinitely rigid (equiv. first-order rigid). This is a generalization of recent proofs of profinite rigidity of affine Coxeter groups [1, 7, 22]. Our proof uses model theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15494v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Carolillo, Gianluca Paolini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreducible representations of simple Lie algebras with maximum weight multiplicity 2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14940v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We determine the irreducible representations of simple Lie algebras with maximum weight multiplicity 2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14940v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Zalesski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing infinite torsion subgroups of the circle through arithmetic-type sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15257v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a recent work [Das et al., Bull. Sci. Math. 199 (2025), 103580], the structure of characterized subgroups corresponding to arithmetic-type sequences was investigated. Building upon this work, we further show that a characterized subgroup associated with an arithmetic-type sequence is countable if and only if it is torsion. Further we prove that any infinite torsion subgroup of the circle can be characterized by an arithmetic-type sequence with bounded ratio. Moreover, our findings demonstrate that the dichotomy observed in Eggleston's theorem [Theorem 16, Eggleston, Proc. Lond. Math. Soc. 54(2) (1952), 42--93] for arithmetic sequences does not extend, in general, to the broader class of arithmetic-type sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15257v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayan Ghosh, Pratulananda Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On homomorphic images of ultraproducts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09228v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this short note we answer some questions of Bergman regarding homomorphic images of (ultra)products of groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09228v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel M. Corson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dense and empty BNSR-invariants of the McCool groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18826v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An automorphism of the free group $F_n$ is called pure symmetric if it sends each generator to a conjugate of itself. The group $\mathrm{PSAut}_n$ of all pure symmetric automorphisms, and its quotient $\mathrm{PSOut}_n$ by the group of inner automorphisms, are called the McCool groups. In this paper we prove that every BNSR-invariant $\Sigma^m$ of a McCool group is either dense or empty in the character sphere, and we characterize precisely when each situation occurs. Our techniques involve understanding higher generation properties of abelian subgroups of McCool groups, coming from the McCullough-Miller space. We also investigate further properties of the second invariant $\Sigma^2$ for McCool groups, using a general criterion due to Meinert for a character to lie in $\Sigma^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18826v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Ershov, Matthew C. B. Zaremsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistically characterized subgroups related to some non-arithmetic sequence of integers II (a quest for countable subgroups)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13626v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Following the work of [Dikranjan et al., Fund. Math. 249:185-209, 2020] for arithmetic sequences, very recently in [Das et al., Expo. Math. 43(3):125653, 2025], statistically characterized subgroups have been investigated for certain types of non-arithmetic sequences. Building on this work, we investigate further and demonstrate that, for a particular class of non-arithmetic sequences, the statistically characterized subgroup coincides with the corresponding characterized subgroup. In this context it should be kept in mind that statistical convergence (convergence w.r. to the ideal of natural density zero sets) encompasses much more sequences than usual convergence (convergence w.r. to the ideal of finite sets) and it had already been shown that statistically characterized subgroups corresponding to arithmetic sequences can not be characterized by any sequence [Das et al., Bull. Sci. Math. 179(2):103157, 2022] and they are always of the size of the continuum. From the very beginning it has been an open question as to whether statistically characterized subgroups can be small in size i.e. countably infinite. Our observation thus sheds new light on the crucial role of sequences generating subgroups of the circle group and at the same time one can subsequently identify a class of sequences for which statistically characterized subgroups are countably infinite. This result provides a negative solution to Problem 2.16 posed in [Das et al., Expo. Math. 43(3):125653, 2025] and Question 6.3 from [Dikranjan et al., Fund. Math. 249:185-209, 2020]. Additionally, our findings resolve several open problems from [Dikranjan et al., Topo. Appl., 2025].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13626v2</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pratulananda Das, Ayan Ghosh, Tamim Aziz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two axes in non-commutative algebras with a Frobenius form</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11303v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Throughout this paper $A$ is a commutative non-associative algebra over a field $\mathbb{F}$ of characteristic not $2.$ In addition $A$ posses a Frobenius form. We obtain detailed information about the multiplication in $A$ given two axes of type half in $A.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11303v4</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoav Segev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
