<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 04:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly bounded generation in transformation groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Word metrics on finitely generated groups have canonical quasi-isometry classes, making quasi-isometry invariants genuine group invariants. Rosendal generalized this phenomenon to topological groups through CB-generation, but in the general topological setting the resulting quasi-isometry invariants are not invariants of the underlying abstract group. Specializing to the discrete case yields what we call SB-generated groups, where the invariants are genuinely algebraic. We show that SB-generation arises naturally in transformation groups by identifying several broad families of examples: the identity component of homeomorphism groups of closed manifolds, certain big mapping class groups, and homeomorphism groups of compact well-ordered spaces with successor limit capacity. These results demonstrate that SB-generation provides a robust extension of finite generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07541v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas G. Vlamis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adjoining universal inverses to families of elements of free monoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $&lt;X&gt;$ be the free monoid on a generating set $X$, and suppose one adjoins to $&lt;X&gt;$ universal 2-sided inverses to a finite set $S$ of its elements. We note an elementary algorithm which yields a normal form for elements of the resulting monoid $M$.
  We then show that if $S$ is allowed to be infinite, a similar normal form exists, though it cannot necessarily be computed algorithmically.
  We raise a couple of questions.
  We note work by others on the related topic of monoids presented by finite families of relations of the form $w = 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07617v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George M. Bergman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic Hecke algebras in the infinite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aiming for a revival of the theory of crystallographic complex reflection groups, we compute (minimal) Coxeter-like reflection presentations for the infinite families of those non-genuine groups which satisfy Steinberg's fixed point theorem. These new presentations behave \`{a} la Coxeter, encoding many of the group's properties at a glance, and their signature feature -- named the $x$-relation -- is fully understood in terms of configuration spaces. Crucially, the presentations further achieve the braid theorem, allowing to deform into the generic Hecke algebra. In particular, we revisit the affine GDAHA family in deformation terms of the most general class of Steinberg crystallographic complex reflection groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08209v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Dal Martello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite groups of non-prime-power order with exactly four character codegrees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08221v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For an irreducible complex character \(\chi\) of a finite group \(G\), the \emph{codegree} of \(\chi\) is defined as the ratio \(|G : \ker(\chi)| / \chi(1)\), where \(\ker(\chi)\) represents the kernel of \(\chi\). In this paper, we provide a detailed characterization of finite groups of non-prime power order that have exactly four irreducible character co-degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08221v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zeng, Mehdi Ghaffarzadeh, Mohsen Ghasemi, Dongfang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the $IC$-$\Pi$-property of subgroups of finite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $ H $ be a subgroup of a finite group $ G $. We say that $ H $ satisfies the $ \Pi $-property in $ G $ if $ | G/K : N_{G/K}((H \cap L)K/K)| $ is a $ \pi(( H \cap L)K/K ) $-number for any chief factor $ L/K $ of $ G $; and we call that $ H $ satisfies the $ IC $-$ \Pi $-property in $ G $ if $ H\cap [H, G] $ satisfies the $ \Pi $-property in $ G $. In this paper, we obtain a criterion of a normal subgroup being contained in the $ p\mathfrak{U} $-hypercenter of a finite group by the $IC$-$ \Pi $-property of some $ p $-subgroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08426v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengtian Qiu, Shouhong Qiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Parallel Wall Theorem for CAT(0) even 2-complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the Parallel Wall Theorem for CAT(0) 2-complexes constructed by regular polygons with an even number of sides. This result extends a combination of the works of Janzen and Wise and Hruska and Wise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07448v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carl Kristof-Tessier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper Bounds on the Chromatic Index of Linear Hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07494v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We address the problem of finding upper bounds on the chromatic index $q(V,E)$ of linear (and loopless) hypergraphs. The first bound we find is defined through a color-preserving group on a proper and minimally edge-colored linear hypergraph, whose orbits serve as a finer partition to the hypergraph's coloring, thereby yielding an upper bound on $q(V,E)$. The next set of theorems in this paper relates to combinatorial properties of hypergraph coloring. Our results suggest a plausible approach to solving the Berge-F\"{u}redi conjecture, providing an upper bound on the chromatic index that directly relates $q(V,E)$ and $\Delta([(V,E)]_{2}) + 1$. Furthermore, we provide three sufficient conditions for the conjecture to hold within this framework, when involving the Helly property for hypergraphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07494v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Murff, Xerxes D. Arsiwalla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conjectural Positivity for Pontryagin Product in Equivariant K-theory of Loop Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07689v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a connected simply-connected simple algebraic group over $\mathbb{C}$ and let $T$ be a maximal torus, $B\supset T$ a Borel subgroup and $K$ a maximal compact subgroup. Then, the product in the (algebraic) based loop group $\Omega(K)$ gives rise to a comultiplication in the topological $T$-equivariant $K$-ring $K_T^{top}(\Omega(K))$. Recall that $\Omega(K)$ is identified with the affine Grassmannian $\mathcal{X}$ (of $G$) and hence we get a comultiplication in $ K_T^{top}(\mathcal{X})$. Dualizing, one gets the Pontryagin product in the $T$-equivariant $K$-homology $K^T_0(\mathcal{X})$, which in-turn gets identified with the convolution product (due to S. Kato). Now, $ K_T^{top}(\mathcal{X})$ has a basis $\{\xi^w\}$ over the representation ring $R(T)$ given by the ideal sheaves corresponding to the finite codimension Schubert varieties $X^w$ in $\mathcal{X}$. We make a positivity conjecture on the comultiplication structure constants in the above basis. Using some results of Kato, this conjecture gives rise to an equivalent conjecture on the positivity of the multiplicative structure constants in $T$-equivariant quantum $K$-theory $QK_T(G/B)$ in the Schubert basis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07689v1</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shrawan Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreducible restrictions of spin representations of symmetric and alternating groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08223v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb{F}$ be an algebraically closed field and $G$ be an almost quasi-simple group. An important problem in representation theory is to classify the subgroups $H&lt;G$ and $\mathbb{F} G$-modules $L$ such that the restriction $L\downarrow_H$ is irreducible. This problem is a natural part of the program of describing maximal subgroups in finite classical groups. In this paper we investigate the case of the problem where $G$ is the Schur's double cover of alternating or symmetric group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08223v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kleshchev, Lucia Morotti, Pham Huu Tiep</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Splittings of One-Ended Groups with One-Ended Halfspaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06218v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of halfspaces associated to a group splitting, and investigate the relationship between the coarse geometry of the halfspaces and the coarse geometry of the group. Roughly speaking, the halfspaces of a group splitting are subgraphs of the Cayley graph obtained by pulling back the halfspaces of the Bass--Serre tree. Our first theorem shows that (under mild conditions) any splitting of a one-ended group can be upgraded to a splitting where all the halfspaces are one-ended. Our second theorem demonstrates that a one-ended group usually has a JSJ splitting where all the halfspaces are one-ended. And our third theorem states that if a one-ended finitely presented group $G$ admits a splitting such that some edge stabilizer has more than one end, but the halfspaces associated to the edge stabilizer are one-ended, then $H^2(G,\mathbb ZG)\ne \{0\}$; in particular $G$ is not simply connected at infinity and $G$ is not an $n$-dimensional duality group for $n\geq3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06218v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Mihalik, Sam Shepherd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Word Measures on Wreath Products II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.11316v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Every word $w$ in $F_r$, the free group of rank $r$, induces a probability measure (the $w$-measure) on every finite group $G$, by substitution of random $G$-elements in the letters. This measure is determined by its Fourier coefficients: the $w$-expectations $E_w[\chi]$ of the irreducible characters of $G$. For every finite group $G$, every stable character $\chi$ of $G\wr S_n$ (trace of a finitely generated $FI_G$-module), and every word $w\in F_r$, we approximate $E_w[\chi]$ up to an error term of $O(n^{-\pi(w)})$, where $\pi(w)$ is the primitivity rank of $w$. This generalizes previous works by Puder, Hanany, Magee and the author. As an application we show that random Schreier graphs of representation-stable actions of $G\wr S_n$ are close-to-optimal expanders. The paper reveals a surprising relation between stable representation theory of wreath products and not-necessarily connected Stallings core graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.11316v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yotam Shomroni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abelianization of $\text{SL}_2$ over Dedekind domains of arithmetic type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12638v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We determine the exact group structure of the abelianization of $\text{SL}_2(A)$, where $A$ is a Dedekind domain of arithmetic type with infinitely many units. In particular, our results show that $\text{SL}_2(A)^\text{ab}$ is finite, with exponent dividing $12$ when $\text{char}(A)=0$, and dividing $6$ when $\text{char}(A)&gt;0$. As illustrative cases, we compute $\text{SL}_2(A)^\text{ab}$ explicitly for instances where $A$ is the ring of integers of a real quadratic field or a cyclotomic extension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12638v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Behrooz Mirzaii, Bruno R. Ramos, Thiago Verissimo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a question by Roggenkamp about group algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21316v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate whether the group algebra of a finite group over a localisation of the integers is semiperfect. The main result is a necessary and sufficient arithmetic criterion in the ordinary case. In the modular case, we propose a conjecture, which extends the criterion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21316v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Johnston, Dmitriy Rumynin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On RoCK blocks of double covers of symmetric and alternating groups and the refined Brou\'e conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02147v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, Kleshchev and Livesey proved the existence of RoCK $p$-blocks for double covers of symmetric and alternating groups over large enough coefficient rings. They proved that RoCK blocks of double covers are Morita equivalent to standard ``local" blocks via bimodules with endopermutation source. Based on this, Kleshchev and Livesey proved that these RoCK blocks are splendidly Rickard equivalent to their Brauer correspondents. The analogous result for blocks of symmetric groups, a theorem of Chuang and Kessar, was an important step in Chuang and Rouquier ultimately proving Brou\'e's abelian defect group conjecture for symmetric groups. In this paper we show that the Morita and splendid Rickard equivalences constructed by Kleshchev and Livesey descend to the ring $\mathbb{Z}_p$ of $p$-adic integers, hence prove Kessar and Linckelmann's refinement of Brou\'e's abelian defect group conjecture for these RoCK blocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02147v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yucong Du, Xin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
