<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 05:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Class of Non-Contracting Branch Groups with Non-Torsion Rigid Kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we provide the first example of an infinite family of branch groups in the class of non-contracting self-similar groups. We show that these groups are very strongly fractal, not regular branch, and of exponential growth. Further, we prove that these groups do not have the congruence subgroup property by explicitly calculating the structure of their rigid kernels. This class of groups is also the first example of branch groups with non-torsion rigid kernels. As a consequence of these results, we also determine the Hausdorff dimension of these groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04112v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sagar Saha, K. V. Krishna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Jewett-Krieger theorem for amenable groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Up to now there has been no proof in the literature of the often quoted fact that the Jewett-Krieger theorem is valid for all countable amenable groups. In this brief note I will close this gap by applying a recent result of B. Frej and D. Huczek [FH].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04445v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Weiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite non-parabolic subgroups of relatively hyperbolic groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04469v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a group that is relatively hyperbolic with respect to a collection of subgroups $\{H_{\lambda}\}_{\lambda\in \Lambda}$. Suppose that $G$ is given by a finite relative presentation $\mathcal{P}$ with respect to this collection. We give an upper bound on the orders of finite non-parabolic subgroups of $G$ in terms of some fundamental constants associated with $\mathcal{P}$. This upper bound is computable if $G$ is finitely generated and the word problem in each $H_{\lambda}$, $\lambda\in \Lambda$, is decidable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04469v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Bogopolski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indices of non-supersolvable maximal subgroups in finite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two classic results, due to K. Doerk and P. Hall respectively, establish the solvability of those finite groups all of whose maximal subgroups are supersolvable, and the solvability of finite groups in which all maximal subgroups have prime or squared prime index. In this note we describe the structure of the non-solvable finite groups whose maximal subgroups are either supersolvable or have prime or squared prime index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04537v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Beltr\'an, Changguo Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of some one-generator nilpotent braces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article provides a detailed description of some nilpotent left braces generated by one element.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04567v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martyn R. Dixon, Leonid A. Kurdachenko, Igor Ya. Subbotin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartite $q$-Kneser graphs and two-generated irreducible linear groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05529v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $V:=(\mathbb{F}_q)^d$ be a $d$-dimensional vector space over the field $\mathbb{F}_q$ of order $q$. Fix positive integers $e_1,e_2$ satisfying $e_1+e_2=d$. Motivated by analysing a fundamental algorithm in computational group theory for recognising classical groups, we consider a certain quantity $P(e_1,e_2)$ which arises in both graph theory and group representation theory: $P(e_1,e_2)$ is the proportion of $3$-walks in the `bipartite $q$-Kneser graph' $\Gamma_{e_1,e_2}$ that are closed $3$-arcs. We prove that, for a group $G$ satisfying ${\rm SL}_d(q)\leqslant G\leqslant{\rm GL}_d(q)$, the proportion of certain element-pairs in $G$ called `$(e_1,e_2)$-stingray duos' which generate an irreducible subgroup is also equal to $P(e_1,e_2)$. We give an exact formula for $P(e_1,e_2)$, and prove that $1-q^{-1}-q^{-2}&lt; P(e_1,e_2)&lt; 1-q^{-1}-q^{-2}+2q^{-3}-2q^{-5}$ for $2\leqslant e_2\leqslant e_1$ and $q\geqslant2$.These bounds have implications for the complexity analysis of the state-of-the-art algorithms to recognise classical groups, which we discuss in the final section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05529v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. P. Glasby, Alice C. Niemeyer, Cheryl E. Praeger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Nilpotency of Locally Pro-p Contraction Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15085v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: H. Gl\"ockner and G. A. Willis have recently shown that locally pro-p contraction groups are nilpotent. The proof hinges on a fixed-point result: if the local field $\mathbb{F}_{p}(\!(t)\!)$ acts on its $d$-th power $\mathbb{F}_{p}(\!(t)\!)^{d}$ additively, continuously, and in an appropriately equivariant manner, then the action has a non-zero fixed point. We provide a short proof of this theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15085v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alonso Beaumont</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sheaves of modules on atomic sites and discrete representations of topological groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.13600v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The main goal of this paper is to establish close relations among sheaves of modules on atomic sites, representations of categories, and discrete representations of topological groups. We characterize sheaves of modules on atomic sites as saturated representations, which are precisely representations right perpendicular to torsion representations in the sense of Geigle and Lenzing. Consequently, the category of sheaves is equivalent to the Serre quotient of the category of presheaves by the category of torsion presheaves. We also interpret the sheaf cohomology functors as derived functors of the torsion functor and for some special cases as the local cohomology functors. These results as well as a classical theorem of Artin provides us a new approach to study discrete representations of topological groups. In particular, by importing established facts in representation stability theory, we explicitly classify simple or indecomposable injective discrete representations of some topological groups such as the infinite symmetric group, the infinite general or special linear group over a finite field, and the automorphism group of the linearly ordered set $\mathbb{Q}$. We also show that discrete representations $V$ of these topological groups satisfy a certain stability property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.13600v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenxing Di, Liping Li, Li Liang, Fei Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a Theorem by Lin and Shinder through the Lens of Median Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05197v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, Lin and Shinder constructed non-trivial homomorphisms from Cremona groups of rank &gt;2 to \mathbb{Z} using motivic techniques. In this short note we propose an alternative perspective from median geometry on their theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05197v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony Genevois, Anne Lonjou, Christian Urech</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the number of small Steiner triple systems with Veblen points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16307v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The concept of Schreier extensions of loops was introduced in the general case in [11] and, more recently, it has been explored in the context of Steiner loops in [6]. In the latter case, it gives a powerful method for constructing Steiner triple systems containing Veblen points. Counting all Steiner triple systems of order v is an open problem for v&gt;21. In this paper, we investigate the number of Steiner triple systems of order 19, 27 and 31 containing Veblen points and we present some examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16307v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.disc.2024.114294</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Discrete Math. 348, No. 1, Article ID 114294, 13 p. (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mario Galici, Giuseppe Filippone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factoriality of twisted locally compact group von Neumann algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15733v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this short note, we construct an exotic example of a locally compact group $G$ with a Borel $2$-cocycle $\omega$ such that the non-twisted group von Neumann algebra $L(G)$ is a factor, while the twisted group von Neumann algebra $L_\omega(G)$ has a diffuse center.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15733v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefaan Vaes</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
