<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:00:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Residually finite groups that do not virtually have the unique product property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a finitely generated residually finite group $G$ with the property that every finite index subgroup of $G$ contains a subgroup isomorphic to Promislow's group. Hence $G$ does not have a finite index subgroup with the unique product property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11819v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naomi Bengi, Daniel T. Wise</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The higher connectivity at infinity of mapping class groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The higher connectivity at infinity for mapping class groups of surfaces with boundary components and punctures is understood with the exceptions of the mapping class groups for the closed surfaces of genus 3 and 4. In this paper we prove a general simply connected at infinity result for finitely presented groups that implies all mapping class groups of closed surfaces of genus $\geq 3$ are simply connected at infinity. As these groups are duality groups the Proper Hurewicz Theorem implies that they are $(n-2)$-connected at infinity where $n$ is the dimension of the group. Combining this result with earlier work we give a complete list of all mapping class groups and their connectivity at infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12191v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Mihalik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>M\"obius Strip Diagram Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11591v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce M\"obius strip diagram algebras (and their monoid and categorical versions) as subalgebras of a partition-style diagram calculus in which strands may carry handles and M\"obius strip features. We identify the resulting diagram category with a linear quotient of a nonorientable two-dimensional cobordism category. Finally, we develop the associated cell theory and use it to classify the simple modules and compute dimensions in a range of cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11591v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. W. Collison, D. Tubbenhauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong convergence of random representations of free products of finite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11905v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the polynomial method of Chen--Garza-Vargas--Tropp--van Handel and Magee--Puder--van Handel for operator-norm bounds in random permutation models to the setting where torsion is present. The main new feature is that asymptotic expansion of traces naturally involves fractional powers of $N$ rather than an ordinary Laurent series. We formulate fractional-power analogues of the method's key hypotheses and prove they lead to strong convergence. We verify these analogues for free products of finite groups $\Gamma=G_1*\cdots*G_m$. Concretely, for a uniformly random $\phi_N\in{\rm hom}(\Gamma,{\rm Sym}(N))$, set $\pi_N = {\rm std} \circ \phi_N$, where ${\rm std}$ denotes the standard $(N-1)$-dimensional representation of ${\rm Sym}(N)$ (the permutation representation with the trivial subrepresentation removed). We deduce strong convergence of $\pi_N$ to the left regular representation of $\Gamma$. As applications, we obtain asymptotically sharp spectral gaps for the associated random Schreier graphs, including almost Ramanujan behavior for $C_2*C_2*C_2$ and an explicit non-Ramanujan limiting spectral radius for $C_2*C_3 \cong {\rm PSL}_2({\bf Z})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11905v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Barbieri, Urban Jezernik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Springer categories for regular centralizers in well-generated complex braid groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13022v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In his proof of the K(pi,1) conjecture for complex reflection arrangements, Bessis defined Garside categories suitable for studying braid groups of centralizers of Springer regular elements in well-generated complex reflection groups. We provide a detailed study of these categories, which we call Springer categories.
  We describe in particular the conjugacy of braided reflections of regular centralizer in terms of the Garside structure of the associated Springer category. In so doing we obtain a pure Garside theoretic proof of a theorem of Digne, Marin and Michel on the center of finite index subgroups in complex braid groups in the case of a regular centralizer in a well-generated group. We also provide a "Hurwitz-like" presentation of Springer categories. To this aim we provide additional insights on noncrossing partitions in the infinite series. Lastly, we use this "Hurwitz-like" presentation, along with a generalized Reidemeister-Schreier method we introduce for groupoids, to deduce nice presentations of the complex braid group B(G31).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13022v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Owen Garnier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genericity of sublinearly Morse directions in general metric spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18762v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we show that for a proper statistically convex-cocompact action on a proper geodesic metric space, the sublinearly Morse boundary has full Patterson-Sullivan measure in the horofunction boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18762v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yulan Qing, Wenyuan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Young Diagram Decompositions for Almost Symmetric Numerical Semigroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20688v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces new structural decompositions for almost symmetric numerical semigroups through the combinatorial lens of Young diagrams. To do that, we use the foundational correspondence between numerical sets and Young diagrams, which enables a visual and algorithmic approach to studying properties of numerical semigroups. Central to the paper, a decomposition theorem for almost symmetric numerical semigroups is proved, which reveals that such semigroups can be uniquely expressed as a combination of a numerical semigroup, its dual and an ordinary numerical semigroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20688v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00025-025-02527-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mehmet Ye\c{s}il</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of Shvartsman's conjecture on braid groups of projective complex reflection groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23561v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The purpose of this note is to prove a conjecture of Shvartsman relating a complex projective reflection group with the quotient of a suitable complex braid group by its center. Shvartsman originally proved this result in the case of real projective reflection groups, and we extend it to all complex projective reflection groups. Our study also allows us to correct a result of Brou\'e, Malle, Rouquier on projective reflection groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23561v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Owen Garnier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grothendieck rigidity and virtual retraction of higher-rank GBS groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22477v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A rank $n$ generalized Baumslag-Solitar group ($GBS_n$ group) is a group that splits as a finite graph of groups such that all vertex and edge groups are isomorphic to $\mathbb{Z}^n$. This paper investigates Grothendieck rigidity and virtual retraction properties of $GBS_n$ groups. We show that every residually finite $GBS_n$ group is Grothendieck rigid. Further, we characterize when a $GBS_n$ group satisfies property (VRC), showing that it holds precisely when the monodromy is finite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22477v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daxun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representing in Low Rank I: conjugacy, topological and homological aspects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.22052v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this series of papers, we investigate properties of a finite group which are determined by its low degree irreducible representations over a number field $F$, i.e. its representations on matrix rings $\operatorname{M}_n(D)$ with $n \leq 2$. In particular we focus on representations on $\operatorname{M}_2(D)$ where $D$ is a division algebra having an order $\mathcal{O}$ such that $\mathcal{O}$ has finitely many units, i.e. such that $\operatorname{SL}_2(\mathcal{O})$ has arithmetic rank $1$. In this first part, the focus is on two aspects.
  One aspect concerns characterisations of such representing spaces in terms of Serre's homological goodness property, small virtual cohomological dimension and higher Kleinian-type embeddings. As an application, we obtain several characterisations of the finite groups $G$ whose irreducible representations are of the mentioned form. In particular, such groups $G$ are precisely those such that $\mathcal{U}(R G)$, with $R$ the ring of integers of $F$, can be constructed from groups which virtually map onto a non-abelian free group. Along the way we investigate the latter property for congruence subgroups of higher modular groups and its implications for the congruence kernel. This is used to obtain new information on the congruence kernel of the unit group of a group ring.
  The second aspect concerns the conjugacy classes of the images of finite subgroups of $\mathcal{U}(R G)$ under the irreducible representations of $G$. More precisely, we initiate the study of a blockwise variant of the Zassenhaus conjectures and the subgroup isomorphism problem. Moreover, we contribute to them for the low rank representations above.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.22052v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robynn Corveleyn, Geoffrey Janssens, Doryan Temmerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
