<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR</link>
    <description>math.GR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 05:01:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Lifting solutions of polynomial equations on matrices over field to complete local principal ideal rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\widehat{\mathscr O}$ be a complete local principal ideal ring with residue field $k$ of characteristic not $2$ and $f\in \widehat{\mathscr O}[x_1,x_2,\dots,x_m]$. Take $A\in \mathrm M_n(\widehat{\mathscr O})$ with its reduction $\overline{A}\in \mathrm M_n(k)$. In this article, we study the following lifting problem. Suppose there exists a tuple $(\widetilde{B}_1, \widetilde{B}_2, \dots,\widetilde{B}_m)\in \mathrm M_n(k)^m$ of pairwise commuting matrices such that $f(\widetilde{B}_1, \widetilde{B}_2, \dots,\widetilde{B}_m) = \overline{A}$; under what conditions can this solution be lifted to a tuple $(B_1,B_2,\dots,B_m)\in \mathrm M_n(\widehat{\mathscr O})^m$ of pairwise commuting matrices satisfying $f(B_1,B_2,\dots,B_m)=A$? For $\overline{A}$ cyclic, we show that, under suitable hypotheses analogous to those appearing in Hensel lemma, such a lifting is always possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04576v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikat Panja, Ayon Roy, Anupam Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distorted and undistorted subgroups of the Lodha-Moore group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the Baumslag-Solitar group $BS(1,2)$ is undistorted in the Lodha-Moore group $G_0$ using an explicit lower bound for the word length of $G_0$. We also show that Thompson's group $F$ is distorted in $G_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04839v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuya Kodama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free $\mathbb Q$-groups are residually torsion-free nilpotent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.00402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.00402v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a method to show that some (abstract) groups can be embedded into a free pro-$p$ group. In particular, we show that a finitely generated subgroup of a free $\mathbb Q$-group can be embedded into a free pro-$p$ group for almost all primes $p$. This solves an old problem raised by G. Baumslag: free $\mathbb Q$-groups are residually torsion-free nilpotent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.00402v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Jaikin-Zapirain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some remarks on Grothendieck pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02229v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the paper of Alexander Grothendiek where he introduced Grothendieck pairs and discuss the relation between profinite rigidity and left/right Grothendieck rigidity. We also show that various groups are left and/or right Grothendieck rigid and, in particular, all ascending HNN extensiona of finitely generated free groups are right Grothendieck rigid. Along the way we present a number of questions and suggestions for further research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02229v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Jaikin-Zapirain, Alexander Lubotzky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free groups are $L^2$-subgroup rigid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09515v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the notion of $L^2$-subgroup rigid groups and demonstrate that free groups are $L^2$-subgroup rigid. As a consequence, we establish the equivalence between compressibility, inertness, strong inertness, and $L^2$-independence for a finitely generated subgroup of a free group, confirming a conjecture by Dicks and Ventura as well as the one by Antolin and Jaikin-Zapirain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09515v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Jaikin-Zapirain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On The Relative Cohomology For Algebraic Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00833v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be an algebraic group over a field $k$, and $M$ and $N$ be $G$-modules. In 1961, Hochschild showed how one can define the cohomology groups $\text{Ext}_{G}^{i}(M,N)$. Kimura, in 1965, showed that one can generalize this to get relative cohomology for algebraic groups. The original cohomology groups play an important role in understanding the representation theory of $G$, but the role of relative cohomology is still not well understood.
  In this paper the author expands upon the work of Kimura to prove foundational results about the relative cohomology. The author starts by giving the definitions of relative exact sequences and relative injective modules and proves a variety of basic properties for each that will be essential to define relative cohomology and obtain a relative Grothendieck spectral sequence. In particular, the induction functor will play an important role when studying the relative injective modules. Once the necessary ground work is laid, the definition of relative cohomology is given. Finally, it is stated when there is a relative Grothendieck spectral sequence, and many consequences and examples are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00833v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel T. Loos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On non-freeness of groups generated by two parabolic matrices with rational parameters: limit points and the orbit test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20524v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For $\alpha \in \mathbb{R}$, let $$G_{\alpha}:= \left&lt; \begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 \\ 0 &amp; 1 \end{bmatrix} , \begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0 \\ \alpha &amp; 1 \end{bmatrix} \right&gt; &lt; \mathrm{SL}_2 (\mathbb{R}).$$
  K. Kim and the first author established the orbit test, which provides a sufficient condition for $G_{\alpha}$ not to be a rank-$2$ free group. In this article, we present two main applications of the orbit test. First, using the corresponding modulo homomorphism, we show that the converse of the orbit test does not hold. In particular, we construct explicit counterexamples, all of which are rational. As another application, we construct sequences of non-free rational numbers converging to $3$. These sequences are given by $$ 3 + \frac{3}{2 (9 n - 1)} \quad \text{and} \quad 3 + \frac{9 n + 5}{3 (2 n + 1) (9 n + 4)},$$ and their construction relies on the orbit test together with a modified Pell's equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20524v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wonyong Jang, Dongryung Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realising all countable groups as quasi-isometry groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.06261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given any countable group $G$, we construct uncountably many quasi-isometry classes of proper geodesic metric spaces with quasi-isometry group isomorphic to $G$. Moreover, if the group $G$ is a hyperbolic group, the spaces we construct are hyperbolic metric spaces.
  We make use of a rigidity phenomenon for quasi-isometries exhibited by many symmetric spaces, called strong quasi-isometric rigidity. Our method involves the construction of new examples of strongly quasi-isometrically rigid spaces, arising as graphs of strongly quasi-isometrically rigid rank-one symmetric spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06261v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paula Heim, Joseph MacManus, Lawk Mineh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partial monoid actions on objects in categories with pullbacks and their globalizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11300v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $M$ be a monoid, $\mathscr{C}$ a category with pullbacks and $X$ an object of $\mathscr{C}$. We introduce the notion of a partial action $\alpha$ of $M$ on $X$ and study the globalization question for $\alpha$. If $\alpha$ admits a reflection in the subcategory of global actions, then we reduce the problem to the verification that a certain diagram is a pullback in $\mathscr{C}$. We then give a construction of such a reflection in terms of a colimit of a certain functor with values in $\mathscr{C}$. We specify this construction to the case of categories admitting certain coproducts and coequalizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11300v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jpaa.2024.107734</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Pure and Applied Algebra 228 (2024) 107734</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mykola Khrypchenko, Francisco Klock</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic functions on geometrically finite quotients of the ball</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16620v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be a discrete and torsion-free subgroup of $\mathrm{PU}(n,1)$, the group of biholomorphisms of the unit ball in $\mathbb{C}^{n}$, denoted by $\mathbb{H}^{n}_{\mathbb{C}}$. We show that if $\Gamma$ is Abelian, then $\mathbb{H}^{n}_{\mathbb{C}}/\Gamma$ is a Stein manifold. If the critical exponent $\delta(\Gamma)$ of $\Gamma$ is less than 2, a conjecture of Dey and Kapovich predicts that the quotient $\mathbb{H}^{n}_{\mathbb{C}}/\Gamma$ is Stein. We confirm this conjecture in the case where $\Gamma$ is parabolic or geometrically finite. We also study the case of quotients with $\delta(\Gamma)=2$ that contain compact complex curves and confirm another conjecture of Dey and Kapovich. We finally show that $\mathbb{H}^{n}_{\mathbb{C}}/\Gamma$ is Stein when $\Gamma$ is a parabolic or geometrically finite group preserving a totally real and totally geodesic submanifold of $\mathbb{H}^{n}_{\mathbb{C}}$, without any hypothesis on the critical exponent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16620v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5802/jep.328</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal de l'\'{E}cole polytechnique -- Math\'ematiques, Tome 13 (2026), pp.\ 321--348</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>William Sarem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Parallel Complexity of Identifying Groups and Quasigroups via Decompositions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06478v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the computational complexity of isomorphism testing for finite groups and quasigroups, given by their multiplication tables. We crucially take advantage of their various decompositions to show the following:
  - We first consider the class of groups that admit direct product decompositions, where each indecompsable factor is $O(1)$-generated, and either perfect or centerless. We show any group in this class is identified by the $O(1)$-dimensional count-free Weisfeiler--Leman (WL) algorithm with $O(\log \log n)$ rounds, and the $O(1)$-dimensional counting WL algorithm with $O(1)$ rounds. Consequently, the isomorphism problem for this class is in $\textsf{L}$. This improves upon the previous upper bound of $\textsf{TC}^{1}$, which was obtained using $O(\log n)$ rounds of the $O(1)$-dimensional counting WL (Grochow and Levet; FCT 2023, \textit{J. Comput. Syst. Sci.} 2026).
  - We next consider more generally, the class of groups where each indecomposable factor is $O(1)$-generated. We exhibit an $\textsf{AC}^{3}$ canonical labeling procedure for this class. Here, we accomplish this by showing that in the multiplication table model, the direct product decomposition can be computed in $\textsf{AC}^{3}$, parallelizing the work of Kayal and Nezhmetdinov (ICALP 2009).
  - Isomorphism testing between a central quasigroup $G$ and an arbitrary quasigroup $H$ is in $\textsf{NC}$. Here, we take advantage of the fact that central quasigroups admit an affine decomposition in terms of an underlying Abelian group. Only the trivial bound of $n^{\log(n)+O(1)}$-time was previously known for isomorphism testing of central quasigroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06478v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Johnson, Michael Levet, Petr Vojt\v{e}chovsk\'y, Brett Widholm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galois' Professor's Revenge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09662v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that the groups associated with the Revenge Cube and the Professor's Cube can be realized as Galois groups over the rationals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09662v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Damele, A. Loi, M. Mereb, L. Vendramin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic and topological aspects of the singular twin group and its representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04075v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we introduce the singular twin monoid and its corresponding group, constructed from both algebraic and topological perspectives. We then classify all complex homogeneous $2$-local representations of this constructed group. Moreover, we study the irreducibility of these representations and provide clear conditions under which irreducibility holds. Our results give a structured approach to understanding this new algebraic object and its representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04075v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamad N. Nasser, Nafaa Chbili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embeddings of trees of hyperbolic metric spaces and Cannon--Thurston maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12883v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a tree of hyperbolic metric spaces $\pi:X\to T$ a la Bestvina--Feighn (\cite{BF}), and a hyperbolic subspace $Y$ of $X$ with an induced tree of hyperbolic spaces structure over a subtree $S\subset T$, we address the question as to when the Cannon--Thurston (CT) map exists for the inclusion $Y\to X$. In this paper, we find additional sufficient conditions under which the CT map $\partial Y \to \partial X$ exists. However, we show with examples that this may fail to hold in general. These results about trees of spaces are then applied to graphs of hyperbolic groups to prove various existence results for CT maps. A very special instance of these results is the following:
  \emph{Suppose $G_1$ and $G_2$ are hyperbolic groups with a common quasiconvex subgroup $H$, and the free product with amalgamation $G = G_1 *_H G_2$ is hyperbolic. Suppose $K_i &lt; G_i$, $i = 1,2$ are hyperbolic subgroups containing $H$ and $K=K_1*_H K_2$. Then $K$ (is hyperbolic and,) the inclusion $K\to G$ admits a CT map if the inclusions $K_i\to G_i$, $i=1,2$ admit CT maps.}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12883v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rakesh Halder, Pranab Sardar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
