<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IT</link>
    <description>cs.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 05:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hermitian Hulls of Rational Algebraic Geometry Codes and Applications in Quantum Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interest in the hulls of linear codes has been growing rapidly. More is known when the inner product is Euclidean than Hermitian. A shift to the latter is gaining traction. The focus is on a code whose Hermitian hull dimension and dual distance can be systematically determined. Such a code can serve as an ingredient in designing the parameters of entanglement-assisted quantum error-correcting codes (EAQECCs).
  We use tools from algebraic function fields of one variable to efficiently determine a good lower bound on the Hermitian hull dimensions of generalized rational algebraic geometry (AG) codes. We identify families of AG codes whose hull dimensions can be well estimated by a lower bound. Given such a code, the idea is to select a set of evaluation points for which the residues of the Weil differential associated with the Hermitian dual code has an easily verifiable property.
  The approach allows us to construct codes with designed Hermitian hull dimensions based on known results on Reed-Solomon codes and their generalization. Using the Hermitian method on these maximum distance separable (MDS) codes with designed hull dimensions yields two families of MDS EAQECCs. We confirm that the excellent parameters of the quantum codes from these families are new.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17128v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin Sok, Martianus Frederic Ezerman, Ling San</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-recursive MDS Matrices over Galois Rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $p$ be a prime and $s,m,n$ be positive integers. This paper studies quasi-recursive MDS matrices over Galois rings $GR(p^{s}, p^{sm})$ and proposes various direct construction methods for such matrices. The construction is based on skew polynomial rings $GR(p^{s}, p^{sm})[X;\sigma]$, whose rich factorization properties and enlarged class of polynomials are used to define companion matrices generating quasi-recursive MDS matrices. First, two criteria are established for characterizing polynomials that yield recursive MDS matrices, generalizing existing results, and then an additional criterion is derived in terms of the right roots of the associated Wedderburn polynomial. Using these criteria, methods are developed to construct skew polynomials that give rise to quasi-recursive MDS matrices over Galois rings. This framework extends known constructions to the non-commutative setting and significantly enlarges the family of available matrices, with potential applications to efficient diffusion layers in cryptographic primitives. The results are particularly relevant for practical implementations when $s = 1$ and $p = 2$, i.e., over the finite field $\mathbb{F}_{2^m}$, which is of central interest in real-world cryptographic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17256v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shakir Ali, Atif Ahmad Khan, Abhishek Kesarwani, Susanta Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A distance-free approach to generalized weights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17542v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a unified theory of generalized weights for linear codes endowed with an arbitrary distance. Instead of relying on supports or anticodes, the weights of a code are defined via the intersections of the code with a chosen family of spaces, which we call a test family. The choice of test family determines the properties of the corresponding generalized weights and the characteristics of the code that they capture. In this general framework, we prove that generalized weights are weakly increasing and that certain subsequences are strictly increasing. We also prove a duality result reminiscent of Wei's Duality Theorem. The corresponding properties of generalized Hamming and rank-metric weights follow from our general results by selecting optimal anticodes as a test family. For sum-rank metric codes, we propose a test family that results in generalized weights that are closely connected to -- but not always the same as -- the usual generalized weights. This choice allows us to extend the known duality results for generalized sum-rank weights to some sum-rank-metric codes with a nonzero Hamming component. Finally, we explore a family of generalized weights obtained by intersecting the underlying code with MDS or MRD codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17542v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Di Giusto, Elisa Gorla, Alberto Ravagnani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locally-APN Binomials with Low Boomerang Uniformity in Odd Characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, several studies have shown that when $q\equiv3\pmod{4}$, the function $F_r(x)=x^r+x^{r+\frac{q-1}{2}}$ defined over $\mathbb{F}_q$ is locally-APN and has boomerang uniformity at most~$2$. In this paper, we extend these results by showing that if there is at most one $x\in \mathbb{F}_q$ with $\chi(x)=\chi(x+1)=1$ satisfying $(x+1)^r - x^r = b$ for all $b\in \mathbb{F}_q^*$ and $\gcd(r,q-1)\mid 2$, then $F_r$ is locally-APN with boomerang uniformity at most $2$. Moreover, we study the differential spectra of $F_3$ and $F_{\frac{2q-1}{3}}$, and the boomerang spectrum of $F_2$ when $p=3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17603v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Namhun Koo, Soonhak Kwon, Minwoo Ko, Byunguk Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative Gaussian Approximation for Random Spreading Unsourced Random Access</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive machine-type communications (mMTC) demand robust solutions to support extensive connectivity efficiently. Unsourced random access (URA) has emerged as a promising approach, delivering high spectral and energy efficiency. Among URA code structures, the random spreading (RS) category is a key enabler, providing strong anti-interference capabilities through spectrum spreading gain. Notably, RS-URA approaches theoretical performance limits over the Gaussian multiple access channel in scenarios with few active users. In this paper, we propose an iterative Gaussian approximation decoder designed universally for RS-URA categories. The proposed receiver iterates extrinsic and intrinsic soft information to enhance decoding performance, requiring only a few iterations to converge. Numerical results validate the decoder's effectiveness in terms of performance and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17628v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liandong Hu, Jian Dang, Zaichen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solomonoff-Inspired Hypothesis Ranking with LLMs for Prediction Under Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17145v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reasoning under uncertainty is a key challenge in AI, especially for real-world tasks, where problems with sparse data demands systematic generalisation. Existing approaches struggle to balance accuracy and simplicity when evaluating multiple candidate solutions. We propose a Solomonoff-inspired method that weights LLM-generated hypotheses by simplicity and predictive fit. Applied to benchmark (Mini-ARC) tasks, our method produces Solomonoff-weighted mixtures for per-cell predictions, yielding conservative, uncertainty-aware outputs even when hypotheses are noisy or partially incorrect. Compared to Bayesian Model Averaging (BMA), Solomonoff scoring spreads probability more evenly across competing hypotheses, while BMA concentrates weight on the most likely but potentially flawed candidates. Across tasks, this highlights the value of algorithmic information-theoretic priors for interpretable, reliable multi-hypothesis reasoning under uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17145v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josh Barber (QUT), Rourke Young (QUT), Cameron Coombe (QUT,CSIRO), Will Browne (QUT)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active RIS-Aided Anti-Jamming Wireless Communications: A Stackelberg Game Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17335v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The pervasive threat of jamming attacks, particularly from adaptive jammers capable of optimizing their strategies, poses a significant challenge to the security and reliability of wireless communications. This paper addresses this issue by investigating anti-jamming communications empowered by an active reconfigurable intelligent surface. The strategic interaction between the legitimate system and the adaptive jammer is modeled as a Stackelberg game, where the legitimate user, acting as the leader, proactively designs its strategy while anticipating the jammer's optimal response. We prove the existence of the Stackelberg equilibrium and derive it using a backward induction method. Particularly, the jammer's optimal strategy is embedded into the leader's problem, resulting in a bi-level optimization that jointly considers legitimate transmit power, transmit/receive beamformers, and active reflection. We tackle this complex, non-convex problem by using a block coordinate descent framework, wherein subproblems are iteratively solved via convex relaxation and successive convex approximation techniques. Simulation results demonstrate the significant superiority of the proposed active RIS-assisted scheme in enhancing legitimate transmissions and degrading jamming effects compared to baseline schemes across various scenarios. These findings highlight the effectiveness of combining active RIS technology with a strategic game-theoretic framework for anti-jamming communications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17335v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Tang, Zhen Ma, Bin Li, Cong Li, Qinghe Du, Dusit Niyato, Zhu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timely Information Updating for Mobile Devices Without and With ML Advice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17381v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates an information update system in which a mobile device monitors a physical process and sends status updates to an access point (AP). A fundamental trade-off arises between the timeliness of the information maintained at the AP and the update cost incurred at the device. To address this trade-off, we propose an online algorithm that determines when to transmit updates using only available observations. The proposed algorithm asymptotically achieves the optimal competitive ratio against an adversary that can simultaneously manipulate multiple sources of uncertainty, including the operation duration, the information staleness, the update cost, and the availability of update opportunities. Furthermore, by incorporating machine learning (ML) advice of unknown reliability into the design, we develop an ML-augmented algorithm that asymptotically attains the optimal consistency-robustness trade-off, even when the adversary can additionally corrupt the ML advice. The optimal competitive ratio scales linearly with the range of update costs, but is unaffected by other uncertainties. Moreover, an optimal competitive online algorithm exhibits a threshold-like response to the ML advice: it either fully trusts or completely ignores the ML advice, as partially trusting the advice cannot improve the consistency without severely degrading the robustness. Extensive simulations in stochastic settings further validate the theoretical findings in the adversarial environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17381v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Pin Hsu, Yi-Hsuan Tseng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Additive codes attaining the Griesmer bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Additive codes may have better parameters than linear codes. However, still very few cases are known and the explicit construction of such codes is a challenging problem. Here we show that a Griesmer type bound for the length of additive codes can always be attained with equality if the minimum distance is sufficiently large. This solves the problem for the optimal parameters of additive codes when the minimum distance is large and yields many infinite series of additive codes that outperform linear codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14615v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sascha Kurz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Error Analysis of Channel Estimation for IRS-assisted MIMO Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16827v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As intelligent reflecting surface (IRS) has emerged as a new and promising technology capable of configuring the wireless environment favorably, channel estimation for IRS-assisted multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems has garnered extensive attention in recent years. Despite the development of numerous algorithms to address this challenge, a comprehensive theoretical characterization of the optimal recovery error is still lacking. This paper aims to address this gap by providing theoretical guarantees in terms of stable recovery of channel matrices for noisy measurements. We begin by establishing the equivalence between IRS-assisted MIMO systems in the uplink scenario and a compact tensor train (TT)-based tensor-on-tensor (ToT) regression. Building on this equivalence, we then investigate the restricted isometry property (RIP) for complex-valued subgaussian measurements. Our analysis reveals that successful recovery hinges on the relationship between the number of user terminals and the number of time slots during which channel matrices remain invariant. Utilizing the RIP condition, we establish a theoretical upper bound on the recovery error for solutions to the constrained least-squares optimization problem, as well as a minimax lower bound for the considered model. Our analysis demonstrates that the recovery error decreases inversely with the number of time slots, and increases proportionally with the total number of unknown entries in the channel matrices, thereby quantifying the fundamental trade-offs in channel estimation accuracy. In addition, we explore a multi-hop IRS scheme and analyze the corresponding recovery errors. Finally, we have performed numerical experiments to support our theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16827v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen Qin, Zhihui Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum Spectral Efficiency With Adaptive MQAM Transmissions Over Terrestrial Coherent FSO Links</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22682v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Coherent free-space optical (FSO) communication is recognized as a key enabler for ultra-high-capacity fronthaul and backhaul links in next-generation wireless networks. Spectrally efficient $M$-ary quadrature amplitude modulation (MQAM) formats are well-suited for these links. However, theoretical analyses of adaptive MQAM transmissions over terrestrial FSO channels remain limited. In this letter, we first derive the spectral efficiency limit of adaptive unconstrained MQAM over gamma-gamma turbulence with pointing error. We then show that adaptive transmissions using only six square MQAM constellations performs close to the theoretical limit (within $0.10$-$0.12$ bits/s/Hz) across a wide range of signal-to-noise ratios and channel conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22682v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himani Verma, Kamal Singh, Ranjan K. Mallik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Saturation-Aware Snapshot Compressive Imaging: Theory and Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11869v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Snapshot Compressive Imaging (SCI) uses coded masks to compress a 3D data cube into a single 2D snapshot. In practice, multiplexing can push intensities beyond the sensor's dynamic range, producing saturation that violates the linear SCI model and degrades reconstruction. This paper provides the first theoretical characterization of SCI recovery under saturation. We model clipping as an element-wise nonlinearity and derive a finite-sample recovery bound for compression-based SCI that links reconstruction error to mask density and the extent of saturation. The analysis yields a clear design rule: optimal Bernoulli masks use densities below one-half, decreasing further as saturation strengthens. Guided by this principle, we optimize mask patterns and introduce a novel reconstruction framework, Saturation-Aware PnP Net (SAPnet), which explicitly enforces consistency with saturated measurements. Experiments on standard video-SCI benchmarks confirm our theory and demonstrate that SAPnet significantly outperforms existing PnP-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11869v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyu Zhao, Shirin Jalali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Codebook Design for NOMA Schemes from Bent Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16560v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Uplink grant-free non-orthogonal multiple access (NOMA) is a promising technology for massive connectivity with low latency and high energy efficiency. In code-domain NOMA schemes, the requirements boil down to the design of codebooks that contain a large number of spreading sequences with low peak-to-average power ratio (PAPR) while maintaining low coherence. When employing binary Golay sequences with guaranteed low PAPR in the design, the fundamental problem is to construct a large set of $n$-variable quadratic bent or near-bent functions in a particular form such that the difference of any two is bent for even $n$ or near-bent for odd $n$ to achieve optimally low coherence. In this work, we propose a theoretical construction of NOMA codebooks by applying a recursive approach to those particular quadratic bent functions in smaller dimensions. The proposed construction yields desired NOMA codebooks that contain $6\cdot N$ Golay sequences of length $N=2^{4m}$ for any positive integer $m$ and have the lowest possible coherence $1/\sqrt{N}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16560v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunlei Li, Constanza Riera, Palash Sarkar, Pantelimon Stanica</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
