<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IT</link>
    <description>cs.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 05:00:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Improved decoding algorithms for surface codes under independent bit-flip and phase-flip errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.00972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study exact decoding for the toric code and for planar and rotated surface codes under the standard independent \(X/Z\) noise model, focusing on Separate Minimum Weight (SMW) decoding and Separate Most Likely Coset (SMLC) decoding. For the SMW decoding problem, we show that an \(O(n^{3/2}\log n)\)-time decoder is achievable for surface and toric codes, improving over the \(O(n^{3}\log n)\) worst-case time of the standard approach based on complete decoding graphs. Our approach is based on a local reduction of SMW decoding to the minimum weight perfect matching problem using Fisher gadgets, which preserves planarity for planar and rotated surface codes and genus~\(1\) for the toric code. This reduction enables the use of Lipton--Tarjan planar separator methods and implies that SMW decoding lies in \(\mathrm{NC}\). For SMLC decoding, we show that the planar surface code admits an exact decoder with \(O(n^{3/2})\) algebraic complexity and that the problem lies in \(\mathrm{NC}\), improving over the \(O(n^{2})\) algebraic complexity of Bravyi \emph{et al.} Our approach proceeds via a dual-cycle formulation of coset probabilities and an explicit reduction to planar Pfaffian evaluation using Fisher--Kasteleyn--Temperley constructions. The same complexity measures apply to SMLC decoding of the rotated surface code. For the toric code, we obtain an exact polynomial-time SMLC decoder with \(O(n^{3})\) algebraic complexity. In addition, while the SMLC formulation is motivated by connections to statistical mechanics, we provide a purely algebraic derivation of the underlying duality based on MacWilliams duality and Fourier analysis. Finally, we discuss extensions of the framework to the depolarizing noise model and identify resulting open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.00972v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louay Bazzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Approach of Solving Polynomial Equations Over Binary Extension Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solving quadratic equations over finite fields is a fundamental task in algebraic coding theory and serves as a key subroutine for computing the roots of cubic and quartic polynomials. For the reduced quadratic polynomial $x^2+x+c\in \mathbb{F}_{2^m}[x]$, existing formula-based methods rely on heavy exponentiation or case distinctions on $m$ (odd/even or powers of two), which limits uniformity and efficiency. This paper presents a unified, formula-based solution for all positive integers $m$ that uses only exclusive-OR operations (XORs). The approach leverages a Reed-Muller matrix characterization of evaluations and reduces the problem to solving a binary linear system. The total cost is at most $m^2-2m+1$ XORs, and under parallelism, the latency is $\lceil \log_2 m\rceil$ XORs, making the method attractive for low-power, low-latency applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01079v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leilei Yu, Yunghsiang S. Han, Pingping Li, Jiasheng Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-Shot and Few-Shot Decoding via Stabilizer Redundancy in Bivariate Bicycle Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01137v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bivariate bicycle (BB) codes are a prominent class of quantum LDPC codes constructed from group algebras. While the logical dimension and quantum distance of \emph{coprime} BB codes are known to be determined by a greatest common divisor polynomial $g(z)$, the properties governing their fault tolerance under noisy measurement have remained implicit. In this work, we prove that this same polynomial $g(z)$ dictates the code's stabilizer redundancy and the structure of the classical \emph{syndrome codes} required for single-shot decoding. We derive a strict equality between the quantum rate and the stabilizer redundancy density, and we provide BCH-like bounds on the achievable single-shot measurement error tolerance. Guided by this framework, we construct small coprime BB codes with significantly improved syndrome distance ($d_S$) and evaluate them using BP+OSD. Our analysis reveals a structural bottleneck: within the coprime BB ansatz, high quantum rate imposes an upper bound on syndrome distance, limiting single-shot performance. These results provide concrete algebraic design rules for next-generation 2BGA codes in measurement-limited architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01137v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Rowshan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Structure of the Optimal Detector for Sub-THz Multi-Hop Relays with Unknown Prior: Over-the-Air Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Amplify and forward (AF) relaying is a viable strategy to extend the coverage of sub-terahertz (sub-THz) links, but inevitably propagates noise, leading to cumulative degradation across multiple hops. At the receiver, optimal decoding is desirable, yet challenging under non-Gaussian input distributions (video, voice, etc), for which neither the Minimum Mean Square Error (MMSE) estimator nor the mutual information admits a closed form. A further open question is whether knowledge of Channel State Information (CSI) and noise statistics at the intermediate relays is necessary for optimal detection. Aiming for an optimal decoder, this paper introduces a new framework that interprets the AF relay chain as a variance-preserving diffusion process and employs denoising diffusion implicit models (DDIMs) for signal recovery. We show that each AF hop is mathematically equivalent to a diffusion step with hop-dependent attenuation and noise injection. Consequently, the entire multi-hop chain collapses to an equivalent Gaussian channel fully described by only three real scalars per block: the cumulative complex gain and the effective noise variance. At the receiver, these end-to-end sufficient statistics define a matched reverse schedule that guides the DDIM-based denoiser, enabling near-optimal Bayesian decoding without per-hop CSI. We establish the information-theoretic foundation of this equivalence, proving that decoding performance depends solely on the final effective Signal-to-Noise-Ratio (SNR), regardless of intermediate noise/channel allocation or prior distribution. Simulations under AWGN and Rician fading confirm that the proposed AF-DDIM decoder reduces mean-squared error, symbol error rate, and bit error rate, particularly at moderate SNRs and for higher-order constellations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01194v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ozgur Ercetin, Mohaned Chraiti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic verification algorithm for linear codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01372v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a probabilistic algorithm suitable for any linear code $C$ to determine whether a given vector $\mathbf{x}$ belongs to $ C$. The algorithm achieves $O(n\log n)$ time complexity, $ O(n^2)$ space complexity and with an error probability less than $1/\mathrm{poly}(n)$ in the asymptotic sense.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01372v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingchao Li, Jiyou Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge grouping using methods in Algorithmic Information Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding natural phenomenon through the interactions of different complex systems has become an increasing focus in scientific inquiry. Defining complexity and actually measuring it is an ongoing debate and no standard framework has been established that is both theoretically sound and computationally practical to use. Currently, one of the fields which attempts to formally define complexity is in the realm of Algorithmic Information Theory. The field has shown advances by studying the outputs of 1-dimensional and 2-dimensional Turing machines to determine the complexity values of binary strings and 2-dimensional binary matrices respectively. Using these complexity values, an algorithm called the Block Decomposition Method developed by Zenil, et al. in 2018, has been created to approximate the complexity of adjacency matrices of graphs which has found relative success in grouping graphs based on their complexity values. We use this method along with another method called edge perturbation to exhaustively determine if an edge can be identified to connect two sub-graphs within a graph using the entire symmetric group of its vertices permutation and via unique permutations we call automorphic subsets, which is a special subset of the symmetric group. We also analyze if edges will be grouped closer to their respective sub-graphs in terms of the average algorithmic information contribution. This analysis has been done in order to ascertain if Algorithmic Information Theory can be a viable theory in understanding substructures within graphs and ultimately as a foundation to create frameworks of measuring and analyzing complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01760v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Potestades</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Gradient for Directed Acyclic Graphs: A Score-based Framework for End-to-End Mutual Information Maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a general framework for end-to-end mutual information maximization in communication and sensing systems represented by stochastic directed acyclic graphs (DAGs). We derive a unified formula for the (mutual) information gradient with respect to arbitrary internal parameters, utilizing marginal and conditional score functions. We demonstrate that this gradient can be efficiently computed using vector-Jacobian products (VJP) within standard automatic differentiation frameworks, enabling the optimization of complex networks under global resource constraints. Numerical experiments on both linear multipath DAGs and nonlinear channels validate the proposed framework; the results confirm that the estimator, utilizing score functions learned via denoising score matching, accurately reproduces ground-truth gradients and successfully maximizes end-to-end mutual information. Beyond maximization, we extend our score-based framework to a novel unsupervised paradigm: digital twin calibration via Fisher divergence minimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01789v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadashi Wadayama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Flow in geophysical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new framework for analyzing the evolution of information in geophysical systems. Understanding how information, and its counterpart, uncertainty, propagates is central to predictability studies and has significant implications for applications such as forecast uncertainty quantification and risk management. It also offers valuable insight into the underlying physics of the system. Information propagation is closely linked to causality: how one part of a system influences another, and how some regions remain dynamically isolated. We apply this framework to the one-dimensional, highly nonlinear Kuramoto-Sivashinsky model and to the shallow-water equations, representing a mid-latitude atmospheric strip. Notably, we observe that information can propagate against the fluid flow, and that different model variables exhibit distinct patterns of information evolution. For example, pressure-related information propagates differently from relative vorticity, reflecting the influence of gravity waves versus balanced flow dynamics. This new framework offers a promising addition to the diagnostic tools available for studying complex dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01795v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Jan van Leeuwen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Geometry of Imaging Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Imaging systems are represented as linear operators, and their singular value spectra describe the structure recoverable at the operator level. Building on an operator-based information-theoretic framework, this paper introduces a minimal geometric structure induced by the normalised singular spectra of imaging operators. By identifying spectral equivalence classes with points on a probability simplex, and equipping this space with the Fisher--Rao information metric, a well-defined Riemannian geometry can be obtained that is invariant under unitary transformations and global rescaling. The resulting geometry admits closed-form expressions for distances and geodesics, and has constant positive curvature. Under explicit restrictions, composition enforces boundary faces through rank constraints and, in an aligned model with stated idealisations, induces a non-linear re-weighting of spectral states. Fisher--Rao distances are preserved only in the spectrally uniform case. The construction is abstract and operator-level, introducing no optimisation principles, stochastic models, or modality-specific assumptions. It is intended to provide a fixed geometric background for subsequent analysis of information flow and constraints in imaging pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02111v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Wood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single- and Multi-Objective Stochastic Optimization for Next-Generation Networks in the Generative AI and Quantum Computing Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Next Generation (NG) networks move beyond simply connecting devices to creating an ecosystem of connected intelligence, especially with the support of generative Artificial Intelligence (AI) and quantum computation. These systems are expected to handle large-scale deployments and high-density networks with diverse functionalities. As a result, there is an increasing demand for efficient and intelligent algorithms that can operate under uncertainty from both propagation environments and networking systems. Traditional optimization methods often depend on accurate theoretical models of data transmission, but in real-world NG scenarios, they suffer from high computational complexity in large-scale settings. Stochastic Optimization (SO) algorithms, designed to accommodate extremely high density and extensive network scalability, have emerged as a powerful solution for optimizing wireless networks. This includes various categories that range from model-based approaches to learning-based approaches. These techniques are capable of converging within a feasible time frame while addressing complex, large-scale optimization problems. However, there is currently limited research on SO applied for NG networks, especially the upcoming Sixth-Generation (6G). In this survey, we emphasize the relationship between NG systems and SO by eight open questions involving the background, key features, and lesson learned. Overall, our study starts by providing a detailed overview of both areas, covering fundamental and widely used SO techniques, spanning from single to multi-objective signal processing. Next, we explore how different algorithms can solve NG challenges, such as load balancing, optimizing energy efficiency, improving spectral efficiency, or handling multiple performance trade-offs. Lastly, we highlight the challenges in the current research and propose new directions for future studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02175v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trinh Van Chien, Bui Trong Duc, Nguyen Xuan Tung, Van Duc Nguyen, Waqas Khalid, Symeon Chatzinotas, Lajos Hanzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Site-Specific Beamforming for Next-Generation Spatial Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article proposes generative site-specific beamforming (GenSSBF) for next-generation spatial intelligence in wireless networks. Site-specific beamforming (SSBF) has emerged as a promising paradigm to mitigate the channel acquisition bottleneck in multiantenna systems by exploiting environmental priors. However, classical SSBF based on discriminative deep learning struggles: 1) to properly represent the inherent multimodality of wireless propagation and 2) to effectively capture the structural features of beamformers. In contrast, by leveraging conditional generative models, GenSSBF addresses these issues via learning a conditional distribution over feasible beamformers. By doing so, the synthesis of diverse and high-fidelity beam candidates from coarse channel sensing measurements can be guaranteed. This article presents the fundamentals, system designs, and implementation methods of GenSSBF. Case studies in both indoor and outdoor scenarios show that GenSSBF attains near-optimal beamforming gain with ultra-low channel acquisition overhead. Finally, several open research problems are highlighted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02301v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaolin Wang, Zihao Zhou, Cheng-Jie Zhao, Yuanwei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-Building Decoding of Linear Block Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel maximum-likelihood (ML) soft-decision decoding framework for linear block codes, termed error-building decoding (EBD). The complete decoding process can be performed using only the parity-check matrix, without requiring any other pre-constructed information (such as trellis diagrams or error-pattern lists), and it can also be customized by exploiting the algebraic properties of the code. We formally define error-building blocks, and derive a recursive theorem that allows efficient construction of larger locally optimal blocks from smaller ones, thereby effectively searching for the block associated with the most likely error pattern. The EBD framework is further optimized for extended Hamming codes as an example, through offline and online exclusion mechanisms, leading to a substantial complexity reduction without loss of ML performance. Complexity analysis shows that, for extended Hamming codes of lengths 64, 128, and 256, the fully optimized EBD requires approximately an order of magnitude fewer floating-point operations on average than minimum-edge trellis Viterbi decoding at a frame error rate of $10^{-3}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02330v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoda Qiu, Ling Liu, Yuejun Wei, Liping Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-Aware Routing to Large Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.00823v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large reasoning models (LRMs) have heterogeneous inference energy costs based on which model is used and how much it reasons. To reduce energy, it is important to choose the right LRM and operate it in the right way. As a result, the performance of systems that dispatch tasks to different individual LRMs depend on the balance between mean energy provisioning and stochastic fluctuations. The critical regime is the unique operating point at which neither auxiliary energy nor baseline energy is systematically wasted. Increasing baseline supply shifts the system toward persistent over-supply and baseline-energy waste, while reducing supply induces persistent reliance on auxiliary energy. Yet in this regime, performance remains volatility-limited and so a second-order characterization provides further insights that we develop. Here, performance is governed by how variability is absorbed across time, models, and execution choices. This perspective highlights variance-aware routing and dispatch as a principled design axis, and provides a theoretical basis for developing energy-aware model routing policies. Routing behavior is characterized when dispatch policies are based on training-compute and inference-compute scaling laws for LRMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.00823v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Austin R. Ellis-Mohr, Max Hartman, Lav R. Varshney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gray Area: Characterizing Moderator Disagreement on Reddit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01620v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Volunteer moderators play a crucial role in sustaining online dialogue, but they often disagree about what should or should not be allowed. In this paper, we study the complexity of content moderation with a focus on disagreements between moderators, which we term the ``gray area'' of moderation. Leveraging 5 years and 4.3 million moderation log entries from 24 subreddits of different topics and sizes, we characterize how gray area, or disputed cases, differ from undisputed cases. We show that one-in-seven moderation cases are disputed among moderators, often addressing transgressions where users' intent is not directly legible, such as in trolling and brigading, as well as tensions around community governance. This is concerning, as almost half of all gray area cases involved automated moderation decisions. Through information-theoretic evaluations, we demonstrate that gray area cases are inherently harder to adjudicate than undisputed cases and show that state-of-the-art language models struggle to adjudicate them. We highlight the key role of expert human moderators in overseeing the moderation process and provide insights about the challenges of current moderation processes and tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01620v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shayan Alipour, Shruti Phadke, Seyed Shahabeddin Mousavi, Amirhossein Afsharrad, Morteza Zihayat, Mattia Samory</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Secure Semantic Communications in the Age of Generative and Agentic AI: Threats and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Semantic communication (SemCom) improves communication efficiency by transmitting task-relevant information instead of raw bits and is expected to be a key technology for 6G networks. Recent advances in generative AI (GenAI) further enhance SemCom by enabling robust semantic encoding and decoding under limited channel conditions. However, these efficiency gains also introduce new security and privacy vulnerabilities. Due to the broadcast nature of wireless channels, eavesdroppers can also use powerful GenAI-based semantic decoders to recover private information from intercepted signals. Moreover, rapid advances in agentic AI enable eavesdroppers to perform long-term and adaptive inference through the integration of memory, external knowledge, and reasoning capabilities. This allows eavesdroppers to further infer user private behavior and intent beyond the transmitted content. Motivated by these emerging challenges, this paper comprehensively rethinks the security and privacy of SemCom systems in the age of generative and agentic AI. We first present a systematic taxonomy of eavesdropping threat models in SemCom systems. Then, we provide insights into how GenAI and agentic AI can enhance eavesdropping threats. Meanwhile, we also highlight potential opportunities for leveraging GenAI and agentic AI to design privacy-preserving SemCom systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01791v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunpu Tang, Yuanyuan Jia, Zijiu Yang, Qianqian Yang, Ruichen Zhang, Jun Du, Jihong Park, Zhiguo Shi, Khaled B. Letaief</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surprisal and Metaphor Novelty: Moderate Correlations and Divergent Scaling Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02015v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Novel metaphor comprehension involves complex semantic processes and linguistic creativity, making it an interesting task for studying language models (LMs). This study investigates whether surprisal, a probabilistic measure of predictability in LMs, correlates with different metaphor novelty datasets. We analyse surprisal from 16 LM variants on corpus-based and synthetic metaphor novelty datasets. We explore a cloze-style surprisal method that conditions on full-sentence context. Results show that LMs yield significant moderate correlations with scores/labels of metaphor novelty. We further identify divergent scaling patterns: on corpus-based data, correlation strength decreases with model size (inverse scaling effect), whereas on synthetic data it increases (Quality-Power Hypothesis). We conclude that while surprisal can partially account for annotations of metaphor novelty, it remains a limited metric of linguistic creativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02015v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omar Momen, Emilie Sitter, Berenike Herrmann, Sina Zarrie{\ss}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schwarz maps with symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02282v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The theory of symmetry of quantum mechanical systems is applied to study the structure and properties of several classes of relevant maps in quantum information theory: CPTP, PPT and Schwarz maps. First, we develop the general structure that equivariant maps $\Phi:\mathcal A \to \mathcal B$ between $C^\ast$-algebras satisfy. Then, we undertake a systematic study of unital, Hermiticity-preserving maps that are equivariant under natural unitary group actions. Schwarz maps satisfy Kadison's inequality $\Phi(X^\ast X) \geq \Phi(X)^\ast \Phi(X)$ and form an intermediate class between positive and completely positive maps. We completely classify $U(n)$-equivariant on $M_n(\mathbb C)$ and determine those that are completely positive and Schwarz. Partial classifications are then obtained for the weaker $DU(n)$-equivariance (diagonal unitary symmetry) and for tensor-product symmetries $U(n_1) \otimes U(n_2)$. In each case, the parameter regions where $\Phi$ is Schwarz or completely positive are described by explicit algebraic inequalities, and their geometry is illustrated. Finally, we further show that the $U(n)$-equivariant family satisfies $\mathrm{PPT} \iff \mathrm{EB}$, while the $DU(2)$, symmetric $DU(3)$, $U(2) \otimes U(2)$ and $U(2) \otimes U(3)$, families obey the $\mathrm{PPT}^2$ conjecture through a direct symmetry argument. These results reveal how group symmetry controls the structure of non-completely positive maps and provide new concrete examples where the $\mathrm{PPT}^2$ property holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02282v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alfonso Garc\'ia-Velo, Alberto Ibort</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model non-collapse: Minimax bounds for recursive discrete distribution estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19273v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Learning discrete distributions from i.i.d. samples is a well-understood problem. However, advances in generative machine learning prompt an interesting new, non-i.i.d. setting: after receiving a certain number of samples, an estimated distribution is fixed, and samples from this estimate are drawn and introduced into the sample corpus, undifferentiated from real samples. Subsequent generations of estimators now face contaminated environments, a scenario referred to in the machine learning literature as self-consumption. Empirically, it has been observed that models in fully synthetic self-consuming loops collapse -- their performance deteriorates with each batch of training -- but accumulating data has been shown to prevent complete degeneration. This, in turn, begs the question: What happens when fresh real samples \textit{are} added at every stage? In this paper, we study the minimax loss of self-consuming discrete distribution estimation in such loops. We show that even when model collapse is consciously averted, the ratios between the minimax losses with and without source information can grow unbounded as the batch size increases. In the data accumulation setting, where all batches of samples are available for estimation, we provide minimax lower bounds and upper bounds that are order-optimal under mild conditions for the expected $\ell_2^2$ and $\ell_1$ losses at every stage. We provide conditions for regimes where there is a strict gap in the convergence rates compared to the corresponding oracle-assisted minimax loss where real and synthetic samples are differentiated, and provide examples where this gap is easily observed. We also provide a lower bound on the minimax loss in the data replacement setting, where only the latest batch of samples is available, and use it to find a lower bound for the worst-case loss for bounded estimate trajectories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19273v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIT.2025.3649611</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Millen Kanabar, Michael Gastpar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on Codes Correcting Transpositions of Consecutive Symbols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06692v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The problem of correcting transpositions (or swaps) of consecutive symbols in $ q $-ary strings is studied. Lower bounds on asymptotically achievable rates of codes correcting $ t = \tau n $ transpositions are derived. The first bound is obtained by analyzing the average cardinality of ``transposition balls'' and evaluating the appropriate version of the generalized Gilbert--Varshamov bound, while the second bound follows from a construction of codes correcting an arbitrary number of transpositions (i.e., zero-error codes). Asymptotic bounds on the cardinality of optimal codes correcting $ t = \textrm{const} $ transpositions are also derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06692v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mladen Kova\v{c}evi\'c, Keshav Goyal, Han Mao Kiah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indoor Fluid Antenna Systems Enabled by Layout-Specific Modeling and Group Relative Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15006v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fluid antenna system (FAS) revolutionizes wireless communications via utilizing position-flexible antennas that dynamically optimize channel conditions and mitigate multipath fading. This innovation is particularly valuable in indoor environments, in which signal propagation is severely degraded due to structural obstructions and complex multipath reflections. In this paper, we investigate the channel modeling and the joint optimization of antenna positioning, beamforming, and power allocation for indoor FAS. In particular, we propose a layout-specific channel model, and employ the novel group relative policy optimization (GRPO) algorithm for tackling the optimization problem. Compared to the state-of-the-art Sionna model, our model achieves an 83.3% reduction in computation time with an approximately 3 dB increase in root-mean-square error (RMSE). When simplified to a two-ray model, our model allows for a closed-form antenna position solution with near-optimal performance. For the joint optimization problem, our GRPO algorithm outperforms proximal policy optimization (PPO) and other baselines in sum-rate, while requiring only 50.8% computational resources of PPO, thanks to its group advantage estimation. Simulation results show that increasing either the group size or trajectory length in GRPO does not yield significant improvements in sum-rate, suggesting that these parameters can be selected conservatively without sacrificing performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15006v5</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tong Zhang, Qianren Li, Shuai Wang, Wanli Ni, Jiliang Zhang, Rui Wang, Kai-Kit Wong, Chan-Byoung Chae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutual Information Estimation via Score-to-Fisher Bridge for Nonlinear Gaussian Noise Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05496v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a numerical method to evaluate mutual information (MI) in nonlinear Gaussian noise channels by using denoising score matching (DSM) learning for estimating the score function of channel output. Via de Bruijn's identity, Fisher information estimated from the learned score function yields accurate estimates of MI through a Fisher integral representation for a variety of priors and channel nonlinearities. In this work, we propose a comprehensive theoretical foundation for the Score-to-Fisher bridge methodology, along with practical guidelines for its implementation. We also conduct extensive validation experiments, comparing our approach with closed-form solutions and a kernel density estimation baseline. The results of our numerical experiments demonstrate that the proposed method is both practical and efficient for MI estimation in nonlinear Gaussian noise channels. Additionally, we discuss the theoretical connections between our score-based framework and thermodynamic concepts, such as partition function estimation and optimal transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05496v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadashi Wadayama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Equivalence, Point Set Equivalence, and Polynomial Isomorphism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06843v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The linear code equivalence (LCE) problem is shown to be equivalent to the point set equivalence (PSE) problem, i.e., the problem to check whether two sets of points in a projective space over a finite field differ by a linear change of coordinates. For such a point set $\mathbb{X}$, let $R$ be its homogeneous coordinate ring and $\mathfrak{J}_{\mathbb{X}}$ its canonical ideal. Then the LCE problem is shown to be equivalent to an algebra isomorphism problem for the doubling $R/\mathfrak{J}_{\mathbb{X}}$. As this doubling is an Artinian Gorenstein algebra, we can use its Macaulay inverse system to reduce the LCE problem to a Polynomial Isomorphism (PI) problem for homogeneous polynomials. The last step is polynomial time under some mild assumptions about the codes. Moreover, for indecomposable iso-dual codes we can reduce the LCE search problem to the PI search problem of degree 3 by noting that the corresponding point sets are self-associated and arithmetically Gorenstein, so that we can use the isomorphism problem for the Artinian reductions of the coordinate rings and form their Macaulay inverse systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06843v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Kreuzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information geometry of L\'evy processes and financial models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23646v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the information geometry of L\'evy processes. As a starting point, we derive the $\alpha$-divergence between two L\'evy processes. Subsequently, the Fisher information matrix and the $\alpha$-connection associated with the geometry of L\'evy processes are computed from the $\alpha$-divergence. In addition, we discuss statistical applications of this information geometry. As illustrative examples, we investigate the differential-geometric structures of various L\'evy processes relevant to financial modeling, including tempered stable processes, the CGMY model, and variance gamma processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23646v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaehyung Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Deviations Principle for Isoperimetry and Its Equivalence to Nonlinear Log-Sobolev Inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04030v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The isoperimetric problem is a classic topic in geometric measure theory, yet critical questions regarding the characterization of optimal solutions -- even asymptotically optimal ones -- remain largely unresolved. In this paper, we investigate the large deviations asymptotics (governing sequences of exponentially small sets) for the isoperimetric problem on the product Riemannian manifold $M^{n}$ endowed with the product probability measure $\nu^{\otimes n}$, where $M$ is a Riemannian manifold satisfying $\mathrm{CD}(0,\infty)$. When the probability measure ${\nu}$ admits a finite moment generating function for squared distance, we establish an exact characterization of the large deviations asymptotics of the isoperimetric profile, which reveals a precise equivalence between this asymptotic isoperimetry and an established strengthening of log-Sobolev inequality -- namely, nonlinear log-Sobolev inequality. It is observed that conditional typical sets, a fundamental concept from information theory, form an asymptotically optimal solution to the isoperimetric problem. This class of subsets further yields an upper bound on the isoperimetric profile in the central limit regime (concerning constant-volume sets), expressed as the Gaussian isoperimetric profile times the square root of spectral gap. Furthermore, we apply our results to establish quantitative relations among optimal constants in isoperimetric, concentration and transport inequalities, additionally covering isoperimetry for subexponentially and superexponentially small sets. Our results provide a rigorous justification from the perspective of nonlinear log-Sobolev inequalities for why isoperimetric minimizers behave fundamentally differently across spaces with distinct geometric structures. Our proof idea integrates tools from information theory, optimal transport, and geometric measure theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04030v3</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate Message Passing for Quantum State Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12857v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum state tomography (QST) is an indispensable tool for characterizing many-body quantum systems. However, due to the exponential scaling of the cost of the protocol with system size, many approaches have been developed for quantum states with specific structure, such as low-rank states. In this paper, we show how approximate message passing (AMP), an algorithmic framework for sparse signal recovery, can be used to perform low-rank QST. AMP provides asymptotically optimal performance guarantees for large sparse recovery problems, which suggests its utility for QST. We discuss the design challenges that come with applying AMP to QST, and show that by properly designing the AMP algorithm, we can reduce the reconstruction error by over an order of magnitude compared to existing approaches to low-rank QST. We also performed tomographic experiments on IBM Kingston and considered the effect of device noise on the reliability of the predicted fidelity of state preparation. Our work advances the state of low-rank QST and may be applicable to other quantum tomography protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12857v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah Siekierski, Kausthubh Chandramouli, Christian K\"ummerle, Bojko N. Bakalov, Dror Baron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three results on twisted $G-$codes and skew twisted $G-$codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.00752v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we solve an open question formulated in the original paper of twisted skew group codes regarding when a twisted skew group code is checkable. Also, we prove that all ideals of dimension 3 over a twisted group algebra are abelian group codes, generalising another previous result over group algebras. Finally, we prove a bound on the dimension and distance of a twisted group code, as well as when such bound is reached.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.00752v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alvaro Otero Sanchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
