<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.PR</link>
    <description>q-fin.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 04:01:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Consistent asset modelling with random coefficients and switches between regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09955v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore a stochastic model that enables capturing external influences in two specific ways. The model allows for the expression of uncertainty in the parametrisation of the stochastic dynamics and incorporates patterns to account for different behaviours across various times or regimes. To establish our framework, we initially construct a model with random parameters, where the switching between regimes can be dictated either by random variables or deterministically. Such a model is highly interpretable. We further ensure mathematical consistency by demonstrating that the framework can be elegantly expressed through local volatility models taking the form of standard jump diffusions. Additionally, we consider a Markov-modulated approach for the switching between regimes characterised by random parameters. For all considered models, we derive characteristic functions, providing a versatile tool with wide-ranging applications. In a numerical experiment, we apply the framework to the financial problem of option pricing. The impact of parameter uncertainty is analysed in a two-regime model, where the asset process switches between periods of high and low volatility imbued with high and low uncertainty, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09955v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix L. Wolf, Griselda Deelstra, Lech A. Grzelak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StockGPT: A GenAI Model for Stock Prediction and Trading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05101v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces StockGPT, an autoregressive ``number'' model trained and tested on 70 million daily U.S. stock returns over nearly 100 years. Treating each return series as a sequence of tokens, StockGPT automatically learns the hidden patterns predictive of future returns via its attention mechanism. On a held-out test sample from 2001 to 2023, a daily rebalanced long-short portfolio formed from StockGPT predictions earns an annual return of 119% with a Sharpe ratio of 6.5. The StockGPT-based portfolio completely spans momentum and long-/short-term reversals, eliminating the need for manually crafted price-based strategies, and also encompasses most leading stock market factors. This highlights the immense promise of generative AI in surpassing human in making complex financial investment decisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05101v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dat Mai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
