<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ed-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ed-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ed-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ed-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:05:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities and Challenges in Harnessing Digital Technology for Effective Teaching and Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most of today's educators are in no shortage of digital and online learning technologies available at their fingertips, ranging from Learning Management Systems such as Canvas, Blackboard, or Moodle, online meeting tools, online homework, and tutoring systems, exam proctoring platforms, computer simulations, and even virtual reality/augmented reality technologies. Furthermore, with the rapid development and wide availability of generative artificial intelligence (GenAI) services such as ChatGPT, we are just at the beginning of harnessing their potential to transform higher education. Yet, facing the large number of available options provided by cutting-edge technology, an imminent question on the mind of most educators is the following: how should I choose the technologies and integrate them into my teaching process so that they would best support student learning? We contemplate over these types of important and timely questions and share our reflections on evidence-based approaches to harnessing digital learning tools using a Self-regulated Engaged Learning Framework we have employed in our research in physics education that can be valuable for educators in other disciplines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10777v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/higheredu4010006</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chen, Z.; Singh, C. Opportunities and Challenges in Harnessing Digital Technology for Effective Teaching and Learning. Trends High. Educ. 2025, 4, 6</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhongzhou Chen, Chandralekha Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developing and Evaluating a Large Language Model-Based Automated Feedback System Grounded in Evidence-Centered Design for Supporting Physics Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generative AI offers new opportunities for individualized and adaptive learning, particularly through large language model (LLM)-based feedback systems. While LLMs can produce effective feedback for relatively straightforward conceptual tasks, delivering high-quality feedback for tasks that require advanced domain expertise, such as physics problem solving, remains a substantial challenge. This study presents the design of an LLM-based feedback system for physics problem solving grounded in evidence-centered design (ECD) and evaluates its performance within the German Physics Olympiad. Participants assessed the usefulness and accuracy of the generated feedback, which was generally perceived as useful and highly accurate. However, an in-depth analysis revealed that the feedback contained factual errors in 20% of cases; errors that often went unnoticed by the students. We discuss the risks associated with uncritical reliance on LLM-based feedback systems and outline potential directions for generating more adaptive and reliable LLM-based feedback in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10785v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holger Maus, Paul Tschisgale, Fabian Kieser, Stefan Petersen, Peter Wulff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A DC discharge plasma experiment for undergraduate laboratories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10259v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Plasma physics offers a wide range of fundamental phenomena, making it an excellent subject for undergraduate laboratory instruction. In this work, we present the design, construction, and characterization of a DC glow-discharge plasma chamber developed for the junior-level curriculum, a project carried out by two undergraduate students. The apparatus consists of a 1-meter-long quartz tube with a movable electrode, enabling systematic exploration of plasma behavior under varying pressure, voltage, and geometry. Using this platform, we characterized the Paschen breakdown relation and the voltage-current characteristics of the plasma. We then developed Langmuir probes to map spatial distributions of electron temperature and density, and used Boltzmann plot spectroscopy to measure excitation temperatures across different plasma regions. Finally, with custom Helmholtz coils, we demonstrated magnetic focusing of electrons. We performed Runge-Kutta simulations of particle trajectories and analyzed the electron drift velocity by comparing the focal lengths. Overall, this plasma chamber provides a versatile platform for investigating fundamental plasma phenomena and offers potential for future studies, including microwave-plasma interactions and other student-driven investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10259v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>You-Hsuan Chen, Ting-An Wang, Pisin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Balancing the Byline: Exploring Gender and Authorship Patterns in Canadian Science Publishing Journals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10268v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Canada is internationally recognized for its leadership in science and its commitment to equity, diversity, and inclusion (EDI) in STEM (science, technology, engineering, and math) fields. Despite this leadership, limited research has examined gender disparities in scientific publishing within the Canadian context. This study analyzes over 67,000 articles published in 24 Canadian Science Publishing (CSP) journals between 2010 and 2021 to better understand patterns of gender representation. Findings show that women accounted for less than one-third of published authors across CSP journals. Representation varied by discipline, with higher proportions of women in biomedical sciences and lower proportions of women in engineering - trends that mirror broader national and global patterns. Notably, the proportion of women submitting manuscripts closely matched those published, suggesting that broader workforce disparities may play a larger role than publication bias. Women were less likely to be solo authors or to hold prominent authorship positions, such as first or last author - roles typically associated with research leadership and career advancement. These findings point to the need for a two-fold response: continued efforts to address systemic barriers to women's participation in science, and a review of publishing practices to ensure equitable access, recognition, and inclusion for all researchers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10268v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eden J. Hennessey, Amanda Desnoyers, Margaret Christ, Adrianna Tassone, Skye Hennessey, Bianca Dreyer, Alex Jay, Patricia Sanchez, Shohini Ghose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bringing together African &amp; European research communities with an inclusive astronomy conference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12834v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report on an international scientific conference, where we brought together African and European academic astronomers. This aimed to bridge the gap between those in position of privilege, with ease of access to international events (i.e., the typical experience of academics in Western institutions), with those historically excluded (affecting the majority of African scientists/institutions). We describe how we designed the conference around cutting-edge research problems, but with a parallel focus on building networking and professional relationships. Significant effort went into: (1) ensuring a diversity of participants; (2) practically and financially supporting those who may never have attended an international conference and; (3) creating an inclusive and supportive environment through a careful programme of activities, both before and during the event. Maintaining scientific integrity was a core commitment throughout. We summarise successes, challenges and lessons learnt from organising this conference. We also present feedback obtained from participants immediately after the conference, and a discussion of some longer-term impacts, which we identified around 1 year later. We found an overall achievement of our objectives, and multiple longer-term benefits. With this report we provide some key recommendations for groups, from any research field, who may wish to lead similar initiatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12834v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris M. Harrison (Newcastle University), Leah Morabito (Durham University), Ann Njeri (Newcastle University, on behalf of the Organising Committees)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
