<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO</link>
    <description>stat.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 04:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multivariate strong invariance principle and uncertainty assessment for time in-homogeneous cyclic MCMC samplers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time in-homogeneous cyclic Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) samplers, including deterministic scan Gibbs samplers and Metropolis within Gibbs samplers, are extensively used for sampling from multi-dimensional distributions. We establish a multivariate strong invariance principle (SIP) for Markov chains associated with these samplers. The rate of this SIP essentially aligns with the tightest rate available for time homogeneous Markov chains. The SIP implies the strong law of large numbers (SLLN) and the central limit theorem (CLT), and plays an essential role in uncertainty assessments. Using the SIP, we give conditions under which the multivariate batch means estimator for estimating the covariance matrix in the multivariate CLT is strongly consistent. Additionally, we provide conditions for a multivariate fixed volume sequential termination rule, which is associated with the concept of effective sample size (ESS), to be asymptotically valid. Our uncertainty assessment tools are demonstrated through various numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10194v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoxiang Li, Qian Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No More Mumbles: Enhancing Robot Intelligibility through Speech Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09708v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spoken language interaction is at the heart of interpersonal communication, and people flexibly adapt their speech to different individuals and environments. It is surprising that robots, and by extension other digital devices, are not equipped to adapt their speech and instead rely on fixed speech parameters, which often hinder comprehension by the user. We conducted a speech comprehension study involving 39 participants who were exposed to different environmental and contextual conditions. During the experiment, the robot articulated words using different vocal parameters, and the participants were tasked with both recognising the spoken words and rating their subjective impression of the robot's speech. The experiment's primary outcome shows that spaces with good acoustic quality positively correlate with intelligibility and user experience. However, increasing the distance between the user and the robot exacerbated the user experience, while distracting background sounds significantly reduced speech recognition accuracy and user satisfaction. We next built an adaptive voice for the robot. For this, the robot needs to know how difficult it is for a user to understand spoken language in a particular setting. We present a prediction model that rates how annoying the ambient acoustic environment is and, consequentially, how hard it is to understand someone in this setting. Then, we develop a convolutional neural network model to adapt the robot's speech parameters to different users and spaces, while taking into account the influence of ambient acoustics on intelligibility. Finally, we present an evaluation with 27 users, demonstrating superior intelligibility and user experience with adaptive voice parameters compared to fixed voice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09708v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3401117</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Qiaoqiao Ren, Yuanbo Hou, Dick Botteldooren, Tony Belpaeme</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Process-based Inference for Spatial Energetics Using Bayesian Predictive Stacking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09906v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rapid developments in streaming data technologies have enabled real-time monitoring of human activity that can deliver high-resolution data on health variables over trajectories or paths carved out by subjects as they conduct their daily physical activities. Wearable devices, such as wrist-worn sensors that monitor gross motor activity, have become prevalent and have kindled the emerging field of ``spatial energetics'' in environmental health sciences. We devise a Bayesian inferential framework for analyzing such data while accounting for information available on specific spatial coordinates comprising a trajectory or path using a Global Positioning System (GPS) device embedded within the wearable device. We offer full probabilistic inference with uncertainty quantification using spatial-temporal process models adapted for data generated from ``actigraph'' units as the subject traverses a path or trajectory in their daily routine. Anticipating the need for fast inference for mobile health data, we pursue exact inference using conjugate Bayesian models and employ predictive stacking to assimilate inference across these individual models. This circumvents issues with iterative estimation algorithms such as Markov chain Monte Carlo. We devise Bayesian predictive stacking in this context for models that treat time as discrete epochs and that treat time as continuous. We illustrate our methods with simulation experiments and analysis of data from the Physical Activity through Sustainable Transport Approaches (PASTA-LA) study conducted by the Fielding School of Public Health at the University of California, Los Angeles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09906v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoya Wakayama, Sudipto Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Fredholm Integral Equations of the First Kind via Wasserstein Gradient Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.09936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.09936v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Solving Fredholm equations of the first kind is crucial in many areas of the applied sciences. In this work we adopt a probabilistic and variational point of view by considering a minimization problem in the space of probability measures with an entropic regularization. Contrary to classical approaches which discretize the domain of the solutions, we introduce an algorithm to asymptotically sample from the unique solution of the regularized minimization problem. As a result our estimators do not depend on any underlying grid and have better scalability properties than most existing methods. Our algorithm is based on a particle approximation of the solution of a McKean--Vlasov stochastic differential equation associated with the Wasserstein gradient flow of our variational formulation. We prove the convergence towards a minimizer and provide practical guidelines for its numerical implementation. Finally, our method is compared with other approaches on several examples including density deconvolution and epidemiology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.09936v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca R. Crucinio, Valentin De Bortoli, Arnaud Doucet, Adam M. Johansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform Pessimistic Risk and Optimal Portfolio</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.07158v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The optimal allocation of assets has been widely discussed with the theoretical analysis of risk measures, and pessimism is one of the most attractive approaches beyond the conventional optimal portfolio model. The $\alpha$-risk plays a crucial role in deriving a broad class of pessimistic optimal portfolios. However, estimating an optimal portfolio assessed by a pessimistic risk is still challenging due to the absence of a computationally tractable model. In this study, we propose an integral of $\alpha$-risk called the \textit{uniform pessimistic risk} and the computational algorithm to obtain an optimal portfolio based on the risk. Further, we investigate the theoretical properties of the proposed risk in view of three different approaches: multiple quantile regression, the proper scoring rule, and distributionally robust optimization. Real data analysis of three stock datasets (S\&amp;P500, CSI500, KOSPI200) demonstrates the usefulness of the proposed risk and portfolio model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.07158v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sungchul Hong, Jong-June Jeon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When is Plasmode simulation superior to parametric simulation when estimating the MSE of the least squares estimator in linear regression?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04077v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Simulation is a crucial tool for the evaluation and comparison of statistical methods. How to design fair and neutral simulation studies is therefore of great interest for researchers developing new methods and practitioners confronted with the choice of the most suitable method. The term simulation usually refers to parametric simulation, that is, computer experiments using artificial data made up of pseudo-random numbers. Plasmode simulation, that is, computer experiments using the combination of resampling feature data from a real-life dataset and generating the target variable with a known user-selected outcome-generating model (OGM), is an alternative that is often claimed to produce more realistic data. We compare parametric and Plasmode simulation for the example of estimating the mean squared error (MSE) of the least squares estimator (LSE) in linear regression. If the true underlying data-generating process (DGP) and the OGM were known, parametric simulation would obviously be the best choice in terms of estimating the MSE well. However, in reality, both are usually unknown, so researchers have to make assumptions: in Plasmode simulation for the OGM, in parametric simulation for both DGP and OGM. Most likely, these assumptions do not exactly reflect the truth. Here, we aim to find out how assumptions deviating from the true DGP and the true OGM affect the performance of parametric and Plasmode simulations in the context of MSE estimation for the LSE and in which situations which simulation type is preferable. Our results suggest that the preferable simulation method depends on many factors, including the number of features, and on how and to what extent the assumptions of a parametric simulation differ from the true DGP. Also, the resampling strategy used for Plasmode influences the results. In particular, subsampling with a small sampling proportion can be recommended.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04077v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1371/journal.pone.0299989</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PLOS ONE (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marieke Stolte, Nicholas Schreck, Alla Slynko, Maral Saadati, Axel Benner, J\"org Rahnenf\"uhrer, Andrea Bommert</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
