<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO</link>
    <description>stat.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>MCMC using $\textit{bouncy}$ Hamiltonian dynamics: A unifying framework for Hamiltonian Monte Carlo and piecewise deterministic Markov process samplers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Piecewise-deterministic Markov process (PDMP) samplers constitute a state of the art Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) paradigm in Bayesian computation, with examples including the zig-zag and bouncy particle sampler (BPS). Recent work on the zig-zag has indicated its connection to Hamiltonian Monte Carlo, a version of the Metropolis algorithm that exploits Hamiltonian dynamics. Here we establish that, in fact, the connection between the paradigms extends far beyond the specific instance. The key lies in (1) the fact that any time-reversible deterministic dynamics provides a valid Metropolis proposal and (2) how PDMPs' characteristic velocity changes constitute an alternative to the usual acceptance-rejection. We turn this observation into a rigorous framework for constructing rejection-free Metropolis proposals based on bouncy Hamiltonian dynamics which simultaneously possess Hamiltonian-like properties and generate discontinuous trajectories similar in appearance to PDMPs. When combined with periodic refreshment of the inertia, the dynamics converge strongly to PDMP equivalents in the limit of increasingly frequent refreshment. We demonstrate the practical implications of this new paradigm, with a sampler based on a bouncy Hamiltonian dynamics closely related to the BPS. The resulting sampler exhibits competitive performance on challenging real-data posteriors involving tens of thousands of parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08290v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Chin, Akihiko Nishimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fast and Scalable Pathwise-Solver for Group Lasso and Elastic Net Penalized Regression via Block-Coordinate Descent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop fast and scalable algorithms based on block-coordinate descent to solve the group lasso and the group elastic net for generalized linear models along a regularization path. Special attention is given when the loss is the usual least squares loss (Gaussian loss). We show that each block-coordinate update can be solved efficiently using Newton's method and further improved using an adaptive bisection method, solving these updates with a quadratic convergence rate. Our benchmarks show that our package adelie performs 3 to 10 times faster than the next fastest package on a wide array of both simulated and real datasets. Moreover, we demonstrate that our package is a competitive lasso solver as well, matching the performance of the popular lasso package glmnet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08631v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Yang, Trevor Hastie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Subsampling Inference for Deep Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08276v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep neural networks (DNN) has received increasing attention in machine learning applications in the last several years. Recently, a non-asymptotic error bound has been developed to measure the performance of the fully connected DNN estimator with ReLU activation functions for estimating regression models. The paper at hand gives a small improvement on the current error bound based on the latest results on the approximation ability of DNN. More importantly, however, a non-random subsampling technique--scalable subsampling--is applied to construct a `subagged' DNN estimator. Under regularity conditions, it is shown that the subagged DNN estimator is computationally efficient without sacrificing accuracy for either estimation or prediction tasks. Beyond point estimation/prediction, we propose different approaches to build confidence and prediction intervals based on the subagged DNN estimator. In addition to being asymptotically valid, the proposed confidence/prediction intervals appear to work well in finite samples. All in all, the scalable subsampling DNN estimator offers the complete package in terms of statistical inference, i.e., (a) computational efficiency; (b) point estimation/prediction accuracy; and (c) allowing for the construction of practically useful confidence and prediction intervals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08276v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kejin Wu, Dimitris N. Politis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplifying Debiased Inference via Automatic Differentiation and Probabilistic Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce an algorithm that simplifies the construction of efficient estimators, making them accessible to a broader audience. 'Dimple' takes as input computer code representing a parameter of interest and outputs an efficient estimator. Unlike standard approaches, it does not require users to derive a functional derivative known as the efficient influence function. Dimple avoids this task by applying automatic differentiation to the statistical functional of interest. Doing so requires expressing this functional as a composition of primitives satisfying a novel differentiability condition. Dimple also uses this composition to determine the nuisances it must estimate. In software, primitives can be implemented independently of one another and reused across different estimation problems. We provide a proof-of-concept Python implementation and showcase through examples how it allows users to go from parameter specification to efficient estimation with just a few lines of code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08675v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Luedtke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zigzag path connects two Monte Carlo samplers: Hamiltonian counterpart to a piecewise deterministic Markov process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.07694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.07694v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Zigzag and other piecewise deterministic Markov process samplers have attracted significant interest for their non-reversibility and other appealing properties for Bayesian posterior computation. Hamiltonian Monte Carlo is another state-of-the-art sampler, exploiting fictitious momentum to guide Markov chains through complex target distributions. We establish an important connection between the zigzag sampler and a variant of Hamiltonian Monte Carlo based on Laplace-distributed momentum. The position and velocity component of the corresponding Hamiltonian dynamics travels along a zigzag path paralleling the Markovian zigzag process; however, the dynamics is non-Markovian in this position-velocity space as the momentum component encodes non-immediate pasts. This information is partially lost during a momentum refreshment step, in which we preserve its direction but re-sample magnitude. In the limit of increasingly frequent momentum refreshments, we prove that Hamiltonian zigzag converges strongly to its Markovian counterpart. This theoretical insight suggests that, when retaining full momentum information, Hamiltonian zigzag can better explore target distributions with highly correlated parameters by suppressing the diffusive behavior of Markovian zigzag. We corroborate this intuition by comparing performance of the two zigzag cousins on high-dimensional truncated multivariate Gaussians, including a 11,235-dimensional target arising from a Bayesian phylogenetic multivariate probit modeling of HIV virus data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.07694v3</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiko Nishimura, Zhenyu Zhang, Marc A. Suchard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Inverse Conditional Flows Can Serve as a Substitute for Distributional Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05429v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural network representations of simple models, such as linear regression, are being studied increasingly to better understand the underlying principles of deep learning algorithms. However, neural representations of distributional regression models, such as the Cox model, have received little attention so far. We close this gap by proposing a framework for distributional regression using inverse flow transformations (DRIFT), which includes neural representations of the aforementioned models. We empirically demonstrate that the neural representations of models in DRIFT can serve as a substitute for their classical statistical counterparts in several applications involving continuous, ordered, time-series, and survival outcomes. We confirm that models in DRIFT empirically match the performance of several statistical methods in terms of estimation of partial effects, prediction, and aleatoric uncertainty quantification. DRIFT covers both interpretable statistical models and flexible neural networks opening up new avenues in both statistical modeling and deep learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05429v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Kook, Chris Kolb, Philipp Schiele, Daniel Dold, Marcel Arpogaus, Cornelius Fritz, Philipp F. Baumann, Philipp Kopper, Tobias Pielok, Emilio Dorigatti, David R\"ugamer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
