<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO</link>
    <description>stat.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 08:28:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Strategies for Repulsive Spatial Point Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is increasing interest to develop Bayesian inferential algorithms for point process models with intractable likelihoods. A purpose of this paper is to illustrate the utility of using simulation based strategies, including approximate Bayesian computation (ABC) and Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods for this task. Shirota and Gelfand (2017) proposed an extended version of an ABC approach for repulsive spatial point processes, including the Strauss point process and the determinantal point process, but their algorithm was not correctly detailed. We explain that is, in general, intractable and therefore impractical to use, except in some restrictive situations. This motivates us to instead consider an ABC-MCMC algorithm developed by Fearnhead and Prangle (2012). We further explore the use of the exchange algorithm, together with the recently proposed noisy Metropolis-Hastings algorithm (Alquier et al., 2016). As an extension of the exchange algorithm, which requires a single simulation from the likelihood at each iteration, the noisy Metropolis-Hastings algorithm considers multiple draws from the same likelihood function. We find that both of these inferential approaches yield good performance for repulsive spatial point processes in both simulated and real data applications and should be considered as viable approaches for the analysis of these models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15133v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaoyi Lu, Nial Friel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GIST: Gibbs self-tuning for locally adaptive Hamiltonian Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel and flexible framework for localized tuning of Hamiltonian Monte Carlo samplers by sampling the algorithm's tuning parameters conditionally based on the position and momentum at each step. For adaptively sampling path lengths, we show that randomized Hamiltonian Monte Carlo, the No-U-Turn Sampler, and the Apogee-to-Apogee Path Sampler all fit within this unified framework as special cases. The framework is illustrated with a simple alternative to the No-U-Turn Sampler for locally adapting path lengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15253v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nawaf Bou-Rabee, Bob Carpenter, Milo Marsden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Indicator Imputation for Missing Not At Random Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14534v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Imputation methods for dealing with incomplete data typically assume that the missingness mechanism is at random (MAR). These methods can also be applied to missing not at random (MNAR) situations, where the user specifies some adjustment parameters that describe the degree of departure from MAR. The effect of different pre-chosen values is then studied on the inferences. This paper proposes a novel imputation method, the Random Indicator (RI) method, which, in contrast to the current methodology, estimates these adjustment parameters from the data. For an incomplete variable $X$, the RI method assumes that the observed part of $X$ is normal and the probability for $X$ to be missing follows a logistic function. The idea is to estimate the adjustment parameters by generating a pseudo response indicator from this logistic function. Our method iteratively draws imputations for $X$ and the realization of the response indicator $R$, to which we refer as $\dot{R}$, for $X$. By cross-classifying $X$ by $R$ and $\dot{R}$, we obtain various properties on the distribution of the missing data. These properties form the basis for estimating the degree of departure from MAR. Our numerical simulations show that the RI method performs very well across a variety of situations. We show how the method can be used in a real life data set. The RI method is automatic and opens up new ways to tackle the problem of MNAR data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14534v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahab Jolani, Stef van Buuren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A sensitivity analysis to quantify the impact of neuroimaging preprocessing strategies on subsequent statistical analyses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14882v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Even though novel imaging techniques have been successful in studying brain structure and function, the measured biological signals are often contaminated by multiple sources of noise, arising due to e.g. head movements of the individual being scanned, limited spatial/temporal resolution, or other issues specific to each imaging technology. Data preprocessing (e.g. denoising) is therefore critical. Preprocessing pipelines have become increasingly complex over the years, but also more flexible, and this flexibility can have a significant impact on the final results and conclusions of a given study. This large parameter space is often referred to as multiverse analyses. Here, we provide conceptual and practical tools for statistical analyses that can aggregate multiple pipeline results along with a new sensitivity analysis testing for hypotheses across pipelines such as "no effect across all pipelines" or "at least one pipeline with no effect". The proposed framework is generic and can be applied to any multiverse scenario, but we illustrate its use based on positron emission tomography data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14882v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brize Ozenne, Martin Norgaard, Cyril Pernet, Melanie Ganz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Gaussian process based approach for validation of multi-variable measurement systems: application to SAR measurement systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.12907v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Resource-efficient and robust validation of systems designed to measure a multi-dimensional parameter space is an unsolved problem as it would require millions of test permutations for comprehensive validation coverage. In the paper, an efficient and comprehensive validation approach based on a Gaussian Process (GP) model of the test system has been developed that can operate system-agnostically, avoids calibration to a fixed set of known validation benchmarks, and supports large configuration spaces. The approach consists of three steps that can be performed independently by different parties: 1) GP model creation, 2) model confirmation, and 3) targeted search for critical cases. It has been applied to two systems that measure specific absorption rate (SAR) for compliance testing of wireless devices and apply different SAR measurement methods: a probe-scanning system (per IEC/IEEE 62209-1528), and a static sensor-array system (per IEC 62209-3). The results demonstrate that the approach is practical, feasible, suitable for proving effective equivalence, and can be applied to any measurement method and implementation. The presented method is sufficiently general to be of value not only for SAR system validation, but also in a wide variety of applications that require critical, independent, and efficient validation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.12907v3</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Bujard, E. Neufeld, M. Douglas, J. Wiart, N. Kuster</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Convergence of Black-Box Variational Inference: Should We Stick the Landing?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.14642v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that black-box variational inference (BBVI) with control variates, particularly the sticking-the-landing (STL) estimator, converges at a geometric (traditionally called "linear") rate under perfect variational family specification. In particular, we prove a quadratic bound on the gradient variance of the STL estimator, one which encompasses misspecified variational families. Combined with previous works on the quadratic variance condition, this directly implies convergence of BBVI with the use of projected stochastic gradient descent. For the projection operator, we consider a domain with triangular scale matrices, which the projection onto is computable in $\Theta(d)$ time, where $d$ is the dimensionality of the target posterior. We also improve existing analysis on the regular closed-form entropy gradient estimators, which enables comparison against the STL estimator, providing explicit non-asymptotic complexity guarantees for both.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.14642v5</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyurae Kim, Yian Ma, Jacob R. Gardner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
