<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO</link>
    <description>stat.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 02:46:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Mixing Times of Simulated Tempering for Mixture Targets by Conductance Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the theoretical complexity of simulated tempering for sampling from mixtures of log-concave components differing only by location shifts. The main result establishes the first polynomial-time guarantee for simulated tempering combined with the Metropolis-adjusted Langevin algorithm (MALA) with respect to the problem dimension $d$, maximum mode displacement $D$, and logarithmic accuracy $\log \epsilon^{-1}$. The proof builds on a general state decomposition theorem for $s$-conductance, applied to an auxiliary Markov chain constructed on an augmented space. We also obtain an improved complexity estimate for simulated tempering combined with random-walk Metropolis. Our bounds assume an inverse-temperature ladder with smallest value $\beta_1 = O(D^{-2})$ and spacing $\beta_{i+1}/\beta_i = 1 + O( d^{-1/2} )$, both of which are shown to be asymptotically optimal up to logarithmic factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00708v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle Filter Made Simple: A Step-by-Step Beginner-friendly Guide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The particle filter is a powerful framework for estimating hidden states in dynamic systems where uncertainty, noise, and nonlinearity dominate. This mini-book offers a clear and structured introduction to the core ideas behind particle filters-how they represent uncertainty through random samples, update beliefs using observations, and maintain robustness where linear or Gaussian assumptions fail. Starting from the limitations of the Kalman filter, the book develops the intuition that drives the particle filter: belief as a cloud of weighted hypotheses that evolve through prediction, measurement, and resampling. Step by step, it connects these ideas to their mathematical foundations, showing how probability distributions can be approximated by a finite set of particles and how Bayesian reasoning unfolds in sampled form. Illustrated examples, numerical walk-throughs, and Python code bring each concept to life, bridging the gap between theory and implementation. By the end, readers will not only understand the algorithmic flow of the particle filter but also develop an intuitive grasp of how randomness and structure together enable systems to infer, adapt, and make sense of noisy observations in real time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01281v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Rajesh Dhayalkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Derivative Estimation for Discontinuous Sample Performances: A Leibniz Integration Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00006v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a novel stochastic derivative estimation framework for sample performance functions that are discontinuous in the parameter of interest, based on the multidimensional Leibniz integral rule. When discontinuities arise from indicator functions, we embed the indicator functions into the sample space, yielding a continuous performance function over a parameter-dependent domain. Applying the Leibniz integral rule in this case produces a single-run, unbiased derivative estimator. For general discontinuous functions, we apply a change of variables to shift parameter dependence into the sample space and the underlying probability measure. Applying the Leibniz integral rule leads to two terms: a standard likelihood ratio (LR) term from differentiating the underlying probability measure and a surface integral from differentiating the boundary of the domain. Evaluating the surface integral may require simulating multiple sample paths. Our proposed Leibniz integration framework generalizes the generalized LR (GLR) method and provides intuition as to when the surface integral vanishes, thereby enabling single-run, easily implementable estimators. Numerical experiments demonstrate the effectiveness and robustness of our methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00006v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Ren, Michael C. Fu, Pierre L'Ecuyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient Boosted Mixed Models: Flexible Joint Estimation of Mean and Variance Components for Clustered Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00217v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Linear mixed models are widely used for clustered data, but their reliance on parametric forms limits flexibility in complex and high-dimensional settings. In contrast, gradient boosting methods achieve high predictive accuracy through nonparametric estimation, but do not accommodate clustered data structures or provide uncertainty quantification.
  We introduce Gradient Boosted Mixed Models (GBMixed), a framework and algorithm that extends boosting to jointly estimate mean and variance components via likelihood-based gradients. In addition to nonparametric mean estimation, the method models both random effects and residual variances as potentially covariate-dependent functions using flexible base learners such as regression trees or splines, enabling nonparametric estimation while maintaining interpretability.
  Simulations and real-world applications demonstrate accurate recovery of variance components, calibrated prediction intervals, and improved predictive accuracy relative to standard linear mixed models and nonparametric methods. GBMixed provides heteroscedastic uncertainty quantification and introduces boosting for heterogeneous random effects. This enables covariate-dependent shrinkage for cluster-specific predictions to adapt between population and cluster-level data. Under standard causal assumptions, the framework enables estimation of heterogeneous treatment effects with reliable uncertainty quantification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00217v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mitchell L. Prevett, Francis K. C. Hui, Zhi Yang Tho, A. H. Welsh, Anton H. Westveld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Representational Similarity Analysis Reliable? A Comparison with Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00395v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Representational Similarity Analysis (RSA) is a popular method for analyzing neuroimaging and behavioral data. Here we evaluate the accuracy and reliability of RSA in the context of model selection, and compare it to that of regression. Although RSA offers flexibility in handling high-dimensional, cross-modal, and cross-species data, its reliance on a transformation of raw data into similarity structures may result in the loss of critical stimulus-response information. Across extensive simulation studies and empirical analyses, we show that RSA leads to lower model selection accuracy, regardless of sample size, noise level, feature dimensionality, or multicollinearity, relative to regression. While principal component analysis and feature reweighting mitigate RSA's deficits driven by multicollinearity, regression remains superior in accurately distinguishing between models. Empirical data and a follow-up fMRI simulation further support these conclusions. Our findings suggest that researchers should carefully consider which approach to use: RSA is less effective than linear regression for model selection and fitting when direct stimulus-response mappings are available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00395v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuanji Gao, Gang Chen, Svetlana V. Shinkareva, Rutvik H. Desai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-theoretic minimax and submodular optimization algorithms for multivariate Markov chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00769v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study an information-theoretic minimax problem for finite multivariate Markov chains on $d$-dimensional product state spaces. Given a family $\mathcal B=\{P_1,\ldots,P_n\}$ of $\pi$-stationary transition matrices and a class $\mathcal F = \mathcal{F}(\mathbf{S})$ of factorizable models induced by a partition $\mathbf S$ of the coordinate set $[d]$, we seek to minimize the worst-case information loss by analyzing $$\min_{Q\in\mathcal F}\max_{P\in\mathcal B} D_{\mathrm{KL}}^{\pi}(P\|Q),$$ where $D_{\mathrm{KL}}^{\pi}(P\|Q)$ is the $\pi$-weighted KL divergence from $Q$ to $P$. We recast the above minimax problem into concave maximization over the $n$-probability-simplex via strong duality and Pythagorean identities that we derive. This leads us to formulate an information-theoretic game and show that a mixed strategy Nash equilibrium always exists; and propose a projected subgradient algorithm to approximately solve the minimax problem with provable guarantee. By transforming the minimax problem into an orthant submodular function in $\mathbf{S}$, this motivates us to consider a max-min-max submodular optimization problem and investigate a two-layer subgradient-greedy procedure to approximately solve this generalization. Numerical experiments for Markov chains on the Curie-Weiss and Bernoulli-Laplace models illustrate the practicality of these proposed algorithms and reveals sparse optimal structures in these examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00769v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheyuan Lai, Michael C. H. Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Path Coefficients to Targeted Estimands: A Comparison of Structural Equation Models (SEM) and Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation (TMLE)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01040v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) has gained popularity in the social sciences and causal inference due to its flexibility in modeling complex relationships between variables and its availability in modern statistical software. To move beyond the parametric assumptions of SEM, this paper reviews targeted maximum likelihood estimation (TMLE), a doubly robust, machine learning-based approach that builds on nonparametric SEM. We demonstrate that both TMLE and SEM can be used to estimate standard causal effects and show that TMLE is robust to model misspecification. We conducted simulation studies under both correct and misspecified model conditions, implementing SEM and TMLE to estimate these causal effects. The simulations confirm that TMLE consistently outperforms SEM under misspecification in terms of bias, mean squared error, and the validity of confidence intervals. We applied both approaches to a real-world dataset to analyze the mediation effects of poverty on access to high school, revealing that the direct effect is no longer significant under TMLE, whereas SEM indicates significance. We conclude with practical guidance on using SEM and TMLE in light of recent developments in targeted learning for causal inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01040v1</guid>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junjie Ma, Xiaoya Zhang, Guangye He, Yuting Han, Ting Ge, Feng Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Guarantees for Variational Inference in the Presence of Even and Elliptical Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01064v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend several recent results providing symmetry-based guarantees for variational inference (VI) with location-scale families. VI approximates a target density~$p$ by the best match $q^*$ in a family $Q$ of tractable distributions that in general does not contain $p$. It is known that VI can recover key properties of $p$, such as its mean and correlation matrix, when $p$ and $Q$ exhibit certain symmetries and $q^*$ is found by minimizing the reverse Kullback-Leibler divergence. We extend these guarantees in two important directions. First, we provide symmetry-based guarantees for a broader family of divergences, highlighting the properties of variational objectives under which VI provably recovers the mean and correlation matrix. Second, we obtain further guarantees for VI when the target density $p$ exhibits even and elliptical symmetries in some but not all of its coordinates. These partial symmetries arise naturally in Bayesian hierarchical models, where the prior induces a challenging geometry but still possesses axes of symmetry. We illustrate these theoretical results in a number of experimental settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01064v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles C. Margossian, Lawrence K. Saul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Progress Should Be Measured by Capability-Per-Resource, Not Scale Alone: A Framework for Gradient-Guided Resource Allocation in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01077v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This position paper challenges the "scaling fundamentalism" dominating AI research, where unbounded growth in model size and computation has led to unsustainable environmental impacts and widening resource inequality. We argue that LLM development should be fundamentally reoriented toward capability-per-resource rather than capability alone. We present a theoretical framework demonstrating that resource-allocation decisions guided by gradient influence patterns can dramatically improve efficiency throughout the AI lifecycle. Our analysis shows that in transformer-based models, where a small fraction of parameters exert outsized influence (following heavy-tailed distributions), three critical insights emerge: (1) updating only high-influence parameters strictly outperforms full-parameter tuning on a performance-per-resource basis; (2) simple gradient norms provide computationally efficient proxies for identifying these high-influence components; and (3) coordinated parameter and data selection yields multiplicative efficiency gains, potentially reducing resource requirements by orders of magnitude. Building on these theoretical foundations, we propose a two stage paradigm marginal-return pretraining for foundation developers and influence guided adaptation for downstream users bridged by gradient blueprints, metadata describing which parameters matter most for various tasks. This capability-per-resource perspective transforms what were once considered pragmatic hardware workarounds into theoretically optimal strategies, democratizing access to cutting-edge AI capabilities while significantly reducing environmental impact. By embedding resource consciousness into how we develop, adapt, and evaluate models, we can reshape AI progress toward a more sustainable and equitable future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01077v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David McCoy, Yulun Wu, Zachary Butzin-Dozier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sampling by averaging: A multiscale approach to score estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15069v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel framework for efficient sampling from complex, unnormalised target distributions by exploiting multiscale dynamics. Traditional score-based sampling methods either rely on learned approximations of the score function or involve computationally expensive nested Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) loops. In contrast, the proposed approach leverages stochastic averaging within a slow-fast system of stochastic differential equations (SDEs) to estimate intermediate scores along a diffusion path without training or inner-loop MCMC. Two algorithms are developed under this framework: MultALMC, which uses multiscale annealed Langevin dynamics, and MultCDiff, based on multiscale controlled diffusions for the reverse-time Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process. Both overdamped and underdamped variants are considered, with theoretical guarantees of convergence to the desired diffusion path. The framework is extended to handle heavy-tailed target distributions using Student's t-based noise models and tailored fast-process dynamics. Empirical results across synthetic and real-world benchmarks, including multimodal and high-dimensional distributions, demonstrate that the proposed methods are competitive with existing samplers in terms of accuracy and efficiency, without the need for learned models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15069v2</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paula Cordero-Encinar, Andrew B. Duncan, Sebastian Reich, O. Deniz Akyildiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piecewise deterministic sampling with splitting schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.02537v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithms based on numerical approximations of piecewise-deterministic Markov processes obtained with the framework of splitting schemes. We present unadjusted as well as adjusted algorithms, for which the asymptotic bias due to the discretisation error is removed applying a non-reversible Metropolis-Hastings filter. In a general framework we demonstrate that the unadjusted schemes have weak error of second order in the step size, while typically maintaining a computational cost of only one gradient evaluation of the negative log-target function per iteration. Focusing then on unadjusted schemes based on the Bouncy Particle and Zig-Zag samplers, we provide conditions ensuring geometric ergodicity and consider the expansion of the invariant measure in terms of the step size. We analyse the dependence of the leading term in this expansion on the refreshment rate and on the structure of the splitting scheme, giving a guideline on which structure is best. Finally, we illustrate promising results for our samplers with numerical experiments on a Bayesian imaging inverse problem and a system of interacting particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.02537v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Bertazzi, Paul Dobson, Pierre Monmarch\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>bayesCureRateModel: Bayesian Cure Rate Modeling for Time to Event Data in R</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10221v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The family of cure models provides a unique opportunity to simultaneously model both the proportion of cured subjects (those not facing the event of interest) and the distribution function of time-to-event for susceptibles (those facing the event). In practice, the application of cure models is mainly facilitated by the availability of various R packages. However, most of these packages primarily focus on the mixture or promotion time cure rate model. This article presents a fully Bayesian approach implemented in R to estimate a general family of cure rate models in the presence of covariates. It builds upon the work by Papastamoulis and Milienos (2024) by additionally considering various options for describing the promotion time, including the Weibull, exponential, Gompertz, log-logistic and finite mixtures of gamma distributions, among others. Moreover, the user can choose any proper distribution function for modeling the promotion time (provided that some specific conditions are met). Posterior inference is carried out by constructing a Metropolis-coupled Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampler, which combines Gibbs sampling for the latent cure indicators and Metropolis-Hastings steps with Langevin diffusion dynamics for parameter updates. The main MCMC algorithm is embedded within a parallel tempering scheme by considering heated versions of the target posterior distribution. The package is illustrated on a real dataset analyzing the duration of the first marriage under the presence of various covariates such as the race, age and the presence of kids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10221v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panagiotis Papastamoulis, Fotios Milienos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Inference in Location-Scale Families: Exact Recovery of the Mean and Correlation Matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11067v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given an intractable target density $p$, variational inference (VI) attempts to find the best approximation $q$ from a tractable family $Q$. This is typically done by minimizing the exclusive Kullback-Leibler divergence, $\text{KL}(q||p)$. In practice, $Q$ is not rich enough to contain $p$, and the approximation is misspecified even when it is a unique global minimizer of $\text{KL}(q||p)$. In this paper, we analyze the robustness of VI to these misspecifications when $p$ exhibits certain symmetries and $Q$ is a location-scale family that shares these symmetries. We prove strong guarantees for VI not only under mild regularity conditions but also in the face of severe misspecifications. Namely, we show that (i) VI recovers the mean of $p$ when $p$ exhibits an \textit{even} symmetry, and (ii) it recovers the correlation matrix of $p$ when in addition~$p$ exhibits an \textit{elliptical} symmetry. These guarantees hold for the mean even when $q$ is factorized and $p$ is not, and for the correlation matrix even when~$q$ and~$p$ behave differently in their tails. We analyze various regimes of Bayesian inference where these symmetries are useful idealizations, and we also investigate experimentally how VI behaves in their absence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11067v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles C. Margossian, Lawrence K. Saul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differential privacy guarantees of Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper aims to provide differential privacy (DP) guarantees for Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithms. In a first part, we establish DP guarantees on samples output by MCMC algorithms as well as Monte Carlo estimators associated with these methods under assumptions on the convergence properties of the underlying Markov chain. In particular, our results highlight the critical condition of ensuring the target distribution is differentially private itself. In a second part, we specialise our analysis to the unadjusted Langevin algorithm and stochastic gradient Langevin dynamics and establish guarantees on their (R\'enyi) DP. To this end, we develop a novel methodology based on Girsanov's theorem combined with a perturbation trick to obtain bounds for an unbounded domain and in a non-convex setting. We establish: (i) uniform in $n$ privacy guarantees when the state of the chain after $n$ iterations is released, (ii) bounds on the privacy of the entire chain trajectory. These findings provide concrete guidelines for privacy-preserving MCMC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17150v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ICML 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Bertazzi, Tim Johnston, Gareth O. Roberts, Alain Durmus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation and Optimization of Leave-one-out Cross-validation for the Lasso</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14368v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: I develop an algorithm to produce the piecewise quadratic that computes leave-one-out cross-validation for the lasso as a function of its hyperparameter. The algorithm can be used to find exact hyperparameters that optimize leave-one-out cross-validation either globally or locally, and its practicality is demonstrated on real-world data sets. I also show how the algorithm can be modified to compute approximate leave-one-out cross-validation, making it suitable for larger data sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14368v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Burn</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
