<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.ML updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML</link>
    <description>stat.ML updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Some variation of COBRA in sequential learning setup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This research paper introduces innovative approaches for multivariate time series forecasting based on different variations of the combined regression strategy. We use specific data preprocessing techniques which makes a radical change in the behaviour of prediction. We compare the performance of the model based on two types of hyper-parameter tuning Bayesian optimisation (BO) and Usual Grid search. Our proposed methodologies outperform all state-of-the-art comparative models. We illustrate the methodologies through eight time series datasets from three categories: cryptocurrency, stock index, and short-term load forecasting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04539v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aryan Bhambu, Arabin Kumar Dey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Computation of Leave-One-Out Cross-Validation for $k$-NN Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe a fast computation method for leave-one-out cross-validation (LOOCV) for $k$-nearest neighbours ($k$-NN) regression. We show that, under a tie-breaking condition for nearest neighbours, the LOOCV estimate of the mean square error for $k$-NN regression is identical to the mean square error of $(k+1)$-NN regression evaluated on the training data, multiplied by the scaling factor $(k+1)^2/k^2$. Therefore, to compute the LOOCV score, one only needs to fit $(k+1)$-NN regression only once, and does not need to repeat training-validation of $k$-NN regression for the number of training data. Numerical experiments confirm the validity of the fast computation method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04919v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motonobu Kanagawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Structural Causal Models through Deep Generative Models: Methods, Guarantees, and Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper provides a comprehensive review of deep structural causal models (DSCMs), particularly focusing on their ability to answer counterfactual queries using observational data within known causal structures. It delves into the characteristics of DSCMs by analyzing the hypotheses, guarantees, and applications inherent to the underlying deep learning components and structural causal models, fostering a finer understanding of their capabilities and limitations in addressing different counterfactual queries. Furthermore, it highlights the challenges and open questions in the field of deep structural causal modeling. It sets the stages for researchers to identify future work directions and for practitioners to get an overview in order to find out the most appropriate methods for their needs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05025v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Audrey Poinsot, Alessandro Leite, Nicolas Chesneau, Mich\`ele S\'ebag, Marc Schoenauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust deep learning from weakly dependent data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent developments on deep learning established some theoretical properties of deep neural networks estimators. However, most of the existing works on this topic are restricted to bounded loss functions or (sub)-Gaussian or bounded input. This paper considers robust deep learning from weakly dependent observations, with unbounded loss function and unbounded input/output. It is only assumed that the output variable has a finite $r$ order moment, with $r &gt;1$. Non asymptotic bounds for the expected excess risk of the deep neural network estimator are established under strong mixing, and $\psi$-weak dependence assumptions on the observations. We derive a relationship between these bounds and $r$, and when the data have moments of any order (that is $r=\infty$), the convergence rate is close to some well-known results. When the target predictor belongs to the class of H\"older smooth functions with sufficiently large smoothness index, the rate of the expected excess risk for exponentially strongly mixing data is close to or as same as those for obtained with i.i.d. samples. Application to robust nonparametric regression and robust nonparametric autoregression are considered. The simulation study for models with heavy-tailed errors shows that, robust estimators with absolute loss and Huber loss function outperform the least squares method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05081v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Kengne, Modou Wade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Transductive Learning Equivalent to PAC Learning?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most work in the area of learning theory has focused on designing effective Probably Approximately Correct (PAC) learners. Recently, other models of learning such as transductive error have seen more scrutiny. We move toward showing that these problems are equivalent by reducing agnostic learning with a PAC guarantee to agnostic learning with a transductive guarantee by adding a small number of samples to the dataset. We first rederive the result of Aden-Ali et al. arXiv:2304.09167 reducing PAC learning to transductive learning in the realizable setting using simpler techniques and at more generality as background for our main positive result. Our agnostic transductive to PAC conversion technique extends the aforementioned argument to the agnostic case, showing that an agnostic transductive learner can be efficiently converted to an agnostic PAC learner. Finally, we characterize the performance of the agnostic one inclusion graph algorithm of Asilis et al. arXiv:2309.13692 for binary classification, and show that plugging it into our reduction leads to an agnostic PAC learner that is essentially optimal. Our results imply that transductive and PAC learning are essentially equivalent for supervised learning with pseudometric losses in the realizable setting, and for binary classification in the agnostic setting. We conjecture this is true more generally for the agnostic setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05190v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaddin Dughmi, Yusuf Kalayci, Grayson York</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentially Private Synthetic Data with Private Density Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04554v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The need to analyze sensitive data, such as medical records or financial data, has created a critical research challenge in recent years. In this paper, we adopt the framework of differential privacy, and explore mechanisms for generating an entire dataset which accurately captures characteristics of the original data. We build upon the work of Boedihardjo et al, which laid the foundations for a new optimization-based algorithm for generating private synthetic data. Importantly, we adapt their algorithm by replacing a uniform sampling step with a private distribution estimator; this allows us to obtain better computational guarantees for discrete distributions, and develop a novel algorithm suitable for continuous distributions. We also explore applications of our work to several statistical tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04554v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolija Bojkovic, Po-Ling Loh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Decentralized Gradient Tracking for Federated Minimax Optimization with Local Updates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04566v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Federated learning (FL) for minimax optimization has emerged as a powerful paradigm for training models across distributed nodes/clients while preserving data privacy and model robustness on data heterogeneity. In this work, we delve into the decentralized implementation of federated minimax optimization by proposing \texttt{K-GT-Minimax}, a novel decentralized minimax optimization algorithm that combines local updates and gradient tracking techniques. Our analysis showcases the algorithm's communication efficiency and convergence rate for nonconvex-strongly-concave (NC-SC) minimax optimization, demonstrating a superior convergence rate compared to existing methods. \texttt{K-GT-Minimax}'s ability to handle data heterogeneity and ensure robustness underscores its significance in advancing federated learning research and applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04566v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Junchi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven Error Estimation: Upper Bounding Multiple Errors with No Technical Debt</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04636v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We formulate the problem of constructing multiple simultaneously valid confidence intervals (CIs) as estimating a high probability upper bound on the maximum error for a class/set of estimate-estimand-error tuples, and refer to this as the error estimation problem. For a single such tuple, data-driven confidence intervals can often be used to bound the error in our estimate. However, for a class of estimate-estimand-error tuples, nontrivial high probability upper bounds on the maximum error often require class complexity as input -- limiting the practicality of such methods and often resulting in loose bounds. Rather than deriving theoretical class complexity-based bounds, we propose a completely data-driven approach to estimate an upper bound on the maximum error. The simple and general nature of our solution to this fundamental challenge lends itself to several applications including: multiple CI construction, multiple hypothesis testing, estimating excess risk bounds (a fundamental measure of uncertainty in machine learning) for any training/fine-tuning algorithm, and enabling the development of a contextual bandit pipeline that can leverage any reward model estimation procedure as input (without additional mathematical analysis).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04636v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanath Kumar Krishnamurthy, Susan Athey, Emma Brunskill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causality Pursuit from Heterogeneous Environments via Neural Adversarial Invariance Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04715v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Statistics suffers from a fundamental problem, "the curse of endogeneity" -- the regression function, or more broadly the prediction risk minimizer with infinite data, may not be the target we wish to pursue. This is because when complex data are collected from multiple sources, the biases deviated from the interested (causal) association inherited in individuals or sub-populations are not expected to be canceled. Traditional remedies are of hindsight and restrictive in being tailored to prior knowledge like untestable cause-effect structures, resulting in methods that risk model misspecification and lack scalable applicability. This paper seeks to offer a purely data-driven and universally applicable method that only uses the heterogeneity of the biases in the data rather than following pre-offered commandments. Such an idea is formulated as a nonparametric invariance pursuit problem, whose goal is to unveil the invariant conditional expectation $m^\star(x)\equiv \mathbb{E}[Y^{(e)}|X_{S^\star}^{(e)}=x_{S^\star}]$ with unknown important variable set $S^\star$ across heterogeneous environments $e\in \mathcal{E}$. Under the structural causal model framework, $m^\star$ can be interpreted as certain data-driven causality in general. The paper contributes to proposing a novel framework, called Focused Adversarial Invariance Regularization (FAIR), formulated as a single minimax optimization program that can solve the general invariance pursuit problem. As illustrated by the unified non-asymptotic analysis, our adversarial estimation framework can attain provable sample-efficient estimation akin to standard regression under a minimal identification condition for various tasks and models. As an application, the FAIR-NN estimator realized by two Neural Network classes is highlighted as the first approach to attain statistically efficient estimation in general nonparametric invariance learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04715v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihong Gu, Cong Fang, Peter B\"uhlmann, Jianqing Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A general error analysis for randomized low-rank approximation with application to data assimilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04811v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Randomized algorithms have proven to perform well on a large class of numerical linear algebra problems. Their theoretical analysis is critical to provide guarantees on their behaviour, and in this sense, the stochastic analysis of the randomized low-rank approximation error plays a central role. Indeed, several randomized methods for the approximation of dominant eigen- or singular modes can be rewritten as low-rank approximation methods. However, despite the large variety of algorithms, the existing theoretical frameworks for their analysis rely on a specific structure for the covariance matrix that is not adapted to all the algorithms. We propose a general framework for the stochastic analysis of the low-rank approximation error in Frobenius norm for centered and non-standard Gaussian matrices. Under minimal assumptions on the covariance matrix, we derive accurate bounds both in expectation and probability. Our bounds have clear interpretations that enable us to derive properties and motivate practical choices for the covariance matrix resulting in efficient low-rank approximation algorithms. The most commonly used bounds in the literature have been demonstrated as a specific instance of the bounds proposed here, with the additional contribution of being tighter. Numerical experiments related to data assimilation further illustrate that exploiting the problem structure to select the covariance matrix improves the performance as suggested by our bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04811v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Scotto Di Perrotolo, Youssef Diouane, Selime G\"urol, Xavier Vasseur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning with Posterior Sampling for Revenue Management under Time-varying Demand</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04910v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper discusses the revenue management (RM) problem to maximize revenue by pricing items or services. One challenge in this problem is that the demand distribution is unknown and varies over time in real applications such as airline and retail industries. In particular, the time-varying demand has not been well studied under scenarios of unknown demand due to the difficulty of jointly managing the remaining inventory and estimating the demand. To tackle this challenge, we first introduce an episodic generalization of the RM problem motivated by typical application scenarios. We then propose a computationally efficient algorithm based on posterior sampling, which effectively optimizes prices by solving linear programming. We derive a Bayesian regret upper bound of this algorithm for general models where demand parameters can be correlated between time periods, while also deriving a regret lower bound for generic algorithms. Our empirical study shows that the proposed algorithm performs better than other benchmark algorithms and comparably to the optimal policy in hindsight. We also propose a heuristic modification of the proposed algorithm, which further efficiently learns the pricing policy in the experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04910v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuma Shimizu, Junya Honda, Shinji Ito, Shinji Nakadai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guiding adaptive shrinkage by co-data to improve regression-based prediction and feature selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The high dimensional nature of genomics data complicates feature selection, in particular in low sample size studies - not uncommon in clinical prediction settings. It is widely recognized that complementary data on the features, `co-data', may improve results. Examples are prior feature groups or p-values from a related study. Such co-data are ubiquitous in genomics settings due to the availability of public repositories. Yet, the uptake of learning methods that structurally use such co-data is limited. We review guided adaptive shrinkage methods: a class of regression-based learners that use co-data to adapt the shrinkage parameters, crucial for the performance of those learners. We discuss technical aspects, but also the applicability in terms of types of co-data that can be handled. This class of methods is contrasted with several others. In particular, group-adaptive shrinkage is compared with the better-known sparse group-lasso by evaluating feature selection. Finally, we demonstrate the versatility of the guided shrinkage methodology by showing how to `do-it-yourself': we integrate implementations of a co-data learner and the spike-and-slab prior for the purpose of improving feature selection in genetics studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04917v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark A. van de Wiel, Wessel N. van Wieringen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-fidelity Hamiltonian Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05033v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Numerous applications in biology, statistics, science, and engineering require generating samples from high-dimensional probability distributions. In recent years, the Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) method has emerged as a state-of-the-art Markov chain Monte Carlo technique, exploiting the shape of such high-dimensional target distributions to efficiently generate samples. Despite its impressive empirical success and increasing popularity, its wide-scale adoption remains limited due to the high computational cost of gradient calculation. Moreover, applying this method is impossible when the gradient of the posterior cannot be computed (for example, with black-box simulators). To overcome these challenges, we propose a novel two-stage Hamiltonian Monte Carlo algorithm with a surrogate model. In this multi-fidelity algorithm, the acceptance probability is computed in the first stage via a standard HMC proposal using an inexpensive differentiable surrogate model, and if the proposal is accepted, the posterior is evaluated in the second stage using the high-fidelity (HF) numerical solver. Splitting the standard HMC algorithm into these two stages allows for approximating the gradient of the posterior efficiently, while producing accurate posterior samples by using HF numerical solvers in the second stage. We demonstrate the effectiveness of this algorithm for a range of problems, including linear and nonlinear Bayesian inverse problems with in-silico data and experimental data. The proposed algorithm is shown to seamlessly integrate with various low-fidelity and HF models, priors, and datasets. Remarkably, our proposed method outperforms the traditional HMC algorithm in both computational and statistical efficiency by several orders of magnitude, all while retaining or improving the accuracy in computed posterior statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05033v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhruv V. Patel, Jonghyun Lee, Matthew W. Farthing, Peter K. Kitanidis, Eric F. Darve</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biology-inspired joint distribution neurons based on Hierarchical Correlation Reconstruction allowing for multidirectional neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05097v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Popular artificial neural networks (ANN) optimize parameters for unidirectional value propagation, assuming some guessed parametrization type like Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP) or Kolmogorov-Arnold Network (KAN). In contrast, for biological neurons e.g. "it is not uncommon for axonal propagation of action potentials to happen in both directions" \cite{axon} - suggesting they are optimized to continuously operate in multidirectional way. Additionally, statistical dependencies a single neuron could model is not just (expected) value dependence, but entire joint distributions including also higher moments. Such agnostic joint distribution neuron would allow for multidirectional propagation (of distributions or values) e.g. $\rho(x|y,z)$ or $\rho(y,z|x)$ by substituting to $\rho(x,y,z)$ and normalizing. There will be discussed Hierarchical Correlation Reconstruction (HCR) for such neuron model: assuming $\rho(x,y,z)=\sum_{ijk} a_{ijk} f_i(x) f_j(y) f_k(z)$ type parametrization of joint distribution with polynomial basis $f_i$, which allows for flexible, inexpensive processing including nonlinearities, direct model estimation and update, trained through standard backpropagation or novel ways for such structure up to tensor decomposition. Using only pairwise (input-output) dependencies, its expected value prediction becomes KAN-like with trained activation functions as polynomials, can be extended by adding higher order dependencies through included products - in conscious interpretable way, allowing for multidirectional propagation of both values and probability densities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05097v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jarek Duda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty quantification in metric spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel uncertainty quantification framework for regression models where the response takes values in a separable metric space, and the predictors are in a Euclidean space. The proposed algorithms can efficiently handle large datasets and are agnostic to the predictive base model used. Furthermore, the algorithms possess asymptotic consistency guarantees and, in some special homoscedastic cases, we provide non-asymptotic guarantees. To illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed uncertainty quantification framework, we use a linear regression model for metric responses (known as the global Fr\'echet model) in various clinical applications related to precision and digital medicine. The different clinical outcomes analyzed are represented as complex statistical objects, including multivariate Euclidean data, Laplacian graphs, and probability distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05110v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G\'abor Lugosi, Marcos Matabuena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Model Selection of Gaussian Graphical Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.05690v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In Gaussian graphical model selection, noise-corrupted samples present significant challenges. It is known that even minimal amounts of noise can obscure the underlying structure, leading to fundamental identifiability issues. A recent line of work addressing this "robust model selection" problem narrows its focus to tree-structured graphical models. Even within this specific class of models, exact structure recovery is shown to be impossible. However, several algorithms have been developed that are known to provably recover the underlying tree-structure up to an (unavoidable) equivalence class.
  In this paper, we extend these results beyond tree-structured graphs. We first characterize the equivalence class up to which general graphs can be recovered in the presence of noise. Despite the inherent ambiguity (which we prove is unavoidable), the structure that can be recovered reveals local clustering information and global connectivity patterns in the underlying model. Such information is useful in a range of real-world problems, including power grids, social networks, protein-protein interactions, and neural structures. We then propose an algorithm which provably recovers the underlying graph up to the identified ambiguity. We further provide finite sample guarantees in the high-dimensional regime for our algorithm and validate our results through numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.05690v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abrar Zahin, Rajasekhar Anguluri, Lalitha Sankar, Oliver Kosut, Gautam Dasarathy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity-Aware Amortized Bayesian Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11122v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sensitivity analyses reveal the influence of various modeling choices on the outcomes of statistical analyses. While theoretically appealing, they are overwhelmingly inefficient for complex Bayesian models. In this work, we propose sensitivity-aware amortized Bayesian inference (SA-ABI), a multifaceted approach to efficiently integrate sensitivity analyses into simulation-based inference with neural networks. First, we utilize weight sharing to encode the structural similarities between alternative likelihood and prior specifications in the training process with minimal computational overhead. Second, we leverage the rapid inference of neural networks to assess sensitivity to data perturbations and preprocessing steps. In contrast to most other Bayesian approaches, both steps circumvent the costly bottleneck of refitting the model for each choice of likelihood, prior, or data set. Finally, we propose to use deep ensembles to detect sensitivity arising from unreliable approximation (e.g., due to model misspecification). We demonstrate the effectiveness of our method in applied modeling problems, ranging from disease outbreak dynamics and global warming thresholds to human decision-making. Our results support sensitivity-aware inference as a default choice for amortized Bayesian workflows, automatically providing modelers with insights into otherwise hidden dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11122v5</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lasse Elsem\"uller, Hans Olischl\"ager, Marvin Schmitt, Paul-Christian B\"urkner, Ullrich K\"othe, Stefan T. Radev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Self-Supervised Image Denoising with Denaturation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01124v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Self-supervised learning for image denoising problems in the presence of denaturation for noisy data is a crucial approach in machine learning. However, theoretical understanding of the performance of the approach that uses denatured data is lacking. To provide better understanding of the approach, in this paper, we analyze a self-supervised denoising algorithm that uses denatured data in depth through theoretical analysis and numerical experiments. Through the theoretical analysis, we discuss that the algorithm finds desired solutions to the optimization problem with the population risk, while the guarantee for the empirical risk depends on the hardness of the denoising task in terms of denaturation levels. We also conduct several experiments to investigate the performance of an extended algorithm in practice. The results indicate that the algorithm training with denatured images works, and the empirical performance aligns with the theoretical results. These results suggest several insights for further improvement of self-supervised image denoising that uses denatured data in future directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01124v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Waida, Kimihiro Yamazaki, Atsushi Tokuhisa, Mutsuyo Wada, Yuichiro Wada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bump hunting through density curvature features</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.00174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.00174v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bump hunting deals with finding in sample spaces meaningful data subsets known as bumps. These have traditionally been conceived as modal or concave regions in the graph of the underlying density function. We define an abstract bump construct based on curvature functionals of the probability density. Then, we explore several alternative characterizations involving derivatives up to second order. In particular, a suitable implementation of Good and Gaskins' original concave bumps is proposed in the multivariate case. Moreover, we bring to exploratory data analysis concepts like the mean curvature and the Laplacian that have produced good results in applied domains. Our methodology addresses the approximation of the curvature functional with a plug-in kernel density estimator. We provide theoretical results that assure the asymptotic consistency of bump boundaries in the Hausdorff distance with affordable convergence rates. We also present asymptotically valid and consistent confidence regions bounding curvature bumps. The theory is illustrated through several use cases in sports analytics with datasets from the NBA, MLB and NFL. We conclude that the different curvature instances effectively combine to generate insightful visualizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.00174v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11749-023-00872-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>TEST 32 (2023) 1251-1275</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e E. Chac\'on, Javier Fern\'andez Serrano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the Impact of Model Width and Density on Generalization in Presence of Label Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.08003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.08003v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Increasing the size of overparameterized neural networks has been a key in achieving state-of-the-art performance. This is captured by the double descent phenomenon, where the test loss follows a decreasing-increasing-decreasing pattern (or sometimes monotonically decreasing) as model width increases. However, the effect of label noise on the test loss curve has not been fully explored. In this work, we uncover an intriguing phenomenon where label noise leads to a \textit{final ascent} in the originally observed double descent curve. Specifically, under a sufficiently large noise-to-sample-size ratio, optimal generalization is achieved at intermediate widths. Through theoretical analysis, we attribute this phenomenon to the shape transition of test loss variance induced by label noise. Furthermore, we extend the final ascent phenomenon to model density and provide the first theoretical characterization showing that reducing density by randomly dropping trainable parameters improves generalization under label noise. We also thoroughly examine the roles of regularization and sample size. Surprisingly, we find that larger $\ell_2$ regularization and robust learning methods against label noise exacerbate the final ascent. We confirm the validity of our findings through extensive experiments on ReLu networks trained on MNIST, ResNets/ViTs trained on CIFAR-10/100, and InceptionResNet-v2 trained on Stanford Cars with real-world noisy labels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.08003v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihao Xue, Kyle Whitecross, Baharan Mirzasoleiman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StepMix: A Python Package for Pseudo-Likelihood Estimation of Generalized Mixture Models with External Variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.03853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.03853v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: StepMix is an open-source Python package for the pseudo-likelihood estimation (one-, two- and three-step approaches) of generalized finite mixture models (latent profile and latent class analysis) with external variables (covariates and distal outcomes). In many applications in social sciences, the main objective is not only to cluster individuals into latent classes, but also to use these classes to develop more complex statistical models. These models generally divide into a measurement model that relates the latent classes to observed indicators, and a structural model that relates covariates and outcome variables to the latent classes. The measurement and structural models can be estimated jointly using the so-called one-step approach or sequentially using stepwise methods, which present significant advantages for practitioners regarding the interpretability of the estimated latent classes. In addition to the one-step approach, StepMix implements the most important stepwise estimation methods from the literature, including the bias-adjusted three-step methods with Bolk-Croon-Hagenaars and maximum likelihood corrections and the more recent two-step approach. These pseudo-likelihood estimators are presented in this paper under a unified framework as specific expectation-maximization subroutines. To facilitate and promote their adoption among the data science community, StepMix follows the object-oriented design of the scikit-learn library and provides an additional R wrapper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.03853v5</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sacha Morin, Robin Legault, F\'elix Lalibert\'e, Zsuzsa Bakk, Charles-\'Edouard Gigu\`ere, Roxane de la Sablonni\`ere, \'Eric Lacourse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Study of Bayesian Neural Network Surrogates for Bayesian Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.20028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.20028v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bayesian optimization is a highly efficient approach to optimizing objective functions which are expensive to query. These objectives are typically represented by Gaussian process (GP) surrogate models which are easy to optimize and support exact inference. While standard GP surrogates have been well-established in Bayesian optimization, Bayesian neural networks (BNNs) have recently become practical function approximators, with many benefits over standard GPs such as the ability to naturally handle non-stationarity and learn representations for high-dimensional data. In this paper, we study BNNs as alternatives to standard GP surrogates for optimization. We consider a variety of approximate inference procedures for finite-width BNNs, including high-quality Hamiltonian Monte Carlo, low-cost stochastic MCMC, and heuristics such as deep ensembles. We also consider infinite-width BNNs, linearized Laplace approximations, and partially stochastic models such as deep kernel learning. We evaluate this collection of surrogate models on diverse problems with varying dimensionality, number of objectives, non-stationarity, and discrete and continuous inputs. We find: (i) the ranking of methods is highly problem dependent, suggesting the need for tailored inductive biases; (ii) HMC is the most successful approximate inference procedure for fully stochastic BNNs; (iii) full stochasticity may be unnecessary as deep kernel learning is relatively competitive; (iv) deep ensembles perform relatively poorly; (v) infinite-width BNNs are particularly promising, especially in high dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.20028v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yucen Lily Li, Tim G. J. Rudner, Andrew Gordon Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic covariance models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03590v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In covariance matrix estimation, one of the challenges lies in finding a suitable model and an efficient estimation method. Two commonly used modelling approaches in the literature involve imposing linear restrictions on the covariance matrix or its inverse. Another approach considers linear restrictions on the matrix logarithm of the covariance matrix. In this paper, we present a general framework for linear restrictions on different transformations of the covariance matrix, including the mentioned examples. Our proposed estimation method solves a convex problem and yields an $M$-estimator, allowing for relatively straightforward asymptotic (in general) and finite sample analysis (in the Gaussian case). In particular, we recover standard $\sqrt{n/d}$ rates, where $d$ is the dimension of the underlying model. Our geometric insights allow to extend various recent results in covariance matrix modelling. This includes providing unrestricted parametrizations of the space of correlation matrices, which is alternative to a recent result utilizing the matrix logarithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03590v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Zwiernik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian taut splines for estimating the number of modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05825v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The number of modes in a probability density function is representative of the complexity of a model and can also be viewed as the number of subpopulations. Despite its relevance, there has been limited research in this area. A novel approach to estimating the number of modes in the univariate setting is presented, focusing on prediction accuracy and inspired by some overlooked aspects of the problem: the need for structure in the solutions, the subjective and uncertain nature of modes, and the convenience of a holistic view that blends local and global density properties. The technique combines flexible kernel estimators and parsimonious compositional splines in the Bayesian inference paradigm, providing soft solutions and incorporating expert judgment. The procedure includes feature exploration, model selection, and mode testing, illustrated in a sports analytics case study showcasing multiple companion visualisation tools. A thorough simulation study also demonstrates that traditional modality-driven approaches paradoxically struggle to provide accurate results. In this context, the new method emerges as a top-tier alternative, offering innovative solutions for analysts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05825v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.csda.2024.107961</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computational Statistics and Data Analysis 196 (2024) 107961</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e E. Chac\'on, Javier Fern\'andez Serrano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contextualized Policy Recovery: Modeling and Interpreting Medical Decisions with Adaptive Imitation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07918v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Interpretable policy learning seeks to estimate intelligible decision policies from observed actions; however, existing models force a tradeoff between accuracy and interpretability, limiting data-driven interpretations of human decision-making processes. Fundamentally, existing approaches are burdened by this tradeoff because they represent the underlying decision process as a universal policy, when in fact human decisions are dynamic and can change drastically under different contexts. Thus, we develop Contextualized Policy Recovery (CPR), which re-frames the problem of modeling complex decision processes as a multi-task learning problem, where each context poses a unique task and complex decision policies can be constructed piece-wise from many simple context-specific policies. CPR models each context-specific policy as a linear map, and generates new policy models $\textit{on-demand}$ as contexts are updated with new observations. We provide two flavors of the CPR framework: one focusing on exact local interpretability, and one retaining full global interpretability. We assess CPR through studies on simulated and real data, achieving state-of-the-art performance on predicting antibiotic prescription in intensive care units ($+22\%$ AUROC vs. previous SOTA) and predicting MRI prescription for Alzheimer's patients ($+7.7\%$ AUROC vs. previous SOTA). With this improvement, CPR closes the accuracy gap between interpretable and black-box methods, allowing high-resolution exploration and analysis of context-specific decision models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07918v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jannik Deuschel, Caleb N. Ellington, Yingtao Luo, Benjamin J. Lengerich, Pascal Friederich, Eric P. Xing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Federated Q-Learning: Linear Regret Speedup with Low Communication Cost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15023v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider federated reinforcement learning for tabular episodic Markov Decision Processes (MDP) where, under the coordination of a central server, multiple agents collaboratively explore the environment and learn an optimal policy without sharing their raw data. While linear speedup in the number of agents has been achieved for some metrics, such as convergence rate and sample complexity, in similar settings, it is unclear whether it is possible to design a model-free algorithm to achieve linear regret speedup with low communication cost. We propose two federated Q-Learning algorithms termed as FedQ-Hoeffding and FedQ-Bernstein, respectively, and show that the corresponding total regrets achieve a linear speedup compared with their single-agent counterparts when the time horizon is sufficiently large, while the communication cost scales logarithmically in the total number of time steps $T$. Those results rely on an event-triggered synchronization mechanism between the agents and the server, a novel step size selection when the server aggregates the local estimates of the state-action values to form the global estimates, and a set of new concentration inequalities to bound the sum of non-martingale differences. This is the first work showing that linear regret speedup and logarithmic communication cost can be achieved by model-free algorithms in federated reinforcement learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15023v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong Zheng, Fengyu Gao, Lingzhou Xue, Jing Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical results for uncertainty propagation through trained machine learning regression models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11224v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) models are increasingly being used in metrology applications. However, for ML models to be credible in a metrology context they should be accompanied by principled uncertainty quantification. This paper addresses the challenge of uncertainty propagation through trained/fixed machine learning (ML) regression models. Analytical expressions for the mean and variance of the model output are obtained/presented for certain input data distributions and for a variety of ML models. Our results cover several popular ML models including linear regression, penalised linear regression, kernel ridge regression, Gaussian Processes (GPs), support vector machines (SVMs) and relevance vector machines (RVMs). We present numerical experiments in which we validate our methods and compare them with a Monte Carlo approach from a computational efficiency point of view. We also illustrate our methods in the context of a metrology application, namely modelling the state-of-health of lithium-ion cells based upon Electrical Impedance Spectroscopy (EIS) data</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11224v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Linear Utility Functions From Pairwise Comparison Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02612v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study learnability of linear utility functions from pairwise comparison queries. In particular, we consider two learning objectives. The first objective is to predict out-of-sample responses to pairwise comparisons, whereas the second is to approximately recover the true parameters of the utility function. We show that in the passive learning setting, linear utilities are efficiently learnable with respect to the first objective, both when query responses are uncorrupted by noise, and under Tsybakov noise when the distributions are sufficiently "nice". In contrast, we show that utility parameters are not learnable for a large set of data distributions without strong modeling assumptions, even when query responses are noise-free. Next, we proceed to analyze the learning problem in an active learning setting. In this case, we show that even the second objective is efficiently learnable, and present algorithms for both the noise-free and noisy query response settings. Our results thus exhibit a qualitative learnability gap between passive and active learning from pairwise preference queries, demonstrating the value of the ability to select pairwise queries for utility learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02612v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luise Ge, Brendan Juba, Yevgeniy Vorobeychik</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
