<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.ML updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML</link>
    <description>stat.ML updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed features in supervised machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supervised machine learning involves approximating an unknown functional relationship from a limited dataset of features and corresponding labels. The classical approach to feature-based machine learning typically relies on applying linear regression to standardized features, without considering their physical meaning. This may limit model explainability, particularly in scientific applications. This study proposes a physics-informed approach to feature-based machine learning that constructs non-linear feature maps informed by physical laws and dimensional analysis. These maps enhance model interpretability and, when physical laws are unknown, allow for the identification of relevant mechanisms through feature ranking. The method aims to improve both predictive performance in regression tasks and classification skill scores by integrating domain knowledge into the learning process, while also enabling the potential discovery of new physical equations within the context of explainable machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17112v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Margherita Lampani, Sabrina Guastavino, Michele Piana, Federico Benvenuto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal rule ensemble approach for multi-arm data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heterogeneous treatment effect (HTE) estimation is critical in medical research. It provides insights into how treatment effects vary among individuals, which can provide statistical evidence for precision medicine. While most existing methods focus on binary treatment situations, real-world applications often involve multiple interventions. However, current HTE estimation methods are primarily designed for binary comparisons and often rely on black-box models, which limit their applicability and interpretability in multi-arm settings. To address these challenges, we propose an interpretable machine learning framework for HTE estimation in multi-arm trials. Our method employs a rule-based ensemble approach consisting of rule generation, rule ensemble, and HTE estimation, ensuring both predictive accuracy and interpretability. Through extensive simulation studies and real data applications, the performance of our method was evaluated against state-of-the-art multi-arm HTE estimation approaches. The results indicate that our approach achieved lower bias and higher estimation accuracy compared with those of existing methods. Furthermore, the interpretability of our framework allows clearer insights into how covariates influence treatment effects, facilitating clinical decision making. By bridging the gap between accuracy and interpretability, our study contributes a valuable tool for multi-arm HTE estimation, supporting precision medicine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17166v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke Wan, Kensuke Tanioka, Toshio Shimokawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood-Free Variational Autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational Autoencoders (VAEs) typically rely on a probabilistic decoder with a predefined likelihood, most commonly an isotropic Gaussian, to model the data conditional on latent variables. While convenient for optimization, this choice often leads to likelihood misspecification, resulting in blurry reconstructions and poor data fidelity, especially for high-dimensional data such as images. In this work, we propose \textit{EnVAE}, a novel likelihood-free generative framework that has a deterministic decoder and employs the energy score -- a proper scoring rule -- to build the reconstruction loss. This enables likelihood-free inference without requiring explicit parametric density functions. To address the computational inefficiency of the energy score, we introduce a fast variant, \textit{FEnVAE}, based on the local smoothness of the decoder and the sharpness of the posterior distribution of latent variables. This yields an efficient single-sample training objective that integrates seamlessly into existing VAE pipelines with minimal overhead. Empirical results on standard benchmarks demonstrate that \textit{EnVAE} achieves superior reconstruction and generation quality compared to likelihood-based baselines. Our framework offers a general, scalable, and statistically principled alternative for flexible and nonparametric distribution learning in generative modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17622v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Xu, Qiang Wang, Lijun Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Uncertainty in Deep Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable uncertainty estimates are crucial in modern machine learning. Deep Gaussian Processes (DGPs) and Deep Sigma Point Processes (DSPPs) extend GPs hierarchically, offering promising methods for uncertainty quantification grounded in Bayesian principles. However, their empirical calibration and robustness under distribution shift relative to baselines like Deep Ensembles remain understudied. This work evaluates these models on regression (CASP dataset) and classification (ESR dataset) tasks, assessing predictive performance (MAE, Accu- racy), calibration using Negative Log-Likelihood (NLL) and Expected Calibration Error (ECE), alongside robustness under various synthetic feature-level distribution shifts. Results indicate DSPPs provide strong in-distribution calibration leveraging their sigma point approximations. However, compared to Deep Ensembles, which demonstrated superior robustness in both per- formance and calibration under the tested shifts, the GP-based methods showed vulnerabilities, exhibiting particular sensitivity in the observed metrics. Our findings underscore ensembles as a robust baseline, suggesting that while deep GP methods offer good in-distribution calibration, their practical robustness under distribution shift requires careful evaluation. To facilitate reproducibility, we make our code available at https://github.com/matthjs/xai-gp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17719v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthijs van der Lende, Jeremias Lino Ferrao, Niclas M\"uller-Hof</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Im)possibility of Automated Hallucination Detection in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17004v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Is automated hallucination detection possible? In this work, we introduce a theoretical framework to analyze the feasibility of automatically detecting hallucinations produced by large language models (LLMs). Inspired by the classical Gold-Angluin framework for language identification and its recent adaptation to language generation by Kleinberg and Mullainathan, we investigate whether an algorithm, trained on examples drawn from an unknown target language $K$ (selected from a countable collection) and given access to an LLM, can reliably determine whether the LLM's outputs are correct or constitute hallucinations.
  First, we establish an equivalence between hallucination detection and the classical task of language identification. We prove that any hallucination detection method can be converted into a language identification method, and conversely, algorithms solving language identification can be adapted for hallucination detection. Given the inherent difficulty of language identification, this implies that hallucination detection is fundamentally impossible for most language collections if the detector is trained using only correct examples from the target language.
  Second, we show that the use of expert-labeled feedback, i.e., training the detector with both positive examples (correct statements) and negative examples (explicitly labeled incorrect statements), dramatically changes this conclusion. Under this enriched training regime, automated hallucination detection becomes possible for all countable language collections.
  These results highlight the essential role of expert-labeled examples in training hallucination detectors and provide theoretical support for feedback-based methods, such as reinforcement learning with human feedback (RLHF), which have proven critical for reliable LLM deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17004v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amin Karbasi, Omar Montasser, John Sous, Grigoris Velegkas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relationship between H\"{o}lder Divergence and Functional Density Power Divergence: Intersection and Generalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17008v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we discuss the relationship between two families of density-power-based divergences with functional degrees of freedom -- the H\"{o}lder divergence and the functional density power divergence (FDPD) -- based on their intersection and generalization. These divergence families include the density power divergence and the $\gamma$-divergence as special cases. First, we prove that the intersection of the H\"{o}lder divergence and the FDPD is limited to a general divergence family introduced by Jones et al. (Biometrika, 2001). Subsequently, motivated by the fact that H\"{o}lder's inequality is used in the proofs of nonnegativity for both the H\"{o}lder divergence and the FDPD, we define a generalized divergence family, referred to as the $\xi$-H\"{o}lder divergence. The nonnegativity of the $\xi$-H\"{o}lder divergence is established through a combination of the inequalities used to prove the nonnegativity of the H\"{o}lder divergence and the FDPD. Furthermore, we derive an inequality between the composite scoring rules corresponding to different FDPDs based on the $\xi$-H\"{o}lder divergence. Finally, we prove that imposing the mathematical structure of the H\"{o}lder score on a composite scoring rule results in the $\xi$-H\"{o}lder divergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17008v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Kobayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Weighted-likelihood framework for class imbalance in Bayesian prediction models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Class imbalance occurs when data used for training classification models has a different number of observations or samples within each category or class. Models built on such data can be biased towards the majority class and have poor predictive performance and generalisation for the minority class. We propose a Bayesian weighted-likelihood (power-likelihood) approach to deal with class imbalance: each observation's likelihood is raised to a weight inversely proportional to its class proportion, with weights normalized to sum to the number of samples. This embeds cost-sensitive learning directly into Bayesian updating and is applicable to binary, multinomial and ordered logistic prediction models. Example models are implemented in Stan, PyMC, and Turing.jl, and all code and reproducible scripts are archived on Github: https://github.com/stanlazic/weighted_likelihoods. This approach is simple to implement and extends naturally to arbitrary error-cost matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17013v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanley E. Lazic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whence Is A Model Fair? Fixing Fairness Bugs via Propensity Score Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17066v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fairness-aware learning aims to mitigate discrimination against specific protected social groups (e.g., those categorized by gender, ethnicity, age) while minimizing predictive performance loss. Despite efforts to improve fairness in machine learning, prior studies have shown that many models remain unfair when measured against various fairness metrics. In this paper, we examine whether the way training and testing data are sampled affects the reliability of reported fairness metrics. Since training and test sets are often randomly sampled from the same population, bias present in the training data may still exist in the test data, potentially skewing fairness assessments. To address this, we propose FairMatch, a post-processing method that applies propensity score matching to evaluate and mitigate bias. FairMatch identifies control and treatment pairs with similar propensity scores in the test set and adjusts decision thresholds for different subgroups accordingly. For samples that cannot be matched, we perform probabilistic calibration using fairness-aware loss functions. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach can (a) precisely locate subsets of the test data where the model is unbiased, and (b) significantly reduce bias on the remaining data. Overall, propensity score matching offers a principled way to improve both fairness evaluation and mitigation, without sacrificing predictive performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17066v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kewen Peng, Yicheng Yang, Hao Zhuo, Tim Menzies</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OUI Need to Talk About Weight Decay: A New Perspective on Overfitting Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the Overfitting-Underfitting Indicator (OUI), a novel tool for monitoring the training dynamics of Deep Neural Networks (DNNs) and identifying optimal regularization hyperparameters. Specifically, we validate that OUI can effectively guide the selection of the Weight Decay (WD) hyperparameter by indicating whether a model is overfitting or underfitting during training without requiring validation data. Through experiments on DenseNet-BC-100 with CIFAR- 100, EfficientNet-B0 with TinyImageNet and ResNet-34 with ImageNet-1K, we show that maintaining OUI within a prescribed interval correlates strongly with improved generalization and validation scores. Notably, OUI converges significantly faster than traditional metrics such as loss or accuracy, enabling practitioners to identify optimal WD (hyperparameter) values within the early stages of training. By leveraging OUI as a reliable indicator, we can determine early in training whether the chosen WD value leads the model to underfit the training data, overfit, or strike a well-balanced trade-off that maximizes validation scores. This enables more precise WD tuning for optimal performance on the tested datasets and DNNs. All code for reproducing these experiments is available at https://github.com/AlbertoFdezHdez/OUI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17160v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Fern\'andez-Hern\'andez, Jose I. Mestre, Manuel F. Dolz, Jose Duato, Enrique S. Quintana-Ort\'i</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signal Recovery from Random Dot-Product Graphs Under Local Differential Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of recovering latent information from graphs under $\varepsilon$-edge local differential privacy where the presence of relationships/edges between two users/vertices remains confidential, even from the data curator. For the class of generalized random dot-product graphs, we show that a standard local differential privacy mechanism induces a specific geometric distortion in the latent positions. Leveraging this insight, we show that consistent recovery of the latent positions is achievable by appropriately adjusting the statistical inference procedure for the privatized graph. Furthermore, we prove that our procedure is nearly minimax-optimal under local edge differential privacy constraints. Lastly, we show that this framework allows for consistent recovery of geometric and topological information underlying the latent positions, as encoded in their persistence diagrams. Our results extend previous work from the private community detection literature to a substantially richer class of models and inferential tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17274v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Vishwanath, Jonathan Hehir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to R package `mvs`</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17546v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In biomedical science, a set of objects or persons can often be described by multiple distinct sets of features obtained from different data sources or modalities (called "multi-view data"). Classical machine learning methods ignore the multi-view structure of such data, limiting model interpretability and performance. The R package `mvs` provides methods that were designed specifically for dealing with multi-view data, based on the multi-view stacking (MVS) framework. MVS is a form of supervised (machine) learning used to train multi-view classification or prediction models. MVS works by training a learning algorithm on each view separately, estimating the predictive power of each view-specific model through cross-validation, and then using another learning algorithm to assign weights to the view-specific models based on their estimated predictions. MVS is a form of ensemble learning, dividing the large multi-view learning problem into smaller sub-problems. Most of these sub-problems can be solved in parallel, making it computationally attractive. Additionally, the number of features of the sub-problems is greatly reduced compared with the full multi-view learning problem. This makes MVS especially useful when the total number of features is larger than the number of observations (i.e., high-dimensional data). MVS can still be applied even if the sub-problems are themselves high-dimensional by adding suitable penalty terms to the learning algorithms. Furthermore, MVS can be used to automatically select the views which are most important for prediction. The R package `mvs` makes fitting MVS models, including such penalty terms, easily and openly accessible. `mvs` allows for the fitting of stacked models with any number of levels, with different penalty terms, different outcome distributions, and provides several options for missing data handling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17546v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wouter van Loon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aerial Image Classification in Scarce and Unconstrained Environments via Conformal Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17655v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a comprehensive empirical analysis of conformal prediction methods on a challenging aerial image dataset featuring diverse events in unconstrained environments. Conformal prediction is a powerful post-hoc technique that takes the output of any classifier and transforms it into a set of likely labels, providing a statistical guarantee on the coverage of the true label. Unlike evaluations on standard benchmarks, our study addresses the complexities of data-scarce and highly variable real-world settings. We investigate the effectiveness of leveraging pretrained models (MobileNet, DenseNet, and ResNet), fine-tuned with limited labeled data, to generate informative prediction sets. To further evaluate the impact of calibration, we consider two parallel pipelines (with and without temperature scaling) and assess performance using two key metrics: empirical coverage and average prediction set size. This setup allows us to systematically examine how calibration choices influence the trade-off between reliability and efficiency. Our findings demonstrate that even with relatively small labeled samples and simple nonconformity scores, conformal prediction can yield valuable uncertainty estimates for complex tasks. Moreover, our analysis reveals that while temperature scaling is often employed for calibration, it does not consistently lead to smaller prediction sets, underscoring the importance of careful consideration in its application. Furthermore, our results highlight the significant potential of model compression techniques within the conformal prediction pipeline for deployment in resource-constrained environments. Based on our observations, we advocate for future research to delve into the impact of noisy or ambiguous labels on conformal prediction performance and to explore effective model reduction strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17655v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farhad Pourkamali-Anaraki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Neural Network Approaches for Conditional Optimal Transport with Applications in Bayesian Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16975v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present two neural network approaches that approximate the solutions of static and dynamic $\unicode{x1D450}\unicode{x1D45C}\unicode{x1D45B}\unicode{x1D451}\unicode{x1D456}\unicode{x1D461}\unicode{x1D456}\unicode{x1D45C}\unicode{x1D45B}\unicode{x1D44E}\unicode{x1D459}\unicode{x0020}\unicode{x1D45C}\unicode{x1D45D}\unicode{x1D461}\unicode{x1D456}\unicode{x1D45A}\unicode{x1D44E}\unicode{x1D459}\unicode{x0020}\unicode{x1D461}\unicode{x1D45F}\unicode{x1D44E}\unicode{x1D45B}\unicode{x1D460}\unicode{x1D45D}\unicode{x1D45C}\unicode{x1D45F}\unicode{x1D461}$ (COT) problems. Both approaches enable conditional sampling and conditional density estimation, which are core tasks in Bayesian inference$\unicode{x2013}$particularly in the simulation-based ($\unicode{x201C}$likelihood-free$\unicode{x201D}$) setting. Our methods represent the target conditional distribution as a transformation of a tractable reference distribution. Obtaining such a transformation, chosen here to be an approximation of the COT map, is computationally challenging even in moderate dimensions. To improve scalability, our numerical algorithms use neural networks to parameterize candidate maps and further exploit the structure of the COT problem. Our static approach approximates the map as the gradient of a partially input-convex neural network. It uses a novel numerical implementation to increase computational efficiency compared to state-of-the-art alternatives. Our dynamic approach approximates the conditional optimal transport via the flow map of a regularized neural ODE; compared to the static approach, it is slower to train but offers more modeling choices and can lead to faster sampling. We demonstrate both algorithms numerically, comparing them with competing state-of-the-art approaches, using benchmark datasets and simulation-based Bayesian inverse problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16975v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheyu Oliver Wang, Ricardo Baptista, Youssef Marzouk, Lars Ruthotto, Deepanshu Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variation Due to Regularization Tractably Recovers Bayesian Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10671v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Uncertainty quantification in deep learning is crucial for safe and reliable decision-making in downstream tasks. Existing methods quantify uncertainty at the last layer or other approximations of the network which may miss some sources of uncertainty in the model. To address this gap, we propose an uncertainty quantification method for large networks based on variation due to regularization. Essentially, predictions that are more (less) sensitive to the regularization of network parameters are less (more, respectively) certain. This principle can be implemented by deterministically tweaking the training loss during the fine-tuning phase and reflects confidence in the output as a function of all layers of the network. We show that regularization variation (RegVar) provides rigorous uncertainty estimates that, in the infinitesimal limit, exactly recover the Laplace approximation in Bayesian deep learning. We demonstrate its success in several deep learning architectures, showing it can scale tractably with the network size while maintaining or improving uncertainty quantification quality. Our experiments across multiple datasets show that RegVar not only identifies uncertain predictions effectively but also provides insights into the stability of learned representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10671v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James McInerney, Nathan Kallus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of Diffusion Models Under the Manifold Hypothesis in High-Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18804v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Models (DDPM) are powerful state-of-the-art methods used to generate synthetic data from high-dimensional data distributions and are widely used for image, audio, and video generation as well as many more applications in science and beyond. The \textit{manifold hypothesis} states that high-dimensional data often lie on lower-dimensional manifolds within the ambient space, and is widely believed to hold in provided examples. While recent results have provided invaluable insight into how diffusion models adapt to the manifold hypothesis, they do not capture the great empirical success of these models, making this a very fruitful research direction.
  In this work, we study DDPMs under the manifold hypothesis and prove that they achieve rates independent of the ambient dimension in terms of score learning. In terms of sampling complexity, we obtain rates independent of the ambient dimension w.r.t. the Kullback-Leibler divergence, and $O(\sqrt{D})$ w.r.t. the Wasserstein distance. We do this by developing a new framework connecting diffusion models to the well-studied theory of extrema of Gaussian Processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18804v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iskander Azangulov, George Deligiannidis, Judith Rousseau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Convergence of Diffusion Models Under the Manifold Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09046v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Score-matching generative models have proven successful at sampling from complex high-dimensional data distributions. In many applications, this distribution is believed to concentrate on a much lower $d$-dimensional manifold embedded into $D$-dimensional space; this is known as the manifold hypothesis. The current best-known convergence guarantees are either linear in $D$ or polynomial (superlinear) in $d$. The latter exploits a novel integration scheme for the backward SDE. We take the best of both worlds and show that the number of steps diffusion models require in order to converge in Kullback-Leibler~(KL) divergence is linear (up to logarithmic terms) in the intrinsic dimension $d$. Moreover, we show that this linear dependency is sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09046v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Potaptchik, Iskander Azangulov, George Deligiannidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponentially Consistent Nonparametric Linkage-Based Clustering of Data Sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13922v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider nonparametric clustering of $M$ independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) data sequences generated from {\em unknown} distributions. The distributions of the $M$ data sequences belong to $K$ underlying distribution clusters. Existing results on exponentially consistent nonparametric clustering algorithms, like single linkage-based (SLINK) clustering and $k$-medoids distribution clustering, assume that the maximum intra-cluster distance ($d_L$) is smaller than the minimum inter-cluster distance ($d_H$). First, in the fixed sample size (FSS) setting, we show that exponential consistency can be achieved for SLINK clustering under a less strict assumption, $d_I &lt; d_H$, where $d_I$ is the maximum distance between any two sub-clusters of a cluster that partition the cluster. Note that $d_I &lt; d_L$ in general. Thus, our results show that SLINK is exponentially consistent for a larger class of problems than previously known. In our simulations, we also identify examples where $k$-medoids clustering is unable to find the true clusters, but SLINK is exponentially consistent. Then, we propose a sequential clustering algorithm, named SLINK-SEQ, based on SLINK and prove that it is also exponentially consistent. Simulation results show that the SLINK-SEQ algorithm requires fewer expected number of samples than the FSS SLINK algorithm for the same probability of error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13922v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhupender Singh, Ananth Ram Rajagopalan, Srikrishna Bhashyam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty Quantification With Noise Injection in Neural Networks: A Bayesian Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12314v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Model uncertainty quantification involves measuring and evaluating the uncertainty linked to a model's predictions, helping assess their reliability and confidence. Noise injection is a technique used to enhance the robustness of neural networks by introducing randomness. In this paper, we establish a connection between noise injection and uncertainty quantification from a Bayesian standpoint. We theoretically demonstrate that injecting noise into the weights of a neural network is equivalent to Bayesian inference on a deep Gaussian process. Consequently, we introduce a Monte Carlo Noise Injection (MCNI) method, which involves injecting noise into the parameters during training and performing multiple forward propagations during inference to estimate the uncertainty of the prediction. Through simulation and experiments on regression and classification tasks, our method demonstrates superior performance compared to the baseline model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12314v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xueqiong Yuan, Jipeng Li, Ercan Engin Kuruoglu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal prediction of future insurance claims in the regression problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03659v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the current insurance literature, prediction of insurance claims in the regression problem is often performed with a statistical model. This model-based approach may potentially suffer from several drawbacks: (i) model misspecification, (ii) selection effect, and (iii) lack of finite-sample validity. This article addresses these three issues simultaneously by employing conformal prediction -- a general machine learning strategy for valid predictions. The proposed method is both model-free and tuning-parameter-free. It also guarantees finite-sample validity at a pre-assigned coverage probability level. Examples, based on both simulated and real data, are provided to demonstrate the excellent performance of the proposed method and its applications in insurance, especially regarding meeting the solvency capital requirement of European insurance regulation, Solvency II.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03659v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse Gaussian Neural Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01650v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite significant recent advances in probabilistic meta-learning, it is common for practitioners to avoid using deep learning models due to a comparative lack of interpretability. Instead, many practitioners simply use non-meta-models such as Gaussian processes with interpretable priors, and conduct the tedious procedure of training their model from scratch for each task they encounter. While this is justifiable for tasks with a limited number of data points, the cubic computational cost of exact Gaussian process inference renders this prohibitive when each task has many observations. To remedy this, we introduce a family of models that meta-learn sparse Gaussian process inference. Not only does this enable rapid prediction on new tasks with sparse Gaussian processes, but since our models have clear interpretations as members of the neural process family, it also allows manual elicitation of priors in a neural process for the first time. In meta-learning regimes for which the number of observed tasks is small or for which expert domain knowledge is available, this offers a crucial advantage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01650v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommy Rochussen, Vincent Fortuin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Throughput-Optimal Scheduling Algorithms for LLM Inference and AI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07347v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As demand for Large Language Models (LLMs) and AI agents rapidly grows, optimizing systems for efficient LLM inference becomes critical. While significant efforts have focused on system-level engineering, little is explored from a mathematical modeling and queuing perspective.
  In this paper, we aim to develop the queuing fundamentals for large language model (LLM) inference, bridging the gap between the queueing theory and LLM system communities. In particular, we study the throughput aspect in LLM inference systems. We prove that a large class of 'work-conserving' scheduling algorithms can achieve maximum throughput for individual inference LLM engine, highlighting 'work-conserving' as a key design principle in practice. In a network of LLM agents, work-conserving scheduling alone is insufficient, particularly when facing specific workload structures and multi-class workflows that require more sophisticated scheduling strategies. Evaluations of real-world systems show that Orca and Sarathi-serve are throughput-optimal, reassuring practitioners, while FasterTransformer and vanilla vLLM are not maximally stable and should be used with caution. Our results highlight the substantial benefits that the queueing community can offer in improving LLM inference systems and call for more interdisciplinary development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07347v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueying Li, Jim Dai, Tianyi Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise Error Rates for Computationally Efficient Testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00289v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the fundamental question of simple-versus-simple hypothesis testing with an eye towards computational complexity, as the statistically optimal likelihood ratio test is often computationally intractable in high-dimensional settings. In the classical spiked Wigner model with a general i.i.d. spike prior we show (conditional on a conjecture) that an existing test based on linear spectral statistics achieves the best possible tradeoff curve between type I and type II error rates among all computationally efficient tests, even though there are exponential-time tests that do better. This result is conditional on an appropriate complexity-theoretic conjecture, namely a natural strengthening of the well-established low-degree conjecture. Our result shows that the spectrum is a sufficient statistic for computationally bounded tests (but not for all tests).
  To our knowledge, our approach gives the first tool for reasoning about the precise asymptotic testing error achievable with efficient computation. The main ingredients required for our hardness result are a sharp bound on the norm of the low-degree likelihood ratio along with (counterintuitively) a positive result on achievability of testing. This strategy appears to be new even in the setting of unbounded computation, in which case it gives an alternate way to analyze the fundamental statistical limits of testing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00289v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankur Moitra, Alexander S. Wein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Bayesian Causal Inference via Structural Marginalisation and Autoregressive Orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14781v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The traditional two-stage approach to causal inference first identifies a single causal model (or equivalence class of models), which is then used to answer causal queries. However, this neglects any epistemic model uncertainty. In contrast, Bayesian causal inference does incorporate epistemic uncertainty into query estimates via Bayesian marginalisation (posterior averaging) over all causal models. While principled, this marginalisation over entire causal models, i.e., both causal structures (graphs) and mechanisms, poses a tremendous computational challenge. In this work, we address this challenge by decomposing structure marginalisation into the marginalisation over (i) causal orders and (ii) directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) given an order. We can marginalise the latter in closed form by limiting the number of parents per variable and utilising Gaussian processes to model mechanisms. To marginalise over orders, we use a sampling-based approximation, for which we devise a novel auto-regressive distribution over causal orders (ARCO). Our method outperforms state-of-the-art in structure learning on simulated non-linear additive noise benchmarks, and yields competitive results on real-world data. Furthermore, we can accurately infer interventional distributions and average causal effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14781v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Toth, Christian Knoll, Franz Pernkopf, Robert Peharz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PARMESAN: Parameter-Free Memory Search and Transduction for Dense Prediction Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11743v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work addresses flexibility in deep learning by means of transductive reasoning. For adaptation to new data and tasks, e.g., in continual learning, existing methods typically involve tuning learnable parameters or complete re-training from scratch, rendering such approaches unflexible in practice. We argue that the notion of separating computation from memory by the means of transduction can act as a stepping stone for solving these issues. We therefore propose PARMESAN (parameter-free memory search and transduction), a scalable method which leverages a memory module for solving dense prediction tasks. At inference, hidden representations in memory are being searched to find corresponding patterns. In contrast to other methods that rely on continuous training of learnable parameters, PARMESAN learns via memory consolidation simply by modifying stored contents. Our method is compatible with commonly used architectures and canonically transfers to 1D, 2D, and 3D grid-based data. The capabilities of our approach are demonstrated at the complex task of continual learning. PARMESAN learns by 3-4 orders of magnitude faster than established baselines while being on par in terms of predictive performance, hardware-efficiency, and knowledge retention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11743v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-85181-0_1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>LNCS, volume 15297, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Philip Matthias Winter, Maria Wimmer, David Major, Dimitrios Lenis, Astrid Berg, Theresa Neubauer, Gaia Romana De Paolis, Johannes Novotny, Sophia Ulonska, Katja B\"uhler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Rates for Robust Stochastic Convex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11003v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine learning algorithms in high-dimensional settings are highly susceptible to the influence of even a small fraction of structured outliers, making robust optimization techniques essential. In particular, within the $\epsilon$-contamination model, where an adversary can inspect and replace up to an $\epsilon$-fraction of the samples, a fundamental open problem is determining the optimal rates for robust stochastic convex optimization (SCO) under such contamination. We develop novel algorithms that achieve minimax-optimal excess risk (up to logarithmic factors) under the $\epsilon$-contamination model. Our approach improves over existing algorithms, which are not only suboptimal but also require stringent assumptions, including Lipschitz continuity and smoothness of individual sample functions. By contrast, our optimal algorithms do not require these stringent assumptions, assuming only population-level smoothness of the loss. Moreover, our algorithms can be adapted to handle the case in which the covariance parameter is unknown, and can be extended to nonsmooth population risks via convolutional smoothing. We complement our algorithmic developments with a tight information-theoretic lower bound for robust SCO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11003v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changyu Gao, Andrew Lowy, Xingyu Zhou, Stephen J. Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proofs for Folklore Theorems on the Radon-Nikodym Derivative</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18374v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, rigorous statements and formal proofs are presented for both foundational and advanced folklore theorems on the Radon-Nikodym derivative. The cases of conditional and marginal probability measures are carefully considered, which leads to an identity involving the sum of mutual and lautum information suggesting a new interpretation for such a sum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18374v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaiza Bermudez, Gaetan Bisson, I\~naki Esnaola, Samir M. Perlaza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prediction-Powered Inference with Imputed Covariates and Nonuniform Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18577v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine learning models are increasingly used to produce predictions that serve as input data in subsequent statistical analyses. For example, computer vision predictions of economic and environmental indicators based on satellite imagery are used in downstream regressions; similarly, language models are widely used to approximate human ratings and opinions in social science research. However, failure to properly account for errors in the machine learning predictions renders standard statistical procedures invalid. Prior work uses what we call the Predict-Then-Debias estimator to give valid confidence intervals when machine learning algorithms impute missing variables, assuming a small complete sample from the population of interest. We expand the scope by introducing bootstrap confidence intervals that apply when the complete data is a nonuniform (i.e., weighted, stratified, or clustered) sample and to settings where an arbitrary subset of features is imputed. Importantly, the method can be applied to many settings without requiring additional calculations. We prove that these confidence intervals are valid under no assumptions on the quality of the machine learning model and are no wider than the intervals obtained by methods that do not use machine learning predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18577v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan M. Kluger, Kerri Lu, Tijana Zrnic, Sherrie Wang, Stephen Bates</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attainability of Two-Point Testing Rates for Finite-Sample Location Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05730v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: LeCam's two-point testing method yields perhaps the simplest lower bound for estimating the mean of a distribution: roughly, if it is impossible to well-distinguish a distribution centered at $\mu$ from the same distribution centered at $\mu+\Delta$, then it is impossible to estimate the mean by better than $\Delta/2$. It is setting-dependent whether or not a nearly matching upper bound is attainable. We study the conditions under which the two-point testing lower bound can be attained for univariate mean estimation; both in the setting of location estimation (where the distribution is known up to translation) and adaptive location estimation (unknown distribution). Roughly, we will say an estimate nearly attains the two-point testing lower bound if it incurs error that is at most polylogarithmically larger than the Hellinger modulus of continuity for $\tilde{\Omega}(n)$ samples.
  Adaptive location estimation is particularly interesting as some distributions admit much better guarantees than sub-Gaussian rates (e.g. $\operatorname{Unif}(\mu-1,\mu+1)$ permits error $\Theta(\frac{1}{n})$, while the sub-Gaussian rate is $\Theta(\frac{1}{\sqrt{n}})$), yet it is not obvious whether these rates may be adaptively attained by one unified approach. Our main result designs an algorithm that nearly attains the two-point testing rate for mixtures of symmetric, log-concave distributions with a common mean. Moreover, this algorithm runs in near-linear time and is parameter-free. In contrast, we show the two-point testing rate is not nearly attainable even for symmetric, unimodal distributions.
  We complement this with results for location estimation, showing the two-point testing rate is nearly attainable for unimodal distributions, but unattainable for symmetric distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05730v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spencer Compton, Gregory Valiant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Analysis Prediction over Multiple Unseen Datasets: A Vector Embedding Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17060v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The massive increase in the data volume and dataset availability for analysts compels researchers to focus on data content and select high-quality datasets to enhance the performance of analytics operators. While selecting the highest quality data for analysis highly increases task accuracy and efficiency, it is still a hard task, especially when the number of available inputs is very large. To address this issue, we propose a novel methodology that infers the outcome of analytics operators by creating a model from datasets similar to the queried one. Dataset similarity is performed via projecting each dataset to a vector embedding representation. The vectorization process is performed using our proposed deep learning model NumTabData2Vec, which takes a whole dataset and projects it into a lower vector embedding representation space. Through experimental evaluation, we compare the prediction performance and the execution time of our framework to another state-of-the-art modelling operator framework, illustrating that our approach predicts analytics outcomes accurately. Furthermore, our vectorization model can project different real-world scenarios to a lower vector embedding representation and distinguish between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17060v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Loizou, Dimitrios Tsoumakos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Resampling with Bootstrap for Noisy Multi-Objective Optimization Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21495v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The challenge of noisy multi-objective optimization lies in the constant trade-off between exploring new decision points and improving the precision of known points through resampling. This decision should take into account both the variability of the objective functions and the current estimate of a point in relation to the Pareto front. Since the amount and distribution of noise are generally unknown, it is desirable for a decision function to be highly adaptive to the properties of the optimization problem. This paper presents a resampling decision function that incorporates the stochastic nature of the optimization problem by using bootstrapping and the probability of dominance. The distribution-free estimation of the probability of dominance is achieved using bootstrap estimates of the means. To make the procedure applicable even with very few observations, we transfer the distribution observed at other decision points. The efficiency of this resampling approach is demonstrated by applying it in the NSGA-II algorithm with a sequential resampling procedure under multiple noise variations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21495v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timo Budszuhn, Mark Joachim Krallmann, Daniel Horn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Effective Gram Matrix Characterizes Generalization in Deep Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16450v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive a differential equation that governs the evolution of the generalization gap when a deep network is trained by gradient descent. This differential equation is controlled by two quantities, a contraction factor that brings together trajectories corresponding to slightly different datasets, and a perturbation factor that accounts for them training on different datasets. We analyze this differential equation to compute an ``effective Gram matrix'' that characterizes the generalization gap after training in terms of the alignment between this Gram matrix and a certain initial ``residual''. Empirical evaluations on image classification datasets indicate that this analysis can predict the test loss accurately. Further, at any point during training, the residual predominantly lies in the subspace of the effective Gram matrix with the smallest eigenvalues. This indicates that the training process is benign, i.e., it does not lead to significant deterioration of the generalization gap (which is zero at initialization). The alignment between the effective Gram matrix and the residual is different for different datasets and architectures. The match/mismatch of the data and the architecture is primarily responsible for good/bad generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16450v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rubing Yang, Pratik Chaudhari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyper-Transforming Latent Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16580v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a novel generative framework for functions by integrating Implicit Neural Representations (INRs) and Transformer-based hypernetworks into latent variable models. Unlike prior approaches that rely on MLP-based hypernetworks with scalability limitations, our method employs a Transformer-based decoder to generate INR parameters from latent variables, addressing both representation capacity and computational efficiency. Our framework extends latent diffusion models (LDMs) to INR generation by replacing standard decoders with a Transformer-based hypernetwork, which can be trained either from scratch or via hyper-transforming-a strategy that fine-tunes only the decoder while freezing the pre-trained latent space. This enables efficient adaptation of existing generative models to INR-based representations without requiring full retraining.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16580v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio Peis, Batuhan Koyuncu, Isabel Valera, Jes Frellsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
