<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.ML updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML</link>
    <description>stat.ML updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 04:07:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Framework for Entropy Search and Expected Improvement in Bayesian Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bayesian optimization is a widely used method for optimizing expensive black-box functions, with Expected Improvement being one of the most commonly used acquisition functions. In contrast, information-theoretic acquisition functions aim to reduce uncertainty about the function's optimum and are often considered fundamentally distinct from EI. In this work, we challenge this prevailing perspective by introducing a unified theoretical framework, Variational Entropy Search, which reveals that EI and information-theoretic acquisition functions are more closely related than previously recognized. We demonstrate that EI can be interpreted as a variational inference approximation of the popular information-theoretic acquisition function, named Max-value Entropy Search. Building on this insight, we propose VES-Gamma, a novel acquisition function that balances the strengths of EI and MES. Extensive empirical evaluations across both low- and high-dimensional synthetic and real-world benchmarks demonstrate that VES-Gamma is competitive with state-of-the-art acquisition functions and in many cases outperforms EI and MES.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18756v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuojin Cheng, Leonard Papenmeier, Stephen Becker, Luigi Nardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptivity and Convergence of Probability Flow ODEs in Diffusion Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18863v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Score-based generative models, which transform noise into data by learning to reverse a diffusion process, have become a cornerstone of modern generative AI. This paper contributes to establishing theoretical guarantees for the probability flow ODE, a widely used diffusion-based sampler known for its practical efficiency. While a number of prior works address its general convergence theory, it remains unclear whether the probability flow ODE sampler can adapt to the low-dimensional structures commonly present in natural image data. We demonstrate that, with accurate score function estimation, the probability flow ODE sampler achieves a convergence rate of $O(k/T)$ in total variation distance (ignoring logarithmic factors), where $k$ is the intrinsic dimension of the target distribution and $T$ is the number of iterations. This dimension-free convergence rate improves upon existing results that scale with the typically much larger ambient dimension, highlighting the ability of the probability flow ODE sampler to exploit intrinsic low-dimensional structures in the target distribution for faster sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18863v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqi Tang, Yuling Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trustworthy Evaluation of Generative AI Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18897v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generative AI (GenAI) models have recently achieved remarkable empirical performance in various applications, however, their evaluations yet lack uncertainty quantification. In this paper, we propose a method to compare two generative models based on an unbiased estimator of their relative performance gap. Statistically, our estimator achieves parametric convergence rate and asymptotic normality, which enables valid inference. Computationally, our method is efficient and can be accelerated by parallel computing and leveraging pre-storing intermediate results. On simulated datasets with known ground truth, we show our approach effectively controls type I error and achieves power comparable with commonly used metrics. Furthermore, we demonstrate the performance of our method in evaluating diffusion models on real image datasets with statistical confidence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18897v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijun Gao, Yan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Through Change: Bounds and Recommendations for Time-Varying Bayesian Optimization Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time-Varying Bayesian Optimization (TVBO) is the go-to framework for optimizing a time-varying, expensive, noisy black-box function. However, most of the solutions proposed so far either rely on unrealistic assumptions on the nature of the objective function or do not offer any theoretical guarantees. We propose the first analysis that asymptotically bounds the cumulative regret of TVBO algorithms under mild and realistic assumptions only. In particular, we provide an algorithm-independent lower regret bound and an upper regret bound that holds for a large class of TVBO algorithms. Based on this analysis, we formulate recommendations for TVBO algorithms and show how an algorithm (BOLT) that follows them performs better than the state-of-the-art of TVBO through experiments on synthetic and real-world problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18963v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony Bardou, Patrick Thiran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Transport-based Conformal Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conformal Prediction (CP) is a principled framework for quantifying uncertainty in blackbox learning models, by constructing prediction sets with finite-sample coverage guarantees. Traditional approaches rely on scalar nonconformity scores, which fail to fully exploit the geometric structure of multivariate outputs, such as in multi-output regression or multiclass classification. Recent methods addressing this limitation impose predefined convex shapes for the prediction sets, potentially misaligning with the intrinsic data geometry. We introduce a novel CP procedure handling multivariate score functions through the lens of optimal transport. Specifically, we leverage Monge-Kantorovich vector ranks and quantiles to construct prediction region with flexible, potentially non-convex shapes, better suited to the complex uncertainty patterns encountered in multivariate learning tasks. We prove that our approach ensures finite-sample, distribution-free coverage properties, similar to typical CP methods. We then adapt our method for multi-output regression and multiclass classification, and also propose simple adjustments to generate adaptive prediction regions with asymptotic conditional coverage guarantees. Finally, we evaluate our method on practical regression and classification problems, illustrating its advantages in terms of (conditional) coverage and efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18991v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gauthier Thurin (CNRS), Kimia Nadjahi (CNRS), Claire Boyer (LMO)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Prediction in Hierarchical Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19038v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conformal prediction has emerged as a widely used framework for constructing valid prediction sets in classification and regression tasks. In this work, we extend the split conformal prediction framework to hierarchical classification, where prediction sets are commonly restricted to internal nodes of a predefined hierarchy, and propose two computationally efficient inference algorithms. The first algorithm returns internal nodes as prediction sets, while the second relaxes this restriction, using the notion of representation complexity, yielding a more general and combinatorial inference problem, but smaller set sizes. Empirical evaluations on several benchmark datasets demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed algorithms in achieving nominal coverage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19038v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Mortier, Alireza Javanmardi, Yusuf Sale, Eyke H\"ullermeier, Willem Waegeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning While Repositioning in On-Demand Vehicle Sharing Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a network inventory problem motivated by one-way, on-demand vehicle sharing services. Due to uncertainties in both demand and returns, as well as a fixed number of rental units across an $n$-location network, the service provider must periodically reposition vehicles to match supply with demand spatially while minimizing costs. The optimal repositioning policy under a general $n$-location network is intractable without knowing the optimal value function. We introduce the best base-stock repositioning policy as a generalization of the classical inventory control policy to $n$ dimensions, and establish its asymptotic optimality in two distinct limiting regimes under general network structures. We present reformulations to efficiently compute this best base-stock policy in an offline setting with pre-collected data.
  In the online setting, we show that a natural Lipschitz-bandit approach achieves a regret guarantee of $\widetilde{O}(T^{\frac{n}{n+1}})$, which suffers from the exponential dependence on $n$. We illustrate the challenges of learning with censored data in networked systems through a regret lower bound analysis and by demonstrating the suboptimality of alternative algorithmic approaches. Motivated by these challenges, we propose an Online Gradient Repositioning algorithm that relies solely on censored demand. Under a mild cost-structure assumption, we prove that it attains an optimal regret of $O(n^{2.5} \sqrt{T})$, which matches the regret lower bound in $T$ and achieves only polynomial dependence on $n$. The key algorithmic innovation involves proposing surrogate costs to disentangle intertemporal dependencies and leveraging dual solutions to find the gradient of policy change. Numerical experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19208v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hansheng Jiang, Chunlin Sun, Zuo-Jun Max Shen, Shunan Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Pareto Optimality for the Multinomial Logistic Bandit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a new online learning algorithm for tackling the Multinomial Logit Bandit (MNL-Bandit) problem. Despite the challenges posed by the combinatorial nature of the MNL model, we develop a novel Upper Confidence Bound (UCB)-based method that achieves Pareto optimality by balancing regret minimization and estimation error of the assortment revenues and the MNL parameters. We develop theoretical guarantees characterizing the tradeoff between regret and estimation error for the MNL-Bandit problem through information-theoretic bounds, and propose a modified UCB algorithm that incorporates forced exploration to improve parameter estimation accuracy while maintaining low regret. Our analysis sheds critical insights into how to optimally balance the collected revenues and the treatment estimation in dynamic assortment optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19277v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jierui Zuo, Hanzhang Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is causal about causal models and representations?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19335v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Causal Bayesian networks are 'causal' models since they make predictions about interventional distributions. To connect such causal model predictions to real-world outcomes, we must determine which actions in the world correspond to which interventions in the model. For example, to interpret an action as an intervention on a treatment variable, the action will presumably have to a) change the distribution of treatment in a way that corresponds to the intervention, and b) not change other aspects, such as how the outcome depends on the treatment; while the marginal distributions of some variables may change as an effect. We introduce a formal framework to make such requirements for different interpretations of actions as interventions precise. We prove that the seemingly natural interpretation of actions as interventions is circular: Under this interpretation, every causal Bayesian network that correctly models the observational distribution is trivially also interventionally valid, and no action yields empirical data that could possibly falsify such a model. We prove an impossibility result: No interpretation exists that is non-circular and simultaneously satisfies a set of natural desiderata. Instead, we examine non-circular interpretations that may violate some desiderata and show how this may in turn enable the falsification of causal models. By rigorously examining how a causal Bayesian network could be a 'causal' model of the world instead of merely a mathematical object, our formal framework contributes to the conceptual foundations of causal representation learning, causal discovery, and causal abstraction, while also highlighting some limitations of existing approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19335v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frederik Hytting J{\o}rgensen, Luigi Gresele, Sebastian Weichwald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Fixed Horizons: A Theoretical Framework for Adaptive Denoising Diffusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new class of generative diffusion models that, unlike conventional denoising diffusion models, achieve a time-homogeneous structure for both the noising and denoising processes, allowing the number of steps to adaptively adjust based on the noise level. This is accomplished by conditioning the forward process using Doob's $h$-transform, which terminates the process at a suitable sampling distribution at a random time. The model is particularly well suited for generating data with lower intrinsic dimensions, as the termination criterion simplifies to a first-hitting rule. A key feature of the model is its adaptability to the target data, enabling a variety of downstream tasks using a pre-trained unconditional generative model. These tasks include natural conditioning through appropriate initialization of the denoising process and classification of noisy data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19373v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S\"oren Christensen, Claudia Strauch, Lukas Trottner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster Convergence of Riemannian Stochastic Gradient Descent with Increasing Batch Size</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many models used in machine learning have become so large that even computer computation of the full gradient of the loss function is impractical. This has made it necessary to efficiently train models using limited available information, such as batch size and learning rate. We have theoretically analyzed the use of Riemannian stochastic gradient descent (RSGD) and found that using an increasing batch size leads to faster RSGD convergence than using a constant batch size not only with a constant learning rate but also with a decaying learning rate, such as cosine annealing decay and polynomial decay. In particular, RSGD has a better convergence rate $O(\frac{1}{\sqrt{T}})$ than the existing rate $O(\frac{\sqrt{\log T}}{\sqrt[4]{T}})$ with a diminishing learning rate, where $T$ is the number of iterations. The results of experiments on principal component analysis and low-rank matrix completion problems confirmed that, except for the MovieLens dataset and a constant learning rate, using a polynomial growth batch size or an exponential growth batch size results in better performance than using a constant batch size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18164v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kanata Oowada, Hideaki Iiduka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing Cell-type Taxonomy by Optimal Transport with Relaxed Marginal Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18650v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid emergence of single-cell data has facilitated the study of many different biological conditions at the cellular level. Cluster analysis has been widely applied to identify cell types, capturing the essential patterns of the original data in a much more concise form. One challenge in the cluster analysis of cells is matching clusters extracted from datasets of different origins or conditions. Many existing algorithms cannot recognize new cell types present in only one of the two samples when establishing a correspondence between clusters obtained from two samples. Additionally, when there are more than two samples, it is advantageous to align clusters across all samples simultaneously rather than performing pairwise alignment. Our approach aims to construct a taxonomy for cell clusters across all samples to better annotate these clusters and effectively extract features for downstream analysis. A new system for constructing cell-type taxonomy has been developed by combining the technique of Optimal Transport with Relaxed Marginal Constraints (OT-RMC) and the simultaneous alignment of clusters across multiple samples. OT-RMC allows us to address challenges that arise when the proportions of clusters vary substantially between samples or when some clusters do not appear in all the samples. Experiments on more than twenty datasets demonstrate that the taxonomy constructed by this new system can yield highly accurate annotation of cell types. Additionally, sample-level features extracted based on the taxonomy result in accurate classification of samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18650v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Pena, Lin Lin, Jia Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Data Generation for Augmenting Small Samples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18741v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Small datasets are common in health research. However, the generalization performance of machine learning models is suboptimal when the training datasets are small. To address this, data augmentation is one solution. Augmentation increases sample size and is seen as a form of regularization that increases the diversity of small datasets, leading them to perform better on unseen data. We found that augmentation improves prognostic performance for datasets that: have fewer observations, with smaller baseline AUC, have higher cardinality categorical variables, and have more balanced outcome variables. No specific generative model consistently outperformed the others. We developed a decision support model that can be used to inform analysts if augmentation would be useful. For seven small application datasets, augmenting the existing data results in an increase in AUC between 4.31% (AUC from 0.71 to 0.75) and 43.23% (AUC from 0.51 to 0.73), with an average 15.55% relative improvement, demonstrating the nontrivial impact of augmentation on small datasets (p=0.0078). Augmentation AUC was higher than resampling only AUC (p=0.016). The diversity of augmented datasets was higher than the diversity of resampled datasets (p=0.046).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18741v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Liu, Samer El Kababji, Nicholas Mitsakakis, Lisa Pilgram, Thomas Walters, Mark Clemons, Greg Pond, Alaa El-Hussuna, Khaled El Emam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(\sqrt{T})$ Regret in Average-Reward POMDPs with Known Observation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18790v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We tackle average-reward infinite-horizon POMDPs with an unknown transition model but a known observation model, a setting that has been previously addressed in two limiting ways: (i) frequentist methods relying on suboptimal stochastic policies having a minimum probability of choosing each action, and (ii) Bayesian approaches employing the optimal policy class but requiring strong assumptions about the consistency of employed estimators. Our work removes these limitations by proving convenient estimation guarantees for the transition model and introducing an optimistic algorithm that leverages the optimal class of deterministic belief-based policies. We introduce modifications to existing estimation techniques providing theoretical guarantees separately for each estimated action transition matrix. Unlike existing estimation methods that are unable to use samples from different policies, we present a novel and simple estimator that overcomes this barrier. This new data-efficient technique, combined with the proposed \emph{Action-wise OAS-UCRL} algorithm and a tighter theoretical analysis, leads to the first approach enjoying a regret guarantee of order $\mathcal{O}(\sqrt{T \,\log T})$ when compared against the optimal policy, thus improving over state of the art techniques. Finally, theoretical results are validated through numerical simulations showing the efficacy of our method against baseline methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18790v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Russo, Alberto Maria Metelli, Marcello Restelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Optimization with Preference Exploration by Monotonic Neural Network Ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18792v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many real-world black-box optimization problems have multiple conflicting objectives. Rather than attempting to approximate the entire set of Pareto-optimal solutions, interactive preference learning allows to focus the search on the most relevant subset. However, few previous studies have exploited the fact that utility functions are usually monotonic. In this paper, we address the Bayesian Optimization with Preference Exploration (BOPE) problem and propose using a neural network ensemble as a utility surrogate model. This approach naturally integrates monotonicity and supports pairwise comparison data. Our experiments demonstrate that the proposed method outperforms state-of-the-art approaches and exhibits robustness to noise in utility evaluations. An ablation study highlights the critical role of monotonicity in enhancing performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18792v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanyang Wang, Juergen Branke, Matthias Poloczek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compositional Generalization Requires More Than Disentangled Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18797v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Composition-the ability to generate myriad variations from finite means-is believed to underlie powerful generalization. However, compositional generalization remains a key challenge for deep learning. A widely held assumption is that learning disentangled (factorized) representations naturally supports this kind of extrapolation. Yet, empirical results are mixed, with many generative models failing to recognize and compose factors to generate out-of-distribution (OOD) samples. In this work, we investigate a controlled 2D Gaussian "bump" generation task, demonstrating that standard generative architectures fail in OOD regions when training with partial data, even when supplied with fully disentangled $(x, y)$ coordinates, re-entangling them through subsequent layers. By examining the model's learned kernels and manifold geometry, we show that this failure reflects a "memorization" strategy for generation through the superposition of training data rather than by combining the true factorized features. We show that models forced-through architectural modifications with regularization or curated training data-to create disentangled representations in the full-dimensional representational (pixel) space can be highly data-efficient and effective at learning to compose in OOD regions. These findings underscore that bottlenecks with factorized/disentangled representations in an abstract representation are insufficient: the model must actively maintain or induce factorization directly in the representational space in order to achieve robust compositional generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18797v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiyao Liang, Daoyuan Qian, Liu Ziyin, Ila Fiete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural SDEs as a Unified Approach to Continuous-Domain Sequence Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the ubiquitous use of differential equations to model continuous dynamics across diverse scientific and engineering domains, we propose a novel and intuitive approach to continuous sequence modeling. Our method interprets time-series data as \textit{discrete samples from an underlying continuous dynamical system}, and models its time evolution using Neural Stochastic Differential Equation (Neural SDE), where both the flow (drift) and diffusion terms are parameterized by neural networks. We derive a principled maximum likelihood objective and a \textit{simulation-free} scheme for efficient training of our Neural SDE model. We demonstrate the versatility of our approach through experiments on sequence modeling tasks across both embodied and generative AI. Notably, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to show that SDE-based continuous-time modeling also excels in such complex scenarios, and we hope that our work opens up new avenues for research of SDE models in high-dimensional and temporally intricate domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18871v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Macheng Shen, Chen Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Supervised Learning Using Nonlinear Dependence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18875v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Self-supervised learning has gained significant attention in contemporary applications, particularly due to the scarcity of labeled data. While existing SSL methodologies primarily address feature variance and linear correlations, they often neglect the intricate relations between samples and the nonlinear dependencies inherent in complex data. In this paper, we introduce Correlation-Dependence Self-Supervised Learning (CDSSL), a novel framework that unifies and extends existing SSL paradigms by integrating both linear correlations and nonlinear dependencies, encapsulating sample-wise and feature-wise interactions. Our approach incorporates the Hilbert-Schmidt Independence Criterion (HSIC) to robustly capture nonlinear dependencies within a Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Space, enriching representation learning. Experimental evaluations on diverse benchmarks demonstrate the efficacy of CDSSL in improving representation quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18875v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Hadi Sepanj, Benyamin Ghojogh, Paul Fieguth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Generalization in Physics Informed Models through Affine Variety Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18879v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, physics-informed machine learning has gained significant attention for its ability to enhance statistical performance and sample efficiency by integrating physical structures into machine learning models. These structures, such as differential equations, conservation laws, and symmetries, serve as inductive biases that can improve the generalization capacity of the hybrid model. However, the mechanisms by which these physical structures enhance generalization capacity are not fully understood, limiting the ability to guarantee the performance of the models. In this study, we show that the generalization performance of linear regressors incorporating differential equation structures is determined by the dimension of the associated affine variety, rather than the number of parameters. This finding enables a unified analysis of various equations, including nonlinear ones. We introduce a method to approximate the dimension of the affine variety and provide experimental evidence to validate our theoretical insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18879v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeshi Koshizuka, Issei Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lightspeed Geometric Dataset Distance via Sliced Optimal Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18901v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce sliced optimal transport dataset distance (s-OTDD), a model-agnostic, embedding-agnostic approach for dataset comparison that requires no training, is robust to variations in the number of classes, and can handle disjoint label sets. The core innovation is Moment Transform Projection (MTP), which maps a label, represented as a distribution over features, to a real number. Using MTP, we derive a data point projection that transforms datasets into one-dimensional distributions. The s-OTDD is defined as the expected Wasserstein distance between the projected distributions, with respect to random projection parameters. Leveraging the closed form solution of one-dimensional optimal transport, s-OTDD achieves (near-)linear computational complexity in the number of data points and feature dimensions and is independent of the number of classes. With its geometrically meaningful projection, s-OTDD strongly correlates with the optimal transport dataset distance while being more efficient than existing dataset discrepancy measures. Moreover, it correlates well with the performance gap in transfer learning and classification accuracy in data augmentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18901v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khai Nguyen, Hai Nguyen, Tuan Pham, Nhat Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Surprising Agreement Between Convex Optimization Theory and Learning-Rate Scheduling for Large Model Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that learning-rate schedules for large model training behave surprisingly similar to a performance bound from non-smooth convex optimization theory. We provide a bound for the constant schedule with linear cooldown; in particular, the practical benefit of cooldown is reflected in the bound due to the absence of logarithmic terms. Further, we show that this surprisingly close match between optimization theory and practice can be exploited for learning-rate tuning: we achieve noticeable improvements for training 124M and 210M Llama-type models by (i) extending the schedule for continued training with optimal learning-rate, and (ii) transferring the optimal learning-rate across schedules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18965v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Schaipp, Alexander H\"agele, Adrien Taylor, Umut Simsekli, Francis Bach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-learning of shared linear representations beyond well-specified linear regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18975v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by multi-task and meta-learning approaches, we consider the problem of learning structure shared by tasks or users, such as shared low-rank representations or clustered structures. While all previous works focus on well-specified linear regression, we consider more general convex objectives, where the structural low-rank and cluster assumptions are expressed on the optima of each function. We show that under mild assumptions such as \textit{Hessian concentration} and \textit{noise concentration at the optimum}, rank and clustered regularized estimators recover such structure, provided the number of samples per task and the number of tasks are large enough. We then study the problem of recovering the subspace in which all the solutions lie, in the setting where there is only a single sample per task: we show that in that case, the rank-constrained estimator can recover the subspace, but that the number of tasks needs to scale exponentially large with the dimension of the subspace. Finally, we provide a polynomial-time algorithm via nuclear norm constraints for learning a shared linear representation in the context of convex learning objectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18975v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Even, Laurent Massouli\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Model Calibration -- A gentle introduction and visual exploration of calibration and the expected calibration error (ECE)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19047v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To be considered reliable, a model must be calibrated so that its confidence in each decision closely reflects its true outcome. In this blogpost we'll take a look at the most commonly used definition for calibration and then dive into a frequently used evaluation measure for model calibration. We'll then cover some of the drawbacks of this measure and how these surfaced the need for additional notions of calibration, which require their own new evaluation measures. This post is not intended to be an in-depth dissection of all works on calibration, nor does it focus on how to calibrate models. Instead, it is meant to provide a gentle introduction to the different notions and their evaluation measures as well as to re-highlight some issues with a measure that is still widely used to evaluate calibration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19047v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maja Pavlovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Multi-Task Learning Has Low Amortized Intrinsic Dimensionality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19067v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep learning methods are known to generalize well from training to future data, even in an overparametrized regime, where they could easily overfit. One explanation for this phenomenon is that even when their *ambient dimensionality*, (i.e. the number of parameters) is large, the models' *intrinsic dimensionality* is small, i.e. their learning takes place in a small subspace of all possible weight configurations.
  In this work, we confirm this phenomenon in the setting of *deep multi-task learning*. We introduce a method to parametrize multi-task network directly in the low-dimensional space, facilitated by the use of *random expansions* techniques. We then show that high-accuracy multi-task solutions can be found with much smaller intrinsic dimensionality (fewer free parameters) than what single-task learning requires. Subsequently, we show that the low-dimensional representations in combination with *weight compression* and *PAC-Bayesian* reasoning lead to the first *non-vacuous generalization bounds* for deep multi-task networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19067v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Zakerinia, Dorsa Ghobadi, Christoph H. Lampert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pareto-frontier Entropy Search with Variational Lower Bound Maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19073v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study considers multi-objective Bayesian optimization (MOBO) through the information gain of the Pareto-frontier. To calculate the information gain, a predictive distribution conditioned on the Pareto-frontier plays a key role, which is defined as a distribution truncated by the Pareto-frontier. However, it is usually impossible to obtain the entire Pareto-frontier in a continuous domain, and therefore, the complete truncation cannot be known. We consider an approximation of the truncate distribution by using a mixture distribution consisting of two possible approximate truncation obtainable from a subset of the Pareto-frontier, which we call over- and under-truncation. Since the optimal balance of the mixture is unknown beforehand, we propose optimizing the balancing coefficient through the variational lower bound maximization framework, by which the approximation error of the information gain can be minimized. Our empirical evaluation demonstrates the effectiveness of the proposed method particularly when the number of objective functions is large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19073v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masanori Ishikura, Masayuki Karasuyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bias-Correction Decentralized Stochastic Gradient Algorithm with Momentum Acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Distributed stochastic optimization algorithms can handle large-scale data simultaneously and accelerate model training. However, the sparsity of distributed networks and the heterogeneity of data limit these advantages. This paper proposes a momentum-accelerated distributed stochastic gradient algorithm, referred to as Exact-Diffusion with Momentum (EDM), which can correct the bias caused by data heterogeneity and introduces the momentum method commonly used in deep learning to accelerate the convergence of the algorithm. We theoretically demonstrate that this algorithm converges to the neighborhood of the optimum sub-linearly irrelevant to data heterogeneity when applied to non-convex objective functions and linearly under the Polyak-{\L}ojasiewicz condition (a weaker assumption than $\mu$-strongly convexity). Finally, we evaluate the performance of the proposed algorithm by simulation, comparing it with a range of existing decentralized optimization algorithms to demonstrate its effectiveness in addressing data heterogeneity and network sparsity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19082v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Hu, Xi Chen, Weidong Liu, Xiaojun Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Theoretical Justification for Asymmetric Actor-Critic Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19116v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In reinforcement learning for partially observable environments, many successful algorithms were developed within the asymmetric learning paradigm. This paradigm leverages additional state information available at training time for faster learning. Although the proposed learning objectives are usually theoretically sound, these methods still lack a theoretical justification for their potential benefits. We propose such a justification for asymmetric actor-critic algorithms with linear function approximators by adapting a finite-time convergence analysis to this setting. The resulting finite-time bound reveals that the asymmetric critic eliminates an error term arising from aliasing in the agent state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19116v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaspard Lambrechts, Damien Ernst, Aditya Mahajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the inductive bias of infinite-depth ResNets and the bottleneck rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19149v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We compute the minimum-norm weights of a deep linear ResNet, and find that the inductive bias of this architecture lies between minimizing nuclear norm and rank. This implies that, with appropriate hyperparameters, deep nonlinear ResNets have an inductive bias towards minimizing bottleneck rank.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19149v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enric Boix-Adsera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-agent Multi-armed Bandit with Fully Heavy-tailed Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19239v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study decentralized multi-agent multi-armed bandits in fully heavy-tailed settings, where clients communicate over sparse random graphs with heavy-tailed degree distributions and observe heavy-tailed (homogeneous or heterogeneous) reward distributions with potentially infinite variance. The objective is to maximize system performance by pulling the globally optimal arm with the highest global reward mean across all clients. We are the first to address such fully heavy-tailed scenarios, which capture the dynamics and challenges in communication and inference among multiple clients in real-world systems. In homogeneous settings, our algorithmic framework exploits hub-like structures unique to heavy-tailed graphs, allowing clients to aggregate rewards and reduce noises via hub estimators when constructing UCB indices; under $M$ clients and degree distributions with power-law index $\alpha &gt; 1$, our algorithm attains a regret bound (almost) of order $O(M^{1 -\frac{1}{\alpha}} \log{T})$. Under heterogeneous rewards, clients synchronize by communicating with neighbors, aggregating exchanged estimators in UCB indices; With our newly established information delay bounds on sparse random graphs, we prove a regret bound of $O(M \log{T})$. Our results improve upon existing work, which only address time-invariant connected graphs, or light-tailed dynamics in dense graphs and rewards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19239v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Wang, Mengfan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear $Q$-Learning Does Not Diverge: Convergence Rates to a Bounded Set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19254v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: $Q$-learning is one of the most fundamental reinforcement learning algorithms. Previously, it is widely believed that $Q$-learning with linear function approximation (i.e., linear $Q$-learning) suffers from possible divergence. This paper instead establishes the first $L^2$ convergence rate of linear $Q$-learning to a bounded set. Notably, we do not make any modification to the original linear $Q$-learning algorithm, do not make any Bellman completeness assumption, and do not make any near-optimality assumption on the behavior policy. All we need is an $\epsilon$-softmax behavior policy with an adaptive temperature. The key to our analysis is the general result of stochastic approximations under Markovian noise with fast-changing transition functions. As a side product, we also use this general result to establish the $L^2$ convergence rate of tabular $Q$-learning with an $\epsilon$-softmax behavior policy, for which we rely on a novel pseudo-contraction property of the weighted Bellman optimality operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19254v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Liu, Zixuan Xie, Shangtong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Value of Prediction in Identifying the Worst-Off</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19334v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine learning is increasingly used in government programs to identify and support the most vulnerable individuals, prioritizing assistance for those at greatest risk over optimizing aggregate outcomes. This paper examines the welfare impacts of prediction in equity-driven contexts, and how they compare to other policy levers, such as expanding bureaucratic capacity. Through mathematical models and a real-world case study on long-term unemployment amongst German residents, we develop a comprehensive understanding of the relative effectiveness of prediction in surfacing the worst-off. Our findings provide clear analytical frameworks and practical, data-driven tools that empower policymakers to make principled decisions when designing these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19334v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Unai Fischer-Abaigar, Christoph Kern, Juan Carlos Perdomo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PUATE: Semiparametric Efficient Average Treatment Effect Estimation from Treated (Positive) and Unlabeled Units</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19345v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The estimation of average treatment effects (ATEs), defined as the difference in expected outcomes between treatment and control groups, is a central topic in causal inference. This study develops semiparametric efficient estimators for ATE estimation in a setting where only a treatment group and an unknown group-comprising units for which it is unclear whether they received the treatment or control-are observable. This scenario represents a variant of learning from positive and unlabeled data (PU learning) and can be regarded as a special case of ATE estimation with missing data. For this setting, we derive semiparametric efficiency bounds, which provide lower bounds on the asymptotic variance of regular estimators. We then propose semiparametric efficient ATE estimators whose asymptotic variance aligns with these efficiency bounds. Our findings contribute to causal inference with missing data and weakly supervised learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19345v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Kato, Fumiaki Kozai, Ryo Inokuchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding-based Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Language models have recently been shown capable of performing regression tasks wherein numeric predictions are represented as decoded strings. In this work, we provide theoretical grounds for this capability and furthermore investigate the utility of causal auto-regressive sequence models when they are applied to any feature representation. We find that, despite being trained in the usual way - for next-token prediction via cross-entropy loss - decoding-based regression is as performant as traditional approaches for tabular regression tasks, while being flexible enough to capture arbitrary distributions, such as in the task of density estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19383v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyou Song, Dara Bahri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection Is All You Need: A Feasible Optimal Prior-Free Black-Box Approach For Piecewise Stationary Bandits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the problem of piecewise stationary bandits without prior knowledge of the underlying non-stationarity. We propose the first $\textit{feasible}$ black-box algorithm applicable to most common parametric bandit variants. Our procedure, termed Detection Augmented Bandit (DAB), is modular, accepting any stationary bandit algorithm as input and augmenting it with a change detector. DAB achieves optimal regret in the piecewise stationary setting under mild assumptions. Specifically, we prove that DAB attains the order-optimal regret bound of $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(\sqrt{N_T T})$, where $N_T$ denotes the number of changes over the horizon $T$, if its input stationary bandit algorithm has order-optimal stationary regret guarantees. Applying DAB to different parametric bandit settings, we recover recent state-of-the-art results. Notably, for self-concordant bandits, DAB achieves optimal dynamic regret, while previous works obtain suboptimal bounds and require knowledge on the non-stationarity. In simulations on piecewise stationary environments, DAB outperforms existing approaches across varying number of changes. Interestingly, despite being theoretically designed for piecewise stationary environments, DAB is also effective in simulations in drifting environments, outperforming existing methods designed specifically for this scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19401v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Argyrios Gerogiannis, Yu-Han Huang, Subhonmesh Bose, Venugopal V. Veeravalli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Significance of Feature Importance Rankings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15800v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Feature importance scores are ubiquitous tools for understanding the predictions of machine learning models. However, many popular attribution methods suffer from high instability due to random sampling. Leveraging novel ideas from hypothesis testing, we devise techniques that ensure the most important features are correct with high-probability guarantees. These assess the set of $K$ top-ranked features, as well as the order of its elements. Given a set of local or global importance scores, we demonstrate how to retrospectively verify the stability of the highest ranks. We then introduce two efficient sampling algorithms that identify the $K$ most important features, perhaps in order, with probability exceeding $1-\alpha$. The theoretical justification for these procedures is validated empirically on SHAP and LIME.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15800v4</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy Goldwasser, Giles Hooker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regression Trees Know Calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13846v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Regression trees have emerged as a preeminent tool for solving real-world regression problems due to their ability to deal with nonlinearities, interaction effects and sharp discontinuities. In this article, we rather study regression trees applied to well-behaved, differentiable functions, and determine the relationship between node parameters and the local gradient of the function being approximated. We find a simple estimate of the gradient which can be efficiently computed using quantities exposed by popular tree learning libraries. This allows the tools developed in the context of differentiable algorithms, like neural nets and Gaussian processes, to be deployed to tree-based models. To demonstrate this, we study measures of model sensitivity defined in terms of integrals of gradients and demonstrate how to compute them for regression trees using the proposed gradient estimates. Quantitative and qualitative numerical experiments reveal the capability of gradients estimated by regression trees to improve predictive analysis, solve tasks in uncertainty quantification, and provide interpretation of model behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13846v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Wycoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Learn-then-Test: Statistically Valid and Efficient Hyperparameter Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15844v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce adaptive learn-then-test (aLTT), an efficient hyperparameter selection procedure that provides finite-sample statistical guarantees on the population risk of AI models. Unlike the existing learn-then-test (LTT) technique, which relies on conventional p-value-based multiple hypothesis testing (MHT), aLTT implements sequential data-dependent MHT with early termination by leveraging e-processes. As a result, aLTT can reduce the number of testing rounds, making it particularly well-suited for scenarios in which testing is costly or presents safety risks. Apart from maintaining statistical validity, in applications such as online policy selection for offline reinforcement learning and prompt engineering, aLTT is shown to achieve the same performance as LTT while requiring only a fraction of the testing rounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15844v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Zecchin, Sangwoo Park, Osvaldo Simeone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MVG-CRPS: A Robust Loss Function for Multivariate Probabilistic Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09133v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multivariate Gaussian (MVG) distributions are central to modeling correlated continuous variables in probabilistic forecasting. Neural forecasting models typically parameterize the mean vector and covariance matrix of the distribution using neural networks, optimizing with the log-score (negative log-likelihood) as the loss function. However, the sensitivity of the log-score to outliers can lead to significant errors in the presence of anomalies. Drawing on the continuous ranked probability score (CRPS) for univariate distributions, we propose MVG-CRPS, a strictly proper scoring rule for MVG distributions. MVG-CRPS admits a closed-form expression in terms of neural network outputs, thereby integrating seamlessly into deep learning frameworks. Experiments on real-world datasets across multivariate autoregressive and univariate sequence-to-sequence (Seq2Seq) forecasting tasks show that MVG-CRPS improves robustness, accuracy, and uncertainty quantification in probabilistic forecasting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09133v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Zhihao Zheng, Lijun Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Dynamics of Alternating Minimization for Bilinear Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04751v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the dynamics of alternating minimization applied to a bilinear regression task with normally distributed covariates, under the asymptotic system size limit where the number of parameters and observations diverge at the same rate. This is achieved by employing the replica method to a multi-temperature glassy system which unfolds the algorithm's time evolution. Our results show that the dynamics can be described effectively by a two-dimensional discrete stochastic process, where each step depends on all previous time steps, revealing the structure of the memory dependence in the evolution of alternating minimization. The theoretical framework developed in this work can be applied to the analysis of various iterative algorithms, extending beyond the scope of alternating minimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04751v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koki Okajima, Takashi Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Universality Theorem for Deep and Shallow Joint-Group-Equivariant Machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13682v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a constructive universal approximation theorem for learning machines equipped with joint-group-equivariant feature maps, called the joint-equivariant machines, based on the group representation theory. "Constructive" here indicates that the distribution of parameters is given in a closed-form expression known as the ridgelet transform. Joint-group-equivariance encompasses a broad class of feature maps that generalize classical group-equivariance. Particularly, fully-connected networks are not group-equivariant but are joint-group-equivariant. Our main theorem also unifies the universal approximation theorems for both shallow and deep networks. Until this study, the universality of deep networks has been shown in a different manner from the universality of shallow networks, but our results discuss them on common ground. Now we can understand the approximation schemes of various learning machines in a unified manner. As applications, we show the constructive universal approximation properties of four examples: depth-$n$ joint-equivariant machine, depth-$n$ fully-connected network, depth-$n$ group-convolutional network, and a new depth-$2$ network with quadratic forms whose universality has not been known.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13682v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sho Sonoda, Yuka Hashimoto, Isao Ishikawa, Masahiro Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linearization Turns Neural Operators into Function-Valued Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05072v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural operators generalize neural networks to learn mappings between function spaces from data. They are commonly used to learn solution operators of parametric partial differential equations (PDEs) or propagators of time-dependent PDEs. However, to make them useful in high-stakes simulation scenarios, their inherent predictive error must be quantified reliably. We introduce LUNO, a novel framework for approximate Bayesian uncertainty quantification in trained neural operators. Our approach leverages model linearization to push (Gaussian) weight-space uncertainty forward to the neural operator's predictions. We show that this can be interpreted as a probabilistic version of the concept of currying from functional programming, yielding a function-valued (Gaussian) random process belief. Our framework provides a practical yet theoretically sound way to apply existing Bayesian deep learning methods such as the linearized Laplace approximation to neural operators. Just as the underlying neural operator, our approach is resolution-agnostic by design. The method adds minimal prediction overhead, can be applied post-hoc without retraining the network, and scales to large models and datasets. We evaluate these aspects in a case study on Fourier neural operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05072v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emilia Magnani, Marvin Pf\"ortner, Tobias Weber, Philipp Hennig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contraction of Private Quantum Channels and Private Quantum Hypothesis Testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18651v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A quantum generalized divergence by definition satisfies the data-processing inequality; as such, the relative decrease in such a divergence under the action of a quantum channel is at most one. This relative decrease is formally known as the contraction coefficient of the channel and the divergence. Interestingly, there exist combinations of channels and divergences for which the contraction coefficient is strictly less than one. Furthermore, understanding the contraction coefficient is fundamental for the study of statistical tasks under privacy constraints. To this end, here we establish upper bounds on contraction coefficients for the hockey-stick divergence under privacy constraints, where privacy is quantified with respect to the quantum local differential privacy (QLDP) framework, and we fully characterize the contraction coefficient for the trace distance under privacy constraints. With the machinery developed, we also determine an upper bound on the contraction of both the Bures distance and quantum relative entropy relative to the normalized trace distance, under QLDP constraints. Next, we apply our findings to establish bounds on the sample complexity of quantum hypothesis testing under privacy constraints. Furthermore, we study various scenarios in which the sample complexity bounds are tight, while providing order-optimal quantum channels that achieve those bounds. Lastly, we show how private quantum channels provide fairness and Holevo information stability in quantum learning settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18651v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIT.2025.3527859</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Theshani Nuradha, Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse decision-making using neural amortized Bayesian actors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03710v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bayesian observer and actor models have provided normative explanations for many behavioral phenomena in perception, sensorimotor control, and other areas of cognitive science and neuroscience. They attribute behavioral variability and biases to interpretable entities such as perceptual and motor uncertainty, prior beliefs, and behavioral costs. However, when extending these models to more naturalistic tasks with continuous actions, solving the Bayesian decision-making problem is often analytically intractable. Inverse decision-making, i.e. performing inference over the parameters of such models given behavioral data, is computationally even more difficult. Therefore, researchers typically constrain their models to easily tractable components, such as Gaussian distributions or quadratic cost functions, or resort to numerical approximations. To overcome these limitations, we amortize the Bayesian actor using a neural network trained on a wide range of parameter settings in an unsupervised fashion. Using the pre-trained neural network enables performing efficient gradient-based Bayesian inference of the Bayesian actor model's parameters. We show on synthetic data that the inferred posterior distributions are in close alignment with those obtained using analytical solutions where they exist. Where no analytical solution is available, we recover posterior distributions close to the ground truth. We then show how our method allows for principled model comparison and how it can be used to disentangle factors that may lead to unidentifiabilities between priors and costs. Finally, we apply our method to empirical data from three sensorimotor tasks and compare model fits with different cost functions to show that it can explain individuals' behavioral patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03710v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Straub, Tobias F. Niehues, Jan Peters, Constantin A. Rothkopf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking the Curse of Multiagency in Robust Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20067v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Standard multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) algorithms are vulnerable to sim-to-real gaps. To address this, distributionally robust Markov games (RMGs) have been proposed to enhance robustness in MARL by optimizing the worst-case performance when game dynamics shift within a prescribed uncertainty set. RMGs remains under-explored, from reasonable problem formulation to the development of sample-efficient algorithms. Two notorious and open challenges are the formulation of the uncertainty set and whether the corresponding RMGs can overcome the curse of multiagency, where the sample complexity scales exponentially with the number of agents. In this work, we propose a natural class of RMGs inspired by behavioral economics, where each agent's uncertainty set is shaped by both the environment and the integrated behavior of other agents. We first establish the well-posedness of this class of RMGs by proving the existence of game-theoretic solutions such as robust Nash equilibria and coarse correlated equilibria (CCE). Assuming access to a generative model, we then introduce a sample-efficient algorithm for learning the CCE whose sample complexity scales polynomially with all relevant parameters. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first algorithm to break the curse of multiagency for RMGs, regardless of the uncertainty set formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20067v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laixi Shi, Jingchu Gai, Eric Mazumdar, Yuejie Chi, Adam Wierman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provable Weak-to-Strong Generalization via Benign Overfitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04638v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The classic teacher-student model in machine learning posits that a strong teacher supervises a weak student to improve the student's capabilities. We instead consider the inverted situation, where a weak teacher supervises a strong student with imperfect pseudolabels. This paradigm was recently brought forth by Burns et al.'23 and termed \emph{weak-to-strong generalization}. We theoretically investigate weak-to-strong generalization for binary and multilabel classification in a stylized overparameterized spiked covariance model with Gaussian covariates where the weak teacher's pseudolabels are asymptotically like random guessing. Under these assumptions, we provably identify two asymptotic phases of the strong student's generalization after weak supervision: (1) successful generalization and (2) random guessing. Our techniques should eventually extend to weak-to-strong multiclass classification. Towards doing so, we prove a tight lower tail inequality for the maximum of correlated Gaussians, which may be of independent interest. Understanding the multilabel setting reinforces the value of using logits for weak supervision when they are available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04638v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David X. Wu, Anant Sahai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning multivariate Gaussians with imperfect advice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12700v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of distribution learning within the framework of learning-augmented algorithms. In this setting, we explore the scenario where a probability distribution is provided as potentially inaccurate advice on the true, unknown distribution. Our objective is to develop learning algorithms whose sample complexity decreases as the quality of the advice improves, thereby surpassing standard learning lower bounds when the advice is sufficiently accurate.
  Specifically, we demonstrate that this outcome is achievable for the problem of learning a multivariate Gaussian distribution $N(\boldsymbol{\mu}, \boldsymbol{\Sigma})$ in the PAC learning setting. Classically, in the advice-free setting, $\tilde{\Theta}(d^2/\varepsilon^2)$ samples are sufficient and worst case necessary to learn $d$-dimensional Gaussians up to TV distance $\varepsilon$ with constant probability. When we are additionally given a parameter $\tilde{\boldsymbol{\Sigma}}$ as advice, we show that $\tilde{O}(d^{2-\beta}/\varepsilon^2)$ samples suffices whenever $\| \tilde{\boldsymbol{\Sigma}}^{-1/2} \boldsymbol{\Sigma} \tilde{\boldsymbol{\Sigma}}^{-1/2} - \boldsymbol{I_d} \|_1 \leq \varepsilon d^{1-\beta}$ (where $\|\cdot\|_1$ denotes the entrywise $\ell_1$ norm) for any $\beta &gt; 0$, yielding a polynomial improvement over the advice-free setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12700v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Davin Choo, Philips George John, Themis Gouleakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoElicit: Using Large Language Models for Expert Prior Elicitation in Predictive Modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17284v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) acquire a breadth of information across various domains. However, their computational complexity, cost, and lack of transparency often hinder their direct application for predictive tasks where privacy and interpretability are paramount. In fields such as healthcare, biology, and finance, specialised and interpretable linear models still hold considerable value. In such domains, labelled data may be scarce or expensive to obtain. Well-specified prior distributions over model parameters can reduce the sample complexity of learning through Bayesian inference; however, eliciting expert priors can be time-consuming. We therefore introduce AutoElicit to extract knowledge from LLMs and construct priors for predictive models. We show these priors are informative and can be refined using natural language. We perform a careful study contrasting AutoElicit with in-context learning and demonstrate how to perform model selection between the two methods. We find that AutoElicit yields priors that can substantially reduce error over uninformative priors, using fewer labels, and consistently outperform in-context learning. We show that AutoElicit saves over 6 months of labelling effort when building a new predictive model for urinary tract infections from sensor recordings of people living with dementia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17284v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Capstick, Rahul G. Krishnan, Payam Barnaghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge of Stochastic Stability: Revisiting the Edge of Stability for SGD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20553v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent findings by Cohen et al., 2021, demonstrate that when training neural networks with full-batch gradient descent with a step size of $\eta$, the largest eigenvalue $\lambda_{\max}$ of the full-batch Hessian consistently stabilizes at $\lambda_{\max} = 2/\eta$. These results have significant implications for convergence and generalization. This, however, is not the case of mini-batch stochastic gradient descent (SGD), limiting the broader applicability of its consequences. We show that SGD trains in a different regime we term Edge of Stochastic Stability (EoSS). In this regime, what stabilizes at $2/\eta$ is *Batch Sharpness*: the expected directional curvature of mini-batch Hessians along their corresponding stochastic gradients. As a consequence $\lambda_{\max}$--which is generally smaller than Batch Sharpness--is suppressed, aligning with the long-standing empirical observation that smaller batches and larger step sizes favor flatter minima. We further discuss implications for mathematical modeling of SGD trajectories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20553v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arseniy Andreyev, Pierfrancesco Beneventano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Representation of Density-Power-Based Divergences Reducible to M-Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16287v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Density-power-based divergences are known to provide robust inference procedures against outliers, and their extensions have been widely studied. A characteristic of successful divergences is that the estimation problem can be reduced to M-estimation. In this paper, we define a norm-based Bregman density power divergence (NB-DPD) -- density-power-based divergence with functional flexibility within the framework of Bregman divergences that can be reduced to M-estimation. We show that, by specifying the function $\phi_\gamma$, NB-DPD reduces to well-known divergences, such as the density power divergence and the $\gamma$-divergence. Furthermore, by examining the combinations of functions $\phi_\gamma$ corresponding to existing divergences, we show that a new divergence connecting these existing divergences can be derived. Finally, we show that the redescending property, one of the key indicators of robustness, holds only for the $\gamma$-divergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16287v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Kobayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
