<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.ML updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML</link>
    <description>stat.ML updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.ML" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 05:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Latent-IMH: Efficient Bayesian Inference for Inverse Problems with Approximate Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study sampling from posterior distributions in Bayesian linear inverse problems where $A$, the parameters to observables operator, is computationally expensive. In many applications, $A$ can be factored in a manner that facilitates the construction of a cost-effective approximation $\tilde{A}$. In this framework, we introduce Latent-IMH, a sampling method based on the Metropolis-Hastings independence (IMH) sampler. Latent-IMH first generates intermediate latent variables using the approximate $\tilde{A}$, and then refines them using the exact $A$. Its primary benefit is that it shifts the computational cost to an offline phase. We theoretically analyze the performance of Latent-IMH using KL divergence and mixing time bounds. Using numerical experiments on several model problems, we show that, under reasonable assumptions, it outperforms state-of-the-art methods such as the No-U-Turn sampler (NUTS) in computational efficiency. In some cases, Latent-IMH can be orders of magnitude faster than existing schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20888v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youguang Chen, George Biros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Causal Structure Learning via Modular Subgraph Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Learning causal structures from observational data remains a fundamental yet computationally intensive task, particularly in high-dimensional settings where existing methods face challenges such as the super-exponential growth of the search space and increasing computational demands. To address this, we introduce VISTA (Voting-based Integration of Subgraph Topologies for Acyclicity), a modular framework that decomposes the global causal structure learning problem into local subgraphs based on Markov Blankets. The global integration is achieved through a weighted voting mechanism that penalizes low-support edges via exponential decay, filters unreliable ones with an adaptive threshold, and ensures acyclicity using a Feedback Arc Set (FAS) algorithm. The framework is model-agnostic, imposing no assumptions on the inductive biases of base learners, is compatible with arbitrary data settings without requiring specific structural forms, and fully supports parallelization. We also theoretically establish finite-sample error bounds for VISTA, and prove its asymptotic consistency under mild conditions. Extensive experiments on both synthetic and real datasets consistently demonstrate the effectiveness of VISTA, yielding notable improvements in both accuracy and efficiency over a wide range of base learners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21014v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haixiang Sun, Pengchao Tian, Zihan Zhou, Jielei Zhang, Peiyi Li, Andrew L. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Diffusive Classification Loss for Learning Energy-based Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Score-based generative models have recently achieved remarkable success. While they are usually parameterized by the score, an alternative way is to use a series of time-dependent energy-based models (EBMs), where the score is obtained from the negative input-gradient of the energy. Crucially, EBMs can be leveraged not only for generation, but also for tasks such as compositional sampling or building Boltzmann Generators via Monte Carlo methods. However, training EBMs remains challenging. Direct maximum likelihood is computationally prohibitive due to the need for nested sampling, while score matching, though efficient, suffers from mode blindness. To address these issues, we introduce the Diffusive Classification (DiffCLF) objective, a simple method that avoids blindness while remaining computationally efficient. DiffCLF reframes EBM learning as a supervised classification problem across noise levels, and can be seamlessly combined with standard score-based objectives. We validate the effectiveness of DiffCLF by comparing the estimated energies against ground truth in analytical Gaussian mixture cases, and by applying the trained models to tasks such as model composition and Boltzmann Generator sampling. Our results show that DiffCLF enables EBMs with higher fidelity and broader applicability than existing approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21025v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Grenioux, RuiKang OuYang, Jos\'e Miguel Hern\'andez-Lobato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion-based Annealed Boltzmann Generators : benefits, pitfalls and hopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21026v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sampling configurations at thermodynamic equilibrium is a central challenge in statistical physics. Boltzmann Generators (BGs) tackle it by combining a generative model with a Monte Carlo (MC) correction step to obtain asymptotically unbiased samples from an unnormalized target. Most current BGs use classic MC mechanisms such as importance sampling, which both require tractable likelihoods from the backbone model and scale poorly in high-dimensional, multi-modal targets. We study BGs built on annealed Monte Carlo (aMC), which is designed to overcome these limitations by bridging a simple reference to the target through a sequence of intermediate densities. Diffusion models (DMs) are powerful generative models and have already been incorporated into aMC-based recalibration schemes via the diffusion-induced density path, making them appealing backbones for aMC-BGs. We provide an empirical meta-analysis of DM-based aMC-BGs on controlled multi-modal Gaussian mixtures (varying mode separation, number of modes, and dimension), explicitly disentangling inference effects from learning effects by comparing (i) a perfectly learned DM and (ii) a DM trained from data. Even with a perfect DM, standard integrations using only first-order stochastic denoising kernels fail systematically, whereas second-order denoising kernels can substantially improve performance when covariance information is available. We further propose a deterministic aMC integration based on first-order transport maps derived from DMs, which outperforms the stochastic first-order variant at higher computational cost. Finally, in the learned-DM setting, all DM-aMC variants struggle to produce accurate BGs; we trace the main bottleneck to inaccurate DM log-density estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21026v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Grenioux, Maxence Noble</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An efficient, accurate, and interpretable machine learning method for computing probability of failure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21089v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel machine learning method called the Penalized Profile Support Vector Machine based on the Gabriel edited set for the computation of the probability of failure for a complex system as determined by a threshold condition on a computer model of system behavior. The method is designed to minimize the number of evaluations of the computer model while preserving the geometry of the decision boundary that determines the probability. It employs an adaptive sampling strategy designed to strategically allocate points near the boundary determining failure and builds a locally linear surrogate boundary that remains consistent with its geometry by strategic clustering of training points. We prove two convergence results and we compare the performance of the method against a number of state of the art classification methods on four test problems. We also apply the method to determine the probability of survival using the Lotka--Volterra model for competing species.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21089v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Zhu, Donald Estep</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-dimensional learning dynamics of multi-pass Stochastic Gradient Descent in multi-index models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the learning dynamics of a multi-pass, mini-batch Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD) procedure for empirical risk minimization in high-dimensional multi-index models with isotropic random data. In an asymptotic regime where the sample size $n$ and data dimension $d$ increase proportionally, for any sub-linear batch size $\kappa \asymp n^\alpha$ where $\alpha \in [0,1)$, and for a commensurate ``critical'' scaling of the learning rate, we provide an asymptotically exact characterization of the coordinate-wise dynamics of SGD. This characterization takes the form of a system of dynamical mean-field equations, driven by a scalar Poisson jump process that represents the asymptotic limit of SGD sampling noise. We develop an analogous characterization of the Stochastic Modified Equation (SME) which provides a Gaussian diffusion approximation to SGD.
  Our analyses imply that the limiting dynamics for SGD are the same for any batch size scaling $\alpha \in [0,1)$, and that under a commensurate scaling of the learning rate, dynamics of SGD, SME, and gradient flow are mutually distinct, with those of SGD and SME coinciding in the special case of a linear model. We recover a known dynamical mean-field characterization of gradient flow in a limit of small learning rate, and of one-pass/online SGD in a limit of increasing sample size $n/d \to \infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21093v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhou Fan, Leda Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilevel and Sequential Monte Carlo for Training-Free Diffusion Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the problem of accurate, training-free guidance for conditional generation in trained diffusion models. Existing methods typically rely on point-estimates to approximate the posterior score, often resulting in biased approximations that fail to capture multimodality inherent to the reverse process of diffusion models. We propose a sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) framework that constructs an unbiased estimator of $p_\theta(y|x_t)$ by integrating over the full denoising distribution via Monte Carlo approximation. To ensure computational tractability, we incorporate variance-reduction schemes based on Multi-Level Monte Carlo (MLMC). Our approach achieves new state-of-the-art results for training-free guidance on CIFAR-10 class-conditional generation, achieving $95.6\%$ accuracy with $3\times$ lower cost-per-success than baselines. On ImageNet, our algorithm achieves $1.5\times$ cost-per-success advantage over existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21104v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Gleich, Scott C. Schmidler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provably Reliable Classifier Guidance through Cross-entropy Error Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Classifier-guided diffusion models generate conditional samples by augmenting the reverse-time score with the gradient of a learned classifier, yet it remains unclear whether standard classifier training procedures yield effective diffusion guidance. We address this gap by showing that, under mild smoothness assumptions on the classifiers, controlling the cross-entropy error at each diffusion step also controls the error of the resulting guidance vectors: classifiers achieving conditional KL divergence $\varepsilon^2$ from the ground-truth conditional label probabilities induce guidance vectors with mean squared error $\widetilde{O}(d \varepsilon )$. Our result yields an upper bound on the sampling error under classifier guidance and bears resemblance to a reverse log-Sobolev-type inequality. Moreover, we show that the classifier smoothness assumption is essential, by constructing simple counterexamples demonstrating that, without it, control of the guidance vector can fail for almost all distributions. To our knowledge, our work establishes the first quantitative link between classifier training and guidance alignment, yielding both a theoretical foundation for classifier guidance and principled guidelines for classifier selection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21200v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharan Sahu, Arisina Banerjee, Yuchen Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Flexible Empirical Bayes Approach to Generalized Linear Models, with Applications to Sparse Logistic Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21217v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a flexible empirical Bayes approach for fitting Bayesian generalized linear models. Specifically, we adopt a novel mean-field variational inference (VI) method and the prior is estimated within the VI algorithm, making the method tuning-free. Unlike traditional VI methods that optimize the posterior density function, our approach directly optimizes the posterior mean and prior parameters. This formulation reduces the number of parameters to optimize and enables the use of scalable algorithms such as L-BFGS and stochastic gradient descent. Furthermore, our method automatically determines the optimal posterior based on the prior and likelihood, distinguishing it from existing VI methods that often assume a Gaussian variational. Our approach represents a unified framework applicable to a wide range of exponential family distributions, removing the need to develop unique VI methods for each combination of likelihood and prior distributions. We apply the framework to solve sparse logistic regression and demonstrate the superior predictive performance of our method in extensive numerical studies, by comparing it to prevalent sparse logistic regression approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21217v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongyue Xie, Wanrong Zhu, Matthew Stephens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk-Calibrated Credal Ambiguity Sets: Fast, Tractable Decision Making under Out-of-Sample Contamination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Distributionally robust optimisation (DRO) minimises the worst-case expected loss over an ambiguity set that can capture distributional shifts in out-of-sample environments. While Huber (linear-vacuous) contamination is a classical minimal-assumption model for an $\varepsilon$-fraction of arbitrary perturbations, including it in an ambiguity set can make the worst-case risk infinite and the DRO objective vacuous unless one imposes strong boundedness or support assumptions. We address these challenges by introducing bulk-calibrated credal ambiguity sets: we learn a high-mass bulk set from data while considering contamination inside the bulk and bounding the remaining tail contribution separately. This leads to a closed-form, finite $\mathrm{mean}+\sup$ robust objective and tractable linear or second-order cone programs for common losses and bulk geometries. Through this framework, we highlight and exploit the equivalence between the imprecise probability (IP) notion of upper expectation and the worst-case risk, demonstrating how IP credal sets translate into DRO objectives with interpretable tolerance levels. Experiments on heavy-tailed inventory control, geographically shifted house-price regression, and demographically shifted text classification show competitive robustness-accuracy trade-offs and efficient optimisation times, using Bayesian, frequentist, or empirical reference distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21324v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengqi Chen, Thomas B. Berrett, Theodoros Damoulas, Michele Caprio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statsformer: Validated Ensemble Learning with LLM-Derived Semantic Priors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce Statsformer, a principled framework for integrating large language model (LLM)-derived knowledge into supervised statistical learning. Existing approaches are limited in adaptability and scope: they either inject LLM guidance as an unvalidated heuristic, which is sensitive to LLM hallucination, or embed semantic information within a single fixed learner. Statsformer overcomes both limitations through a guardrailed ensemble architecture. We embed LLM-derived feature priors within an ensemble of linear and nonlinear learners, adaptively calibrating their influence via cross-validation. This design yields a flexible system with an oracle-style guarantee that it performs no worse than any convex combination of its in-library base learners, up to statistical error. Empirically, informative priors yield consistent performance improvements, while uninformative or misspecified LLM guidance is automatically downweighted, mitigating the impact of hallucinations across a diverse range of prediction tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21410v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erica Zhang, Naomi Sagan, Danny Tse, Fangzhao Zhang, Mert Pilanci, Jose Blanchet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Questioning the Coverage-Length Metric in Conformal Prediction: When Shorter Intervals Are Not Better</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21455v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conformal prediction (CP) has become a cornerstone of distribution-free uncertainty quantification, conventionally evaluated by its coverage and interval length. This work critically examines the sufficiency of these standard metrics. We demonstrate that the interval length might be deceptively improved through a counter-intuitive approach termed Prejudicial Trick (PT), while the coverage remains valid. Specifically, for any given test sample, PT probabilistically returns an interval, which is either null or constructed using an adjusted confidence level, thereby preserving marginal coverage. While PT potentially yields a deceptively lower interval length, it introduces practical vulnerabilities: the same input can yield completely different prediction intervals across repeated runs of the algorithm. We formally derive the conditions under which PT achieves these misleading improvements and provides extensive empirical evidence across various regression and classification tasks. Furthermore, we introduce a new metric interval stability which helps detect whether a new CP method implicitly improves the length based on such PT-like techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21455v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yizhou Min, Yizhou Lu, Lanqi Li, Zhen Zhang, Jiaye Teng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Decomposable Forward Process in Diffusion Models for Time-Series Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21812v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a model-agnostic forward diffusion process for time-series forecasting that decomposes signals into spectral components, preserving structured temporal patterns such as seasonality more effectively than standard diffusion. Unlike prior work that modifies the network architecture or diffuses directly in the frequency domain, our proposed method alters only the diffusion process itself, making it compatible with existing diffusion backbones (e.g., DiffWave, TimeGrad, CSDI). By staging noise injection according to component energy, it maintains high signal-to-noise ratios for dominant frequencies throughout the diffusion trajectory, thereby improving the recoverability of long-term patterns. This strategy enables the model to maintain the signal structure for a longer period in the forward process, leading to improved forecast quality. Across standard forecasting benchmarks, we show that applying spectral decomposition strategies, such as the Fourier or Wavelet transform, consistently improves upon diffusion models using the baseline forward process, with negligible computational overhead. The code for this paper is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/D-FDP-4A29.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21812v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Caldas, Sahil Kumar, Cl\'audia Soares</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Judge-Aware Ranking Framework for Evaluating Large Language Models without Ground Truth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21817v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Evaluating large language models (LLMs) on open-ended tasks without ground-truth labels is increasingly done via the LLM-as-a-judge paradigm. A critical but under-modeled issue is that judge LLMs differ substantially in reliability; treating all judges equally can yield biased leaderboards and misleading uncertainty estimates. More data can make evaluation more confidently wrong under misspecified aggregation. We propose a judge-aware ranking framework that extends the Bradley-Terry-Luce model by introducing judge-specific discrimination parameters, jointly estimating latent model quality and judge reliability from pairwise comparisons without reference labels. We establish identifiability up to natural normalizations and prove consistency and asymptotic normality of the maximum likelihood estimator, enabling confidence intervals for score differences and rank comparisons. Across multiple public benchmarks and a newly collected dataset, our method improves agreement with human preferences, achieves higher data efficiency than unweighted baselines, and produces calibrated uncertainty quantification for LLM rankings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21817v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyuan Xu, Xinzi Tan, Jiawei Wu, Doudou Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Modeling of Discrete Data Using Geometric Latent Subspaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21831v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the use of latent subspaces in the exponential parameter space of product manifolds of categorial distributions, as a tool for learning generative models of discrete data. The low-dimensional latent space encodes statistical dependencies and removes redundant degrees of freedom among the categorial variables. We equip the parameter domain with a Riemannian geometry such that the spaces and distances are related by isometries which enables consistent flow matching. In particular, geodesics become straight lines which makes model training by flow matching effective. Empirical results demonstrate that reduced latent dimensions suffice to represent data for generative modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21831v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Gonzalez-Alvarado, Jonas Cassel, Stefania Petra, Christoph Schn\"orr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Forgetting and Stability of Score-based Generative models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21868v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the stability and long-time behavior of generative models is a fundamental problem in modern machine learning. This paper provides quantitative bounds on the sampling error of score-based generative models by leveraging stability and forgetting properties of the Markov chain associated with the reverse-time dynamics. Under weak assumptions, we provide the two structural properties to ensure the propagation of initialization and discretization errors of the backward process: a Lyapunov drift condition and a Doeblin-type minorization condition. A practical consequence is quantitative stability of the sampling procedure, as the reverse diffusion dynamics induces a contraction mechanism along the sampling trajectory. Our results clarify the role of stochastic dynamics in score-based models and provide a principled framework for analyzing propagation of errors in such approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21868v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanislas Strasman, Gabriel Cardoso, Sylvain Le Corff, Vincent Lemaire, Antonio Ocello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clustering in Deep Stochastic Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transformers have revolutionized deep learning across various domains but understanding the precise token dynamics remains a theoretical challenge. Existing theories of deep Transformers with layer normalization typically predict that tokens cluster to a single point; however, these results rely on deterministic weight assumptions, which fail to capture the standard initialization scheme in Transformers. In this work, we show that accounting for the intrinsic stochasticity of random initialization alters this picture. More precisely, we analyze deep Transformers where noise arises from the random initialization of value matrices. Under diffusion scaling and token-wise RMS normalization, we prove that, as the number of Transformer layers goes to infinity, the discrete token dynamics converge to an interacting-particle system on the sphere where tokens are driven by a \emph{common} matrix-valued Brownian noise. In this limit, we show that initialization noise prevents the collapse to a single cluster predicted by deterministic models. For two tokens, we prove a phase transition governed by the interaction strength and the token dimension: unlike deterministic attention flows, antipodal configurations become attracting with positive probability. Numerical experiments confirm the predicted transition, reveal that antipodal formations persist for more than two tokens, and demonstrate that suppressing the intrinsic noise degrades accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21942v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lev Fedorov, Micha\"el E. Sander, Romuald Elie, Pierre Marion, Mathieu Lauri\`ere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Path Samplers via Sequential Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a diffusion-based sampler for target distributions known up to a normalising constant. To this end, we rely on the well-known diffusion path that smoothly interpolates between a (simple) base distribution and the target distribution, widely used in diffusion models. Our approach is based on a practical implementation of diffusion-annealed Langevin Monte Carlo, which approximates the diffusion path with convergence guarantees. We tackle the score estimation problem by developing an efficient sequential Monte Carlo sampler that evolves auxiliary variables from conditional distributions along the path, which provides principled score estimates for time-varying distributions. We further develop novel control variate schedules that minimise the variance of these score estimates. Finally, we provide theoretical guarantees and empirically demonstrate the effectiveness of our method on several synthetic and real-world datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21951v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Matthew Young, Paula Cordero-Encinar, Sebastian Reich, Andrew Duncan, O. Deniz Akyildiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-Optimal Private Tests for Simple and MLR Hypotheses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a near-optimal testing procedure under the framework of Gaussian differential privacy for simple as well as one- and two-sided tests under monotone likelihood ratio conditions. Our mechanism is based on a private mean estimator with data-driven clamping bounds, whose population risk matches the private minimax rate up to logarithmic factors. Using this estimator, we construct private test statistics that achieve the same asymptotic relative efficiency as the non-private, most powerful tests while maintaining conservative type I error control. In addition to our theoretical results, our numerical experiments show that our private tests outperform competing DP methods and offer comparable power to the non-private most powerful tests, even at moderately small sample sizes and privacy loss budgets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21959v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Wei Chen, Raghu Pasupathy, Jordan Awan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Stochastic Optimisation via Sequential Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22003v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The problem of optimising functions with intractable gradients frequently arise in machine learning and statistics, ranging from maximum marginal likelihood estimation procedures to fine-tuning of generative models. Stochastic approximation methods for this class of problems typically require inner sampling loops to obtain (biased) stochastic gradient estimates, which rapidly becomes computationally expensive. In this work, we develop sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) samplers for optimisation of functions with intractable gradients. Our approach replaces expensive inner sampling methods with efficient SMC approximations, which can result in significant computational gains. We establish convergence results for the basic recursions defined by our methodology which SMC samplers approximate. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach on the reward-tuning of energy-based models within various settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22003v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Cuin, Davide Carbone, Yanbo Tang, O. Deniz Akyildiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supervised Guidance Training for Infinite-Dimensional Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Score-based diffusion models have recently been extended to infinite-dimensional function spaces, with uses such as inverse problems arising from partial differential equations. In the Bayesian formulation of inverse problems, the aim is to sample from a posterior distribution over functions obtained by conditioning a prior on noisy observations. While diffusion models provide expressive priors in function space, the theory of conditioning them to sample from the posterior remains open. We address this, assuming that either the prior lies in the Cameron-Martin space, or is absolutely continuous with respect to a Gaussian measure. We prove that the models can be conditioned using an infinite-dimensional extension of Doob's $h$-transform, and that the conditional score decomposes into an unconditional score and a guidance term. As the guidance term is intractable, we propose a simulation-free score matching objective (called Supervised Guidance Training) enabling efficient and stable posterior sampling. We illustrate the theory with numerical examples on Bayesian inverse problems in function spaces. In summary, our work offers the first function-space method for fine-tuning trained diffusion models to accurately sample from a posterior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20756v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth L. Baker, Alexander Denker, Jes Frellsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Causality in the SDG Network: Evidence from Panel VAR and Conditional Independence Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20875v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The achievement of the 2030 Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) is dependent upon strategic resource distribution. We propose a causal discovery framework using Panel Vector Autoregression, along with both country-specific fixed effects and PCMCI+ conditional independence testing on 168 countries (2000-2025) to develop the first complete causal architecture of SDG dependencies. Utilizing 8 strategically chosen SDGs, we identify a distributed causal network (i.e., no single 'hub' SDG), with 10 statistically significant Granger-causal relationships identified as 11 unique direct effects. Education to Inequality is identified as the most statistically significant direct relationship (r = -0.599; p &lt; 0.05), while effect magnitude significantly varies depending on income levels (e.g., high-income: r = -0.65; lower-middle-income: r = -0.06; non-significant). We also reject the idea that there exists a single 'keystone' SDG. Additionally, we offer a proposed tiered priority framework for the SDGs namely, identifying upstream drivers (Education, Growth), enabling goals (Institutions, Energy), and downstream outcomes (Poverty, Health). Therefore, we conclude that effective SDG acceleration can be accomplished through coordinated multi-dimensional intervention(s), and that single-goal sequential strategies are insufficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20875v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Muhtasim Munif Fahim, Md Jahid Hasan Imran, Luknath Debnath, Tonmoy Shill, Md. Naim Molla, Ehsanul Bashar Pranto, Md Shafin Sanyan Saad, Md Rezaul Karim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Theory of Universal Agnostic Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20961v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a complete theory of optimal universal rates for binary classification in the agnostic setting. This extends the realizable-case theory of Bousquet, Hanneke, Moran, van Handel, and Yehudayoff (2021) by removing the realizability assumption on the distribution. We identify a fundamental tetrachotomy of optimal rates: for every concept class, the optimal universal rate of convergence of the excess error rate is one of $e^{-n}$, $e^{-o(n)}$, $o(n^{-1/2})$, or arbitrarily slow. We further identify simple combinatorial structures which determine which of these categories any given concept class falls into.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20961v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steve Hanneke, Shay Moran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signal from Structure: Exploiting Submodular Upper Bounds in Generative Flow Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generative Flow Networks (GFlowNets; GFNs) are a class of generative models that learn to sample compositional objects proportionally to their a priori unknown value, their reward. We focus on the case where the reward has a specified, actionable structure, namely that it is submodular. We show submodularity can be harnessed to retrieve upper bounds on the reward of compositional objects that have not yet been observed. We provide in-depth analyses of the probability of such bounds occurring, as well as how many unobserved compositional objects can be covered by a bound. Following the Optimism in the Face of Uncertainty principle, we then introduce SUBo-GFN, which uses the submodular upper bounds to train a GFN. We show that SUBo-GFN generates orders of magnitude more training data than classical GFNs for the same number of queries to the reward function. We demonstrate the effectiveness of SUBo-GFN in terms of distribution matching and high-quality candidate generation on synthetic and real-world submodular tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21061v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Larouche, Audrey Durand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thompson sampling: Precise arm-pull dynamics and adaptive inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Adaptive sampling schemes are well known to create complex dependence that may invalidate conventional inference methods. A recent line of work shows that this need not be the case for UCB-type algorithms in multi-armed bandits. A central emerging theme is a `stability' property with asymptotically deterministic arm-pull counts in these algorithms, making inference as easy as in the i.i.d. setting.
  In this paper, we study the precise arm-pull dynamics in another canonical class of Thompson-sampling type algorithms. We show that the phenomenology is qualitatively different: the arm-pull count is asymptotically deterministic if and only if the arm is suboptimal or is the unique optimal arm; otherwise it converges in distribution to the unique invariant law of an SDE. This dichotomy uncovers a unifying principle behind many existing (in)stability results: an arm is stable if and only if its interaction with statistical noise is asymptotically negligible.
  As an application, we show that normalized arm means obey the same dichotomy, with Gaussian limits for stable arms and a semi-universal, non-Gaussian limit for unstable arms. This not only enables the construction of confidence intervals for the unknown mean rewards despite non-normality, but also reveals the potential of developing tractable inference procedures beyond the stable regime.
  The proofs rely on two new approaches. For suboptimal arms, we develop an `inverse process' approach that characterizes the inverse of the arm-pull count process via a Stieltjes integral. For optimal arms, we adopt a reparametrization of the arm-pull and noise processes that reduces the singularity in the natural SDE to proving the uniqueness of the invariant law of another SDE. We prove the latter by a set of analytic tools, including the parabolic H\"ormander condition and the Stroock-Varadhan support theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21131v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiyang Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Powers of Precision: Structure-Informed Detection in Complex Systems -- From Customer Churn to Seizure Onset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Emergent phenomena -- onset of epileptic seizures, sudden customer churn, or pandemic outbreaks -- often arise from hidden causal interactions in complex systems. We propose a machine learning method for their early detection that addresses a core challenge: unveiling and harnessing a system's latent causal structure despite the data-generating process being unknown and partially observed. The method learns an optimal feature representation from a one-parameter family of estimators -- powers of the empirical covariance or precision matrix -- offering a principled way to tune in to the underlying structure driving the emergence of critical events. A supervised learning module then classifies the learned representation. We prove structural consistency of the family and demonstrate the empirical soundness of our approach on seizure detection and churn prediction, attaining competitive results in both. Beyond prediction, and toward explainability, we ascertain that the optimal covariance power exhibits evidence of good identifiability while capturing structural signatures, thus reconciling predictive performance with interpretable statistical structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21170v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Augusto Santos, Teresa Santos, Catarina Rodrigues, Jos\'e M. F. Moura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Missing-Data-Induced Phase Transitions in Spectral PLS for Multimodal Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21294v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Partial Least Squares (PLS) learns shared structure from paired data via the top singular vectors of the empirical cross-covariance (PLS-SVD), but multimodal datasets often have missing entries in both views. We study PLS-SVD under independent entry-wise missing-completely-at-random masking in a proportional high-dimensional spiked model. After appropriate normalization, the masked cross-covariance behaves like a spiked rectangular random matrix whose effective signal strength is attenuated by $\sqrt{\rho}$, where $\rho$ is the joint entry retention probability. As a result, PLS-SVD exhibits a sharp BBP-type phase transition: below a critical signal-to-noise threshold the leading singular vectors are asymptotically uninformative, while above it they achieve nontrivial alignment with the latent shared directions, with closed-form asymptotic overlap formulas. Simulations and semi-synthetic multimodal experiments corroborate the predicted phase diagram and recovery curves across aspect ratios, signal strengths, and missingness levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21294v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anders Gj{\o}lbye, Ida Kargaard, Emma Kargaard, Lars Kai Hansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving $\varepsilon^{-2}$ Dependence for Average-Reward Q-Learning with a New Contraction Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21301v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the convergence rates of synchronous and asynchronous Q-learning for average-reward Markov decision processes, where the absence of contraction poses a fundamental challenge. Existing non-asymptotic results overcome this challenge by either imposing strong assumptions to enforce seminorm contraction or relying on discounted or episodic Markov decision processes as successive approximations, which either require unknown parameters or result in suboptimal sample complexity. In this work, under a reachability assumption, we establish optimal $\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-2})$ sample complexity guarantees (up to logarithmic factors) for a simple variant of synchronous and asynchronous Q-learning that samples from the lazified dynamics, where the system remains in the current state with some fixed probability. At the core of our analysis is the construction of an instance-dependent seminorm and showing that, after a lazy transformation of the Markov decision process, the Bellman operator becomes one-step contractive under this seminorm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21301v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijun Chen, Zaiwei Chen, Nian Si, Shengbo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partial Feedback Online Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21462v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study partial-feedback online learning, where each instance admits a set of correct labels, but the learner only observes one correct label per round; any prediction within the correct set is counted as correct. This model captures settings such as language generation, where multiple responses may be valid but data provide only a single reference. We give a near-complete characterization of minimax regret for both deterministic and randomized learners in the set-realizable regime, i.e., in the regime where sublinear regret is generally attainable. For deterministic learners, we introduce the Partial-Feedback Littlestone dimension (PFLdim) and show it precisely governs learnability and minimax regret; technically, PFLdim cannot be defined via the standard version space, requiring a new collection version space viewpoint and an auxiliary dimension used only in the proof. We further develop the Partial-Feedback Measure Shattering dimension (PMSdim) to obtain tight bounds for randomized learners. We identify broad conditions ensuring inseparability between deterministic and randomized learnability (e.g., finite Helly number or nested-inclusion label structure), and extend the argument to set-valued online learning, resolving an open question of Raman et al. [2024b]. Finally, we show a sharp separation from weaker realistic and agnostic variants: outside set realizability, the problem can become information-theoretically intractable, with linear regret possible even for $|H|=2$. This highlights the need for fundamentally new, noise-sensitive complexity measures to meaningfully characterize learnability beyond set realizability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21462v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shihao Shao, Cong Fang, Zhouchen Lin, Dacheng Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PPI-SVRG: Unifying Prediction-Powered Inference and Variance Reduction for Semi-Supervised Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21470v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study semi-supervised stochastic optimization when labeled data is scarce but predictions from pre-trained models are available. PPI and SVRG both reduce variance through control variates -- PPI uses predictions, SVRG uses reference gradients. We show they are mathematically equivalent and develop PPI-SVRG, which combines both. Our convergence bound decomposes into the standard SVRG rate plus an error floor from prediction uncertainty. The rate depends only on loss geometry; predictions affect only the neighborhood size. When predictions are perfect, we recover SVRG exactly. When predictions degrade, convergence remains stable but reaches a larger neighborhood. Experiments confirm the theory: PPI-SVRG reduces MSE by 43--52\% under label scarcity on mean estimation benchmarks and improves test accuracy by 2.7--2.9 percentage points on MNIST with only 10\% labeled data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21470v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruicheng Ao, Hongyu Chen, Haoyang Liu, David Simchi-Levi, Will Wei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Best Arm Identification with LLM Judges and Limited Human</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21471v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study fixed-confidence best-arm identification (BAI) where a cheap but potentially biased proxy (e.g., LLM judge) is available for every sample, while an expensive ground-truth label can only be acquired selectively when using a human for auditing. Unlike classical multi-fidelity BAI, the proxy is biased (arm- and context-dependent) and ground truth is selectively observed. Consequently, standard multi-fidelity methods can mis-select the best arm, and uniform auditing, though accurate, wastes scarce resources and is inefficient. We prove that without bias correction and propensity adjustment, mis-selection probability may not vanish (even with unlimited proxy data). We then develop an estimator for the mean of each arm that combines proxy scores with inverse-propensity-weighted residuals and form anytime-valid confidence sequences for that estimator. Based on the estimator and confidence sequence, we propose an algorithm that adaptively selects and audits arms. The algorithm concentrates audits on unreliable contexts and close arms and we prove that a plug-in Neyman rule achieves near-oracle audit efficiency. Numerical experiments confirm the theoretical guarantees and demonstrate the superior empirical performance of the proposed algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21471v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruicheng Ao, Hongyu Chen, Siyang Gao, Hanwei Li, David Simchi-Levi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differential Dynamic Causal Nets: Model Construction, Identification and Group Comparisons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21478v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Pathophysiolpgical modelling of brain systems from microscale to macroscale remains difficult in group comparisons partly because of the infeasibility of modelling the interactions of thousands of neurons at the scales involved. Here, to address the challenge, we present a novel approach to construct differential causal networks directly from electroencephalogram (EEG) data. The proposed network is based on conditionally coupled neuronal circuits which describe the average behaviour of interacting neuron populations that contribute to observed EEG data. In the network, each node represents a parameterised local neural system while directed edges stand for node-wise connections with transmission parameters. The network is hierarchically structured in the sense that node and edge parameters are varying in subjects but follow a mixed-effects model. A novel evolutionary optimisation algorithm for parameter inference in the proposed method is developed using a loss function derived from Chen-Fliess expansions of stochastic differential equations. The method is demonstrated by application to the fitting of coupled Jansen-Rit local models. The performance of the proposed method is evaluated on both synthetic and real EEG data. In the real EEG data analysis, we track changes in the parameters that characterise dynamic causality within brains that demonstrate epileptic activity. We show evidence of network functional disruptions, due to imbalance of excitatory-inhibitory interneurons and altered epileptic brain connectivity, before and during seizure periods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21478v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang You, Gary Green, Jian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Bang for the Buck: Improving the Inference of Large Language Models at a Fixed Budget using Reset and Discard (ReD)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21522v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The performance of large language models (LLMs) on verifiable tasks is usually measured by pass@k, the probability of answering a question correctly at least once in k trials. At a fixed budget, a more suitable metric is coverage@cost, the average number of unique questions answered as a function of the total number of attempts. We connect the two metrics and show that the empirically-observed power-law behavior in pass@k leads to a sublinear growth of the coverage@cost (diminishing returns). To solve this problem, we propose Reset-and-Discard (ReD), a query method of LLMs that increases coverage@cost for any given budget, regardless of the pass@k form. Moreover, given a pass@k, we can quantitatively predict the savings in the total number of attempts using ReD. If pass@k is not available for the model, ReD can infer its power-law exponent. Experiments on three LLMs using HumanEval demonstrate that ReD substantially reduces the required attempts, tokens, and USD cost to reach a desired coverage, while also offering an efficient way to measure inference power-laws.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21522v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sagi Meir, Tommer D. Keidar, Noam Levi, Shlomi Reuveni, Barak Hirshberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sampling-Free Privacy Accounting for Matrix Mechanisms under Random Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21636v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study privacy amplification for differentially private model training with matrix factorization under random allocation (also known as the balls-in-bins model). Recent work by Choquette-Choo et al. (2025) proposes a sampling-based Monte Carlo approach to compute amplification parameters in this setting. However, their guarantees either only hold with some high probability or require random abstention by the mechanism. Furthermore, the required number of samples for ensuring $(\epsilon,\delta)$-DP is inversely proportional to $\delta$. In contrast, we develop sampling-free bounds based on R\'enyi divergence and conditional composition. The former is facilitated by a dynamic programming formulation to efficiently compute the bounds. The latter complements it by offering stronger privacy guarantees for small $\epsilon$, where R\'enyi divergence bounds inherently lead to an over-approximation. Our framework applies to arbitrary banded and non-banded matrices. Through numerical comparisons, we demonstrate the efficacy of our approach across a broad range of matrix mechanisms used in research and practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21636v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Schuchardt, Nikita Kalinin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Independent Component Discovery in Temporal Count Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21696v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Advances in data collection are producing growing volumes of temporal count observations, making adapted modeling increasingly necessary. In this work, we introduce a generative framework for independent component analysis of temporal count data, combining regime-adaptive dynamics with Poisson log-normal emissions. The model identifies disentangled components with regime-dependent contributions, enabling representation learning and perturbations analysis. Notably, we establish the identifiability of the model, supporting principled interpretation. To learn the parameters, we propose an efficient amortized variational inference procedure. Experiments on simulated data evaluate recovery of the mixing function and latent sources across diverse settings, while an in vivo longitudinal gut microbiome study reveals microbial co-variation patterns and regime shifts consistent with clinical perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21696v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Chaussard, Anna Bonnet, Sylvain Le Corff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On sample complexity for covariance estimation via the unadjusted Langevin algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21717v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish sample complexity guarantees for estimating the covariance matrix of strongly log-concave smooth distributions using the unadjusted Langevin algorithm (ULA). We quantitatively compare our complexity estimates on single-chain ULA with embarrassingly parallel ULA and derive that the sample complexity of the single-chain approach is smaller than that of embarrassingly parallel ULA by a logarithmic factor in the dimension and the reciprocal of the prescribed precision, with the difference arising from effective bias reduction through burn-in. The key technical contribution is a concentration bound for the sample covariance matrix around its expectation, derived via a log-Sobolev inequality for the joint distribution of ULA iterates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21717v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shogo Nakakita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LoRA and Privacy: When Random Projections Help (and When They Don't)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21719v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the (Wishart) projection mechanism, a randomized map of the form $S \mapsto M f(S)$ with $M \sim W_d(1/r I_d, r)$ and study its differential privacy properties. For vector-valued queries $f$, we prove non-asymptotic DP guarantees without any additive noise, showing that Wishart randomness alone can suffice. For matrix-valued queries, however, we establish a sharp negative result: in the noise-free setting, the mechanism is not DP, and we demonstrate its vulnerability by implementing a near perfect membership inference attack (AUC $&gt; 0.99$). We then analyze a noisy variant and prove privacy amplification due to randomness and low rank projection, in both large- and small-rank regimes, yielding stronger privacy guarantees than additive noise alone. Finally, we show that LoRA-style updates are an instance of the matrix-valued mechanism, implying that LoRA is not inherently private despite its built-in randomness, but that low-rank fine-tuning can be more private than full fine-tuning at the same noise level. Preliminary experiments suggest that tighter accounting enables lower noise and improved accuracy in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21719v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaxi Hu, Johanna D\"ungler, Bernhard Sch\"olkopf, Amartya Sanyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Adam Works Better with $\beta_1 = \beta_2$: The Missing Gradient Scale Invariance Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21739v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Adam has been at the core of large-scale training for almost a decade, yet a simple empirical fact remains unaccounted for: both validation scores and the qualitative behaviour of the training runs improve when the momentum parameters satisfy $\beta_{1}=\beta_{2}$. Some recent studies have reported this pattern, but there is still no explanation for why this choice helps. We show that this choice is closely tied to a structural property that we refer to as \textit{gradient scale invariance}. We formalize this notion and prove that Adam becomes gradient scale invariant of first order if and only if $\beta_{1}=\beta_{2}$. This perspective places the balanced regime of Adam in direct alignment with the design principles underlying several recent optimizers that explicitly enforce scale-robust updates. The theory is supported by experiments across vision and language tasks, and across different architectural families, in which rescaling the gradient has a markedly smoother effect on the update when $\beta_{1}=\beta_{2}$. Overall, our results offer a coherent explanation for an open question in the behavior of Adam and provide a simple principle that helps guide the design of future optimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21739v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Fern\'andez-Hern\'andez, Cristian P\'erez-Corral, Jose I. Mestre, Manuel F. Dolz, Enrique S. Quintana-Ort\'i</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-field Variational Bayes for Sparse Probit Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21765v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider Bayesian variable selection for binary outcomes under a probit link with a spike-and-slab prior on the regression coefficients. Motivated by the computational challenges encountered by Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) samplers in high-dimensional regimes, we develop a mean-field variational Bayes approximation in which all variational factors admit closed-form updates, and the evidence lower bound is available in closed form. This, in turn, allows the development of an efficient coordinate ascent variational inference algorithm to find the optimal values of the variational parameters. The approach produces posterior inclusion probabilities and parameter estimates, enabling interpretable selection and prediction within a single framework. As shown in both simulated and real data applications, the proposed method successfully identifies the important variables and is orders of magnitude faster than MCMC, while maintaining comparable accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21765v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Augusto Fasano, Giovanni Rebaudo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECSEL: Explainable Classification via Signomial Equation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21789v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce ECSEL, an explainable classification method that learns formal expressions in the form of signomial equations, motivated by the observation that many symbolic regression benchmarks admit compact signomial structure. ECSEL directly constructs a structural, closed-form expression that serves as both a classifier and an explanation. On standard symbolic regression benchmarks, our method recovers a larger fraction of target equations than competing state-of-the-art approaches while requiring substantially less computation. Leveraging this efficiency, ECSEL achieves classification accuracy competitive with established machine learning models without sacrificing interpretability. Further, we show that ECSEL satisfies some desirable properties regarding global feature behavior, decision-boundary analysis, and local feature attributions. Experiments on benchmark datasets and two real-world case studies i.e., e-commerce and fraud detection, demonstrate that the learned equations expose dataset biases, support counterfactual reasoning, and yield actionable insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21789v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adia Lumadjeng, Ilker Birbil, Erman Acar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blind Ultrasound Image Enhancement via Self-Supervised Physics-Guided Degradation Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21856v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrasound (US) interpretation is hampered by multiplicative speckle, acquisition blur from the point-spread function (PSF), and scanner- and operator-dependent artifacts. Supervised enhancement methods assume access to clean targets or known degradations; conditions rarely met in practice. We present a blind, self-supervised enhancement framework that jointly deconvolves and denoises B-mode images using a Swin Convolutional U-Net trained with a \emph{physics-guided} degradation model. From each training frame, we extract rotated/cropped patches and synthesize inputs by (i) convolving with a Gaussian PSF surrogate and (ii) injecting noise via either spatial additive Gaussian noise or complex Fourier-domain perturbations that emulate phase/magnitude distortions. For US scans, clean-like targets are obtained via non-local low-rank (NLLR) denoising, removing the need for ground truth; for natural images, the originals serve as targets. Trained and validated on UDIAT~B, JNU-IFM, and XPIE Set-P, and evaluated additionally on a 700-image PSFHS test set, the method achieves the highest PSNR/SSIM across Gaussian and speckle noise levels, with margins that widen under stronger corruption. Relative to MSANN, Restormer, and DnCNN, it typically preserves an extra $\sim$1--4\,dB PSNR and 0.05--0.15 SSIM in heavy Gaussian noise, and $\sim$2--5\,dB PSNR and 0.05--0.20 SSIM under severe speckle. Controlled PSF studies show reduced FWHM and higher peak gradients, evidence of resolution recovery without edge erosion. Used as a plug-and-play preprocessor, it consistently boosts Dice for fetal head and pubic symphysis segmentation. Overall, the approach offers a practical, assumption-light path to robust US enhancement that generalizes across datasets, scanners, and degradation types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21856v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shujaat Khan, Syed Muhammad Atif, Jaeyoung Huh, Syed Saad Azhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pathwise Learning of Stochastic Dynamical Systems with Partial Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21860v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The reconstruction and inference of stochastic dynamical systems from data is a fundamental task in inverse problems and statistical learning. While surrogate modeling advances computational methods to approximate these dynamics, standard approaches typically require high-fidelity training data. In many practical settings, the data are indirectly observed through noisy and nonlinear measurement. The challenge lies not only in approximating the coefficients of the SDEs, but in simultaneously inferring the posterior updates given the observations. In this work, we present a neural path estimation approach to solve stochastic dynamical systems based on variational inference. We first derive a stochastic control problem that solve filtering posterior path measure corresponding to a pathwise Zakai equation. We then construct a generative model that maps the prior path measure to posterior measure through the controlled diffusion and the associated Randon-Nykodym derivative. Through an amortization of sample paths of the observation process, the control is learned by an embedding of the noisy observation paths. Thus, we learn the unknown prior SDE and the control can recover the conditional path measure given the observation sample paths and we learn an associated SDE which induces the same path measure. In the end, we perform experiments on nonlinear dynamical systems, demonstrating the model's ability to learn multimodal, chaotic, or high dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21860v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicole Tianjiao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Rank Plus Sparse Matrix Transfer Learning under Growing Representations and Ambient Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning systems often expand their ambient features or latent representations over time, embedding earlier representations into larger spaces with limited new latent structure. We study transfer learning for structured matrix estimation under simultaneous growth of the ambient dimension and the intrinsic representation, where a well-estimated source task is embedded as a subspace of a higher-dimensional target task.
  We propose a general transfer framework in which the target parameter decomposes into an embedded source component, low-dimensional low-rank innovations, and sparse edits, and develop an anchored alternating projection estimator that preserves transferred subspaces while estimating only low-dimensional innovations and sparse modifications. We establish deterministic error bounds that separate target noise, representation growth, and source estimation error, yielding strictly improved rates when rank and sparsity increments are small.
  We demonstrate the generality of the framework by applying it to two canonical problems. For Markov transition matrix estimation from a single trajectory, we derive end-to-end theoretical guarantees under dependent noise. For structured covariance estimation under enlarged dimensions, we provide complementary theoretical analysis in the appendix and empirically validate consistent transfer gains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21873v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinhang Chai, Xuyuan Liu, Elynn Chen, Yujun Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VSE: Variational state estimation of complex model-free process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21887v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We design a variational state estimation (VSE) method that provides a closed-form Gaussian posterior of an underlying complex dynamical process from (noisy) nonlinear measurements. The complex process is model-free. That is, we do not have a suitable physics-based model characterizing the temporal evolution of the process state. The closed-form Gaussian posterior is provided by a recurrent neural network (RNN). The use of RNN is computationally simple in the inference phase. For learning the RNN, an additional RNN is used in the learning phase. Both RNNs help each other learn better based on variational inference principles. The VSE is demonstrated for a tracking application - state estimation of a stochastic Lorenz system (a benchmark process) using a 2-D camera measurement model. The VSE is shown to be competitive against a particle filter that knows the Lorenz system model and a recently proposed data-driven state estimation method that does not know the Lorenz system model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21887v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustav Nor\'en, Anubhab Ghosh, Fredrik Cumlin, Saikat Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learn-to-Distance: Distance Learning for Detecting LLM-Generated Text</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21895v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern large language models (LLMs) such as GPT, Claude, and Gemini have transformed the way we learn, work, and communicate. Yet, their ability to produce highly human-like text raises serious concerns about misinformation and academic integrity, making it an urgent need for reliable algorithms to detect LLM-generated content. In this paper, we start by presenting a geometric approach to demystify rewrite-based detection algorithms, revealing their underlying rationale and demonstrating their generalization ability. Building on this insight, we introduce a novel rewrite-based detection algorithm that adaptively learns the distance between the original and rewritten text. Theoretically, we demonstrate that employing an adaptively learned distance function is more effective for detection than using a fixed distance. Empirically, we conduct extensive experiments with over 100 settings, and find that our approach demonstrates superior performance over baseline algorithms in the majority of scenarios. In particular, it achieves relative improvements from 57.8\% to 80.6\% over the strongest baseline across different target LLMs (e.g., GPT, Claude, and Gemini).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21895v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongyi Zhou, Jin Zhu, Erhan Xu, Kai Ye, Ying Yang, Chengchun Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Approximate Computation of Critical Points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that computing even very coarse approximations of critical points is intractable for simple classes of nonconvex functions. More concretely, we prove that if there exists a polynomial-time algorithm that takes as input a polynomial in $n$ variables of constant degree (as low as three) and outputs a point whose gradient has Euclidean norm at most $2^n$ whenever the polynomial has a critical point, then P=NP. The algorithm is permitted to return an arbitrary point when no critical point exists. We also prove hardness results for approximate computation of critical points under additional structural assumptions, including settings in which existence and uniqueness of a critical point are guaranteed, the function is lower bounded, and approximation is measured in terms of distance to a critical point. Overall, our results stand in contrast to the commonly-held belief that, in nonconvex optimization, approximate computation of critical points is a tractable task.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21917v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Ali Ahmadi, Georgina Hall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimistic Transfer under Task Shift via Bellman Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study online transfer reinforcement learning (RL) in episodic Markov decision processes, where experience from related source tasks is available during learning on a target task. A fundamental difficulty is that task similarity is typically defined in terms of rewards or transitions, whereas online RL algorithms operate on Bellman regression targets. As a result, naively reusing source Bellman updates introduces systematic bias and invalidates regret guarantees.
  We identify one-step Bellman alignment as the correct abstraction for transfer in online RL and propose re-weighted targeting (RWT), an operator-level correction that retargets continuation values and compensates for transition mismatch via a change of measure. RWT reduces task mismatch to a fixed one-step correction and enables statistically sound reuse of source data.
  This alignment yields a two-stage RWT $Q$-learning framework that separates variance reduction from bias correction. Under RKHS function approximation, we establish regret bounds that scale with the complexity of the task shift rather than the target MDP. Empirical results in both tabular and neural network settings demonstrate consistent improvements over single-task learning and na\"{i}ve pooling, highlighting Bellman alignment as a model-agnostic transfer principle for online RL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21924v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinhang Chai, Enpei Zhang, Elynn Chen, Yujun Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchy of discriminative power and complexity in learning quantum ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22005v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Distance metrics are central to machine learning, yet distances between ensembles of quantum states remain poorly understood due to fundamental quantum measurement constraints. We introduce a hierarchy of integral probability metrics, termed MMD-$k$, which generalizes the maximum mean discrepancy to quantum ensembles and exhibit a strict trade-off between discriminative power and statistical efficiency as the moment order $k$ increases. For pure-state ensembles of size $N$, estimating MMD-$k$ using experimentally feasible SWAP-test-based estimators requires $\Theta(N^{2-2/k})$ samples for constant $k$, and $\Theta(N^3)$ samples to achieve full discriminative power at $k = N$. In contrast, the quantum Wasserstein distance attains full discriminative power with $\Theta(N^2 \log N)$ samples. These results provide principled guidance for the design of loss functions in quantum machine learning, which we illustrate in the training quantum denoising diffusion probabilistic models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22005v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Yao, Pengtao Li, Xiaohui Chen, Quntao Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing regularisation paths of (conjugate) gradient estimators in ridge regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05542v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider standard gradient descent, gradient flow and conjugate gradients as iterative algorithms for minimising a penalised ridge criterion in linear regression. While it is well known that conjugate gradients exhibit fast numerical convergence, the statistical properties of their iterates are more difficult to assess due to inherent non-linearities and dependencies. On the other hand, standard gradient flow is a linear method with well-known regularising properties when stopped early. By an explicit non-standard error decomposition we are able to bound the prediction error for conjugate gradient iterates by a corresponding prediction error of gradient flow at transformed iteration indices. This way, the risk along the entire regularisation path of conjugate gradient iterations can be compared to that for regularisation paths of standard linear methods like gradient flow and ridge regression. In particular, the oracle conjugate gradient iterate shares the optimality properties of the gradient flow and ridge regression oracles up to a constant factor. Numerical examples show the similarity of the regularisation paths in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05542v4</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Hucker, Markus Rei{\ss}, Thomas Stark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>POLAR: A Pessimistic Model-based Policy Learning Algorithm for Dynamic Treatment Regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20406v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dynamic treatment regimes (DTRs) provide a principled framework for optimizing sequential decision-making in domains where decisions must adapt over time in response to individual trajectories, such as healthcare, education, and digital interventions. However, existing statistical methods often rely on strong positivity assumptions and lack robustness under partial data coverage, while offline reinforcement learning approaches typically focus on average training performance, lack statistical guarantees, and require solving complex optimization problems. To address these challenges, we propose POLAR, a novel pessimistic model-based policy learning algorithm for offline DTR optimization. POLAR estimates the transition dynamics from offline data and quantifies uncertainty for each history-action pair. A pessimistic penalty is then incorporated into the reward function to discourage actions with high uncertainty. Unlike many existing methods that focus on average training performance or provide guarantees only for an oracle policy, POLAR directly targets the suboptimality of the final learned policy and offers theoretical guarantees, without relying on computationally intensive minimax or constrained optimization procedures. To the best of our knowledge, POLAR is the first model-based DTR method to provide both statistical and computational guarantees, including finite-sample bounds on policy suboptimality. Empirical results on both synthetic data and the MIMIC-III dataset demonstrate that POLAR outperforms state-of-the-art methods and yields near-optimal, history-aware treatment strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20406v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruijia Zhang, Xiangyu Zhang, Zhengling Qi, Yue Wu, Yanxun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vecchia-Inducing-Points Full-Scale Approximations for Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05064v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gaussian processes are flexible, probabilistic, non-parametric models widely used in machine learning and statistics. However, their scalability to large data sets is limited by computational constraints. To overcome these challenges, we propose Vecchia-inducing-points full-scale (VIF) approximations combining the strengths of global inducing points and local Vecchia approximations. Vecchia approximations excel in settings with low-dimensional inputs and moderately smooth covariance functions, while inducing point methods are better suited to high-dimensional inputs and smoother covariance functions. Our VIF approach bridges these two regimes by using an efficient correlation-based neighbor-finding strategy for the Vecchia approximation of the residual process, implemented via a modified cover tree algorithm. We further extend our framework to non-Gaussian likelihoods by introducing iterative methods that substantially reduce computational costs for training and prediction by several orders of magnitudes compared to Cholesky-based computations when using a Laplace approximation. In particular, we propose and compare novel preconditioners and provide theoretical convergence results. Extensive numerical experiments on simulated and real-world data sets show that VIF approximations are both computationally efficient as well as more accurate and numerically stable than state-of-the-art alternatives. All methods are implemented in the open source C++ library GPBoost with high-level Python and R interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05064v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Gyger, Reinhard Furrer, Fabio Sigrist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal differentially private kernel learning with random projection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17544v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Differential privacy has become a cornerstone in the development of privacy-preserving learning algorithms. This work addresses optimizing differentially private kernel learning within the empirical risk minimization (ERM) framework. We propose a novel differentially private kernel ERM algorithm based on random projection in the reproducing kernel Hilbert space using Gaussian processes. Our method achieves minimax-optimal excess risk for both the squared loss and Lipschitz-smooth convex loss functions under a local strong convexity condition. We further show that existing approaches based on alternative dimension reduction techniques, such as random Fourier feature mappings or $\ell_2$ regularization, yield suboptimal generalization performance. Our key theoretical contribution also includes the derivation of dimension-free generalization bounds for objective perturbation-based private linear ERM -- marking the first such result that does not rely on noisy gradient-based mechanisms. Additionally, we obtain sharper generalization bounds for existing differentially private kernel ERM algorithms. Empirical evaluations support our theoretical claims, demonstrating that random projection enables statistically efficient and optimally private kernel learning. These findings provide new insights into the design of differentially private algorithms and highlight the central role of dimension reduction in balancing privacy and utility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17544v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bonwoo Lee, Cheolwoo Park, Jeongyoun Ahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the Accuracy of Amortized Model Comparison with Self-Consistency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20614v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Amortized Bayesian inference (ABI) offers fast, scalable approximations to posterior densities by training neural surrogates on data simulated from the statistical model. However, ABI methods are highly sensitive to model misspecification: when observed data fall outside the training distribution (generative scope of the statistical models), neural surrogates can behave unpredictably. This makes it a challenge in a model comparison setting, where multiple statistical models are considered, of which at least some are misspecified. Recent work on self-consistency (SC) provides a promising remedy to this issue, accessible even for empirical data (without ground-truth labels). In this work, we investigate how SC can improve amortized model comparison conceptualized in four different ways. Across two synthetic and two real-world case studies, we find that approaches for model comparison that estimate marginal likelihoods through approximate parameter posteriors consistently outperform methods that directly approximate model evidence or posterior model probabilities. SC training improves robustness when the likelihood is available, even under severe model misspecification. The benefits of SC for methods without access of analytic likelihoods are more limited and inconsistent. Our results suggest practical guidance for reliable amortized Bayesian model comparison: prefer parameter posterior-based methods and augment them with SC training on empirical datasets to mitigate extrapolation bias under model misspecification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20614v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\v{S}imon Kucharsk\'y, Aayush Mishra, Daniel Habermann, Stefan T. Radev, Paul-Christian B\"urkner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Matching Bandits with Rare Optimization Updates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04194v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a bandit framework for stochastic matching under the multinomial logit (MNL) choice model. In our setting, $N$ agents on one side are assigned to $K$ arms on the other side, where each arm stochastically selects an agent from its assigned pool according to unknown preferences and yields a corresponding reward over a horizon $T$. The objective is to minimize regret by maximizing the cumulative revenue from successful matches. A naive approach requires solving an NP-hard combinatorial optimization problem at every round, resulting in a prohibitive computational cost. To address this challenge, we propose batched algorithms that strategically limit the number of times matching assignments are updated to $\Theta(\log\log T)$ over the entire horizon. By invoking expensive combinatorial optimization only on a vanishing fraction of rounds, our algorithms substantially reduce overall computational overhead while still achieving a regret bound of $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(\sqrt{T})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04194v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jung-hun Kim, Min-hwan Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Adversarial Robustness of Learning-based Conformal Novelty Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00463v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies the adversarial robustness of conformal novelty detection. In particular, we focus on two powerful learning-based frameworks that come with finite-sample false discovery rate (FDR) control: one is AdaDetect (by Marandon et al., 2024) that is based on the positive-unlabeled classifier, and the other is a one-class classifier-based approach (by Bates et al., 2023). While they provide rigorous statistical guarantees under benign conditions, their behavior under adversarial perturbations remains underexplored. We first formulate an oracle attack setup, under the AdaDetect formulation, that quantifies the worst-case degradation of FDR, deriving an upper bound that characterizes the statistical cost of attacks. This idealized formulation directly motivates a practical and effective attack scheme that only requires query access to the output labels of both frameworks. Coupling these formulations with two popular and complementary black-box adversarial algorithms, we systematically evaluate the vulnerability of both frameworks on synthetic and real-world datasets. Our results show that adversarial perturbations can significantly increase the FDR while maintaining high detection power, exposing fundamental limitations of current error-controlled novelty detection methods and motivating the development of more robust alternatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00463v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daofu Zhang, Mehrdad Pournaderi, Hanne M. Clifford, Yu Xiang, Pramod K. Varshney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Bayesian Experimental Design for Partially Observed Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04403v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bayesian experimental design (BED) provides a principled framework for optimizing data collection by choosing experiments that are maximally informative about unknown parameters. However, existing methods cannot deal with the joint challenge of (a) partially observable dynamical systems, where only noisy and incomplete observations are available, and (b) fully online inference, which updates posterior distributions and selects designs sequentially in a computationally efficient manner. Under partial observability, dynamical systems are naturally modeled as state-space models (SSMs), where latent states mediate the link between parameters and data, making the likelihood -- and thus information-theoretic objectives like the expected information gain (EIG) -- intractable. We address these challenges by deriving new estimators of the EIG and its gradient that explicitly marginalize latent states, enabling scalable stochastic optimization in nonlinear SSMs. Our approach leverages nested particle filters for efficient online state-parameter inference with convergence guarantees. Applications to realistic models, such as the susceptible-infectious-recovered (SIR) and a moving source location task, show that our framework successfully handles both partial observability and online inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04403v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara P\'erez-Vieites, Sahel Iqbal, Simo S\"arkk\"a, Dominik Baumann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion differentiable resampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10401v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with differentiable resampling in the context of sequential Monte Carlo (e.g., particle filtering). We propose a new informative resampling method that is instantly differentiable, based on an ensemble score diffusion model. We theoretically prove that our diffusion resampling method provides a consistent resampling distribution, and we show empirically that it outperforms the state-of-the-art differentiable resampling methods on multiple filtering and parameter estimation benchmarks. Finally, we show that it achieves competitive end-to-end performance when used in learning a complex dynamics-decoder model with high-dimensional image observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10401v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Rosina Andersson, Zheng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Models in Simulation-Based Inference: A Tutorial Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20685v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diffusion models have recently emerged as powerful learners for simulation-based inference (SBI), enabling fast and accurate estimation of latent parameters from simulated and real data. Their score-based formulation offers a flexible way to learn conditional or joint distributions over parameters and observations, thereby providing a versatile solution to various modeling problems. In this tutorial review, we synthesize recent developments on diffusion models for SBI, covering design choices for training, inference, and evaluation. We highlight opportunities created by various concepts such as guidance, score composition, flow matching, consistency models, and joint modeling. Furthermore, we discuss how efficiency and statistical accuracy are affected by noise schedules, parameterizations, and samplers. Finally, we illustrate these concepts with case studies across parameter dimensionalities, simulation budgets, and model types, and outline open questions for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20685v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Arruda, Niels Bracher, Ullrich K\"othe, Jan Hasenauer, Stefan T. Radev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Mice to Trains: Amortized Bayesian Inference on Graph Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02241v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graphs arise across diverse domains, from biology and chemistry to social and information networks, as well as in transportation and logistics. Inference on graph-structured data requires methods that are permutation-invariant, scalable across varying sizes and sparsities, and capable of capturing complex long-range dependencies, making posterior estimation on graph parameters particularly challenging. Amortized Bayesian Inference (ABI) is a simulation-based framework that employs generative neural networks to enable fast, likelihood-free posterior inference. We adapt ABI to graph data to address these challenges to perform inference on node-, edge-, and graph-level parameters. Our approach couples permutation-invariant graph encoders with flexible neural posterior estimators in a two-module pipeline: a summary network maps attributed graphs to fixed-length representations, and an inference network approximates the posterior over parameters. In this setting, several neural architectures can serve as the summary network. In this work we evaluate multiple architectures and assess their performance on controlled synthetic settings and two real-world domains - biology and logistics - in terms of recovery and calibration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02241v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svenja Jedhoff, Elizaveta Semenova, Aura Raulo, Anne Meyer, Paul-Christian B\"urkner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Provable Suboptimality of Momentum SGD in Nonstationary Stochastic Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.12238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.12238v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we provide a comprehensive theoretical analysis of Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD) and its momentum variants (Polyak Heavy-Ball and Nesterov) for tracking time-varying optima under strong convexity and smoothness. Our finite-time bounds reveal a sharp decomposition of tracking error into transient, noise-induced, and drift-induced components. This decomposition exposes a fundamental trade-off: while momentum is often used as a gradient-smoothing heuristic, under distribution shift it incurs an explicit drift-amplification penalty that diverges as the momentum parameter $\beta$ approaches 1, yielding systematic tracking lag. We complement these upper bounds with minimax lower bounds under gradient-variation constraints, proving this momentum-induced tracking penalty is not an analytical artifact but an information-theoretic barrier: in drift-dominated regimes, momentum is unavoidably worse because stale-gradient averaging forces systematic lag. Our results provide theoretical grounding for the empirical instability of momentum in dynamic settings and precisely delineate regime boundaries where vanilla SGD provably outperforms its accelerated counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.12238v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharan Sahu, Cameron J. Hogan, Martin T. Wells</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Learning of Stationary Diffusions with Stein-type Discrepancies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16597v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Learning a stationary diffusion amounts to estimating the parameters of a stochastic differential equation whose stationary distribution matches a target distribution. We build on the recently introduced kernel deviation from stationarity (KDS), which enforces stationarity by evaluating expectations of the diffusion's generator in a reproducing kernel Hilbert space. Leveraging the connection between KDS and Stein discrepancies, we introduce the Stein-type KDS (SKDS) as an alternative formulation. We prove that a vanishing SKDS guarantees alignment of the learned diffusion's stationary distribution with the target. Furthermore, under broad parametrizations, SKDS is convex with an empirical version that is $\epsilon$-quasiconvex with high probability. Empirically, learning with SKDS attains comparable accuracy to KDS while substantially reducing computational cost and yields improvements over the majority of competitive baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16597v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Bleile, Sarah Lumpp, Mathias Drton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Evaluation of LLM Performance with Statistical Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20251v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exhaustively evaluating many large language models (LLMs) on a large suite of benchmarks is expensive. We cast benchmarking as finite-population inference and, under a fixed query budget, seek tight confidence intervals (CIs) for model accuracy with valid frequentist coverage. We propose Factorized Active Querying (FAQ), which (a) leverages historical information through a Bayesian factor model; (b) adaptively selects questions using a hybrid variance-reduction/active-learning sampling policy; and (c) maintains validity through Proactive Active Inference -- a finite-population extension of active inference (Zrnic &amp; Cand\`es, 2024) that enables direct question selection while preserving coverage. With negligible overhead cost, FAQ delivers up to $5\times$ effective sample size gains over strong baselines on two benchmark suites, across varying historical-data missingness levels: this means that it matches the CI width of uniform sampling while using up to $5\times$ fewer queries. We release our source code and our curated datasets to support reproducible evaluation and future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20251v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Skyler Wu, Yash Nair, Emmanuel J. Cand\`es</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parametrized Power-Iteration Clustering for Directed Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.00310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.00310v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vertex-level clustering for directed graphs (digraphs) remains challenging as edge directionality breaks the key assumptions underlying popular spectral methods, which also incur the overhead of eigen-decomposition. This paper proposes Parametrized Power-Iteration Clustering (ParPIC), a random-walk-based clustering method for weakly connected digraphs. This builds over the Power-Iteration Clustering paradigm, which uses the rows of the iterated diffusion operator as a data embedding. ParPIC has three important features: the use of parametrized reversible random walk operators, the automatic tuning of the diffusion time, and the efficient truncation of the final embedding, which produces low-dimensional data representations and reduces complexity. Empirical results on synthetic and real-world graphs demonstrate that ParPIC achieves competitive clustering accuracy with improved scalability relative to spectral and teleportation-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.00310v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gwendal Debaussart-Joniec, Harry Sevi, Matthieu Jonckheere, Argyris Kalogeratos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Detection of Changes in Moment-Based Projections: When to Retrain Deep Learners or Update Portfolios?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.07198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.07198v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Training deep learning neural networks often requires massive amounts of computational ressources. We propose to sequentially monitor network predictions to trigger retraining only if the predictions are no longer valid. This can reduce drastically computational costs and opens a door to green deep learning. Our approach is based on the relationship to projected second moments monitoring, a problem also arising in other areas such as computational finance. Various open--end as well as closed--end monitoring rules are studied under mild assumptions on the training sample and the observations of the monitoring period. The results allow for high--dimensional non-stationary time series data and thus, especially, non--i.i.d. training data. Asymptotics is based on Gaussian approximations of projected partial sums allowing for an estimated projection vector. Estimation of projection vectors is studied both for classical non--$\ell_0$--sparsity as well as under sparsity. For the case that the optimal projection depends on the unknown covariance matrix, hard-- and soft--thresholded estimators are studied. The method is analyzed by simulations and supported by synthetic data experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.07198v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ansgar Steland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal approximation property of Banach space-valued random feature models including random neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08410v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a Banach space-valued extension of random feature learning, a data-driven supervised machine learning technique for large-scale kernel approximation. By randomly initializing the feature maps, only the linear readout needs to be trained, which reduces the computational complexity substantially. Viewing random feature models as Banach space-valued random variables, we prove a universal approximation result in the corresponding Bochner space. Moreover, we derive approximation rates and an explicit algorithm to learn an element of the given Banach space by such models. The framework of this paper includes random trigonometric/Fourier regression and in particular random neural networks which are single-hidden-layer feedforward neural networks whose weights and biases are randomly initialized, whence only the linear readout needs to be trained. For the latter, we can then lift the universal approximation property of deterministic neural networks to random neural networks, even within function spaces over non-compact domains, e.g., weighted spaces, $L^p$-spaces, and (weighted) Sobolev spaces, where the latter includes the approximation of the (weak) derivatives. In addition, we analyze when the training costs for approximating a given function grow polynomially in both the input/output dimension and the reciprocal of a pre-specified tolerated approximation error. Furthermore, we demonstrate in a numerical example the empirical advantages of random feature models over their deterministic counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08410v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Neufeld, Philipp Schmocker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Laws for Downstream Task Performance of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04177v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Scaling laws provide important insights that can guide the design of large language models (LLMs). Existing work has primarily focused on studying scaling laws for pretraining (upstream) loss. However, in transfer learning settings, in which LLMs are pretrained on an unsupervised dataset and then finetuned on a downstream task, we often also care about the downstream performance. In this work, we study the scaling behavior in a transfer learning setting, where LLMs are finetuned for machine translation tasks. Specifically, we investigate how the choice of the pretraining data and its size affect downstream performance (translation quality) as judged by: downstream cross-entropy and translation quality metrics such as BLEU and COMET scores. Our experiments indicate that the size of the finetuning dataset and the distribution alignment between the pretraining and downstream data significantly influence the scaling behavior. With sufficient alignment, both downstream cross-entropy and translation quality scores improve monotonically with more pretraining data. In such cases, we show that it is possible to predict the downstream translation quality metrics with good accuracy using a log-law. However, there are cases where moderate misalignment causes the downstream translation scores to fluctuate or get worse with more pretraining, whereas downstream cross-entropy monotonically improves. By analyzing these, we provide new practical insights for choosing appropriate pretraining data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04177v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Berivan Isik, Natalia Ponomareva, Hussein Hazimeh, Dimitris Paparas, Sergei Vassilvitskii, Sanmi Koyejo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Identifiable Latent Additive Noise Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15711v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Causal representation learning (CRL) offers the promise of uncovering the underlying causal model by which observed data was generated, but the practical applicability of existing methods remains limited by the strong assumptions required for identifiability and by challenges in applying them to real-world settings. Most current approaches are applicable only to relatively restrictive model classes, such as linear or polynomial models, which limits their flexibility and robustness in practice. One promising approach to this problem seeks to address these issues by leveraging changes in causal influences among latent variables. In this vein we propose a more general and relaxed framework than typically applied, formulated by imposing constraints on the function classes applied. Within this framework, we establish partial identifiability results under weaker conditions, including scenarios where only a subset of causal influences change. We then extend our analysis to a broader class of latent post-nonlinear models. Building on these theoretical insights, we develop a flexible method for learning latent causal representations. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach on synthetic and semi-synthetic datasets, and further showcase its applicability in a case study on human motion analysis, a complex real-world domain that also highlights the potential to broaden the practical reach of identifiable CRL models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15711v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhang Liu, Zhen Zhang, Dong Gong, Erdun Gao, Biwei Huang, Mingming Gong, Anton van den Hengel, Kun Zhang, Javen Qinfeng Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harmonizing Safety and Speed: A Human-Algorithm Approach to Enhance the FDA's Medical Device Clearance Policy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11823v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The United States Food and Drug Administration's (FDA's) 510(k) pathway allows manufacturers to gain medical device approval by demonstrating substantial equivalence to a legally marketed device. However, the inherent ambiguity of this regulatory procedure has been associated with high recall among many devices cleared through this pathway, raising significant safety concerns. In this paper, we develop a combined human-algorithm approach to assist the FDA in improving its 510(k) medical device clearance process by reducing recall risk and regulatory workload. We first develop machine learning methods to estimate the risk of recall of 510(k) medical devices based on the information available at the time of submission. We then propose a data-driven clearance policy that recommends acceptance, rejection, or deferral to FDA's committees for in-depth evaluation. We conduct an empirical study using a unique dataset of over 31,000 submissions that we assembled based on data sources from the FDA and Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Service (CMS). Compared to the FDA's current practice, which has a recall rate of 10.3% and a normalized workload measure of 100%, a conservative evaluation of our policy shows a 32.9% improvement in the recall rate and a 40.5% reduction in the workload. Our analyses further suggest annual cost savings of approximately $1.7 billion for the healthcare system driven by avoided replacement costs, which is equivalent to 1.1% of the entire United States annual medical device expenditure. Our findings highlight the value of a holistic and data-driven approach to improve the FDA's current 510(k) pathway.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11823v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Zhalechian, Soroush Saghafian, Omar Robles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expected information gain estimation via density approximations: Sample allocation and dimension reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08390v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Computing expected information gain (EIG) from prior to posterior (equivalently, mutual information between candidate observations and model parameters or other quantities of interest) is a fundamental challenge in Bayesian optimal experimental design. We formulate flexible transport-based schemes for EIG estimation in general nonlinear/non-Gaussian settings, compatible with both standard and implicit Bayesian models. These schemes are representative of two-stage methods for estimating or bounding EIG using marginal and conditional density estimates. In this setting, we analyze the optimal allocation of samples between training (density estimation) and approximation of the outer prior expectation. We show that with this optimal sample allocation, the mean squared error (MSE) of the resulting EIG estimator converges more quickly than that of a standard nested Monte Carlo scheme. We then address the estimation of EIG in high dimensions, by deriving gradient-based upper bounds on the mutual information lost by projecting the parameters and/or observations to lower-dimensional subspaces. Minimizing these upper bounds yields projectors and hence low-dimensional EIG approximations that outperform approximations obtained via other linear dimension reduction schemes. Numerical experiments on a PDE-constrained Bayesian inverse problem also illustrate a favorable trade-off between dimension truncation and the modeling of non-Gaussianity, when estimating EIG from finite samples in high dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08390v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fengyi Li, Ricardo Baptista, Youssef Marzouk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Probabilistic Air-Sea Flux Parameterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03990v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurately quantifying air-sea fluxes is important for understanding air-sea interactions and improving coupled weather and climate systems. This study introduces a probabilistic framework to represent the highly variable nature of air-sea fluxes, which is missing in deterministic bulk algorithms. Assuming Gaussian distributions conditioned on the input variables, we use artificial neural networks and eddy-covariance measurement data to estimate the mean and variance by minimizing negative log-likelihood loss. The trained neural networks provide alternative mean flux estimates to existing bulk algorithms, and quantify the uncertainty around the mean estimates. Stochastic parameterization of air-sea turbulent fluxes can be constructed by sampling from the predicted distributions. Tests in a single-column forced upper-ocean model suggest that changes in flux algorithms influence sea surface temperature and mixed layer depth seasonally. The ensemble spread in stochastic runs is most pronounced during spring restratification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03990v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiarong Wu, Pavel Perezhogin, David John Gagne, Brandon Reichl, Aneesh C. Subramanian, Elizabeth Thompson, Laure Zanna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incorporating the ChEES Criterion into Sequential Monte Carlo Samplers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02627v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods are a powerful but computationally expensive way of performing non-parametric Bayesian inference. MCMC proposals which utilise gradients, such as Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC), can better explore the parameter space of interest if the additional hyper-parameters are chosen well. The No-U-Turn Sampler (NUTS) is a variant of HMC which is extremely effective at selecting these hyper-parameters but is slow to run and is not suited to GPU architectures. An alternative to NUTS, Change in the Estimator of the Expected Square HMC (ChEES-HMC) was shown not only to run faster than NUTS on GPU but also sample from posteriors more efficiently. Sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) samplers are another sampling method which instead output weighted samples from the posterior. They are very amenable to parallelisation and therefore being run on GPUs while having additional flexibility in their choice of proposal over MCMC. We incorporate (ChEEs-HMC) as a proposal into SMC samplers and demonstrate competitive but faster performance than NUTS on a number of tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02627v2</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Millard, Joshua Murphy, Daniel Frisch, Simon Maskell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilising Gradient-Based Proposals Within Sequential Monte Carlo Samplers for Training of Partial Bayesian Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03797v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Partial Bayesian neural networks (pBNNs) have been shown to perform competitively with fully Bayesian neural networks while only having a subset of the parameters be stochastic. Using sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) samplers as the inference method for pBNNs gives a non-parametric probabilistic estimation of the stochastic parameters, and has shown improved performance over parametric methods. In this paper we introduce a new SMC-based training method for pBNNs by utilising a guided proposal and incorporating gradient-based Markov kernels, which gives us better scalability on high dimensional problems. We show that our new method outperforms the state-of-the-art in terms of predictive performance and optimal loss. We also show that pBNNs scale well with larger batch sizes, resulting in significantly reduced training times and often better performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03797v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Millard, Joshua Murphy, Simon Maskell, Zheng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metric Graph Kernels via the Tropical Torelli Map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12129v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the first graph kernels for metric graphs via tropical algebraic geometry. In contrast to conventional graph kernels based on graph combinatorics such as nodes, edges, and subgraphs, our metric graph kernels are purely based on the geometry and topology of the underlying metric space. A key characterizing property of our construction is its invariance under edge subdivision, making the kernels intrinsically well-suited for comparing graphs representing different underlying metric spaces. We develop efficient algorithms to compute our kernels and analyze their complexity, which depends primarily on the genus of the input graphs rather than their size. Through experiments on synthetic data and selected real-world datasets, we demonstrate that our kernels capture complementary geometric and topological information overseen by standard combinatorial approaches, particularly in label-free settings. We further showcase their practical utility with an urban road network classification task.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12129v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueqi Cao, Anthea Monod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representative Action Selection for Large Action Space Bandit Families</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18269v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the problem of selecting a subset from a large action space shared by a family of bandits, with the goal of achieving performance nearly matching that of using the full action space. Indeed, in many natural situations, while the nominal set of actions may be large, there also exist significant correlations between the rewards of different actions. In this paper we propose an algorithm that can significantly reduce the action space when such correlations are present, without the need to a-priori know the correlation structure. We provide theoretical guarantees on the performance of the algorithm and demonstrate its practical effectiveness through empirical comparisons with Thompson Sampling and Upper Confidence Bound methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18269v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quan Zhou, Mark Kozdoba, Shie Mannor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dealing with Uncertainty in Contextual Anomaly Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04490v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Contextual anomaly detection (CAD) aims to identify anomalies in a target (behavioral) variable conditioned on a set of contextual variables that influence the normalcy of the target variable but are not themselves indicators of anomaly. In many anomaly detection tasks, there exist contextual variables that influence the normalcy of the target variable but are not themselves indicators of anomaly. In this work, we propose a novel framework for CAD, normalcy score (NS), that explicitly models both the aleatoric and epistemic uncertainties. Built on heteroscedastic Gaussian process regression, our method regards the Z-score as a random variable, providing confidence intervals that reflect the reliability of the anomaly assessment. Through experiments on benchmark datasets and a real-world application in cardiology, we demonstrate that NS outperforms state-of-the-art CAD methods in both detection accuracy and interpretability. Moreover, confidence intervals enable an adaptive, uncertainty-driven decision-making process, which may be very important in domains such as healthcare.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04490v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Bindini, Lorenzo Perini, Stefano Nistri, Jesse Davis, Paolo Frasconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Effort, Low Gain: Fundamental Limits of Active Learning for Linear Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11907v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we consider the problem of identifying an unknown linear dynamical system given a finite hypothesis class. In particular, we analyze the effect of the excitation input on the sample complexity of identifying the true system with high probability. To this end, we present sample complexity lower bounds that capture the choice of the selected excitation input. The sample complexity lower bound gives rise to a system theoretic condition to determine the potential benefit of experiment design. Informed by the analysis of the sample complexity lower bound, we propose a persistent excitation (PE) condition tailored to the considered setting, which we then use to establish sample complexity upper bounds. Notably, the PE condition is weaker than in the case of an infinite hypothesis class and allows analyzing different excitation inputs modularly. Crucially, the lower and upper bounds share the same dependency on key problem parameters. Finally, we leverage these insights to propose an active learning algorithm that sequentially excites the system optimally with respect to the current estimate, and provide sample complexity guarantees for the presented algorithm. Concluding simulations showcase the effectiveness of the proposed algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11907v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Chatzikiriakos, Kevin Jamieson, Andrea Iannelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning. The Science of Selection under Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21547v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Learning, whether natural or artificial, is a process of selection. It starts with a set of candidate options and selects the more successful ones. In the case of machine learning the selection is done based on empirical estimates of prediction accuracy of candidate prediction rules on some data. Due to randomness of data sampling the empirical estimates are inherently noisy, leading to selection under uncertainty. The book provides statistical tools to obtain theoretical guarantees on the outcome of selection under uncertainty. We start with concentration of measure inequalities, which are the main statistical instrument for controlling how much an empirical estimate of expectation of a function deviates from the true expectation. The book covers a broad range of inequalities, including Markov's, Chebyshev's, Hoeffding's, Bernstein's, Empirical Bernstein's, Unexpected Bernstein's, kl, and split-kl. We then study the classical (offline) supervised learning and provide a range of tools for deriving generalization bounds, including Occam's razor, Vapnik-Chervonenkis analysis, and PAC-Bayesian analysis. The latter is further applied to derive generalization guarantees for weighted majority votes. After covering the offline setting, we turn our attention to online learning. We present the space of online learning problems characterized by environmental feedback, environmental resistance, and structural complexity. A common performance measure in online learning is regret, which compares performance of an algorithm to performance of the best prediction rule in hindsight, out of a restricted set of prediction rules. We present tools for deriving regret bounds in stochastic and adversarial environments, and under full information and bandit feedback.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21547v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yevgeny Seldin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DPMM-CFL: Clustered Federated Learning via Dirichlet Process Mixture Model Nonparametric Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07132v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Clustered Federated Learning (CFL) improves performance under non-IID client heterogeneity by clustering clients and training one model per cluster, thereby balancing between a global model and fully personalized models. However, most CFL methods require the number of clusters K to be fixed a priori, which is impractical when the latent structure is unknown. We propose DPMM-CFL, a CFL algorithm that places a Dirichlet Process (DP) prior over the distribution of cluster parameters. This enables nonparametric Bayesian inference to jointly infer both the number of clusters and client assignments, while optimizing per-cluster federated objectives. This results in a method where, at each round, federated updates and cluster inferences are coupled, as presented in this paper. The algorithm is validated on benchmark datasets under Dirichlet and class-split non-IID partitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07132v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariona Jaramillo-Civill, Peng Wu, Pau Closas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Policy Learning with Abstention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19672v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Policy learning algorithms are widely used in areas such as personalized medicine and advertising to develop individualized treatment regimes. However, most methods force a decision even when predictions are uncertain, which is risky in high-stakes settings. We study policy learning with abstention, where a policy may defer to a safe default or an expert. When a policy abstains, it receives a small additive reward on top of the value of a random guess. We propose a two-stage learner that first identifies a set of near-optimal policies and then constructs an abstention rule from their disagreements. We establish fast O(1/n)-type regret guarantees when propensities are known, and extend these guarantees to the unknown-propensity case via a doubly robust (DR) objective. We further show that abstention is a versatile tool with direct applications to other core problems in policy learning: it yields improved guarantees under margin conditions without the common realizability assumption, connects to distributionally robust policy learning by hedging against small data shifts, and supports safe policy improvement by ensuring improvement over a baseline policy with high probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19672v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayush Sawarni, Jikai Jin, Justin Whitehouse, Vasilis Syrgkanis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry-Aware Deep Congruence Networks for Manifold Learning in Cross-Subject Motor Imagery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18940v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cross-subject motor-imagery decoding remains a major challenge in EEG-based brain-computer interfaces. To mitigate strong inter-subject variability, recent work has emphasized manifold-based approaches operating on covariance representations. Yet dispersion scaling and orientation alignment remain largely unaddressed in existing methods. In this paper, we address both issues through congruence transforms and introduce three complementary geometry-aware models: (i) Discriminative Congruence Transform (DCT), (ii) Deep Linear DCT (DLDCT), and (iii) Deep DCT-UNet (DDCT-UNet). These models are evaluated both as pre-alignment modules for downstream classifiers and as end-to-end discriminative systems trained via cross-entropy backpropagation with a custom logistic-regression head. Across challenging motor-imagery benchmarks, the proposed framework improves transductive cross-subject accuracy by 2-3%, demonstrating the value of geometry-aware congruence learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18940v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjeev Manivannan (Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai, India), Chandrashekar Lakshminarayan (Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai, India)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Set of Rules for Model Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20711v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The validation of a data-driven model is the process of assessing the model's ability to generalize to new, unseen data in the population of interest. This paper proposes a set of general rules for model validation. These rules are designed to help practitioners create reliable validation plans and report their results transparently. While no validation scheme is flawless, these rules can help practitioners ensure their strategy is sufficient for practical use, openly discuss any limitations of their validation strategy, and report clear, comparable performance metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20711v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/cem.70110</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Camacho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pushing the Limits of Distillation-Based Class-Incremental Learning via Lightweight Plugins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03537v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Existing replay and distillation-based class-incremental learning (CIL) methods are effective at retaining past knowledge but are still constrained by the stability-plasticity dilemma. Since their resulting models are learned over a sequence of incremental tasks, they encode rich representations and can be regarded as pre-trained bases. Building on this view, we propose a plug-in extension paradigm termed Deployment of LoRA Components (DLC) to enhance them. For each task, we use Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) to inject task-specific residuals into the base model's deep layers. During inference, representations with task-specific residuals are aggregated to produce classification predictions. To mitigate interference from non-target LoRA plugins, we introduce a lightweight weighting unit. This unit learns to assign importance scores to different LoRA-tuned representations. Like downloadable content in software, DLC serves as a plug-and-play enhancement that efficiently extends the base methods. Remarkably, on the large-scale ImageNet-100, with merely 4\% of the parameters of a standard ResNet-18, our DLC model achieves a significant 8\% improvement in accuracy, demonstrating exceptional efficiency. Under a fixed memory budget, methods equipped with DLC surpass state-of-the-art expansion-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03537v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiming Xu, Baile Xu, Jian Zhao, Furao Shen, Suorong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Let the Optimizers Optimize Themselves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06370v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We lay the theoretical foundation for automating optimizer design in gradient-based learning. Based on the greedy principle, we formulate the problem of designing optimizers and their hyperparameters as maximizing the instantaneous decrease in loss. By treating an optimizer as a function that translates loss gradient signals into parameter motions, the problem reduces to a family of convex optimization problems over the space of optimizers. Solving these problems under various constraints not only recovers a wide range of popular optimizers as closed-form solutions, but also produces the optimal hyperparameters of these optimizers with respect to the problems at hand. This enables a systematic approach to design optimizers and tune their hyperparameters dynamically according to the gradient statistics that are collected during the training process. Furthermore, this optimization of optimization can be performed dynamically during training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06370v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaerin Lee, Kyoung Mu Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autoregressive Language Models are Secretly Energy-Based Models: Insights into the Lookahead Capabilities of Next-Token Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.15605v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Autoregressive models (ARMs) currently constitute the dominant paradigm for large language models (LLMs). Energy-based models (EBMs) represent another class of models, which have historically been less prevalent in LLM development, yet naturally characterize the optimal policy in post-training alignment. In this paper, we provide a unified view of these two model classes. Taking the chain rule of probability as a starting point, we establish an explicit bijection between ARMs and EBMs in function space, which we show to correspond to a special case of the soft Bellman equation in maximum entropy reinforcement learning. Building upon this bijection, we derive the equivalence between supervised learning of ARMs and EBMs. Furthermore, we analyze the distillation of EBMs into ARMs by providing theoretical error bounds. Our results provide insights into the ability of ARMs to plan ahead, despite being based on the next-token prediction paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.15605v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Blondel, Michael E. Sander, Germain Vivier-Ardisson, Tianlin Liu, Vincent Roulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorizable joint shift revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.15036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.15036v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Factorizable joint shift (FJS) represents a type of distribution shift (or dataset shift) that comprises both covariate and label shift. Recently, it has been observed that FJS actually arises from consecutive label and covariate (or vice versa) shifts. Research into FJS so far has been confined to the case of categorical labels. We propose a framework for analysing distribution shift in the case of a general label space, thus covering both classification and regression models. Based on the framework, we generalise existing results on FJS to general label spaces and present and analyse a related extension of the expectation maximisation (EM) algorithm for class prior probabilities. We also take a fresh look at generalized label shift (GLS) in the case of a general label space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.15036v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dirk Tasche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence Analysis of Randomized Subspace Normalized SGD under Heavy-Tailed Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20399v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Randomized subspace methods reduce per-iteration cost; however, in nonconvex optimization, most analyses are expectation-based, and high-probability bounds remain scarce even under sub-Gaussian noise. We first prove that randomized subspace SGD (RS-SGD) admits a high-probability convergence bound under sub-Gaussian noise, achieving the same order of oracle complexity as prior in-expectation results. Motivated by the prevalence of heavy-tailed gradients in modern machine learning, we then propose randomized subspace normalized SGD (RS-NSGD), which integrates direction normalization into subspace updates. Assuming the noise has bounded $p$-th moments, we establish both in-expectation and high-probability convergence guarantees, and show that RS-NSGD can achieve better oracle complexity than full-dimensional normalized SGD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20399v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaku Omiya, Pierre-Louis Poirion, Akiko Takeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
