<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AC</link>
    <description>math.AC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 05:01:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Locally prime modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a commutative unital ring $R$ with fixed ideals $I$ and $J$, we introduce and study $I$-prime $R$-modules and $(I, J)$-prime $R$-modules together with their duals $I$-coprime $R$-modules and $(I,J)$-coprime $R$-modules respectively. We employ category-theoretic techniques to reveal their structural properties. Our main results are versions of the Greenlees-May Duality and the Matlis-Greenlees-May Equivalence to the setting of these prime and coprime modules. This generalizes work on $I$-reduced modules and $I$-coreduced modules. We demonstrate that these ``locally prime" modules serve as a tool for studying the classical ``globally prime" modules, creating a bridge between local and global primality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18804v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sholastica Luambano, David Ssevviiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Betti numbers of ideals generated by $n+1$ powers of general linear forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.19978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.19978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study ideals generated by $n+1$ powers of general linear forms in $R= k[x_1,\dots,x_n]$. By generalizing the ideas in a recent paper of Diethorn et al., we determine the Betti numbers of such ideals when at least one generator is a square. It follows that all such ideals are level. As a consequence, we show that a generic ideal in $R$ generated by $n+1$ forms, with at least one quadric generator, is level. We also determine the Betti numbers of the Artinian Gorenstein algebras linked to these almost complete intersections. By describing the dual generators of these algebras, we obtain a family of forms, including the elementary symmetric polynomials, whose annihilator ideals have the strong Lefschetz property. Finally, we give explicit generators for the annihilator ideal of any elementary symmetric polynomial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.19978v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Dannetun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Balanced pairs, virtually Gorenstein rings, and cotorsion torsion triples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18818v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For any ring $R$, we investigate balanced pairs of classes of modules and their relations to cotorsion triples. We characterize the case when a balanced pair generates a tilting cotorsion pair, and dually, when it cogenerates a cotilting cotorsion pair. If $R$ is right noetherian, we prove that the pair consisting of Gorenstein projective modules and Gorenstein injective modules is balanced if and only if $R$ is right virtually Gorenstein.
  In [4], cotorsion torsion triples in abelian categories were employed in the representation theory of rectangular grids occurring in persistent homology theory. For module categories, we use infinite dimensional tilting theory to completely classify all cotorsion torsion triples by means of $1$-resolving subcategories of $\rfmod R$, and to give an explicit 1-1 correspondence between the formally dual notions of cotorsion torsion triples of right $R$-modules and torsion cotorsion triples of left $R$-modules. This correspondence is bijective in case the underlying ring $R$ is left noetherian, but not in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18818v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Estrada, Jiangsheng Hu, Jan Trlifaj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relevant maps and the algebraic skeleton of simplicial toric prevarieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.19765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.19765v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Morphisms between schemes arising from multigraded rings are essential for understanding geometric relationships in algebraic geometry, yet a systematic theory for such maps has been lacking. In this paper, we develop a comprehensive framework for rational maps between multigraded Proj schemes by introducing several notions of maps between their underlying multigraded rings. A key challenge is that to induce actual morphisms (rather than just rational maps), the ring homomorphism $\varphi\colon R \to S$ must hit every relevant element in $S$. To address this, we introduce the use of relevant subsets $B \subseteq S_+$ (where $S_+$ is the ideal generated by all relevant elements), $B \unlhd S$, which allow us to control this condition more flexibly.
  As an application, we show that multigraded noetherian polynomial rings naturally encode combinatorial data, giving rise to systems of fans and thus to toric prevarieties. By leveraging our notion of rational maps with those relevant subsets, we prove that the category of triples $(D, S, B)$ - where $D$ is a finitely generated abelian group, $S$ is a $D$-graded noetherian polynomial ring, and $B \unlhd S$ is a subset of $S_+$ - together with rational maps of conical rings, is anti-equivalent to the category of simplicial toric prevarieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.19765v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Goebler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector invariants for two-dimensional orthogonal groups over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.06039</link>
      <description>arXiv:1612.06039v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb{F}_{q}$ be a finite field of characteristic $2$ and $O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q})$ be the $2$-dimensional orthogonal group of plus type over $\mathbb{F}_{q}$. Consider the standard representation $V$ of $O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q})$ and the ring of vector invariants $\mathbb{F}_{q}[mV]^{O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q})}$ for any $m\in \mathbb{N}^{+}$. We prove a first main theorem for $(O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q}),V)$, i.e., we find a minimal generating set for $\mathbb{F}_{q}[mV]^{O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q})}$. As a consequence, we derive the Noether number $\beta_{mV}(O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q}))=\max\{q-1,m\}$. We construct a free basis for $\mathbb{F}_{q}[2V]^{O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q})}$ over a suitably chosen homogeneous system of parameters. We also obtain a generating set of the Hilbert ideal for $\mathbb{F}_{q}[mV]^{O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q})}$ which shows that the Hilbert ideal can be generated by invariants of degree $\leqslant q-1=\frac{|O_2^+(\mathbb{F}_{q})|}{2}$, positively confirming a conjecure of Derksen and Kemper for this particular case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1612.06039v3</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00605-017-1111-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monatsh. Math. 187 (2018) 479--497</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prime ideals of Moh and the characteristic of the field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21692v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We reprove and generalize a result of Moh which gives a lower bound on the minimal number of generators of an ideal in a power series ring in three variables x,y,z over a field k. As a consequence, in each characteristic of the field k, we obtain a minimal generating set for the prime ideal P of Moh corresponding to n=3. We deduce that the minimal number of generators of P might decrease depending on the characteristic of k. This contradicts a statement of Sally and leaves as an open problem to find families of prime ideals in the power series ring in the variables x,y,z with an unbounded minimal number of generators, when k has characteristic other than zero. Finally, we show that these minimal generating sets of P are standard basis with the negative degree reverse lexicographic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21692v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Gonz\'alez, Francesc Planas-Vilanova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CW-complexes and minimal Hilbert vector of graded Artinian Gorenstein algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13276v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I introduce a geometric interpretation of the set of standard graded Artinian Gorenstein algebras of codimension n and degree d: the standard locus, which is a subset of the projective space of degree d polynomials in n variables, and I characterize it. Under opportune hypothesis, I prove that the locus of full Perazzo polynomials is the union of the minimal dimensional irreducible components of the standard locus and it is a pure dimensional subset. On the other hand, I associate to any homogeneous polynomial a topological space, which is a CW-complex. Using all these sets, I prove that the Hilbert function restricted to the standard locus has minimal values on any irreducible component of the domain. I apply all this to the Full Perazzo Conjecture and I prove it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13276v3</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armando Capasso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost Noetherian rings and modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05996v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the notions of almost Noetherian rings and modules. In details, we give the Cohen type theorem, Eakin-Nagata type theorem, Kaplansky type Theorem and Hilbert basis theorem and some other rings constructions for almost Noetherian rings. In particular, we resolve a question proposed in \cite[9, B. Zavyalov, {\it Almost coherent modules and almost coherent sheaves}, Memoirs of the European Mathematical Society 19. Berlin: European Mathematical Society (EMS), 2025] under a certain condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05996v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaolei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macaulay Constants and Vanishing of Cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16619v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dub\'e introduced cone decompositions and their Macaulay constants and used them to obtain an upper bound on the degrees of the generators in a Gr\"obner basis of an ideal. Liang extended the theory to submodules of a free module. In this paper, Macaulay constants of any finitely generated graded module $M$ over a polynomial ring are introduced by adapting the concept of a cone decomposition to $M$. It is shown that these constants provide upper bounds for the degrees in which the local cohomology modules of $M$ are not zero. The results include an upper bound on the Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity of $M$ and a generalization of Gotzmann's Regularity Theorem from ideals to modules. As an application, an upper bound on the Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity of any coherent sheaf on projective space is established. The mentioned bounds are sharp even for cyclic modules. Furthermore, Macaulay constants are utilized to provide a characterization of Hilbert polynomials of finitely generated graded modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16619v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uwe Nagel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Complete Intersection Discrepancy of a Curve II: Families of Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16558v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study equisingularity of families of reduced curves over smooth parameter spaces of arbitrary positive dimension, using the difference between two analytic invariants of a curve singularity: the multiplicity of its Jacobian ideal and its complete intersection discrepancy. This difference provides a fiberwise multiplicity criterion for Whitney equisingularity. We prove that Whitney equisingularity (equivalently, strong simultaneous resolution) is characterized by equidimensionality of the fibers of the exceptional locus of either the relative conormal space or the relative Nash blowup. We further show that this condition is equivalent to the emptiness of the relative polar variety of smallest dimension. In addition, we establish that the Milnor number of a reduced curve is Zariski upper semicontinuous. As an application, we show that the constancy of the Milnor number in a family of reduced curves is equivalent to its topological equisingularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16558v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Bengu\c{s}-Lasnier, Terence Gaffney, Antoni Rangachev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graded Betti numbers of the Jacobian algebra of surfaces in $\mathbb P^3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.09966v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute an explicit closed formula for the Hilbert polynomial of the Jacobian algebra $M(f)$ of a reduced surface $X:f=0$ in $\mathbb P^3$ in terms of the graded Betti numbers of the algebra $M(f)$. When $X$ has only isolated singularities, a result by A. du Plessis and C. T. C. Wall yields new necessary condition for a set of positive integers to be the graded Betti numbers of the Jacobian algebra of such a surface. The comparison with the plane curve case is discussed in detail and additional information is given in the case of nodal surfaces. In the final section we construct four natural Jacobian syzygies for surfaces $X$ coming from pencils of surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.09966v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandru Dimca, Gabriel Sticlaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
