<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AC</link>
    <description>math.AC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 05:00:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Symbolic powers and integral closures via extremal ideals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper demonstrates that extremal ideals can be used to great effect to compute integral closures of powers and symbolic powers of square-free monomial ideals. We show that the generators of these powers are images of the generators of the corresponding powers of extremal ideals under a specific ring homomorphism.
  Extremal ideals provide sharp bounds for a variety of invariants widely studied in the literature, including resurgence, asymptotic resurgence, and symbolic defect, as well as Betti numbers of symbolic powers and of integral closures of powers of square-free monomial ideals. When restricted to the class of extremal ideals, algebraic computations are reduced to problems of discrete geometry and linear programming, allowing the use of a wide variety of techniques.
  As a result, in situations where computations are feasible for extremal ideals, we provide concrete sharp bounds for many of these invariants. Our methods reduce finding homological invariants and algebraic constructions for infinitely many ideals to computations for a single highly symmetric ideal, based solely on the number of generators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05076v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trung Chau, Art Duval, Sara Faridi, Thiago Holleben, Susan Morey, Liana \c{S}ega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagonal F-thresholds for determinants and Pfaffians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05761v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the diagonal F-thresholds of determinantal hypersurfaces arising from a generic matrix and from a generic symmetric matrix, as well as of the Pfaffian hypersurface arising from a generic skew-symmetric matrix of even size. The main ingredient is a cohomology vanishing theorem for certain line bundles on flag varieties in characteristic $p$. In the cases of the generic matrix and the generic skew-symmetric matrix, we show that the diagonal F-threshold attains its minimal possible value, namely the negative of the a-invariant. The symmetric case is more subtle and relies in addition on a polynomiality result for representations afforded by cohomology, building on work of the second author with VandeBogert.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05761v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barbara Betti, Claudiu Raicu, Francesco Romeo, Jyoti Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational Interpreters for Discrete Dynamics: Existence, Exactness, and Decomposition over $p$-adic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05433v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We address an inverse problem in non-Archimedean dynamics: given a finite discrete dynamical system (equivalently, a functional graph on $N$ states), construct a continuous $p$-adic dynamical system whose residue-level behavior reproduces the prescribed transitions. Using the cylinder partition of $\mathcal{O}_K$ (viewed as \emph{Witt cylinders} for unramified $K/\mathbb{Q}_p$), we encode states by pairwise disjoint closed balls and formalize an \textbf{interpreter} as a map sending each state ball into its target ball.
  Our main existence result constructs rational interpreters that are analytic (hence pole-free) on the prescribed state cylinders, combining rigid-analytic Runge approximation with finite interpolation constraints. Under a linear-dominance condition on each cylinder, ball images are explicit and locally affine, leading to a robust classification of discrete behavior into contractive, indifferent, and expansive regimes. Good reduction provides a selection principle for natural interpreters; effective degree and height bounds for general rational interpreters remain open.
  For composite alphabets we prove a \textbf{Dynamic Chinese Remainder Theorem} for congruence-preserving systems: the CRT isomorphism $\Theta:\mathbb{Z}/m\mathbb{Z}\xrightarrow{\sim}\prod_i\mathbb{Z}/p_i^{k_i}\mathbb{Z}$ (for $m=\prod p_i^{k_i}$) yields a factorization of the \emph{dynamics} (equivalently, the functional graph) on $\mathbb{Z}/m\mathbb{Z}$ into dynamics on the prime-power components, compatible with reduction. Finally, we discuss an inverse-limit (profinite) extension: compatible towers define a $1$-Lipschitz map on $\mathbb{Z}_p$, while selecting compatible analytic/rational interpreters across levels becomes a separate problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05433v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Rogelio P\'erez-Buend\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Almost) Complete Intersection Lov\'{a}sz-Saks-Schrijver ideals and regularity of their powers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.09190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.09190v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss the property of (almost) complete intersection of LSS-ideals of graphs of some special forms, like trees, unicyclic, and bicyclic graphs. Further, we give a sufficient condition for the complete intersection property of twisted LSS-ideals in terms of a new graph theoretical invariant called twisted positive matching decomposition number denoted by tpmd.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.09190v4</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0219498826500933</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Marie Amalore Nambi, Neeraj Kumar, Chitra Venugopal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abelian extensions of equicharacteristic regular rings need not be Cohen-Macaulay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19800v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By a theorem of Roberts, the integral closure of a regular local ring in a finite abelian extension of its fraction field is Cohen-Macaulay, provided that the degree of the extension is coprime to the characteristic of the residue field. We show that the result need not hold in the absence of this requirement on the characteristic: for each positive prime integer $p$, we construct polynomial rings over fields of characteristic $p$, whose integral closure in an elementary abelian extension of order $p^2$ is not Cohen-Macaulay. Localizing at the homogeneous maximal ideal preserves the essential features of the construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19800v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aryaman Maithani, Anurag K. Singh, Prashanth Sridhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
