<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.other updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other</link>
    <description>cond-mat.other updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 01:50:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exclusive-or encoded algebraic structure for efficient quantum dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09312v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a formalism that captures the algebraic structure of many-body two-level quantum systems, and directly motivates an efficient numerical method. This formalism is based on the binary representation of the enumeration-indices of the elements of the corresponding Lie algebra. The action of arbitrarily large elements of that algebra reduces to a few bit-wise exclusive-or operations. This formalism naturally produces sparse representations of many-body density operators, the size of which we control through a dynamic truncation method. We demonstrate how this formalism applies to real-time evolution, dissipative Lindblad action, imaginary-time evolution, and projective measurement processes. We find that this approach to calculating quantum dynamics scales close to linearly with the number of non-zero components in the density operator. We refer to this exclusive-or represented quantum algebra as ORQA. As a proof of concept, we provide a numerical demonstration of this formalism by simulating quantum annealing processes for the maximum independent set problem for up to 22 two-level systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09312v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Broers, Ludwig Mathey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet time-crystals as sensors of AC fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03927v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The long range spatial and temporal ordering displayed by discrete time crystals, can become advantageous properties when used for sensing extremely weak signals. Here, we investigate their performance as quantum sensors of weak AC-fields and demonstrate, using the quantum Fisher information measure, that they can overcome the shot noise limit while allowing long interrogation times. In such systems, collective interactions stabilize their dynamics against noise making them robust enough to protocol imperfections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03927v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Iemini, Rosario Fazio, Anna Sanpera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bang-bang preparation of quantum many-body ground states in two dimensions: optimization of the algorithm with a two-dimensional tensor network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09158v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A bang-bang (BB) algorithm prepares the ground state of a two-dimensional (2D) quantum many-body Hamiltonian $H=H_1+H_2$ by evolving an initial product state alternating between $H_1$ and $H_2$. We use the neighborhood tensor update to simulate the BB evolution with an infinite pair-entangled projected state (iPEPS). The alternating sequence is optimized with the final energy as a cost function. The energy is calculated with the tangent space methods for the sake of their stability.
  The method is benchmarked in the 2D transverse field quantum Ising model near its quantum critical point against a ground state obtained by variational optimization of the iPEPS. The optimal BB sequence differs non-perturbatively from a sequence simulating quantum annealing or adiabatic preparation (AP) of the ground state. The optimal BB energy converges with the number of bangs much faster than the optimal AP energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09158v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yintai Zhang, Jacek Dziarmaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
