<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.other updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other</link>
    <description>cond-mat.other updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 02:30:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting quantum materials properties using novel faithful machine learning embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine Learning (ML) is accelerating the progress of materials prediction and classification, with particular success in CGNN designs. While classical ML methods remain accessible, advanced deep networks are still challenging to build and train. We introduce two new adaptations and refine two existing ML networks for generic crystalline quantum materials properties prediction and optimization. These new models achieve state-of-the-art performance in predicting TQC classification and strong performance in predicting band gaps, magnetic classifications, formation energies, and symmetry group. All networks easily generalize to all quantum crystalline materials property predictions. To support this, full implementations and automated methods for data handling and materials predictions are provided, facilitating the use of deep ML methods in quantum materials science. Finally, dataset error rates are analyzed using an ensemble model to identify and highlight highly atypical materials for further investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18388v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gavin Nop, Micah Mundy, Durga Paudyal, Jonathan Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Piezoelectricity in Sustainable-by-design Chitosan Nanocomposite Elastomers for Prosthetics, Robotics, and Circular Electronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Piezoelectricity, the generation of electric charge in response to mechanical stress, is a key property in both natural and synthetic materials. This study significantly boosts the piezoelectric response of chitosan, a biodegradable biopolymer, by integrating chitin/chitosan nanocrystals into natural chitosan-based thin film elastomers. The resulting materials achieve d$_{33}$ values of 15-19 pmV$^{-1}$, a marked improvement over the 5-9 pmV$^{-1}$ observed in pure chitosan films thanks to increased crystallinity from the nanocrystals. We utilize piezoresponse force microscopy (PFM) to accurately measure the d$_{33}$ coefficient, employing an engineered extraction method that eliminates the electrostatic contribution, which can overestimate the piezoelectric response. The resulting chitosan elastomers exhibit elastic deformation up to 40\% strain and a Young's modulus of approximately 100 MPa, similar to soft tissues. These properties, along with the fact that the employed materials can be entirely crafted from upcycled biowaste, make these elastomers ideal for prosthetics, wearable devices, energy harvesters, and sustainable transducers. Our findings underscore the potential of chitosan-based piezoelectric materials for advanced applications in biotechnology, soft robotics, and the green Internet of Things.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18585v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Nicoletti, Leonardo Puppulin, Julie Routurier, Saimir Frroku, Nouha Loudhaief, Claudia Crestini, Alvise Perosa, Maurizio Selva, Matteo Gigli, Domenico De Fazio, Giovanni Antonio Salvatore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diverging shift current responses in the gapless limit of two-dimensional systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18565v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The shift current responses of two-dimensional systems in the gapless limit are investigated. As the energy gap becomes smaller, the interband transition probability becomes larger at the band edges. We found the divergence of the shift current response in a manner proportional to the inverse of the gap size when the system becomes a two-dimensional Weyl semimetal in the gapless limit. This behavior is different from that for electric polarization, which has a jump across the gapless case. It means that the quantitative relationship between electric polarizations and shift currents is broken in this gapless limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18565v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Yoshida, Shuichi Murakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superfluid Spin-up: 3D Simulations of Postglitch Dynamics in Neutron Stars Cores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18810v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Following a glitch, a neutron star interior undergoes a transfer of angular momentum from the star's crust to the core, resulting in the spin-up of the latter. The crust-core coupling, which determines how quickly this spin-up proceeds, can be achieved through various physical processes, including Ekman pumping, superfluid vortex-mediated mutual friction, and magnetic fields. While the complexity of the problem has hindered studies of the mechanisms' combined action, analytical work on individual processes suggests different spin-up timescales depending on the relative strength of Coriolis, viscous, and mutual friction forces, and the magnetic field, respectively. However, experimental and numerical validations of these results are limited. In this paper, we focus on viscous effects and mutual friction and conduct non-linear hydrodynamical simulations of the spin-up problem in a two-component fluid by solving the incompressible Hall$-$Vinen$-$Bekarevich$-$Khalatnikov (HVBK) equations in the full sphere (i.e., including $r=0$) for the first time. We find that the viscous (normal) component accelerates due to Ekman pumping, although the mutual friction coupling to the superfluid component alters the spin-up dynamics compared to the single-fluid scenario. Close to the sphere's surface, the response of the superfluid is accurately described by the mutual friction timescale irrespective of its coupling strength with the normal component. However, as we move deeper into the sphere, the superfluid accelerates on different timescales due to the slow viscous spin-up of the internal normal fluid layers. We discuss potential implications for neutron stars and requirements for future work to build more realistic models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18810v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. R. Fuentes, Vanessa Graber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corner and Edge States in Topological Sierpinski Carpet Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13774v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fractal lattices, with their self-similar and intricate structures, offer potential platforms for engineering physical properties on the nanoscale and also for realizing and manipulating high order topological insulator states in novel ways. Here we present a theoretical discussion on localized corner and edge states, as well as electronic properties emerging from topological phases in Sierpinski Carpet within a $\pi$-flux regime. A topological hopping parameter phase diagram is constructed from which different spatial localized states are identified following signatures of distinct fractal generations. The specific geometry and scaling properties of the fractal systems can guide the supported topological states types and their associated functionalities. A conductive device is proposed by coupling identical Sierpinski Carpet units providing transport response through projected edge states that carrier the details of the Sierpinski Carpet topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13774v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. L. Lage, N. C. Rappe, A. Latg\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the origins of charge transport in spin crossover complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17517v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Spin crossover (SCO) complexes are highly promising candidates for a myriad of potential applications in room-temperature electronics; however, as it stands, establishing a clear connection between their spin-state switching and transport properties has been far from trivial. In this letter, an effort to unravel the underlying charge transport mechanism in these SCO complexes, via a general theory, is made. The theory presented herein is aimed at providing a unifying picture that explains the widely different trends observed in the spin-crossover-dependent carrier transport properties in the SCO molecular thin film systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17517v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Archit Dhingra, M. Zaid Zaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
