<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.other updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other</link>
    <description>cond-mat.other updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 04:00:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-Electron Interactions, Magnetism, and Superconductivity: Lecture Notes for Introduction to Solid State Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lecture notes used as part of a graduate-level Introduction to Solid State Physics course at Cornell University. I attempt to unify and update the discussion of magnetism and superconductivity relative to standard textbook treatments, and include connections to recent research. A few related homework problems are attached at the end.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11169v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel C. Ralph</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a theory of phase transitions in quantum control landscapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Control landscape phase transitions (CLPTs) occur as abrupt changes in the cost function landscape upon varying a control parameter, and can be revealed by non-analytic points in statistical order parameters. A prime example are quantum speed limits (QSL) which mark the onset of controllability as the protocol duration is increased. Here we lay the foundations of an analytical theory for CLPTs by developing Dyson, Magnus, and cumulant expansions for the cost function that capture the behavior of CLPTs with a controlled precision. Using linear and quadratic stability analysis, we reveal that CLPTs can be associated with different types of instabilities of the optimal protocol. This allows us to explicitly relate CLPTs to critical structural rearrangements in the extrema of the control landscape: utilizing path integral methods from statistical field theory, we trace back the critical scaling of the order parameter at the QSL to the topological and geometric properties of the set of optimal protocols, such as the number of connected components and its dimensionality. We verify our predictions by introducing a numerical sampling algorithm designed to explore this optimal set via a homotopic stochastic update rule. We apply this new toolbox explicitly to analyze CLPTs in the single- and two-qubit control problems whose landscapes are analytically tractable, and compare the landscapes for bang-bang and continuous protocols. Our work provides the first steps towards a systematic theory of CLPTs and paves the way for utilizing statistical field theory techniques for generic complex control landscapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11110v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\`o Beato, Pranay Patil, Marin Bukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-trivial Topological Surface States Regulation of 1T-OsCoTe$_2$ Enables Selective C-C Coupling for Highly Efficient Photochemical CO$_2$ Reduction Toward C$_{2+}$ hydrocarbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite ongoing research, the rational design of nontrivial topological semimetal surface states for the selective photocatalytic CO$_2$ conversion into valuable products remains full of challenges. Herein, we present the synthesis of 1T-OsCoTe$_2$ for the photoreduction upgrading of CO$_2$ to tricarbon alkane C$_3$H$_8$,by the integration of experimental work and theory calculation. Experimental studies suggested a high electron based selectivity of 71.2% for C$_3$H$_8$ and an internal quantum efficiency of 54.6% at 380 nm. In-situ X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy and X-ray absorption fine structure spectroscopy demonstrated that Co and Os atoms coordinated with Te atoms enable an efficient Os-Te-Co electron transfer to activate the generation of *CH$_3$,*CHOCO and *CH$_2$OCOCO. Density functional theory calculations further confirmed Os-Te-Co electron bridging on the improved CO$_2$ conversion kinetics. To our knowledge, this is the first report suggesting the role of Os atoms in accelerating the photocatalytic CO$_2$ conversion activity of the topological semimetal 1T-OsCoTe$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11369v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Catalysis B: Environment and Energy,2024,352,124058</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kangwang Wang, Mingjie Wu, Peifeng Yu, Hector F. Garces, Ying Liang, Longfu Li, Lingyong Zeng, Kuan Li, Chao Zhang, Kai Yan, Huixia Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the nontrivial topological surface states of catalysts for effective photochemical carbon dioxide conversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11373v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological semimetals with protected surface states mark a new paradigm of research beyond the early landmarks of band-structure engineering, allowing fabrication of efficient catalyst to harness the rich metallic surface states to activate specific chemical processes. Herein, we demonstrate a facile solid-phase method for in-situ doping of Ir at the Os sites in the Os3Sn7, an alloy with topological states, which significantly improves the photocatalytic performance for the reduction of CO2 to CO and CH4. Experimental evidence combined with theoretical calculations reveal that the nontrivial topological surface states greatly accelerate charge-separation/electron-enrichment and adsorption/activation of CO2 molecules, rendering highly efficient reaction channels to stimulate the formation of *COOH and *CO, as well CHO*. This work shows the promise of achieving high photocatalytic performances with synthesizing topological catalysts and provides hints on the design of novel topological catalysts with superior photoactivity towards the CO2 reduction reaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Catalysis B: Environment and Energy,2024,358,124428</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kangwang Wang, Longfu Li, Peifeng Yu, Nannan Tang, Lingyong Zeng, Kuan Li, Chao Zhang, Rui Chen, Zaichen Xiang, Huichao Wang, Yongqing Cai, Kai Yan, Huixia Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent broadband polarization entanglement from electronic and phononic four-wave mixing indistinguishability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11602v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently [PRA 108, L051501 (2023)], it has been shown that in a centrosymmetric cubic system, two-photons from a broadband intense laser field can be converted into a pair of Stokes and anti-Stokes entangled photons. Here we properly explain, demonstrate, quantify (for diamond) and explore the possibilities offered by such system, designing an entanglement map based on changes in the light-matter system. In particular, we show how the broadband polarization entanglement, that emerges from the interference between electronic and phononic degrees of freedom in the four-wave mixing process, depends on parameters such as Stokes-anti-Stokes Raman shift, scattering geometry and laser bandwidth, opening the avenue of exploration of such phenomenon in information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11602v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Sier, Lucas Valente, Tiago A. Freitas, Marcelo F. Santos, Carlos H. Monken, Raul Corr\^ea, Ado Jorio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fitting to magnetic forces improves the reliability of magnetic Moment Tensor Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07069v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We developed a method for fitting machine-learning interatomic potentials with magnetic degrees of freedom, namely, magnetic Moment Tensor Potentials (mMTP). The main feature of our method consists in fitting mMTP to magnetic forces (negative derivatives of energies with respect to magnetic moments) as obtained spin-polarized density functional theory calculations. We test our method on the bcc Fe-Al system with different compositions. Specifically, we calculate formation energies, equilibrium lattice parameter, and total cell magnetization. Our findings demonstrate an accurate correspondence between the values calculated with mMTP and those obtained by DFT at zero temperature. Additionally, using molecular dynamics, we estimate the finite-temperature lattice parameter and capture the cell expansion as was previously revealed in experiment. Furthermore, we demonstrate that fitting to magnetic forces increases the reliability of structure relaxation (or, equilibration), in the sense of ensuring that every relaxation run ends up with a successfully relaxed structure (the failure may otherwise be caused by falsely driving a configuration away from the region covered in the training set).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07069v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey S. Kotykhov, Konstantin Gubaev, Vadim Sotskov, Christian Tantardini, Max Hodapp, Alexander V. Shapeev, Ivan S. Novikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
