<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.other updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other</link>
    <description>cond-mat.other updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 04:00:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quasicrystalline 30$^{\circ}$ twisted bilayer graphene: Fractal patterns and electronic localization properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05126v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The recently synthesized 30$^\circ$ twisted bilayer graphene (30$^\circ$-TBG) systems are unique quasicrystal systems possessing dodecagonal symmetry with graphene's relativistic properties.
  We employ a real-space numerical atomistic framework that respects both the dodecagonal rotational symmetry and the massless Dirac nature of the electrons to describe the local density of states of the system.
  The approach we employ is very efficiency for systems with very large unit cells and does not rely on periodic boundary conditions. These features allow us to address a broad class of multilayer two-dimensional crystal with incommensurate configurations, particularly TBGs. Our results reveal that the 30$^\circ$-TBG electronic spectrum consist of extended states together with a set of localized wave functions. The localized states exhibit fractal patterns consistent with the quasicrystal tiling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05126v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin J. U. Vidarte, Caio Lewenkopf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Classify Quantum Phases of Matter with a Few Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the identification of quantum phases of matter, at zero temperature, when only part of the phase diagram is known in advance. Following a supervised learning approach, we show how to use our previous knowledge to construct an observable capable of classifying the phase even in the unknown region. By using a combination of classical and quantum techniques, such as tensor networks, kernel methods, generalization bounds, quantum algorithms, and shadow estimators, we show that, in some cases, the certification of new ground states can be obtained with a polynomial number of measurements. An important application of our findings is the classification of the phases of matter obtained in quantum simulators, e.g., cold atom experiments, capable of efficiently preparing ground states of complex many-particle systems and applying simple measurements, e.g., single qubit measurements, but unable to perform a universal set of gates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05188v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehran Khosrojerdi, Jason L. Pereira, Alessandro Cuccoli, Leonardo Banchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast quantum gates for exchange-only qubits using simultaneous exchange pulses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05843v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The benefit of exchange-only qubits compared to other spin qubit types is the universal control using only voltage controlled exchange interactions between neighboring spins. As a compromise, qubit operations have to be constructed from non-orthogonal rotation axes of the Bloch sphere and result in rather long pulsing sequences. This paper aims to develop a faster implementation of single-qubit and two-qubit gates using simultaneous exchange pulses. We introduce pulse sequences in which single-qubit gates could be executed faster and show that subsequences on three spins in two-qubit gates could be implemented in fewer steps. Our findings can particularly speed up gate sequences for realistic idle times between sequential pulses and we show that this advantage increases with more interconnectivity of the quantum dots. We further demonstrate how a phase operation can introduce a relative phase between the computational and some of the leakage states, which can be advantageous for the construction of two-qubit gates. In addition to our theoretical analysis, we experimentally demonstrate and characterize a simultaneous exchange implementation of $X$ rotations in a SiGe quantum dot device and compare to the state of the art with sequential exchange pulses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05843v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irina Heinz, Felix Borjans, Matthew Curry, Roza Kotlyar, Florian Luthi, Mateusz T. M\k{a}dzik, Fahd A. Mohiyaddin, Nathaniel Bishop, Guido Burkard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MultiCarroll dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.07002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.07002v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Unlike a single Carroll particle, a multiparticle Carroll system can move under suitable conditions, as we demonstrate it explicitly for two particles with a momentum-dependent interaction: the center-of-mass remains fixed, however relative motion is possible, confirming previous statements made by Bergshoeff, Casalbuoni, and their collaborators. Analogous results are obtained for electric dipoles with the roles of the center-of-mass and the relative position interchanged.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.07002v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. -M. Zhang, H-X. Zeng, P. A. Horvathy</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
