<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.other updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other</link>
    <description>cond-mat.other updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the relationship between the Weyl semimetal phase and the three-dimensional quantum Hall phase in ZrTe$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The material ZrTe$_5$ exhibits distinct topological phases, including a Weyl semimetal phase, characterized by a chiral anomaly and in-plane Hall effect, and a three-dimensional quantum Hall phase. The relationship between these phases remains poorly understood. This work systematically explores their connection in ZrTe$_5$ through rotatable, pressure-dependent measurements. At ambient pressure, both phases are observed; the WSM phase requires strong electronic polarization, while the 3D QH phase appears when the characteristic resistivity peak temperature $T_p$ is approximately 90 K. Under applied pressure, the polarization diminishes, weakening the WSM phase and its associated nontrivial Hall signals. Concurrently, $T_p$ rises dramatically from 2 K at ambient pressure to 70 K at 2.2 GPa, approaching the expected regime for the 3D QH phase. These findings clarify the conditions underlying the WSM and 3D QH phases and suggest that exploring the 3D QH phase at even higher pressures is a promising direction for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12361v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahao Chen, Yu Cao, Hong Du, Yuanze Li, Ruidan Zhong, Tian Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anonymous leadership and stochastic resonance in collectives of self-propelled robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12580v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the influence of an anonymous leader on a collective of self-propelled robots using Kilobot experiments and numerical simulations. A single leader alternated deterministically between clockwise and counterclockwise motion, while the other robots followed a stochastic majority rule. Although the leader does not change global order, it induces correlations with the collective response that peak at intermediate perturbation levels, resembling stochastic resonance. Simulations confirm that this resonance occurs when the leader's reversal period matches the mean residence time of the unperturbed system. Our results contribute to understanding decision-making in active matter and suggesting principles for steering robotic swarms with minimal leadership input.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12580v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Dizenhaus, Franco De Simone, German A. Patterson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Strain-Induced Pseudogauge Fields on Exciton Dispersion, Transport, and Interactions in Transition Metal Dichalcogenides Nanoribbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13691v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the effects of strain on exciton dynamics in transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD) nanoribbons. Using the Bethe-Salpeter formalism, we derive the exciton dispersion relation in strained TMDs and demonstrate that strain-induced pseudo-gauge fields significantly influence exciton transport and interactions. Our results show that low-energy excitons occur at finite center-of-mass momentum, leading to modified diffusion properties. Furthermore, the exciton dipole moment depends on center-of-mass momentum, which enhances exciton-exciton interactions. These findings highlight the potential of strain engineering as a powerful tool for controlling exciton transport and interactions in nanoribbon-based TMD optoelectronic and quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13691v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiva Heidari, Shervin Parsi, Pouyan Ghaemi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin Simulations Toolbox of the Nitrogen-Vacancy Center in Diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18759v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The nitrogen-vacancy (NV) center in diamond is a crucial platform for quantum technologies, where its precise numerical modeling is indispensable for the continued advancement of the field. We present here a Python library for simulating the NV spin dynamics under general experimental conditions, i.e. a digital twin. Our library accounts for electromagnetic pulses and other environmental inputs, which are used to solve the system's time evolution, resulting in a physical output in the form of a quantum observable given by fluorescence. The simulation framework is based on a non-perturbative time-dependent Hamiltonian model, where the states initialization and readout are postulated from the interaction with optical fields. By eliminating oversimplifications such as the adoption of rotating frames for the microwave and radio frequency fields, our simulations reveal subtle dynamics emerging from realistic pulse constraints. The software is illustrated with three examples and validated by comparing the simulations with experimental reports, relevant to the fields of quantum computing (conditional logic gates), sensing (dynamical decoupling sequences with coupled spins) and networks (state teleportation). Overall, this digital twin delivers a robust numerical modeling of the NV spin dynamics, with simple and accessible usability, which can be used for a wide range of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18759v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Tsunaki, Anmol Singh, Sergei Trofimov, Boris Naydenov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
