<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.other updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other</link>
    <description>cond-mat.other updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.other" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 04:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Field Theory and Neural Structures Dynamics V: Synthesis and extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24896v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a unified field-theoretic framework for the dynamics of activity and connectivity in interacting neuronal systems. Building upon previous works, where a field approach to activity--connectivity dynamics, formation of collective states and effective fields of collective states were successively introduced, the present paper synthesizes and extends these results toward a general description of multiple hierarchical collective structures. Starting with the dynamical system representing collective states in terms of connections, activity levels, and internal frequencies, we analyze its stability, emphasizing the possibility of transitions between configurations. Then, turning to the field formalism of collective states, we extend this framework to include substructures (subobjects) participating in larger assemblies while retaining intrinsic properties. We define activation classes describing compatible or independent activity patterns between objects and subobjects, and study stability conditions arising from their alignment or mismatch. The global system is described as the collection of landscapes of coexisting and interacting collective states, each characterized both by continuous (activity, frequency) and discrete (class) variables. A corresponding field formalism is developed, with an action functional incorporating both internal dynamics and interaction terms. This nonlinear field model captures cascading transitions between collective states and the formation of composite structures, providing a coherent theoretical basis for emergent neuronal assemblies and their mutual couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24896v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Gosselin, A\"ileen Lotz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon dynamics and chiral modes in the two-dimensional square-octagon lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25071v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chiral phonons, originally identified in two-dimensional hexagonal lattices and later extended to kagome, square, and other lattices, have been extensively studied as manifestations of broken inversion and time-reversal symmetries in vibrational dynamics. In this work, we investigate the vibrational dynamics of the two-dimensional square-octagon lattice using a spring-mass model with central-force interactions. The model incorporates mass contrast and variable coupling strengths among nearest, next-nearest, and third-nearest neighbors. From the dynamical matrix, we obtain the phonon dispersion relations and identify tunable phononic band gaps governed by both mass and spring-constant ratios. The angular dependence of phase and group velocities is analyzed to reveal the pronounced anisotropy inherent to this lattice geometry. We also examine the distinctive features of the square-octagon geometry, including flat-band anomalies in the density of states and anisotropic sound propagation induced by longer-range couplings. In addition, we explore the emergence of chiral phonons by introducing a time reversal symmetry-breaking term in the dynamical matrix, and to elucidate their optical signatures, we construct a minimal model to study infrared circular dichroism arising from chiral phonon modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25071v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravi Kiran, A. Taraphder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic phase diagram of multiferroic and magnetocaloric TmFeO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17291v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutron diffraction experiments of TmFeO$_3$ single crystals were performed in the external magnetic fields. The field along $c$-axis increases temperature of spin-reorientation transition TSR from phase ${\Gamma}4$ to ${\Gamma}2$. Application of the field along $b$-axis led to the decrease of TSR and to the formation of new phases. Based on the temperature and field dependence of the Bragg reflection intensity, the configuration of magnetically induced phases was proposed. The magneto-structural effects were observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17291v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. I. Tkachenko, P. Fabrykiewicz, A. K. Ovsianikov, M. Meven, O. V. Usmanov, I. A. Zobkalo, K. A. Shaykhutdinov, K. Yu. Terentjev, S. V. Semenov, E. Ressouche, K. Beauvois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact analysis of AC sensors based on Floquet time crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22731v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the behavior of general Floquet Time Crystals (FTCs), including prethermal ones, in closed systems acting as AC sensors. We provide an analytical treatment of their quantum Fisher information (QFI) dynamics, which characterizes the ultimate sensor accuracy. By tuning the direction and frequency of the AC field, we show how to induce transitions resonantly between macroscopic paired cat states in the FTC sensor. This allows for robust Heisenberg scaling precision (QFI $\sim N^2 t^2$) for exponentially long times in the system size. The QFI dynamics exhibit, moreover, a characteristic step-like structure in time due to the eventual dephasing along the cat subspaces. The behavior is discussed for various initial sensor preparations, including ground states and low- and high-correlated states. Furthermore, we examine the performance of the sensor along the FTC phase transition; with the QFI capturing its critical exponents. Our findings are presented for both linear and nonlinear response regimes and illustrated for a specific FTC based on the long-range interacting LMG model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22731v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Tsypilnikov, Matheus Fibger, Fernando Iemini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An accurate DFT-1/2 approach for shallow defect states: Efficient calculation of donor binding energies in silicon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14738v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of shallow-donor electron binding energies is critical for device modeling, dopant activation, and donor-based quantum technologies. Traditional beyond-DFT approaches (e.g., hybrid functionals, GW) are prohibitively expensive for the large supercells needed to capture the extended, hydrogenic wavefunctions, while semi-local DFT underestimates band gaps and suffers from delocalization errors. We present a simple, practical protocol for shallow donors based on the DFT-1/2 approximate quasiparticle correction that maintains the computational cost of standard DFT and enables supercells up to thousands of atoms. This approach provides a straightforward and reproducible workflow that delivers reliable donor binding energies with minimal computational overhead. Applied to group-V donors in Si, Si:X (X= P, As, Sb, Bi), the method yields binding energies in close agreement with experiment. We found that, for Si:Bi, it is essential to include spin-orbit coupling to achieve near-experimental values with a difference of only $\sim$ 4 meV. For arsenic, the method yields excellent agreement with experiment, with a difference of only ~0.3 meV. For antimony, the results match experiment to within ~5 meV, and for phosphorus, the deviation is within ~8 meV. Beyond its high accuracy, DFT-1/2 offers a significant practical advantage, providing a straightforward, reproducible, and transferable workflow that is less demanding than hybrid functional approaches while remaining fully generalizable to other shallow impurities in semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14738v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Claes, Bart Partoens, Dirk Lamoen, Marcelo Marques, Lara K. Teles</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
