<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.TR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.TR</link>
    <description>q-fin.TR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.TR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Liquidity Competition Between Brokers and an Informed Trader</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08287v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a multi-agent setting in which brokers transact with an informed trader. Through a sequential Stackelberg-type game, brokers manage trading costs and adverse selection with an informed trader. In particular, supplying liquidity to the informed traders allows the brokers to speculate based on the flow information. They simultaneously attempt to minimize inventory risk and trading costs with the lit market based on the informed order flow, also known as the internalization-externalization strategy. We solve in closed form for the trading strategy that the informed trader uses with each broker and propose a system of equations which classify the equilibrium strategies of the brokers. By solving these equations numerically we may study the resulting strategies in equilibrium. Finally, we formulate a competitive game between brokers in order to determine the liquidity prices subject to precommitment supplied to the informed trader and provide a numerical example in which the resulting equilibrium is not Pareto efficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08287v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Donnelly, Zi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Option Market Making via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.01814v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Market making of options with different maturities and strikes is a challenging problem due to its highly dimensional nature. In this paper, we propose a novel approach that combines a stochastic policy and reinforcement learning-inspired techniques to determine the optimal policy for posting bid-ask spreads for an options market maker who trades options with different maturities and strikes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.01814v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhou Fang, Haiqing Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
