<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 02:37:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Energy landscape interpretation of universal linearly increasing absorption with frequency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03341v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Absorption of elastic waves in complex media often depends on frequency in a linear way for both longitudinal and shear waves. This universal property occurs in media such as rocks, unconsolidated sediments, and human tissue. Absorption is due to relaxation processes and we argue that these processes are thermally activated. Unusual for ultrasonics and seismics, we can therefore express absorption as an integral over an activation energy landscape weighted by an energy distribution. The universal power-law property corresponds to the special case of a flat activation energy landscape. The derived distribution agrees with results in soft glassy and glassy media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03341v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sverre Holm, Joakim Bergli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spheroidal harmonics for generalizing the morphological decomposition of closed parametric surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spherical harmonics (SH) have been extensively used as a basis for analyzing the morphology of particles in granular mechanics. The use of SH is facilitated by mapping the particle coordinates onto a unit sphere, in practice often a straightforward rescaling of the radial coordinate. However, when applied to oblate- or prolate-shaped particles the SH analysis quality degenerates with significant oscillations appearing after the reconstruction. Here, we propose a spheroidal harmonics (SOH) approach for the expansion and reconstruction of prolate and oblate particles. This generalizes the SH approach by providing additional parameters that can be adjusted per particle to minimize geometric distortion, thus increasing the analysis quality. We propose three mapping techniques for handling both star-shaped and non-star-shaped particles onto spheroidal domains. The results demonstrate the ability of the SOH to overcome the shortcomings of SH without requiring computationally expensive solutions or drastic changes to existing codes and processing pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03350v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmoud Shaqfa, Wim M. van Rees</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural Lubricity and Molecular Contamination: Rejuvenation, Aging, and Friction Switches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03360v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using atomic force microscopy experiments and molecular dynamics simulations of gold nanoislands on graphite, we investigate why ultra-small friction commonly associated with structural lubricity can be observed even under ambient conditions. Measurements conducted within a few days after sample synthesis reveal previously undiscovered phenomena in structurally lubric systems: rejuvenation, a drop in kinetic friction of an order of magnitude shortly after the onset of sliding; aging, a significant increase in kinetic friction forces after a rest period of 30 minutes or more; switches, spontaneous jumps between distinct friction branches. These three effects are drastically suppressed a few weeks later. Imaging of a contamination layer and simulations provide a consistent picture of how single- and double-layer contamination underneath the gold nanoislands as well as contamination surrounding the nanoislands affect structural lubricity but not lead to its breakdown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03360v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wai H. Oo, Hongyu Gao, Martin H. M\"user, Mehmet Z. Baykara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control of friction: shortcuts and optimization for the rate- and state-variable equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Frictional forces are a key ingredient of any physical description of the macroscopic world, as they account for the phenomena causing transformation of mechanical energy into heat. They are ubiquitous in nature, and a wide range of practical applications involve the manipulation of physical systems where friction plays a crucial role. In this paper, we apply control theory to dynamics governed by the paradigmatic rate- and state-variable law for solid-on-solid friction. Several control problems are considered for the case of a slider dragged on a surface by an elastic spring. By using swift state-to-state protocols, we show how to drive the system between two arbitrary stationary states characterized by different constant sliding velocities in a given time. Remarkably, this task proves to be feasible even when specific constraints are imposed on the dynamics, such as preventing the instantaneous sliding velocity or the frictional force from exceeding a prescribed bound. The derived driving protocols also allow to avoid a stick-slip instability, which instead occurs when velocity is suddenly switched. By exploiting variational methods, we also address the functional minimization problem of finding the optimal protocol that connects two steady states in a specified time, while minimizing the work done by the friction. We find that the optimal strategy can change qualitatively depending on the time imposed for the duration of the process. Our results mark a significant step forward in establishing a theoretical framework for control problems in the presence of friction and naturally pave the way for future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03696v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Plati, Alberto Petri, Marco Baldovin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapse of active nematic order through a two-stage dynamic transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03723v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel two-stage transition of the ordered active nematic state of a system of bundled microtubules into a biphasic active fluid. Specifically, we show that upon light-induced solidification of the underlying medium, microtubule-kinesin motor mixtures first undergo a cascade of folding in on themselves, which is then followed by a progressive formation of isotropic fluid domains, transforming the system into a biphasic active suspension. Using an active lyotropic model, we show that the two-stage transition in the system is governed by screening effects that become important upon substrate changes, leading to higher activity modes to become important. Specifically, the combined effect of friction and quadrupolar activity leads to the hierarchical folding that follows the intrinsic bend instability. Our results demonstrate the dynamics of the collapse of orientational order in active nematics and present a new route for controlling active matter by modifying the activity through changing the surrounding environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03723v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandra Arda\v{s}eva, Ignasi V\'elez-Cer\'on, Martin Cramer Pedersen, Jordi Ign\'es-Mullol, Francesc Sagu\'es, Amin Doostmohammadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-chemophoresis in the thin diffuse interface approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Self-chemophoresis is an appealing and quite successful interpretation of the motility exhibited by certain chemically active colloidal particles suspended in a solution of their "fuel": the particle has a phoretic response to self-generated, rather than externally imposed, inhomogeneities in the chemical composition of the solution. The postulated mechanism of chemophoresis is the interaction of the particle (via an adsorption potential) with the chemical inhomogeneities in the surrounding medium. When the range of this interaction is much smaller than any other relevant scale in the system, the (translational and rotational) phoretic velocities can be described in terms of a phoretic coefficient and a slip fluid velocity at the surface of the particle. Using the case of a spherical particle as a simple and physically insightful example, here we exploit an integral representation of the rigid-body motion to critically re-examine this framework. The systematic analysis highlights two steps in the approximation: first the thin-layer approximation (very large particle size), and subsequently a lubrication approximation (slow variation of the adsorption potential along the tangential direction). We also discuss how these approximations could be relaxed and the effect of this on the particle's motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03767v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alvaro Dom\'inguez, Mihail N. Popescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Membrane-mediated interactions between arc-shaped particles strongly depend on membrane curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Besides direct molecular interactions, proteins and nanoparticles embedded in or adsorbed to membranes experience indirect interactions that are mediated by the membranes. These membrane-mediated interactions arise from the membrane curvature induced by the particles and can lead to assemblies of particles that generate highly curved spherical or tubular membranes shapes, but have mainly been quantified for planar or weakly curved membranes. In this article, we systematically investigate the membrane-mediated interactions of arc-shaped particles adsorbed to a variety of tubular and spherical membrane shapes with coarse-grained modelling and simulations. We determine both the pairwise interaction free energy, with includes entropic contributions due to rotational entropy loss at close particle distances, and the pairwise interaction energy without entropic components from particle distributions observed in the simulations. For membrane shapes with small curvature, the membrane-mediated interaction free energies of particle pairs exceed the thermal energy kT and can lead to particle ordering and aggregation. The interactions strongly decrease with increasing curvature of the membrane shape and are minimal for tubular shapes with membrane curvatures close to the particle curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04027v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.SC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Bonazzi, Thomas R. Weikl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocal interactions drive capillary waves in active liquid crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active liquid crystals exert nonequilibrium stresses on their surroundings through constant consumption of energy, giving rise to dynamical steady states not present in equilibrium. The paradigmatic example of an active liquid crystal is a suspension of microtubule bundles powered by kinesin motor proteins, which exhibits self-sustained spatiotemporal chaotic flows. This system has been modelled using continuum theories that couple the microtubule orientation to active flows. Recently the focus has shifted to the interfacial properties of mixtures of active liquid crystals and passive fluids. Active/passive interfaces have been shown to support propagating capillary waves in the absence of inertia and offer a promising route for relating experimental parameters to those of the continuum theory. In this paper we report the derivation of a minimal model that captures the linear dynamics of the interface between an active liquid crystal and a passive fluid. We show that the dynamics of the interface, although powered by active flows throughout the bulk, is qualitatively captured by equations that couple non-reciprocally interface height and nematic director at the interface. This minimal model reproduces the dynamical structure factor evaluated from numerical simulations and the qualitative form of the wave dispersion relation seen in experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04196v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paarth Gulati, Fernando Caballero, Itamar Kolvin, Zhihong You, M. Cristina Marchetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformational and static properties of tagged chains in solvents: effect of chain connectivity in solvent molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04262v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polymer chains immersed in different solvent molecules exhibit diverse properties due to multiple spatiotemporal scales and complex interactions. Using molecular dynamics simulations, we study the conformational and static properties of tagged chains in different solvent molecules. Two types of solvent molecules were examined: one type consisted of chain molecules connected by bonds, while the other type consisted of individual bead molecules without any bonds. The only difference between the two solvent molecules lay in the chain connectivity. Our results show a compression of the tagged chains with the addition of bead or chain molecules. Chain molecule confinement induces a stronger compression compared to bead molecule confinement. In chain solvent molecules, the tagged chain's radius of gyration reached a minimum at a monomer volume fraction of $\sim0.3$. Notably, the probability distributions of chain size remain unchanged at different solvent densities, irrespective of whether the solvent consists of beads or polymers. Furthermore, as solvent density increases, a crossover from a unimodal to a bimodal distribution of bond angles is observed, indicating the presence of both compressed and expanded regions within the chain. The effective monomer-solvent interaction is obtained by calculating the partial radial distribution function and the potential of the mean force. In chain solvent, the correlation hole effect results in a reduced number of nearest neighbors around tagged monomers compared to bead solvents. The calculation of pore size distribution reveals that the solvent nonhomogeneity induced by chain connectivity leads to a broader distribution of pore sizes and larger pore dimensions at low volume fractions. These findings provide a deeper understanding of the conformational behavior of polymer chains in different solvent environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04262v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D3SM01473H</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Soft Matter, 2024, 20, 3073-3081</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Yao Li, Bokai Zhang, Zhi-Yong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Glass formation in mechanically interlocked ring polymers: the role of induced chain stiffness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polymer-related materials exhibit rich glassy behaviors at different length scales due to their various molecular structures and topological constraints. Recent studies have identified transient interpenetration of the long-chain rings contributing to dynamic arrest on the center-of-mass level. Interpenetration of rings is proposed as an approach to facilitate glass formation in polymer melts. In this work, inspired by recent advances in the synthesis of mechanically interlocked polymers, we investigate glass transition on the nanometer-scale segments influenced by permanent interpenetration of rings using molecular dynamics simulations. We find that decreasing chain length in the mechanically interlocked system is equivalent to inducing an effective chain stiffness on the sub-rings. The induced stiffness provides a unified explanation for these unique structural features and transient dynamic arrest in the system of interlocked rings with rather short chains. Further, a crossover is observed in the scaling relation between localization and glassy depth upon cooling. Our work reveals a dynamic transition from weak to strong caging at the crossover temperature. According to the localization model, we demonstrate that the chain stiffness increases the critical temperature and oscillation distance, therefore leads to more fragile dynamics and deeper glassy state. These findings are consistent with the predictions of molecular simulations and theories for polymers with real local stiffness. Our work deepens the understanding of the role of induced stiffness on glass transition, and opens up a new direction to design rich glass materials by manipulating stiffness through mechanical bonds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04269v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.macromol.2c01368</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Macromolecules 2023, 56, 2, 589-600</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jian Li, Bokai Zhang, Yushan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular viscoelastic perturbation to soft lubrication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Soft lubrication has been shown to drastically affect the mobility of an object immersed in a viscous fluid in the vicinity of a purely elastic wall. In this theoretical study, we develop a minimal model incorporating  viscoelasticity, carrying out a  perturbation analysis in both the elastic deformation of the wall and its viscous damping. Our approach reveals the singular-perturbation nature of viscoelasticity to soft lubrication. Numerical resolution of the resulting non-linear, singular and coupled equations of motion reveals  peculiar effects of viscoelasticity on confined colloidal mobility, opening the way towards the description of complex migration scenarios near realistic polymeric substrates and biological membranes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04319v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bharti Bharti (UiO, LOMA), Quentin Ferreira (LOMA), Aditya Jha (LOMA), Andreas Carlson (UiO), David S. Dean (LOMA), Yacine Amarouchene (LOMA), Tak Shing Chan (UiO), Thomas Salez (LOMA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow fields around active droplets squeezing through tight confinements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biological microswimmers, like euglena, deform their body shape to swim through tight confinements having length scales comparable to the microswimmer length scale. Recently, it was shown that self-propelling active droplets can also squeeze through tight microconfinements by elongating their shape. However, the evolution of the hydrodynamic signature, or the velocity field, generated by the active droplet, as it deforms its shape to swim through increasingly tight microconfinements, has remained scarcely studied. Using high-resolution fluorescence microscopy and $\mu$-Particle Image Velocimetry (PIV) analysis, we show here that as the swimming active droplet deforms from a spherical shape to a `stadium'-like shape, and eventually to an elongated `capsule'-like shape in increasingly tighter microchannels, its hydrodynamic signature changes from a `pusher'-like velocity field to a `puller'-like velocity field, and finally to an asymmetric velocity field. We characterize such alterations in the active droplet dynamics using the distributions of the local velocity magnitude, axial and transverse components of the local flow velocity, vorticity, and the filled micelle concentration. Finally, we use finite-element based numerical simulations to explain the aforementioned evolution of the velocity field stemming from the underlying physico-chemical hydrodynamics in the presence of a thin lubrication film between the swimming active droplet and the tight microconfinement walls. The present work provides a comprehensive understanding of the chemo-hydrodynamic characteristics of active droplets navigating extreme confined spaces, which can be beneficial for many autonomous cargo-delivery applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04324v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhasish Guchhait, Smita Sontakke, Shubhadeep Mandal, Ranabir Dey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of a maximum flow rate in electro-osmotic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the effect of the hydrodynamic wall-fluid friction in electro-osmotic flows. First, we present the solution to the electro-hydrodynamic equation for the electro-osmotic velocity profile, which is derived for an ionic system composed of cations immersed in uncharged solvent particles. The system (solution and walls) is kept electrically neutral using negatively charged walls and will here be referred to as a "counterion-only" system. The theory predicts the existence of a counterion concentration that results in a maximum electro-osmotic flow rate, but only if the wall-fluid friction, or equivalently the slip length, is correlated with the system electrostatic screening length. Through equilibrium molecular dynamics simulations we precisely determine the hydrodynamic slip from the wall-fluid friction, and this is then used as input to the theoretical predictions. Comparison between the theory and independent non-equilibrium molecular dynamics simulation data confirms the existence of the maximum. Also, we find that standard hydrodynamic theory quantitatively agrees with simulation results for charged nanoscale systems for sufficiently small charge densities and ion charges, if the correct slip boundaries are applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04390v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sleeba Varghese, Billy D. Todd, Jesper S. Hansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical mechanics of crystal nuclei of hard spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the study of crystal nucleation via computer simulations, hard spheres are arguably the most extensively explored model system. Nonetheless, even in this simple model system, the complex thermodynamics of crystal nuclei can sometimes give rise to counterintuitive results, such as the recent observation that the pressure inside a critical nucleus is lower than that of the surrounding fluid, seemingly clashing with the strictly positive Young--Laplace pressure we would expect in liquid droplets. Here, we re-derive many of the founding equations associated with crystal nucleation, and use the hard-sphere model to demonstrate how they give rise to this negative pressure difference. We exploit the fact that, in the canonical ensemble, a nucleus can be in a (meta)stable equilibrium with the fluid, and measure the surface stress for both flat and curved interfaces. Additionally, we explain the effect of defects on the chemical potential inside the crystal nucleus. Lastly, we present a simple, fitted thermodynamic model to capture the properties of the nucleus, including the work required to form critical nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marjolein de Jager, Carlos Vega, Pablo Montero de Hijes, Frank Smallenburg, Laura Filion</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Assembly of Active Bivalent Patchy Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present work, with the intent of exploring the out-of-equilibrium polymerization of active patchy particles in linear chains, we study a suspension of active bivalent Brownian particles (ABBPs). At all studied temperatures and densities, ABBPs self-assemble in aggregating chains, as opposed to the uniformly space-distributed chains observed in the corresponding passive systems. The main effect of activity, other than inducing chain aggregation, is to reduce the chain length and favor alignment of the propulsion vectors in the bonding process. At low activities, attraction dominates over activity in the bonding process, leading self-assembly to occur randomly regardless of the particle orientations.Interestingly, we find that at the lowest temperature, as density increases, chains aggregate forming a novel state: MISP, i.e., Motility-Induced Spirals, where spirals are characterised by a finite angular velocity. On the contrary, at the highest temperature, density and activity, chains aggregate forming a different novel state (a spinning crystalline cluster) characterized by a compact and hexagonal ordered structure, both translating and rotating. The rotation arises from an effective torque generated by the presence of competing domains where particles self-propel in the same direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04572v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caterina Landi, John Russo, Francesco Sciortino, Chantal Valeriani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experiment on intrinsically nonequilibrium distribution of large ions in charged small nanopores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent theoretical research on locally nonchaotic gravitational energy barrier led to an interesting finding: beyond the boundaries of Boltzmann's H-theorem, there may be macroscopic systems with nontrivial energy properties. The fundamental mechanism is rooted in the intrinsically nonequilibrium steady state. In the current investigation, we experimentally verify this concept, with the weak gravitational force being changed to the strong Coulomb force. The tests are performed on capacitive cells with the same nanoporous electrodes and various electrolyte concentrations. The key characteristic is that the nanopore size is only slightly larger than the ion size, less than twice the ion size. The confinement effect of the nanopore walls plays the role of the spontaneously nonequilibrium dimension (SND). At first glance, the capacitive cells exhibit "normal" charge curves. However, their steady-state ion distribution significantly differs from thermodynamic equilibrium. The measured potential difference is nearly an order of magnitude larger than the prediction of equilibrium thermodynamics. Such phenomena are in line with the molecular dynamics simulations reported in the open literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04599v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Qiao, Meng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric fluctuations and self-folding of active interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the structure and dynamics of the interface separating a passive fluid from a microtubule-based active fluid. Turbulent-like active flows power giant interfacial fluctuations, which exhibit pronounced asymmetry between regions of positive and negative curvature. Experiments, numerical simulations, and theoretical arguments reveal how the interface breaks up the spatial symmetry of the fundamental bend instability to generate local vortical flows that lead to asymmetric interface fluctuations. The magnitude of interface deformations increases with activity: In the high activity limit, the interface self-folds invaginating passive droplets and generating a foam-like phase, where active fluid is perforated with passive droplets. These results demonstrate how active stresses control the structure, dynamics, and break-up of soft, deformable, and reconfigurable liquid-liquid interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04679v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Zhao, Paarth Gulati, Fernando Caballero, Itamar Kolvin, Raymond Adkins, M. Cristina Marchetti, Zvonimir Dogic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting solvation free energies for neutral molecules in any solvent with openCOSMO-RS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03434v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The accurate prediction of solvation free energies is critical for understanding various phenomena in the liquid phase, including reaction rates, equilibrium constants, activity coefficients, and partition coefficients. Despite extensive research, precise prediction of solvation free energies remains challenging. In this study, we introduce openCOSMO-RS 24a, an improved version of the open-source COSMO-RS model, capable of predicting solvation free energies alongside other liquid-phase properties. We parameterize openCOSMO-RS 24a using quantum chemical calculations from ORCA 6.0, leveraging a comprehensive dataset that includes solvation free energies, partition coefficients, and infinite dilution activity coefficients for various solutes and solvents at 25 {\deg}C. Additionally, we develop a Quantitative Structure-Property Relationships model to predict molar volumes of the solvents, an essential requirement for predicting solvation free energies from structure alone. Our results show that openCOSMO-RS 24a achieves an average absolute deviation of 0.45 kcal/mol for solvation free energies, 0.76 for partition coefficients, and 0.51 for infinite dilution activity coefficients, demonstrating improvements over the previous openCOSMO-RS 22 parameterization and comparable results to COSMOtherm 24 TZVP. A new command line interface for openCOSMO-RS 24a was developed which allows easy acces to the solvation energy model directly from within ORCA 6.0. This represents a significant advancement in the predictive modeling of solvation free energies and other solution-phase properties, providing researchers with a robust tool for applications in chemical and materials science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03434v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon M\"uller, Thomas Nevolianis, Miquel Garcia-Rat\'es, Christoph Riplinger, Kai Leonhard, Irina Smirnova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The interplay of shape and catalyst distribution in the yield of compressible flow microreactors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03944v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a semi-analytical model for transport in structured catalytic microreactors, where both reactant and product are compressible fluids. Making use of the lubrication and Fick-Jacobs approximations, we reduce the three-dimensional governing equations to an effective one-dimensional set of equations. Our model captures the effect of compressibility, of corrugations in the shape of the reactor, as well as of an inhomogeneous catalytic coating of the reactor walls. We show that in the weakly compressible limit (e.g., liquid-phase reactors), the distribution of catalyst does not influence the reactor yield, which we verify experimentally. Beyond this limit, we show that introducing inhomogeneities in the catalytic coating and corrugations to the reactor walls can improve the yield.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03944v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. C. Antunes, J. Jim\'enez-Sanch\'ez, P. Malgaretti, J. Bachmann, J. Harting</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniaxial Recovery Perspective of Glassy Polymer Nanoindentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07565v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sharp tip nanoindentation of glassy polymers is a constrained, localized viscoelastoplastic deformation. We interpret this complexity, in terms of the well-understood uniaxial deformation. From the uniaxial compression data in the literature, for PMMA, PC and crosslinked SU-8, we obtain their universal, yield-normalized recovery curves, with eps*=eps/eps_y, being one measure of the corresponding strain states (CSS). Nanoindentation recovery is determined from the 2sec constant rate unloading h-P data, modeled by a generalized power-law (variable power exponent). Comparing these data-sets, yields the correlation coefficient between the notional nanoindentation strain rate epsdot_N and strain and true strain rate and strain, c=epsdot_N/epsdot_t=eps_N/eps_t. The equivalent strain, eps, and the c value for any polymer, are within a narrow range, from the onset of indentation. Combining residual profiles via scanning probe microscopy with mathematical modeling of the indenter tip, provides the strain distribution beneath the tip. CSS measures examined here, indicate polymer-specific regions to regions common to glassy polymers, which are reached very early in the nanoindentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07565v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prakash Sarkar (Department of Metallurgical Engineering,Materials Science, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay), Hemant Nanavati (Department of Chemical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of cholesterol on hydrogen-bond dynamics of water molecules in lipid-bilayer systems at varying temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08289v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cholesterol (Chol) plays a crucial role in shaping the intricate physicochemical attributes of biomembranes, exerting considerable influence on water molecules proximal to the membrane interface. In this study, we conducted molecular dynamics simulations on the bilayers of two lipid species, dipalmitoyl phosphatidylcholine (DPPC) and palmitoyl sphingomyelin (PSM); they are distinct with respect to the structures of the hydrogen-bond (H-bond) acceptors. Our investigation focuses on the dynamic properties and H-bonds of water molecules in the lipid-membrane systems, with particular emphasis on the influence of Chol at varying temperatures. Notably, in the gel phase at 303 K, the presence of Chol extends the lifetimes of H-bonds of the oxygen atoms acting as H-bond acceptors within DPPC with water molecules by a factor of 1.5 to 2.5. In the liquid-crystalline phase at 323 K, on the other hand, H-bonding dynamics with lipid membranes remain largely unaffected by Chol. This observed shift in H-bonding states serves as a crucial key to unraveling the subtle control mechanisms governing water dynamics in lipid-membrane systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08289v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0208008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 161, 015102 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kokoro Shikata, Kento Kasahara, Nozomi Morishita Watanabe, Hiroshi Umakoshi, Kang Kim, Nobuyuki Matubayasi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural fluctuations in active glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08243v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The glassy dynamics of dense active matter have recently become a topic of interest due to their importance in biological processes such as wound healing and tissue development. However, while the liquid-state properties of dense active matter have been studied in relation to the glass transition of active matter, the solid-state properties of active glasses have yet to be understood. In this work, we study the structural fluctuations in the active glasses composed of self-propelled particles. We develop a formalism to describe the solid-state properties of active glasses in the harmonic approximation limit and use it to analyze the displacement fields in the active glasses. Our findings reveal that the dynamics of high-frequency normal modes become quasi-static with respect to the active forces, and consequently, excitations of these modes are significantly suppressed. This leads to a violation of the equipartition law, suppression of particle displacements, and the apparent collective motion of active glasses. Overall, our results provide a fundamental understanding of the solid-state properties of active glasses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08243v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaki Yoshida, Hideyuki Mizuno, Atsushi Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empowering AlphaFold2 for protein conformation selective drug discovery with AlphaFold2-RAVE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07102v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Small molecule drug design hinges on obtaining co-crystallized ligand-protein structures. Despite AlphaFold2's strides in protein native structure prediction, its focus on apo structures overlooks ligands and associated holo structures. Moreover, designing selective drugs often benefits from the targeting of diverse metastable conformations. Therefore, direct application of AlphaFold2 models in virtual screening and drug discovery remains tentative. Here, we demonstrate an AlphaFold2 based framework combined with all-atom enhanced sampling molecular dynamics and induced fit docking, named AF2RAVE-Glide, to conduct computational model based small molecule binding of metastable protein kinase conformations, initiated from protein sequences. We demonstrate the AF2RAVE-Glide workflow on three different protein kinases and their type I and II inhibitors, with special emphasis on binding of known type II kinase inhibitors which target the metastable classical DFG-out state. These states are not easy to sample from AlphaFold2. Here we demonstrate how with AF2RAVE these metastable conformations can be sampled for different kinases with high enough accuracy to enable subsequent docking of known type II kinase inhibitors with more than 50% success rates across docking calculations. We believe the protocol should be deployable for other kinases and more proteins generally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07102v3</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7554/eLife.99702.1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Gu, Akashnathan Aranganathan, Pratyush Tiwary</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
