<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 04:00:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic, second-order homogenization of linear elastic beam networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11316v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a general approach to the higher-order homogenization of discrete elastic networks made up of linear elastic beams or springs in dimension 2 or 3. The network may be nearly (rather than exactly) periodic: its elastic and geometric properties are allowed to vary slowly in space, in addition to being periodic at the scale of the unit cell. The reference configuration may be prestressed. A homogenized strain energy depending on both the macroscopic strain $\boldsymbol{\varepsilon}$ and its gradient $\nabla \boldsymbol{\varepsilon}$ is obtained by means of a two-scale expansion. The homogenized energy is asymptotically exact two orders beyond that obtained by classical homogenization. The homogenization method is implemented in a symbolic calculation language and applied to various types of networks, such as a 2D honeycomb, a 2D Kagome lattice, a 3D truss and a 1D pantograph. It is validated by comparing the predictions of the microscopic displacement to that obtained by full, discrete simulations. This second-order method remains highly accurate even when the strain gradient effects are significant, such as near the lips of a crack tip or in regions where a gradient of pre-strain is imposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11316v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmps.2024.105637</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Mech. Phys. Sol. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yang Ye, Basile Audoly, Claire Lestringant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition Graphs of Interacting Hysterons: Structure, Design, Organization and Statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collections of bistable elements called hysterons provide a powerful model to capture the sequential response and memory effects of frustrated, multistable media in the athermal, quasistatic limit. While a century of work has elucidated, in great detail, the properties of ensembles of non-interacting hysterons - the so-called Preisach model - comparatively little is known about the behavior and properties of interacting hysterons. Here we discuss a general framework for interacting hysterons, focussing on the relation between the design parameters that specify the hysterons and their interactions, and the resulting transition graphs (t-graphs). We show how the structure of such t-graphs can be thought of as being composed of a scaffold that is dressed by (avalanche) transitions selected from finite binary trees. Moreover, we provide a systematic framework to straightforwardly determine the design inequalities for a given t-graph, and discuss an effective method to determine if a certain t-graph topology is realizable by a set of interacting hysterons. Altogether, our work builds on the Preisach model by generalizing the hysteron-dependent switching fields to the state-dependent switching fields. As a result, while in the Preisach model, the main loop identifies the critical hysterons that trigger a transition, in the case of interacting hysterons, the scaffold contains this critical information and assumes a central role in determining permissible transitions. In addition, our work suggests strategies to deal with the combinatorial explosion of the number and variety of t-graphs for interacting hysterons. This approach paves the way for a deeper theoretical understanding of the properties and statistics of t-graphs, and opens a route to materializing complex pathways, memory effects and embodied computations in (meta)materials based on interacting hysterons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11344v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Margot H. Teunisse, Martin van Hecke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A methodology of quantifying membrane permeability based on returning probability theory and molecular dynamics simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a theoretical approach to estimate the permeability coefficient of substrates (permeants) for crossing membranes from donor (D) phase to acceptor (A) phase by means of molecular dynamics (MD) simulation. A fundamental aspect of our approach involves reformulating the returning probability (RP) theory, a rigorous bimolecular reaction theory, to describe permeation phenomena. This reformulation relies on the parallelism between permeation and bimolecular reaction processes. In the present method, the permeability coefficient is represented in terms of the thermodynamic and kinetic quantities for the reactive (R) phase that exists within the inner region of membranes. One can evaluate these quantities using multiple MD trajectories starting from phase R. We apply the RP theory to the permeation of ethanol and methylamine at different concentrations (infinitely dilute and 1 mol% conditions of permeants). Under the 1 mol% condition, the present method yields a larger permeability coefficient for ethanol ($0.12 \pm 0.01 ~\mathrm{cm~s^{-1}}$) than for methylamine ($0.069\pm 0.006~\mathrm{cm~s^{-1}}$), while the values of the permeability coefficient are satisfactorily close to those obtained from the brute-force MD simulations [$0.18\pm 0.03 ~\mathrm{cm~s^{-1}}$ and $0.052 \pm 0.005 ~\mathrm{cm~s^{-1}}$ for ethanol and methylamine, respectively]. Moreover, upon analyzing the thermodynamic and kinetic contributions to the permeability, we clarify that a higher concentration dependency of permeability for ethanol, as compared to methylamine, arises from the sensitive nature of ethanol's free-energy barrier within the inner region of the membrane against ethanol concentration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11363v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuya Matsubara, Ryo Okabe, Ren Masayama, Nozomi Morishita Watanabe, Hiroshi Umakoshi, Kento Kasahara, Nobuyuki Matubayasi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonnegative tensor train for the multicomponent Smoluchowski equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose an efficient implementation of the numerical tensor-train (TT) based algorithm solving the multicomponent coagulation equation preserving the nonnegativeness of solution. Unnatural negative elements in the constructed approximation arise due to the errors of the low-rank decomposition and discretization scheme. In this work, we propose to apply the rank-one corrections in the TT-format proportional to the minimal negative element. Such an element can be found via application of the global optimization methods that can be fully implemented within efficient operations in the tensor train format. We incorporate this trick into the time-integration scheme for the multicomponent coagulation equation and also use it for post-processing of the stationary solution for the problem with the source of particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10898v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey A. Matveev, Ilya Tretyak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hexagonal quasiperiodic tilings as decorations of periodic lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11378v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Symmetry sharing facilitates coherent interfaces which can transition from periodic to quasiperiodic structures. Motivated by the design and construction of such systems, we present hexagonal quasiperiodic tilings with a single edge-length which can be considered as decorations of a periodic lattice. We introduce these tilings by modifying an existing family of golden-mean trigonal and hexagonal tilings, and discuss their properties in terms of this wider family. Then, we show how the vertices of these new systems can be considered as decorations or sublattice sets of a periodic triangular lattice. We conclude by simulating a simple Ising model on one of these decorations, and compare this system to a triangular lattice with random defects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11378v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam Coates</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amino Acids Stabilizing Effect on Protein and Colloidal Dispersions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11574v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite being used for decades as stabilizers, amino acids (AAs) remain mysterious components of many medical and biological formulations. Hypotheses on their role vary ranging from hydrotropic to protein-specific effects (stabilization against misfolding). Here, we deduce that AAs possess a new and broad colloidal property by finding that stabilizing effect of the AAs is comparable on dispersion of various proteins, plasmid DNA, and non-biological nanoparticles. The interactions among colloidal particles in dispersion are carefully evaluated by the second osmotic virial coefficient (B_22) and the potential of mean force. We propose a theoretical framework that explains the stabilization as the effect of weakly interacting small molecules with patchy nanoscale colloids. We validate it through quantitative comparison with experimental data by comparing equilibrium dissociation constants for AA/proteins obtained either by fitting the B22 data with this theory or experimentally. We find excellent quantitative agreement (e.g. proline/lysozyme 1.18 and 2.28 M, respectively) and indeed that the interactions are very weak. The theory presented implies that (i) charged AAs will be effective only for proteins of opposite charge; (ii) short peptides composed of n AAs will be as or more effective than n separate AAs; (iii) any small molecule weakly interacting with nanoscale colloids that increases the solvation of the surface will have a stabilizing effect. The experimental evidences corroborate all three predictions. Much like the ionic strength of the solution is commonly reported, our results imply that the same should be done for the small molecules, as they also affect fundamentally colloidal properties. As an example, we show that AAs vary the cloud point of a lysozyme solution by as much as 4 K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11574v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting Mao, Xufeng Xu, Pamina M. Winkler, C\'ecilia Siri, Ekaterina Poliukhina, Paulo Jacob Silva, Zhi Luo, Quy Ong, Alfredo-Alexander Katz, Francesco Stellacci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photo-activated dynamic isomerization induced large density changes in liquid crystal polymers: A molecular dynamics study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.14990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.14990v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use molecular dynamics simulations to unravel the physics underpinning the light-induced density changes caused by the dynamic trans-cis-trans isomerization cycles of azo-mesogens embedded in a liquid crystal polymer network, an intriguing experimental observation reported in the literature. We employ two approaches, cyclic and probabilistic switching of isomers, to simulate dynamic isomerization. The cyclic switching of isomers confirms that dynamic isomerization can lead to density changes at specific switch-time intervals. The probabilistic switching approach further deciphers the physics behind the non-monotonous relation between density reduction and light intensities observed in experiments. Light intensity variations in experiments are accounted for in simulations by varying the trans-to-cis and cis-to-trans isomerization probabilities. The simulations show that an optimal combination of these two probabilities results in a maximum density reduction, corroborating the experimental observations. At such an optimal combination of probabilities, the dynamic trans-cis-trans isomerization cycles occur at a specific frequency, causing significant distortion in the polymer network, resulting in a maximum density reduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.14990v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0187320</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 14 March 2024; 160 (10): 104902</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Akhil Reddy Peeketi, Edwin Joseph, Narasimhan Swaminathan, Ratna Kumar Annabattula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface Tension of Aqueous Electrolyte Solutions. A Thermomechanical Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10753v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We determine the surface tension of aqueous electrolyte solutions in contact with non-polar dielectric media using a thermomechanical approach, which involves deriving the stress tensor from the thermodynamic potential of an inhomogeneous fluid. To obtain the surface tension, we calculate both the normal and tangential pressures using the components of the stress tensor, recently derived by us [Y. A. Budkov and P. E. Brandyshev, The Journal of Chemical Physics 159 (2023)] within the framework of Wang's variational field theory. Using this approach, we derive an analytical expression for the surface tension in the linear approximation. At low ionic concentrations, this expression represents the classical Onsager-Samaras limiting law. By utilizing only one fitting parameter, which is related to the affinity of anions to the dielectric boundary, we can approximate various experimental data regarding the surface tension of aqueous electrolyte solutions. This approximation applies to both the solution-air and solution-dodecane interfaces, covering a wide range of electrolyte concentrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10753v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yury A. Budkov, Nikolai N. Kalikin, Petr E. Brandyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning-enabled exploration of mesoscale architectures in amphiphilic-molecule self-assembly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.19019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.19019v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Amphiphilic molecules spontaneously form self-assembled structures of various shapes depending on their molecular structures, the temperature, and other physical conditions. The functionalities of these structures are dictated by their formations and their properties must be evaluated for reproduction using molecular simulations. However, the assessment of such intricate structures involves many procedural steps. This study investigates the potential of machine-learning models to extract structural features from mesoscale non-ordered self-assembled structures, and suggests a methodology in which machine-learning models for the structural analysis of self-assembled structures are trained on particle types and coordinate data. In the proposed approach, graph neural networks are utilised to extract local structural data for analysis. In simulations using several hundred self-assembled structures of up to 4050 coarse-grained particles, local structures are successfully extracted and classified with up to 78.35 % accuracy. As the machine-learning models learn structural characteristics without the need for human-made feature engineering, the proposed method has important potential applications in the field of materials science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.19019v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeo Sudo, Satoki Ishiai, Yuuki Ishiwatari, Takahiro Yokoyama, Kenji Yasuoka, Noriyoshi Arai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-range translational order and hyperuniformity in two-dimensional chiral active crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.19192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.19192v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We numerically study two-dimensional athermal chiral active particles at high densities. The particles in this system perform the circular motion with frequency $\Omega$. We show that the system in the fluid phase crystallizes at high densities even in two dimensions. The true long-range translational order arises due to the suppression of displacement fluctuations associated with hyperuniformity. We also find that $\Omega=0$ is singular, where the system never crystallizes because the system is similar to a quenched random system for which the lower critical dimension is $4$. Our numerical results are quantitatively explained by a linear elastic theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.19192v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuta Kuroda, Takeshi Kawasaki, Kunimasa Miyazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Study of Cleavable Bond-Modified Polyethylene for Circular Polymer Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09341v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There is considerable interest in designing new polymeric materials with built-in mechanisms for recycling. In this work, we present a systematic exploration of several polyethylene-based polymers that contain strategically incorporated cleavable bonds that are susceptible to chemical degradation. We consider ten distinct telechelic functionalities across varying chain lengths: ester, aromatic ester, anhydride, carbonate, urethane, siloxane, oxalate, acetal, urea, and amide linkages. Our study is focused on the effects of cleavable bonds on density, diffusion, enthalpy, and melting temperatures. We also examine the crystallization process. These are key properties for polymer processing and, by comparing them to those of linear polyethylene, we establish a platform that will help guide future synthetic efforts towards the design of sustainable plastics with performance comparable to that of traditional, high-performance polyolefin-based materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09341v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Ley-Flores, Archit Chabbi, Riccardo Alessandri, Sam Marsden, Isabella Vettese, Stuart J. Rowan, Juan J. de Pablo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slender Phoretic Loops and Knots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10217v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an asymptotic theory for solving the dynamics of slender autophoretic loops and knots. Our formulation is valid for non-intersecting 3D centrelines, with arbitrary chemical patterning and varying (circular) cross-sectional radius, allowing a broad class of slender active loops and knots to be studied. The theory is amenable to closed-form solutions in simpler cases, allowing us to analytically derive the swimming speed of chemically patterned tori, and the pumping strength (stresslet) of a uniformly active slender torus. Using simple numerical solutions of our asymptotic equations, we then elucidate the behaviour of many exotic active particle geometries, such as a bumpy uniformly active torus that spins and a Janus trefoil knot, which rotates as it swims forwards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10217v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panayiota Katsamba, Matthew D. Butler, Lyndon Koens, Thomas D. Montenegro-Johnson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relating absorbing and hard wall boundary conditions for a one-dimensional run-and-tumble particle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13200v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The connection between absorbing boundary conditions and hard walls is well established in the mathematical literature for a variety of stochastic models, including for instance the Brownian motion. In this paper we explore this duality for a different type of process which is of particular interest in physics and biology, namely the run-tumble-particle, a toy model of active particle. For a one-dimensional run-and-tumble particle subjected to an arbitrary external force, we provide a duality relation between the exit probability, i.e. the probability that the particle exits an interval from a given boundary before a certain time $t$, and the cumulative distribution of its position in the presence of hard walls at the same time $t$. We show this relation for a run-and-tumble particle in the stationary state by explicitly computing both quantities. At finite time, we provide a derivation using the Fokker-Planck equation. All the results are confirmed by numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13200v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathis Gu\'eneau, L\'eo Touzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
