<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 05:01:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Actuation of Cell Sheets in 3D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17834v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The alignment of fibers and cells in living tissues affect their mechanical properties and functionality. In this context, one can draw an analogy between living tissues and nematic liquid crystal elastomers. We explore this analogy by growing fibroblasts to high density on 2D patterned substrates and observing the contraction of cell sheets upon detachment from the substrates. When the fibroblast sheets detach, they undergo an anisotropic contraction, with a maximum contraction along the nematic director, like nematic elastomers do during a phase transition. We first quantify this anisotropy using substrates patterned with stripes to induce uniaxial alignment, finding that the cell sheets resemble nematic elastomers with a negative Poisson ratio. Then, we apply design principles used for programming curvature in nematic elastomers to actuate 3D structures in the detached fibroblast layers, demonstrating an application of these principles. This proof of concept shows the ability to control the 3-D shape through 2-D patterning in soft cell layers, leading to promising avenues to program tissues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17834v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirsten Endresen, Aniruddh Murali, Francesca Serra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immobility of isolated swarmer cells due to local liquid depletion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bacterial swarming is a complex phenomenon in which thousands of self-propelled rod-shaped cells move coherently on surfaces, providing an excellent example of active matter. However, bacterial swarming is different from most studied examples of active systems because single isolated cells do not move, while clusters do. The biophysical aspects underlying this behavior are unclear. In this work we explore the case of low local cell densities, where single cells become temporarily immobile. We show that immobility is related to local depletion of liquid. In addition, it is also associated with the state of the flagella. Specifically, the flagellar bundles at (temporarily) liquid depleted regions are completely spread-out. Our results suggest that dry models of self-propelled agents, which only consider steric alignments and neglect hydrodynamic effects, are oversimplified and are not sufficient to describe swarming bacteria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17842v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ajesh Jose, Benjamin Perez-Estay, Shira Omer Bendori, Avigdor Eldar, Daniel B. Kearns, Gil Ariel, Avraham Beer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation Dynamics of Entangled Linear Polymer Melts via Molecular Dynamics Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17953v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an extensive analysis of the relaxation dynamics of entangled linear polymer melts via long-time molecular dynamics simulations of a generic bead-spring model. We study the mean-squared displacements, the autocorrelation function of the end-to-end vector, $P(t)$, the single-chain dynamic structure factor, $S(q,t)$, and the linear viscoelastic properties, especially the shear stress relaxation modulus, $G(t)$. The simulation data are compared with the theoretically expected scaling laws for different time regimes of entangled melts, and with analytical expressions that account for different relaxation mechanisms in the tube model, namely, reptation, contour length fluctuation (CLF), and constraint release (CR). CLF involves a $t^{1/4}$ scaling regime in the time-dependence of $(1-P(t))$. With increasing chain length, a gradual development of this scaling regime is observed. In the absence of CR, the tube model further predicts that at long times, the chain dynamics is governed by one central quantity, the ``surviving tube fraction'' $\mu(t)$. As a result, one expects $S(q,t) \propto G(t) \propto P(t)$ in that time regime. We test this prediction by comparing $S(q,t)$ and $G(t)$ with $P(t)$. For both quantities, proportionality with $P(t)$ is not observed, indicating that CR has an important effect on the relaxation of these two quantities. Instead, to a very good approximation, we find $G(t)\propto P(t)^{2}$ at late times, which is consistent with the dynamic tube dilation or double reptation approximations for the CR process. In addition, we calculate non-local mobility functions, which can be used in dynamic density functional theories for entangled inhomogeneous polymer blends, and discuss the effect of entanglements on the shape of these functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17953v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alireza F. Behbahani, Friederike Schmid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological defects lead to energy transfer in active nematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active nematics are fluids in which the components have nematic symmetry and are driven out of equilibrium due to the microscopic generation of an active stress. When the active stress is high, it drives flows in the nematic and can lead to the proliferation of topological defects, a state we refer to as defect chaos. Using numerical simulations of active nematics, we observe energy transfer between length scales during defect chaos. We demonstrate that this energy transfer is driven by the exchange between variations in the orientation and degree of order in the nematic that predominantly occur during defect creation and annihilation. We then show that the primary features of energy transfer during defect chaos scale with the active length scale. Finally, we identify a second regime that features few defects, but rather bend walls. Similar to topological defects, these bend walls co-localize variations in the orientation with variations in the scalar order parameter leading to energy transfer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18214v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. G. Pearce, Berta Mart\'inez-Prat, Jordi Ign\'es-Mullol, Francesc Sagu\'es</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PyMatterSim: a Python Data Analysis Library for Computer Simulations of Materials Science, Physics, Chemistry, and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17970v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Computer simulation has become one of the most important tools in scientific research in many disciplines. Benefiting from the dynamical trajectories regulated by versatile interatomic interactions, various material properties can be quantitatively characterized at the atomic scale. This greatly deepens our understanding of Nature and provides incredible insights supplementing experimental observations. Hitherto, a plethora of literature discusses the computational discoveries in studying glasses in which positional disorder is inherent in their configurations. Motivated by active research and knowledge sharing, we developed a data analysis library in Python for computational materials science research. We hope to help promote scientific progress and narrow some technical gaps for the wide communities. The toolkit mainly focuses on physical analyses of glassy properties from the open-source simulator LAMMPS. Nevertheless, the code design renders high flexibility, with functionalities extendable to other computational tools. The library provides data-driven insights for different subjects and can be incorporated into advanced machine-learning workflows. The scope of the data analysis methodologies applies not only to materials science but also to physics, chemistry, and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17970v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. -C. Hu, J. Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-crystalline order in vibrated granular matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.01643v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quasi-crystals are aperiodic structures that present crystallographic properties which are not compatible with that of a single unit cell. Their revolutionary discovery in a metallic alloy, less than three decades ago, has required a full reconsideration of what we defined as a crystal structure. Surprisingly, quasi-crystalline structures have been discovered also at much larger length scales in different microscopic systems for which the size of elementary building blocks ranges between the nanometric to the micrometric scale. Here, we report the first experimental observation of spontaneous quasi-crystal self-assembly at the millimetric scale. This result is obtained in a fully athermal system of macroscopic spherical grains vibrated on a substrate. Starting from a liquid-like disordered phase, the grains begin to locally arrange into three types of squared and triangular tiles that eventually align, forming 8-fold symmetric quasi-crystal that has been predicted in simulation but not yet observed experimentally in non-atomic systems. These results are not only the proof of a novel route to spontaneously assemble quasi-crystals but are of fundamental interest for the connection between equilibrium and non-equilibrium statistical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.01643v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-023-02364-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Physics volume 20, 465-471 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Plati, Raphael Maire, Etienne Fayen, Francois Boulogne, Frederic Restagno, Frank Smallenburg, Giuseppe Foffi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shape Switching and Tunable Oscillations of Adaptive Droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08664v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Living materials adapt their shape to signals from the environment, yet the impact of shape changes on signal processing and associated feedback dynamics remain unclear. We find that droplets with signal-responsive interfacial tensions exhibit shape bistability, excitable dynamics, and oscillations. The underlying critical points reveal novel mechanisms for physical signal processing through shape adaptation in soft active materials. We recover signatures of one such critical point in experimental data from zebrafish embryos, where it supports boundary formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08664v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Dullweber, Roman Belousov, Camilla Autorino, Nicoletta Petridou, Anna Erzberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological transition in filamentous cyanobacteria: from motion to structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06314v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many active systems are capable of forming intriguing patterns at scales significantly larger than the size of their individual constituents. Cyanobacteria are one of the most ancient and important phyla of organisms that has allowed the evolution of more complex life forms. Despite its importance, the role of motility on the pattern formation of their colonies is not understood. Here, we investigate the large-scale collective effects and rich dynamics of gliding filamentous cyanobacteria colonies, while still retaining information about the individual constituents' dynamics and their interactions. We investigate both the colony's transient and steady-state dynamics and find good agreement with experiments. We furthermore show that the Peclet number and aligning interaction strength govern the system's topological transition from an isotropic distribution to a state of large-scale reticulate patterns. Although the system is topologically non-trivial, the parallel and perpendicular pair correlation functions provide structural information about the colony, and thus can be used to extract information about the early stages of biofilm formation. Finally, we find that the effects of the filaments' length cannot be reduced to a system of interacting points. Our model proves to reproduce both cyanobacteria colonies and systems of biofilaments where curvature is transported by motility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06314v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-024-01866-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jan Cammann, Mixon K. Faluweki, Nayara Dambacher, Lucas Goehring, Marco G. Mazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the Efficiency and Effective Temperature of Bacterial Heat Engines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19059v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a Brownian dynamics simulation of the bacterial Stirling engine studied by Krishnamurthy et al., Nat. Phys. 12, 1134 (2016). In their experimental setup, an overdamped colloid in an optical trap with time-modulated stiffness interacts with a bacterial bath that we represent by an ensemble of overdamped active particles. In the parameter regime of the experiment the thermodynamic performance is governed by an effective temperature and can be parametrized analytically by active Brownian particle models. We quantitatively reproduce the efficiencies reported for the experiments under the assumption that energy exchange with the bath during isochores of the cycle is entirely recuperated and in agreement with the second law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19059v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roland Wiese, Klaus Kroy, Viktor Holubec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Ornstein-Uhlenbeck Model for Bacterial Heat Engines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19794v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use Brownian dynamics simulations to study a model of a cyclic bacterial heat engine based on a harmonically confined colloidal probe particle in a bath formed by active Brownian particles. For intermediate activities, active noise experienced by large enough probes becomes Gaussian with exponential autocorrelation function. We show that, in this experimentally pertinent regime, the probability densities for stochastic work, heat, and efficiency are well represented by those of an effective active Ornstein-Uhlenbeck particle (AOUP). Due to the probe's fast relaxation in the potential in typical experimental implementations, good agreement can prevail even when the noise autocorrelation function develops non-exponential tails. Our results show that the AOUP provides a convenient and accurate, analytically tractable effective model to mimic and analyze experimental bacterial heat engines, especially when operating with comparatively large probes and stiff traps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19794v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roland Wiese, Klaus Kroy, Viktor Holubec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planar network statistics for two-dimensional rupturing foams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We conduct experiments on a class of two-dimensional semiwet foams generated through compressing a three-dimensional soap foam between two glass plates. To induce a spatially uniform rupturing process on foam boundaries, an additional plate is heated and placed on top of the unheated plates. For 30 separate foam samples, we record network statistics related to cell side numbers and areas as the foam coarsens over a half-minute. We find that the Aboav law and a quadratic Lewis Law, two commonly used relations between network topology and geometry, hold well for preheated foams. To track how well these laws are maintained as the foam ages, we introduce metrics for measuring a foam's disorder over time and build simple autonomous models for these metrics. While the quadratic Lewis Law is found to hold well throughout the rupture process, the Aboav law breaks down rapidly when the Gini coefficient, used for measuring disparity of cell areas, is approximately 0.8.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20858v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Klobusicky, Elif Onat, Vasilios Konstantinou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freely Suspended Nematic and Smectic Films and Free-Standing Smectic Filaments in the Ferroelectric Nematic Realm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04019v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that stable, freely suspended liquid crystal films can be made from the ferroelectric nematic ($\mathrm{N_F}$) phase and from the recently discovered polar, lamellar $\mathrm{SmZ_A}$ and $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ phases. The $\mathrm{N_F}$ films display two-dimensional, smectic-like parabolic focal conic textures comprising director/polarization bend that are a manifestation of the electrostatic suppression of director splay in the film plane. In the $\mathrm{SmZ_A}$ and $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ phases, the smectic layers orient preferentially normal to the film surfaces, a condition never found in typical thermotropic or lyotropic lamellar LC phases, with the $\mathrm{SmZ_A}$ films exhibiting focal-conic fan textures mimicking the appearance of typical smectics in glass cells when the layers are oriented normal to the plates, and the $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ films showing a texture of plaquettes of uniform in-plane orientation where both bend and splay are suppressed, separated by grain boundaries. The $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ phase can also be drawn into thin filaments, in which X-ray scattering reveals that the smectic layer planes are normal to the filament axis. Remarkably, the filaments are mechanically stable even if they break, forming free-standing, fluid filaments supported only at one end. The unique architectures of these films and filaments are stabilized by the electrostatic self-interaction of the liquid crystal polarization field, which enables the formation of confined, fluid structures that are fundamentally different from those of their counterparts made using previously known liquid crystal phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04019v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keith G. Hedlund, Vikina Martinez, Xi Chen, Cheol S. Park, Joseph E. Maclennan, Matthew A. Glaser, Noel A. Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective dynamics of densely confined active polar disks with self- and mutual alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13705v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the emerging collective states in a simple mechanical model of a dense group of self-propelled polar disks with off-centered rotation, confined within a circular arena. Each disk presents self-alignment towards the sum of contact forces acting on it, resulting from disk-substrate interactions, while also displaying mutual alignment with neighbors due to having its center of rotation located a distance R behind its centroid so that central contact forces can also introduce torques. The effect of both alignment mechanisms produces a variety of collective states that combine high-frequency localized circular oscillations with low-frequency milling around the center of the arena, in fluid or solid regimes. We consider cases with small/large R values, isotropic/anisotropic disk-substrate damping, smooth/rough arena boundaries, different densities, and multiple systems sizes, showing that the emergent collective states that we identify are robust, generic, and potentially observable in real-world natural or artificial systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13705v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weizhen Tang, Yating Zheng, Amir Shee, Guozheng Lin, Zhangang Han, Pawel Romanczuk, Cristi\'an Huepe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum dynamics of photophysical aggregates in conjugated polymers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14675v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Photophysical aggregates are ubiquitous in many solid-state microstructures adopted by conjugated polymers, in which $\pi$ electrons interact with those in other polymer chains or those in other chromophores along the chain. These interactions fundamentally define the electronic and optical properties of the polymer film. While valuable insight can be gained from linear excitation and photoluminescence spectra, nonlinear coherent excitation spectral lineshapes provide intricate understanding on the electronic couplings that define the aggregate and their fluctuations. Here, we discuss the coherent two-dimensional excitation lineshape of a model hairy-rod conjugated polymer. At zero population waiting time, we find a $\pi/2$ phase shift between the 0-0 and 0-1 vibronic peaks in the real and imaginary components of the complex coherent spectrum, as well as a dynamic phase rotation with population waiting time over timescales that are longer than the optical dephasing time. We conjecture that these are markers of relaxation of the photophysical aggregate down the tight manifold of the exciton band. These results highlight the potential for coherent spectroscopy via analysis of the complex spectral lineshape to become a key tool to develop structure-property relationships in complex functional materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14675v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry J. Kantrow, Elizabeth Guti\'errez-Meza, Hongmo Li, Qiao He, Martin Heeney, Natalie Stingelin, Eric R. Bittner, Carlos Silva-Acu\~na</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular chirality quantification: Tools and benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08114v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Molecular chirality has traditionally been viewed as a binary property where a molecule is classified as either chiral or achiral, yet in the recent decades mathematical methods for quantifying chirality have been explored. Here we use toy molecular systems to systematically compare the performance of two state of the art chirality measures (1) the Continuous Chirality Measure (CCM) and (2) the Chirality Characteristic ($\chi$). We find that both methods exhibit qualitatively similar behavior when applied to simple molecular systems such as a four-site molecule or the polymer double-helix, but we show that the CCM may be more suitable for evaluating the chirality of arbitrary molecules or abstract structures such as normal vibrational modes. We discuss a range of considerations for applying these methods to molecular systems in general, and we provide links to user-friendly codes for both methods. We aim this paper to serve as a concise resource for scientists attempting to familiarize themselves with these chirality measures or attempting to implement chirality measures in their own work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08114v4</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0200716</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 160, 164104 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Abraham, Abraham Nitzan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Green-Kubo relation for friction in nanofluidics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07134v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A central aim of statistical mechanics is to establish connections between a system's microscopic fluctuations and its macroscopic response to a perturbation. For non-equilibrium transport properties, this amounts to establishing Green-Kubo (GK) relationships. In hydrodynamics, relating such GK expressions for liquid-solid friction to macroscopic slip boundary conditions has remained a long-standing problem due to two challenges: (i) The GK running integral of the force autocorrelation function decays to zero rather than reaching a well-defined plateau value; and (ii) debates persist on whether such a transport coefficient measures an intrinsic interfacial friction or an effective friction in the system. Inspired by ideas from the coarse-graining community, we derive a GK relation for liquid-solid friction where the force autocorrelation is sampled with a constraint of momentum conservation in the liquid. Our expression does not suffer from the "plateau problem" and unambiguously measures an effective friction coefficient, in an analogous manner to Stokes' law. We further establish a link between the derived friction coefficient and the hydrodynamic slip length, enabling a straightforward assessment of continuum hydrodynamics across length scales. We find that continuum hydrodynamics describes the simulation results quantitatively for confinement length scales all the way down to 1 nm. Our approach amounts to a straightforward modification to the present standard method of quantifying interfacial friction from molecular simulations, making possible a sensible comparison between surfaces of vastly different slippage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07134v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0238363</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 161, 201102 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anna T. Bui, Stephen J. Cox</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
