<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 04:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrodynamic Spin-Pairing and Active Polymerization of Oppositely Spinning Rotors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07554v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rotors are common in nature - from rotating membrane-proteins to superfluid-vortices. Yet, little is known about the collective dynamics of heterogeneous populations of rotors. Here, we show experimentally, numerically, and analytically that at small but finite inertia, a mixed population of oppositely spinning rotors spontaneously self-assembles into active chains, which we term gyromers. The gyromers are formed and stabilized by fluid motion and steric interactions alone. A detailed analysis of pair interaction shows that rotors with the same spin repel and orbit each other while opposite rotors spin-pair and propagate together as bound dimers. Rotor dimers interact with individual rotors, each other, and the boundaries to form chains. A minimal model predicts the formation of gyromers in numerical simulations and their possible subsequent folding into secondary structures of lattices and rings. This inherently out-of-equilibrium polymerization process holds promise for engineering self-assembled metamaterials such as artificial proteins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07554v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattan Gelvan, Artyom Chirko, Jonathan Kirpitch, Yahav Lavie, Noa Israel, Naomi Oppenheimer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-organization and memory in a cyclically driven elasto-plastic model of an amorphous solid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mechanical behavior of disordered materials such as dense suspensions, glasses or granular materials depends on their thermal and mechanical past. Here we report the memory behavior of a quenched mesoscopic elasto-plastic (QMEP) model. After prior oscillatory training, a simple read-out protocol gives access to both the training protocol's amplitude and the last shear direction. The memory of direction emerges from the development of a mechanical polarization during training. The analysis of sample-to-sample fluctuations gives direct access to the irreversibility transition. Despite the quadrupolar nature of the elastic interactions in amorphous solids, a behavior close to Return Point Memory (RPM) is observed. The quasi RPM property is used to build a simple Preisach-like model of directional memory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07621v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dheeraj Kumar, Muhittin Mungan, Sylvain Patinet, Damien Vandembroucq</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous behavior of electric-field Fr\'eedericksz transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fr\'eedericksz transitions in nematic liquid crystals are re-examined with a focus on differences between systems with magnetic fields and those with electric fields. A magnetic field can be treated as uniform in a liquid-crystal medium; while a nonuniform director field will in general cause nonuniformity of the local electric field as well. Despite these differences, the widely held view is that the formula for the threshold of local instability in an electric-field Fr\'eedericksz transition can be obtained from that for the magnetic-field transition in the same geometry by simply replacing the magnetic parameters by their electric counterparts. However, it was shown in [Arakelyan, Karayan, and Chilingaryan, Sov. Phys. Dokl., 29 (1984) 202-204] that in two of the six classical electric-field Fr\'eedericksz transitions, the local-instability threshold should be strictly greater than that predicted by this magnetic-field analogy. Why this elevation of the threshold occurs is carefully examined, and a simple test to determine when it can happen is given. This "anomalous behavior" is not restricted to classical Fr\'eedericksz transitions and is shown to be present in certain layered systems (planar cholesterics, smectic-A) and in certain nematic systems that exhibit periodic instabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07654v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene C. Gartland Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature induces and enhances transport of spinning colloids through narrow channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The effect of curvature and how it induces and enhances the transport of colloidal particles driven through narrow channels represent an unexplored research avenue. Here we combine experiments and simulations to investigate the dynamics of magnetically driven colloidal particles confined through a narrow, circular channel. We use an external precessing magnetic field to induce a net torque and spin the particles at a defined angular velocity. Due to the spinning, the particle propulsion emerges from the different hydrodynamic coupling with the inner and outer walls and strongly depends on the curvature. The experimental findings are combined with finite element numerical simulations that predict a positive rotation translation coupling in the mobility matrix. Further, we explore the collective transport of many particles across the curved geometry, making an experimental realization of a driven single file system. With our finding, we elucidate the effect of curvature on the transport of microscopic particles which could be important to understand the complex, yet rich, dynamics of particle systems driven through curved microfluidic channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07661v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D4SM00829D</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Eric Cereceda-L\'opez, Marco De Corato, Ignacio Pagonabarraga, Fanlong Meng, Pietro Tierno, Antonio Ortiz-Ambriz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical hysterons with tunable interactions of general sign</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hysterons are the basic units of hysteresis that underlie many of the complex behaviors of disordered matter. Recent work has sought to develop designs for mechanical hysterons, both to better understand their interactions and to create materials that respond to their mechanical environment in novel ways. Elastic structures including slender beams, creased sheets, and shells offer the requisite bistability for artificial hysterons, but producing and controlling interactions between such structures has proven challenging. Here we report a mechanical hysteron composed of rigid bars and linear springs, which has controllable properties and tunable interactions of general sign. We derive an approximate mapping from the system parameters to the hysteron properties, and we show how collective behaviors of multiple hysterons can be targeted by adjusting geometric parameters on the fly. Our results provide a basic step towards hysteron-based materials that can sense, compute, and respond to their mechanical environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07726v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph D. Paulsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric control and memory in networks of bistable elements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sequential response of driven frustrated media encodes memory effects and hidden computational capabilities. While abstract hysteron models can capture these effects, they require phenomenologically introduced interactions, limiting their predictive power. Here we introduce networks of bistable elements - physical hysterons - whose interactions are controlled by the networks' geometry. These networks realize a wide range of previously unobserved exotic pathways, including those that surpass current hysteron models. Our work paves the way for advanced microscopic models of memory and the rational design of (meta)materials with targeted pathways and capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07804v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dor Shohat, Martin van Hecke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of pressure on the carbon dioxide hydrate-water interfacial free energy along its dissociation line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of pressure on the carbon dioxide (CO$_{2}$) hydrate-water interfacial free energy along its dissociation line using advanced computer simulation techniques. In previous works, we have determined the interfacial energy of the hydrate at $400 \,\text{bar}$ using the TIP4P/ice and TraPPE molecular models for water and CO$_{2}$, respectively, in combination with two different extensions of the Mold Integration technique [J. Chem. Phys. 141, 134709 (2014)]. Results obtained from computer simulation, $29(2)$ and $30(2)\,\text{mJ/m}^{2}$, are found to be in excellent agreement with the only two measurements that exist in the literature, $28(6)\,\text{mJ/m}^{2}$ determined by Uchida et al. [J. Phys. Chem. B 106, 8202 (2002)] and $30(3)\,\text{mJ/m}^{2}$ by Anderson et al. [J. Phys. Chem. B 107, 3507 (2002)]. Since the experiments do not allow to obtain the variation of the interfacial energy along the dissociation line of the hydrate, we extend our previous studies to quantify the effect of pressure on the interfacial energy at different pressures. Our results suggest that there exists a correlation between the interfacial free energy values and the pressure, i.e., it decreases with the pressure between $100$ and $1000\,\text{bar}$. We expect that the combination of reliable molecular models and advanced simulation techniques could help to improve our knowledge of the thermodynamic parameters that control the interfacial free energy of hydrates from a molecular perspective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07844v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0139699</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 158, 194704 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Crist\'obal Romero-Guzm\'an, Iv\'an M. Zer\'on, Jes\'us Algaba, Bruno Mendiboure, Jos\'e Manuel M\'iguez, Felipe J. Blas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Un)buckling mechanics of epithelial monolayers under compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When cell sheets fold during development, their apical or basal surfaces constrict and cell shapes approach the geometric singularity in which these surfaces vanish. Here, we reveal the mechanical consequences of this geometric singularity for tissue folding in a minimal vertex model of an epithelial monolayer. In simulations of the buckling of the epithelium under compression and numerical solutions of the corresponding continuum model, we discover an "unbuckling" bifurcation: At large compression, the buckling amplitude can decrease with increasing compression. By asymptotic solution of the continuum equations, we reveal that this bifurcation comes with a large stiffening of the epithelium. Our results thus provide the mechanical basis for absorption of compressive stresses by tissue folds such as the cephalic furrow during germband extension in Drosophila.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07928v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chandraniva Guha Ray, Pierre A. Haas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loading-dependent microscale measures control bulk properties in granular material: an experimental test of the Stress-Force-Fabric relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08140v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The bulk behaviour of granular materials is tied to its mesoscale and particle-scale features: strength properties arise from the buildup of various anisotropic structures at the particle-scale induced by grain connectivity (fabric), force transmission, and frictional mobilization. More fundamentally, these anisotropic structures work collectively to define features like the bulk friction coefficient and the stress tensor at the macroscale and can be explained by the Stress-Force-Fabric (SFF) relationship stemming from the microscale. Although the SFF relation has been extensively verified by discrete numerical simulations, a laboratory realization has remained elusive due to the challenge of measuring both normal and frictional contact forces. In this study, we analyze experiments performed on a photoelastic granular system under four different loading conditions: uniaxial compression, isotropic compression, pure shear, and annular shear. During these experiments, we record particle locations, contacts, and normal and frictional forces vectors to measure the particle-scale response to progressing strain. We track microscale measures like the packing fraction, average coordination number and average normal force along with anisotropic distributions of contacts and forces. We match the particle-scale anisotropy to the bulk using the SFF relation, which is founded on two key principles, a Stress Rule to describe the stress tensor and a Sum Rule to describe the bulk friction coefficient; we find that the Sum and Stress Rules accurately describe bulk measurements. Additionally, we test the assumption that fabric and forces transmit load equally through our granular packings and show that this assumption is sufficient at large strain values, and can be applied to areas like rock mechanics, soft colloids, or cellular tissue where force information is inaccessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08140v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carmen L. Lee, Ephraim Bililign, Emilien Az\'ema, Karen E. Daniels</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reversible Electron-Beam Patterning of Colloidal Nanoparticles at Fluid Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08192v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The directed self-assembly of colloidal nanoparticles (NPs) using external fields guides the formation of sophisticated hierarchical materials but becomes less effective with decreasing particle size. As an alternative, electron-beam-driven assembly offers a potential avenue for targeted nanoscale manipulation, yet remains poorly controlled due to the variety and complexity of beam interaction mechanisms. Here, we investigate the beam-particle interaction of silica NPs pinned to the fluid-vacuum interface of ionic liquid droplets. In these experiments, scanning electron microscopy of the droplet surface resolves NP trajectories over space and time while simultaneously driving their reorganization. With this platform, we demonstrate the ability to direct particle transport and create transient, reversible colloidal patterns on the droplet surface. By tuning the beam voltage, we achieve precise control over both the strength and sign of the beam-particle interaction, with low voltages repelling particles and high voltages attracting them. This response stems from the formation of well-defined solvent flow fields generated from trace radiolysis of the ionic liquid, as determined through statistical analysis of single-particle trajectories under varying solvent composition. Altogether, electron-beam-guided assembly introduces a versatile strategy for nanoscale colloidal manipulation, offering new possibilities for the design of dynamic, reconfigurable systems with applications in adaptive photonics and catalysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08192v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan G. Raybin, Ethan J. Dunsworth, Veronica Guo, Naomi S. Ginsberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shape, temperature and density interplay in depletion forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Via numerical simulations and analytical calculations, depletion forces are studied in mixtures of small and big particles that interact via soft repulsive potentials. While big particles are spherical, small particles are nonspherical with shapes that vary gradually, from squares to rods via intermediate shapes. The mixtures are studied for a wide range of densities and temperature. Depletion forces and their resulting potentials depend on the interplay of shape, temperature and density, an argument that is elaborated qualitatively and quantitatively. While in some thermodynamic conditions, depletion potentials of distinct shapes are distinguishable, in different conditions, they are very similar. Finally, I propose novel computational models and experiments for further investigation of the effect of morphology on phase separation in and out of thermal equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08209v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itay Azizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical phase transitions in the non-reciprocal Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-reciprocal interactions in many-body systems lead to time-dependent states, commonly observed in biological, chemical, and ecological systems. The stability of these states in the thermodynamic limit, as well as the criticality of the phase transition from static to time-dependent states remains an open question. To tackle these questions, we study a minimalistic system endowed with non-reciprocal interactions: an Ising model with two spin species having opposing goals. The mean-field equation predicts three stable phases: disordered, ordered, and a time-dependent swap phase. Large scale numerical simulations support the following: (i) in 2D, the swap phase is destabilized by defects; (ii) in 3D, the swap phase is stable, and has the properties of a time-crystal; (iii) the transition from disorder to swap in 3D is characterized by the critical exponents of the 3D XY model, in agreement with the emerging continuous symmetry of time translation invariance; (iv) when the two species have fully anti-symmetric couplings, the static-order phase is unstable in any dimension due to droplet growth; (v) in the general case of asymmetric couplings, static order can be restored by a droplet-capture mechanism preventing the droplets from growing indefinitely. We provide details on the full phase diagram which includes first- and second-order-like phase transitions and study the coarsening dynamics of the swap as well as the static-order phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07481v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yael Avni, Michel Fruchart, David Martin, Daniel Seara, Vincenzo Vitelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hammering at the entropy: A GENERIC-guided approach to learning polymeric rheological constitutive equations using PINNs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07545v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a versatile framework that employs Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) to discover the entropic contribution that leads to the constitutive equation for the extra-stress in rheological models of polymer solutions. In this framework the training of the Neural Network is guided by an evolution equation for the conformation tensor which is GENERIC-compliant. We compare two training methodologies for the data-driven PINN constitutive models: one trained on data from the analytical solution of the Oldroyd-B model under steady-state rheometric flows (PINN-rheometric), and another trained on in-silico data generated from complex flow CFD simulations around a cylinder that use the Oldroyd-B model (PINN-complex). The capacity of the PINN models to provide good predictions are evaluated by comparison with CFD simulations using the underlying Oldroyd-B model as a reference. Both models are capable of predicting flow behavior in transient and complex conditions; however, the PINN-complex model, trained on a broader range of mixed flow data, outperforms the PINN-rheometric model in complex flow scenarios. The geometry agnostic character of our methodology allows us to apply the learned PINN models to flows with different topologies than the ones used for training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07545v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Nieto Simavilla, Andrea Bonfanti, Imanol Garc\'ia de Beristain, Pep Espa\~nol, Marco Ellero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Nonequilibrium Multicomponent Coexistence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07620v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multicomponent phase separation is a routine occurrence in both living and synthetic systems. Thermodynamics provides a straightforward path to determine the phase boundaries that characterize these transitions for systems at equilibrium. The prevalence of phase separation in complex systems outside the confines of equilibrium motivates the need for a genuinely nonequilibrium theory of multicomponent phase coexistence. Here, we develop a mechanical theory for coexistence that casts coexistence criteria into the familiar form of equality of state functions. Our theory generalizes traditional equilibrium notions such as the species chemical potential and thermodynamic pressure to systems out of equilibrium. Crucially, while these notions may not be identifiable for all nonequilibrium systems, we numerically verify their existence for a variety of systems by introducing the phenomenological Multicomponent Active Model B+. Our work establishes an initial framework for understanding multicomponent coexistence that we hope can serve as the basis for a comprehensive theory for high-dimensional nonequilibrium phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07620v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Jen Chiu, Daniel Evans, Ahmad K. Omar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Interplay Between Forces, Particle Rearrangements, and Macroscopic Stress Fluctuations in Sheared 2D Granular Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05479v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent studies have established correlations between non-affine motion and macroscopic stress fluctuations in sheared granular media. However, a comprehensive examination of the relationship between non-affine motion, macroscopic stress fluctuations, and inter-particle forces remains lacking. We investigated this interplay in 2D granular media subjected to plane shear. We found that particle rearrangements originated from regions featuring the greatest instantaneous reduction of inter-particle forces. This "greatest reduction" (GR) region coincided with the location in which the maximal non-affine motion, as quantified by D2min, first coalesced into a single connected region. The magnitude of the maximal non-affine motion correlated strongly with the magnitude of the macroscopic stress fluctuation. Furthermore, this correlation increased when particles in a larger neighborhood of the point of maximal non-affine motion were included in the calculation, suggesting that plastic events are best thought of not as point-like events but regional events. Our results held for various sliding coefficients and a variety of sample sizes. Our findings suggest that elastoplastic models should consider plastic events as regional rather than point-like.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05479v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kwangmin Lee, Ryan C. Hurley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning collective actuation of active solids by optimizing activity localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13682v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Active solids, more specifically elastic lattices embedded with polar active units, exhibit collective actuation when the elasto-active feedback, generically present in such systems, exceeds some critical value. The dynamics then condensates on a small fraction of the vibrational modes, the selection of which obeys non trivial rules rooted in the nonlinear part of the dynamics. So far the complexity of the selection mechanism has limited the design of specific actuation. Here we investigate numerically how, localizing the activity on a fraction of modes, one can select non-trivial collective actuation. We perform numerical simulations of an agent based model on triangular and disordered lattices and vary the concentration and the localization of the active agents on the lattices nodes. Both contribute to the distribution of the elastic energy across the modes. We then introduce an algorithm, which, for a given fraction of active nodes, evolves the localization of the activity in such a way that the energy distribution on a few targeted modes is maximized -- or minimized. We illustrate on a specific targeted actuation, how the algorithm performs as compared to manually chosen localization of the activity. While, in the case of the ordered lattice, a well educated guess performs better than the algorithm, the latter outperform the manual trials in the case of the disordered lattice. Finally, the analysis of the results in the case of the ordered lattice leads us to introduce a design principle based on a measure of the susceptibility of the modes to be activated along certain activation paths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13682v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davi Lazzari, Olivier Dauchot, Carolina Brito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-correlation between excitations and locally-favored structures in glass-forming systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12738v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dynamics that are microscopic in space and time, in which particles commit to a position, so-called excitations, are considered the elementary unit of relaxation in the Dynamic Facilitation (DF) theory of the glass transition. Meanwhile, geometric motifs known as locally favored structures (LFS) are associated with vitrification in many glassformers. Recent work indicates that the probability of particles found both in locally favored structures (LFS) and excitations decreases significantly upon supercooling suggesting that there is an anti-correlation between them [Ortlieb et al, Nature Commun. 14, 2621 (2023)]. However, the spatial relationship between excitations and LFS remains unclear. By employing state-of-the-art GPU computer simulations and colloid experiments, we analyze this relationship between LFS and excitations in model glassformers. We demonstrate that there is a spatial separation between the two in deeply supercooled liquids. This may be due to the fact that LFS are well-packed, thus they are relatively stable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12738v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danqi Lang, Camille Scalliet, C. Patrick Royall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integer Topological Defects Reveal Anti-Symmetric Forces in Active Nematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15431v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cell layers are often categorized as contractile or extensile active nematics but recent experiments on neural progenitor cells with induced $+1$ topological defects challenge this classification. In a bottom-up approach, we first study a relevant particle-level model and then analyze a continuous theory derived from it. We show that both model and theory account qualitatively for the main experimental result, i.e. accumulation of cells at the core of any type of +1 defect. We argue that cell accumulation is essentially due to two generally ignored 'effective active forces'.
  We finally discuss the relevance and consequences of our findings in the context of other cellular active nematics experiments and previously proposed theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15431v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihui Zhao, Yisong Yao, He Li, Yongfeng Zhao, Yujia Wang, Hepeng Zhang, Hugues Chat'e, Masaki Sano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying topological floppy modes in the continuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15850v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In floppy mechanical lattices, robust edge states and bulk Weyl modes are manifestations of underlying topological invariants. To explore the universality of these phenomena independent of microscopic detail, we formulate topological mechanics in the continuum. By augmenting standard linear elasticity with additional fields of soft modes, we define a continuum version of Maxwell counting, which balances degrees of freedom and mechanical constraints. With one additional field, these augmented elasticity theories can break spatial inversion symmetry and harbor topological edge states. We also show that two additional fields are necessary to harbor Weyl points in two dimensions, and define continuum invariants to classify these states. In addition to constructing the general form of topological elasticity based on symmetries, we derive the coefficients based on the systematic homogenization of microscopic lattices. By solving the resulting partial differential equations, we efficiently predict coarse-grained deformations due to topological floppy modes without the need for a detailed lattice-based simulation. Our discovery formulates novel design principles and efficient computational tools for topological states of matter, and points to their experimental implementation in mechanical metamaterials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15850v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Tan, Anton Souslov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat-induced liquid hovering in liquid-gas coexistence under gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05817v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a liquid-gas coexistence system in a container under gravity with heat flow in the direction opposite to gravity. By molecular dynamics simulation, we find that the liquid buoys up and continues to float steadily. The height at which the liquid floats is determined by a dimensionless parameter related to the ratio of the temperature gradient to gravity. We confirm that supercooled gas remains stable above the liquid. We provide a phenomenological argument for explaining the phenomenon from a simple thermodynamic assumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05817v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.117101</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 117101 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Akira Yoshida, Naoko Nakagawa, Shin-ichi Sasa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yielding is an absorbing phase transition with vanishing critical fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11797v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The yielding transition in athermal complex fluids can be interpreted as an absorbing phase transition between an elastic, absorbing state with high mesoscopic degeneracy and a flowing, active state. We characterize quantitatively this phase transition in an elastoplastic model under fixed applied shear stress, using a finite-size scaling analysis. We find vanishing critical fluctuations of the order parameter (i.e., the shear rate), and relate this property to the convex character of the phase transition ($\beta &gt;1$). We show explicitly that the CDP class is recovered when both properties are relaxed. We locate yielding within a family of models akin to fixed-energy sandpile (FES) models, only with long-range redistribution kernels with zero-modes that result from mechanical equilibrium. For redistribution kernels with sufficiently fast decay, this family of models belong to a short-range universality class distinct from the Conserved Directed Percolation class of usual FES, which is induced by zero modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11797v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.268203</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tristan Jocteur, Shana Figueiredo, Kirsten Martens, Eric Bertin, Romain Mari</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
