<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 04:00:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Ordering in Binary Mixtures of Active Nematic Fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19061v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use a continuum, two-fluid approach to study a mixture of two active nematic fluids. Even in the absence of thermodynamically-driven ordering, for mixtures of different activities we observe turbulent microphase separation, where domains form and disintegrate chaotically in an active turbulent background. This is a weak effect if there is no elastic nematic alignment between the two fluid components, but is greatly enhanced in the presence of an elastic alignment or substrate friction. We interpret the results in terms of relative flows between the two species which result from active anchoring at concentration gradients. Our results may have relevance in interpreting epithelial cell sorting and the dynamics of multi-species bacterial colonies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19061v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saraswat Bhattacharyya, Julia M. Yeomans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-reverting vortices in chiral active matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is currently a strong interest in the collective behavior of chiral active particles that can propel and rotate themselves. In the presence of alignment interactions for many chiral particles, chiral self-propulsion can induce vortex patterns in the velocity fields. However, these emerging patterns are non-permanent, and do not induce global vorticity. Here we combine theoretical arguments and computer simulations to predict a so-far unknown class of collective behavior. We show that, for chiral active particles, vortices with significant dynamical coherence emerge spontaneously. They originate from the interplay between attraction interactions and chirality in the absence of alignment interactions. Depending on parameters, the vortices can either feature a constant vorticity or a vorticity that oscillates periodically in time, resulting in self-reverting vortices. Our results may guide future experiments to realize customized collective phenomena such as spontaneously rotating gears and patterns with a self-reverting order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19062v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Caprini, Benno Liebchen, Hartmut L\"owen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear microrheology with time-dependent forces -- Application to recoils in viscoelastic fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a theoretical analysis of the motion of a tracer colloid driven by a time-dependent force through a viscoelastic fluid. The recoil of the colloid after application of a strong force is determined. It provides insights into the elastic forces stored locally in the fluid and their weakening by plastic processes. We generalize the mode coupling theory of microrheology to include time-dependent forces. After deriving the equations of motion for the tracer correlator and simplifying to a schematic model we apply the theory to a switch-off force protocol that features the recoiling of the tracer after cessation of the driving. We also include Langevin dynamics simulations to compare to the results of the theory. A non-monotonic trend of the recoil amplitude is found in the theory and confirmed in the simulations. The linear-response approximation is also verified in the small-force regime. While the overall agreement between simulation and theory is good, simulation shows that the theory predicts a too strong non-monotonous dependence of the recoil distance on the applied force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19085v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolas Ditz, Antonio M. Puertas, M. Fuchs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of static to dynamic mechanical behavior in topological nonreciprocal robotic metamaterials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on the Maxwell-Beatty reciprocity theorem, static non-reciprocity has been realized by using nonlinearity, but this non-reciprocity has strict restrictions on input amplitude and structure size(number of units). Here, we design a robotic metamaterial with two components of displacement and rotation, which uses active control to add external forces on the units to break reciprocity at the level of the interactions between the units. We show analytically and simulatively that breaking reciprocity at the level of the interactions directly leads to a strong asymmetric response of displacement in a static system, this displacement-specific characteristic not only has no restrictions on size, input amplitude, and suitable geometric asymmetry, but also can be transferred to rotation by coupling under large deformation. After the evolution from statics to dynamics, asymmetric transmission and unidirectional amplification of vector solitons are both implemented in this system. Our research uncovers the evolution of static non-reciprocity to dynamic non-reciprocity while building a bridge between non-reciprocity physics and soliton science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19231v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zehuan Tang, Yuanwen Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure and dynamics of amphiphilic patchy cubes in a nanoslit under shear</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Patchy nanocubes are intriguing materials with simple shapes and space-filling and multidirectional bonding properties. Previous studies have revealed various mesoscopic structures such as colloidal crystals in the solid regime and rod-like or fractal-like aggregates in the liquid regime of the phase diagram. Recent studies have also shown that mesoscopic structural properties, such as average cluster size $\left\langle M \right\rangle$ and orientational order, in amphiphilic nanocube suspensions are associated with macroscopic viscosity changes, mainly owing to differences in cluster shape among patch arrangements. Although many studies have been conducted on the self-assembled structures of nanocubes in bulk, little is known about their self-assembly in nanoscale spaces or structural changes under shear. In this study, we investigated mixtures of one- and two-patch amphiphilic nanocubes confined in two flat parallel plates at rest and under shear using molecular dynamics simulations coupled with multiparticle collision dynamics. We considered two different patch arrangements for the two-patch particles and two different slit widths $H$ to determine the degree of confinement in constant-volume fractions in the liquid regime of the phase diagram. We revealed two unique cluster morphologies that have not been previously observed under bulk conditions. At rest, the size of the rod-like aggregates increased with decreasing $H$, whereas that of the fractal-like aggregates remained constant. Under weak shear with strong confinement, the rod-like aggregates maintained a larger $\left\langle M \right\rangle$ than the fractal-like aggregates, which were more rigid and maintained a larger $\left\langle M \right\rangle$ than the rod-like aggregates under bulk conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19270v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Ikeda, Yusei Kobayashi, Masashi Yamakawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of strain-rate softening behavior in jammed granular media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The strain-rate sensitivity of confined granular materials has been widely explored, with most findings exhibiting rate-strengthening behaviors. This study, however, reveals a distinct rate-softening behavior across a certain strain rate range based on triaxial tests on particle clusters of various materials with different surface properties, particle sizes, shapes, and stiffness. This softening effect is especially pronounced in the case of common rice particles. By examining the behavior of rice particles under different confining pressure and surface conditions, and directly measuring the frictional coefficient across various loading rates, we find that the reduction in surface frictional coefficient with the increasing strain rate predominantly contributes to this rate-softening behavior. This conclusion is validated by results from Finite Element Method (FEM) simulations. Additionally, we identify confining pressure as a critical factor regulating the normal stress between particles, and thereby enhancing frictional behavior. Rheometer tests reveal that the shear modulus exhibits a similar rate-softening trend. This study of rate-softening behavior in granular materials enhances our understanding of the mechanisms during their deformation under confining pressure. It also suggests that local inter-particle tribology significantly impacts overall granular behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19321v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingchao Liu, Weining Mao, Yiqiu Zhao, Qin Xu, Yixiang Gan, Yifan Wang, K Jimmy Hsia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pinning Disfavors Nucleation in Colloidal Vapor Deposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vapor deposition, known for precise structural control, is inevitably influenced by impurities. These impurities, often distinct from the depositing material, can significantly impact material properties, including local structure. Interestingly, the effect of immobilizing some of the depositing particles themselves, which would still preserve local structural symmetry, remains largely unexplored. By introducing a small fraction of pinned sites during colloidal vapor deposition and employing a combination of thermodynamic and kinematic measurements, we demonstrate that pinned sites, termed "mobility impurities", are disfavored as nucleation centers. Moreover, tuning the mobility of mobile colloids can adjust the likelihood of nucleation. In later stages of growth, pinning induces mode localization, altering the thin film's vibrational spectrum. Our research underscores the potential of strategically incorporating mobility impurities to engineer material properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19425v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noman Hanif Barbhuiya, Pritam K. Mohanty, Saikat Mondal, Aminul Hussian, Adhip Agarwala, Chandan K. Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine-tuning the Microstructure and Photophysical Characteristics of Fluorescent Conjugated Copolymers Using Photoalignment and Liquid-crystalline Ordering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Replicating the microstructure and near-unity excitation energy transfer efficiency in natural light-harvesting complexes (LHCs) remains a major challenge for synthetic energy-harvesting devices. Biological photosynthesis can spontaneously regulate the active ensembles of involved energy absorbing and funnelling chlorophyll-containing proteins in response to fluctuating sunlight. Here we utilize liquid crystalline (LC) ordering to fine-tune the polymer packing and photophysical properties in liquid crystalline conjugated polymer (LCCP) films for LHC biomimicry and optimizing photoluminescence quantum efficiency (PLQE). We show that the long-range orientational ordering present in a LC phase of poly(9,9-dioctylfluorene-co-benzothiadiazole) (F8BT) stabilizes a small fraction of randomly-oriented F8BT nanocrystals dispersed in an amorphous matrix of disordered F8BT chains, hence resembling a self-doped host-guest system whereby excitation energy funnelling and PLQE are reinforced significantly by three-dimensional donor-to-acceptor Forster resonance energy transfer (FRET) and dominant intrachain emission in the nano-crystalline acceptor. Furthermore, the photoalignment of nematic F8BT layers is combined to fabricate long-sought large-area-extended monodomains which exhibit &gt;60% crystallinity and ~20 nm-long interchain packing order, whilst also promoting linearly polarized emission, a new band-edge absorption species, and an extra emissive interchain excited state. Our micro-PL spectral results support the feasibility of making use of self-doped F8BT nematic films for bio-mimicry of certain structural basis and light-harvesting properties of naturally occurring LHCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19435v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuping Shi, Katharina Landfester, Stephen M. Morris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirality and odd mechanics in active columnar phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral active materials display odd dynamical effects in both their elastic and viscous responses. We show that the most symmetric mesophase with two-dimensional odd elasticity in three dimensions is chiral, polar and columnar, with two-dimensional translational order in the plane perpendicular to the columns and no elastic restoring force for their relative sliding. We derive its hydrodynamic equations from those of a chiral active variant of model H. The most striking prediction of the odd dynamics is two distinct types of column oscillation whose frequencies do not vanish at zero wavenumber. In addition, activity leads to a buckling instability coming from the generic force-dipole active stress analogous to the mechanical Helfrich-Hurault instability in passive materials, while the chiral torque-dipole active stress fundamentally modifies the instability by the selection of helical column undulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19514v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. J. Kole, Gareth P. Alexander, Ananyo Maitra, Sriram Ramaswamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>curvedSpaceSim: A framework for simulating particles interacting along geodesics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19751v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A large number of powerful, high-quality, and open-source simulation packages exist to efficiently perform molecular dynamics simulations, and their prevalence has greatly accelerated discoveries across a wide range of scientific domains. These packages typically simulate particles in free (Euclidean) space, with options to specify a variety of boundary conditions. While more exotic, many physical systems are constrained to and interact across curved surfaces, such as organisms moving across the landscape, colloids pinned at curved fluid-fluid interfaces, and layers of epithelial cells forming highly curved tissues. The calculation of distances and the updating of equations of motion in idealized geometries (namely, on surfaces of constant curvature) can be done analytically, but it is much more challenging to efficiently perform molecular-dynamics-like simulations on arbitrarily curved surfaces. This article discusses a simulation framework which combines tools from particle-based simulations with recent work in discrete differential geometry to model particles that interact via geodesic distances and move on an arbitrarily curved surface. We present computational cost estimates for a variety of surface complexities with and without various algorithmic specializations (e.g., restrictions to short-range interaction potentials, or multi-threaded parallelization). Our flexible and extensible framework is set up to easily handle both equilibrium and non-equilibrium dynamics, and will enable researchers to access time- and particle-number-scales previously inaccessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19751v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toler H. Webb, Daniel M. Sussman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric transport properties of the quasi-one-dimensional dimer-Mott insulator $\beta'$-(BEDT-TTF)$_2$ICl$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19137v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Low-dimensional materials, in which the electronic and transport properties are drastically modified in comparison to those of three-dimensional bulk materials, yield a key class of thermoelectric materials with high conversion efficiency. Among such materials, the organic compounds may serve peculiar properties owing to their unique molecular-based low-dimensional structures with highly anisotropic molecular orbitals. Here we present the thermoelectric transport properties of the quasi-one-dimensional dimer-Mott insulator $\beta'$-(BEDT-TTF)$_2$ICl$_2$, where BEDT-TTF stands for bis(ethylenedithio)-tetrathiafulvalene. We find that the thermopower exhibits typical activation-type temperature variation expected for insulators but its absolute value is anomalously large compared to the expected value from the activation-type temperature dependence of the electrical resistivity. Successively, the Jonker-plot analysis, in which the thermopower is usually scaled by the logarithm of the resistivity, shows an unusual relation among such transport quantities. We discuss a role of the low dimensionality for the enhanced thermopower along with recent observations of such a large thermopower in several low-dimensional materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19137v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyohei Eguchi, Takeru Ito, Yoshiki J. Sato, Ryuji Okazaki, Hiromi Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of particle aggregation in dewetting films of complex liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19701v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the dynamic wetting and dewetting processes of films and droplets of complex liquids on planar surfaces, focusing on the case of colloidal suspensions, where the particle interactions can be sufficiently attractive to cause agglomeration of the colloids within the film. This leads to an interesting array of dynamic behaviours within the liquid and of the liquid-air interface. Incorporating concepts from thermodynamics and using the thin-film approximation, we construct a model consisting of a pair of coupled partial differential equations that represent the evolution of the liquid film and the effective colloidal height profiles. We determine the relevant phase behaviour of the uniform system, including finding associated binodal and spinodal curves, helping to uncover how the emerging behaviour depends on the particle interactions. Performing a linear stability analysis of our system enables us to identify parameter regimes where agglomerates form, which we independently confirm through numerical simulations and continuation of steady states, to construct bifurcation diagrams. We obtain various dynamics such as uniform colloidal profiles in an unstable situation evolving into agglomerates and thus elucidate the interplay between dewetting and particle aggregation in complex liquids on surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19701v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Zhang, D. N. Sibley, D. Tseluiko, A. J. Archer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Monovalent and Divalent Cations on the Rheology of Entangled DNA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.10886v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate the effects of varying cation valency and concentration on the rheology of entangled lambda DNA solutions. We show that monovalent cations moderately increase the viscoelasticty of the solutions mainly by stabilising linear condensation of lambda DNA ``monomers'' via hybridisation of their sticky ends. On the contrary, divalent cations have a far more complex and dramatic effect on the rheology of the solution and we observe evidence of inter-molecular DNA-DNA bridging by Mg2+. We argue that these results may be interesting in the context of dense solutions of single and double stranded DNA, e.g. in vivo or in biotechnology applications such as DNA origami and DNA hydrogels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.10886v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D3SM00957B</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 Soft Matter</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Harnett, Simon Weir, Davide Michieletto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of shear flow on the transverse thermal conductivity of polymer melts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07027v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The effect of shear flows on the thermal conductivity of polymer melts is investigated using a reversed nonequilibrium molecular dynamics (RNEMD) method. We extended the original RNEMD method to simultaneously produce spatial gradients of temperature and flow velocity in a single direction. This method enables accurate measurement of the thermal conductivity in the direction transverse to shear flow.
  The Weissenberg number defined with the shear rate and the relaxation time of the polymer conformation can uniformly differentiate the occurrence of shear rate dependence of the thermal conductivity across different chain lengths. The stress-thermal rule (STR) (i.e., the linear relationship between anisotropic parts of the stress tensor and the thermal conductivity tensor) holds for entangled polymer melts even under shear flows but not for unentangled polymer melts. Furthermore, once entanglements form in polymer chains, the stress-thermal coefficient in the STR remains independent of the polymer chain length.
  These observations align with the theoretical foundation of the STR, which focuses on energy transmission along the network structure of entangled polymer chains [Brule, Rheol. Acta 28, 257 (1989)]. However, under driven shear flows, the stress-thermal coefficient is notably smaller than that measured in the literature for a quasi-quiescent state without external forces. Although the mechanism of the STR in shear flows has yet to be fully elucidated, our study confirmed the validity of the STR in shear flows. This allows us to use the STR as a constitutive equation for computational thermo-fluid dynamics of polymer melts, thus having broad engineering applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07027v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kotaro Oda, Shugo Yasuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative particle dynamics for coarse-grained models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04932v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a computational method based on Dissipative Particle Dynamics (DPD) that introduces solvent hydrodynamic interactions to coarse-grained models of solutes, such as ions, molecules, or polymers. DPD-solvent (DPDS) is a fully off-lattice method that allows straightforward incorporation of hydrodynamics at desired solvent viscosity, compressibility and solute diffusivity with any particle-based solute model. Solutes interact with the solvent only through the DPD thermostat, which ensures that the equilibrium properties of the solute system are not affected by the introduction of the DPD solvent. Thus, DPDS can be used as a replacement for traditional molecular dynamics thermostats such as Nos\'e-Hoover and Langevin. We demonstrate the applicability of DPDS on the case of polymer dynamics and electroosmotic flow through a nanopore. The method should be broadly useful as means to introduce hydrodynamics to existing coarse-grained models of molecules and soft materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04932v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 160 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tine Curk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable transport in bi-disperse porous materials with vascular structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14628v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study transport in synthetic, bi-disperse porous structures, with arrays of microchannels interconnected by a nanoporous layer. These structures are inspired by the xylem tissue in vascular plants, in which sap water travels from the roots to the leaves to maintain hydration and carry micronutrients. We experimentally evaluate transport in three conditions: high pressure-driven flow, spontaneous imbibition, and transpiration-driven flow. The latter case resembles the situation in a living plant, where bulk liquid water is transported upwards in a metastable state (negative pressure), driven by evaporation in the leaves; here we report stable, transpiration-driven flows down to $\sim -15$ MPa of driving force. By varying the shape of the microchannels, we show that we can tune the rate of these transport processes in a predictable manner, using a simple analytical (effective medium) approach and numerical simulations of the flow field in the bi-disperse media. We also show that the spontaneous imbibition behavior of a single structure - with fixed geometry - can behave very differently depending on its preparation (filled with air, vs. evacuated), because of a dramatic change in the conductance of vapor in the microchannels; this change offers a second way to tune the rate of transport in bi-disperse, xylem-like structures, by switching between air-filled and evacuated states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14628v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivier Vincent, Th\'eo Tassin, Erik J. Huber, Abraham D. Stroock</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An electronic structure investigation of PEDOT with AlCl4- anions, a promising redox combination for energy storage applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.11720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.11720v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The conducting polymer poly(3,4-ethylenedioxythiophene) (PEDOT) is one of the most researched materials. The 1980s bipolaron model remains the dominant interpretation of the electronic structure of PEDOT. Recent theoretical studies have provided updated definitions of key concepts such as bipolarons or polaron pairs, but these have not yet become widely known. In this work, we use density functional theory to investigate the electronic structure of PEDOT oligomers with co-located AlCl4- anions, a promising combination for energy storage. By considering the influence of oligomer length, oxidation or anion concentration and spin state, we find no evidence for self-localisation of positive charges in PEDOT as predicted by the bipolaron model at the hybrid functional level. Our results show distortions that exhibit either a single or a double peak in bond length alternations and charge density. Either can occur at different oxidation or anion concentrations. We note that other distortion shapes are also possible. Rather than representing bipolarons or polaron pairs in the original model, these are electron distributions driven by a range of factors. Localisation of distortions occurs with anions, and distortions can span an arbitrary number of nearby anions. Conductivity in conducting polymers has been observed to reduce at anion concentrations above 0.5. We show at high anion concentrations, the energy of the localised, non-bonding anionic orbitals approaches that of the system HOMO due to Coulombic repulsion between anions. We hypothesize that with nucleic motion in the macropolymer, these orbitals will interfere with the hopping of charge carriers between sites of similar energy, lowering conductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.11720v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Craig, Peter Townsend, Carlos Ponce de Leon, Chris Kriton-Skylaris, Denis Kramer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
