<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 05:01:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Economical and versatile subunit design principles for self-assembled DNA origami structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Self-assembly of nanoscale synthetic subunits is a promising bottom-up strategy for fabrication of functional materials. Here, we introduce a design principle for DNA origami nanoparticles of 50-nm size, exploiting modularity, to make a family of versatile subunits that can target an abundant variety of self-assembled structures. The subunits are based on a core module that remains constant among all the subunits. Variable bond modules and angle modules are added to the exterior of the core to control interaction specificity, strength and structural geometry. A series of subunits with designed bond/angle modules are demonstrated to self-assemble into a rich variety of structures with different Gaussian curvatures, exemplified by sheets, spherical shells, and tubes. The design features flexible joints implemented using single-stranded angle modules between adjacent subunits whose mechanical properties, such as bending elastic moduli, are inferred from cryo-EM. Our findings suggest that incorporating a judicious amount of flexibility in the bond provides error tolerances in design and fabrication while still guaranteeing target fidelity. Lastly, while increasing flexibility could introduce greater variability and potential errors in assembly, these effects can be counterbalanced by increasing the number of distinct bonds, thereby allowing for precise targeting of specific structural binding angles within a broad range of configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09801v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Shao Wei, Thomas E. Videb{\ae}k, Daichi Hayakawa, Rupam Saha, W. Benjamin Rogers, Seth Fraden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive creep compliance characterization of orthotropic materials using a cost-effective automated system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Determining the creep compliances of orthotropic composite materials requires experiments in at least three different uniaxial and biaxial loading directions. Up to date, data respecting multiple climates and all anatomical directions are sparse for hygro-responsive materials like Norway spruce. Consequently, simulation models of wood frequently over-simplify creep, e.g., by proportionally scaling missing components or neglecting climatic influences. To overcome such simplifications, an automated computer-controlled climatized creep rack was developed, that experimentally assesses moisture-dependent viscoelasticity and mechanosorption in all anatomical directions. The device simultaneously measures the creep strains of three dogbone tension samples, three flat compression samples, and six Arcan shear samples via Digital Image Correlation. This allows for ascertaining the complete orthotropic compliance tensors while accounting for loading direction asymmetries. This paper explains the creep rack's structure and demonstrates its use by determining all nine independent creep compliance components of Norway spruce at 65% relative humidity. The data shows that loading asymmetry effects amount up to 16%. Furthermore, the found creep compliance tensor is not proportional to the elastic compliance tensor. By clustering the compliance components, we identify four necessary components to represent the full orthotropy of the compliance tensor, obtainable from not less than two experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10044v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas M. Maas, Falk K. Wittel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale stress dynamics in sheared liquid foams revealed by tomo-rheoscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rheology aims at quantifying the response of materials to mechanical forcing. However, standard rheometers provide only global macroscopic quantities, such as viscoelastic moduli. They fail to capture the heterogeneous flow of soft amorphous materials at the mesoscopic scale, arising from the rearrangements of the microstructural elements, that must be accounted for to build predictive models. To address this experimental challenge, we have combined shear rheometry and time-resolved X-ray micro-tomography on 3D liquid foams used as model glassy materials, yielding a unique access to the stresses and contact network topology at the bubble scale. We reveal a universal scaling behavior of the local stress build-up and relaxation associated with topological modifications. Moreover, these plastic events redistribute stress non-locally, as if the foam were an elastic medium subjected to a quadrupolar deformation. Our findings clarify how the macroscopic elastoplastic behavior of amorphous materials emerges from the spatiotemporal stress variations induced by microstructural rearrangements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10338v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Schott, Benjamin Dollet, St\'ephane Santucci, Christian Matthias Schlep\"utz, Cyrille Claudet, Stefan Gst\"ohl, Christophe Raufaste, Rajmund Mokso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric dependence of curvature-induced rigidity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bending the edge of a thin elastic material promotes rigidity far from its clamped boundary. However, this curvature-induced rigidity can be overwhelmed by gravity or other external loading, resulting in elastic buckling and large deformations. We consider the role of body geometry on this competition using experiments, numerical simulations, and reduced-order models. Finite element simulations are performed using a model nonlinear hyperelastic material, and a theoretical framework is proposed that incorporates small lateral curvatures, large longitudinal rotations, and a varying cross-sectional width. A particular focus is on the comparison between rectangular and triangular sheets, and trapezoidal sheets in between. Sheet geometry affects downward tip deflection by changing the relative importance of the sheet's weight and the rigidity provided by curvature, often in subtle ways. In extreme cases, non-monotonic deflection is observed with increasing sheet length, and a region of hysteretic bistability emerges, becoming more pronounced with rectangular sheets and large imposed curvatures. These findings demonstrate the profound impact of geometry on the competition between curvature-induced rigidity and gravity-induced deformation in thin elastic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10382v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanzhang Mao, Thomas G. J. Chandler, Mark Han, Saverio E. Spagnolie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploitation-exploration transition in the physics of fluid-driven branching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Self-organized branching structures can emerge spontaneously as interfacial instabilities in both simple and complex fluids, driven by the interplay between bulk material rheology, boundary constraints, and interfacial forcing. In our experiments, injecting dye between a source and a sink in a Hele-Shaw cell filled with a yield-stress fluid reveals an abrupt transition in morphologies as a function of injection rate. Slow injection leads to a direct path connecting the source to the sink, while fast injection leads to a rapid branching morphology that eventually converges to the sink. This shift from an exploitative (direct) to an exploratory (branched) strategy resembles search strategies in living systems; however, here it emerges in a simple physical system from a combination of global constraints (fluid conservation) and a switch-like local material response. We show that the amount of fluid needed to achieve breakthrough is minimal at the transition, and that there is a trade-off between speed and accuracy in these arborization patterns. Altogether, our study provides an embodied paradigm for fluidic computation driven by a combination of local material response (body) and global boundary conditions (environment).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10426v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Tauber, J. Asnacios, L. Mahadevan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Ionic Strength on the Morphology, Scattering, and Mechanical Response of Neurofilament-Derived Protein Brushes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.02463v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Protein brushes not only play a key role in the functionality of neurofilaments but also have wide applications in biomedical materials. Here, we investigate the effect of ionic strength on the morphology of protein brushes using a continuous-space self-consistent field theory. A coarse-grained multi-block charged macromolecular model is developed to capture the chemical identity of amino acid sequences. For neurofilament heavy (NFH) brushes at pH 2.4, we predict three morphological regimes: swollen brushes, condensed brushes, and coexisting brushes which consist of both a dense inner layer and a diffuse outer layer. The brush height predicted by our theory is in good agreement with experimental data for a wide range of ionic strengths. The dramatic height decrease is a result of the electrostatic screening-induced transition from the overlapping state to the isolated state of the coexisting brushes. We also study the evolution of the scattering and mechanical responses accompanying the morphological change. The oscillation in the reflectivity spectra characterizes the existence and microstructure of the inner condensed layer, whereas the shoulder in the force spectra signifies the swollen morphology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.02463v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.biomac.3c01002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Biomacromolecules 2024, 25, 328-337</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takashi J. Yokokura, Chao Duan, Erika A. Ding, Sanjay Kumar, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanics and thermodynamics of contractile entropic biopolymer networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07287v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Contractile biopolymer networks, such as the actomyosin meshwork of animal cells, are ubiquitous in living organisms. The active gel theory, which provides the thermodynamic framework for these materials, has been mostly used in conjunction with the assumption that the microstructure of the biopolymer network is based on rigid rods. However, experimentally, crosslinked actin network exhibits entropic elasticity. Here we combine an entropic elasticity kinetic theory, in the spirit of the Green and Tobolsky model of transiently crosslinked networks, with an active flux modelling biological activity. We determine this active flux using Onsager reciprocal relations and interpret the corresponding microscopic dynamics. We obtain a closed-form model of the macroscopic mechanical behaviour. We show how this model can be written using the framework of multiplicative strain gradient decomposition, which is convenient for the resolution of such problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07287v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Jallon, Pierre Recho, Jocelyn \'Etienne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microphase Segregation in Polyelectrolyte Brushes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00199v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polyelectrolyte (PE) brushes have ubiquitous applications as surface modifiers which regulate various structural and dynamic properties. Here, we apply a continuous-space self-consistent field theory to study the structural heterogeneity in PE brushes induced by competing electrostatic and hydrophobic interactions. For brushes with high grafting densities, we find a series of microphase-segregated morphologies with alternating polymer-rich and polymer-poor layers in the direction normal to the substrate. The transitions between multi-layer morphologies with consecutive numbers of condensed layers as well as the melting transition to the fully swollen brush are all discontinuous. We also elucidate that the segregated layers are formed by different subpopulations of all chains, significantly different from the scenario of the pearl-necklace structure formed by a single PE in poor solvents. Furthermore, we bridge the microstructure of multi-layer brushes to experimentally measurable reflectivity spectra, where the oscillation period and amplitude in the spectra are shown to be very sensitive to the number of layers and the sharpness of the polymer-solvent interface. The multi-layer morphology predicted by our theory is in good agreement with the lamellae structure experimentally observed at hydrated Nafion film interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00199v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Yokokura, Chao Duan, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous Optimized Mechanical Stiffness and Cell Growth on Scaffold by Morphology Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23295v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The morphology of microstructures in scaffolds is a critical factor influencing both mechanical properties and biological performance, such as cell growth, in bone tissue engineering. While metamaterials with optimized mechanical properties, such as hyperelasticity, thermal efficiency, or energy absorption, have been designed through complex microstructural geometry with the help of numerical simulation of multi-physics, optimizing biological performance alongside these physical traits remains a significant challenge. This is primarily because biological performance must be evaluated through laboratory experiments. To address this issue, we propose a novel approach that simultaneously optimizes mechanical stiffness and cell growth effectiveness through a data-driven morphology learning method. Our approach effectively extracts and learns shape patterns from a specifically selected dataset of microstructures recognized for their superior cell growth performance. We then integrate these patterns into a computational framework based on topology optimization, enabling the generation of new microstructures that maintain high levels of cell growth while enhancing mechanical stiffness. Using this morphology learning-based method, we identified a scaffold design for bone tissue engineering that demonstrates a significant improvement in both mechanical stiffness (by 29.69%) and cell proliferation (by 37.05% on Day 7 and 33.30% on Day 14). From a broader perspective, this work introduces a general approach to integrating factors that cannot be directly evaluated through numerical simulations into structural optimization. This approach opens up many new possibilities for designing structures that balance diverse and complex requirements, making it applicable to a broader range of fields from biomedical engineering to product design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23295v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiming Wang, Yanhao Hou, Renbo Su, Weiguang Wang, Charlie C. L. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable molecular simulation of electrolyte solutions with quantum chemical accuracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.12535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.12535v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Electrolyte solutions play critical role in a vast range of important applications, yet an accurate and scalable method of predicting their properties without fitting to experiment has remained out of reach, despite over a century of effort. Here, we combine state-of-the-art density functional theory and equivariant neural network potentials to demonstrate this capability, reproducing key structural, thermodynamic, and kinetic properties. We show that neural network potentials (NNPs) can be recursively trained on a subset of their own output to enable coarse-grained/continuum-solvent molecular simulations that can access much longer timescales than possible with all atom simulations. We observe the surprising formation of Li cation dimers along with identical anion-anion pairing of chloride and bromide anions. Finally, we reproduce simulate the crystal phase and infinite dilution pairing free energies despite being trained only on moderate concentration solutions. This approach should be scaled to build a greatly expanded database of electrolyte solution properties than currently exists.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.12535v4</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junji Zhang, Joshua Pagotto, Tim Gould, Timothy T. Duignan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mesoscale Field Theory for Quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17091v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a mesoscale field theory unifying the modeling of growth, elasticity, and dislocations in quasicrystals. The theory is based on the amplitudes entering their density-wave representation. We introduce a free energy functional for complex amplitudes and assume non-conserved dissipative dynamics to describe their evolution. Elasticity, including phononic and phasonic deformations, along with defect nucleation and motion, emerges self-consistently by prescribing only the symmetry of quasicrystals. Predictions on the formation of semi-coherent interfaces and dislocation kinematics are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17091v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcello De Donno, Luiza Angheluta, Ken R. Elder, Marco Salvalaglio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
