<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 01:40:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Flexoelectricity versus Electrostatics in Polar Nematic Liquid Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polar nematic liquid crystals have two special features, compared with conventional nematic liquid crystals. First, because of flexoelectricity, the combination of polar order and splay reduces the free energy. Second, because of electrostatics, any splay generates a bound charge density, which increases the free energy. To assess the competition between these two effects, we develop a theory that combines flexoelectricity and electrostatics. The theory predicts a phase diagram that includes ferroelectric, antiferroelectric, and conventional nematic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10347v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lincoln Paik, Jonathan V. Selinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermomechanical Approach to Calculating Mechanical Stresses in Inhomogeneous Ionic Fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This extended article presents a thermomechanical approach for calculating the stress tensor from the thermodynamic potential of ionic fluids. Our technique, which is based on the invariance of the thermodynamic potential with respect to spatial transformations of shear and rotation, offers an alternative to the general covariant approach recently developed by two of us. We apply this technique in both pure mean field theories of ionic fluids and in a theory that includes thermal fluctuations of the electrostatic potential, using variational field theory. We also apply the thermomechanical approach to fluid models described by vector order parameters, such as liquid dielectrics, and obtained for this case a general expression for the stress tensor. Additionally, we discuss specific issues related to the calculation of disjoining pressure in ionic fluids confined in nanoscale slit-like pores with conductive or dielectric walls.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10597v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. A. Budkov, N. N. Kalikin, P. E. Brandyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An active filament on a cylindrical surface: morphologies and dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10677v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Structure and dynamics of an active polymer on a smooth cylindrical surface are studied by Brownian dynamics simulations. The effect of active force on the polymer adsorption behavior and the combined effect of chain mobility, length N, rigidity \k{appa}, and cylinder radius, R, on phase diagrams are systemically investigated. We find that complete adsorption is replaced by irregular alternative adsorption/desorption process at a large driving force. Three typical (spiral, helix-like, rod-like) conformations of the active polymer are observed, dependent on N, \k{appa}, and R. Dynamically, the polymer shows rotational motion in spiral state, snake-like motion in the intermediate state, and straight translational motion without turning back in the rod-like state. In the spiral state, we find that rotation velocity {\omega} and chain length follows a power-law relation {\omega}~N^(-0.42), consistent with the torque-balance theory of general Archimedean spirals. And the polymer shows super-diffusive behavior along the cylinder at long time in the helix-like and rod-like states. Our results highlight the mobility, rigidity, as well as curvature of surface can be used to regulate the polymer behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10677v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Shen, Chao-ran Qin, Tian-liang Xu, Kang Chen, Wen-de Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse Regression for Discovery of Constitutive Models from Oscillatory Shear Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose sparse regression as an alternative to neural networks for the discovery of parsimonious constitutive models (CMs) from oscillatory shear experiments. Symmetry and frame-invariance are strictly imposed by using tensor basis functions to isolate and describe unknown nonlinear terms in the CMs. We generate synthetic experimental data using the Giesekus and Phan-Thien Tanner CMs, and consider two different scenarios. In the complete information scenario, we assume that the shear stress, along with the first and second normal stress differences, is measured. This leads to a sparse linear regression problem that can be solved efficiently using $l_1$ regularization. In the partial information scenario, we assume that only shear stress data is available. This leads to a more challenging sparse nonlinear regression problem, for which we propose a greedy two-stage algorithm. In both scenarios, the proposed methods fit and interpolate the training data remarkably well. Predictions of the inferred CMs extrapolate satisfactorily beyond the range of training data for oscillatory shear. They also extrapolate reasonably well to flow conditions like startup of steady and uniaxial extension that are not used in the identification of CMs. We discuss ramifications for experimental design, potential algorithmic improvements, and implications of the non-uniqueness of CMs inferred from partial information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10762v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sachin Shanbhag, Gordon Erlebacher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Analysis of the Structure, Thermodynamics, and Shear Elasticity of Deeply Metastable Hard Sphere Fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The structure, thermodynamics and slow activated dynamics of the equilibrated metastable regime of glass-forming fluids remains a poorly understood problem of high theoretical and experimental interest. We apply a highly accurate microscopic equilibrium liquid state integral equation theory that has not been previously explored in the deeply metastable regime, in conjunction with na\"ive mode coupling theory of particle localization, to study in a unified manner the structural correlations, thermodynamic properties, and dynamic elastic shear modulus in deeply metastable hard sphere fluids. New and distinctive behaviors are predicted including divergent inverse critical power laws for the contact value of the pair correlation function, pressure, and inverse dimensionless compressibility, and a splitting of the second peak and large suppression of interstitial configurations of the pair correlation function. The dynamic elastic modulus is predicted to exhibit two distinct exponential growth regimes with packing fraction that have strongly different slopes. These new thermodynamic, structural, and elastic modulus results are consistent with simulations and experiments. Perhaps most unexpectedly, connections between the amplitude of long wavelength density fluctuations, dimensionless compressibility, local structure, and the dynamic elastic shear modulus are discovered. These connections are more broadly relevant to understand the slow activated relaxation and mechanical response of colloidal suspensions in the ultra-dense metastable region and deeply supercooled thermal liquids in equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10922v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhashish Chaki, Baicheng Mei, Kenneth S. Schweizer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hysteretic response to different modes of ramping an external field in sparse and dense Ising spin glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10329v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the hysteretic behavior of Ising spin glasses at $T=0$ for various modes of driving. Previous studies mostly focused on an infinitely slow speed $\dot{H}$ by which the external field $H$ was ramped to trigger avalanches of spin flips by starting with destabilizing a single spin while few have focused on the effect of different driving methods. First, we show that this conventional protocol imposes a system size dependence. Then, we numerically analyze the response of Ising spin glasses at rates $\dot{H}$ that are fixed as well, to elucidate the differences in the response. Specifically, we compare three different modes of ramping ($\dot{H}=c/N$, $\dot{H}=c/\sqrt{N}$, and $\dot{H}=c$ for constant $c$) for two types of spin glass systems of size $N$, representing dense networks by the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model and sparse networks by the lattice spin glass in $d=3$ dimensions known as the Edwards Anderson model. Depending on the mode of ramping, we find that the response of each system, in form of spin-flip avalanches and other observables, can vary considerably. In particular, in the $N$-independent mode applied to the lattice spin glass, which is closest to experimental reality, we observe a percolation transition with a broad avalanche distribution between phases of localized and system-spanning responses. We explore implications for combinatorial optimization problems pertaining to sparse systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10329v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahajabin Rahman (Emory U), Stefan Boettcher (Emory U)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring pNIPAM Lyogels: Experimental Study on Swelling Equilibria in Various Organic Solvents and Mixtures, Supported by COSMO-RS Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07592v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Stimuli-responsive lyogels are considered to be smart materials due to their capability of undergoing significant macroscopic changes in response to external triggers. Due to their versatile and unique properties, smart lyogels exhibit great potential in various applications such as drug delivery or actuation processes. While Poly-N-isopropylacrylamide (pNIPAM) is widely known as a thermo-responsive material, it also shows significant solvent-responsive swelling behavior. As polar solvents induce strong swelling due to hydrogen bonding with the amide group, nonpolar solvents lead to significant shrinkage of the lyogels. The aim of this study is to investigate and to model this behavior for future application in chemical or biochemical reactors. As a current area of research, incorporating smart hydrogel technology into (bio-)chemical reactors facilitates the development of smart reactor systems. Applying thermodynamic modelling with the gE model COSMO-RS on the monomer or oligomers of pNIPAM, the correlation between solvent-polymer interactions and the degree of swelling can be observed. pNIPAM derivatives exhibit low infinitive dilution activity coefficients (IDACs) in polar solvents with large degrees of swelling, while displaying an increase of IDACs in nonpolar solvents. Hydrogen bonds dominate the swelling behavior of lyogels not only in pure solvents but also in mixtures of solvents with varying polarity. Even in mixtures containing high amounts of nonpolar solvents, large degrees of swelling were observed due to the uptake of the polar solvent in the lyogel matrix. This effect can be observed in binary solvent mixtures but also in representative mixtures along an esterification reaction with varying carboxylic chain length of alcohol and carboxylic acids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07592v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.fluid.2024.114182</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Fluid Phase Equilibria 586 (November 1, 2024): 114182</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kathrin Marina Eckert, Simon M\"uller, Gerrit A. Luinstra, Irina Smirnova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closely piling up of multiple adhesive fronts in adhesive friction due to re-attachment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05283v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Friction impacts a wide range of fields, spanning engineering, geology, biomechanics, and numerous others. As a fundamental force, it influences various aspects of our daily lives and industrial processes across multiple disciplines. To understand how adhesive friction seemingly breaks the size limit dictated by the fracture theory, here we investigate the sliding of elastic solids adhered to a rigid surface via multiple adhesive springs. With the consideration of random re-attachment of detached adhesive springs, we find that the shear-off force of the interface can significantly exceed predictions made by the fracture theory, with substantial adhesive forces distributed across the entire interface. Through this observation, we identify multiple adhesive fronts closely aligning along the interface, exhibiting similar force profiles. Moreover, the number of these regions seems to generally increase with the interface size, resulting in a linear rise in the calculated shear-off force with interface size. Therefore, we conclude that the close accumulation of multiple adhesive fronts along an interface aids each other through random healing so as to erase the size effect of the fracture theory, which offers valuable insights into understanding the phenomena associated with adhesive friction along an interface in various fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05283v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Puyu Cao, Meicheng Yao, Bin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous rheology of puller-type microswimmer suspensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15785v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the mechanism behind the anomalous rheology of puller-type microswimmer suspensions through direct hydrodynamic simulations. Our simulations demonstrate that swimmers' orientations near boundary walls predominantly control the overall swimming states and the resultant rheological properties. Hydrodynamic interactions due to specific flow fields characteristic of pullers cause the swimmers to line up vertically, particularly close to the walls where swimmer density peaks, enhancing the polar order of collective motion. Furthermore, the swimming directions near the walls depend significantly on the aspect ratio of the swimmer's body: rod-like swimmers tend to swim toward the flow direction, while swimmers with spherical bodies swim against the flow direction. The present results contrast with our previous simulations of suspensions of pusher-type swimmers, where weak orientation order in bulk regions determines the steady-state properties. Furthermore, these findings highlight that the rheological properties of active suspensions vary widely depending on the swimmers' properties, such as their shapes and swimming mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15785v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruki Hayano, Akira Furukawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Escape of an Active Ring from an Attractive Surface: Behaving Like a Self-Propelled Brownian Particle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20613v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Escape of active agents from metastable states is of great interest in statistical and biological physics. In this study, we investigate the escape of a flexible active ring, composed of active Brownian particles, from a flat attractive surface using Brownian dynamics simulations. To systematically explore the effects of activity, persistence time, and the shape of attractive potentials, we calculate escape time and effective temperature. We observe two distinct escape mechanisms: Kramers-like thermal activation at small persistence times and the maximal force problem at large persistence time, where escape time is determined by persistence time. The escape time explicitly depends on the shape of the potential barrier at high activity and large persistence time. Moreover, when the propulsion force is biased along the ring's contour, escape becomes more difficult and is primarily driven by thermal noise. Our findings highlight that, despite its intricate configuration, the active ring can be effectively modeled as a self-propelled Brownian particle when studying its escape from a smooth surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20613v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Tang, Jin-cheng Gao, Kang Chen, Tian Hui Zhang, Wen-de Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking of a floating particle raft by water waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16188v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When particles of a few tens of microns are spread on the surface of water, they aggregate under the action of capillary forces and form a thin floating membrane, a particle raft. In a tank with a raft made of graphite powder, we generate in the laboratory gravity surface waves, whose wavelength {about 17 cm} is very large compared to the thickness of the raft {of order 10 microns}. For a sufficiently strong wave amplitude, the raft breaks up progressively by developing cracks and producing fragments whose sizes decrease on a time scale long compared to the period of the wave. We characterize the breaking mechanisms. Then, we investigate the area distribution of the fragments produced during the fragmentation process. The visual appearance of the fragments distributed in size and surrounded by open water bears a {notable} resemblance to the floes produced by the fracturing of sea ice by waves in the polar oceans. Fragmentation concepts and morphological tools built for sea ice floes can be applied to our macroscopic analog, on which the entire dynamic evolution is accessible. {However, the mechanic of the two systems differ, as our particle raft breaks due to the viscous stresses, whereas the sea-ice fractures due its bending by the waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16188v5</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Saddier, Ambre Palotai, Matheo Aksil, Michel Tsamados, Michael Berhanu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
