<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 01:58:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Microstructure of polydisperse colloidal gels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use confocal microscopy to image colloidal gels formed from highly polydisperse particles. We suspend our polydisperse particles in a density matched solvent, and let the particles spontaneously aggregate through the van der Waals force. The particle size distribution $P(R)$ is roughly log-normal, with the largest particles more than 15 times the size of the smallest particles. The pairing of nearest neighbor particles is consistent with a null hypothesis that pairings are made randomly, that is, any two particle sizes have a probability of being neighbors consistent with their proportionality in $P(R)$. That being said, as expected, larger particles have more nearest neighbors than small ones. This leads to an over-representation of large particles in tetrahedral structures where four particles are mutually nearest neighbors, showing that large particles help provide rigidity to the gel structure. We discuss the implications of how other size distributions $P(R)$ would affect the gel structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10321v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin F. Lonial, Eric R. Weeks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Close Packing of Semi-Flexible Polymers in Two Dimensions: Emergence of Local and Global Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10376v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Through extensive Monte Carlo simulations, we systematically study the effect of chain stiffness on the packing ability of linear polymers composed of hard spheres in extremely confined monolayers, corresponding effectively to 2D films. First, we explore the limit of random close packing as a function of the equilibrium bending angle and then quantify the local and global order by the degree of crystallinity and the nematic or tetratic orientational order parameter, respectively. A multi-scale wealth of structural behavior is observed, which is inherently absent in the case of athermal individual monomers and is surprisingly richer than its 3D counterpart under bulk conditions. As a general trend an isotropic to nematic transition is observed at sufficiently high surfaces coverages which is followed by the establishment of the tetratic state, which in turn marks the onset of the random close packing. For chains with right-angle bonds, the incompatibility of the imposed bending angle with the neighbor geometry of the triangular crystal leads to a singular intra- and inter-polymer tiling pattern made of squares and triangles with optimal local filling at high surface concentrations. The present study could serve as a first step towards the design of hard colloidal polymers with tunable structural behavior for 2D applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10376v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Martinez-Fernandez, Clara Pedrosa, Miguel Herranz, Katerina Foteinopoulou, Nikos Ch. Karayiannis, Manuel Laso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Segregation Kinetics of Miktoarm Star Polymers: A Dissipative Particle Dynamics Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the phase separation kinetics of miktoarm star polymer (MSP) melts and blends with diverse architectures using dissipative particle dynamics simulations. Our study focuses on symmetric and asymmetric miktoarm star polymer (SMSP/AMSP) mixtures based on arm composition and number. For a fixed MSP chain size, the characteristic microphase-separated domains initially show diffusive growth with a growth exponent $\phi \sim 1/3$ for both melts that gradually crossover to saturation at late times. The simulation results demonstrate that the evolution morphology of SMSP melts exhibits perfect dynamic scaling with varying arm numbers; the time scale follows a power-law decay with an exponent $\theta \simeq 1$ as the number of arms increases. The structural constraints on AMSP melts cause the domain growth rate to decrease as the number of one type of arms increases while their length remains fixed. This increase in the number of arms for AMSP corresponds to increased off-criticality. The saturation length in AMSP follows a power law increase with an exponent $\lambda \simeq 2/3$ as off-criticality decreases. Additionally, macrophase separation kinetics in SMSP/AMSP blends show a transition from viscous ($\phi \sim 1$) to inertial ($\phi \sim 2/3$) hydrodynamic growth regimes at late times; this exhibits the same dynamical universality class as linear polymer blends, with slight deviations at early stages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10495v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dorothy Gogoi, Avinash Chauhan, Sanjay Puri, Awaneesh Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse design of programmable shape-morphing kirigami structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shape-morphing structures have the capability to transform from one state to another, making them highly valuable in engineering applications. In this study, it is propose a two-stage shape-morphing framework inspired by kirigami structures to design structures that can deploy from a compacted state to a prescribed state under certain mechanical stimuli -- although the framework may also be extended to accommodate various physical fields, such as magnetic, thermal, and electric fields. The framework establishes a connection between the geometry and mechanics of kirigami structures. The proposed approach combines the finite element analysis (FEA), genetic algorithm (GA), and an analytical energy-based model to obtain kirigami designs with robustness and efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10566v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyuan Ying, Dilum Fernando, Marcelo A. Dias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemotactic behavior for a self-phoretic Janus particle near a patch source of fuel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many biological microswimmers are capable of chemotaxis, i.e., they can sense an ambient chemical gradient and adjust their mechanism of motility to move towards or away from the source of the gradient. Synthetic active colloids endowed with chemotactic behavior hold considerable promise for targeted drug delivery and the realization of programmable and reconfigurable materials. Here we study the chemotactic behavior of a Janus particle, which converts ``fuel'' molecules, released at an axisymmetric chemical patch located on a planar wall, into ``product'' molecules at its catalytic cap and moves by self-phoresis induced by the product. The chemotactic behavior is characterized as a function of the interplay between the rates of release (at the patch) and the consumption (at the particle) of fuel, as well as of details of the phoretic response of the particle (i.e., its phoretic mobility). Among others, we find that, under certain conditions, the particle is attracted to a stable ``hovering state'' in which it aligns its axis normal to the wall and rests (positions itself) at an activity-dependent distance above the center of the patch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10568v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viviana Mancuso, Mihail N. Popescu, William E. Uspal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trapping of isotropic droplets by disclinations in nematic liquid crystals controlled by surface anchoring and elastic constant disparity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linear defects such as dislocations and disclinations in ordered materials attract foreign particles since they replace strong elastic distortions at the defect cores. In this work, we explore the behavior of isotropic droplets nucleating at singular disclinations in a nematic liquid crystal, predesigned by surface photopatterning. Experiments show that in the biphasic nematic-isotropic region, although the droplets are attracted to the disclination cores, their centers of mass shift away from the core centers as the temperature increases. The shift is not random, being deterministically defined by the surrounding director field. The effect is explained by the balance of interfacial anchoring and bulk elasticity. An agreement with the experiment can be achieved only if the model accounts for the disparity of the nematic elastic constants; the so-called one-constant approximation, often used in the theoretical analysis of liquid crystals, produces qualitatively wrong predictions. In particular, the experimentally observed shift towards the bend region around a +1/2 disclination core can be explained only when the bend constant is larger than the splay constant. The described dependence of the precise location of a foreign inclusion at defect cores on the elastic and surface anchoring properties can be used in the rational design of microscale architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10684v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.109.064703</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review E 109, 064703 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nilanthi P. Haputhanthrige, Sathyanarayana Paladugu, Maxim O. Lavrentovich, Oleg D. Lavrentovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Properties of Liquid Dynamics Predicted from a Single Configuration: Pseudoisomorphs for Harmonic-Bonded Molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10859v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Isomorphs are curves in the thermodynamic phase diagram of invariant excess entropy, structure, and dynamics, while pseudoisomorphs are curves of invariant structure and dynamics, but not of the excess entropy. The latter curves have been shown to exist in molecular models with flexible bonds [Olsen et al., J. Chem. Phys. 145, 241103 (2016)]. We here present three force-based methods to trace out pseudoisomorphs based on a single configuration and test them on the asymmetric dumbbell and 10-bead Lennard-Jones chain models with bonds modeled as harmonic springs. The three methods are based on requiring that particle forces, center-of-mass forces, and torques, respectively, are invariant in reduced units. For each of the two investigated models we identify a method that works well for tracing out pseudoisomorphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10859v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahraa Sheydaafar, Jeppe C. Dyre, Thomas B. Schr{\o}der</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic theory of dilute granular gases having an inverse power law potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The kinetic theory of dilute granular gases having an inverse power law repulsive potential is studied. We derive the time evolution of the temperature and the transport coefficients from the Boltzmann equation. We also investigate the linear stability analysis of the hydrodynamics, and study the softness dependence of the thresholds for the shear and heat modes against the restitution coefficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10864v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satoshi Takada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integer defects, flow localization, and bistability on curved active surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11465v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biological surfaces, such as developing epithelial tissues, exhibit in-plane polar or nematic order and can be strongly curved. Recently, integer (+1) topological defects have been identified as morphogenetic hotspots in living systems. Yet, while +1 defects in active matter on flat surfaces are well-understood, the general principles governing curved active defects remain unknown. Here, we study the dynamics of integer defects in an extensile or contractile polar fluid on two types of morphogenetically-relevant substrates : (1) a cylinder terminated by a spherical cap, and (2) a bump on an otherwise flat surface. Because the Frank elastic energy on a curved surface generically induces a coupling to $\textit{deviatoric}$ curvature, $\mathcal{D}$ (difference between squared principal curvatures), a +1 defect is induced on both surface types. We find that $\mathcal{D}$ leads to surprising effects including localization of orientation gradients and active flows, and particularly for contractility, to hysteresis and bistability between quiescent and flowing defect states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11465v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rushikesh Shinde, Rapha\"el Voituriez, Andrew Callan-Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotropic tensor fields in amorphous solids: Correlation functions of displacement and strain tensor fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generalizing recent work on isotropic tensor fields in isotropic and achiral condensed matter systems from two to arbitrary dimensions we address both mathematical aspects assuming perfectly isotropic systems and applications focusing on correlation functions of displacement and strain field components in amorphous solids. Various general points are exemplified using simulated polydisperse Lennard-Jones particles in two dimensions. It is shown that the strain components in reciprocal space have essentially a complex circularly-symmetric Gaussian distribution albeit weak non-Gaussianity effects become visible for large wavenumbers q where also anisotropy effects become relevant. The dynamical strain correlation functions are strongly non-monotonic with respect to q with a minimum roughly at the breakdown of the continuum limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11588v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. P. Wittmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charged drop impinging on particles dispersed over a metallic plate: A method of particle cleaning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10994v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An electric field applied to a droplet impinging on a hydrophobic surface has an extensive variety of applications, including ant-icing, heat transfer enhancement, self-cleaning, droplet manipulation, and electrostatic spraying. The present study demonstrates an effective method of particle removal using a charged droplet. This method employs a pin-plate electrode setup to investigate the dynamics of a charged droplet impact on the surface covered with particles. The particles of different properties such as wettability, electrical conductivity, etc. have been used. Silane-coated glass beads, carbon black, and glass beads are dispersed over the ground copper electrode. The applied potential is also varied from 2 kV to 4 kV. A high-speed imaging is employed to visualize the drop motion, dynamic behavior, and self-cleaning phenomenon. The experimental results indicate that drop generation and impact occur at applied potentials of 2.5, 3, and 3.5 kV, in contrast, at 2 kV, there is no droplet pinch-off. At 4 kV, electric breakdown and bridging of the droplet between the capillary and ground electrode are observed. The drop impact on the silane-coated glass bead leads to their attachment due to the adhesiveness of the particles and the droplet. The silane-coated particles are removed from the droplet surface due to the deformation of the drop and the electric repulsive force. In the case of carbon black and glass beads, the particles are captured by the droplet due to the electrostatic force of attraction. Higher electric potentials lead to an increased spreading diameter of the droplet. The higher electric field enhances the contact area between the droplet and the particles, thereby removing more particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10994v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Biswal, S. K. Saroj, B. Ray, Debabrata Dasgupta, R. M. Thaokar, Y. S. Mayya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A cascade model for the discontinuous absorbing phase transition between turbulent and laminar flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11324v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a minimal model of energy transfer through scales to describe, at a qualitative level, the subcritical transition between laminar and turbulent flows, viewed in a statistical physics framework as a discontinuous absorbing phase transition. The main control parameter of the model is a Reynolds number that compares energy transfer to viscous dissipation on a large length scale. In spite of its simplicity, the model qualitatively reproduces a number of salient features of the subcritical laminar-turbulent transition, including the existence of an absorbing laminar state, the discontinuous onset of a metastable fluctuating turbulent state above a threshold Reynolds number, and a faster-than-exponential increase of the turbulence lifetime when increasing the Reynolds number. The behavior of the model is also consistent, at high Reynolds number, with the Kolmogorov K41 phenomenology of fully developed turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11324v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Bertin, Alex Andrix, Ga\"el Le Godais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic depletion interactions in two-temperature mixtures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11616v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The phase separation that occurs in two-temperature mixtures, which are driven out of equilibrium at the local scale, has been thoroughly characterized, but much less is known about the depletion interactions that drive it Using numerical simulations in dimension 2, we show that the depletion interactions extend beyond two particle diameters in dilute systems, as expected at equilibrium, and decay algebraically with an exponent $-4$. Solving for the $N$-particle distribution function in the stationary state, perturbatively in the interaction potential, we show that the algebraic correlations arise from triplets of particles at different temperatures, and recover the exponent $-4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11616v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Damman, Vincent D\'emery, Guillaume Palumbo, Quentin Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Site-percolation transition of run-and-tumble particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study percolation transition of run and tumble particles (RTPs) on a two dimensional square lattice. RTPs in these models run to the nearest neighbour along their internal orientation with unit rate, and to other nearest neighbours with rates $p$. In addition, they tumble to change their internal orientation with rate $\omega$. We show that for small tumble rates, RTP-clusters created by joining occupied nearest neighbours irrespective of their orientation form a phase separated state when the rate of positional diffusion $p$ crosses a threshold; with further increase of $p$ the clusters disintegrate and another transition to a mixed phase occurs. The critical exponents of this re-entrant site-percolation transition of RTPs vary continuously along the critical line in the $\omega$-$p$ plane, but a scaling function remains invariant. This function is identical to the corresponding universal scaling function of percolation transition observed in the Ising model. We also show that the critical exponents of the underlying motility induced phase separation transition are related to corresponding percolation-critical-exponents by constant multiplicative factors known from the correspondence of magnetic and percolation critical exponents of Ising model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11726v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya K. Saha, Aikya Banerjee, P. K. Mohanty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Interfacial Energetic Landscape in Organic Solar Cells Reveals Pathways to Reducing Nonradiative Losses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11735v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bulk heterojunction (BHJ) organic solar cells have made remarkable inroads towards 20% efficiency, yet nonradiative recombination losses ({\Delta}Vnr) remain high compared to silicon and perovskite photovoltaics. Interfaces buried within BHJ blends hold the key to recombination losses but access to their energetic landscape underpinning charge transfer (CT) states and their disorder remain elusive. Here, we reveal the energetic landscape and CT state manifold of modern BHJs with both spatial and energetic resolutions and link the offset between singlet (ES1) and CT energy (ES1-CT) and interfacial energetic disorder with {\Delta}Vnr. We do so by locally mapping the energy distributions of modern PM6-based BHJs with IT4F, Y6 and PC71BM acceptors and combine it, for the first time, with sensitive EQE measurements, to visualize and quantify donor (D) and acceptor (A) energetics at interfaces and associated them with CT states within a modified Marcus framework. A key new ability is the identification of the specific BHJ interfaces associated with the CT manifold, including where the lowest energy CT states reside. Moreover, we quantify energy levels and electronic disorders directly at these and other interfaces and connect these contributions to the energy losses. We delineate the influences of S1-CT offset and interfacial energetic disorder on {\Delta}Vnr across morphologically varied BHJs. Our results show both factors influencing energy losses in different ways. We demonstrate that PM6:Y6 can achieve low {\Delta}Vnr by forming a nominally sharp D/A interface with exceptionally low interfacial disorder via judicious processing combined with a low S1 to CT offset. This provides a design rule to minimize {\Delta}Vnr for modern NFAs: sharp D/A interfaces with low S1 to CT offset exhibiting minimal interfacial disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11735v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurab J. Thapa, Mihirsinh Chauhan, Jacob P. Mauthe, Daniel B. Dougherty, Aram Amassian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Condensate Formation in a Chiral Lattice Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11807v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the formation of condensates in a binary lattice gas in the presence of chiral interactions. These interactions differ between a given microscopic configuration and its mirror image. We consider a two dimensional lattice gas with nearest-neighbour interactions to which we add interactions involving favoured local structures that are chiral. We focus on favoured local structures that have the shape of the letter L and explore condensate formation through simulations and analytical calculations. At low temperature, this model can exhibit four different phases that are characterised by different periodic tiling patterns, depending on the strength of interactions and the chemical potential. When particle numbers are conserved, some of these phases can coexist. We analyse the structure and surface tension of interfaces between coexisting phases and determine the condensate shapes of minimal free energy. We show that these shapes can be quadrilaterals or octagons of different orientation and symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11807v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyi Wang, Frank J\"ulicher, Patrick Pietzonka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immersed boundary method for dynamic simulation of polarizable colloids of arbitrary shape in explicit ion electrolytes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04865v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a computational method for modeling electrostatic interactions of arbitrarily-shaped, polarizable objects on colloidal length scales, including colloids/nanoparticles, polymers, and surfactants, dispersed in explicit ion electrolytes and nonionic solvents. Our method computes the nonuniform polarization charge distribution induced in a colloidal particle by both externally applied electric fields and local electric fields arising from other charged objects in the dispersion. This leads to expressions for electrostatic energies, forces, and torques that enable efficient molecular dynamics and Brownian dynamics simulations of colloidal dispersions in electrolytes, which can be harnessed to accurately predict structural and transport properties. We describe an implementation in which colloidal particles are modeled as rigid composites of small spherical beads that tessellate the surface of the particle. The electrostatics calculations are accelerated using a spectrally-accurate particle-mesh-Ewald technique implemented on a graphics processing unit (GPU) and regularized such that the electrostatic calculations are well-defined even for overlapping bodies. We demonstrate the effectiveness of this approach through a series of calculations, including the induced dipole moments and forces for one, two, and lattices of spherical colloids in an electric field; the induced dipole moment and torque for anisotropic particles in an electric field; the equilibrium distribution of ions in the double layer around charged colloids; the dynamics of charged colloids; and ions in the double layer around a polarizable colloid exposed to an electric field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04865v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Krucker-Velasquez, James W. Swan, Zachary Sherman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse forces and glassy liquids in infinite dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10856v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the dynamics of a simple liquid whose particles, in addition to standard potential-based interactions, are also subjected to transverse forces preserving the Boltzmann distribution. We derive the effective dynamics of one and two tracer particles in the infinite-dimensional limit. We determine the amount of acceleration of the dynamics caused by the transverse forces, in particular in the vicinity of the glass transition. We analyze the emergence and evolution of odd transport phenomena induced by the transverse forces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10856v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.109.064133</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 109, 064133 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Federico Ghimenti, Ludovic Berthier, Grzegorz Szamel, Fr\'ed\'eric van Wijland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase diagram and coarsening dynamics in dry apolar active nematics with reciprocal local alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11642v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using the Lebwohl-Lasher interaction for reciprocal local alignment, we present a comprehensive phase diagram for a dry, apolar, active nematic system using its stochastic dynamics. The nematic-isotropic transition in this system is first-order and fluctuation-dominated. Our phase diagram identifies three distinct regions based on activity and orientational noise relative to alignment strength: a homogeneous isotropic phase, a nematic phase with giant density fluctuations, and a coexistence region. Using mean-field analysis and hydrodynamic theory, we demonstrate that reciprocal interactions lead to a density fluctuation-induced first-order transition and derive a phase boundary consistent with numerical results. Quenching from the isotropic to nematic phase reveals coarsening dynamics with nematic ordering preceding particle clustering and similar scaling behaviors for density and nematic fields, exhibiting dynamic exponents between 2 and 3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11642v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Sinha, Debasish Chaudhuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating meV-scale Equilibrium Atomic Dynamics with X-Rays: focus on disordered materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08670v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper reviews non-resonant meV-resolved inelastic x-ray scattering (IXS) as a complementary method to inelastic neutron scattering (INS). Two aspects of IXS that are notable in this context are (1) that IXS allows straightforward measurements of phonons in small (sub-mm, and even $\sim 0.01$ mm) samples with $\sim 1$ meV resolution and excellent Q resolution and (2) that IXS avoids the kinematic constraints of INS. The first allows both new geometries (thin films, diamond anvil cells) and easy access to new materials, while the second allows high quality data on disordered materials, such as scans with sub-meV resolution to arbitrarily high energy transfer become possible , even at momentum transfers as small as 1/nm. The review briefly discusses the spectrometers and compares the practical forms for the dynamic structure factor for crystals, glasses and liquids. This is followed by a longer review of work on liquids and then shorter discussion of work on glasses, crystals, and discussion of specific geometries. This paper complements the longer introduction/review of IXS at arxiv:1504.01098 .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08670v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Hamon Volume 34 Number 1 2024 p3</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alfred Q. R. Baron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of bacterial glass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.10436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.10436v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Densely packed, motile bacteria can adopt collective states not seen in conventional, passive materials. These states remain in many ways mysterious, and their physical characterization can aid our understanding of natural bacterial colonies and biofilms as well as materials in general. Here, we overcome challenges associated with generating uniformly growing, large, quasi-two-dimensional bacterial assemblies by a membrane-based microfluidic device and report the emergence of glassy states in two-dimensional suspension of Escherichia coli. As the number density increases by cell growth, populations of motile bacteria transition to a glassy state, where cells are packed and unable to move. This takes place in two steps, the first one suppressing only the orientational modes and the second one vitrifying the motion completely. Characterizing each phase through statistical analyses and investigations of individual motion of bacteria, we find not only characteristic features of glass such as rapid slowdown, dynamic heterogeneity and cage effects, but also a few properties distinguished from those of thermal glass. These distinctive properties include the spontaneous formation of micro-domains of aligned cells with collective motion, the appearance of an unusual signal in the dynamic susceptibility, and the dynamic slowdown with a density dependence generally forbidden for thermal systems. Our results are expected to capture general characteristics of such active rod glass, which may serve as a physical mechanism underlying dense bacterial aggregates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.10436v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae238</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PNAS Nexus (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hisay Lama, Masahiro J. Yamamoto, Yujiro Furuta, Takuro Shimaya, Kazumasa A. Takeuchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning probability flows and entropy production rates in active matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12991v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Active matter systems, from self-propelled colloids to motile bacteria, are characterized by the conversion of free energy into useful work at the microscopic scale. They involve physics beyond the reach of equilibrium statistical mechanics, and a persistent challenge has been to understand the nature of their nonequilibrium states. The entropy production rate and the probability current provide quantitative ways to do so by measuring the breakdown of time-reversal symmetry. Yet, their efficient computation has remained elusive, as they depend on the system's unknown and high-dimensional probability density. Here, building upon recent advances in generative modeling, we develop a deep learning framework to estimate the score of this density. We show that the score, together with the microscopic equations of motion, gives access to the entropy production rate, the probability current, and their decomposition into local contributions from individual particles. To represent the score, we introduce a novel, spatially-local transformer network architecture that learns high-order interactions between particles while respecting their underlying permutation symmetry. We demonstrate the broad utility and scalability of the method by applying it to several high-dimensional systems of active particles undergoing motility-induced phase separation (MIPS). We show that a single network trained on a system of 4096 particles at one packing fraction can generalize to other regions of the phase diagram, including systems with as many as 32768 particles. We use this observation to quantify the spatial structure of the departure from equilibrium in MIPS as a function of the number of particles and the packing fraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12991v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1073/pnas.2318106121</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas M. Boffi, Eric Vanden-Eijnden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A classical density functional theory for solvation across length scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02873v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A central aim of multiscale modeling is to use results from the Schr\"odinger Equation to predict phenomenology on length scales that far exceed those of typical molecular correlations. In this work, we present a new approach rooted in classical density functional theory (cDFT) that allows us to accurately describe the solvation of apolar solutes across length scales. Our approach builds on the Lum, Chandler and Weeks (LCW) theory of hydrophobicity [J. Phys. Chem. B 103, 4570 (1999)] by constructing a free energy functional that uses a slowly-varying component of the density field as a reference. From a practical viewpoint, the theory we present is numerically simpler and generalizes to solutes with soft-core repulsion more easily than LCW theory. Furthermore, by assessing the local compressibility and its critical scaling behavior, we demonstrate that our LCW-style cDFT approach contains the physics of critical drying, which has been emphasized as an essential aspect of hydrophobicity by recent theories. As our approach is parameterized on the two-body direct correlation function of the uniform fluid and the liquid-vapor surface tension, it straightforwardly captures the temperature dependence of solvation. Moreover, we use our theory to describe solvation at a first-principles level, on length scales that vastly exceed what is accessible to molecular simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02873v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna T. Bui, Stephen J. Cox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parameter identification and uncertainty propagation of hydrogel coupled diffusion-deformation using POD-based reduced-order modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08968v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study explores reduced-order modeling for analyzing the time-dependent diffusion-deformation of hydrogels. The full-order model describing hydrogel transient behavior consists of a coupled system of partial differential equations in which chemical potential and displacements are coupled. This system is formulated in a monolithic fashion and solved using the finite element method. We employ proper orthogonal decomposition as a model order reduction approach. The reduced-order model performance is tested through a benchmark problem on hydrogel swelling and a case study simulating co-axial printing. Then, we embed the reduced-order model into an optimization loop to efficiently identify the coupled problem's material parameters using full-field data. Finally, a study is conducted on the uncertainty propagation of the material parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08968v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gopal Agarwal, Jorge-Humberto Urrea-Quintero, Henning Wessels, Thomas Wick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo Simulations of the Blinking-Checkers Model for Polyamorphic Fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12445v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The blinking-checkers model [F. Caupin and M. A. Anisimov, Phys. Rev. Lett, 127,185701 (2021)] is a minimal lattice model which has demonstrated that, in the meanfield approximation, it can reproduce the phenomenon of fluid polyamorphism. This model is a binary lattice-gas, in which each site has three possible states: empty, occupied with particles of type 1, and occupied with particles of type 2. Additionally, the two types of particles may interconvert from one to another. Equilibrium interconversion imposes a constraint that makes this model thermodynamically equivalent to a single-component system. In this work, Monte-Carlo simulations of the blinking-checkers model are performed, demonstrating polyamorphic phase behavior. The locations of the liquid-liquid and liquid-gas critical points are found to be different from the meanfield predictions for this model with the same interaction parameters, as the phase behavior is significantly affected by critical fluctuations. Based on the computed values of the critical exponents of the order parameter, susceptibility, correlation length, and surface tension, we confirm that the blinking-checkers model, for both liquid-gas and liquid-liquid equilibria, belongs to the three-dimensional Ising class of critical-point universality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12445v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey V. Buldyrev, Thomas J. Longo, Frederic Caupin, Mikhail A. Anisimov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
