<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Viscotaxis of Beating Flagella at Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many biological microorganisms and artificial microswimmers react to external cues of environmental gradients by changing their swimming directions. We study here the behavior of eukarytic flagellated microswimmers in linear viscosity gradients. We employ a model of flagellum consisting of a semi-flexible filament with a travelling wave of spontaneous curvature to study viscotaxis of actively beating flagella in two spatial dimensions. The propulsion of the flagellum in a fluid due to a hydrodynamic friction anisotropy is described by resistive-force theory. Using numerical simulations and analytical theory, we show that beating flagella exhibit positive viscotaxis, reorienting themselves toward higher viscosity areas. We quantify this behavior by characterization of the dependence of the rotational velocity on beat amplitude, swimming speed, and wave length. We also examining the effects of asymmetric flagellar wave forms, which imply circular trajectories in the absence of viscosity gradients; here, large asymmetry leads to trochoid-like trajectories perpendicular to the gradient in the form drifting circles. The flagellar deformability strongly reduce the beat amplitude and the viscotatic response. The viscotatic response is shown to be captured by a universal function of the sperm number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14059v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Anand, Jens Elgeti, Gerhard Gompper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directed Swarm Assembly due to Mixed Misaligned Perception-Dependent Motility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A mixture of particles with perception-dependent motility and opposite misaligned visual perception shows to spontaneously self-organize into a self-propelling bean-shaped cluster. The two species initially rotate in opposite directions, which together with the steric interactions, makes them segregate into two main counter-rotating domains forming a cohesive and persistently propelling single cluster. Mixtures of particles with misaligned perception and discontinuous motility are therefore a promising pathway for the design of programmable active matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14062v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Saavedra, Marisol Ripoll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tip angle dependence for resistive force into dry granular materials at shallow cone penetration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In relation to the interaction of the earth's surface with machines and organisms, and its engineering applications, there has been a recent increase in interest in the penetration resistive force into granular materials at shallow depths. Previous studies have proposed various models for penetration resistive forces into dry granular materials. This study focuses on the model which has a coefficient depending on the angle of repose and the increase of resistive force in proportion to the penetration volume. In the previous studies, the model has been validated for several geometries such as cylinders, cones, and spheres. However, for cones, the model has only been validated under conditions of a tip angle close to the angle of repose. In this study, the effect of cone tip angle on penetration resistive force is investigated under several conditions with different angles of repose. This study carries out cone penetration simulations using the discrete element method. For the cone geometry, five tip angles ranging from sharp to blunt (tip angles are 15, 30, 45, 60, 75 deg) are used. The simulation results show that the penetration resistive forces for blunt cones are much higher than that computed by the model. To solve the discrepancy between the model and simulation results, this study modifies the model by assuming that the stagnant zone formed in front of the cone penetrating the granular material behaves as an effective cone. Thereby, the proposed model can calculate penetration resistive forces more accurately for cones with a wider range of tip angles than in the previous model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14291v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Iikawa, Hiroaki Katsuragi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental constants explain sub-millimeter liquid shear forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14458v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: From its links to fundamental physical constants to the identification of liquid shear elasticity, over the past decade, new ways are emerging to understand viscosity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14458v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science Advances 9 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Laurence Noirez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blockage of thermocapillary flows by surface-active impurities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thermocapillary convection is particularly effective for the control of thin liquid film topography or for the actuation of microparticles at the liquid-air interface. Experiments with water are challenging, however, as its interface is prone to contamination by surface-active impurities that profoundly alter its hydrodynamic response. Despite numerous reports highlighting the hindrance of thermocapillary flows, quantitative information on interface contamination is definitely lacking. We therefore introduce a general framework in order to account for the presence of a low concentration of insoluble surfactants at the water-air interface. Focusing on the low-compressibility limit, we identify the inverse Marangoni number as the appropriate small parameter in the modeling. The transport equations can then be linearized without any further assumption regarding the other dimensionless groups. It is shown in particular that the surfactant concentration adapts to the thermocapillary forcing in order to cancel the interfacial viscous stress. Several experimentally relevant situations are discussed with emphasis on physical observables. Besides the excellent agreement between theory and experiment, our predictions provide a quantitative assessment of the impurity concentration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14493v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Bickel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetotaxis in droplet microswimmers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetotaxis is a well known phenomenon in swimming microorganisms which sense magnetic fields e.g. by incorporating crystalline magnetosomes. In designing artificial active matter with tunable dynamics, external magnetic fields can provide a versatile method for guidance. Here, it is the question what material properties are necessary to elicit a significant response. In this working paper, we document in experiments on self-propelling nematic microdroplets that the weak diamagnetic torques exerted by a sub-Tesla magnetic field are already sufficient to significantly affect the dynamics of these swimmers. We find a rich and nontrivial variety of dynamic modes by varying droplet size, state of confinement and magnetic field strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14558v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin W. Wagner, Freek Domburg, Carsten Kr\"uger, Jens Meyer, Jiaqi Zhang, Prashanth Ramesh, Corinna C. Maass</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity correlations and the onset of charge ordering at charged interfaces: a modified Poisson-Fermi approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Charge layering in the close vicinity of charged interfaces is a well known effect, extensively reported in both experiments and simulations of Room Temperature Ionic Liquids (RTIL) and concentrated aqueous-like electrolytes. The traditional Poisson-Fermi (PF) theory is able to successfully describe overcrowding effects, but fails to reproduce charge ordering even in strong coupling regimes. Simple models, yet capable to investigate the interplay between these important interfacial phenomena, are still lacking. In order to bridge this gap, we herein present a modified PF (mPF) approach which is able to capture layering effects in strong coupling regimes typical of RTIL. The modification is based on the introduction of charge cavities around test-particles, which simply extend the exclusion volume effects to also incorporate the accompanying depletion of charges due to particle insertion. Addition of this simple ingredient is shown to reproduce overscreening and charge ordering, thereby extending the predictive power of the PF approach to strong coupling regimes. Using a linear response theory, we are able to study the emergence of charge ordering based on two characteristic lengths: a wavelength responsible by charge layering, along with a dumping length which screens charge oscillations. At large ionic strengths and strong couplings, the system undergoes a transition to undumped charge layering. The transition takes place when the poles of the Fourier components of the linear potential become real-valued. This criteria allows one to identify the transition line across the parameter space, thus delimiting the region of stability against unscreneed charge ordering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14642v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ot\'avio David Braga, Thiago Colla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological edge flows drive macroscopic re-organization in magnetic colloids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic colloids can be driven with time-varying fields to form clusters and voids that re-organize over vastly different timescales. However, the driving force behind these non-equilibrium dynamics is not well-understood. Here, we introduce a topological framework that predicts protected edge flows that drive reorganization, despite strong thermal motion. We verify this theory experimentally using micron-sized super-paramagnetic colloids to demonstrate how large-scale flow properties emerge. Our results elucidate fundamental principles that shape and control non-equilibrium colloidal aggregates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15068v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandra Nelson, Dana M. Lobmeyer, Sibani L. Biswal, Evelyn Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Off-Lattice Markov Chain Monte Carlo Simulations of Mechanically Driven Polymers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop off-lattice simulations of semiflexible polymer chains subjected to applied mechanical forces using Markov Chain Monte Carlo. Our approach models the polymer as a chain of fixed-length bonds, with configurations updated through adaptive non-local Monte Carlo moves. This proposed method enables precise calculation of a polymer's response to a wide range of mechanical forces, which traditional on-lattice models cannot achieve. Our approach has shown excellent agreement with theoretical predictions of persistence length and end-to-end distance in quiescent states, as well as stretching distances under tension. Moreover, our model eliminates the orientational bias present in on-lattice models, which significantly impacts calculations such as the scattering function, a crucial technique for revealing polymer conformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15223v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lijie Ding, Chi-Huan Tung, Bobby G. Sumpter, Wei-Ren Chen, Changwoo Do</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why gauge invariance applies to statistical mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14166v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give an introductory account of the recently identified gauge invariance of the equilibrium statistical mechanics of classical many-body systems [J. M\"uller et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. (to appear) arXiv:2406.19235]. The gauge transformation is a non-commutative shifting operation on phase space that keeps the differential phase space volume element and hence the Gibbs integration measure conserved. When thermally averaged any observable is an invariant, including thermodynamic and structural quantities. Shifting transformations are canonical in the sense of classical mechanics. They also form an infinite-dimensional group with generators of infinitesimal transformations that build a non-commutative Lie algebra. We lay out the connections with the underlying geometry of coordinate displacement and with Noether's theorem. Spatial localization of the shifting yields differential operators that satisfy commutator relationships, which we describe both in purely configurational and in full phase space setups. Standard operator calculus yields corresponding equilibrium hyperforce correlation sum rules for general observables and order parameters. Using Monte Carlos simulations we demonstrate explicitly the gauge invariance for finite shifting. We argue in favour of using the gauge invariance as a statistical mechanical construction principle for obtaining exact results and for formulating smart sampling algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14166v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johanna M\"uller, Florian Samm\"uller, Matthias Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions in chromatin: mesoscopic and mean-field approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14270v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By means of a minimal physical model, we investigate the interplay of two phase transitions at play in chromatin organization: (1) liquid-liquid phase separation (LLPS) within the fluid solvating chromatin, resulting in the formation of biocondensates, and (2) the coil-globule crossover of the chromatin fiber, which drives the condensation or extension of the chain. In our model, a species representing a domain of chromatin is embedded in a binary fluid. This fluid phase separates to form a droplet rich in a macromolecule (B). Chromatin particles are trapped in a harmonic potential to reproduce the coil and globular phases of an isolated polymer chain. We investigate the role of the droplet material B on the radius of gyration of this polymer and find that this radius varies nonmonotonically with respect to the volume fraction of B. This behavior is reminiscent of a phenomenon known as $\textit{co-non-solvency}$: a polymer chain in good solvent (S) may collapse when a second good solvent (here B) is added in low quantity, and expand at higher B concentration. Additionally, the presence of finite-size effects on the coil-globule transition results in a qualitatively different impact of the droplet material on polymers of various sizes. In the context of genetic regulation, our results suggest that the size of chromatin domains and the quantity of condensate proteins are key parameters to control whether chromatin may respond to an increase of the quantity of chromatin-binding proteins by condensing or expanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14270v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reda Tiani, Marie Jardat, Vincent Dahirel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The route of random process to ultraslow aging phenomena</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14422v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Logarithmic aging phenomena are prevalent in various systems, including electronic materials and biological structures. This study utilizes a generalized continuous time random walk (CTRW) framework to investigate the mechanisms behind the logarithmic aging phenomena. By incorporating non-Markovian jump processes with significant memory effects, we modify traditional diffusion models to exhibit logarithmic decay in both survival and return probabilities. In addition, we analyze the impact of aging on autocorrelation functions, illustrating how long-term memory behaviors affect the temporal evolution of physical properties. These results connect microscopic models to macroscopic manifestations in real-world systems, advancing the understanding of ultraslow dynamics in disordered systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14422v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunyan Li, Haiwen Liu, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Membrane tubes with active pumping: water transport, vacuole formation and osmoregulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14835v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The need for organisms to regulate their volume and osmolarity when surrounded by freshwater is a basic physical challenge for many bacteria, protists and algae. Taking inspiration from the contractile vacuole complex found in many protists, we discuss how simple models of active membrane tubes can give insights into the fluid and active ionic transport properties of such systems. We show that a simple membrane tube with unidirectional ion pumps, and passive ion and water channels, forms a large vacuole due to osmotically-driven water flow and that this can be used to actively pump water out of the cell interior. We discuss the use of this system as a possible minimal method for osmoregulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14835v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sami C. Al-Izzi, Matthew S. Turner, Pierre Sens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermostatting of Active Hamiltonian Systems via Symplectic Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14864v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a class of non-standard, two-dimensional (2D) Hamiltonian models that may show features of active particle dynamics, and therefore, we refer to these models as active Hamiltonian (AH) systems. The idea is to consider a spin fluid where -- on top of spin-spin and particle-particle interactions -- spins are coupled to the particle's velocities via a vector potential. Continuous spin variables interact with each other as in a standard $XY$ model. Typically, the AH models exhibit non-standard thermodynamic properties (e.g., for temperature and pressure) and equations of motion with non-standard forces. This implies that the derivation of symplectic algorithms to solve Hamilton's equations of motion numerically, as well as the thermostatting for these systems, is not straightforward. Here, we derive a symplectic integration scheme and propose a Nos\'e-Poincar\'e thermostat, providing a correct sampling in the canonical ensemble. The expressions for AH systems that we find for temperature and pressure might have parallels with the ongoing debate about the definition of pressure and the equation of state in active matter systems. For a specific AH model, recently proposed by Casiulis et al. [Phys. Rev. Lett. {\bf 124}, 198001 (2020)], we rationalize the symplectic algorithm and the proposed thermostatting, and investigate the transition from a fluid at high temperature to a cluster phase at low temperature where, due to the coupling of velocities and spins, the cluster phase shows a collective motion that is reminiscent to that observed in a variety of active systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14864v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antik Bhattacharya, J\"urgen Horbach, Smarajit Karmakar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Fluctuation Dissipation Relations for Active Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14977v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Breakdown of time-reversal symmetry is a defining property of non-equilibrium systems, such as active matter, which is composed of units that consume energy. We employ a formalism that allows us to derive a class of identities associated with the time-reversal transformation in non-equilibrium field theories, in the spirit of Ward-Takahashi identities. We present a generalization of the fluctuation-dissipation theorem valid for active systems as a particular realization of such an identity, and apply it to the Non-Reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard model for which we verify the identity via a graphical summation method. The field theoretical toolbox developed here helps to quantify the degree of non-equilibrium activity of complex systems exhibiting collective behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14977v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Kj{\o}llesdal Johnsrud, Ramin Golestanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement transition in random rod packings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04903v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Random packings of stiff rods are self-supporting mechanical structures stabilized by long range interactions induced by contacts. To understand the geometrical and topological complexity of the packings, we first deploy X-ray computerized tomography to unveil the structure of the packing. This allows us to directly visualize the spatial variations in density, orientational order and the entanglement, a mesoscopic field that we define in terms of a local average crossing number, a measure of the topological complexity of the packing. We find that increasing the aspect ratio of the constituent rods in a packing leads to a proliferation of regions of strong entanglement that eventually percolate through the system, and correlated with a sharp transition in the mechanical stability of the packing. To corroborate our experimental findings, we use numerical simulations of contacting elastic rods and characterize their stability to static and dynamic loadings. Our experiments and computations lead us to an entanglement phase diagram which we also populate using published experimental data from pneumatically tangled filaments, worm blobs, and bird nests along with additional numerical simulations using these data sets. Together, these show the regimes associated with mechanically stable entanglement as a function of the statistics of the packings and loading, with lessons for a range of systems from reconfigurable architectures and textiles to active morphable filamentous assemblies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04903v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yeonsu Jung, Thomas Plumb-Reyes, Hao-Yu Greg Lin, L. Mahadevan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freely Suspended Nematic and Smectic Films and Free-Standing Smectic Filaments in the Ferroelectric Nematic Realm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04019v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that stable, freely suspended liquid crystal films can be made from the ferroelectric nematic ($\mathrm{N_F}$) phase and from the recently discovered polar, lamellar $\mathrm{SmZ_A}$ and $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ phases. The $\mathrm{N_F}$ films display two-dimensional, smectic-like parabolic focal conic textures comprising director/polarization bend that are a manifestation of the electrostatic suppression of director splay in the film plane. In the $\mathrm{SmZ_A}$ and $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ phases, the smectic layers orient preferentially normal to the film surfaces, a condition never found in typical thermotropic or lyotropic lamellar LC phases, with the $\mathrm{SmZ_A}$ films exhibiting focal-conic fan textures mimicking the appearance of typical smectics in glass cells when the layers are oriented normal to the plates, and the $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ films showing a texture of plaquettes of uniform in-plane orientation where both bend and splay are suppressed, separated by grain boundaries. The $\mathrm{SmA_F}$ phase can also be drawn into thin filaments, in which X-ray scattering reveals that the smectic layer planes are normal to the filament axis. Remarkably, the filaments are mechanically stable even if they break, forming free-standing, fluid filaments supported only at one end. The unique architectures of these films and filaments are stabilized by the electrostatic self-interaction of the liquid crystal polarization field, which enables the formation of confined, fluid structures that are fundamentally different from those of their counterparts made using previously known liquid crystal phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04019v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keith G. Hedlund, Vikina Martinez, Xi Chen, Cheol S. Park, Joseph E. Maclennan, Matthew A. Glaser, Noel A. Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Segregation, Finite Time Elastic Singularities and Coarsening in Renewable Active Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09050v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Material renewability in active living systems, such as in cells and tissues, can drive the large-scale patterning of forces, with distinctive phenotypic consequences. This is especially significant in the cell cytoskeleton, where multiple species of myosin bound to actin, apply contractile stresses and undergo continual turnover, that result in patterned force channeling. Here we study the dynamical patterning of stresses that emerge in a hydrodynamic model of a renewable active actomyosin elastomer comprising two myosin species. We find that a uniform active contractile elastomer spontaneously segregates into spinodal stress patterns, followed by a finite-time collapse into tension carrying singular structures that display self-similar scaling and caustics. These singular structures move and merge, and gradually result in a slow coarsening dynamics in one dimension. In addition, the nonreciprocal nature of the underlying dynamics gives rise to exceptional points that are associated with a variety of travelling states -- from peristalsis to swap and trains of regular and singular stress patterns, that may coexist with each other. Both the novel segregation and excitability are consequences of time reversal symmetry breaking of the underlying active dynamics. We discuss the implications of our findings to the emergence of stress fibers and the spatial patterning of myosin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09050v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayan Roychowdhury, Saptarshi Dasgupta, Madan Rao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extreme-value analysis in nano-biological systems: Applications and Implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01007v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Extreme value analysis (EVA) is a statistical method that studies the properties of extreme values of datasets, crucial for fields like engineering, meteorology, finance, insurance, and environmental science. EVA models extreme events using distributions such as Fr\'echet, Weibull, or Gumbel, aiding in risk prediction and management. This review explores EVA's application to nanoscale biological systems. Traditionally, biological research focuses on average values from repeated experiments. However, EVA offers insights into molecular mechanisms by examining extreme data points. We introduce EVA's concepts with simulations and review its use in studying motor protein movements within cells, highlighting the importance of in vivo analysis due to the complex intracellular environment. We suggest EVA as a tool for extracting motor proteins' physical properties in vivo and discuss its potential in other biological systems. While there have been only a few applications of EVA to biological systems, it holds promise for uncovering hidden properties in extreme data, promoting its broader application in life sciences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01007v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kumiko Hayashi, Nobumichi Takamatsu, Shunki Takaramoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory and Personality Shape Ideological Polarization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06660v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We do experiments on physical agents with dynamic binary ideologies, deep memories of previous probes of neigboring agents, but fixed personalities that interpret the memory content to make ideological decisions. We find experimentally a critical memory depth below which complete ideological polarization of the collective cannot occur, and above which it is inevitable, an emergent symmetry breaking that is memory depth dependent. Depending on the details of the personalities, the polarization can be static or dynamic in time, even in certain cases chaotic due to nonreciprocity in how the agents respond to other agents. Thus, agents with different personalities and depths of memory serve as a physics analog of the ideology dynamics among biased individuals, illuminating how decisions influenced by individual memories of past interactions can shape and influence subsequent polarization. Perhaps such applications of physics-based systems to political systems will help us to understand the ideological instabilities observed today.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06660v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengkai Li, Trung V. Phan, Luca Di Carlo, Gao Wang, Van H. Do, Elia Mikhail, Robert H. Austin, Liyu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
