<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 02:44:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of poroelastic spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study experimentally the impact on rigid surfaces of different soft porous solids saturated with liquid: hydrogel balls and liquid-saturated foam balls. The static con tact of such soft solids with the substrate is well described by Hertz contact theory. However, their rebound behavior can only be explained by invoking a variety of dissipa tion mechanisms. We find that the restitution coefficient of soft porous balls generally increases with the impact velocity. We propose that this behavior can be explained by a combination of three wet dissipation mechanisms: capillary adhesion, viscous dissipa tion in a liquid film between the ball and the substrate, and poroelastic dissipation due to porous flow inside the ball. While the first two dissipations are known, we present a new theory for poroelastic dissipation, and show that it allows experimental data for saturated foam balls to be reduced to a master curve against a suitably normalized impact velocity. The understanding of this dissipation mechanism with its dependence on both permeability of the porous solid and liquid viscosity can open the way towards engineering a new generation of shock absorbers and cushions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05891v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gorin Benjamin, Ribe Neil, Bonn Daniel, Kellay Hamid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Granular flows over normally vibrated inclined bases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate granular flows over an inclined rigid base, which is vibrated externally in a direction normal to itself, through discrete element simulations. We vary the base inclination angle theta, vibration frequency f, and amplitude A to study changes in the granular flow profile and the mass flow rate Q. We find that the flow velocity profiles for the vibrated bases are nonlinear, unlike their fixed base counterparts. Our study reveals that Q may be maintained nearly constant in flows over vibrated bases utilizing appropriate combinations of theta, A, and f. At the same time, by vibrating the base at a fixed inclination, we may increase the mass flow rate by as much as 30 times the value found in flows over a stationary base. Finally, we show that Q depends upon a nondimensional number S obtained by taking the ratio of vibrational and gravitational energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06093v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prasad Sonar, Ashish Bhateja, Ishan Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solid-liquid interfacial free energy from computer simulations: Challenges and recent advances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The theory of interfacial properties in liquid-liquid or liquid-vapour systems is nearly 200 years old. The advent of computational tools has greatly advanced the field, mainly through the use of Molecular Dynamics simulations. Despite the successes and advances in the theory of interfacial phenomena for liquid-liquid systems, the study of solid-liquid interfaces remains a challenge both theoretically and experimentally. The main reason why the treatment of solid-liquid systems has fallen behind that of liquid-liquid systems is that there are complications that arise whenever an interface involving solid systems is considered involving both theory of the solid-liquid interface and the calculations using MD simulations. An example of the former is that, contrary to the liquid-liquid case, the interfacial properties of solids depend on the lattice orientation. The main complications in these calculations arise from the fact that for solids the ``mechanical route'' cannot be used. To overcome this problem, several numerical approaches were proposed. The main purpose of this review is to provide an overview of these different methodologies and to discuss their strengths and weaknesses. We classify these methodologies into two main groups: direct and indirect methods. Direct methods are those that can calculate directly the properties of interfaces, while in indirect approaches the properties of the interface are not the primary result of the simulations. We also included a discussion on the origin of the difficulties in considering solid interfaces from a thermodynamic point of view. In the second part of the review, we discuss two key related topics: nucleation theory and curved interfaces. They both represent an important problem in the study of interfaces and in the context of solid-liquid ones for which the research is still extremely active.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06231v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicodemo Di Pasquale, Jesus Algaba, Pablo Montero de Hijes, Ignacio Sanchez-Burgos, Andres R. Tejedor, Stephen R. Yeandel, Felipe J. Blas, Ruslan L. Davidchack, Jorge R. Espinosa, Colin L. Freeman, John H. Harding, Brian B. Laird, Eduardo Sanz, Carlos Vega, Lorenzo Rovigatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-free hydrodynamic theory of the colloidal glass transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a phenomenological, model-free theory for the large-distance hydrodynamic response of a viscous fluid hosting colloidal particles. The flow of the host fluid is affected by the presence of the particles, thus reflecting their liquid or solid state. On the liquid side of the glass transition we identify a dynamic length scale $\ell$ beyond which the host fluid's response is that of a viscous fluid with increased effective viscosity $\eta$. As the glass transition is approached, $\ell$ increases indefinitely as $\ell \sim \eta^{1/2}$. At the transition the large-distance response changes qualitatively, marking the host fluid's loss of translation invariance. On the solid side of the transition we identify another dynamic length, $\ell_s$, beyond which the host fluid responds as a viscous fluid of increased effective viscosity $\eta^+$, confined in a porous medium of effective pore size $\ell_s$. As the glass transition is approached from the solid side, $\ell_s$ grows indefinitely, more sharply than $(\eta^+)^{1/2}$. We discuss various experimental implications of the results and their possible relation to microscopic theories of the colloidal glass transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06270v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haim Diamant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why can a hydrophilic polyelectrolyte precipitate and redissolve below the critical micelle concentration of an oppositely-charged surfactant ?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically study the reentrant condensation of a polyelectrolyte in the presence of an oppositely-charged surfactant,a phenomenon whose phase-transition mechanism remains under discussion. We focus on the adsorption and attraction effects of surfactant near/on polymer chains, and ignore their own non-essential mixing effects if surfactant molecules are far away from polymer chains. This approach allows us to construct a simple mean-field theory and solve it analytically, and finally rationalize the essential features (such as the "egg shape" of spinodal phase diagrams) of the reentrant condensation of a polyelectrolyte induced by diluted oppositely-charged surfactants. By theoretical analysis, we found that a strong electrostatic adsorption between the ionic monomers and surfactant ions is critical to understand the peculiar phenomenon that both the collapse and reentry transitions of polyelectrolytes can occur when the concentration of surfactant is lower than its bulk critical micelle concentration (CMC). The analytical solution of the theory indicates that a minimum coupling energy for the nonlinear hydrophobic-aggregation effect of adsorbed surfactant is essential for phase transition to occur,which explains why polyelectrolytes show phase transition only if the surfactant chain length is longer than a minimum length. The obtained results will shed light on a deep understanding of liquid-liquid phase separation in biological systems where ionic surfactant-like proteins/peptides bound to bio-polyelectrolytes play an important role.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06355v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaisong Yong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A fast transferable method for predicting the glass transition temperature of polymers from chemical structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06461v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new method that successfully predicts the glass transition temperature $T_{\! \textrm{g}}$ of polymers based on their monomer structure. The model combines ideas from Group Additive Properties (GAP) and Quantitative Structure Property Relationship (QSPR) methods, where GAP (or Group Contributions) assumes that sub-monomer motifs contribute additively to $T_{\! \textrm{g}}$, and QSPR links $T_{\! \textrm{g}}$ to the physico-chemical properties of the structure through a set of molecular descriptors. This method yields fast and accurate predictions of $T_{\! \textrm{g}}$ for polymers based on chemical motifs outside the data sample, which resolves the main limitation of the GAP approach. Using a genetic algorithm, we show that only two molecular descriptors are necessary to predict $T_{\! \textrm{g}}$ for PAEK polymers. Our QSPR-GAP method is readily transferred to other physical properties, to measures of activity (QSAR), or to different classes of polymers such as conjugated or bio-polymers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06461v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Brierley-Croft, Peter D. Olmsted, Peter J. Hine, Richard J. Mandle, Adam Chaplin, John Grasmeder, Johan Mattsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tetratic Phase in 2D Crystals of Squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Melting in 2D is described by the celebrated Kosterlitz-Thouless-Halperin-Nelson-Young (KTHNY) theory. The unbinding of two different types of topological defects destroys translational and orientational order at different temperatures. The intermediate phase is called hexatic and has been measured in 2D colloidal monolayers of isotropic particles. The hexatic is a fluid with six-fold quasi-long-ranged orientational order. Here, the melting of a quadratic, 4-fold crystal is investigated, consisting of squares of about $4 \times 4\;\mu\mathrm{m}$. The anisotropic particles are manufactured from a photoresist using a 3D nanoprinter. In aqueous solution, particles sediment by gravity to a thin cover slide where they form a monolayer. The curvature of the cover slide can be adjusted from convex to concave, which allows to vary the area density of the monolayer in the field of view. For low densities, the squares are free to diffuse and form a 2D fluid while for high densities they form a quadratic crystal. Using a four-fold bond-order correlation function, we resolve the tetratic phase with quasi long ranged orientational order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06464v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert L\"offler, Lukas Siedentop, Peter Keim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft wetting ridge rotation in sessile droplets and capillary bridges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the deformation of soft solid layers in the presence of sessile droplets or capillary bridges. By incorporating the surface tension balance at the contact line, we examine the rotation of the wetting ridge and the corresponding change in the contact angle. Our findings reveal that the rotation direction of the wetting ridge aligns with the sign of the Laplace pressure. Notably, while a softer solid layer typically decreases the contact angle for sessile droplets, a negative Laplace pressure in a hydrophilic capillary bridge pulls the solid-liquid interface, leading to an increased contact angle. The interplay between soft layer deformation and droplet contact angle modulation offers insights for controlling droplet motion through elastocapillarity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06800v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boxue Zheng, Tak Shing Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Viscoelastic peeling of thin tapes with frictional sliding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Peeling is one of the most common detachment mechanisms adopted in industrial applications. However, although several experimental investigations have proven the possible occurrence of relative sliding at the interface close to the peeling front, a comprehensive model considering the effect of both the tape viscoelasticity and frictional interfacial dissipation on the peeling behavior is lacking. The present study aims at providing a theoretical framework to investigate the peeling process of a thin viscoelastic tape from a rigid substrate in the presence of frictional sliding at the interface. It shows that, under certain conditions, significantly tougher adhesive performance can be achieved compared to stuck elastic conditions with no interfacial sliding, and that the delamination resistance of the system strongly depends on the propagation velocity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06874v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-62616-6_39</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Marco Ceglie, Nicola Menga, Giuseppe Carbone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferroelectric order in nematic liquids: Flexoelectricity vs electrostatics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent discovery of ferroelectric nematic liquid crystalline phases marks a major breakthrough in soft matter research. An intermediate phase, often observed between the nonpolar and the ferroelectric nematic phase, shows a distinct antiferroelectric response to electric fields. However, its structure and formation mechanisms remain debated, with flexoelectric and electrostatics effects proposed as competing mechanisms. By controlling the magnitude of electrostatic forces through ion addition in two representative ferroelectric nematic materials, we show that the primary mechanism for the emergence of antiferroelectric order is the flexoelectric coupling between electric polarization and splay deformation of the nematic director. The addition of ions significantly expands the temperature range over which the antiferroelectric phase is observed, with this range increasing with increasing ion concentration. Polarizing optical microscopy studies and second harmonic generation microscopy reveal the splayed structure modulated in two dimensions, while SHG interferometry confirms its antiferroelectric character. We extend the model previously used to describe pretransitional behaviour by incorporating the electrostatic contribution of ions. The model shows qualitative agreement with the experiments, accurately reproducing the phase diagram and temperature-dependent evolution of the modulation period of the observed structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06915v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Medle Rupnik, Ema Han\v{z}el, Matija Lov\v{s}in, Natan Osterman, Calum J. Gibb, Richard J. Mandle, Nerea Sebasti\'an, Alenka Mertelj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Printing of Near-Ambient Responsive Liquid Crystal Elastomers with Enhanced Nematic Order and Pluralized Transformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06931v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Liquid Crystal Elastomers with near-ambient temperature-responsiveness (NAT-LCEs) have been extensively studied for building bio-compatible, low-power consumption devices and robotics. However, conventional manufacturing methods face limitations in programmability (e.g., molding) or low nematic order (e.g., DIW printing). Here, a hybrid cooling strategy is proposed for programmable 3D printing of NAT-LCEs with enhanced nematic order, intricate shape forming, and morphing capability. By integrating a low-temperature nozzle and a cooling platform into a 3D printer, the resulting temperature field synergistically facilitates mesogen alignment during extrusion and disruption-free UV cross-linking. This method achieves a nematic order 3000% higher than those fabricated using traditional room temperature 3D printing. Enabled by shifting of transition temperature during hybrid cooling printing, printed sheets spontaneously turn into 3D structures after release from the platform, exhibiting bidirectional deformation with heating and cooling. By adjusting the nozzle and plate temperatures, NAT-LCEs with graded properties can be fabricated for intricate shape morphing. A wristband system with enhanced heart rate monitoring is also developed based on 3D-printed NAT-LCE. Our method may open new possibilities for soft robotics, biomedical devices, and wearable electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06931v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongxiao Li, Yuxuan Sun, Xingjian Li, Xingxiang Li, Zhengqing Zhu, Boxi Sun, Shutong Nong, Jiyang Wu, Tingrui Pan, Weihua Li, Shiwu Zhang, Mujun Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Azimuthal variation of apparent contact angles on structured surfaces featuring micrometric ramps, pyramids and staggered cubes at two different inherent wettabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As new manufacturing methods enable manufacturing of microstructured surfaces with varying structure geometries, questions remain on some effects on the wetting behavior and the resulting apparent contact angles. In this study, we report the manufacturing process using 3D Direct Laser Writing (3D-DLW) and hot embossing for Poly-methylmethacrylate (PMMA) surfaces with micrometric pyramids, cubes on a staggered grid and two types of ramped structures. We measure the azimuthal variation of the apparent contact angle of sessile droplets on the surfaces. Using plasma polymerization or no treatment of the surfaces, two different inherent wettabilities are studied. We find that while all structure types cause an azimuthal variation of the apparent contact angle, pinning at the ramp tops increases the contact angle more strongly on one side. On pyramid structures, pinning lines can occur on the structure axes and diagonals similarly. For cubes on a hexagonal grid, the strongest contact angle increases are observed along the primary structure axes, where pinning is preferred while smaller peaks are seen on the secondary axes at 60{\deg} and 120{\deg} to the primary axis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06961v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Palmetshofer (Institute of Aerospace Thermodynamics, University of Stuttgart), S. Hengsbach (Institute of Microstructure Technology), M. Guttmann (Institute of Microstructure Technology), M. Worgull (Institute of Microstructure Technology), B. Weigand (Institute of Aerospace Thermodynamics, University of Stuttgart)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metadensity functional theory for classical fluids: Extracting the pair potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The excess free energy functional of classical density functional theory depends upon the type of fluid model, specifically on the choice of (pair) potential, is unknown in general, and is approximated reliably only in special cases. We present a machine learning scheme for training a neural network that acts as a generic metadensity functional for truncated but otherwise arbitrary pair potentials. Automatic differentiation and neural functional calculus then yield, for one-dimensional fluids, accurate predictions for inhomogeneous states and immediate access to the pair distribution function. The approach provides a means of addressing a fundamental problem in the physics of liquids, and for soft matter design: How best to invert structural data to obtain the pair potential?</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06972v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefanie M. Kampa, Florian Samm\"uller, Matthias Schmidt, Robert Evans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The orientational structure of a model patchy particle fluid: simulations, integral equations, density functional theory and machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the orientational properties of a homogeneous and inhomogeneous tetrahedral 4-patch fluid (Kern--Frenkel model). Using integral equations, either (i) HNC or (ii) a modified HNC scheme with simulation input, the full orientational dependence of pair and direct correlation functions is determined. Density functionals for the inhomogeneous problem are constructed via two different methods. The first, molecular density functional theory, utilizes the full direct correlation function and an isotropic hard-sphere bridge functional. The second method, a machine learning approach, uses a decomposition of the functional into an isotropic reference part and a mean-field orientational part, where both parts are improved by machine learning techniques. Comparison to simulation data at hard walls and around hard tracers show a similar performance of the two functionals. Machine learning strategies are discussed to eliminate residual differences, with the goal of obtaining machine-learning enhanced functionals for the general anisotropic fluid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06973v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Simon, Luc Belloni, Daniel Borgis, Martin Oettel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Azurin-Based Peptide p28 Arrests the p53-HDM2 Interactions: A Novel Anti-Cancer Pathway</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Azurin and its derived peptides, notably p28, exhibit significant anticancer properties, primarily by stabilizing the tumor suppressor protein p53 and preventing its degradation. Previous studies have shown that p28 binds to p53's DNA-binding domain, protecting it from degradation mechanisms. Expanding on these findings, our research explored whether p28 acts on additional cancer pathways beyond p53 stabilization. Specifically, we examined the interactions between p28 and Human Double Minute 2 (HDM2), a protein that downregulates p53's tumor-suppressive activity by binding to its transactivation domain (TAD). HDM2 is crucial in diminishing p53's function, and our study aimed to determine if p28 disrupts this HDM2-p53 interaction. Using HADDOCK docking and molecular dynamics simulations, we identified three stable conformations of the HDM2-p28 complex. These conformations effectively block HDM2's hydrophobic pocket, allowing for sustained inter-chain interactions and showing favorable binding energies. Further analysis pinpointed essential residues in these interactions, and we calculated interaction energies using the Molecular Mechanics Poisson-Boltzmann Surface Area (MMPBSA) method. Our findings reveal that by blocking HDM2's binding sites, p28 helps maintain p53's transcriptional activity, thus enhancing its tumor-suppressive functions, including apoptosis and cell cycle arrest in cancer cells. This study enhances understanding of azurin-derived peptides' anticancer mechanisms and highlights p28's potential as a peptide-based anticancer agent. These findings also suggest the possibility of designing additional peptide therapies targeting HDM2 and other cancer-related pathways, opening new directions in anticancer therapeutics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07124v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albin Joy, Anand Srivastava, Rajib Biswas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>cgNA+min: computation of sequence-dependent dsDNA energy-minimising minicircle configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06036v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: DNA minicircles are closed double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) fragments that have been demonstrated to be an important experimental tool to understand supercoiled, or stressed, DNA mechanics, such as nucleosome positioning and DNA-protein interactions. Specific minicircles can be simulated using Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulation. However, the enormous sequence space makes it unfeasible to exhaustively explore the sequence-dependent mechanics of DNA minicircles using either experiment or MD. For linear fragments, the cgNA+ model, a computationally efficient sequence-dependent coarse-grained model using enhanced Curves+ internal coordinates (rigid base plus rigid phosphate) of double-stranded nucleic acids (dsNAs), predicts highly accurate nonlocal sequence-dependent equilibrium distributions for an arbitrary sequence when compared with MD simulations. This article addresses the problem of modeling sequence-dependent topologically closed and, therefore, stressed fragments of dsDNA. We introduce cgNA+min, a computational approach within the cgNA+ framework, which extends the cgNA+ model applicability to compute the sequence-dependent energy minimising configurations of covalently closed dsDNA minicircles of various lengths and linking numbers (Lk). The main idea is to derive the appropriate chain rule to express the cgNA+ energy in absolute coordinates involving quaternions where the closure condition is simple to handle. We also present a semi-analytic method for efficiently computing sequence-dependent initial minicircles having arbitrary Lk and length. For different classes and lengths of sequences, we demonstrate that the dsDNA minicircle energies computed using cgNA+min agree well with the energies approximated from experimentally measured J-factor values. Finally, we present the minicircle shape, energy, and multiplicity of Lk for more than 120K random DNA sequences of different lengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06036v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raushan Singh, Jaroslaw Glowacki, Marius Beaud, Federica Padovano, Robert S. Manning, John H. Maddocks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terahertz-permittivity of Carbon Nitrides: Revealing humidity-enhanced dielectric properties on the picosecond timescales relevant for charge carrier photogeneration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06226v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Organic based semiconductor materials offer emerging and sustainable solutions for solar energy conversion technologies and electronics. However, knowledge of their intrinsic (photo)physical properties and light-matter interactions is often limited, especially with respect to the frequency dependent dielectric properties on the relevant timescales of exciton separation and charge generation (fs-ps). By using terahertz-time-domain spectroscopy (THz-TDS), we show that the complex permittivity and THz conductivity of different polymer materials and graphitic carbon nitrides - melon and poly(heptazine imides) (K-PHI) - can be measured directly and accurately in different environmental humidities. Its effects are most strongly observed in the ionic and 2D carbon nitride, K-PHI, where both real permittivity and THz conductivity double from dry to humid conditions (~4-8 and 75-150 S/m, respectively) surpassing the intrinsic dielectric response from water or K-PHI through synergistic effects. Our findings are backed by fs-ps transient absorption spectroscopy (TAS), confirming the impact of humidity on light conversion behaviour on the ps-timescale in K-PHI. We highlight the importance of dielectric property characterization at THz frequencies as critical for understanding photophysical behaviour at exciton or charge separation time scales, especially in the presence of water and hydrated ions, which may also be beneficial for computation, exploring next generation photocatalysts, electronics or ionotronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06226v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reehab Jahangir (Department of Chemistry and Centre for Processable Electronics - Imperial College London - UK, National Physical Laboratory - Teddington - UK), Filip Podjaski (Department of Chemistry and Centre for Processable Electronics - Imperial College London - UK), Paransa Alimard (Department of Chemistry and Centre for Processable Electronics - Imperial College London - UK), Sam A. J. Hillman (Department of Chemistry and Centre for Processable Electronics - Imperial College London - UK), Stuart Davidson (National Physical Laboratory - Teddington - UK), Stefan Stoica (National Physical Laboratory - Teddington - UK), Andreas Kafizas (Department of Chemistry and Centre for Processable Electronics - Imperial College London - UK), Mira Naftaly (National Physical Laboratory - Teddington - UK), James R. Durrant (Department of Chemistry and Centre for Processable Electronics - Imperial College London - UK)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-range depinning in the presence of velocity-weakening</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06732v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Phenomena including friction and earthquakes are complicated by the joint presence of disorder and non-linear instabilites, such as those triggered by the presence of velocity weakening. In [de Geus and Wyart, Phys. Rev. E 106, 065001 (2022)], we provided a theory for the nucleation of flow and the magnitude of hysteresis, building on recent results on disorder-free systems described by so called rate-and-state descriptions of the frictional interface, and treating disorder perturbatively. This theory was tested for models of frictional interfaces, where long range elastic interactions are present. Here we test it for short-range depinning, and confirm that (i) nucleation is triggered by avalanches, governed by a critical point at some threshold force $f_c$ close to the minimum of the flow curve and that (ii) due to an armouring mechanism by which the elastic manifold displays very little plasticity after a big slip event, very slowly decaying finite size effects dominate the hysteresis magnitude, with an exponent we can relate to other observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06732v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom W. J. de Geus, Matthieu Wyart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanism of the Nonequilibrium Phase Transition in Self-Propelled Particles with Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06818v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Self-propelled particles with alignment, displaying ordered collective motions such as swarming, can be investigated by the well-known Vicsek model. However, challenges still remain regarding the nature of the associated phase transition. Here, we use the landscape-flux approach combined with the coarse-grained mapping method to reveal the underlying mechanism of the continuous or discontinuous order-disorder nonequilibrium phase transition in Vicsek model systems featuring diverse noise characteristics. It is found that the nonequilibrium flux inside the landscape in the density-alignment degree phase space always rotates counterclockwise, and tends to delocalize or destabilize the point attractor states, providing the dynamical driving force for altering the landscape shape and the system state. Furthermore, the variations in the averaged flux and entropy production rate exhibit pronounced differences across various noise types. This not only helps to reveal the dynamical and thermodynamical mechanisms of the order-disorder transition but also offers a useful tool to recognize the continuity of the transition. Our findings present a novel perspective for exploring nonequilibrium phase transition behaviors and other collective motions in various complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06818v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruizhe Yan, Jie Su, Jin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cell bulging and extrusion in a three-dimensional bubbly vertex model for curved epithelial sheets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07141v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cell extrusion is an essential mechanism for controlling cell density in epithelial tissues. Another essential element of epithelia is curvature, which is required to achieve complex shapes, like in the lung or intestine. Here we introduce a three-dimensional bubbly vertex model to study the interplay between extrusion and curvature. We find a generic cellular bulging instability at topological defects which is much stronger than for standard vertex models. To clarify the underlying mechanism, we analytically calculate the energy landscape for a single bulging cell in a mean field tissue. We find that extrusion is energetically preferred at topological defects due to a redistribution of Gaussian curvature into the defect. We show that it can be driven both by a decrease in apico-basal tension or by contractile line tensions. We also show that extrusion can be suppressed by luminal pressure and interfacial bending rigidity, allowing for additional control of this important process. Our theory suggests that epithelial curvature naturally leads to cell bulging and extrusion because the interfacial curvature of individual cells at the defects strongly amplifies buckling effected by tissue-scale topological defects in elastic sheets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07141v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver M. Drozdowski (Heidelberg University, Germany), Ulrich S. Schwarz (Heidelberg University, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inertial active matter with Coulomb friction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Friction is central to the motion of active (self-propelled) objects such as bacteria, animals, and robots. While in a viscous fluid friction is described by Stokes's law, objects in contact with other solid bodies are often governed by more complex empirical friction laws. Here, we study active particles subject to Coulomb friction using a combination of active granular experiments and simulations, supported by theoretical predictions. The interplay of friction and activity forces induces a rich behavior resulting in three distinct dynamical regimes. While for low activity, Brownian motion is recovered, for large activity we observe a dynamical Stop &amp; Go regime that continuously switches from diffusion and accelerated motion. For greater activity, we observe a super-mobile dynamical regime characterized by a fully accelerated motion which is described by an anomalous scaling of the diffusion coefficient with the activity. These findings cannot be observed with Stokes viscous forces typical of active swimmers but are central in dry active objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06615v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.198301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 198301 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander P. Antonov, Lorenzo Caprini, Anton Ldov, Christian Scholz, Hartmut L\"owen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drying of Soft Colloidal Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08821v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Thin films made of deformable micro- and nano-units, such as biological membranes, polymer interfaces, and particle-laden liquid surfaces, exhibit a complex behavior during drying, with consequences for various applications like wound healing, coating technologies, and additive manufacturing. Studying the drying dynamics and structural changes of soft colloidal films thus holds the potential to yield valuable insights to achieve improvements for applications. In this study, we employ interfacial monolayers of core-shell microgels with varying degrees of softness as model systems and investigate their drying behavior on differently modified solid substrates (hydrophobic vs. hydrophilic). By leveraging on video microscopy, particle tracking, and thin film interference, we shed light on the interplay between microgel adhesion to solid surfaces and the immersion capillary forces that arise in the thin liquid film. We discovered that a dried replica of the interfacial microstructure can be more accurately achieved on a hydrophobic substrate relative to a hydrophilic one, particularly when employing softer colloids as opposed to harder counterparts. These observations are qualitatively supported by experiments with a thin film pressure balance which allows mimicking and controlling the drying process and by computer simulations with coarse-grained models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08821v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/advs.202406977</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Sci. 2024, 2406977</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Keumkyung Kuk, Julian Ringling, Kevin Gr\"aff, Sebastian H\"ansch, Virginia Carrasco-Fadanelli, Andrey A. Rudov, Igor I. Potemkin, Regine von Klitzing, Ivo Buttinoni, Matthias Karg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effects of fibre spatial distribution and relative orientation on the percolation and mechanics of stochastic fibre networks: A model of peptide hydrogels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03894v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The structures of fibre networks can vary greatly due to fibre interactions during formation. We have modified the steps of generating Mikado networks to create two new model classes by altering the spatial distribution and relative orientation of their fibres to mimic the structures of self-assembling peptide hydrogels (SAPHs), whose physical properties depend strongly on their fibres' interactions. The results of our models and experiments on a set of beta-sheet forming SAPHs show that modifying a network's structure affects the percolation threshold and the mechanical behaviour of the material, both near percolation and at higher densities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03894v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Hossein Namdar, Nastaran Zoghi, Aline Miller, Alberto Saiani, Tom Shearer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Damage due to Ice Crystallization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04670v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The freezing of water is one of the major causes of mechanical damage in materials during wintertime; surprisingly this happens even in situations where water only partially saturates the material so that the ice has room to grow. Here we perform freezing experiments in cylindrical glass vials of various sizes and wettability properties, using a dye that exclusively colors the liquid phase; this allows to precisely observe the freezing front. The visualization reveals that damage occurs in partially water-saturated media when a closed liquid inclusion forms within the ice due to the freezing of air/water meniscus. When this water inclusion subsequently freezes, the volume expansion leads to very high pressures leading to the fracture of both the surrounding ice and the glass vial. The pressure can be understood quantitatively based on thermodynamics which correctly predicts that the crystallization pressure is independent of the volume of the liquid pocket. Finally, our results also reveal that by changing the wetting properties of the confining walls, the formation of the liquid pockets that cause the mechanical damage can be avoided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04670v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Menno Demmenie, Paul Kolpakov, Boaz van Casteren, Dirk Bakker, Daniel Bonn, Noushine Shahidzadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk aversion can promote cooperation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05971v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cooperative dynamics are central to our understanding of many phenomena in living and complex systems. However, we lack a universal mechanism to explain the emergence of cooperation. We present a novel framework for modelling social dilemma games with an arbitrary number of players by combining reaction networks, methods from quantum mechanics applied to stochastic complex systems, game theory and stochastic simulations of molecular reactions. Using this framework, we propose a novel and robust mechanism for cooperation based on risk aversion that leads to cooperative behaviour in population games. Rather than individuals seeking to maximise payouts in the long run, individuals seek to obtain a minimum set of resources with a given level of confidence and in a limited time span. We show that this mechanism can lead to the emergence of new equilibria in a range of social dilemma games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05971v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jay Armas, Wout Merbis, Janusz Meylahn, Soroush Rafiee Rad, Mauricio J. del Razo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Dynamics from Multicellular Graphs with Deep Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12196v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multicellular self-assembly into functional structures is a dynamic process that is critical in the development and diseases, including embryo development, organ formation, tumor invasion, and others. Being able to infer collective cell migratory dynamics from their static configuration is valuable for both understanding and predicting these complex processes. However, the identification of structural features that can indicate multicellular motion has been difficult, and existing metrics largely rely on physical instincts. Here we show that using a graph neural network (GNN), the motion of multicellular collectives can be inferred from a static snapshot of cell positions, in both experimental and synthetic datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12196v3</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PRXLife.2.043010</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Haiqian Yang, Florian Meyer, Shaoxun Huang, Liu Yang, Cristiana Lungu, Monilola A. Olayioye, Markus J. Buehler, Ming Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second Law of Thermodynamics without Einstein Relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17142v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Materials that are constantly driven out of thermodynamic equilibrium, such as active and living systems, typically violate the Einstein relation. This may arise from active contributions to particle fluctuations which are unrelated to the dissipative resistance of the surrounding medium. We show that in these cases the widely used relation between informatic entropy production and heat dissipation does not hold. Consequently, fluctuation relations for the mechanical work, such as the Jarzynski and Crooks theorems, are invalid. We relate the breaking of the correspondence between entropy production and heat dissipation to departure from the fluctuation-dissipation theorem. We propose a temperaturelike variable that restores this correspondence and gives rise to a generalized second law of thermodynamics, whereby the dissipated heat is necessarily non-negative and vanishes at equilibrium. The Clausius inequality, Carnot maximum efficiency theorem, and relation between the extractable work and the change of free energy are recovered as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17142v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Sorkin, Haim Diamant, Gil Ariel, Tomer Markovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
