<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 01:51:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The influence of active agent motility on SIRS epidemiological dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active Brownian disks moving in two dimensions that exchange information about their internal state stochastically are chosen to model epidemic spread in a self-propelled population of agents under the susceptible-infected-recovered-susceptible (SIRS) framework. The state of infection of an agent, or disk, governs its self-propulsion speed; consequently, the activity of the agents in the system varies in time. Two different protocols (one-to-one and one-to-many) are considered for the transmission of disease from the infected to susceptible populations. The effectiveness of the two protocols are practically identical at high values of the infection transmission rate. The one-to-many protocol, however, outperforms the one-to-one protocol at lower values of the infection transmission rate. Salient features of the macroscopic SIRS model are revisited, and compared to predictions from the agent-based model. Lastly, the motility induced phase separation in a population of such agents with a fluctuating fraction of active disks is found to be well-described by theories governing phase separation in a mixture of active and passive particles with a constant fraction of passive disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01865v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Kailasham, Aditya S. Khair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant cluster formation in a simple model for globular colloidal aggregates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A simple model of fluid whose constituent particles interact via a short range attractive and long range repulsive potential is used to model the aggregation of giant clusters made up of hundreds of particles. The model can be thought of as a simplistic representation membraneless organelles or a straightforward rendition of colloid flocculation into large spherical aggregates. We illustrate how temperature and particle density influence the cluster size distribution and vary specially the inter-cluster dynamics. The system is shown to exhibit two well separated length and time scales, which can be tuned by the balance between repulsive and attractive forces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02091v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio D\'iaz-Pozuelo, Diego Gonz\'alez-Salgado, Enrique Lomba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timescale bridging in atomistic simulations of epoxy polymer mechanics using non-affine deformation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Developing a deep understanding of macroscopic mechanical properties of amorphous systems which lack structural periodicity, has posed a key challenge, not only at the level of theory but also in molecular simulations. Despite significant advancements in computational resources, there is a vast timescale disparity, more than 6 orders of magnitude, between mechanical properties probed in simulations compared to experiments. Using the theoretical framework of non-affine lattice dynamics (NALD), based on the instantaneous normal modes analysis determined through the dynamical matrix of the system, we study the viscoelastic response of a cross-linked epoxy system of diglycidyl ether of bisphenol A (DGEBA) and poly(oxypropylene) diamine, over many orders of magnitude in deformation frequency, below the glass transition temperature. Predictions of the elastic modulus are satisfactorily validated against the non-equilibrium molecular dynamics simulations in the high-frequency regime, and against experimental data from dynamic mechanical analysis at frequencies $ \sim 1 {\rm Hz}$, hence successfully bridging the timescale gap. The comparison shows that non-affine displacements at the atomic level account for nearly two orders of magnitude reduction in the low-frequency elastic modulus of the polymer glass, compared to affine elasticity estimates. The analysis also reveals the role of internal stresses (as reflected in the instantaneous normal modes), which act as to strengthen the mechanical response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02113v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinay Vaibhav, Timothy W. Sirk, Alessio Zaccone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normal Modes of Rouse-Ham Symmetric Star Polymer Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Rouse-Ham model is a simple yet useful dynamics model for an unentangled branched polymer. In this work, we study the normal modes of the Rouse-Ham type coarse-grained symmetric star polymer model. We model a star polymer by connecting multiple arm beads to a center bead by harmonic springs. In the Rouse-Ham model, the dynamics of the bead positions can be decomposed into the normal modes, which are chosen to be orthogonal to each other. Due to the existence of degenerate eigenvalues, the eigenmodes do not directly correspond to the normal modes. We propose several methods to construct the normal modes for the coarse-grained symmetric star polymer model. We show that we can construct the normal modes by using a simple permutation or the Hadamard matrix. These methods give symple and highly symmetric orthogonal modes, but work just for a special number of arms. We also show that we can construct the normal modes by using the discrete Fourier transform (DFT) matrix. This method is applicable for an arbitrary number of arms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02168v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Uneyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When does the elastic regime begin in viscoelastic pinch-off?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this experimental and numerical study, we revisit the question of the onset of the elastic regime in viscoelastic pinch-off. This is relevant for all modern filament thinning techniques which aim at measuring the extensional properties of low-viscosity polymer solutions such as the Slow Retraction Method (SRM) in Capillary Breakup Extensional Rheometry (CaBER) as well as the dripping method where a drop detaches from a nozzle. In these techniques, a stable liquid bridge is slowly brought to its stability threshold where capillary-driven thinning starts, slowing down dramatically at a critical radius $h_1$ marking the onset of the elastic regime where the bridge becomes a filament with elasto-capillary thinning dynamics. While a theoretical scaling for this transition radius exists for the classical step-strain CaBER protocol, where polymer chains stretch without relaxing during the fast plate separation, we show that it is not necessarily valid for a slow protocol such as in SRM since polymer chains only start stretching (beyond their equilibrium coiled configuration) when the bridge thinning rate becomes comparable to the inverse of their relaxation time. We derive a universal scaling for $h_1$ valid for both low and high-viscosity polymer solution which is validated by both CaBER (SRM) experiments with different polymer solutions, plate diameters and sample volumes and by numerical simulations using the FENE-P model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02303v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Gaillard, M. A. Herrada, A. Deblais, C. van Poelgeest, L. Laruelle, J. Eggers, D. Bonn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning dynamical models from stochastic trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamics of biological systems, from proteins to cells to organisms, is complex and stochastic. To decipher their physical laws, we need to bridge between experimental observations and theoretical modeling. Thanks to progress in microscopy and tracking, there is today an abundance of experimental trajectories reflecting these dynamical laws. Inferring physical models from noisy and imperfect experimental data, however, is challenging. Because there are no inference methods that are robust and efficient, model reconstruction from experimental trajectories is a bottleneck to data-driven biophysics. In this Thesis, I present a set of tools developed to bridge this gap and permit robust and universal inference of stochastic dynamical models from experimental trajectories. These methods are rooted in an information-theoretical framework that quantifies how much can be inferred from trajectories that are short, partial and noisy. They permit the efficient inference of dynamical models for overdamped and underdamped Langevin systems, as well as the inference of entropy production rates. I finally present early applications of these techniques, as well as future research directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02363v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Ronceray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct measurement of the viscocapillary lift force near a liquid interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02374v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lift force of viscous origin is widespread across disciplines, from mechanics to biology. Here, we present the first direct measurement of the lift force acting on a particle moving in a viscous fluid along the liquid interface that separates two liquids. The force arises from the coupling between the viscous flow induced by the particle motion and the capillary deformation of the interface. The measurements show that the lift force increases as the distance between the sphere and the interface decreases, reaching saturation at small distances. The experimental results are in good agreement with the model and numerical calculation developed within the framework of the soft lubrication theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02374v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Zhang, Zaicheng Zhang, Aditya Jha, Yacine Amarouchene, Thomas Salez, Thomas Gu\'erin, Chaouqi Misbah, Abdelhamid Maali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal limiting behaviour of reaction-diffusion systems with conservation laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Making sense of complex inhomogeneous systems composed of many interacting species is a grand challenge that pervades basically all natural sciences. Phase separation and pattern formation in reaction-diffusion systems have largely been studied as two separate paradigms. Here we show that in reaction-diffusion systems composed of many species, the presence of a conservation law constrains the evolution of the conserved quantity to be governed by a Cahn-Hilliard-like equation. This establishes a direct link with the paradigm of coexistence and recent "active" field theories. Hence, even for complex many-species systems a dramatically simplified but accurate description emerges over coarse spatio-temporal scales. Using the nullcline (the line of homogeneous steady states) as the central motif, we develop a geometrical framework through endowing chemical space with a basis and suitable coordinates. This framework allows us to capture and understand the effect of eliminating fast non-conserved degrees of freedom, and to explicitly construct coefficients of the coarse field theory. We expect that the theory we develop here will be particularly relevant to advance our understanding of biomolecular condensates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02409v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua F. Robinson, Thomas Machon, Thomas Speck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry, anomaly, topology, and transport in Weyl fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01667v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Weyl fermions are one of the simplest objects that link ideas in geometry and topology to highenergy physics and condensed matter physics. Although the existence of Weyl fermions as elementary particles remains dubious, there is mounting evidence of their existence as quasiparticles in certain condensed matter systems. Such systems are termed Weyl semimetals (WSMs). Needless to say, WSMs have emerged as a fascinating class of materials with unique electronic properties, offering a rich playground for both fundamental research and potential technological applications. This review examines recent advancements in understanding electron transport in Weyl semimetals (WSMs). We begin with a pedagogical introduction to the geometric and topological concepts critical to understanding quantum transport in Weyl fermions. We then explore chiral anomaly (CA), a defining feature of WSMs, and its impact on transport phenomena such as longitudinal magnetoconductance (LMC) and the planar Hall effect (PHE). The Maxwell-Boltzmann transport theory extended beyond the standard relaxation-time approximation is then discussed in the context of Weyl fermions, which is used to evaluate various transport properties. Attention is also given to the effects of strain-induced gauge fields and external magnetic fields in both time-reversal broken and inversion asymmetric inhomogeneous WSMs. The review synthesizes theoretical insights, experimental observations, and numerical simulations to provide a comprehensive understanding of the complex transport behaviors in WSMs, aiming to bridge the gap between theoretical predictions and experimental verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01667v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azaz Ahmad, Gautham Varma K., Gargee Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Thermodynamics of Micromagnetics with Spin Torque</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02220v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we study the stochastic dynamics of micro-magnetics interacting with a spin-current torque. We extend the previously constructed stochastic Landau-Lifshitz equation to the case with spin-current torque, and verify the conditions of detailed balance. Then we construct various thermodynamics quantities such as work and heat, and prove the second law of thermodynamics. Due to the existence of spin-torque and the asymmetry of the kinetic matrix, a novel effect of entropy pumping shows up. As a consequence, the system may behave as a heat engine which constantly transforms heat into magnetic work. Finally, we derive a fluctuation theorem for the joint probability density function of the pumped entropy and the total work, and verify it using numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02220v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingnan Ding, Jun Wu, Xiangjun Xing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of surfactants on droplet formation in piezoacoustic inkjet printing across microsecond-to-second timescales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02389v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In piezo acoustic drop-on-demand inkjet printing a single droplet is produced for each piezo driving pulse. This droplet is typically multicomponent, including surfactants to control the spreading and drying of the droplet on the substrate. However, the role of these surfactants on the droplet formation process remains rather elusive. Surfactant concentration gradients may manifest across microsecond-to-second timescales, spanning both the rapid ejection of ink from the nozzle exit and the comparatively slower idling timescale governing the firing of successive droplets. In the present work, we study the influence of surfactants on droplet formation across 6 orders of magnitude in time. To this end, we visualize the microsecond droplet formation process using stroboscopic laser-induced fluorescence microscopy while we vary the nozzle idle time. Our results show that increasing the idle time up to O(1) s affects only the break-up dynamics of the inkjet but not its velocity. By contrast, for idle times $&gt;$ O(1) s, both the break-up dynamics are altered and the velocity of the inkjet increases. We show that the increased velocity results from a decreased surface tension of the ejected droplet, which we extracted from the observed shape oscillations of the jetted droplets in flight. The measured decrease in surface tension is surprising as the $\mu$s timescale of droplet formation is much faster than the typical ms-to-s timescale of surfactant adsorption. By varying the bulk surfactant concentration, we show that the fast decrease in surface tension results from a local surfactant concentration increase to more than 200 times the CMC. Our results suggest that a local high concentration of surfactant allows for surfactant adsorption to the interface of an inkjet at the $\mu$s-to-ms timescale, which is much faster than the typical ms-to-s timescale of surfactant adsorption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02389v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maaike Rump, Christian Diddens, Uddalok Sen, Michel Versluis, Detlef Lohse, Tim Segers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrahigh Poisson's ratio glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.10993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.10993v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The manner in which metallic glasses fail under external loading is known to correlate well with those glasses' Poisson's ratio $\nu$: low-$\nu$ (compressible) glasses typically feature brittle failure patterns with scarce plastic deformation, while high-$\nu$ (incompressible) glasses typically fail in a ductile manner, accompanied by a high degree of plastic deformation and extensive liquid-like flow. Since the technological utility of metallic glasses depends on their ductility, materials scientists have been concerned with fabricating high-$\nu$ glassy alloys. To shed light on the underlying micromechanical origin of high-$\nu$ metallic glasses, we employ computer simulations of a simple glass-forming model with a single tunable parameter that controls the interparticle-potential's stiffness. We show that the presented model gives rise to ultra high-$\nu$ glasses, reaching $\nu\!=\!0.45$ and thus exceeding the most incompressible laboratory metallic glass. We discuss the possible role of the so-called unjamming transition in controlling the elasticity of ultra high-$\nu$ glasses. To this aim, we show that our higher-$\nu$ computer glasses host relatively softer quasilocalized glassy excitations, and establish relations between their associated characteristic frequency, macroscopic elasticity, and mechanical disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.10993v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Materials 6, 065604 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Edan Lerner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microswimmers knead nematics into cholesterics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05262v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The hydrodynamic stresses created by active particles can destabilise orientational order present in the system. This is manifested, for example, by the appearance of a bend instability in active nematics or in quasi-2-dimensional living liquid crystals consisting of swimming bacteria in thin nematic films. Using large-scale scale hydrodynamics simulations, we study a system consisting of spherical microswimmers within a 3-dimensional nematic liquid crystal. We observe a spontaneous chiral symmetry breaking, where the uniform nematic state is kneaded into a continously twisting state, corresponding to a helical director configuration akin to a cholesteric liquid crystal. The transition arises from the hydrodynamic coupling between the liquid crystalline elasticity and the swimmer flow fields, leading to a twist-bend instability of the nematic order. It is observed for both pusher (extensile) and puller (contractile) swimmers. Further, we show that the liquid crystal director and particle trajectories are connected: in the cholesteric state the particle trajectories become helicoidal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05262v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.238301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 238301 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bhavesh Gautam, Juho Lintuvuori</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
