<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 04:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Brownian motion of droplets induced by thermal noise"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We simulate phase separated fluids using the Cahn-Hillard fluctuating hydrodynamic (CH-FHD) model and measure the statistical properties of capillary waves generated by thermal fluctuations. Our measurements are in good agreement with stochastic lubrication theory and molecular dynamics simulations but differ significantly from recent CH-FHD results by Zhang et al. (Phys. Rev. E 109 024208 (2024)). Specifically, we find that capillary wave statistics at thermodynamic equilibrium are independent of transport properties, namely viscosity and species diffusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01444v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. B. Bell, A. Nonaka, A. L. Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approach and rotation of reconnecting topological defect lines in liquid crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological defects are a universal concept across many disciplines, such as crystallography, liquid-crystalline physics, low-temperature physics, cosmology, and even biology. In nematic liquid crystals, topological defects called disclinations have been widely studied. For their three-dimensional (3D) dynamics, however, only recently have theoretical approaches dealing with fully 3D configurations been reported. Further, recent experiments have observed 3D disclination line reconnections, a phenomenon characteristic of defect line dynamics, but detailed discussions were limited to the case of approximately parallel defects. In this study, we focus on the case of two disclination lines that approach at finite angles and lie in separate planes, a more fundamentally 3D reconnection configuration. Observation and analysis showed the square-root law of the distance between disclinations and the decrease of the inter-disclination angle over time. We compare the experimental results with theory and find qualitative agreement on the scaling of distance and angle with time, but quantitative disagreement on distance and angle relative mobilities. To probe this disagreement, we derive the equations of motion for systems with reduced twist constant and also carry out simulations for this case. These, together with the experimental results, suggest that deformations of disclinations may be responsible for the disagreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01480v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yohei Zushi, Cody D. Schimming, Kazumasa A. Takeuchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rugged potential of mean force and underscreening of polarizable colloids in concentrated electrolytes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study uses advanced numerical methods to estimate the mean force potential (PMF) between charged, polarizable colloidal particles in dense electrolytes. We observe that when the Debye screening length, $\lambda_{\mathrm{D}}$, is below the hydrated ion size, the PMF shows discernible oscillations, contrasting with the expected decay in DLVO theory. Our findings provide evidence for the existence of anomalous underscreening in electrostatically stabilized suspensions, potentially having significant implications for our understanding of colloidal stability and the forces that govern the behavior of concentrated charged soft matter systems beyond DLVO theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01512v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Krucker-Velasquez, Martin Z. Bazant, Alfredo Alexander-Katz, James W. Swan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drop impact on wet granular beds: water-content effects on the cratering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Drop impact events on wet granular bed show rich variety by changing the substrate composition. We observe the drop impact onto dry/wet granular substrates with different grain size (50-400 {\mu}m) and water content (0-22 vol %). Although the impactor condition is fixed (impact velocity: 4.0 m/s, water drop radius: 1.8 mm), the experiment reveals that the post-impact behaviors of both impactor and target are strongly affected by the substrate composition. We sort these behaviors into several phases regarding liquid splashing and crater shapes left after the event. As these phases show relevance each other, we measure the mechanical characteristics of the substrates and find that the onset of splashing and particle ejection are explained by a fracture of the substrate. Furthermore, we discuss several timescales of the event to understand more detailed phase separations. Consequently, we find that the splashing phase and the crater shape are determined by a competition of the timescales of impact, penetration, and contact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01631v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Zhang, Hiroaki Katsuragi, Ken Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equilibrium and Non-Equilibrium Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Thermo-Osmosis: Enhanced Effects on Polarized Graphene Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thermo-osmotic flows, generated by applying a thermal gradient along a liquid-solid interface, could be harnessed to convert waste heat into electricity. While this phenomenon has been known for almost a century, there is a crucial need to gain a better understanding of the molecular origins of thermo-osmosis. In this paper, we start by detailing the multiple contributions to thermo-osmosis. We then showcase three approaches to compute the thermo-osmotic coefficient using molecular dynamics; a first method based on the computation of the interfacial enthalpy excess and Derjaguin's theoretical framework, a second approach based on the computation of the interfacial entropy excess using the so-called dry-surface method, and a novel non-equilibrium method to compute the thermo-osmotic coefficient in a periodic channel. We show that the three methods align with each other, in particular for smooth surfaces. In addition, for a polarized graphene-water interface, we observe large variations of thermo-osmotic responses, and multiple changes in flow direction with increasing surface charge. Overall, this study showcases the versatility of osmotic flows and calls for experimental investigation of thermo-osmotic behavior in the vicinity of charged surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01708v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehdi Ouadfel (ILM), Samy Merabia (ILM), Yasutaka Yamaguchi (ILM), Laurent Joly (ILM)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation and time series analysis of responsive active Brownian particles (rABPs) with memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To realise the goals of active matter at the micro- and nano-scale, the next generation of microrobots must be capable of autonomously sensing and responding to their environment to carry out pre-programmed tasks. Memory effects are proposed to have a significant effect on the dynamics of responsive robotic systems, drawing parallels to strategies used in nature across all length-scales. Inspired by the integral feedback control mechanism by which E.coli are proposed to sense their environment, we develop a numerical responsive active Brownian particle (rABP) model in which the rABPs continuously react to changes in the physical parameters dictated by their local environment. The resulting generated time series are then used to classify and characterise their response, leading to the identification of conditional heteroscedasticity in their physics. We then train recurrent neural networks (RNNs) capable of quantitatively describing the responsiveness of rABPs using their 2-D trajectories. We believe that our proposed strategy to determine the parameters governing the dynamics of rABPs can be applied to guide the design of microrobots with physical intelligence encoded during their fabrication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01944v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Bailey, Fabio Grillo, Lucio Isa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotropic to nematic transition in alcohol ferrofluids of barium hexaferrite nanoplatelets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alcohol ferrofluids made of ferrimagnetic barium hexaferrite (BHF) nanoplatelets (NPLs) form a unique example of a dipolar fluid - a liquid magnet. Its formation is induced at a high enough concentration of the NPLs. The key interactions between the NPLs are long-ranged dipolar magnetic and screened anisotropic electrostatic. Herein, we report the results on tuning the isotropic-nematic phase transition (i.e., the NPLs threshold concentration) in 1-butanol ferrofluids of BHF NPLs by affecting the interactions in the ferrofluids. The threshold concentration was determined by polarizing optical microscopy (POM) combined with a system for magnetic field manipulation and was in the range between 4.6 and 6.6 \% (v/v) depending on the ferrofluid. We observed that the threshold concentration decreased for 0.6 \% (v/v) with a larger mean diameter of the NPLs, up to 0.6 \% (v/v) with increased ionic strength of the ferrofluid, and for $\sim$ 2 \% (v/v) with higher saturation magnetization of the NPLs. We showed that by tuning the parameters affecting the ferrofluid's interplatelet interactions, we can alter the threshold concentration for the liquid magnet formation. The results elucidate the importance of a delicate balance between the repulsive screened electrostatic and attractive dipolar magnetic interactions for the liquid magnet formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01956v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.molliq.2021.118038</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Molecular Liquids, 118038 (2021)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Patricija Hribar Bo\v{s}tjan\v{c}i\v{c}, \v{Z}iga Gregorin, Nerea Sebasti\'an, Natan Osterman, Darja Lisjak, Alenka Mertelj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Granular aqueous suspensions with controlled inter-particular friction and adhesion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a simple route to obtain large quantities of suspensions of non-Brownian particles with stimuli-responsive surface properties to study the relation between their flow and interparticle inter- actions. We perform an alkaline hydrolysis reaction on poly(methyl methacrylate) (PMMA) particles to obtain poly(sodium methacrylate) (PMAA-Na) particles. We characterize the quasi-static macro- scopic frictional response of their aqueous suspensions using a rotating drum. The suspensions are frictionless when the particles are dispersed in pure water. We relate this state to the presence of elec- trosteric repulsion between the charged surfaces of the ionized PMAA-Na particles in water. Then we add monovalent and multivalent ions (Na+, Ca2+, La3+) and we observe that the suspensions become frictional whatever the valency. For divalent and trivalent ions, the quasi-static avalanche angle {\theta}c at large ionic strength is greater than that of frictional PMMA particles in water, suggest- ing the presence of adhesion. Finally, a decrease in the pH of the suspending solution leads to a transition between a frictionless plateau and a frictional one. We perform Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM) to relate our macroscopic observations to the surface features of the particles. In particular, we show that the increase in friction in the presence of multivalent ions or under acidic conditions is driven by a nanoscopic phase separation and the bundling of polyelectrolyte chains at the surface of the particle. Our results highlight the importance of surface interactions in the rheology of gran- ular suspensions. Our particles provide a simple, yet flexible platform to study frictional suspension flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02071v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lily Blaiset, Bruno Bresson, Ludovic Olanier, \'Elisabeth Guazzelli, Matthieu Roch\'e, Nicolas Sanson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow Of Information In a Mechanically Quenched Confined Flock</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01942v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Living entities in a group communicate and transfer information to one another for a variety of reasons. It might be for foraging food, migration, or escaping threats and obstacles, etc. They do so by interacting with each other and also with the environment. The tools from statistical mechanics and information theory can be useful to analyze the flow of information among the living entities modelled as active (i.e. self-propelling) particles. Here we consider the active particles confined in a circular trap. The self-organisation of the particles crucially depends on whether the trap boundary is soft or hard. We quench the trap boundary from soft to hard instantaneously. After the mechanical quench, the particles suddenly find themselves in a hard potential. The self-organised cluster of the active particles, which was stable when the boundary was soft, becomes unstable. The cluster undergoes extreme deformation after the quench to find another stable configuration suitable for the hard potential. Together with the structural relaxation, information regarding the quench also flows throughout the deforming cluster. Here, we quantify the flow of information by computing local transfer entropy. We find that the flow spans the whole cluster, propagating ballistically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01942v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md. Samsuzzaman, Mohammad Hasanuzzaman, Ahmed Sayeed, Arnab Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric Fields Near Undulating Dielectric Membranes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00570v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dielectric interfaces are crucial to the behavior of charged membranes, from graphene to synthetic and biological lipid bilayers. Understanding electrolyte behavior near these interfaces remains a challenge, especially in the case of rough dielectric surfaces. A lack of analytical solutions consigns this problem to numerical treatments. We report an analytic method for determining electrostatic potentials near curved dielectric membranes in a two-dimensional periodic 'slab' geometry using a periodic summation of Green's functions. This method is amenable to simulating arbitrary groups of charges near surfaces with two-dimensional deformations. We concentrate on one-dimensional undulations. We show that increasing membrane undulation increases the asymmetry of interfacial charge distributions due to preferential ionic repulsion from troughs. In the limit of thick membranes we recover results mimicking those for electrolytes near a single interface. Our work demonstrates that rough surfaces generate charge patterns in electrolytes of charged molecules or mixed-valence ions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00570v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0185570</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 160, 094704 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Pogharian, Alexandre P. dos Santos, Ali Ehlen, Monica Olvera de la Cruz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Janus microswimmers are poor hydrodynamic mixers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03022v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The generation of fluid flows by autophoretic microswimmers has been proposed as a mechanism to enhance mass transport and mixing at the micro- and nanoscale. Here, we experimentally investigate the ability of model 2-D "active baths" of photocatalytic silica-titania Janus microspheres to enhance the diffusivity of tracer particles at different microswimmer densities below the onset of collective behaviour. Inspired by the similarities between our experimental findings and previous results for biological microorganisms, we then model our Janus microswimmers using a general squirmer framework, specifically treating them as neutral squirmers. The numerical simulations faithfully capture our observations, offer an insight into the microscopic mechanism underpinning tracer transport, and allow us to expand the parameter space beyond our experimental system. We find strong evidence that near-field interactions dominate enhancements in tracer diffusivity in active Janus baths, leading to the identification of an operating window for enhanced tracer transport by chemical microswimmers based on scaling arguments. Based on this argumentation, we suggest that for many chemically active colloidal systems, hydrodynamics alone is likely to be insufficient to induce appreciable mixing of passive components with large diffusion coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03022v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Bailey, Dmitry Fedosov, Federico Paratore, Fabio Grillo, Gerhard Gompper, Lucio Isa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk condensation by an active interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18329v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present experiments, supported by mechanically detailed simulations, establishing bulk vapor-liquid condensation of a hard-bead fluid by a tiny population of orientable motile grains that self-assembles into a moving polarized monolayer. In a quasi-1D geometry two such layers, oppositely aligned, immobilize the condensed non-motile component. We account for our observations through a continuum theory with a naturally non-reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard structure, whose predicted trends as a function of packing fraction are consistent with our observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18329v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raushan Kant, Rahul Kumar Gupta, Harsh Soni, A K Sood, Sriram Ramaswamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capillary adhesion of stick insects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11173v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Scientific progress within the last few decades has revealed the functional morphology of an insect's sticky footpads -- a soft, sponge-like pad that secretes a thin liquid film. However, the physico-chemical mechanisms underlying their adhesion remain elusive. Here, we explore these underlying mechanisms by simultaneously measuring adhesive force and contact geometry of the adhesive footpads of live, tethered Indian stick insects, \textit{Carausius morosus}, spanning more than two orders of magnitude in body mass. We find that the adhesive force we measure is similar to previous measurements that use a centrifuge. Our measurements afford use the opportunity to directly probe the adhesive stress \textit{in vivo}, and use existing theory on capillary adhesion to predict the surface tension of the secreted liquid and compare it to previous assumptions. From our predictions, we find that the surface tension required to generate the adhesive stresses we observed ranges between 0.68 mN/m and 12 mN/m. The low surface tension of the liquid would enhance the wetting of the stick insect's footpads and promote their ability to conform to various substrates. Our insights may inform the biomimetic design of capillary-based, reversible adhesives and motivate future studies on the capillary properties of the secreted liquid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11173v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo J. Amador, Brett Klaassen van Oorschot, Uddalok Sen, Benjamin Karman, Rutger Leenders</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of inertial particles under velocity resetting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12685v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate stochastic resetting in coupled systems involving two degrees of freedom, where only one variable is reset. The resetting variable, which we think of as hidden, indirectly affects the remaining observable variable through correlations. We derive the Fourier-Laplace transform of the observable variable's propagator and provide a recursive relation for all the moments, facilitating a comprehensive examination of the process. We apply this framework to inertial transport processes where we observe particle position while the velocity is hidden and is being reset at a constant rate. We show that velocity resetting results in a linearly growing spatial mean squared displacement at late times, independently of reset-free dynamics, due to resetting-induced tempering of velocity correlations. General expressions for the effective diffusion and drift coefficients are derived as function of resetting rate. Non-trivial dependence on the rate may appear due to multiple timescales and crossovers in the reset-free dynamics. An extension that incorporates refractory periods after each reset is considered, where the post-resetting pauses can lead to anomalous diffusive behavior. Our results are of relevance to a wide range of systems, including inertial transport where mechanical momentum is lost in collisions with the environment, or the behavior of living organisms where stop-and-go locomotion with inertia is ubiquitous. Numerical simulations for underdamped Brownian motion and the random acceleration process confirm our findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12685v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristian St{\o}levik Olsen, Hartmut L\"owen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
