<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 04:01:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pull-off strength of mushroom-shaped fibrils adhered to rigid substrates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The exceptional adhesion properties of biological fibrillar structures -- such as those found in geckos -- have inspired the development of synthetic adhesive surfaces. Among these, mushroom-shaped fibrils have demonstrated superior pull-off strength compared to other geometries. In this study, we employ a computational approach based on a Dugdale cohesive zone model to analyze the detachment behavior of these fibrils when adhered to a rigid substrate. The results provide complete pull-off curves, revealing that the separation process is inherently unstable under load control, regardless of whether detachment initiates at the fibril edge or center. Our findings show that fibrils with a wide, thin mushroom cap effectively reduce stress concentrations and promote central detachment, leading to enhanced adhesion. However, detachment from the center is not observed in all geometries, whereas edge detachment can occur under certain conditions in all cases. Additionally, we investigate the impact of adhesion defects at the fibril center, showing that they can significantly reduce pull-off strength, particularly at high values of the dimensionless parameter \c{hi}. These insights contribute to the optimization of bio-inspired adhesives and microstructured surfaces for various engineering applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20745v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Beteg\'on, C. Rodr\'iguez, E. Mart\'inez-Pa\~neda, R. M. McMeeking</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From the dynamic to the static glass transition via hypersonic measurements using Brillouin spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the fragile, low-molecular-weight liquid diglycidyl ether of bisphenol A (DGEBA), we report on the dynamic glass transition and a further acoustic anomaly in the vicinity of the thermal glass transition based on hypersonic investigations of the longitudinal elastic modulus using Brillouin spectroscopy. This additional acoustic anomaly of the longitudinally polarized phonon is confirmed by the occurrence of an anomaly of the shear phonon at the same thermal glass transition temperature. Analysis of the generalized Cauchy relation suggests that both anomalies are coupled to a glass transition phenomenon independent of the so-called {\alpha}-relaxation process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20808v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan-Kristian Kr\"uger, Rafael J. Jim\'enez Riob\'oo, Bernd Wetzel, Andreas Klingler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confusion-driven machine learning of structural phases of a flexible, magnetic Stockmayer polymer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use a semi-supervised, neural-network based machine learning technique, the confusion method, to investigate structural transitions in magnetic polymers, which we model as chains of magnetic colloidal nanoparticles characterized by dipole-dipole and Lennard-Jones interactions. As input for the neural network we use the particle positions and magnetic dipole moments of equilibrium polymer configurations, which we generate via replica-exchange Wang--Landau simulations. We demonstrate that by measuring the classification accuracy of neural networks, we can effectively identify transition points between multiple structural phases without any prior knowledge of their existence or location. We corroborate our findings by investigating relevant, conventional order parameters. Our study furthermore examines previously unexplored low-temperature regions of the phase diagram, where we find new structural transitions between highly ordered helicoidal polymer configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20899v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jctc.5c00381</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dilina Perera, Samuel McAllister, Joan Josep Cerd\`a, Thomas Vogel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field-induced clustering in nanocomposite films of highly polarizable inclusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20903v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A nanocomposite film containing highly polarizable inclusions in a fluid background is explored when an external electric field is applied perpendicular to the planar film. For small electric fields, the induced dipole moments of the inclusions are all polarized in field direction, resulting in a mutual repulsion between the inclusions. Here we show that this becomes qualitatively different for high fields: the total system self-organizes into a state which contains both polarizations, parallel and antiparallel to the external field such that a fraction of the inclusions is counter-polarized to the electric field direction. We attribute this unexpected counter-polarization to the presence of neighboring dipoles which are highly polarized and locally revert the direction of the total electric field. Since dipoles with opposite moments are attractive, the system shows a wealth of novel equilibrium structures for varied inclusion density and electric field strength. These include fluids and solids with homogeneous polarizations as well as equilibrium clusters and demixed states with two different polarization signatures. Based on computer simulations of a linearized polarization model, our results can guide the control of nanocomposites for various applications, including sensing external fields, directing light within plasmonic materials, and controlling the functionality of biological membranes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20903v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jcis.2024.04.134</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Colloid and Interface Science 668 (2024) 587-598</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Elshad Allahyarov, Hartmut L\"owen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling active nematics via the nematic locking principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20996v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active nematic systems consist of rod-like internally driven subunits that interact with one another to form large-scale coherent flows. They are important examples of far-from-equilibrium fluids, which exhibit a wealth of nonlinear behavior. This includes active turbulence, in which topological defects braid around one another in a chaotic fashion. One of the most studied examples of active nematics is a dense two-dimensional layer of microtubules, crosslinked by kinesin molecular motors that inject extensile deformations into the fluid. Though numerous studies have modeled microtubule-based active nematics, no consensus has emerged on how to fully capture the features of the experimental system. To better understand the foundations for modeling this system, we propose a fundamental principle we call the nematic locking principle: individual microtubules cannot rotate without all neighboring microtubules also rotating. Physically, this is justified by the high density of the microtubules, their elongated nature, and their corresponding steric interactions. We assert that nematic locking holds throughout the majority of the material but breaks down in the neighborhood of topological defects and other regions of low density. We derive the most general nematic transport equation consistent with this principle and also derive the most general term that violates it. We examine the standard Beris-Edwards approach used to model this system and show that it violates nematic locking throughout the majority of the material. We then propose a modification to the Beris-Edwards model that enforces nematic locking nearly everywhere. This modification shuts off fracturing except in regions where the order parameter is reduced. The resulting simulations show strong nematic locking throughout the bulk of the material, consistent with experimental observation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20996v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin A. Mitchell, Md Mainul Hasan Sabbir, Sean Ricarte, Brandon Klein, Daniel A. Beller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microphase Separation Controls the Dynamics of Associative Vitrimers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21066v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vitrimers are a class of polymers characterized by dynamic covalent networks, where specific monomer units, which are know as stickers, form reversible crosslinks that enable network rearrangement without loss of overall connectivity. The conventional wisdom is that the sticker dynamics control chain relaxation behavior, and hence the mechanical properties of associative vitrimers where the number of crosslinked sticker pairs is precisely constant over time. Instead, here we show that the chemical differences between sticker groups and nonsticky chain monomers can cause them to microphase separate. Under these conditions, the slow exchange of a sticker from one microphase to an adjacent one controls relaxation behavior. Controlling sticker aggregation is thus a key to tailoring the properties of these polymers with immediate relevance to a circular polymer economy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21066v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Karmakar, Abhishek S. Chankapure, Srikanth Sastry, Sanat K. Kumar, Tarak K. Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of Morphology Evolution in a Polymer-Clay Nanocomposite using Multiscale Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular simulations provide an effective route for investigating morphology evolution and structure-property relationship in polymer-clay nanocomposites (PCNCs) incorporating layered silicates like montmorillonite (MMT), an important class of materials that show a significant enhancement over the constituent polymer for several properties. However, long relaxation times and large system size requirements limit the application to systems of practical interest. In this work, we have developed a coarse-grained (CG) model of organically modified MMT (oMMT) compatible with the MARTINI force field, a chemically-specific interaction model with high transferability. The dispersive and polar components of cleavage energy, basal spacing, and mechanical properties of MMT with tetramethylammonium (TMA) as intergallery ions were used to obtain a rational estimate for clay particle MARTINI bead types in accordance with the polarity of the functional group. The CG model provided accurate concurrent estimates for the structural, thermodynamic, and dynamical properties of PE in a PE/TMA-MMT PCNC, with less than 4% deviation from all atom (AA) simulations. The slow clay-induced redistribution of the PE-b-PEG block copolymer in the PCNCs was investigated using the developed CG model, with conformational changes occurring over a microsecond timescale. The preferential interaction coefficient and cluster analysis of individual blocks of PE-b-PEG were used to study the effect of clay arrangement (exfoliated versus tactoid) on copolymer reorientation and assembly at the clay surface. We find that the oMMT coated with PE-b-PEG acts as a neutral surface (small difference in polymer-polymer and polymer-oMMT+PE-b-PEG enthalpic interactions) and the primary influence of the nanofiller is a result of confinement and steric effect of the clay sheets on the PE chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21339v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parvez Khana, Ankit Patidara, Gaurav Goel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical Calculation of Viscosity in Rouse Networks Below Gelation Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work establishes an exact relationship between the zero-shear viscosity and the radius of gyration for generalized Rouse model with arbitrary network configurations. Building on this fundamental relationship, we develop a random graph approach to derive analytical expressions for network viscosity in mean-field connected systems through coarse-grained graph viscosity relations. The theory fully characterizes the subcritical regime, determining precise asymptotic behavior in both dilute and pre-gelation limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21399v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bohan Lyu, Jie Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystallization of metallic glass as a grain-boundary nucleated process: experimental and theoretical evidence for the grain structure of metallic glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21261v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Experimental DSC and Avrami curves for the crystallization of metallic glasses demonstrate nucleation at grain boundaries and thus indicate their grain structure, which refutes the generally accepted idea of glass as a homogeneous frozen liquid obtained as a result of avoiding crystallization. Under certain conditions, this nucleation mechanism results in the appearance of two-peak DSC curves and three-step Avrami plots which are observed experimentally. To clarify these conditions, isothermal and non-isothermal surface-nucleated crystallization of a spherical particle is considered within the framework of a simple analytical model of nucleation and growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21261v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolay V. Alekseechkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular motion at the experimental glass transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel strategy to study numerically the glass transition of molecular fluids. Our approach combines the construction of simple yet realistic models with the development of Monte Carlo algorithms to accelerate equilibration and sampling. Inspired by the well-studied ortho-terphenyl glass-former, we construct a molecular model with an analogous triangular geometry and construct a `flip' Monte Carlo algorithm. We demonstrate that the flip Monte Carlo algorithm achieves a sampling speedup of about $10^9$ at the experimental glass transition temperature $T_g$. This allows us to systematically analyze the equilibrium structure and molecular dynamics of the model over a temperature regime previously inaccessible. We carefully compare the observed physical behavior to earlier studies that used atomistic models. In particular, we find that the glass fragility and the departure from the Stokes-Einstein relation are much closer to experimental observations. We characterize the development and temperature evolution of spatial correlations in the relaxation dynamics, using both orientational and translational degrees of freedom. Excess wings emerge at intermediate frequencies in dynamic rotational spectra, and we directly visualize the corresponding molecular motion near $T_g$. Our approach can be generalized to a number of molecular geometries and paves the way to a complete understanding of how molecular details may affect more universal physical aspects characterizing molecular liquids approaching their glass transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21290v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romain Simon, Jean-Louis Barrat, Ludovic Berthier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interradical motion can push magnetosensing precision towards quantum limits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21389v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetosensitive spin-correlated radical-pairs (SCRPs) offer a promising platform for noise-robust quantum metrology. However, unavoidable interradical interactions, such as electron-electron dipolar and exchange couplings, alongside deleterious perturbations resulting from intrinsic radical motion, typically degrade their potential as magnetometers. In contrast to this, we show how structured molecular motion modulating interradical interactions in a live chemical sensor in cryptochrome can, in fact, increase sensitivity and, more so, push precision in estimating magnetic field directions closer to the quantum Cram\'{e}r-Rao bound, suggesting near-optimal metrological performance. Remarkably, this approach to optimality is amplified under environmental noise and persists with increasing complexity of the spin system, suggesting that perturbations inherent to such natural systems have enabled them to operate closer to the quantum limit to more effectively extract information from the weak geomagnetic field. This insight opens the possibility of channeling the underlying physical principles of motion-induced modulation of electron spin-spin interactions towards devising efficient handles over emerging molecular quantum information technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21389v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke D. Smith, Farhan T. Chowdhury, Jonas Glatthard, Daniel R. Kattnig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing the Hyperuniformity of Disordered Network Metamaterials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22013v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Advancements in materials design and manufacturing have allowed for the production of ordered and disordered metamaterials with diverse and novel properties. Hyperuniform two-phase heterogeneous materials, which anomalously suppress density fluctuations on large length scales compared to typical disordered systems, and network materials are two classes of metamaterial that have desirable physical properties. Recent focus has been placed on the design of disordered hyperuniform network metamaterials that inherit the desirable properties of both of these metamaterial classes. In this work, we focus on determining the extent to which network structures derived from the spatial tessellations of hyperuniform point patterns inherit the hyperuniformity of the progenitor point patterns. In particular, we examine the Delaunay, Voronoi, Delaunay-Centroidal, and Gabriel tessellations of nonhyperuniform and hyperuniform point patterns in two- and three-dimensional Euclidean space. We use the spectral density to characterize the density fluctuations of two-phase media created by thickening the edges of these tessellations in two dimensions and introduce a novel variance-based metric to characterize the network structures directly in two and three dimensions. We find that, while none of the tessellations completely inherit the hyperuniformity of the progenitor point pattern, the degree to which the hyperuniformity is inherited is sensitive to the tessellation scheme and the short- and long-range translational disorder in the point pattern, but not to the choice of beam shape when mapping the networks into two-phase media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22013v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/l5hk-kwyn</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 111, 065420 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Charles Emmett Maher, Katherine A. Newhall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the influence of electrolytic gradient orientation on phoretic transport in dead-end pores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04380v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electrolytic diffusiophoresis refers to directional migration of colloids due to interfacial forces that develop in response to local electrolytic concentration ($c$) gradients. This physicochemical transport provides an efficient alternative in numerous microscale applications where advection-induced transport is infeasible. Phoretic withdrawal and injection in dead-end pores can be controlled by orienting salt gradients into or out of the pore; however, the extent to which this orientation influences spatiotemporal transport patterns is not thoroughly explored. In this study, we find that it has a significant influence: colloidal withdrawal in solute-out mode ($\beta=c_\infty/c_{\text{pore}}&lt;1$) is faster and shallower, whereas the solute-in mode enables deeper withdrawal. Similarly, solute-out injection features rapidly propagating wavefronts, whereas the solute-in mode ($\beta &gt;1$) promotes uniform and gradual injection. Each mode's transport is found to evolve and persist over different time scales. We characterize the performance of these modes and find that while persistence of the solute-out mode strengthens with a growing electrolytic gradient [$\sim \ln(\beta^{-0.4})$], solute-in mode diminishes and eventually its persistence is insensitive to $\beta$. We also incorporate the variable mobility model to examine the impact of large zeta potentials, which intensifies the transport of solute-out mode further and weakens the solute-in mode. Additionally, we investigate how osmotic flows of the two modes affect injection and withdrawal patterns. We find that osmosis-induced mixing can counterintuitively inhibit injection effectiveness in solute-out mode. These insights bring attention to the distinctions between different phoretic transport modes and contribute to the rational design and setup of electrolytic gradients in numerous microscale applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04380v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kushagra Tiwari, Jitendra Dhakar, Kapil Upadhyaya, Akash Choudhary</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
