<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 01:25:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A New Approach to the Glass Transition of Percolated Polymers from the Perspective of Thermal Volume Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1995, the Nobel Price winner P.W. Anderson made the following remarkable statement: The deepest and most interesting unsolved problem in solid state theory is probably the theory of the nature of glass and glass transition. Although there have been new theoretical developments in the meantime, in our opinion, this situation has only improved marginally to date. One of the main reasons is the insufficient consideration of experimental boundary conditions. A central experimental problem arises from the fact that the time constants required to achieve thermodynamic equilibrium increase sharply in the vicinity of and above a hypothetical static glass transition. If these equilibrium conditions are violated, additional internal thermodynamic variables come into play that normally alter the static and dynamic susceptibilities significantly and thus lead to misinterpretations of the experimental data. This raises, for example, the question of whether there are static property changes during the canonical glass transition and how these correlate with dynamic precursors. In this article, we attempt to find answers to these questions using a new experimental method called temperature-modulated optical refractometry in combination with the temperature-jump technique. The total time required to investigate the glass transition behaviour of our model epoxy was approximately two years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03174v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan-Kristian Kr\"uger, Bernd Wetzel, Andreas Klingler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Review on Phenomenological Models for Chromonic Liquid Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chromonic liquid crystals (CLCs) are lyotropic materials which are attracting growing interest for their adaptability to living systems. A considerable body of works has been devoted to exploring their properties and applications. In this paper, I endeavour to review some of the contributions concerning their theoretical modelling, aimed at rationalizing experimental observations. The elastic theory of CLCs is not completely established. Their ground state in the 3D space, as revealed by a number of recent experiments, is quite different from that of ordinary nematic liquid crystals: it is twisted instead of uniform. The common explanation provided for this state within the classical Oseen-Frank elastic theory demands that one Ericksen's inequality is violated. Since such a violation would make the Oseen-Frank stored energy density unbounded below, the legitimacy of these theoretical treatments is threatened by a number of mathematical issues. To overcome these difficulties, a novel elastic theory has been proposed and tested for CLCs; it extends the classical Oseen-Frank energy by incorporating a quartic twist term. Another key characteristic of CLCs is that they exhibit broad biphasic regions, in which the nematic and isotropic phases coexist. Mathematical models inspired by experimental settings have been developed for CLC droplets in 2D. The contributions reviewed here address the morphogenesis of nuclei and topological defects during phase transitions, the topological shape transformations arising from the interplay of nematic elastic constants, and the prediction of shape bistability (yet to be observed) where tactoids and smooth-edged discoids can coexist in equilibrium. General methods have also been applied to experimental data to extract estimates of the isotropic surface tension at the nematic isotropic interface and the chromonics' planar anchoring strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03266v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Paparini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Material parameter influence on the expression of Solitary-Wave-Induced Surface Dilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03275v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate a method for predicting peak particle forces in a Solitary Wave (SW) wavefront within a randomly filled 3D granular channel. The SW in our simulation are driven by a sustained impact originating in the bumpy floor of the channel. We show that, when generated in this manner, forces in the driven SW wavefront within the 3D assembly follow the same power law scaling on material properties and impact velocity as in a 1D chain. A simple scaling of the 1D forces matches results from simulated impact tests we conduct using Soft Sphere Discrete Element method simulations. We then quantify the magnitude of Solitary Wave Induced Surface Dilation (SID) that occurs as a result of varied material properties and gravitational environments, giving an equation that can be used to predict the lofting depth (depth to which particles experience bulk density changes as a result of a laterally propagating SW wavefront). As predicted by our equation and confirmed with simulated results, SID is amplified as particle material properties become closer to lunar regolith grains, supporting the hypothesis that SID is the Lunar Cold Spot formation mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03275v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10035-024-01460-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Granular Matter 26.4 (2024): 90</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eric Frizzell, Christine Hartzell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying many-body contributions to depletion forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective interactions inherently encompass many-body effects that appear unified. Analyzing these in reverse, that is, separating them into contributions from pairs, triples, or larger groups, is typically intricate and seldom pursued. However, this could offer essential insights into the structural architecture of complex systems, such as soft materials. This contribution tackles this issue employing a new simulation-based approach to accurately determine effective interactions. The approach is sufficiently sensitive to assess the effects of higher-order terms in the depletion potentials between large particles. Previous research has primarily focused on the role of small particles, and this work expands on these findings. However, understanding the contributions of large particles on the effective forces, particularly beyond the dilute limit, remains challenging and is not yet fully grasped, leading us to primarily focus on exploring this topic. Within the range of particle concentrations examined here, while maintaining a constant chemical potential for smaller particles, we have observed that the concentration of larger particles has no impact on the entropic potential between large colloids, as long as the size ratio remains below $q=0.15$. This confirms a long-established prediction founded on purely geometric considerations, which we have confirmed by means of direct observation. In contrast, for mixtures with less size asymmetry, such effects become considerably influential. Specifically, we have conducted an in-depth examination of scenarios with size asymmetries of $q=0.45$ and $0.60$. Our results for the depletion forces were directly compared with those obtained from the integral equation theory, which has also enabled us to improve and refine the approaches involved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03342v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel P\'erez-Angel, Marco A. Ram\'irez-Gu\'izar, N\'estor M. De Los Santos-L\'opez, Jos\'e M. M\'endez-Alcaraz, Ram\'on Casta\~neda-Priego</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variation-matching sensitivity-based virtual fields for hyperelastic material model calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate identification of nonlinear material parameters from three-dimensional full-field deformation data remains a challenge in experimental mechanics. The virtual fields method (VFM) provides a powerful, computationally efficient approach for material model calibration, however, its success depends critically on the choice of virtual fields and the informativeness of available kinematic data. In this work, we advance the state-of-the-art discrete formulation of the sensitivity-based virtual fields (SBVF) method by systematically developing and comparing alternative variational and analytical SBVFs within a strain-invariant-based modeling framework.
  A central contribution of this work is the implementation and assessment of variation-based SBVFs (vSBVFs), formulated using directional G\^ateaux derivatives, as well as virtual fields derived from analytical differentiation (aSBVFs) which provide explicit, model-tailored virtual displacement fields for parameter identification. Using simulated noisy volumetric datasets, we demonstrate that vSBVFs and aSBVFs enable procedural, automated construction of optimal virtual fields for each material parameter, substantially enhancing the robustness and efficiency of calibration without the need for manual field selection or high temporal resolution in the data acquisition. We quantify data richness -- the effective diversity of sampled kinematic states -- showing that increased data richness via sample geometry and loading protocols leads to improved parameter identifiability. These findings establish a pathway for automated, noise-robust material model calibration suitable for future deployment with experimental full-field imaging of soft, complex materials, and provide a foundation for optimizing shape topology and extending to viscoelastic and anisotropic behaviors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03363v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denislav P. Nikolov, Zhiren Zhu, Jonathan B. Estrada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control across scales: signals, information, and adaptive biological mechanical function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biological systems perform an astonishing array of dynamical processes -- including development and repair, regulation, behavior and motor control, sensing and signaling, and adaptation, among others. Powered by the transduction of stored energy resources, these behaviors enable biological systems to regulate functions, achieve specific outcomes, and maintain stability far from thermodynamic equilibrium. These behaviors span orders of magnitude in length and time: from nanometer-scale molecular motors driving morphogenesis to kilometer-scale seasonal migrations, and from millisecond reflexes to millennia of evolutionary adaptations. While physical laws govern the dynamics of biological systems, they alone are insufficient to fully explain how living systems sense, decide, adapt, and, ultimately, control their dynamics. In this article, we argue that control theory provides a powerful, unifying framework for understanding how biological systems regulate dynamics to maintain stability across length and time scales far from equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03418v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Clarke, Jake McGrath, Colin Johnson, Jos\'e Alvarado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirality, confinement and dimensionality govern re-entrant transitions in active matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The non-equilibrium dynamics of individual chiral active particles underpin the complex behavior of chiral active matter. Here we present an exact analytical framework, supported by simulations, to characterize the steady states of two-dimensional chiral active Brownian particles and three-dimensional torque-driven counterparts in a harmonic trap. Using a Laplace-transform approach of the Fokker-Planck equation, we derive closed-form expressions for displacement moments and excess kurtosis, providing a precise probe of non-Gaussian statistics. Our analysis reveals three distinct regimes: bimodal active states with off-center peaks, Gaussian-like passive states, and weakly heavy-tailed distributions unique to two dimensions. We show that dimensionality plays a decisive role: in two dimensions, increasing chirality suppresses activity and restores passive behavior, while in three dimensions torque preserves activity along the torque axis, producing anisotropic steady states. These behaviors are captured by simple active length-scale arguments that map the boundaries between passive and active phases. Our results offer concrete experimental signatures - including kurtosis crossovers, off-center peaks, and torque-induced anisotropy - that establish confinement as a powerful tool to probe and control chiral and torque-driven active matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03448v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anweshika Pattanayak, Amir Shee, Debasish Chaudhuri, Abhishek Chaudhuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rosette formations as symmetry-breaking events: theory and experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20543v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multicellular rosettes are observed in different situations such as morphogenesis, wound healing, and cancer progression. While some molecular insights have been gained to explain the presence of these assemblies of five or more cells around a common center, what are the tunable, global features that favors/hinders their formation is still largely unknown. Here, we made use of a Voronoi dynamical model to investigate the ingredients driving the emergence of rosettes characterized by different degree of stability and organization. We found that (i) breaking the local spatial symmetry of the system, i.e., introducing curvature-inducing defects, allows for the formation of rosette-like structures (ii) whose probability of formation depends on the characteristic of the cellular layer. In particular, a trade-off between tissue fluidity and single cell deformability dictates the assembly of transient rosettes, that are strongly stabilized in the presence of cell alignment interactions. To test our model predictions, we performed fluorescence microscopy experiments on rosette-forming neural populations derived from induced pluripotent stem cells, finding significant agreement. Overall, our work may set the stage to gain an unifying understanding of the plethora of biophysical mechanisms involving the occurrence of rosette-like structure both in physiology and their altered formation in pathology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20543v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Miotto, Giorgio Gosti, Maria Rosito, Michela Dell'Omo, Viola Folli, Valeria de Turris, Giancarlo Ruocco, Alessandro Rosa, Matteo Paoluzzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use of Physicochemical Modification Methods for Producing Traditional and Nanomodified Polymeric Composites with Improved Operational Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Various aspects of the methods of physical and physicochemical modification of components of filled thermoplastic composite materials are analyzed, aimed at improving the surface properties of the fillers and the technological properties of the polymer matrix during their interaction. It is noted that the improvement of the interfacial interaction of the components of polymer reactoplastic composites, including adhesive strength, is a key factor for improving the reliability of the cured filled composite. As a promising area of research, a modification of the surface of the reinforcing fibrous filler and the technological characteristics of the liquid polymer binder, aimed at increasing their contact properties in the composite, was chosen. The effectiveness of the physical method of modifying the components of composites in the form of low-frequency ultrasonic processing is described. The peculiarities of cluster formation and physicochemical modification of epoxy polymers filled with dispersed fillers are analyzed. Attention is focused on the effectiveness of ultrasonic processing in the cavitation mode for deagglomeration and uniform distribution of nanoparticles in a liquid medium during the creation of nanocomposites. Experimentally confirmed is the improvement of the technological properties of liquid epoxy polymers, modified by ultrasound, used for the impregnation of oriented fibrous fillers, as well as the improvement of the physicomechanical properties of the sonicated epoxy matrices. Some issues of biological modifications of components of polymers for functional application are briefly reviewed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02572v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1155/2019/1258727</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Polymer Science, Volume 2019, Article ID 1258727</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandr E. Kolosov, Volodymyr I. Sivetskii, Elena P. Kolosova, Volodymyr V. Vanin, Aleksandr V. Gondlyakh, Dmytro E. Sidorov, Igor I. Ivitskiy, Volodymyr P. Symoniuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Narwhals and their blessings: exact coherent structures of elastic turbulence in channel flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03175v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solutions of long, flexible polymer molecules are complex fluids that simultaneously exhibit fluid-like and solid-like behaviour. When subjected to external flows, dilute polymer solutions develop elastic turbulence - a unique chaotic flow state absent in Newtonian fluids such as water. Unlike turbulence in Newtonian fluids, elastic turbulence arises from polymer stretching and alignment in the flow, and can occur even at vanishing inertia. While experimental realisations of elastic turbulence are well documented, its underlying mechanism remains poorly understood.
  In this paper, we present a perspective on the transition to elastic turbulence in pressure-driven channel flows, drawing on recent computational work from our group. We outline our current understanding of the transition in both two and three spatial dimensions, centred on two key building blocks: (i) narwhals, exact coherent states of the flow, and (ii) blessings, spatio-temporal intermittent states made up of several localised narwhal solutions.
  This contribution is based on a talk given by one of us (A.M.) at the 2024 APS DFD meeting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03175v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Morozov, Martin Lellep, Damiano Capocci, Moritz Linkmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speeding up Brownian escape via intermediate finite potential barriers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03449v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The mean first-passage time (MFPT) for a Brownian particle to surmount a potential barrier of height $\Delta U$ is a fundamental quantity governing a wide array of physical and chemical processes. According to the Arrhenius Law, the MFPT typically grows exponentially with increasing barrier height, reflecting the rarity of thermally activated escape events. In this work, we demonstrate that the MFPT can be significantly reduced by reshaping the original single-barrier potential into a structured energy landscape comprising multiple intermediate barriers of lower heights, while keeping the total barrier height $\Delta U$ unchanged. Furthermore, this counterintuitive result holds across both linear and nonlinear potential profiles. Our findings suggest that tailoring the energy landscape -- by introducing well-placed intermediate barriers -- can serve as an effective control strategy to accelerate thermally activated transitions. These predictions are amenable to experimental validation using optical trapping techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03449v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishwajeet Kumar, Ohad Shpielberg, Arnab Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principled model selection for stochastic dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10339v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Complex dynamical systems, from macromolecules to ecosystems, are often modeled by stochastic differential equations. To learn such models from data, a common approach involves sparse selection among a large function library. However, we show that overfitting arises not just from individual model complexity, but also from the combinatorial growth of possible models. To address this, we introduce Parsimonious Stochastic Inference (PASTIS), a principled method combining likelihood-estimation statistics with extreme value theory to suppress superfluous parameters. PASTIS outperforms existing methods and reliably identifies minimal models, even with low sampling rates or measurement error. It extends to stochastic partial differential equations, and applies to ecological networks and reaction-diffusion dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10339v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andonis Gerardos, Pierre Ronceray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerically Discovered Inherent States are Always Protocol Dependent in Jammed Packings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09284v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The energy landscape for soft sphere packings exists in a high-dimensional space and plays host to an astronomical number of local minima in a hierarchical and ultrametric arrangement. Each point in the landscape is a configuration that can be unambiguously mapped to its inherent state, defined as the local minimum that the configuration will flow to under perfectly overdamped continuous dynamics. Typically, discrete in time dynamics are used to computationally find local minima, but it is not known whether these algorithms are capable of reliably finding inherent states. Here, we use steepest descent dynamics to find the distribution of the largest time step, $\delta_\textrm{best}$, which finds the inherent state. We find that for systems of $N$ particles, $\delta_\textrm{best}$ is approximately proportional to $N^{-3}$, and weakly dependent on d and $\varphi$. We argue that the proportionality is due to saddle points in the energy landscape. Our results suggest that it is impossible, in practice, to reliably find inherent states for systems of about 64 particles or more.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09284v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eddie Bautista, Eric I. Corwin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Percolation transition in entangled granular networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00216v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Highly nonconvex granular particles, such as staples and metal shavings, can form solid-like cohesive structures through geometric entanglement (interlocking). The network structure formed by this entanglement, however, remains largely unexplored. Here we utilize network science to investigate the entanglement networks of C-shaped granular particles under vibration through experiments and simulations. By analyzing key network properties, we demonstrate that these networks undergo a percolation transition as the number of links increases logarithmically over time; the entangled particles form a giant cluster when the number of links exceeds a critical threshold. We propose a continuum percolation model of rings that effectively describes the observed transition. Additionally, we find that particle's opening angle significantly affects mechanical bonding and, consequently, the network structure. This work highlights the potential of network-based approaches to study entangled materials, paving the way for advancements in applications ranging from mechanical metamaterials to entangled robot swarms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00216v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seongmin Kim, Daihui Wu, Yilong Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Equilibrium Dynamics of Hard Spheres in the Fluid, Crystalline, and Glassy Regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04599v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the response of a system of hard spheres to two classes of perturbations over a range of densities spanning the fluid, crystalline, and glassy regimes within a molecular dynamics framework. Firstly, we consider the relaxation of a "thermal inhomogeneity," in which a central region of particles is given a higher temperature than its surroundings and is then allowed to evolve under Newtonian dynamics. In this case, the hot central "core" of particles expands and collides with the cold surrounding material, creating a transient radially-expanding "compression wave," which is rapidly dissipated by particle-particle collisions and interaction with periodic images at the boundary, leading to a rapid relaxation to equilibrium. Secondly, we consider a rapid compression of the spheres into a disordered glassy state at high densities. Such rapidly compressed systems exhibit very slow structural relaxation times, many orders of magnitude longer than thermalization times for simple temperature inhomogeneities. We find that thermal relaxation of the velocity distribution is determined simply by the total collision rate, whereas structural relaxation requires coordinated collective motion, which is strongly suppressed at high density, although some particle rearrangement nevertheless occurs. We further find that collisions propagate significantly faster through glassy systems than through crystalline systems at the same density, which leads to very rapid relaxation of velocity perturbations, although structural relaxation remains very slow. These results extend the validity of previous observations that glassy systems exhibit a hybrid character, sharing features with both equilibrium and non-equilibrium systems. Finally, we introduce the hard sphere causal graph, a network-based characterization of the dynamical history of a hard sphere system, which encapsulates several useful...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04599v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/471m-qjvl</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 112, 034103 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Kafker, Xerxes D. Arsiwalla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RinQ: Towards predicting central sites in proteins on current quantum computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01501v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce RinQ, a hybrid quantum-classical framework for identifying functionally critical residues in proteins by formulating centrality detection as a Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problem. Protein structures are modeled as residue interaction networks (RINs), and the QUBO formulations are solved using D-Wave's simulated annealing. Applied to a diverse set of proteins, RinQ consistently identifies central residues that closely align with classical benchmarks, demonstrating both the accuracy and robustness of the approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01501v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shah Ishmam Mohtashim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
