<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 04:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Interfacial Cavitation with Surface Tension: New Insights into Failure of Particle Reinforced Polymers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding and mitigating the failure of reinforced elastomers has been a long-standing challenge in many industrial applications. In an early attempt to shed light on the fundamental mechanisms of failure, Gent and Park presented a systematic experimental study examining the field that develops near rigid beads that are embedded in the material and describe two distinct failure phenomena: cavitation that occurs near the bead in the bulk of the material, and debonding at the bead-rubber interface [Gent, A.N. and Park, B., 1984. Journal of Materials Science, 19, pp.1947-1956]. Although the interpretation of their results has not been challenged, several questions stemming from their work remain unresolved -- specifically, the reported dependence of the cavitation stress on the diameter of the bead and the counterintuitive relationship between the delamination threshold and the material stiffness. In this work, we revisit the work of Gent and Park and consider an alternative explanation of their observations, interfacial cavitation. A numerically validated semi-analytical model shows that in presence of surface tension, defects at the bead-rubber interface may be prone to cavitate at lower pressures compared to bulk cavitation, and that surface tension can explain the reported length-scale effects. A phase-map portrays the distinct regions of `cavitation dominated' and `delamination dominated' failure and confirms that for the expected range of material properties of the rubbers used by Gent and Park, interfacial cavitation is a likely explanation. Crucially, this result offers a new avenue to tune and optimize the performance of reinforced polymers and other multi-material systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15631v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanhe Li, Brendan Unikewicz, S. Chockalingam, Hudson Borja da Rocha, Tal Cohen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transient Chirality in the Gelation of Adhesive Spinner Monolayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active systems of self-rotating elements inherently exhibit chirality, making them of fundamental interest due to parity violation. Using large-scale hydrodynamic simulations, we investigate the gelation of adhesive spinners confined to quasi-2D monolayers at low Reynolds numbers. Unlike the coarsening dynamics of passive colloids, spinner gelation follows a different pathway, displaying structural chirality during the early stages of aggregation. However, this chirality dissipates upon dynamical arrest, resulting in a final gel structure that resembles a conventional colloidal gel. As a result, we find no sign of odd mechanical responses. Nonetheless, the elastic modulus and gelation time remain tunable through spinning activity, providing a new avenue for the bottom-up design of programmable soft materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15744v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujie Jiang, Yiting Liu, Haoran Li, Yang Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collecting Particles in Confined Spaces by Active Filamentous Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The potential of compliant and adaptable active matter for particle transport presents a promising avenue for the development of efficient, autonomous systems. However, achieving optimal task efficiency often depends on external control mechanisms, which can limit the autonomy of such systems. In this study, we draw inspiration from Tubifex tubifex and Lumbriculus variegatus, centimeter-sized worms that exhibit an extraordinary ability to aggregate dispersed particles within confined environments. By observing their natural behaviors, we identify a simple yet effective particle collection strategy driven by flexibility and activity. Using these biological insights, we develop larger-scale robotic systems and simulations that replicate the particle aggregation dynamics of living worms. Our results reveal that coupling between activity and flexibility governs the efficiency of particle clustering, and this principle applies universally across biological, robotic, and simulated filaments. These results allow us to offer new particle collection strategies by tuning the design elements like topology or bending stiffness of soft active filaments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15755v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Sinaasappel, K. R. Prathyusha, H. Tuazon, E. Mirzahossein, P. Illien, S. Bhamla, A. Deblais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic displacements and viscous hydrodynamic flows in wedge-shaped geometries featuring a straight edge: Green's functions for forces oriented parallel to the edge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For homogeneous and isotropic linearly elastic solids and for incompressible fluids under low-Reynolds-number conditions the fundamental solutions of the associated continuum equations were derived a long time ago for bulk systems. That is, the corresponding Green's functions are available in infinitely extended systems, where boundaries do not play any role. However, introducing boundaries renders the situation significantly more complex. Here, we derive the corresponding Green's functions for a linearly elastic homogeneous and isotropic material in a wedge-shaped geometry. Two flat boundaries confine the material and meet at a straight edge. No-slip and free-slip conditions are considered. The force is oriented in a direction parallel to the straight edge of the wedge. Assuming incompressibility, our expressions also apply to the situation of low-Reynolds-number hydrodynamic viscous fluid flows. Thus, they may be used, for instance, to describe the motion of self-propelled objects guided by an edge or the distortion of soft elastic actuators in wedge-shaped environments of operation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16116v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdallah Daddi-Moussa-Ider, Lukas Fischer, Marc Pradas, Andreas M. Menzel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring nonlinear ion dynamics in polymer electrolytes from the perspective of hopping models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Relevant information about the nature of the dynamics of ions in electrolytes can be obtained by studying the nonlinear dependence on an applied electric field. Here we use molecular dynamics (MD) simulations to study the field effects for a polymer electrolyte, i.e. a mixture of PEO with Li-TFSI salt, for a range of different temperatures and salt contents. Specifically, the effects of the electric field on the current and the diffusivities parallel and orthogonal to the electric fields are analyzed. It is argued that the nonlinear effects in the weak-field regime provide information about the nature of the disorder. In contrast, the nonlinear effects in the high-field regime allow one to extract effective hopping distances. They are in close agreement with typical nearest-neighbor length scales obtained from detailed structural analysis and are hardly dependent on the salt content. Furthermore, from the study of the temperature dependence in the high-field regime, effective barrier heights can be determined, which in this regime decrease linearly with increasing field. The disappearance of the effective barriers, estimated by linear extrapolation, occurs close to the fields where the MD simulations start to be numerically unstable. Finally, the interpretation is supported by a comparison with analytically known solutions of disordered hopping models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16136v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alina Wettstein, Diddo Diddens, Andreas Heuer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of the vortex line density in superfluids under thermal activation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study explores the development of the vortex line density in superfluids under thermal activation. This problem is of interest to both applied and fundamental research, and has been investigated by many authors in various aspects. Despite the important and impressive results obtained, a significant part of the process, namely the kinetics of processes leading to equilibrium state, remained unexplored. In this article, we conduct a study of kinetic phenomena and focus our attention on the evolution of the vortex line density (VLD) L(t), the total length of the filament per unit volume. The initial development of VLD is due to random thermal fluctuations. The increase in the vortex line length L(t) can be obtained based on the famous Novikov-Furutsu theorem, which shows that the growth rate of L(t) is proportional to a random force correlator. As the length of the vortex filaments increases, the interaction between the vortices becomes significant and affects the dynamics process. At this point, we turn to the phenomenological Feynman-Vinen theory, which offers various models for the evolution of the quantity L(t). Next we examine the evolution of a vortex tangle as a combination of growth due to random thermal excitations and decay in the Feynman-Vinen theory. Several applications leading to significant and remarkable results are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16190v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Nemirovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Negative specific heats: where Clausius and Boltzmann entropies separate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15999v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Steady nonequilibria dissipate energy and, when changing external parameters, an extra or excess heat accompanies the relaxation to the new nonequilibrium condition. For nonequilibrium systems in contact with a thermal bath, the heat capacity is defined as that excess heat per degree temperature for a quasistatic change of the bath temperature. It is fairly common to find negative heat capacities for steady nonequilibrium systems, in contrast with the situation for systems in thermal equilibrium. We discuss and illustrate the origin of that negative thermal response using Markov models. We find that the negativity results from an anticorrelation between quasipotential and (a change in) pseudopotential, the first measuring (excess) heat (and Clausius entropy), and the latter being related to the Boltzmann entropy. It can be quantified via an appropriate choice of effective temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15999v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lander Bogers, Faezeh Khodabandehlou, Christian Maes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous active and diffusive behaviour of asymmetric microclusters in a photophoretic trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16059v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Active and diffusive motion in Brownian particles are regularly observed in fluidic environments, albeit at different time scales. Here, we experimentally study the dynamics of highly asymmetric microclusters trapped in air employing photophoretic forces generated from a loosely focused laser beam, where the trapped particles display active and diffusive dynamics simultaneously in orthogonal spatial directions. Thus, particle motion in the longitudinal direction ($z$) is enslaved to irregular kicks that naturally arise from an interplay of gravitational and photophoretic forces. This leads to a bimodal nature of the probability distribution function with a near-ballistic scaling of mean-squared displacement in the $z$ direction demonstrating active like dynamics, while the dynamics along the transverse ($x$) direction displays diffusive behaviour with a strong dependence on the motion along $z$. To explain these unique characteristics, we developed a 2D-Langevin model of a confined elliptic particle experiencing an additional stochastic force along $z$ to account for the arbitrary jumps. The numerical results show excellent qualitative agreement with the experimental observations. Our findings should pave the way for the design of high-efficiency Brownian engines in air, besides stimulating new research in the emerging field of photophoretic trapping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16059v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anita Pahi, Kirty Ranjan Sahoo, Biswajit Das, Shuvojit Paul, Ayan Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrodynamic Interactions in Particle Suspensions: A Perspective on Stokesian Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16083v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stokesian Dynamics (SD) is a numerical framework used for simulating hydrodynamic interactions in particle suspensions at low Reynolds number. It combines far-field approximations with near-field lubrication corrections, offering a balance between accuracy and efficiency. This work reviews SD and provides a perspective on future directions for this approach. We outline the mathematical foundations, the method's strengths and weaknesses, and the computational challenges that need to be overcome to work with SD effectively. We also discuss recent advancements that improve the algorithm's efficiency, including the use of iterative solvers and matrix-free approaches. In addition, we highlight the limitations of making stronger, albeit more cost-effective approximations to studying hydrodynamic interactions in dense suspensions than made in SD, such as the two-body Rotne-Prager-Yamakawa (RPY) approximation. To overcome these issues, we propose a hybrid framework that replaces SD's full many-body computations with a neural network trained on SD data. That is, we correct the RPY approximation, while avoiding costly matrix inversions. We demonstrate the potential of this method on a simple system, where we find a close match to SD data while algorithmically outperforming RPY. Our work provides an outlook on the way in which large-scale simulations of particle suspensions can be performed in the foreseeable future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16083v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kim William Torre, Joost de Graaf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Fluctuating Hydrodynamics of the Scaled Light-Heavy Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16103v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the exact fluctuating hydrodynamics of the scaled Light-Heavy model (sLH), in which two species of particles (light and heavy) interact with a fluctuating surface. This model is similar in definition to the unscaled Light-Heavy model (uLH), except it uses rates scaled with the system size. The consequence, it turns out, is a phase diagram that differs from that of the unscaled model. We derive the fluctuating hydrodynamics for this model using an action formalism involving the construction of path integrals for the probability of different states that give the complete macroscopic picture starting from the microscopic one. This is then used to obtain the two-point steady-state (static) correlation functions between fluctuations in the two density fields in the homogeneous phase. We show that these theoretical results match well with microscopic simulations away from the critical line. We derive an exponentially decaying form for the two-point steady-state correlation function with a correlation length that diverges as the critical line is approached. Finally, we also compute the dynamic correlations in the homogeneous phase and use them to determine the relaxation dynamics as well as the dynamic exponents of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16103v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilpa Prakash, Mustansir Barma, Kabir Ramola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Theory for Critical Conditions of Like-Charge Attraction Between Polarizable Spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10516v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite extensive experimental and theoretical efforts, a concise quantitative theory to predict the occurrence of like-charge attraction (LCA) between polarizable spheres remains elusive. In this work, we first derive a novel three-point image formula, based on a key observation that connects the classical Neumann's image principle with the incomplete beta function. This approach naturally yields simple yet precise critical conditions for LCA, with a relative discrepancy of less than $1\%$ compared to numerical simulations, validated across diverse parameter settings. The obtained critical conditions may provide physical insights into various processes potentially involving LCA, such as self-assembly, crystallization, and phase separation across different length scales. Additionally, the new image formula is directly applicable to enhance the efficiency of polarizable force field calculations involving polarizable spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10516v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jctc.5c00144</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yanyu Duan, Zecheng Gan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
