<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 05:01:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bacterial dimensions sensitively regulate surface diffusivity and residence time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17477v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Run-and-tumble is a common but vital strategy that bacteria employ to explore environment suffused with boundaries, as well as to escape from entrapment. In this study we reveal how this strategy and the resulting dynamical behavior can be sensitively regulated by bacterial dimensions. Our results demonstrate that the logarithm of the surface residence time for bacteria with constant tumble bias is linearly related to a dimensionless parameter of bacterial intrinsic size characteristics, where a small variation in bacterial dimensions, which is natural in a suspension, reproduces well the experimentally observed large variation in bacterial residence time. Furthermore, our results predict that the optimal tumble bias corresponding to the maximum surface diffusivity depends strongly on bacterial dimensions, where the same small variation in bacterial dimensions gives rise to a strongly diversified optimal tumble bias and an order of magnitude change in surface diffusivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17477v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Premkumar Leishangthem, Xuan Wang, Junan Chen, Shengqi Yang, Xinliang Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-induced upward bending of a magnetoelastomer cantilever residing on a horizontal plane: an unconventional cilium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mechanical response of a cantilever made of a magnetoactive elastomer (MAE) that is positioned on a solid plane surface and is subjected to a uniform magnetic field is studied. The MAE is of the magnetically soft type, i.e., its filler particles become magnetized only in the presence of external field. Test observations with the applied field normal to the plane reveal two possible perturbed configurations of the cantilever: either its free end just bends upward or the cantilever folds into an arc, so that its free end does not detach from the supporting plane. The tests evidence that under cyclic variation of the field both deformation modes exhibit quite a wide bistability region, i.e., a magnetomechanical hysteresis takes place. Theoretical analysis shows that the cantilever bending scenario is indeed similar to that of the first-order transition. However, unlike the customary case, hereby the initial state never ceases to exist and remains stable against infinitesimal perturbations under arbitrary strong fields. Although this conclusion is valid only for an ideal situation, its nontrivial consequence is that the field value under which the transition to the bent state occurs is, in fact, unpredictable. The discovered effect is essentially different from the previously investigated behaviour of MAE cantilevers under an in-plane field; there the transition is of the second-order kind and is completely reversible. Finally, if to consider a horizontal MAE cantilever as an element of an assembly of magnetic cilia, it turns out that it behaves in the way opposite to that of conventional systems where in the initial state the MAE cilia stand normally to the supporting surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17580v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. V. Stolbov, G. V. Stepanov, Yu. L. Raikher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intermittent molecular motion and first passage statistics for the NMR relaxation of confined water</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The structure and dynamics of fluids confined in nanoporous media differ from those in bulk, which can be probed using NMR relaxation measurements. We here show, using atomistic molecular dynamics simulations of water in a slit nanopore, that the behavior of the NMR relaxation rate, R1, with varying surface interaction and confinement strength can be estimated from the exchange statistics of fluid molecules between the adsorbed surface layer and the bulk region, where molecules undergo intermittent dynamics. We employ first return passage time calculations to quantify the molecular exchange statistics, thereby linking microscopic parameters of the confined fluid-such as adsorption time, pore size, and diffusion coefficient-to the NMR relaxation rate. This approach allows to predict and interpret the molecular relaxation of fluids at interfaces using merely concepts of statistical mechanics and can be generalized to closed and open geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17596v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Gravelle, Benoit Coasne, Christian Holm, Alexander Schlaich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cell Deformation Signatures along the Apical-Basal Axis: A 3D Continuum Mechanics Shell Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17810v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) mechanical models of confluent tissues have related the mechanical state of a monolayer of cells to the average perimeter length of the cell cross sections, predicting floppiness or rigidity of the material. For the well-studied system of in-vitro MDCK epithelial cells, however, we find experimentally that cells in mechanically rigid tissues display long perimeters characteristic of a floppy state in 2D models. We suggest that this discrepancy is due to mechanical effects in the third (apical-basal) dimension, including those caused by actin stress fibers near the basal membrane. To quantitatively understand cell deformations in 3D, we develop a continuum mechanics model of epithelial cells as elastic cylindrical shells, with appropriate boundary conditions reflecting both the passive confinement of neighboring cells and the active stress of actomyosin contractility. This formalism yields analytical solutions predicting cell cross sections along the entire cylinder axis. Deconvolution microscopy experimental data confirm the significant and systematic change in cell shape parameters in this apical-basal direction. In addition to providing a wealth of detailed information on deformation on the subcellular scale, the results of the approach alter our understanding of how active tissues balance requirements of their stiffness and integrity, suggesting they are more robust against loss of rigidity than previously inferred.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17810v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jairo M. Rojas, Mayisha Z. Nakib, Vivian W. Tang, William M. Brieher, Sascha Hilgenfeldt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-organised dynamics and emergent shape spaces of active isotropic fluid surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17849v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Theories of self-organised active fluid surfaces have emerged as an important class of minimal models for the shape dynamics of biological membranes, cells and tissues. Here, we develop and apply a variational approach for active fluid surfaces to systematically study the nonlinear dynamics and emergent shape spaces such theories give rise to. To represent dynamic surfaces, we design an arbitrary Lagrangian-Eulerian parameterizations for deforming surfaces. Exploiting the symmetries imposed by Onsager relations, we construct a variational formulation that is based on the entropy production in active surfaces. The resulting dissipation functional is complemented by Lagrange multipliers to relax nonlinear geometric constraints, which allows for a direct computation of steady state solutions of surface shapes and flows. We apply this framework to study the dynamics of open fluid membranes and closed active fluid surfaces, and characterize the space of stationary solutions that corresponding surfaces and flows occupy. Our analysis rationalizes the interplay of first-order shape transitions of internally and externally forced fluid membranes, reveals degenerate regions in stationary shape spaces of mechanochemically active surfaces and identifies a mechanism by which hydrodynamic screening controls the geometry of active surfaces undergoing cell division-like shape transformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17849v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Da Gao, Huayang Sun, Rui Ma, Alexander Mietke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helical Ribbons: Simple Chiral Sedimentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18157v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the sedimentation of chiral particles in viscous fluid flow. We identify helical ribbons as simple particles with strong translation-rotation coupling whose symmetry ensures that the centers of mass, buoyancy, resistance, and mobility coincide. Experimental measurements of both relevant mobility tensors show excellent agreement with simulations of ribbons made of interacting spheres. We observe quasi-periodic angular dynamics causing complex spatial trajectories. In tilt-spin phase space, orbits are closed due to time-reversal and reflection symmetry. Changing the helical ribbon length reveals a bifurcation at which the stable sedimentation orientations switch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18157v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elias Huseby, Josephine Gissinger, Fabien Candelier, Nimish Pujara, Gautier Verhille, Bernhard Mehlig, Greg Voth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principled model selection for stochastic dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10339v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Complex dynamical systems, from macromolecules to ecosystems, are often modeled by stochastic differential equations. To learn such models from data, a common approach involves sparse selection among a large function library. However, we show that overfitting arises - not just from individual model complexity, but also from the combinatorial growth of possible models. To address this, we introduce Parsimonious Stochastic Inference (PASTIS), a principled method combining likelihood-estimation statistics with extreme value theory to suppress superfluous parameters. PASTIS outperforms existing methods and reliably identifies minimal models, even with low sampling rates or measurement error. It extends to stochastic partial differential equations, and applies to ecological networks and reaction-diffusion dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10339v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andonis Gerardos, Pierre Ronceray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal Contrastive Learning through implicit non-equilibrium memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17723v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The backpropagation method has enabled transformative uses of neural networks. Alternatively, for energy-based models, local learning methods involving only nearby neurons offer benefits in terms of decentralized training, and allow for the possibility of learning in computationally-constrained substrates. One class of local learning methods constrasts the desired, clamped behavior with spontaneous, free behavior. However, directly contrasting free and clamped behaviors requires explicit memory. Here, we introduce `Temporal Contrastive Learning', an approach that uses integral feedback in each learning degree of freedom to provide a simple form of implicit non-equilibrium memory. During training, free and clamped behaviors are shown in a sawtooth-like protocol over time. When combined with integral feedback dynamics, these alternating temporal protocols generate an implicit memory necessary for comparing free and clamped behaviors, broadening the range of physical and biological systems capable of contrastive learning. Finally, we show that non-equilibrium dissipation improves learning quality and determine a Landauer-like energy cost of contrastive learning through physical dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17723v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin J. Falk, Adam T. Strupp, Benjamin Scellier, Arvind Murugan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
