<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 05:01:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exact response functions for a compressible thin fluid layer with odd viscosity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fluids composed of chiral active components can exhibit odd viscosity, a property that breaks time-reversal and parity symmetries. We investigate the hydrodynamic response to monopole and dipole singularities in a compressible thin fluid layer with odd viscosity, supported by a conventional lubrication layer. Using the two-dimensional Green's function in Fourier space, we derive exact analytical solutions for the flow and pressure fields. These solutions provide a detailed description of the hydrodynamic interactions governing the motion of colloidal particles and microswimmers in confined chiral fluids, offering insight into the role of odd viscosity in modifying particle dynamics and collective behavior. The derived results are directly applicable to modeling transport, control, and self-organization phenomena in active and chiral microfluidic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18136v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdallah Daddi-Moussa-Ider, Yuto Hosaka, Shigeyuki Komura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of Liquid Crystalline Elastomer Foams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate how controlled foaming alters the mechanical dissipation of liquid crystalline elastomers (LCEs). Using thermal expandable microspheres, we generate homogeneous foams with precisely tuned bubble volume fractions up to 13% and compare their behaviour with non-mesogenic silicon analogues. We show that microsphere expansion induces a particle-centred mesogenic interphase arising from local elastic distortion and preferential alignment of mesogenic units at the inclusion surface. At low bubble volume fraction (0.5 to 5%), these interfaces remain spatially isolated and produce a pronounced no-monotonic enhancement of damping, with the loss factor reaching tan-delta=0.2 even in the isotropic regime. At higher loading, interphase overlaps and mechanical constraints suppress this effect, and the dissipation returns towards baseline elastomeric values. Large-strain tensile tests and impact experiments exhibit the same non-monotonic trend, demonstrating that low density LCE forms achieve the highest mechanical energy absorption per unit mass. Compared with conventional high porosity polymer foams used for acoustic damping, these materials retain sufficient mechanical integrity to sustain impact loads, establishing a microstructural route to engineer high-performance damping in soft solids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18228v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Dai, Andrew Terentjev, Eugene M. Terentjev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling Entropic, Active, and Frictional Forces in Cytoskeletal Crosslinking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The forces that mixtures of motorized and passive crosslinking proteins collectively generate between cytoskeletal filaments within our cells are the key drivers of active cellular mechanics. Despite their importance, a unified theory to describe such crosslinking forces has so far been missing. In this paper, we derive a theory that predicts the forces generated collectively by crosslinking proteins linking two biopolymer filaments from measurable filament and crosslinker properties, using out-of-equilibrium thermodynamics. Our framework allows us to decompose the forces generated by crosslinkers into three separate components: entropic, active, and frictional. In doing so, it offers a clear physical interpretation of the fundamental mechanisms by which crosslinking proteins self-organize and collectively generate forces. We demonstrate the robustness and utility of this framework by applying it to four different experiments that probe the combined roles of passive and motorized crosslinkers. For each experiment, our theoretical approach allows us to disentangle the relative contributions of entropic, active, and frictional forces, clarifying how different physical processes underpin collective force production. In turn, this makes it possible to quantitatively compare and predict how various crosslinker combinations influence force generation between filaments, pattern formation along filaments, and the dynamics of filament pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18342v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cedrik Barutel, Sebastian F\"urthauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise Determination of the Long-Time Asymptotics of the Diffusion Spreadability of Two-Phase Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The time-dependent diffusion spreadability $\mathcal{S}(t)$ is a powerful dynamical probe of the microstructure of two-phase heterogeneous media across length scales [Torquato, S., \emph{Phys. Rev. E.}, 104 054102 (2021)]. It has been shown that when the spectral density takes the power-law form $\tilde{\chi}_{_V}(\mathbf{k})\sim |\mathbf{k}|^\alpha$ as the wavenumber $|\mathbf{k}|$ tends to zero, the normalized excess spreadability $\mathscr{s}^{ex}(t)$ [proportional to $\mathcal{S}(\infty)-\mathcal{S}(t)$] scales as $\mathscr{s}^{ex}(t)\sim t^{-\frac{d+\alpha}{2}}$ in the long-time limit $t\to\infty$, enabling one to determine the infinite-wavelength scaling exponent $\alpha$. An algorithm that allows one to reliably extract the exponent $\alpha$ from long-time spreadability data was previously devised [Wang, H., Torquato, S., \emph{Phys. Rev. Appl.}, 17 034022 (2022)]. In this paper, we further improve this procedure to obtain $\alpha$ even more accurately by incorporating higher-order correction terms to the long-time asymptotics and by utilizing analyticity properties of $\tilde{\chi}_{_V}(k)$ at the origin. We illustrate our procedure by analyzing hyperuniform ($\alpha&gt; 0$), typical nonhyperuniform ($\alpha=0$), and antihyperuniform ($-d &lt; \alpha &lt;0$) models of two-phase media. In addition, by combining the large-$t$ asymptotic expansion of $\mathscr{s}^{ex}(t)$ with the small-$t$ expansion, we have devised a two-point Pad\'e approximant to approximate $\mathscr{s}^{ex}(t)$ for all $t$ with just a few parameters. Our findings facilitate the characterization of the microstructure of two-phase media across length scales as obtained from numerical spreadability data or experimental data obtained from NMR relaxation measurements. Our work can also be applied in the inverse design of two-phase microstructures with targeted spreadability behaviors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17873v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaobing Yuan, Salvatore Torquato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mobility based approach to transport in chiral fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18091v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chiral fluids, for which the mobility tensor has antisymmetric, off-diagonal components, exhibit transport phenomena absent in conventional systems, including interaction-enhanced diffusion and negative mobility. While these effects have been predicted theoretically and observed in simulations, their microscopic origin has remained unclear. Here, we address this question using a mobility-based nonequilibrium approach, analysing the steady-state drift of a tracer driven through an interacting chiral fluid. We show that, under strong chirality, the tracer generates a reversed density wake, in which regions of particle accumulation and depletion are inverted compared to the achiral case. This structural inversion of the wake provides a unified physical mechanism underlying both enhanced diffusion and negative mobility. Furthermore, we demonstrate that these phenomena are robust to changes in the interaction potential, highlighting their generality as a consequence of odd mobility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18091v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Faedi, Erik Kalz, Ralf Metzler, Abhinav Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ori-Sense: origami capacitive sensing for soft robotic applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18379v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work introduces Ori-Sense, a compliant capacitive sensor inspired by the inverted Kresling origami pattern. The device translates torsional deformation into measurable capacitance changes, enabling proprioceptive feedback for soft robotic systems. Using dissolvable-core molding, we fabricated a monolithic silicone structure with embedded conductive TPU electrodes, forming an integrated soft capacitor. Mechanical characterization revealed low stiffness and minimal impedance, with torque values below 0.01 N mm for axial displacements between -15 mm and 15 mm, and up to 0.03 N mm at 30 degrees twist under compression. Finite-element simulations confirmed localized stresses along fold lines and validated the measured torque-rotation response. Electrical tests showed consistent capacitance modulation up to 30%, directly correlated with the twist angle, and maximal sensitivity of S_theta ~ 0.0067 pF/deg at 5 mm of axial deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18379v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo de Souza Oliveira, Xin Li, Mohsen Jafarpour, Edoardo Milana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snapping Actuators with Asymmetric and Sequenced Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Snapping instabilities in soft structures offer a powerful pathway to achieve rapid and energy-efficient actuation. In this study, an eccentric dome-shaped snapping actuator is developed to generate controllable asymmetric motion through geometry-induced instability. Finite element simulations and experiments reveal consistent asymmetric deformation and the corresponding pressure characteristics. By coupling four snapping actuators in a pneumatic network, a compact quadrupedal robot achieves coordinated wavelike locomotion using only a single pressure input. The robot exhibits frequency-dependent performance with a maximum speed of 72.78~mm/s at 7.5~Hz. These findings demonstrate the potential of asymmetric snapping mechanisms for physically controlled actuation and lay the groundwork for fully untethered and efficient soft robotic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18421v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Li, Ye Jin, Mohsen Jafarpour, Hugo de Souza Oliveira, Edoardo Milana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Wound Closure in Living Nematic Epithelia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04922v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study theoretically the closure of a wound in a layer of epithelial cells in a living tissue after damage. Our analysis is informed by our recent experiments observing re-epithelialisation in vivo of Drosophila pupae. On time and length-scales such that the evolution of the epithelial tissue near the wound is well captured by that of a 2D active fluid with local nematic order, we consider the free-surface problem of a hole in a bounded region of tissue, and study the role that active stresses far from the hole play in the closure of the hole. For parallel anchored nematic order at the wound boundary (as we observe in our experiments), we find that closure is accelerated when the active stresses are contractile and slowed down when the stresses are extensile. Parallel anchoring also leads to the appearance of topological defects which annihilate upon wound closure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04922v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry Andralojc, Jake Turley, Helen Weavers, Paul Martin, Isaac V. Chenchiah, Rachel R. Bennett, Tanniemola B. Liverpool</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic turbulence in highly entangled polymers and wormlike micelles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07146v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show theoretically that an initially homogeneous planar Couette flow of a concentrated polymeric fluid is linearly unstable to the growth of two-dimensional (2D) perturbations, within two widely used constitutive models: the Johnson-Segalman model and the Rolie-Poly model. We perform direct nonlinear simulations of both models in 2D to show that this instability leads to a state of elastic turbulence comprising several narrow shear bands that dynamically coalesce, split and interact. Importantly, we show that this 2D instability arises not only in fluids that have a non-monotonic constitutive curve, and therefore show shear banding in 1D calculations, but also in shear thinning fluids with a monotonic constitutive curve, for which an initially homogeneous base state is stable in 1D. For the former category, the high shear branch of the constitutive curve is unstable to 2D instability in both models, so that the high shear band may be turbulent. In the Rolie-Poly model, the low shear branch is also likewise unstable. Our work provides the first simulation evidence for elastic turbulence in highly entangled polymeric fluids. It also potentially explains rheo-chaotic states seen experimentally in shear banding wormlike micelles. We additionally demonstrate elastic turbulence within both models in the planar Poiseuille geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07146v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/k1g3-283t</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Theo A. Lewy, Suzanne M. Fielding, Peter D. Olmsted, Rich R. Kerswell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Melting Coulomb clusters through nonreciprocity-enhanced parametric pumping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16074v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Complex systems out of equilibrium often experience intermittent oscillations between quiescent and highly dynamic states. The type of intermittency depends on how energy is pumped into the system, and how it is dissipated. While intermittency is usually driven by stochastic noise or external forcing, energy can also be sourced from field-mediated interactions between particles, which are often nonreciprocal and effectively violate Newton's 3rd law. Here we demonstrate how nonreciprocal interactions produce intermittency in clusters of charged micron-sized particles confined in a plasma sheath. Through three-dimensional particle tracking, we observe that vertical oscillations, induced by fluctuations of the plasma environment, can be parametrically coupled to the horizontal modes. Experiments and simulations show that nonreciprocal interactions strongly amplify this parametric coupling, creating a positive feedback loop that drives explosive growth of both the horizontal and vertical modes. This mechanism triggers abrupt melting transitions from an ordered cluster to an ergodic gas-like state, and leads to intermittent switching between states over long time scales. Overall, our work identifies nonreciprocal interactions as a key mechanism through which strongly coupled finite systems transform interaction-mediated activity into dynamical nonequilibrium states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16074v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhicheng Shu, Wei-Chih Li, Wentao Yu, Justin C. Burton</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
