<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.soft updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft</link>
    <description>cond-mat.soft updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.soft" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 05:01:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Small equatorial deformation of homogeneous spherical fluid vesicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the reaction of a homogeneous spherical fluid vesicle to the force exerted by a rigid circular ring located at its equator in the linear regime. We solve analytically the linearized first integral of the Euler-Lagrange equation subject to the global constraints of fixed area and volume, as well as to the local constraint imposed by the ring. We determine the first-order perturbations to the generating curve of the spherical membrane, which are characterized by the difference of the radii of the membrane and the ring, and by a parameter depending on the physical quantities of the membrane. We determine the total force that is required to begin the deformation of the membrane, which gives rise to a discontinuity in the curvature of the membrane across the ring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22622v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epje/s10189-025-00553-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. E 49, 7 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es Sol\'is-Cuevas, Pablo V\'azquez-Montejo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Toy Model for the Cycle Rank Dependence of Stretch at Break in Phantom Chain Network Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The relationship between the topological architecture of polymer networks and their macroscopic rupture remains a fundamental challenge in polymer physics. Recent coarse-grained simulations have revealed that the dependence of stretch at break (\lambda_b) on node functionality and reaction conversion can be unified into a universal master curve when plotted against the cycle rank density (\xi). However, a theoretical derivation explaining this universality has been lacking. This study proposes a simple mechanical model to describe the \xi-dependence of fracture strain. The polymer network is modeled as a mechanical system consisting of a sequence of springs representing localized highly stretched strands and the surrounding unstretched network. By relating the stiffness contrast between these regions to the network connectivity defined by \xi, an analytical expression for the stretch at break is derived: \lambda_b\propto\sfrac{\left(2\xi+5\right)}{\left(2\xi+1\right)}. The proposed model is validated against phantom chain simulations using both Gaussian and finite extensibility (FENE) springs. The theoretical prediction shows excellent agreement with simulation data, providing a physical basis for the phenomenological universality observed in polymer network rupture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22641v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuichi Masubuchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient dynamics model for chemically driven running drops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a thermodynamically consistent model for chemically driven running drops on a solid substrate with reversible substrate adsorption of a wettability-changing chemical species. We consider drops confined to a vertical gap, thereby allowing us to first obtain a gradient dynamics description of the closed system, corresponding to a set of coupled dynamical equations for the drop profile and the chemical concentration profiles of species on the substrate and in both fluids (drop, ambient medium). Chemostatting the species in the drop and the ambient medium, we then derive a reduced model for the dynamics of the drop and the adsorbate on the substrate. When the externally imposed chemical potentials are distinct, the system is driven away from thermodynamic equilibrium, allowing for sustained drop self-propulsion across the substrate due to a wettability contrast maintained by chemical reactions. We numerically study the resulting running drops and show how they emerge from drift-pitchfork bifurcations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22962v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justus Niehoff, Florian Voss, Uwe Thiele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial self-organization driven by temporal noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.23098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.23098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The counterintuitive emergence of order from noise is a central phenomenon in science, ranging from pattern formation and synchronization to order-by-disorder in frustrated systems. While large-scale spatial self-organization induced by local spatial noise is well studied, whether temporal noise can also drive such organization remains an open question. Here, by studying interacting particle systems, we show that temporally correlated noise can lead to a self-organized state with suppressed long-range density fluctuations, or hyperuniformity. Further, we develop a fluctuating hydrodynamic theory that quantitatively explains the origin of this phenomenon. Finally, by casting the dynamics as a stochastic optimization problem, we show that temporal correlations lead to better solutions, akin to perturbed gradient descent in neural networks -- where noise is injected during training to escape poor minima. This reveals a striking correspondence between perturbed gradient descent dynamics on the energy landscapes of particle systems and the loss landscapes of neural networks. Our study establishes temporal correlations as a novel mechanism for noise-driven self-organization, with broad implications for self-assembling materials, biological systems, and optimization algorithms that leverage temporal noise for applications like differentially private learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.23098v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satyam Anand, Guanming Zhang, Stefano Martiniani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical density functional theory for dense odd-diffusive fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.23284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.23284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Odd diffusion breaks time-reversal symmetry in overdamped systems through transverse probability currents while preserving equilibrium steady states. In this work, we develop a dynamical density functional theory (DDFT) for dense interacting odd-diffusive fluids and apply it to ultrasoft particles in two dimensions. In bulk, odd diffusion qualitatively reshapes collective relaxation by generating transient circulating current patterns which do not exist in normal fluids. Under harmonic ring confinement, the circulation of probability current induces an angular redistribution of density along the ring during relaxation. This unique footprint of odd diffusion opens up a shorter pathway to equilibrium. Repulsive interactions significantly enhance these effects. Excellent agreement with Brownian dynamics simulations confirms that our odd-DDFT framework quantitatively captures all essential nonequilibrium aspects of the nontrivial odd transport and collective redistribution for dense fluids in both bulk and confined geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.23284v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iman Abdoli, Ren\'e Wittmann, Hartmut L\"owen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resilient-to-Fragile Transition and Excess Volatility in Supply Chain Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20450v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the disequilibrium dynamics of a stylised model of production networks in which firms use perishable and non-substitutable intermediate inputs, so that adverse idiosyncratic productivity shocks can trigger downstream shortages and output losses. To protect against such disruptions, firms hold precautionary inventories that act as buffer stocks. We show that, for a given dispersion of firm-level productivity shocks, there exists a critical level of inventories above which the economy remains in a stable stochastic steady state. Below this critical level, the system becomes fragile, i.e., it becomes prone to system-wide crises. As this resilience-fragility boundary is approached from above, aggregate output volatility rises sharply and diverges, even though shocks are purely idiosyncratic. Because inventories are costly, competitive pressures induce firms to economize on buffers. Although we do not explicitly model such costs, we argue that the resulting behaviour of individual firms drives the system close to criticality, generating persistent excess macroeconomic volatility -- in other words, ``small shocks, large cycles'' -- in line with other settings where efficiency and resilience are in tension with each other. In the language of phase transitions, the resilient-to-fragile transition is continuous (supercritical): the economy exhibits a well-defined stochastic equilibrium with finite volatility on one side of the boundary, while beyond it the probability of a collapse in finite time tends to one. We characterize this transition primarily through numerical simulations and derive an analytical description in a high-perishability, high-connectivity limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20450v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Martin, Jos\'e Moran, Debabrata Panja, Jean-Philippe Bouchaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How adaptation to food resources and death rates shape oscillatory dynamics in a microbial population</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Microbes constantly interact with their environment by depleting and transforming food sources. Theoretical studies have mainly focused on Lotka-Volterra models, which do not account for food source dynamics. In contrast, consumer-resource models, which consider food source dynamics, are less explored. In particular, it is still unclear what physical mechanisms control oscillatory dynamics at a single population level, a phenomenon which can only be captured by a consumer-resource model. Here, we present a minimalistic consumer-resource model of a single microbial population with growth and death dynamics, consuming a continuously replenishing substrate. Our model reveals that decaying oscillations can occur around steady state if and only if the timescale of microbial adaptation to food supply changes exceeds the death timescale. This interplay of timescales allows us to rationalize the emergence of oscillatory dynamics when adding various biophysical ingredients to the model. We find that microbial necromass recycling or complementary use of multiple food sources reduces the parameter range for oscillations and increases the decay rate of oscillations. Requiring multiple simultaneous food sources has the opposite effect. Essentially, facilitating growth reduces the likelihood of oscillations around a fixed point. We further demonstrate that such damped oscillatory behavior is correlated with persistent oscillatory behavior in a noisy environment. We hope our work will motivate further investigations of consumer-resource models to improve descriptions of environments where food source distributions vary in space and time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22967v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedetta Ciarmoli, Sophie Marbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to flock in open space by avoiding collisions and staying together</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15587v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the emergence of cohesive flocking in open, boundless space using a multi-agent reinforcement learning framework. Agents integrate positional and orientational information from their closest topological neighbours and learn to balance alignment and attractive interactions by optimizing a local cost function that penalizes both excessive separation and close-range crowding. The resulting Vicsek-like dynamics is robust to algorithmic implementation details and yields cohesive collective motion with high polar order. The optimal policy is dominated by strong aligning interactions when agents are sufficiently close to their neighbours, and a flexible combination of alignment and attraction at larger separations. We further characterize the internal structure and dynamics of the resulting groups using liquid-state metrics and neighbour exchange rates, finding qualitative agreement with empirical observations in starling flocks. These results suggest that flocking may emerge in groups of moving agents as an adaptive response to the biological imperatives of staying together while avoiding collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15587v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martino Brambati, Antonio Celani, Marco Gherardi, Francesco Ginelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective permeability conditions for diffusive transport through impermeable membranes with gaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10694v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Membranes regulate transport in a wide variety of industrial and biological applications. The microscale geometry of the membrane can significantly affect overall transport through the membrane, but the precise nature of this multiscale coupling is not well characterised in general. Motivated by the application of transport across a bacterial membrane, in this paper we use formal multiscale analysis to derive explicit effective coupling conditions for macroscale transport across a two-dimensional impermeable membrane with periodically spaced gaps, and validate these with numerical simulations. We derive analytic expressions for effective macroscale quantities associated with the membrane, such as the permeability, in terms of the microscale geometry. Our results generalise the classic constitutive membrane coupling conditions to a wider range of membrane geometries and time-varying scenarios. Specifically, we demonstrate that if the exterior concentration varies in time, for membranes with long channels, the transport gains a memory property where the coupling conditions depend on the system history. By applying our effective conditions in the context of small molecule transport through gaps in bacterial membranes called porins, we predict that bacterial membrane permeability is primarily dominated by the thickness of the membrane. Furthermore, we predict how alterations to membrane microstructure, for example via changes to porin expression, might affect overall transport, including when external concentrations vary in time. These results will apply to a broad range of physical applications with similar membrane structures, from medical and industrial filtration to carbon capture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10694v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Molly Brennan, Edwina F. Yeo, Philip Pearce, Mohit P. Dalwadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A finite viscoelastic constitutive model for low to high strain rate response of elastomers with application of strain rate-induced glass transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05405v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Amorphous elastomers exhibit significant rate-stiffening and unique viscous flow characteristics across a wide range of strain rates, often undergoing glass transition above a strain rate threshold. We have developed a thermodynamically-consistent and micromechanically-inspired constitutive model for soft elastomeric materials to capture the rate-dependent stress-strain behavior and hysteresis when subjected to low to high strain rates. Our proposed constitutive model encapsulates the viscous flow of materials through molecular motion at low strain rates and local rearrangement and alignment at high strain rates, essentially covering the glass transition. We applied our constitutive model to uniaxial compression experiments performed at low and high strain rates for polyborosiloxane (PBS) to identify the material parameters, and subsequently, performed numerical simulations of single and multi-cycle compression, stress relaxation, and small amplitude oscillatory tension-compression. Our analyses indicate that the model predicts higher total energy dissipation with increasing strain rate; however, dissipation associated with molecular relaxation decreases (forming a cusp) because, beyond a crossover strain rate, molecular rearrangement and alignment become dominant, which is consistent with the onset of the glass transition. For cyclic loading-unloading, we observed that dissipation over a cycle remains constant at low strain rate but decreases non-monotonically at high strain rates before becoming constant with peak stress over the cycle becoming higher, which can be interpreted as more loading being carried elastically by the polymer network as the molecular rearrangement process occurs. Additionally, our model was able to predict the qualitative nature of the storage modulus and loss modulus in the limit of small strain over a wide range of frequency sweeps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05405v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bibekananda Datta, Sushan Nakarmi, Nitin P. Daphalapurkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clever algorithms for glasses work by time reparametrization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17121v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ultraslow dynamics of glass-formers has been explained by two views considered as mutually exclusive: one invokes locally hindered mobility, the other rests on the complexity of the configuration space. Here we demonstrate that the evolution responds strongly to the details of the dynamics by changing the speed of time-flow: it has time-reparametrization softness. This finding reconciles both views: while local constraints reparametrize the flow of time, the global landscape determines relationships between different correlations at the same times. We show that modern algorithms developed to accelerate the relaxation to equilibrium act by changing the time reparametrization. Their success thus relies on their ability to exploit reparametrization softness. We conjecture that these results extend beyond the realm of glasses to the optimization of more general constraint satisfaction problems and to broader classes of algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17121v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1073/pnas.2520818123</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci USA 123, e2520818123 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Federico Ghimenti, Ludovic Berthier, Jorge Kurchan, Fr\'ed\'eric van Wijland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural changes in the Lennard-Jones supercooled liquid and ideal glass: an improved integral equation for the replica method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.22548v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Framing the glass formation within standard statistical mechanics is an outstanding problem of condensed matter theory. To provide new insight, we investigate the structural properties of the Lennard-Jones fluid in the very-low temperature regime, by using a replicated version of the refined HMSA theory of the liquid state, combined with an appropriate split of the pair potential [Bomont and Bretonnet, J. Chem. Phys. 114, 4141 (2001)]. Our scheme allows one to reach an unprecedented low-temperature domain within both the supercooled liquid and the ideal-glass phase. Therein, a density-dependent temperature is identified, whereupon the radial distribution function experiences clear-cut structural changes, insofar as an additional peak develops in between the main and the second peaks. Such a structural feature points to a local structure of the Lennard-Jones ideal glass with an fcc-like short-range order, in the absence of any long-range order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.22548v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bomont Jean-Marc, Bretonnet Jean-Louis, Costa Dino, Pastore Giorgio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
