<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 05:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the negative coupling O(N) model in 2d at high temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, I consider N-component scalar quantum field theory in two dimensions interacting with an upside-down quartic potential. Working in the large N limit, the model can be solved non-perturbatively using the saddle-point method for sufficiently strong negative coupling. At high temperature, the O(N) model dimensionally reduces to ${\cal PT}$-symmetric quantum mechanics, for which powerful non-perturbative solution methods exist. It is found that the solution from quantum mechanics can be matched by the saddle-point method in quantum field theory when allowing for saddles beyond the principal Riemann sheet. I show that saddle points on non-principal Riemann sheets lead to a fully consistent solution of the 2d negative-coupling O(N) model for all temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10496v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Romatschke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$F$-extremization determines certain large-$N$ CFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10499v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the conformal data of a range of large-$N$ CFTs, the melonic CFTs, are specified by constrained extremization of the universal part of the sphere free energy $F=-\log Z_{S^d}$, called $\tilde{F}$. This family includes the generalized SYK models, the vector models (O$(N)$, Gross-Neveu, etc.), and the tensor field theories. The known $F$ and $a$-maximization procedures in SCFTs are therefore extended to these non-supersymmetric CFTs in continuous $d$. We establish our result using the two-particle irreducible (2PI) effective action, and, equivalently, by Feynman diagram resummation. $\tilde{F}$ interpolates in continuous dimension between the known $C$-functions, so we interpret this result as an extremization of the number of IR degrees of freedom, in the spirit of the generalized $c,F,a$-theorems. The outcome is a complete classification of the melonic CFTs: they are the conformal mean field theories which extremize the universal part of the sphere free energy, subject to an IR marginality condition on the interaction Lagrangian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10499v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludo Fraser-Taliente, John Wheater</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge-invariant charges of the dual graviton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10503v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The free graviton theory given by linearising Einstein's theory has a dual formulation in terms of a dual graviton field. The dual graviton theory has two gauge invariances giving rise to two conserved charges, while the ADM charges of the graviton theory become magnetic charges for the dual graviton theory. These charges can be ill-defined in topologically non-trivial settings and we find improvement terms that can be added to these to give gauge-invariant conserved charges. These gauge-invariant charges, which have local expressions in both the graviton and dual graviton formulation, give topological operators of the theory that should be considered as the generators of the genuine symmetries of the theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10503v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Hull, Ulf Lindstr\"om, Maxwell L. Vel\'asquez Cotini Hutt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How negative can null energy be in large N CFTs?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Smeared null energy has been shown to be bounded from below for free minimally coupled quantum field theories. This is not the case for conformally coupled free bosonic theories where states of unbounded null energy can be constructed by increasing the particle number. Little is known for interacting conformal field theories (CFTs) in dimensions larger than two. In this work we consider states that are superpositions of scalar primary operators or the stress-energy tensor itself in large N CFTs. Within the large N approximation we present arguments that the negative smeared null energy of such states scales at worst as the central charge of theory, $C_T$. This provides evidence for a general bound for CFTs in d-dimensions proportional to the central charge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10618v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jackson R. Fliss, Ben Freivogel, Eleni-Alexandra Kontou, Diego Pardo Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On holographic duals of certain isolated weighted Gorenstein cDV singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on an important mathematical conjecture, together with hypothesis of homological mirror symmetry in the context of Landau-Ginzburg models, we show that a class of compound Du Val singularities do not admit a crepant resolution. Most of these singularities sit in the type cEn. This implies that those singularities are not dual to four dimensional N =1 superconformal quiver gauge theories through stacks of D3 branes placed at the singularities. We verify this statement on the physics side by enumerating consistent gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10698v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanyuan Fang, Zekai Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isospectral local Hermitian theory for the $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric $i\phi^3$ quantum field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10732v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a new method to calculate perturbatively the isospectral Hermitian theory for the $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric $i\phi^3$ quantum field theory in $d$ dimensions, whose result is local. The result of the new method in $1$ dimension reproduces our previous result in the $ix^3$ quantum mechanics, and the new method can be seen as a generalization of our previous method to quantum field theory. We also find the isospectral local Hermitian theory has the same form in all dimensions and differs in coefficients only, and our previous results in quantum mechanics can be used directly to determine the form of the isospectral local Hermitian quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10732v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Da Li, Qing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative R\'enyi Entropy Under Local Quenches in 2D CFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the relative R\'enyi entropy (RRE) under local quenches in two-dimensional conformal field theories (CFTs), focusing on rational CFTs (RCFTs) and holographic CFTs. In RCFTs, the RRE evolves as a monotonic function over time, depending on finite-dimensional matrices. It is sometimes symmetric, prompting an exploration of its relation to the trace squared distance. We also observe that relative entropy can fail to distinguish between operators, as it only captures information entering/exiting the subsystem. In holographic CFTs, an analytic continuation of the RRE reveals insights into the entanglement wedge, offering a new perspective on bulk geometry in AdS/CFT. Our results deepen the understanding of quantum information measures in RCFTs and holographic CFTs, highlighting connections to distinguishability and bulk reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10735v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Xuan Zhao, Song He, Hao Ouyang, Hong-an Zeng, Yu-Xuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of a 3D Field-Theoretic Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the discrete as well as the continuous symmetry transformations for a three $(2+1)$-dimensional $(3D)$ combined system of the free Abelian 1-form and 2-form gauge theories within the framework of Becchi-Rouet-Stora-Tyutin (BRST) formalism and establish their relevance in the context of the algebraic structures that are obeyed by the de Rham cohomological operators of differential geometry. In fact, our present field-theoretic system respects six continuous symmetry transformations and a couple of very useful discrete duality symmetry transformations. Out of the above six continuous symmetry transformations four are off-shell nilpotent (i.e. fermionic) in nature and two are bosonic. The algebraic structures, obeyed by the symmetry operators, are reminiscent of the algebra satisfied by the de Rham cohomological operators. Hence, our present $3D$ field-theoretic system provides a perfect example for Hodge theory where there is convergence of ideas from the physical aspects of the BRST formalism and mathematical ingredients that are connected with the cohomological operators of differential geometry at the algebraic level. One of the highlights of our present investigation is the appearance of a pseudo-scalar field in our theory (on the symmetry ground alone) which carries the negative kinetic term. Thus, it is one of the possible candidates for the ``phantom" fields of the cyclic, bouncing and self-accelerated cosmological models of the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10852v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Kumar, R. P. Malik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical worldlines from scattering amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a systematic diagrammatic investigation of the classical limit of observables computed from scattering amplitudes in quantum field theory through the Kosower-Maybee-O'Connell (KMOC) formalism, motivated by the study of gravitational waves from black hole binaries. We achieve the manifest cancellation of divergences in the $\hbar \to 0$ limit at the integrand level beyond one loop by employing the Schwinger parametrisation to rewrite both cut and uncut propagators in a wordline-like representation before they are combined. The resulting finite classical integrand takes the same form as the counterpart in the worldline quantum field theory (WQFT) formalism of Mogull et al., and in fact exactly coincides with the latter in various examples, showing explicitly the equivalence between scattering amplitude and worldline formalisms. The classical causality flow, as expressed by the retarded propagator prescription, appears as an emergent feature. Examples are presented for impulse observables in electrodynamics and a scalar model at two loops, as well as certain subclasses of diagrams to higher orders and all orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10864v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeno Capatti, Mao Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comments on firewalls in JT gravity with matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11012v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present two discussions of firewalls in JT gravity. First we present an alternative, arguably simpler, derivation of the gray hole conjecture, applying uniformly to all probes of the firewall probability previously discussed. This derivation is based on the wormhole shortening picture using the handle-disk geometry. However we modifies Saad's story utilizing a "Wilsonian" effective gravitational description, adapted to the time scale probed, in which high frequency modes are integrated out generating the gravitational bulk geometries (dual to the genus expansion in the matrix integral side) whereas low frequency modes are more precisely resolved by being represented as eigenvalue D-branes where JT universes can end. This treatment results in an effective "twist factor cutoff" prescription which simplifies the discussion of long time quantities including the firewall probability. In the second part we discuss effects of matter loops on the firewall probability -- while naively such effects lead to new divergences, we argue that those correspond to the necessary modification of quantum field theory renormalization in topologically non-trivial spacetimes, and their effect on the firewall probability is small.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11012v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuanxin Cui, Moshe Rozali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic Interactions of Massive Higher-Spin Fields in 3D via Chiral Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11052v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the issue of electromagnetic interaction for massive higher-spin fields in $3d$ Minkowski space. We show that consistent field equations can be obtained through the dimensional reduction of the higher-spin extension of self-dual Yang-Mills theory, which itself is a truncation of chiral higher-spin gravity in four dimensions. The resulting electromagnetic field satisfies the Bogomolny equation, and the interaction is non-minimal with the gyromagnetic ratio given by $g=1/s$, where $s$ is the spin. As a by-product, we obtain a new Lagrangian for free massive higher-spin fields in $3d$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11052v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Sharapov, David Shcherbatov, Evgeny Skvortsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Corrected Holographic Wilson Loop Correlators and Confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11107v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Confinement is a well-known phenomenon in the infrared regime of (supersymmetric) Yang-Mills theory. Although experiments and numerical simulations have solidly confirmed confinement, its physical origin remains mysterious today, and finding a theoretical explanation for it is a long-standing and challenging problem in physics and mathematics. Inspired by the recent progress in quantum Jackiw-Teitelboim gravity, we compute the Wilson loop correlators of the large-$N$ limit of $\mathscr{N}=4$ super-Yang-Mills theory holographically in an extremal AdS$_5$ Reissner-Nordstr\"om black brane background. The quantum gravity fluctuations of the near-horizon region are considered, which consequently affect the holographic Wilson loop correlators. Within this framework, the results suggest that the confinement of the super-Yang-Mills theory is induced by the near-horizon quantum gravity fluctuations of the bulk extremal AdS$_5$ black brane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11107v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Long Liu, Cong-Yuan Yue, Jun Nian, Wenni Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonperturbative features in the Lie-algebraic K\"ahler sigma model with fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the trans-series structure of a quantum mechanical system originating from a Lie-algebraic K\"ahler sigma model with multiple right-handed chiral fermions, extending previous results for the standard onecomplex projective ($\cp^1$) model [1],[2] to its deformed counterpart. We identify and analyze saddle point solutions and examine their contributions within the perturbative expansions of the ground state energy, revealing that the ambiguity structure observed in the $\cp^1$ model persists in the deformed model as well. Additionally, we explore the role of the elongation parameter and its potential impact on higher-loop corrections, and propose that it becomes relevant in shaping the system's quantum behavior from the three-loop level. This verifies that the trans-series framework provides a comprehensive approach to capturing the structure of quantum fluctuations and ambiguities in these deformed sigma models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11444v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao-Hsiang Sheu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anyon Condensation in Virasoro TQFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Anyon condensation in wormhole geometries is investigated in the Virasoro TQFT (VTQFT) formulation. We first review some elementary techniques of VTQFT and verify its consistency by showing that it reproduces semiclassical results, including the Hawking-Page phase transition and the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy of BTZ blackhole. We then summarize a gauging scheme for non-invertible symmetries referred to as anyon condensation and exhibit that it is applicable to VTQFT even though the category of Wilson lines associated with it is not strictly a modular tensor category (MTC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11486v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunta Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Records from the S-Matrix Marathon: Gravitational Physics from Scattering Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11649v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: These lecture notes explain how classical gravitational physics emerges from scattering amplitudes. We emphasize the role of different kinematic regimes in probing various aspects of bound and unbound problems, as illustrated by the Hydrogen atom example. Classical predictions of General Relativity, such as the Shapiro time delay and perihelion precession, emerge from these considerations. We also explain a number of recent approaches to probing black hole physics from the perspective of amplitudes, including applications of worldline effective field theory in astrophysics, predictions of gravitational waveforms, and the hierarchical three-body problem.
  These notes are based on a series of lectures held during the S-Matrix Marathon workshop at the Institute for Advanced Study on 11--22 March 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11649v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Correia, Holmfridur S. Hannesdottir, Giulia Isabella, Anna M. Wolz, Zihan Zhou, Mathieu Giroux, Sebastian Mizera, Celina Pasiecznik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On topological defects in Chern-Simons theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a new class of topological surface defects in Chern-Simons theory with non-compact, non-Abelian gauge groups. These defects are characterized by isotropic subalgebras defined by solutions of the modified classical Yang-Baxter equation, and their fusion realizes a semi-group structure with non-invertible elements. From a Hamiltonian perspective, we calculate this fusion using the composition of Lagrangian correspondences within the Weinstein symplectic category. Applications include boundary terms and conditions in $AdS_3$ gravity and higher-spin theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11718v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex S. Arvanitakis, Lewis T. Cole, Saskia Demulder, Daniel C. Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collinear anatomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the collinear factorization of off-shell scattering amplitudes in maximally supersymmetric Yang-Mills (sYM) theory. These are constructed starting from six-dimensional N = (1,1) sYM, taking advantage of an available unconstrained spinor-helicity formalism combined with a unitarity-cut sewing procedure. After generalized dimensional reduction, their collinear behavior is dissected with assistance from the Method of Regions. We then construct off-shell splitting amplitudes directly using the same techniques, establishing equivalence to the amplitude analysis. The calculations are performed at one-loop order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11886v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Belitsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying the Massless Sector in AdS_3 Quantum Spectral Curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that in the asymptotic large-volume limit, the original proposal for Quantum Spectral Curve for AdS3 x S3 x T4 with R-R flux has a wider class of solutions, than studied previously. We argue that in this limit the QSC reduces to a finite set of Bethe equations for both massive and massless particle types. We also find that the QSC imposes more constraining conditions on the dressing phases than previously known and we present solutions of those equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11915v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Ekhammar, Nikolay Gromov, Bogdan Stefa\'nski jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Celestial Mellin Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Holographic correlators on the celestial sphere of Minkowski space were recently defined in arXiv:2301.01810 as the extrapolation of bulk time-ordered correlation functions to the celestial sphere. In this work we explore the Mellin representation of such celestial correlators, which is based on the Mellin representation of conformal correlators introduced by Mack in 2009. Perturbative celestial Mellin amplitudes have some similarities with Mellin amplitudes for AdS Witten diagrams: They are meromorphic functions of the Mellin variables, where contact diagrams have polynomial Mellin amplitudes and particle exchanges are encoded by a specific set of poles. We find the Mellin representation to be a useful tool to study and to compute celestial correlators, and we give various examples in scalar field theories at both tree and loop level, for both massive and massless fields. We also discuss the non-perturbative structure of celestial Mellin amplitudes following from the K\"all\'en-Lehmann spectral representation of bulk two-point functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11992v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Pacifico, Paolo Pergola, Charlotte Sleight</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fuzzy Axions and Associated Relics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12012v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study fuzzy axion dark matter in type IIB string theory, for axions descending from the Ramond-Ramond four-form in compactifications on orientifolds of Calabi-Yau hypersurfaces. Such models can be tested by cosmological measurements if a significant relic abundance of fuzzy dark matter arises, which we argue is most common in models with small numbers of axions. We construct a topologically exhaustive ensemble of more than 350,000 Calabi-Yau compactifications yielding up to seven axions, and in this setting we perform a systematic analysis of misalignment production of fuzzy dark matter. In typical regions of moduli space, the fuzzy axion, the QCD axion, and other axions have comparable decay constants of $f_a \approx 10^{16}$ GeV. We find that overproduction of heavier axions is problematic, except at special loci in moduli space where decay constant hierarchies can occur: without a contrived reheating epoch, it is necessary to fine-tune initial displacements. The resulting dark matter is typically a mix of fuzzy axions and heavier axions, including the QCD axion. Dark photons are typically present as a consequence of the orientifold projection. We examine the signatures of these models by simulating halos with multiple fuzzy axions, and by computing new cosmological constraints on ultralight axions and dark radiation. We also give evidence that cosmic birefringence is possible in this setting. Our findings determine the phenomenological correlates of fuzzy axion dark matter in a corner of the landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12012v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elijah Sheridan, Federico Carta, Naomi Gendler, Mudit Jain, David J. E. Marsh, Liam McAllister, Nicole Righi, Keir K. Rogers, Andreas Schachner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black hole solutions in theories of supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supergravity has played a very important role in many advances and developments in black hole physics. Here I will review the history of some of them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12020v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom\'as Ort\'in</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrically constrained localized configurations engendering non-topological profile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work deals with two real scalar fields in two-dimensional spacetime, with the fields coupled to allow the study of localized configurations. We consider models constructed to engender geometric constrictions, and use them to investigate solutions of the lump type, which attain no topological properties. We show how to modify the internal structure of the field configurations and the corresponding energy densities in several distinct ways, making them thinner, thicker and also, in the form of a multi-lump solution composed of two or more lumps or asymmetrically distributed around their associated centers. The results appear to be of current interest in high energy physics and may, in particular, be used to study bright solitons in optical fibers and in Bose-Einstein condensates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12044v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Bazeia, I. Bezerra, R. Menezes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QG from SymQRG: AdS$_3$/CFT$_2$ Correspondence as Topological Symmetry-Preserving Quantum RG Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By analyzing the non-perturbative RG flows that explicitly preserve given symmetries, we demonstrate that they can be expressed as quantum path integrals of the $\textit{SymTFT}$ in one higher dimension. When the symmetries involved include Virasoro defect lines, such as in the case of $T\bar{T}$ deformations, the RG flow corresponds to the 3D quantum gravitational path integral. For each 2D CFT, we identify a corresponding ground state of the SymTFT, from which the Wheeler-DeWitt equation naturally emerges as a non-perturbative constraint. These observations are summarized in the slogan: $\textbf{SymQRG = QG}$. The recently proposed exact discrete formulation of Liouville theory in [1] allows us to identify a universal SymQRG kernel, constructed from quantum $6j$ symbols associated with $U_q(SL(2,\mathbb{R}))$, which manifests itself as an exact and analytical 3D background-independent MERA-type holographic tensor network. Many aspects of the AdS/CFT correspondence, including the factorization puzzle, admit a natural interpretation within this framework. This provides the first evidence suggesting that there is a universal holographic principle encompassing AdS/CFT and topological holography. We propose that the non-perturbative AdS/CFT correspondence is a $\textit{maximal}$ form of topological holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12045v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Bao, Ling-Yan Hung, Yikun Jiang, Zhihan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calabi-Yau Feynman integrals in gravity: $\varepsilon$-factorized form for apparent singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a recently identified four-loop Feynman integral that contains a three-dimensional Calabi-Yau geometry and contributes to the scattering of black holes in classical gravity at fifth post-Minkowskian and second self-force order (5PM 2SF) in the conservative sector. In contrast to previously studied Calabi-Yau Feynman integrals, the higher-order differential equation that this integral satisfies in dimensional regularization exhibits $\varepsilon$-dependent apparent singularities. We introduce an appropriate ansatz which allows us to bring such cases into an $\varepsilon$-factorized form. As a proof of principle, we apply it to the integral at hand.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12057v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hjalte Frellesvig, Roger Morales, Sebastian P\"ogel, Stefan Weinzierl, Matthias Wilhelm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>There is more to the de Sitter horizon than just the area</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well known that the area of the de Sitter cosmological horizon is related to the entropy of the bulk spacetime. Recent work has however shown that the horizon encodes more information about the bulk spacetime than just the entropy. In this work, we show that the horizon contains all of the gauge invariant (diffeomorphism and $U(1)$) information about (static albeit unstable) configurations of charged and rotating objects placed deep inside the de Sitter spacetime. We study highly symmetric objects, such as dipoles and cubes, built of objects with electric charge and angular momentum at their vertices. We show how these configurations affect the geometry of the cosmological horizon and imprint detailed information about the objects in the bulk onto the cosmological horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12097v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Willy Fischler, Hare Krishna, Sarah Racz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A universal framework for the quantum simulation of Yang-Mills theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13161v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a universal framework for the quantum simulation of SU(N) Yang-Mills theories on fault-tolerant digital quantum computers adopting the orbifold lattice formulation. As warm-up examples, we also consider simple models, including scalar field theory and the Yang-Mills matrix model, to illustrate the universality of our formulation, which shows up in the fact that the truncated Hamiltonian can be expressed in the same simple form for any N, any dimension, and any lattice size, in stark contrast to the popular approach based on the Kogut-Susskind formulation. In all these cases, the truncated Hamiltonian can be programmed on a quantum computer using only standard tools well-established in the field of quantum computation. As a concrete application of this universal framework, we consider Hamiltonian time evolution by Suzuki-Trotter decomposition. This turns out to be a straightforward task due to the simplicity of the truncated Hamiltonian. We also provide a simple circuit structure that contains only CNOT and one-qubit gates, independent of the details of the theory investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13161v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jad C. Halimeh, Masanori Hanada, Shunji Matsuura, Franco Nori, Enrico Rinaldi, Andreas Sch\"afer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-Thermalization via Instantons near Dynamical Freezing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10498v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Periodically driven Floquet quantum many-body systems have revealed new insights into the rich interplay of thermalization, and growth of entanglement. The phenomenology of dynamical freezing, whereby a translationally invariant many-body system exhibits emergent conservation laws and a slow growth of entanglement entropy at certain fixed ratios of a drive amplitude and frequency, presents a novel paradigm for retaining memory of an initial state upto late times. Previous studies of dynamical freezing have largely been restricted to a high-frequency Floquet-Magnus expansion, and numerical exact diagonalization, which are unable to capture the slow approach to thermalization (or lack thereof) in a systematic fashion. By employing Floquet flow-renormalization, where the time-dependent part of the Hamiltonian is gradually decoupled from the effective Hamiltonian using a sequence of unitary transformations, we unveil the universal approach to dynamical freezing and beyond, at asymptotically late times. We analyze the fixed-point behavior associated with the flow-renormalization at and near freezing using both exact-diagonalization and tensor-network based methods, and contrast the results with conventional prethermal phenomenon. For a generic non-integrable spin Hamiltonian with a periodic cosine wave drive, the flow approaches an unstable fixed point with an approximate emergent symmetry. We observe that at freezing the thermalization timescales are delayed compared to away from freezing, and the flow trajectory undergoes a series of instanton events. Our numerical results are supported by analytical solutions to the flow equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10498v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Mukherjee, Haoyu Guo, Debanjan Chowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Born-Oppenheimer Renormalization group for High Energy Scattering: the Modified BFKL, or where did it all go?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10560v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We continue exploring the Born-Oppenheimer renormalization group generating evolution in frequency of physical observables. In this paper we study the evolution of the total cross section for dilute-dilute scattering retaining only eikonal emissions. We derive and analyze the analog of the BFKL equation in this framework. The frequency evolution has a very strong effect on the solutions of the BO-BFKL equation, slowing down the evolution of the scattering amplitude in a spectacular fashion: the intercept of the Pomeron is decreased by about a factor of three relative to the canonical LO BFKL result. The anomalous dimension is also modified significantly - from the BFKL value of one it goes down to the negative value of $\approx-0.2$. Introducing saturation boundary as a proxy for the full saturation dynamics, we find that the dependence of the saturation momentum on rapidity $\eta$ becomes quite weak with $Q^2_s\sim e^{a\bar\alpha_s\eta}$ with $a\approx 0.784$ as opposed to the BFKL value $a=4.88$. Our results underscore the necessity to take into account the DGLAP effects in the high energy evolution. This is left for future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10560v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haowu Duan, Alex Kovner, Michael Lublinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic definitions of scattering matrix and inclusive scattering matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The main goal of present paper is to analyze the adiabatic definition of scattering matrix in the formalism of L-functionals.
  This definition leads to the notion of inclusive scattering matrix closely related to inclusive cross sections. We discuss this notion and the relation of our techniques to adiabatic quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10634v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albert Schwarz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Hot QCD Matter 2024 -- Bulk Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10779v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The second Hot QCD Matter 2024 conference at IIT Mandi focused on various ongoing topics in high-energy heavy-ion collisions, encompassing theoretical and experimental perspectives. This proceedings volume includes 19 contributions that collectively explore diverse aspects of the bulk properties of hot QCD matter. The topics encompass the dynamics of electromagnetic fields, transport properties, hadronic matter, spin hydrodynamics, and the role of conserved charges in high-energy environments. These studies significantly enhance our understanding of the complex dynamics of hot QCD matter, the quark-gluon plasma (QGP) formed in high-energy nuclear collisions. Advances in theoretical frameworks, including hydrodynamics, spin dynamics, and fluctuation studies, aim to improve theoretical calculations and refine our knowledge of the thermodynamic properties of strongly interacting matter. Experimental efforts, such as those conducted by the ALICE and STAR collaborations, play a vital role in validating these theoretical predictions and deepening our insight into the QCD phase diagram, collectivity in small systems, and the early-stage behavior of strongly interacting matter. Combining theoretical models with experimental observations offers a comprehensive understanding of the extreme conditions encountered in relativistic heavy-ion and proton-proton collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10779v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prabhakar Palni, Amal Sarkar, Santosh K. Das, Anuraag Rathore, Syed Shoaib, Arvind Khuntia, Amaresh Jaiswal, Victor Roy, Ankit Kumar Panda, Partha Bagchi, Hiranmaya Mishra, Deeptak Biswas, Peter Petreczky, Sayantan Sharma, Kshitish Kumar Pradhan, Ronald Scaria, Dushmanta Sahu, Raghunath Sahoo, Arpan Das, Ranjita K Mohapatra, Jajati K. Nayak, Rupa Chatterjee, Munshi G Mustafa, Aswathy Menon K. R., Suraj Prasad, Neelkamal Mallick, Pushpa Panday, Binoy Krishna Patra, Paramita Deb, Raghava Varma, Ashutosh Dwibedi, Thandar Zaw Win, Subhalaxmi Nayak, Cho Win Aung, Sabyasachi Ghosh, Sesha Vempati, Sunny Kumar Singh, Manu Kurian, Vinod Chandra, Soham Banerjee,  Sumit, Rohit Kumar, Rajkumar Mondal, Nilanjan Chaudhuri, Pradip Roy, Sourav Sarkar, Lokesh Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$q$-Series Invariants of Three-Manifolds and Knots-Quivers Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10885v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Gukov-Pei-Putrov-Vafa (GPPV) conjecture is a relationship between two three-manifold invariants: the Witten-Reshetikhin-Turaev (WRT) invariant and the \(\widehat{Z}\) (``Z-hat'') invariant. In fact, WRT invariant is defined at roots of unity, $\mathbbm{q}\left(\exp\left(\frac{2\pi i}{k+2}\right),~k\in\mathbb{Z}_+,~\text{for}~SU(2)\right)$, and is generally a complex number, whereas $\widehat{Z}$-invariant is a $q$-series with integer coefficients such that $|q|&lt;1$. Therefore, $\widehat{Z}$-invariant can be obtained from WRT-invariant by performing a particular analytic continuation, $\mathbbm{q}\rightarrow q$. In this thesis, we first examine this conjecture for $SO(3)$ and the ortho-symplectic supergroup $OSp(1|2)$. This is done by setting up the WRT invariant for the respective groups and then performing the particular analytic continuation to extract $\widehat{Z}$. As a result of this exercise, we found that $\widehat{Z}^{SU(2)}=\widehat{Z}^{SO(3)}$ and identified a relation between $\widehat{Z}^{SU(2)}$ and $\widehat{Z}^{OSp(1|2)}$. Motivated by the equality of $\widehat{Z}$ for $SU(2)$ and $SO(3)$ groups, we study this conjecture for $SU(N)/\mathbb{Z}_m$ groups, where $\mathbb{Z}_m$ is a subgroup of $\mathbb{Z}_N$, in our second paper. We subsequently found that $\widehat{Z}^{SU(N)/\mathbb{Z}_m}=\widehat{Z}^{SU(N)}$.
  Another theme of the thesis is to study a conjecture between knot theory and quiver representation theory. More precisely, this conjecture relates the generating function of the symmetric $r$-colored HOMFLY-PT polynomial with the motivic generating series associated with a symmetric quiver. In particular, we obtain a quiver representation for a family of knots called double twist knots $K(p,-m)$. Primarily, we exploit the reverse engineering of Melvin-Morton-Rozansky (MMR) formalism to deduce the pattern of the matrix for these quivers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10885v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sachin Chauhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resumming Photon Loops for Inflationary Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11022v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A previous calculation of the 1-loop photon contribution to the graviton self-energy on de Sitter background is considered. We first show that there is no local obstacle to conservation, unlike the contribution from a loop of massless, minimally coupled scalars. This is correlated to the absence of an Eddington ($R^2$) counterterm and to the vanishing of the stress tensor when the photon in integrated out in the presence of a constant graviton field. We also show that there is a secularly growing 1-loop contribution to the electric components of the Weyl tensor for plane wave gravitons. Its coefficient agrees with that of the secular 1-loop correction to the Newtonian potential, and both can be resummed using a variant of the renormalization group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11022v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. J. Foraci, R. P. Woodard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A scattering construction for nonlinear wave equations on Kerr--Anti-de Sitter spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11209v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Existence of a large class of exponentially decaying solutions of the nonlinear massive wave equation $\Box_g\psi+\alpha\psi = \mathcal{F}(\psi,\partial\psi)$ on a Kerr--Anti-de Sitter exterior is established via a backwards scattering construction. Exponentially decaying data is prescribed on the future event horizon, and Dirichlet data on the timelike conformal boundary. The corresponding solutions exhibit the full functional degrees of freedom of the problem, but are exceptional in the sense that (even) general solutions of the forward, linear ($\mathcal{F}=0$) problem are known to decay at best inverse logarithmically. Our construction even applies outside of the \textit{Hawking-Reall bound} on the spacetime angular momentum, in which case, there exist exponentially growing mode solutions of the forward problem. As for the analogous construction in the asymptotically flat case, the assumed exponential decay of the scattering data on the event horizon is exploited to overcome the gravitational blueshift encountered in the backwards construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11209v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gemma L. Hood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Census of the Universe's Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11282v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The question of what is the total entropy of the universe, how it compares to the maximal entropy of de Sitter space, and how it is distributed across the universe's components, bears considerable importance for a number of reasons. Here, we first update the computation of the entropy associated with various sectors of the observed universe, including in the diffuse cosmic and late-time gamma-ray and neutrino backgrounds, in baryonic matter both in diffuse components, in stars and stellar remnants, and in cosmic rays; we then update, crucially, the estimate of entropy in stellar-mass and super-massive black holes, whose abundance and mass function has come into increasingly sharp definition with recent observations and with the rapidly growing statistics of black-hole-black-hole mergers observed with gravity wave detectors. We also provide a new, corrected estimate of the potential entropy associated with a stochastic gravitational wave background, with dark sector radiations, and with several dark matter models. Finally, we utilize the similarly recently updated constraints on the abundance of hypothetical primordial black holes - black holes, that is, of non-stellar origin - to assess the maximal amount entropy they could store. We find that if supermassive primordial black holes exist, they can dominate the entropy budget of the universe consistently with current constraints on their abundance and mass function, to a level potentially not distant from the posited entropy associated with the cosmic event horizon of de Sitter spacetime. The same conclusion holds for certain dark sector models featuring a large number of dark degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11282v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Profumo, Liam Colombo-Murphy, Gabriela Huckabee, Maya Diaz Svensson, Stuti Garg, Ishan Kollipara, Alison Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic Locality from Electromagnetism to Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electromagnetism is the paradigm case of a theory that satisfies relativistic locality. This can be proven by demonstrating that, once the theory's laws are imposed, what is happening within a region fixes what will happen in the contracting light-cone with that region as its base. The Klein-Gordon and Dirac equations meet the same standard. We show that this standard can also be applied to quantum field theory (without collapse), examining two different ways of assigning reduced density matrix states to regions of space. Our preferred method begins from field wave functionals and judges quantum field theory to be local. Another method begins from particle wave functions (states in Fock space) and leads to either non-locality or an inability to assign states to regions, depending on the choice of creation operators. We take this analysis of quantum field theory (without collapse) to show that the many-worlds interpretation of quantum physics is local at the fundamental level. We argue that this fundamental locality is compatible with either local or global accounts of the non-fundamental branching of worlds, countering an objection that has been raised to the Sebens-Carroll derivation of the Born Rule from self-locating uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11532v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Y. S. Chua, Charles T. Sebens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harvesting stabilizer entropy and non-locality from a quantum field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11918v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The harvesting of quantum resources from the vacuum state of a quantum field is a central topic in relativistic quantum information. While several proposals for the harvesting of entanglement from the quantum vacuum exist, less attention has been paid to other quantum resources, such as non-stabilizerness, commonly dubbed magic and quantified by the Stabilizer R\'enyi Entropy (SRE). In this work, we show how to harvest SRE from the vacuum state of a massless field, using accelerated Unruh-DeWitt detectors in Minkowski spacetime. In particular, one can harvest a particular non-local form of SRE that cannot be erased by local operations. We conclude our work with an analysis of the CHSH inequalities: one cannot extract a violation from the quantum field unless these resources are already there.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11918v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Cepollaro, S. Cusumano, A. Hamma, G. Lo Giudice, J. Odavic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wormholes from beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11947v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a brane-world context in which our universe would be a four-dimensional brane embedded into a five-dimensional spacetime or bulk, wormhole geometries are induced on branes. In this article, the Morris-Thorne wormhole and the Molina-Neves wormhole are obtained on the brane using the Nakas-Kanti approach, which starts from a regular five-dimensional spacetime to obtain known black hole and wormhole solutions on the four-dimensional brane. From the bulk perspective, these wormholes are five-dimensional solutions supported by an exotic fluid, but from the brane perspective, such objects are wormholes not supported by any fields or particles that live on the four-dimensional spacetime. Thus, the cause of these wormholes is the bulk influence on the brane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11947v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juliano C. S. Neves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C-R-T Fractionalization in the First Quantized Hamiltonian Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent research has revealed that the CRT symmetry for fermions exhibits a fractionalization distinct from the $\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{C}}\times\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{R}}\times\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{T}}$ for scalar bosons. In fact, the CRT symmetry for fermions can be extended by internal symmetries such as fermion parity, thereby forming a group extension of the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ direct product. Conventionally, a Majorana fermion is defined by one Dirac fermion with trivial charge conjugation. However, when the spacetime dimension $d+1=5,6,7\bmod8$, the real dimension of Majorana fermion (dim$_{\mathbb{R}}\chi_{\mathcal{C}\ell(d,0)}$) aligns with the real dimension of Dirac fermion (dim$_{\mathbb{R}}\psi_{\mathcal{C}\ell(d)}$), rather than being half, which necessitates the introduction of a symplectic Majorana fermion, defined by two Dirac fermions with trivial charge conjugation. To include these two types of Majorana fermions, we embed the theory in $n_{\mathbb{R}}$ and define the Majorana fermion field as a representation of the real Clifford algebra with 8-fold periodicity. Within the Hamiltonian formalism, we identify the 8-fold CRT-internal symmetry groups across general dimensions. Similarly, Dirac fermion field is defined as a representation of the complex Clifford algebra with 2-fold periodicity. Interestingly, we discover that the CRT-internal symmetry groups exhibit an 8-fold periodicity that is distinct from that of the complex Clifford algebra. In certain dimensions where distinct mass terms can span a mass manifold, the CRT-internal symmetries can act non-trivially upon this mass manifold. Employing domain wall reduction method, we are able to elucidate the relationships between symmetries across different dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11958v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang-Yang Li, Zheyan Wan, Juven Wang, Shing-Tung Yau, Yi-Zhuang You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for the Sombrero Galaxy as an Accelerator of the Highest-Energy Cosmic Rays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11966v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrahigh-energy cosmic rays (UHECRs) are the highest energy messenger from space, with energies exceeding 1 EeV. Although UHECRs were discovered over 60 years ago, their origin still remains a mystery. Pinpointing sources of UHECRs is crucial for understanding the extreme astrophysical processes that accelerate particles to such extraordinary energies. We searched for UHECR multiplets via analyzing 17 years of data with energies greater than 40 EeV from the Pierre Auger Observatory. A spatial association is found between a multiplet of $25.7^{+6.2}_{-7.0}$ cosmic rays and the Sombrero galaxy with a local (global) significance of $4.5~\sigma~(3.3~\sigma)$. The Sombrero galaxy hosts a supermassive central black hole with a mass of $\sim1\times 10^9 M_{\odot}$ and exhibits large-scale radio lobes and jets. Our finding provides critical evidence on active supermassive black holes as the source of the highest-energy cosmic rays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11966v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Ning He, Eiji Kido, Kai-Kai Duan, Yang Yang, Ryo Higuchi, Yi-Zhong Fan, Tao Wang, Lu-Yao Jiang, Rong-Lan Li, Ben-Yang Zhu, Xiang Li, Zi-Qing Xia, Shigehiro Nagataki, Da-Ming Wei, Alexander Kusenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Hamiltonian and orthogonal polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12021v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the entanglement Hamiltonian for free-fermion chains with a particular form of inhomogeneity. The hopping amplitudes and chemical potentials are chosen such that the single-particle eigenstates are related to discrete orthogonal polynomials of the Askey scheme. Due to the bispectral properties of these functions, one can construct an operator which commutes exactly with the entanglement Hamiltonian and corresponds to a linear or parabolic deformation of the physical one. We show that this deformation is interpreted as a local inverse temperature and can be obtained in the continuum limit via methods of conformal field theory. Using this prediction, the properly rescaled eigenvalues of the commuting operator are found to provide a very good approximation of the entanglement spectrum and entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12021v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre-Antoine Bernard, Riccarda Bonsignori, Viktor Eisler, Gilles Parez, Luc Vinet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The causal structure of the quark propagator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12033v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the causal structure of the quark propagator with the spectral DSE. The spectral gap equation is solved with the input of the spectral representation of the gluon and a causal STI-construction for the quark-gluon vertex. The latter includes a potential infrared enhancement of the vertex strength of the classical tensor structure that accommodates for the physical strength of chiral symmetry breaking. We find a critical vertex strength, below which the quark has a K\"all\'en-Lehmann representation. While the nature of the first singularity does not change above the critical strength, we find that the quark propagator features at least two additional pairs of complex conjugate poles that are located approximately at the sum of quark pole mass and peak position of the quark-gluon coupling. These additional poles lead to violations of causality, if they persist in $S$-matrix elements. While the vertex strength of the classical tensor structure in full QCD is below the critical one, that of commonly used vertex models, which rely solely on the classical vertex structure, is typically above it. Finally, we discuss how these additional poles could be avoided in full QCD, where part of chiral symmetry breaking is generated by the other tensor structures in the quark-gluon vertex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12033v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan M. Pawlowski, Jonas Wessely</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aspects of $T\bar{T}+J\bar{T }$ deformed Schwarzian: From gravity partition function to late-time spectral form factor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16658v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate different thermodynamic properties of $T\bar{T}+J\bar{T}$ deformed Schwarzian theory and its different gravitational perspectives. First, we compute the partition function of $U(1)$ coupled 2D-gravity with fixed chemical potential, obtained from the dimensional reduction of the four-dimensional Einstein-Maxwell theory. Then, we compute the partition function of the gravity theory which is the dual to the deformed Schwarzian living on its boundary and study the genus expansion of the one and two-point correlation function of the partition function of the theory. Subsequently, we use the one-point function to compute the "Annealed" and "Quenched" free energy in low-temperature limits and make a qualitative comparison with the undeformed theory. Then, using the two-point function, we compute the Spectral Form Factor of the deformed theory in early and late time. We find a dip and ramp structure in early and late time, respectively. We also get a plateau structure in the $\tau$-scaling limit. Last but not least, we comment on the late-time topology change to give a physical interpretation of the ramp of the Spectral Form Factor for our theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16658v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.126015</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 126015 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Bhattacharyya, Saptaswa Ghosh, Sounak Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new approach to superstring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07942v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show how starting with one-string space of states in BRST formalism one can construct a large class of physical quantities containing, in particular, scattering amplitudes for bosonic string and superstring. The same techniques work for heterotic string.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07942v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albert Schwarz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Hamiltonian for fermions of small mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04629v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the algebra of massive fermions restricted to a diamond in two-dimensional Minkowski spacetime, and in the Minkowski vacuum state. While the massless modular Hamiltonian is known for this setting, the derivation of the massive one is an open problem. We compute the small-mass corrections to the modular Hamiltonian in a perturbative approach, finding some terms which were previously overlooked. Our approach can in principle be extended to all orders in the mass, even though it becomes computationally challenging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04629v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00023-024-01508-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ann. H. Poincar\'e (2024) online first</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniela Cadamuro, Markus B. Fr\"ob, Christoph Minz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Improved Framework for Computing Waveforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We combine the observable-based formalism (KMOC), the analytic properties of the scattering amplitude, generalised unitarity and the heavy-mass expansion with a newly introduced IBP reduction for Fourier integrals, to provide an efficient framework for computing scattering waveforms. We apply this framework to the scattering of two charged massive bodies in classical electrodynamics. Our work paves the way for the computation of the analytic one-loop waveform in General Relativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08009v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Brunello, Stefano De Angelis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Calabi-Yau four folds with hybrid and recurrent neural network architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17406v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we report the results of applying deep learning based on hybrid convolutional-recurrent and purely recurrent neural network architectures to the dataset of almost one million complete intersection Calabi-Yau four-folds (CICY4) to machine-learn their four Hodge numbers $h^{1,1}, h^{2,1}, h^{3,1}, h^{2,2}$. In particular, we explored and experimented with twelve different neural network models, nine of which are convolutional-recurrent (CNN-RNN) hybrids with the RNN unit being either GRU (Gated Recurrent Unit) or Long Short Term Memory (LSTM). The remaining four models are purely recurrent neural networks based on LSTM. In terms of the $h^{1,1}, h^{2,1}, h^{3,1}, h^{2,2}$ prediction accuracies, at 72% training ratio, our best performing individual model is CNN-LSTM-400, a hybrid CNN-LSTM with the LSTM hidden size of 400, which obtained 99.74%, 98.07%, 95.19%, 81.01%, our second best performing individual model is LSTM-448, an LSTM-based model with the hidden size of 448, which obtained 99.74%, 97.51%, 94.24%, and 78.63%. These results were improved by forming ensembles of the top two, three or even four models. Our best ensemble, consisting of the top four models, achieved the accuracies of 99.84%, 98.71%, 96.26%, 85.03%. At 80% training ratio, the top two performing models LSTM-448 and LSTM-424 are both LSTM-based with the hidden sizes of 448 and 424. Compared with the 72% training ratio, there is a significant improvement of accuracies, which reached 99.85%, 98.66%, 96.26%, 84.77% for the best individual model and 99.90%, 99.03%, 97.97%, 87.34% for the best ensemble. By nature a proof of concept, the results of this work conclusively established the utility of RNN-based architectures and demonstrated their effective performances compared to the well-explored purely CNN-based architectures in the problem of deep learning Calabi Yau manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17406v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. L. Dao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Null Geometry and Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11132v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we demonstrate that quantizing gravity on a null hypersurface leads to the emergence of a CFT associated with each null ray. This result stems from the ultralocal nature of null physics and is derived through a canonical analysis of the Raychaudhuri equation, interpreted as a constraint generating null time reparametrizations. The CFT exhibits a non-zero central charge, providing a mechanism for the quantum emergence of time in gravitational systems and an associated choice of vacuum state. Our analysis reveals that the central charge quantifies the degrees of freedom along each null ray. Throughout our investigation, the area element of a cut plays a crucial role, necessitating its treatment as a quantum operator due to its dynamic nature in phase space or because of quantum backreaction. Furthermore, we show that the total central charge diverges in a perturbative analysis due to the infinite number of null generators. This divergence is resolved if there is a discrete spectrum for the area form operator. We introduce the concept of `embadons' to denote these localized geometric units of area, the fundamental building blocks of geometry at a mesoscopic quantum gravity scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11132v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)028</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Luca Ciambelli, Laurent Freidel, Robert G. Leigh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Loop Quantum Gravity Inspired Action for the Bosonic String and Emergent Dimensions at Large Scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13807v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a modification of the Nambu-Goto action for the bosonic string which is compatible with the existence of a minimum area at the Planck scale. The result is a phenomenological action based on the observation that LQG tells us that areas of two-surfaces are operators in quantum geometry and are bounded from below. This leads us to a string action which is similar to that of bimetric gravity. We provide formulations of the bimetric string action for both the Nambu-Goto (second order) and Polyakov (first order) formulations. We explore the classical solutions of this action and its quantization and relate it to the conventional string solutions.
  We further construct a string action in which the effect of the background geometry is described in terms of the pullback of the bulk connection, which encodes the bulk geometry, to the worldsheet. The resulting string action is in the form of a gauged sigma model, where the spacetime co-ordinates are now vectors which transform under the Poincar\'e group $ISO(D,1)$. This requires the introduction of an auxiliary bulk co-ordinate which has a natural interpretation as a holographic or scale direction. We discuss possible cosmological implications of such a large scale emergent dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13807v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deepak Vaid, Luigi Teixeira de Sousa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proving the absence of large one-loop corrections to the power spectrum of curvature perturbations in transient ultra-slow-roll inflation within the path-integral approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19742v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit one-loop corrections to the power spectrum of curvature perturbations $\zeta$ in an inflationary scenario containing a transient ultra-slow-roll (USR) period. In Ref.[1], it was argued that one-loop corrections to the power spectrum of $\zeta$ can be larger than the tree-level one within the parameter region generating the seeds of primordial black holes during the USR epoch, which implies the breakdown of perturbation theory. We prove that this is not the case by using a master formula for one-loop corrections to the power spectrum obtained in Ref.[2]. We derive the same formula within the path-integral formalism, which is simpler than the original derivation in [2]. To show the smallness of one-loop corrections, the consistency relations and the effective constancy of tree-level mode functions of $\zeta$ for super-Hubble modes play essential roles, with which the master formula gives a simple expression for one-loop corrections. For concreteness, we provide a reduced set of interactions including the leading-order one, while establishing the consistency relations in a self-consistent manner. We also show how the consistency relations of various operators hold explicitly, which plays a key role in proving the absence of large one-loop corrections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19742v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)095</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP12(2024)095</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ryodai Kawaguchi, Shinji Tsujikawa, Yusuke Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical features, Anderson-Higgs mechanism, and unitarity in Lee-Wick pseudo-electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00314v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, the dimensional reduction is applied to the Lee-Wick electrodynamics in which the classical sources are confined on a spatial plane. As result, the Lee-Wick pseudo-electrodynamics is achieved as a non-local electromagnetism defined in $1+2$ dimensions. The abelian Anderson-Higgs mechanism is so introduced in the Lee-Wick pseudo-electrodynamics through a complex scalar sector in $1+2$ dimensions, breaking spontaneously the $U(1)$-gauge symmetry of the non-local theory. As consequence, the pseudo-Lee-Wick field acquires a light mass, beyond the usual heavy Lee-Wick mass, that is a natural mass parameter of the theory. After the spontaneous symmetry breaking takes place, classical features of the theory are discussed, as the Proca-Lee-Wick pseudo-electrodynamics, with the field equations and conservation laws. The introduction of Lee-Wick fermions also is proposed, in which it opens the discussion of a viable Proca-Lee-Wick pseudo-quantum electrodynamics in $1+2$ dimensions. The unitarity at the tree level of the Lee-Wick pseudo-electrodynamics is discussed through the Optical theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00314v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. J. Neves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On (dis)agreement between different methods of calculation of the imaginary part of the effective action in expanding space-times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02170v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider two approaches to calculate imaginary parts of effective actions in expanding space-times. While the first approach uses Bogolyubov coefficients, the second one uses the functional integral or the Feynman propagator. In eternally expanding space-times these two approaches give different answers for the imaginary parts. The origin of the difference can be traced to the presence if the wave-functionals for the initial and final states in the functional integral. We show this explicitly on the example of the expanding Poincare patch of the de Sitter space-time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02170v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. T. Akhmedov, I. A. Belkovich, D. V. Diakonov, K. A. Kazarnovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ambient space and integration of the trace anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03842v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use the ambient space construction, in which spacetime is mapped into a special lightcone of a higher dimensional manifold, to derive the integrable terms of the trace anomaly in even dimensions. We argue that the natural topological anomaly is the so-called $Q$-curvature, which, when projected from the ambient space, always comes with a Weyl covariant operator that can naturally be adopted for the integration of the anomaly itself in the form of a nonlocal action. The use of the ambient space makes trasparent the fact that there are some new ambiguities in the integration of the anomaly, which we now understand geometrically from the ambient point of view. These ambiguities, which manifest themselves as undetermined parameters in the integrated nonlocal action, become more severe in dimensions $d\geq 6$ and do not seem to be related to a choice of the renormalization scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03842v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregorio Paci, Omar Zanusso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BMS-like algebras: canonical realisations and BRST quantisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14866v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We generalise BMS algebras in three dimensions by the introduction of an arbitrary real parameter $\lambda$, recovering the standard algebras (BMS, extended BMS and Weyl-BMS) for $\lambda=-1$. We exhibit a realisation of the (centreless) Weyl $\lambda$-BMS algebra in terms of the symplectic structure on the space of solutions of the massless Klein-Gordon equation in $2+1$, using the eigenstates of the spacetime momentum operator. The quadratic Casimir of the Lorentz algebra plays an essential r\^ole in the construction. The Weyl $\lambda$-BMS algebra admits a three-parameter family of central extensions, resulting in the (centrally extended) Weyl-BMS algebra, which we reformulate in terms of operator product expansions. We construct the BRST complex of a putative Weyl-BMS string and show that the BRST cohomology is isomorphic to the chiral ring of a topologically twisted $N=2$ superconformal field theory. We also comment on the obstructions to obtaining a conformal BMS Lie algebra -- that is, one that includes in addition the special-conformal generators -- and the need to consider a W-algebra. We then construct the quantum version of this W-algebra in terms of operator product expansions. We show that this W-algebra does not admit a BRST complex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14866v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Batlle, Jos\'e Figueroa-O'Farrill, Joaquim Gomis, Girish Vishwa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monopoles, Dirac Strings and Generalised Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18741v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dirac's formulation of magnetic monopoles is shown to be equivalent to Maxwell theory coupled to 2-form gauge fields so that it has a local 1-form symmetry, with the 2-form gauge fields given in terms of the 2-form current densities associated with the Dirac strings. The field equations of Dirac's theory do not depend on the positions of the Dirac strings provided that they do not intersect the worldlines of any electrically charged particles; this constraint is called the Dirac veto. It is shown that Dirac's action is independent of the positions of the Dirac strings and that this corresponds a local 1-form symmetry. The electric and magnetic 1-form symmetries have a mixed anomaly, and the Dirac veto is shown to correspond to a restriction to gauge transformations for which the anomaly vanishes. The extension to $p$-form gauge fields in d-dimensions coupled to charged branes is discussed, together with the possibility of cancelling the anomaly by embedding in a higher-dimensional theory and so avoiding the veto.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18741v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C M Hull</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(-1)-form symmetries from M-theory and SymTFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19683v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore $(-1)$-form symmetries within the framework of geometric engineering in M-theory. By constructing the Symmetry Topological Field Theory (SymTFT) for selected 5d $\mathcal{N}=1$, 4d $\mathcal{N}=2$ and 4d $\mathcal{N}=1$ theories, we formalize the geometric origin of these symmetries and compute the mixed anomaly polynomials involving $(-1)$-form and higher-form symmetries. Our findings consistently reveal both discrete and continuous $(-1)$-form symmetries, aligning with established field theory results, while also uncovering new $(-1)$-form symmetry factors and structural insights. In particular, we study the SymTFT of 4d $\mathcal{N}=1$ theories from M-theory on a class of spaces with $G_2$ holonomy, and obtain properties such as modified instanton sums and 4-group structures observed in other 4d gauge theories. Additionally, we systematically construct symmetry operators for continuous abelian symmetries, refining existing proposals, and providing an M-theory origin for them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19683v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marwan Najjar, Leonardo Santilli, Yi-Nan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of a CP broken deconfined phase in 4D SU(2) Yang-Mills theory at $\theta =\pi$ from imaginary $\theta$ simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03683v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The spontaneous breaking of CP symmetry in 4D SU($N$) pure Yang-Mills theory at $\theta=\pi$ has recently attracted much attention in the context of the higher-form symmetry and the 't Hooft anomaly matching condition. Here we use Monte Carlo simulations to study the $N=2$ case, which is interesting since it is the case opposite to the large-$N$ limit, where explicit calculations are available. In order to circumvent the severe sign problem due to the $\theta$ term for real $\theta$, we first obtain results at imaginary $\theta$, where the sign problem is absent, and make an analytic continuation to real $\theta$. We use the stout smearing in defining the $\theta$ term in the action to be used in our simulations. Thus we obtain the expectation value of the topological charge and the deconfining temperature at $\theta=\pi$, and provide an evidence that the CP symmetry, which is spontaneously broken at low temperature, gets restored \emph{strictly above} the deconfining temperature. This conclusion is consistent with the anomaly matching condition and yet differs from the prediction in the large-$N$ limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03683v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mitsuaki Hirasawa, Masazumi Honda, Akira Matsumoto, Jun Nishimura, Atis Yosprakob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactions between different Kaluza-Klein modes in brane world</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07628v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In brane-world theory, through Kaluza-Klein (KK) reduction, a higher-dimensional U(1) gauge field manifests on the brane as a series of vector and scalar KK modes, while a bulk fermion field manifests as left- and right-handed components. However, these conclusions rely on the common assumption that there is no interaction between different levels of KK modes. Recent experimental phenomena, such as flavor mixing in particles, suggest that such interactions should be taken into account. To address this, we propose an \emph{Orthonormal Completeness Hypothesis} (OCH) for the basis functions used to expand the higher-dimensional field. By applying the OCH, we demonstrate that the effective action of a free bulk U(1) gauge field is intrinsically gauge-invariant in brane models with codimension-\(d\) (\(d \geq 1\)). This effective action suggests the existence of interactions between different levels of KK modes, which can only be eliminated by choosing specific basis functions, provided the warp factors satisfy special commutation relations. In general, such interactions are universally present. We show the numerical calculations for these coupling coefficients in an interesting 6D brane world. This method can be extended to fermion fields, and it is shown that interactions between different levels of left- and right-handed KK modes exist, providing new insights into phenomena such as flavor mixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07628v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Xuan Ma, Chun-E Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smart Holes: Analogue black holes with the right temperature and entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08517v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In analogue gravity studies, the goal is to replicate black hole phenomena, such as Hawking radiation, within controlled laboratory settings. In the realm of condensed matter systems, this may happen in 2D tilted Dirac cone materials based on honeycomb lattice. In particular, we compute the entropy of this system, and find it has the same form as black hole Bekenstein-Hawking entropy, if an analogue horizon forms. Hence, these systems can be potential analogues of quantum black holes. We show that this entropy is primarily concentrated in the region where the tilt parameter is close to one, which corresponds to the location of the analogue black hole horizon. Additionally, when nonlinear effects are taken into account, the entropy is peaked in a small pocket of the Fermi sea that forms behind the analogue event horizon, which we call the \textit{Fermi puddle}. We further refer to this new type of analogue black hole as a {\it smart hole}, since, in contrast to dumb holes, it can simulate both the correct temperature {\it and} entropy of general relativistic black holes. These results provide an opportunity to illuminate various quantum facets of black hole physics in a laboratory setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08517v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayue Yang, Niayesh Afshordi, Mahdi Torabian, Seyed Akbar Jafari, G. Baskaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The generalized CV conjecture of Krylov complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08925v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We extend the ``complexity=volume" (CV) conjecture in the wormhole to the quantum states in the framework of information geometry. In particular, we conjecture that Krylov complexity equals the volume of the Fubini-Study metric in the information geometry. In order to test our conjecture, we study the general Hermitian two-mode Hamiltonian according to the Weyl algebra both in the closed and open systems. By employing the displacement operator, we find that the wave function for a closed system corresponds to the well-known two-mode squeezed state. For an open system, we can create a wave function known as the open two-mode squeezed state by using the second kind of Meixner polynomials. Remarkably, in both cases, the resulting volume of the corresponding Fubini-Study metric provides strong evidence for the generalized CV conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08925v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke-Hong Zhai, Lei-Hua Liu, Hai-Qing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting a long lived false vacuum with quantum quenches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08340v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Distinguishing whether a system supports alternate low-energy (locally stable) states -- stable (true vacuum) versus metastable (false vacuum) -- by direct observation can be difficult when the lifetime of the state is very long but otherwise unknown. Here we demonstrate, in a tractable model system, that there are physical phenomena on much shorter time scales that can diagnose the difference. Specifically, we study the time evolution of the magnetization following a quench in the tilted quantum Ising model, and show that its magnitude spectrum is an effective diagnostic. Small transition bubbles are more common than large ones, and we see characteristic differences in the size dependence of bubble lifetimes even well below the critical size for false vacuum decay. We expect this sort of behavior to be generic in systems of this kind. We show such signatures persist in a continuum field theory. This also opens the possibility of similar signatures of the potential metastable false vacuum of our universe well before the beginning of a decay process to the true vacuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08340v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.240402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 240402 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Lagnese, Federica Maria Surace, Sid Morampudi, Frank Wilczek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clockwork Neutrinogenesis: Baryogenesis from theory space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.09640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.09640v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a minimal clockwork model to illustrate the possibility of baryogenesis via leptogenesis in a theory space setting. The standard lepton sector is augmented with three copies of a clockwork lattice made of SM neutral fermions. The two boundaries of these one-dimensional lattices are endowed with couplings to the SM leptons and three dark sector fermions, respectively. Small neutrino masses and a resonance enhanced Dirac leptogenesis are naturally obtained for anarchic textures of the Yukawa matrices, with $\sim \mathcal{O}(1)$ elements, provided the heavy clockwork fermions have masses $\gtrsim \mathcal{O}(10 \, \mbox{TeV})$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.09640v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suvam Maharana, Tripurari Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secular growths and their relation to equilibrium states in perturbative QFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00556v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the perturbative treatment of interacting quantum field theories, if the interaction Lagrangian changes adiabatically in a finite interval of time, secular growths may appear in the truncated perturbative series also when the interaction Lagrangian density is returned to be constant. If this happens, the perturbative approach does not furnish reliable results in the evaluation of scattering amplitudes or expectation values. In this paper we show that these effects can be avoided for adiabatically switched-on interactions, if the spatial support of the interaction is compact and if the background state is suitably chosen. We start considering equilibrium background states and show that, when thermalisation occurs (interaction Lagrangian of spatial compact support), secular effects are avoided. Furthermore, no secular effects pop up if the limit where the Lagrangian is supported everywhere in space is taken after thermalisation (large time limit), in contrast to the reversed order. This result is generalized showing that if the interaction Lagrangian is spatially compact, secular growths are avoided for generic background states which are only invariant under time translation and to states whose explicit dependence of time is not too strong. Finally, as an application, the presented theorems are used to study a complex scalar and a Dirac field, on a background KMS state, in a classical external electromagnetic potential and the contribution to the two point-function given by a generic loop diagram arising from a second order perturbative expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00556v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Galanda, Nicola Pinamonti, Leonardo Sangaletti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional topological paramagnets protected by $\mathbb{Z}_3$ symmetry: Properties of the boundary Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15095v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically construct two-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_3$ symmetry-protected topological (SPT) three-state Potts paramagnets with gapless edge modes on a triangular lattice. First, we study microscopic lattice models for the gapless edge and, using the density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) approach, investigate the finite size scaling of the low-lying excitation spectrum and the entanglement entropy. Based on the obtained results, we identify the universality class of the critical edge, namely the corresponding conformal field theory and the central charge. Finally, we discuss the inherent symmetries of the edge models and the emergent winding symmetry distinguishing between two SPT phases. As a result, the two topologically nontrivial and the trivial phases define a general one-dimensional chain supporting a tricriticality, which we argue supports a gapless SPT order in one dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15095v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hrant Topchyan, Vasilii Iugov, Mkhitar Mirumyan, Tigran S. Hakobyan, Tigran A. Sedrakyan, Ara G. Sedrakyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QGP Physics from Attractor Perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17237v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The strong longitudinal expansion characteristic of heavy-ion collisions leads to universal attractor behavior of the resulting drop of quark-gluon plasma (QGP) already at very early times. Assuming approximate boost invariance and neglecting transverse expansion at the initial time, we incorporate subsequent transverse dynamics of this system by linearizing the Mueller-Israel-Stewart theory around the transversely homogeneous attractor. The result is a system of coupled ordinary differential equations which describes the proper-time evolution of Fourier modes encoding the transverse structure of the initial energy deposition. The late-time asymptotic behavior of these solutions is described by transseries which make manifest the stability of the attractor against transverse perturbations. In this framework, information about the structure of the plasma in the transverse plane resides mostly in exponentially suppressed corrections to evolution along the attractor, which are not yet negligible at freeze-out. These findings also suggest a simple numerical approach to QGP dynamics using a finite number of Fourier modes. Physical observables can be expressed in terms of the asymptotic data evaluated at freeze-out. We demonstrate the efficacy of this approach by calculating the final multiplicity distributions and collective flow coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17237v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin An, Micha{\l} Spali\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial naked singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14431v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Primordial black hole formation has been discussed widely, when density perturbations in the early universe cause matter to collapse gravitationally, giving rise to these ultra-compact objects. We propose and point out that such a gravitational collapse would also give rise to primordial naked singularities, that would play an important role in the observable features of present universe. We consider two types of collapse scenarios that give rise to event-like and object-like visible singularities within a cosmological background. We briefly discuss implications of primordial naked singularities, including those for dark matter, vis-a-vis primordial black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14431v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pankaj S. Joshi (Ahmedabad University, India), Sudip Bhattacharyya (TIFR, India)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-horizon chaos beyond Einstein gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09945v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate chaos in the dynamics of massless particles near the horizon of static spherically symmetric black holes in two well-motivated models of $f(R)$ gravity. In both these models, we probe chaos in the particle trajectories (under suitable harmonic confinement) in the vicinity of the black hole horizons, for a set of initial conditions. The particle trajectories, associated Poincar\'e sections, and Lyapunov exponents clearly illustrate the role played by the black hole horizon in the growth of chaos. We find that with increasing energy, the particle trajectories explore regions closer to the black hole horizon, with reduced overlap between two initially close trajectories. We demonstrate how this energy range is controlled by the parameters of the modified gravity theory under consideration. The growth of chaos in such a classical setting is known to respect a surface gravity bound arising from universal aspects of particle dynamics close to the black hole horizon [K. Hashimoto and N. Tanahashi, Phys. Rev. D 95, 024007 (2017)], analogous to the quantum Maldacena, Shenker, and Stanford bound [J. Maldacena et al., J. High Energy Phys. 08 (2016) 106]. Interestingly, both models studied in our work respect the bound, in contrast to some of the other models of $f(R)$ gravity in the existing literature. The work serves as a motivation to use chaos as an additional tool to probe Einstein gravity in the strong gravity regime in the vicinity of black hole horizons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09945v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.124037</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Surajit Das, Surojit Dalui, Rickmoy Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting quantum field theory in Rindler spacetime with superselection rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20995v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum field theory (QFT) in Rindler spacetime is a gateway to understanding unitarity and information loss paradoxes in curved spacetime. Rindler coordinates map Minkowski spacetime onto regions with horizons, effectively dividing accelerated observers into causally disconnected sectors. Employing standard quantum field theory techniques and Bogoliubov transformations between Minkowski and Rindler coordinates yields entanglement between states across these causally separated regions of spacetime. This results in a breakdown of unitarity, implying that information regarding the entangled partner may be irretrievably lost beyond the Rindler horizon. As a consequence, one has a situation of pure states evolving into mixed states. In this paper, we introduce a novel framework for comprehending this phenomenon using a recently proposed formulation of direct-sum quantum field theory (DQFT), which is grounded in superselection rules formulated by the parity and time reversal ($\mathcal{P}\mathcal{T}$) symmetry of Minkowski spacetime. In the context of DQFT applied to Rindler spacetime, we demonstrate that each Rindler observer can, in principle, access pure states within the horizon, thereby restoring unitarity. However, our analysis also reveals the emergence of a thermal spectrum of Unruh radiation. This prompts a reevaluation of entanglement in Rindler spacetime, where we propose a novel perspective on how Rindler observers may reconstruct complementary information beyond the horizon. Furthermore, we revisit the implications of the Reeh-Schlieder theorem within the framework of DQFT. Lastly, we underscore how our findings contribute to ongoing efforts aimed at elucidating the role of unitarity in quantum field theory within the context of de Sitter and black hole spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20995v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10080320</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2024, 10(8), 320</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>K. Sravan Kumar, Jo\~ao Marto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Torsion on Neutron Star Structure in Einstein-Cartan Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05851v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Einstein-Cartan gravity is a close historical sibling of general relativity that allows for spacetime torsion. As a result, angular momentum couples to spacetime geometry in a similar way to energy. While consequences of this are well studied on cosmological scales, their role in neutron star physics is largely under-explored. We study the effects that torsion, sourced by either microphysical spin or macroscopic angular momentum, has on neutron stars. For this, we use a simplified polytropic model to quantify the microphysical coupling to torsion. We also derive expressions to model rotation-induced torsion effects and estimate the consequences for rotating neutron stars with different rotation rates. We find that the presence of torsion in general leads to neutron stars with smaller radii and masses, but higher central densities. Realistic models for microphysical spin lead to torsion effects that have no relevant influence on the neutron star structure. Rotation-induced torsion effects however, can decrease the radius by up to $900\,m$, which is comparable to the increase due to centrifugal forces. Depending on which effect dominates, this leads to a torsion-induced spin-up or spin-down of the neutron star. We conclude that torsion effects due to rotation can not be neglected and are large enough to be tested using current or near-future technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05851v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.104022</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 104022 - Published 12 November, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Jockel, Leon Menger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Stasis from Dynamical Scalars: Tracking Solutions and the Possibility of a Stasis-Induced Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06830v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has recently been realized that many theories of physics beyond the Standard Model give rise to cosmological histories exhibiting extended epochs of cosmological stasis. During such epochs, the abundances of different energy components such as matter, radiation, and vacuum energy each remain fixed despite cosmological expansion. In previous analyses of the stasis phenomenon, these different energy components were modeled as fluids with fixed, unchanging equations of state. In this paper, by contrast, we consider more realistic systems involving dynamical scalars which pass through underdamping transitions as the universe expands. Indeed, such systems might be highly relevant for BSM scenarios involving higher-dimensional bulk moduli and inflatons. Remarkably, we find that stasis emerges even in such situations, despite the appearance of time-varying equations of state. Moreover, this stasis includes several new features which might have important phenomenological implications and applications. For example, in the presence of an additional "background" energy component, we find that the scalars evolve into a "tracking" stasis in which the stasis equation of state automatically tracks that of the background. This phenomenon exists even if the background has only a small initial abundance. We also discuss the intriguing possibility that our results might form the basis of a new "Stasis Inflation" scenario in which no ad-hoc inflaton potential is needed and in which there is no graceful-exit problem. Within such a scenario, the number of e-folds of cosmological expansion produced is directly related to the hierarchies between physical BSM mass scales. Moreover, non-zero matter and radiation abundances can be sustained throughout the inflationary epoch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06830v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keith R. Dienes, Lucien Heurtier, Fei Huang, Tim M. P. Tait, Brooks Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the static spherically symmetric solutions of gravity with a conformally coupled scalar field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14345v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the static spherically symmetric solutions of Einstein's General Relativity with a conformally coupled scalar field in arbitrary dimensions. Using a four rank tensor introduced earlier we recast the field equations in a manifestly symmetric form to elucidate a somewhat less-known feature of dual mapping between solutions. We also show that there is a two-parameter subfamily of solutions which enjoy a duality symmetry and in four dimensions both the BBMB black hole and the Barcelo-Visser wormhole belong to this subfamily. Along the way, we rederive the full three-parameter family of solutions by direct integration of the field equations and a natural choice of ansatz which arguably has several advantages over other previously known methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14345v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad953d</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sourya Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Analytical Taub-NUT like Solution in f(T) Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05172v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct exact analytical Taub-NUT solutions in the context of $f(T)$ gravity. We study the physical properties of the solutions, and compare them with those of the Taub-NUT solution in Einstein gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05172v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua G. Fenwick, Masoud Ghezelbash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous CP Breaking in a QCD-like Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06252v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We examine the phase structure of a QCD-like theory at $\bar\theta =\pi$ obtained from supersymmetric $SU(N)$ QCD perturbed by a small amount of supersymmetry breaking via anomaly mediation (AMSB QCD). The spectrum of this theory matches that of QCD at the massless level, though the superpartners are not decoupled. In this theory it is possible to nail down the phase structure at $\bar\theta=\pi$ as a function of the quark masses and the number of flavors $F$. For one flavor we find that there is a critical quark mass, below which CP is unbroken, while above the critical mass CP is spontaneously broken. At the critical mass there is a second-order phase transition along with a massless $\eta'$. We are able to analytically solve for the minima and the critical mass for $N=2,3$ as well as for the large $N$ limit, while for other $N$ one can find numerical results. For two flavors, we find that CP is always broken as long as the quark masses are equal and non-zero, however there is a non-trivial phase boundary for unequal quark masses, which we find numerically. For $F\geq 3$ we obtain an intricate phase boundary which reproduces the various quark mass limits. All our results are in agreement with the predictions for ordinary QCD that were based on anomaly matching arguments for generalized symmetries and the effective chiral Lagrangian. We also briefly comment on the domain wall solutions first discussed by Draper, and are able to present analytic results for the simplest case of $SU(2)$ with one flavor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06252v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Csaba Cs\'aki, Maximilian Ruhdorfer, Taewook Youn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Family Symmetry in Fluxed GUTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06618v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss modular family symmetry in effective theories based on generic properties of bottom-up local F-theory inspired GUTs broken by fluxes, which we refer to as Fluxed GUTs. We argue that the Yukawa couplings will depend on the complex structure moduli of the matter curves in such a way that they can be modular forms associated with these symmetries. To illustrate the approach we analyse in detail a concrete local fluxed $SU(5)$ GUT with modular $S_4$ family symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06618v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasileios Basiouris, Miguel Crispim Rom\~ao, Stephen F. King, George K. Leontaris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Memory of Primordial Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08472v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Primordial gravitational waves, after they enter the horizon and decay away, leave a residual displacement in test particles: a memory, in analogy with gravitational waves generated by astrophysical sources. The late-time distance between test particles is related to the one at early times by $\xi^i_{\rm late} = \frac{a_{\rm late}}{a_{\rm early}} (\delta^i_j -\frac12 \bar h^i_j)\xi^j_{\rm early}$. Therefore, the deformation of an initial spherical shell does not depend on the cosmological evolution, but only on the primordial value $\bar h^i_{j}$ of the gravitational wave. The memory is thus related to the adiabatic tensor mode that maps the unperturbed FLRW geometries at early and late times; this is analogous to the relation between memory in Minkowski spacetime and the BMS group. The primordial memory is also connected to the consistency relations of cosmological correlators, as the flat-space memory is related to the soft theorems for gravitational wave emission. We comment on the signature of the effect on the CMB $B$-modes and on the large-scale structure. There is also a primordial memory effect that is subleading in the spatial gradients of the wave: it is encoded in the rotation of free-falling gyroscopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08472v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Creminelli, Filippo Vernizzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Stasis from a Single Annihilating Particle Species: Extending Stasis Into the Thermal Domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16255v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has recently been shown that extended cosmological epochs can exist during which the abundances associated with different energy components remain constant despite cosmological expansion. Indeed, this "stasis" behavior has been found to arise generically in many BSM theories containing large towers of states, and even serves as a cosmological attractor. However, all previous studies of stasis took place within non-thermal environments, or more specifically within environments in which thermal effects played no essential role in realizing or sustaining the stasis. In this paper, we demonstrate that stasis can emerge and serve as an attractor even within thermal environments, with thermal effects playing a critical role in the stasis dynamics. Moreover, within such environments, we find that no towers of states are needed -- a single state experiencing two-body annihilations will suffice. This work thus extends the stasis phenomenon into the thermal domain and demonstrates that thermal effects can also generally give rise to an extended stasis epoch, even when only a single matter species is involved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16255v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonah Barber, Keith R. Dienes, Brooks Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality defect in a deformed transverse-field Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17317v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Physical quantities with long lifetimes have both theoretical significance in the study of quantum many-body systems and practical implications for quantum technologies. In this manuscript, we investigate the roles played by topological defects in the construction of quasi-conserved quantities, using as a prototypical example the Kramers-Wannier duality defect in a deformed 1d quantum transverse field Ising model. We construct the duality defect Hamiltonian in three different ways: half-chain Kramers-Wannier transformation, utilization of techniques in the Ising fusion category, and defect-modified weak integrability breaking deformation. The third method is also applicable for the study of generic integrable defects under weak integrability breaking deformations. We also work out the deformation of defect-modified higher charges in the model and study their slower decay behavior. Furthermore, we consider the corresponding duality defect twisted deformed Floquet transverse field Ising model, and investigate the stability of the isolated zero mode associated with the duality defect in the integrable Floquet Ising model, under such weak integrability breaking deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17317v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Yan, Robert Konik, Aditi Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Unruh effect for hyperbolic observers in spacetimes of maximal proper acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18155v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, after the introduction of the notion of spacetime of maximal proper acceleration and its associated fundamental geometric and kinematic properties, the Unruh temperature formula is generalized to the case of hyperbolic observers in spacetimes of maximal proper acceleration. Such a generalization implies the existence of a maximal value for the Unruh temperature. We discuss this result for an electrodynamic model of point charged particle in a spacetime of maximal proper acceleration. It is shown that according to this mathematical model, the maximal Unruh temperature must be of order $10^5\, K$ for current high acceleration gradient laser-plasma acceleration experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18155v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Gallego Torrom\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Chirotropical Grassmannian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07293v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent developments in particle physics have revealed deep connections between scattering amplitudes and tropical geometry. From the heart of this relationship emerged the chirotropical Grassmannian $\text{Trop}^\chi \text{G}(k,n)$ and the chirotropical Dressian $\text{Dr}^\chi(k,n)$, polyhedral fans built from uniform realizable chirotopes that encode the combinatorial structure of Generalized Feynman Diagrams. We prove that $\text{Trop}^\chi \text{G}(3,n) = \text{Dr}^\chi(3,n)$ for $n = 6,7,8$, and develop algorithms to compute these objects from their rays modulo lineality. Using these algorithms, we compute all chirotropical Grassmannians $\text{Trop}^\chi \text{G}(3,n)$ for $n = 6,7,8$ across all isomorphism classes of chirotopes. We prove that each chirotopal configuration space $X^\chi(3,6)$ is diffeomorphic to a polytope and propose an associated canonical logarithmic differential form. Finally, we show that the equality between chirotropical Grassmannian and Dressian fails for $(k,n) = (4,8)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07293v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Antolini, Nick Early</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalization of the optical band gap through an effective Thirring interaction for massive Dirac-like electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10621v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze mass renormalization in massive Dirac-like systems in (2+1) dimensions arising from electron-phonon interactions at finite temperatures, employing the large-$N$ expansion. Our model combines the low-energy description of charge carriers in a buckled honeycomb lattice with the low-energy approximation for phonons and electron-phonon interactions in two-dimensional materials. Consequently, the system is modeled as a massive Dirac-like field coupled to a two-component vector field $\mathcal{A}_i$, representing the phonon modes. This framework allows us to compute the one-loop electron self-energy at finite temperature, from which we derive the renormalized band gap, $m^R$. The effective model is subsequently applied to describe the renormalized optical band gap in monolayers of transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs), including MoS$_2$, MoSe$_2$, WS$_2$, and WSe$_2$. A good agreement is observed with experimental data for reasonable values of the ultraviolet cutoff, $\Lambda \approx 1$ eV. Our main findings indicate that $m^R$ remains nearly constant at low temperatures, whereas at higher temperatures it decreases linearly with the temperature $T$. Specifically, we find that $m^R$ reduces by approximately $\approx [0.1,0.2]$ eV as the temperature increases from $\approx 4$ K to $500$ K, consistent with recent experimental observations. Furthermore, we estimate the temperature range at which the transition to the linear regime occurs, obtaining typical values within $\approx [110,150]$ K for the four materials under consideration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10621v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilberto Bezerra, Van S\'ergio Alves, Leandro O. Nascimento, Luis Fern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connecting Gravity and Quantum Physics: Primordial Black Holes and the Evolution of the Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11047v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study presents a novel framework to explore the fundamental relationship between gravity and quantum mechanics, with particular emphasis on the role of primordial black holes (PBHs) in cosmology. Through the concept of self-gravitating condensed light, specifically in the form of the experimentally discovered photon Bose-Einstein condensate, this work examines the quantum attributes of PBHs and their implications for early universe dynamics, baryogenesis, and the very early formation of galaxies and large-scale structures, established by JWST data. The model also investigates quantized characteristics of PBHs, such as mass, entropy, and temperature, suggesting that quantum processes are fundamental to black hole mechanics. By addressing issues like the cosmological constant problem and the information loss paradox, dark matter, and dark energy, this work provides insights into Planck-scale physics and proposes that PBHs may serve as a bridge between quantum theory and general relativity. This study ultimately posits that understanding PBH physics is essential to resolving major cosmological and astrophysical paradoxes for the ultimate unification of quantum mechanics with gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11047v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Borsevici, Samit Ganguly, Goutam Manna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Local Classical Field Theory with Fractional Operators on $\mathbb{S}^3 \times \mathbb{R}^1$ Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16731v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a theoretical framework on non-local classical field theory using fractional integrodifferential operators. Due to the lack of easily manageable symmetries in traditional fractional calculus and the difficulties that arise in the formalism of multi-fractional calculus over $\mathbb{R}^{\text{D}}$ space, we introduce a set of new fractional operators over the $\mathbb{S}^3 \times \mathbb{R}^1$ space. The redefined fractional integral operator results in the non-trivial measure canonically, and they can account for the spacetime symmetries for the underlying space $\mathbb{S}^3 \times \mathbb{R}^1$ with the Lorentzian signature $(+, -, -, -, -)$. We conclude that the field equation for the non-local classical field can be obtained as the consequence of the optimisation of the action by employing the non-local variations in the field after defining the non-local Lagrangian density, namely, $\mathcal{L}(\phi_{a}\left(x\right), \mathbb{\eth}^\alpha \phi_{a}\left(x\right))$, as the function of the symmetric fractional derivative of the field, e.g. in the context of the kinetic term, and the field itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16731v3</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhi Savaliya, Ayush Bidlan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge fields induced by curved spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03647v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: I found an extended duality (triality) between Dirac fermions in periodic spacetime metrics, nonrelativistic fermions in gauge fields (e.g., Harper-Hofstadter model), and in periodic scalar fields on a lattice (e.g., Aubry-Andr\'e model). This indicates an unexpected equivalence between spacetime metrics, gauge fields, and scalar fields on the lattice, which is understood as different physical representations of the same mathematical object, the quantum group $\mathcal{U}_q(\mathfrak{sl}_2)$. This quantum group is generated by the exponentiation of two canonical conjugate operators, namely a linear combination of position and momentum (periodic spacetime metrics), the two components of the gauge invariant momentum (gauge fields), position and momentum (periodic scalar fields). Hence, on a lattice, Dirac fermions in a periodic spacetime metric are equivalent to nonrelativistic fermions in a periodic scalar field after a proper canonical transformation. The three lattice Hamiltonians (periodic spacetime metric, Harper-Hofstadter, and Aubry-Andr\'e) share the same properties, namely fractal phase diagrams, self-similarity, topological invariants, flat bands, and topological quantized current in the incommensurate regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03647v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Marra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New analysis of SNeIa Pantheon Catalog: Variable speed of light as an alternative to dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05262v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In A&amp;A 412, 35 (2003) Blanchard, Douspis, Rowan-Robinson, and Sarkar (BDRS) slightly modified the primordial fluctuation spectrum and produced an excellent fit to WMAP's CMB power spectrum for an Einstein-de Sitter (EdS) universe, bypassing dark energy. Curiously, they obtained a Hubble value of $H_0\approx46$, in sharp conflict with the canonical range $H_0\sim67-73$. However, we will demonstrate that the reduced value of $H_0\approx46$ achieved by BDRS is fully compatible with the use of variable speed of light in analyzing the late-time cosmic acceleration observed in Type Ia supernovae (SNeIa). In arXiv:2412.04257 [gr-qc] we uncovered a hidden aspect in a generic class of scale-invariant actions: the dynamics of the dilaton can induce a variation in the speed of light as $c\propto\chi^{1/2}$, causing $c$ to vary alongside $\chi$ across spacetime. For an EdS universe with varying $c$, besides the effects of cosmic expansion, light waves emitted from distant SNeIa are further subject to a refraction effect, which alters the Lemaitre redshift relation to $1+z=a^{-3/2}$. Based on this new formula, we achieve a fit to the SNeIa Pantheon Catalog exceeding the quality of the $\Lambda$CDM model. Crucially, our approach does not require dark energy and produces $H_0=47.2$ in strong alignment with the BDRS finding of $H_0\approx46$. Hence, BDRS's analysis of the (early-time) CMB power spectrum and our variable-$c$ analysis of the (late-time) Hubble diagram of SNeIa fully agree on two counts: (i) the dark energy hypothesis is avoided, and (ii) $H_0$ is reduced to $\sim47$, which also yields an age $t_0=2/(3H_0)=13.8$ Gy for an EdS universe, without requiring dark energy. Most importantly, we will demonstrate that the late-time acceleration can be attributed to the declining speed of light in an expanding EdS universe, rather than to a dark energy component.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05262v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoang Ky Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic relativistic viscous hydrodynamics from the Metropolis algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10306v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an algorithm for simulating stochastic relativistic fluid dynamics based on Metropolis updates. Each step of the algorithm begins with an update based on ideal hydrodynamics. This is followed by proposing random (spatial) momentum transfers between fluid cells, keeping the total energy fixed. These proposals are then accepted or rejected using the change in entropy as a statistical weight. The algorithm reproduces relativistic viscous hydrodynamics in the ``Density Frame", which is a formulation of viscous hydrodynamics we review and clarify here. This formulation is first order in time and requires no auxiliary dynamical fields such as $\Pi^{\mu\nu}$. The only parameters are the shear and bulk viscosities and the equation of state. By adopting the 3+1 split of general relativity, we extend the Metropolis algorithm to general space-time coordinates, such as Bjorken coordinates, which are commonly used to simulate heavy-ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10306v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jay Bhambure, Rajeev Singh, Derek Teaney</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
