<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Giant Gravitons and Volume Minimisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a precise correspondence between the giant graviton expansion of the superconformal index of field theories in $D\leq 4$, and the master volume formalism of Gauntlett, Martelli and Sparks (GMS) which determines the near horizon geometries of certain BPS black holes and black strings in supergravity. We focus on 4d $\mathcal{N}=1$ superconformal field theories arising on the world volume of $N$ D3 branes placed at the tip of a cone over a toric Sasaki-Einstein manifold SE$_{5}$, the simplest example of which is $S^5$, corresponding to $\mathcal{N}=4$ super-Yang-Mills. The giant graviton expansion realises the superconformal index as the sum of contributions from wrapped D3 branes in the dual AdS$_{5}\times \text{SE}_{5}$. We argue that, for large wrapping numbers, the asymptotics of each such contribution is governed by the master volume of a particular metric deformation of $\text{SE}_5$ (suitably fibred over $S^{3}$). In particular, the wrapping numbers of a generic giant graviton configuration are identified with K\"{a}hler moduli of the corresponding metric. We further show that at large $N$ the entropy function of the relevant AdS$_5\times \text{SE}_5$ BPS rotating black hole is recovered by extremising over these moduli. Our results suggest that the complex Euclidean geometries corresponding to rotating BPS black holes in AdS$_{5}$ are determined by a close analogue of GMS volume minimisation, and that conversely, the off-shell geometries considered in such minimisation procedures should be understood as the near-horizon geometries of back-reacted giant gravitons. We present analogous results for 3d $\mathcal{N}=2$ theories holographically dual to M-theory on AdS$_4\times \text{SE}_7$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05357v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng-Yu Chen, Nick Dorey, Sanefumi Moriyama, Rishi Mouland, Canberk Sanli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher derivative couplings with multi-tensor multiplets in 6D supergravity, action and anomalies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit six-dimensional (1,0) supergravity coupled to nT tensor multiplets and Yang-Mills fields for nT&gt;1 for which no covariant action exists. We construct the action in the Henneaux-Teitelboim approach and in the presence of a gauge anomaly. We moreover obtain the supersymmetric Green-Schwarz counterterm for the gravitational anomaly for arbitrary matter content.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05365v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Bossard, Axel Kleinschmidt, Ergin Sezgin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The boundary entropy function for interface conformal field theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05381v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1+1 dimensional conformal field theory with a boundary the boundary contribution to the entanglement entropy is determined by a single number $g$ effectively counting the boundary degrees of freedom. In contrast, in 1+1 dimensional interface CFTs the corresponding quantity is a non-trivial {\it function} depending on the position of the interval relative to the interface, giving access to much more detailed information about the defect. In this work we determined this $g$-function in several examples using holography, derive some of its basic properties as well as its behavior under RG flows from holography and strong subadditivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05381v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Afxonidis, Andreas Karch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Correlators in Perturbative Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05384v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite tremendous progress in our understanding of scattering amplitudes in perturbative (super-) gravity, much less is known about other asymptotic observables, such as correlation functions of detector operators. In this paper, we initiate the study of detector operators and their correlation functions in perturbative quantum gravity. Inspired by recent progress in field theory, we introduce a broad class of new asymptotic observables in gravity. We outline how correlation functions of detector operators can be efficiently computed from squared, state-summed amplitudes, allowing us to harness the wealth of perturbative scattering amplitude data to explore these observables. We then compute the two-point correlator of energy detectors in the annihilation of two scalars into gravitons, in Einstein gravity minimally coupled to a massive scalar field. We study the kinematic limits of this correlator, finding that it is finite in the collinear limit, and exhibits a soft divergence in the back-to-back limit, as expected from the understanding of the factorization of gravitational amplitudes in the soft and collinear limits. Our results offer a first exploration into the structure of detector operators and their correlators in perturbative quantum gravity, and we outline numerous directions for future study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05384v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Herrmann, Murat Kologlu, Ian Moult</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdS/CFT Duality and Holographic Renormalization Group: A Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we review aspects of anti de Sitter/conformal field theory (AdS/CFT) duality and the notion of holographic renormalization group (RG) flow. We start by discussing supersymmetry and construct the N = 4 super Yang-Mills theory in d = 4 by Kaluza-Klein dimensional reduction method. Then, we study the large-N limit and how it leads to the AdS/CFT duality. Using AdS/CFT, we then study the super-gravitational dual flows to the RG flows in CFT generated by marginal and relevant deformations, using the N = 4 super Yang-Mills theory as an example. Then, we prove the Zamolodchikov C-theorem holographically. Finally, we discuss the Wilsonian holographic renormalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05446v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative stability of non-Abelian electric field solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05458v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider SU(2) gauge theory with a scalar field in the fundamental representation. The model is known to contain electric field solutions sourced by the scalar field that are distinct from embedded Maxwell electric fields. We examine the perturbative stability of the solution and identify a region of parameter space where the solution is stable. In the regime where the scalar field has a negative mass squared, the solution has two branches and we identify an instability in one of the branches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05458v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jude Pereira, Tanmay Vachaspati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian formalism for Bose excitations in a plasma with a non-Abelian interaction II: plasmon - hard particle scattering and energy loss</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is shown that the Hamiltonian formalism proposed previously in [1] to describe the nonlinear dynamics of only {\it soft} fermionic and bosonic excitations contains much more information than initially assumed. In this paper, we have demonstrated in detail that it also proved to be very appropriate and powerful in describing a wide range of other physical phenomena, including the scattering of colorless plasmons off {\it hard} thermal (or external) color-charged particles moving in hot quark-gluon plasma. A generalization of the Poisson superbracket including both anticommuting variables for hard modes and normal variables of the soft Bose field, is presented for the case of a continuous medium. The corresponding Hamilton equations are defined, and the most general form of the third- and fourth-order interaction Hamiltonians is written out in terms of the normal boson field variables and hard momentum modes of the quark-gluon plasma. The canonical transformations involving both bosonic and hard mode degrees of freedom of the system under consideration, are discussed. The canonicity conditions for these transformations based on the Poisson superbracket, are derived. The most general structure of canonical transformations in the form of integro-power series up to sixth order in a new normal field variable and a new hard mode variable, is presented. For the hard momentum mode of quark-gluon plasma excitations, an ansatz separating the color and momentum degrees of freedom, is proposed. The question of approximation of the total effective scattering amplitude when the momenta of hard excitations are much larger than those of soft excitations of the plasma, is considered. An application of the developed Hamilton theory to the problem of calculating energy loss of an energetic color particle propagating through a hot QCD-medium, is considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05581v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. A. Markov, M. A. Markova, N. Yu. Markov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The UV Sensitivity of Axion Monodromy Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit axion monodromy inflation in the context of UV-complete theories and uncover a novel sensitivity of cosmological observables to heavy fields with masses far above the Hubble scale, such as the moduli of flux compactifications. By studying a string-inspired two-field extension of axion monodromy, we reveal that the oscillatory modulation of the axion potential leads to continuous excitation of heavy fields during inflation when the modulation frequency exceeds the field masses. This finding challenges the conventional single-field description, as heavy moduli cannot be simply integrated out. Using a full bootstrap analysis, we demonstrate that this mechanism produces cosmological collider signals that bypass the usual Boltzmann suppression for heavy masses. Specifically, we identify detectably large signatures of heavy moduli in the primordial bispectrum, offering a promising avenue for probing high-energy physics through cosmological observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05762v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Pajer, Dong-Gang Wang, Bowei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BMS particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct wavefunctions for unitary irreducible representations (UIRs) of the Bondi-Metzner-Sachs (BMS) group, i.e. BMS particles, and show that they describe quantum superpositions of (Poincar\'e) particles propagating on inequivalent gravity vacua. This follows from reconsidering McCarthy's classification of BMS group UIRs through a unique, Lorentz-invariant but non-linear, decomposition of supermomenta into hard and soft pieces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06002v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Bekaert, Laura Donnay, Yannick Herfray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional model of interaction of a non-relativistic particle with scalar mesons in the strong coupling limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bogolyubov transformations are introduced into the nonrelativistic model of particle interaction with scalar mesons. Within the framework of the generalized Hamiltonian formalism developed by Dirac, a translation-invariant perturbation theory in inverse powers of the coupling constant is constructed. Transmission and reflection coefficients are obtained, the S-matrix is written in a holomorphic representation, and the matrix element is calculated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06046v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Shurgaia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertex operators for the superstring with manifest $d=6$ $N=1$ supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: After extending the six-dimensional hybrid formalism for the superstring by adding $d=6$ $N=1$ superspace variables and unconstrained bosonic ghosts, manifestly spacetime supersymmetric vertex operators $U$ are constructed. BRST invariance of $U$ is proven to imply the SYM equations of motion in $d=6$ $N=1$ superspace. It is then shown that spacetime supersymmetric scattering amplitudes can be computed in a similar manner as in the non-minimal pure spinor formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06194v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cassiano A. Daniel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aspects of supersymmetry breaking driven inflation in orbifold models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06315v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider gravitationally induced corrections to inflaton potentials driven by supersymmetry breaking in a five-dimensional supergravity, compactified on a $ S_1/Z_2 $ orbifold. The supersymmetry breaking takes place on the hidden brane and is transmitted to the visible brane through finite one loop graphs giving rise to an inflaton potential which includes gravitationally induced terms. These corrections are significant for inflationary cosmology and have the potential to modify the predictions of widely studied supergravity models if the latter are embedded in this framework. To explore these effects we examine two classes of models those inspired by no-scale supergravity models and $\alpha$-attractors. Both models are compatible with current cosmological observations but face chalenges in reconciling enhanced values for the scalar power spectrum $ P_\zeta$ with cosmological data, particularly regarding the tensor to scalar ratio $r$. In fact $ P_\zeta \gtrsim 10^{-2}$ results to $ r &gt; \mathcal{O} (0.1) $, outside the limits put by current data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06315v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Diamandis, K. Kaskavelis, A. B. Lahanas, G. Pavlopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A time-like window into tensionless worldsheets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rindler worldsheets are known to acquire a Carrollian structure at infinite acceleration, marking their tensionless limit. This work extends the same paradigm to time-evolving worldsheets in the background target spacetime spanning the Kasner wedges. Specifically, we demonstrate that approaching the null horizons of the Kasner worldsheet induces a Carrollian structure, necessitating an infinite limit on the time-evolution parameter. We further examine how the associated Bogoliubov transformations on the usual tensile Kasner worldsheets -- encompassing quantum modes, vacuum states, and oscillators -- provide insights into their yet-unexplored tensionless regime. Intriguingly, phenomena such as null string complementarity (i.e., the emergence of open string physics from closed strings) and Hagedorn physics naturally arise in the quantum vacuum of tensionless worldsheets. These findings validate that time-like entanglement in Kasner worldsheets is not merely analogous to, but exactly equivalent to, space-like entanglement in Rindler worldsheets, viewed in distinct causally-disconnected regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06387v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudip Karan, Bibhas Ranjan Majhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The AdS$_3\times $S$^3$ Virasoro-Shapiro amplitude with RR flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the AdS Virasoro-Shapiro amplitude for scattering of dilatons in type IIB string theory with pure RR flux on $AdS_3\times S^3\times M_4$ for $M_4=T^4$ or $K3$, to all orders in $\alpha'$ in a small AdS curvature expansion. This is achieved by comparing the flat space limit of the dual D1D5 CFT correlator to an ansatz for the amplitude as a worldsheet integral in terms of single valued multiple polylogarithms. The first curvature correction is fully fixed in this way, and satisfies consistency checks in the high energy limit, and by comparison of the energy of massive string operators to a semiclassical expansion. Our result gives infinite predictions for CFT data in the planar limit at strong coupling, which can guide future integrability studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06429v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shai M. Chester, De-liang Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on thermal holographic RG flows in a 3D gauged supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We continue our studies of holographic renormalization group (RG) flows for a 3d truncated supergravity model, the scalar potential of which can have either one or three extrema depending on the radius of the target manifold. We construct numerically and analytically thermal holographic RG flows, which are described by asymptotically AdS$_3$ black holes (non-rotating BTZ) characterized by the value of the scalar field on the horizon. We find two classes of RG flows with monotonic and non-monotonic behavior of the scalar field. The first one exists for both types of the potential, while the second one appears only for the potential with three extrema. For the slowly changing scalar field we find a special class of RG flows, which are described by the scalar field in the BTZ black hole geometry. For such flows we present an analytic solution for the scalar field from the horizon to the boundary. We discuss thermodynamical properties of the constructed holographic RG flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06536v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasia A. Golubtsova, Eric Gourgoulhon, Mikhail A. Podoinitsyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New leading contributions to non-gaussianity in single field inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06616v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the bispectrum of primordial density perturbations in CMB to second order in the slow-roll parameters of single field inflation. We found a large logarithmic contribution which is at least of the same order as the leading order result and can lead to an enhancement by an order of magnitude in a large class of models, including hilltop inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06616v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignatios Antoniadis, Auttakit Chatrabhuti, Jules Cunat, Hiroshi Isono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Edge Modes in Yang-Mills Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the symplectic structure and dynamics of Yang-Mills theory in the presence of a boundary. We introduce a decomposition of the fields on a Cauchy slice such that the symplectic form splits cleanly into independent bulk and edge parts. However, we find that the dynamics inherently couples these two symplectic sectors, a feature arising from the non-abelian nature of the gauge group. This is shown by extending to Yang-Mills theory the dynamical edge mode boundary condition recently introduced in Maxwell theory. We finish with analyses of the weak-field expansion and the horizon limit, finding in the latter case that the dynamical interplay between bulk and edge degrees of freedom persists.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06672v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Ball, Luca Ciambelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-invertible twisted compactification of class $\mathcal S$ theory and $(B,B,B)$ branes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06729v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study non-invertible twisted compactification of class $\mathcal S$ theories on $S^1$: we insert a non-invertible symmetry defect at $S^1$ extending along remaining directions and then compactify on $S^1$. We show that the resulting 3d theory is 3d $\mathcal N=4$ sigma model whose target space is a hyperK\"ahler submanifold of Hitchin moduli space, i.e. a $(B,B,B)$ brane. The $(B,B,B)$ branes arise from finite subgroups of the mapping class group of underlying Riemann surface. For type $A_1$, genus $2$ class $\mathcal S$ theory we calculate concrete examples of these $(B,B,B)$ branes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06729v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yankun Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remnants of black holes from rainbow gravity in terms of a new VSL theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1606.06285</link>
      <description>arXiv:1606.06285v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The gravity's rainbow function is derived in terms of a new varying speed of light (VSL) theory that varying velocity of light in the rainbow gravity becomes smaller when the energy of photons increases. In light of the new theory we calculate the modified temperature, entropy and heat capacity of the Schwarzschild, Kerr, AdS black holes, as well as spinning black rings. Our results demonstrate that in rainbow gravity the behaviors of various black holes have remarkably essential difference from those of standard black holes near the Planck scale, and a logarithmic term emerges in the formula of the entropy of every black object.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1606.06285v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying-Jie Zhao, Xiaojie Li, Guang-Rui Yao, Yan-Fang Ji, Nisar Ahmad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accidental Symmetries, Hilbert Series, and Friends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05359v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accidental symmetries in effective field theories can be established by computing and comparing Hilbert series. This invites us to study them with the tools of invariant theory. Applying this technology, we spotlight three classes of accidental symmetries that hold to all orders for non-derivative interactions. They are broken by derivative interactions and become ordinary finite-order accidental symmetries. To systematically understand the origin and the patterns of accidental symmetries, we introduce a novel mathematical construct - a (non-transitive) binary relation between subgroups that we call $friendship$. Equipped with this, we derive new criteria for all-order accidental symmetries in terms of $friends$, and criteria for finite-order accidental symmetries in terms of $friends\ ma\ non\ troppo$. They allow us to verify and identify accidental symmetries more efficiently without computing the Hilbert series. We demonstrate the success of our new criteria by applying them to a variety of sample accidental symmetries, including the custodial symmetry in the Higgs sector of the Standard Model effective field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05359v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjam\'in Grinstein, Xiaochuan Lu, Carlos Mir\'o, Pablo Qu\'ilez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Invertible Peccei-Quinn Symmetry, Natural 2HDM Alignment, and the Visible Axion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05362v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We identify $m_{12}^2$ as a spurion of non-invertible Peccei-Quinn symmetry in the type II 2HDM with gauged quark flavor. Thus a UV theory which introduces quark color-flavor monopoles can naturally realize alignment without decoupling and can furthermore revive the Weinberg-Wilczek axion. As an example we consider the $SU(9)$ theory of color-flavor unification, which needs no new fermions. This is the first model-building use of non-invertible symmetry to find a Dirac natural explanation for a small $\textit{relevant}$ parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05362v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Delgado, Seth Koren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological entanglement entropy meets holographic entropy inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05484v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological entanglement entropy (TEE) is an efficient way to detect topological order in the ground state of gapped Hamiltonians. The seminal work of Kitaev and Preskill~\cite{preskill-kitaev-tee} and simultaneously by Levin and Wen~\cite{levin-wen-tee} proposed information quantities that can probe the TEE. In the present work, we explain why the subtraction schemes in the proposed information quantities~\cite{levin-wen-tee,preskill-kitaev-tee} work for the computation of TEE and generalize them for arbitrary number of subregions by explicitly noting the necessary conditions for an information quantity to capture TEE. Our conditions differentiate the probes defined by Kitaev-Preskill and Levin-Wen into separate classes. While there are infinitely many possible probes of TEE, we focus particularly on the cyclic quantities $Q_{2n+1}$ and multi-information $I_n$. We also show that the holographic entropy inequalities are satisfied by the quantum entanglement entropy of the non-degenerate ground state of a topologically ordered two-dimensional medium with a mass gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05484v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joydeep Naskar, Sai Satyam Samal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A physical interpretation of Brout-Englert-Higgs mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05495v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new interpretation of the Brout-Englert-Higgs (BEH) mechanism is proposed. The primitive world before the mass generation of fermions occurs is regarded as a relativistic virtual many-body state of massless fermion and antifermion taking both timelike and spacelike paths. In order for the many-body state to have a physical meaning independently of observers, virtual massless fermions and antifermions there should move along a common direction of time, even if they are observed from any inertial fame. As a lowest-energy-state satisfying this condition, the physical vacuum with broken symmetry is derived. Since symmetry breaking arises from the kinematical reason, whatever effective interaction acts on massless fermion, it generates fermion's mass, because it escapes from the role of causing symmetry breaking. In the physical vacuum, pairs of fermion and antifermion behaves as quasi bosons due to the overlap of their wave function. Due to Bose statistics, the physical vacuum shows a kind of rigidity in transverse perturbations, and it explains the origin of the vacuum condensate in the BEH potential. As a dynamical part of the above effective interaction, a Higgs-like excitation appears. This interpretation sheds a new light on the fundamental problems inherent in the BEH mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05495v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun-ichiro Koh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are regular black holes from pure gravity classified within the same thermodynamical topology?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05811v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Regular black holes, which avoid the essential center singularities, can be constructed through various methods, including nonlinear electrodynamics and quantum corrections. Recently, it was shown that via an infinite tower of higher-curvature corrections, one can obtain different regular black hole solutions in any spacetime dimension $D\geq 5$. Utilizing the concept of thermodynamical topology, we examine these black holes as topological thermodynamic defects, classifying them into distinct topological categories based on their generalized free energy. We find that the Hawking temperature of the black hole has at least one zero point at the small horizon radius limit. Under this fact, the regular black holes generated through the purely gravitational theories exhibit universal thermodynamical behaviors, strongly suggesting they belong to the same topological class. We presents a comprehensive analysis of these properties, providing a clearer understanding of the fundamental nature of regular black holes and their classification within the framework of thermodynamical topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05811v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng-Wei Wang, Shan-Ping Wu, Shao-Wen Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chaotic motion of the charged test particle in Kerr-MOG black hole with explicit symplectic algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06122v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, Kerr-MOG black hole has attracted widespread research interest and has been widely used in fields such as galaxy rotation curves, gravitational lensing in galaxy clusters, and the formation of large-scale structures in the universe. In this paper, we mainly focus on dynamics of the charged particle around Kerr-MOG black hole. At first, the field equations for the charged particle under the Scalar-Tensor-Vector Gravity (STVG) theory are presented. Then, according to the characteristics of the Hamiltonian system, the Hamiltonian can be decomposed into five integrable parts, and three kinds of explicit symplectic algorithms are constructed. Numerical experiments show that the $PR{K_6}4$ algorithm is the optimal one. At last, the Poincar\'e section and the fast Lyapunov indicator (FLI) are used to explore dynamic evolution of the particle. From the numerical results, it is easy to find that the energy $E$, the angular momentum $L$, the magnetic field parameter $\beta$, the black hole spin parameter $a$, and the gravitational field strength parameter $\alpha$ have an impact on the motion of the particle. In particular, the chaotic region increases as $E$, $\beta$, or $\alpha$ increases, but decreases with the increases of $a$ or $L$. Moreover, when any two of the five parameters are applied simultaneously, it is easy to observe that $a$ and $L$ play a dominant role.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06122v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Meng Xu, Da-Zhu Ma, Wen-Fu Cao, Kai Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Roberge-Weiss endpoint in $(2+1)$-flavor QCD with background magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06326v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we discuss our preliminary results regarding the so-called Roberge-Weiss (RW) transition, which is found for imaginary values of the baryon chemical potential, in the presence of a background magnetic field. We perform lattice QCD simulations on $N_t = 6, 8$ lattices with $2+1$ flavors of stout-staggered fermions at physical quark masses and the tree-level Symanzik improved gauge action. We determine the location the RW endpoint at finite magnetic fields and we study the order of the transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06326v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Zambello, Massimo D'Elia, Lorenzo Maio, Giuseppe Zanichelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanisms Behind the Aschenbach Effect in Non-Rotating Black Hole Spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06357v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: General relativity predicts that a rotating black hole drags the spacetime due to its spin. This effect can influence the motion of nearby objects, causing them to either fall into the black hole or orbit around it. In classical Newtonian mechanics, as the radius of the orbit increases, the angular velocity of an object in a stable circular orbit decreases. However, Aschenbach discovered that for a hypothetical non-rotating observer, contrary to usual behavior, the angular velocity increases with radius in certain regions. Although the possibility of observing rare and less probable rotational behaviors in a rotating structure is not unlikely or impossible. However, observing such behaviors in a static structure is not only intriguing but also thought-provoking, as it raises questions about the factors that might play a role in such phenomena. In seeking answers to this question, various static models, particularly in the context of nonlinear fields, were examined, with some results presented as examples in the article. Among the models studied, the model of Magnetic Black Holes in 4D Einstein Gauss Bonnet Massive Gravity Coupled to Nonlinear Electrodynamics (M-EGB-Massive) appears to be a candidate for this phenomenon. In the analysis section, we will discuss the commonalities of this model with previous models that have exhibited this phenomenon and examine the cause of this phenomenon. Finally, we will state whether this phenomenon is observable in other black holes and, if not, why</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06357v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Ali S. Afshar, Jafar Sadeghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ising dual-reflection interface: $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry, Majorana strong zero modes and SPT phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate an interface in the transverse field quantum Ising chain connecting an ordered ferromagnetic phase and a disordered paramagnetic phase that are Kramers-Wannier duals of each other. Unlike prior studies focused on non-invertible defects, this interface exhibits a symmetry that combines Kramers-Wannier transformation with spatial reflection. We demonstrate that, under open boundary conditions, this setup gives rise to a discrete $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry, encompassing the conventional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ Ising parity as a subgroup, while in a closed geometry a non-invertible symmetry emerges. Using the Jordan-Wigner transformation, we map the spin chain onto a solvable quadratic Majorana fermion system. In this formulation, the $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry is realized manifestly as a parity-dependent reflection operation with respect to a Majorana site, in contrast to the conventional reflection which mirrors with respect to the central link of the Majorana chain. Additionally, we construct Majorana strong zero modes that retain the $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry, ensure degeneracies of all energy eigenstates, and are robust under generic local symmetry-preserving perturbations of the fermion model, including interactions. In an open geometry of the studied model, we identify two regimes that exhibit different degeneracy patterns. We discuss whether this is a manifestation of distinct fermion symmetry-protected topological orders protected by the $\mathbb{Z}_4$ symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06377v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juliane Graf, Federica Maria Surace, Marcus Berg, Sergej Moroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full-colour double-virtual amplitudes for associated production of a Higgs boson with a bottom-quark pair at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06519v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the double-virtual amplitudes contributing to the production of a Higgs boson in association with a $b\bar{b}$ pair at the Large Hadron Collider. We perform the computation within the five-flavour scheme, which employs massless bottom quarks and finite bottom-Yukawa coupling, taking into account all the colour structures. We derive the analytic form of the helicity amplitudes through finite-field reconstruction techniques. The analytic expressions have been implemented in a public C++ library, and we demonstrate that evaluations are sufficiently stable and efficient for use in phenomenological studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06519v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Badger, Heribertus Bayu Hartanto, Rene Poncelet, Zihao Wu, Yang Zhang, Simone Zoia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of symmetries in finite temperature $N_f=2$ QCD with M\"obius Domain Wall Fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06574v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report on the ongoing study of symmetry of $N_f=2$ QCD around the critical temperature. Our simulations of $N_f = 2$ QCD employ the M\"obius domain-wall fermion action with residual mass $\sim 1\mbox{MeV}$ or less, maintaining a good chiral symmetry. Using the screening masses from the two point spatial correlators we compare the mass difference between channels connected through various symmetry transformations. Our analysis focuses on restoration of the $SU(2)_L\times SU(2)_R$ as well as anomalously broken axial $U(1)_A$. We also present additional study of a potential $SU(2)_{CS}$ symmetry which may emerge at sufficiently high temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06574v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Ward, Sinya Aoki, Yasumichi Aoki, Hidenori Fukaya, Shoji Hashimoto, Issaku Kanamori, Takashi Kaneko, Jishnu Goswami, Yu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal bases for two-parameter quantum groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06670v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, we construct dual PBW bases of the positive and negative subalgebras of the two-parameter quantum groups $U_{r,s}(\mathfrak{g})$ in classical types, as used in our earlier work arXiv:2407.01450. Following the ideas of Leclerc and Clark-Hill-Wang, we introduce the two-parameter shuffle algebra and relate it to the subalgebras above. We then use the combinatorics of dominant Lyndon words to establish the main results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06670v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Martin, Alexander Tsymbaliuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric distances between closed universes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06696v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The large-scale structure of the universe is well-approximated by the Friedmann equations, parameterised by several energy densities which can be observationally inferred. A natural question to ask is: how different would the universe be if these densities took on other values? While there are many ways this can be approached depending on interpretation and mathematical rigour, we attempt an answer by building a "history space" of different cosmologies. A metric is introduced after overcoming technical hurdles related to Lorentzian signature and infinite volume, at least for topologically-closed cases. Geodesics connecting two points on the superspace are computed to express how distant -- in a purely geometric sense -- two universes are. Age can be treated as a free parameter in such an approach, leading to a more general mathematical construct relative to geometrodynamical configuration-space. Connections to bubble inflation and phase transitions are explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06696v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur G. Suvorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matroids and amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06705v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the 1990s, Kita--Yoshida and Cho--Matsumoto introduced intersection forms on the twisted (co)homologies of hyperplane arrangement complements. We give a closed combinatorial formula for these intersection pairings. We show that these intersection pairings are obtained from (continuous and discrete) Laplace transforms of subfans of the Bergman fan of the associated matroid. We compute inverses of these intersection pairings, allowing us to identify (variants of) these intersection forms with the contravariant form of Schechtman--Varchenko, and the bilinear form of Varchenko.
  Building on parallel joint work with C. Eur, we define a notion of scattering amplitudes for matroids. We show that matroid amplitudes satisfy locality and unitarity, and recover biadjoint scalar amplitudes in the case of the complete graphic matroid. We apply our formulae for twisted intersection forms to deduce old and new formulae for scattering amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06705v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Lam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Motion of Compact Objects in Relativistic Viscous Fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06747v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a world-line effective field theory of compact objects moving relativistically through a viscous fluid. The theory is valid when velocity gradients are small compared to the inverse size of the object. Working within the EFT eliminates the need to solve a boundary value problem by turning all interactions between the fluid and the object into a source term in the action. We use the EFT to derive the relativistic equations of motion for a compact object immersed in a viscous fluid in a curved background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06747v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beka Modrekiladze, Ira Z. Rothstein, Jordan Wilson-Gerow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Freeze-In during Warm Inflation and the Seesaw Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06778v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A compelling way to address the inflationary period is via the warm inflation scenario, where the interaction of the inflaton field with other degrees of freedom affects its dynamics in such a way that slow-roll inflation is maintained by dissipative effects in a thermal bath. In this context, if a dark matter particle is coupled to the bath due to non-renormalizable interactions, the observed dark matter abundance may be produced during warm inflation via ultra-violet freeze-in. In this work, we propose applying this scenario in the framework of a $U(1)_{B-L}$ gauge extension of the Standard Model of Particle Physics, where we also employ the seesaw mechanism for generating neutrino masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06778v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rayff de Souza, Jamerson G. Rodrigues, Clarissa Siqueira, Felipe B. M. dos Santos, Jailson Alcaniz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Mechanics of Exponentially Many Low Lying States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.12264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.12264v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has recently been argued that for near-extremal black holes, the entropy and the energy above extremality respectively receive a logT and a T-linear correction, where T is the temperature. We show that both these features can be derived in a low but not too low temperature regime, by assuming the existence of exponentially many low lying states cleanly separated from rest of the spectrum, without using any specific theory. Argument of the logarithm in the expression of entropy is seen to be the ratio of temperature and the bandwidth of the low lying states. We argue that such spectrum might arise in non-supersymmetric extremal brane systems. Our findings strengthen Page's suggestion that there is no true degeneracy for non-supersymmetric extremal black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.12264v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swapnamay Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representations of a quantum-deformed Lorentz algebra, Clebsch-Gordan map, and Fenchel-Nielsen representation of complex Chern-Simons theory at level-${N}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A family of infinite-dimensional irreducible $*$-representations on $\mathcal{H}\simeq L^2(\mathbb{R})\otimes\mathbb{C}^N$ is defined for a quantum-deformed Lorentz algebra $\mathscr{U}_{\bf q}(sl_2)\otimes \mathscr{U}_{\widetilde{\bf {q}}}(sl_2)$, where $\mathbf{q}=\exp[\frac{\pi i}{N}(1+b^2)]$ and $\tilde{\mathbf{q}}=\exp[\frac{\pi i}{N}(1+b^{-2})]$ with $N\in\mathbb{Z}_+$ and $|b|=1$. The representations are constructed with the irreducible representation of quantum torus algebra at level-$N$, which is developed from the quantization of $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})$ Chern-Simons theory. We study the Clebsch-Gordan decomposition of the tensor product representation, and we show that it reduces to the same problem as diagonalizing the complex Fenchel-Nielson length operators in quantizing $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})$ Chern-Simons theory on 4-holed sphere. Finally, we explicitly compute the spectral decomposition of the complex Fenchel-Nielson length operators and the corresponding direct-integral representation of the Hilbert space $\mathcal{H}$, which we call the Fenchel-Nielson representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08176v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muxin Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar Electrodynamics and Higgs Mechanism in the Unfolded Dynamics Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14164v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We put forward a novel method of constructing unfolded formulations of field theories, which is based on initial fixation of the form of an unfolded field and subsequent looking for the corresponding unfolded equation as an identity that this field satisfies. Making use of this method, we find an unfolded formulation for 4d scalar electrodynamics. By considering a symmetry-breaking scalar potential, we study the implementation of the Higgs mechanism within the framework of the unfolded dynamics approach. We explore a deformation of unfolded modules in the symmetry-broken phase and identify a non-invertible unfolded-field redefinition that diagonalizes the higgsed system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14164v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita Misuna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalisation of postquantum-classical gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17844v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the obstacles to reconciling quantum theory with general relativity, is constructing a theory which is both consistent with observation, and and gives finite answers at high energy, so that the theory holds at arbitrarily short distances. Quantum field theory achieves this through the process of renormalisation, but famously, perturbative quantum gravity fails to be renormalisable, even without coupling to matter. Recently, an alternative to quantum gravity has been proposed, in which the geometry of spacetime is taken to be classical rather than quantum, while still being coupled to quantum matter fields [1, 2]. This can be done consistently, provided the dynamics is fundamentally stochastic. Here, we find that the pure gravity theory is formally renormalisable. We do so via the path integral formulation by relating the classical-quantum action to that of quadratic gravity which is renormalisable. Because the action induces stochastic dynamics of space-time, rather than deterministic evolution of a quantum field, the classical-quantum theory is free of tachyons and negative norm ghosts. The key remaining question is whether the renormalisation prescription retains completely positive (CP) dynamics. This consideration appears to single out the scale invariant and asymptotically free theory. We give further evidence that the theory is CP, by showing that the two-point function of the scalar mode is positive. To support the use of precision accelerometers in testing the quantum nature of spacetime, we also compute the power spectral density of the acceleration. The results presented here have a number of implications for inflation, CMB data, and experiments to test the quantum nature of spacetime. They may also provide a way to compute probabilities in the regime of quantum gravity where spacetime can be treated as effectively classical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17844v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej Grudka, Tim R. Morris, Jonathan Oppenheim, Andrea Russo, Muhammad Sajjad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light holographic dilatons near critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04974v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the relation between the emergence of a dilaton in gapped (confining) field theories, and the presence of either complex fixed points or instabilities in the strongly coupled dynamics in two classes of bottom-up holographic models. We demonstrate that in one of the two classes there is a critical line of first-order phase transitions (at zero temperature) that terminates at a critical point. We calculate the mass spectrum of fluctuations of the associated regular gravity backgrounds, which we interpret as bound states in the dual field theories. In proximity to the second-order phase transition, we find a parametrically light scalar state, and its composition leads us to identify it as a dilaton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04974v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ant\'on F. Faedo, Carlos Hoyos, Maurizio Piai, Ronnie Rodgers, Javier G. Subils</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-point functions and contact terms from higher-spin Ward identities of Chern-Simons-matter theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17011v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large $N$ quasifermionic ($QF$) Chern-Simons-matter theories exhibit weakly-broken higher-spin symmetry and contain an infinite-dimensional algebra of almost-conserved higher-spin currents. By analyzing local higher-spin Ward identities, we constrain the higher-spin algebra of this theory, for operators of spin $s&lt;4$. The solution interpolates smoothly between Ward identities of free-fermionic and critical-bosonic $U(N)$ models, in accordance with the bosonization duality. At finite 't Hooft coupling, we decompose four-point current correlators involving $(\partial\cdot J_3)^{QF}$ in terms of free theory structures and identify possible epsilon-transform relations for $QF$ four-point functions. Additionally, we find that higher correlators of the theory develop scheme-independent higher-spin contact terms, stemming from the presence of a background Chern-Simons term in the effective action. These terms are related to similar contact terms of the associated quasibosonic Chern-Simons-matter theory via Legendre transform. The results are supplemented by perturbative checks, including collinear limit computations of $\langle T_{--}J_+J_+\rangle_{QF}$, $\langle T_{--}J_+J_+O\rangle_{QF}$ and $\langle J_{-{}-{}-}J_+J_+J_+\rangle_{QF}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17011v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP11(2024)147</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2024, 147 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Trivko Kukolj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local/Short-range conformal field theories from long-range perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17958v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that by imposing the conformal Wald identity, one can extract conformal data of the corresponding short-range/local CFT from the long-range perturbation theory. We first apply this to the O(N) vector model. We demonstrate that by properly re-sum the perturbative series, one gets reasonable estimations of the critical exponents of the local/short-range CFTs. We then apply this method to study fermionic models with four-fermion interactions. In 2+1 dimensions, the model has the Gross-Neveu coupling and the Thirring coupling. We also consider a 4+1 dimensional theory with a generalized Thirring coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17958v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junchen Rong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic duals of symmetry broken phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01418v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore a novel interpretation of Symmetry Topological Field Theories (SymTFTs) as theories of gravity, proposing a holographic duality where the bulk SymTFT (with the gauging of a suitable Lagrangian algebra) is dual to the universal effective field theory (EFT) that describes spontaneous symmetry breaking on the boundary. We test this conjecture in various dimensions and with many examples involving different continuous symmetry structures, including non-Abelian and non-invertible symmetries, as well as higher groups. For instance, we find that many Abelian SymTFTs are dual to free theories of Goldstone bosons or generalized Maxwell fields, while non-Abelian SymTFTs relate to non-linear sigma models with target spaces defined by the symmetry groups. We also extend our analysis to include the non-invertible $\mathbb{Q}/\mathbb{Z}$ axial symmetry, finding it to be dual to axion-Maxwell theory, and a non-Abelian 2-group structure in four dimensions, deriving a new parity-violating interaction that has implications for the low-energy dynamics of U(N) QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01418v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/prop.202400172</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Fortsch. Phys. 72 (2024) 12, 2400172</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Antinucci, Francesco Benini, Giovanni Rizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological zero modes and bounded modes at smooth domain walls: Exact solutions and dualities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16466v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topology describes global quantities invariant under continuous deformations, such as the number of elementary excitations at a phase boundary, without detailing specifics. Conversely, differential laws are needed to understand the physical properties of these excitations, such as their localization and spatial behavior. For instance, topology mandates the existence of solitonic zero-energy modes at the domain walls between topologically inequivalent phases in topological insulators and superconductors. However, the spatial dependence of these modes is only known in the idealized (and unrealistic) case of a sharp domain wall. Here, we find the analytical solutions of these zero-modes by assuming a smooth and exponentially-confined domain wall. This allows us to characterize the zero-modes using a few length scales: the domain wall width, the exponential decay length, and oscillation wavelength. These quantities define distinct regimes: featureless modes with "no hair" at sharp domain walls, and nonfeatureless modes at smooth domain walls, respectively, with "short hair", i.e., featureless at long distances, and "long hair", i.e., nonfeatureless at all length scales. We thus establish a universal relation between the bulk excitation gap, decay rate, and oscillation momentum of the zero modes, which quantifies the bulk-boundary correspondence in terms of experimentally measurable physical quantities. Additionally, we reveal an unexpected duality between topological zero modes and Shockley modes, unifying the understanding of topologically-protected and nontopological boundary modes. These findings shed some new light on the localization properties of edge modes in topological insulators and Majorana zero modes in topological superconductors and on the differences and similarities between topological and nontopological zero modes in these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16466v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Marra, Angela Nigro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the extension of double copy procedure to higher derivative double field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16524v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Double field theory (DFT) can be constructed from the color-kinematic double copy of Yang- Mills theory. In a recent work, this construction has been extended to higher-derivative terms, starting from the four-derivative extension of Yang-Mills theory, to obtain a conformally invariant DFT action up to the third order. Here, I attempt to extend this idea by introducing a method, inspired by the background independent formulation of DFT, to obtain third order higher derivative terms directly from the second order higher derivative terms. The third-order terms I obtain do not match those obtained directly from the double-copy map. A clear understanding of this mismatch can give valuable information about the double copy procedure for DFT, its relation to background independence, and the conformal symmetry in double configuration space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16524v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasim Y{\i}lmaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Axion is Going Dark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02180v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we explore the effect of a non-Abelian dark sector gauge group that couples to the axion field. In particular, we analyze effects that arise if the dark sector gauge group mixes topologically with the Standard Model. This is achieved by gauging a subgroup of the global center 1-form symmetries which embeds non-trivially in both the visible as well as the dark sector gauge groups. Leaving the local dynamics unchanged, this effect modifies the quantization conditions for the topological couplings of the axion, which enter the estimate of a lower bound on the axion-photon coupling. In the presence of a dark sector this lower bound can be reduced significantly, which might open up interesting new parameter regions for axion physics. We further determine the allowed exotic matter representations in the presence of topological mixing with a dark sector, explore the generalized categorical symmetries of such axion theories, and comment on other model-independent phenomenological consequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02180v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Dierigl, Du\v{s}an Novi\v{c}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Negativity and Replica Symmetry Breaking in General Holographic States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13009v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The entanglement negativity $\mathcal{E}(A:B)$ is a useful measure of quantum entanglement in bipartite mixed states. In random tensor networks (RTNs), which are related to fixed-area states, it was found in [arXiv:2101.11029] that the dominant saddles computing the even R\'enyi negativity $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ generically break the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry. This calls into question previous calculations of holographic negativity using 2D CFT techniques that assumed $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry and proposed that the negativity was related to the entanglement wedge cross section. In this paper, we resolve this issue by showing that in general holographic states, the saddles computing $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ indeed break the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry. Our argument involves an identity relating $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ to the $k$-th R\'enyi entropy on subregion $AB^*$ in the doubled state $|{\rho_{AB}}\rangle_{AA^*BB^*}$, from which we see that the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ replica symmetry is broken down to $\mathbb{Z}_{k}$. For $k&lt;1$, which includes the case of $\mathcal{E}(A:B)$ at $k=1/2$, we use a modified cosmic brane proposal to derive a new holographic prescription for $\mathcal{E}^{(2k)}$ and show that it is given by a new saddle with multiple cosmic branes anchored to subregions $A$ and $B$ in the original state. Using our prescription, we reproduce known results for the PSSY model and show that our saddle dominates over previously proposed CFT calculations near $k=1$. Moreover, we argue that the $\mathbb{Z}_{2k}$ symmetric configurations previously proposed are not gravitational saddles, unlike our proposal. Finally, we contrast holographic calculations with those arising from RTNs with non-maximally entangled links, demonstrating that the qualitative form of backreaction in such RTNs is different from that in gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13009v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Dong, Jonah Kudler-Flam, Pratik Rath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holography for Confined and Deformed Theories: TsT-Generated Solutions in type IIB Supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00094v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a series of solutions of type IIB Supergravity, obtained through the TsT deformation of a seed background that is holographically dual to ${\cal N}=4$ Super Yang-Mills theory compactified on a circle (with a twist). We explore various holographic observables, focusing on disentangling the contributions of confinement, marginal deformations, and their interplay. Additionally, we provide a detailed analysis of how certain observables are influenced by the dynamics of the Kaluza-Klein (KK) modes arising from the circle compactification. Our results offer an improved understanding of the connections between the type IIB deformed backgrounds and the dual QFTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00094v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Castellani, Carlos Nunez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Solutions to the Nonlinear Governing Equations of the Born-Infeld Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09858v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exact finite-energy solutions to the nonlinear governing equations of the Born-Infeld theory of electrodynamics, describing continuous distributions of electric, magnetic, and dyonic charge sources, in both classical and generalized settings, are constructed explicitly. In particular, it is shown that, the finiteness of the total prescribed charges leads to the finiteness of the total energy, of the electromagnetic field system. As a by-product, this result resolves a puzzle arising in the dyonic point charge distribution situation where energy divergence inevitably occurs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09858v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yisong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strings and membranes from $\mathcal{A}$-theory five brane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11197v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $\mathcal{A}$-theory takes U-duality symmetry as a guiding principle, with the SL(5) U-duality symmetry being described as the world-volume theory of a 5-brane. Furthermore, by unifying the 6-dimensional world-volume Lorentz symmetry with the SL(5) spacetime symmetry, it extends to SL(6) U-duality symmetry. The SL(5) spacetime vielbein fields and the 5-brane world-volume vielbein fields are mixed under the SL(6) U-duality transformation. We demonstrate that consistent sectionings of the SL(6) $\mathcal{A}$5-brane world-volume Lagrangian yield Lagrangians of the ${\cal T}$-string with O(D,D) T-duality symmetry, the conventional string, the $\mathcal{M}$5-brane with GL(4) duality symmetry, and the non-perturbative M2-brane in supergravity theory. The GL(4) covariant Lagrangian of the $\mathcal{M}$5-brane derived in this manner is a new, perturbatively quantizable theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11197v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Machiko Hatsuda, Ond\v{r}ej Hul\'ik, William D. Linch, Warren D. Siegel, Di Wang, Yu-Ping Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ginzburg-Landau description of a class of non-unitary minimal models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11714v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has been proposed that the Ginzburg-Landau description of the non-unitary conformal minimal model $M(3,8)$ is provided by the Euclidean theory of two real scalar fields with third-order interactions that have imaginary coefficients. The same lagrangian describes the non-unitary model $M(3,10)$, which is a product of two Yang-Lee theories $M(2,5)$, and the Renormalization Group flow from it to $M(3,8)$. This proposal has recently passed an important consistency check, due to Y. Nakayama and T. Tanaka, based on the anomaly matching for non-invertible topological lines. In this paper, we elaborate the earlier proposal and argue that the two-field theory describes the $D$ series modular invariants of both $M(3,8)$ and $M(3,10)$. We further propose the Ginzburg-Landau descriptions of the entire class of $D$ series minimal models $M(q, 3q-1)$ and $M(q, 3q+1)$, with odd integer $q$. They involve $PT$ symmetric theories of two scalar fields with interactions of order $q$ multiplied by imaginary coupling constants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11714v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Katsevich, Igor R. Klebanov, Zimo Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Induced current in high-dimensional AdS bulk in the presence of a cosmic string and brane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22206v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we analyze the vacuum bosonic current associated with a massive charged scalar field propagating in a $(D+1)$-dimensional anti-de Sitter (AdS) bulk in the presence of an idealized carrying-magnetic-flux cosmic string and also a brane. We assume that the string is perpendicular to the brane which is parallel to the AdS boundary.
  The brane divides the space in two regions with different properties of vacuum states. We investigate the only non-vanishing azimuthal components of the induced currents in both regions. To develop this analysis we calculate first, for both regions, the positive frequency Wightman functions. These present contributions associated with the presence of a cosmic string only plus the other induced by the brane. In this talk we consider only the contributions induced by the brane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22206v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. Oliveira dos Santos, E. R. Bezerra de Mello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Groups as Global Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24142v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study quantum field theories which have quantum groups as global internal symmetries. We show that in such theories operators are generically non-local, and should be thought as living at the ends of topological lines. We describe the general constraints of the quantum group symmetry, given by Ward identities, that correlation functions of the theory should satisfy. We also show that generators of the symmetry can be represented by topological lines with some novel properties. We then discuss a particular example of $U_q(sl_2)$ symmetric CFT, which we solve using the bootstrap techniques and relying on the symmetry. We finally show strong evidence that for a special value of $q$ a subsector of this theory reproduces the fermionic formulation of the Ising model. This suggests that a quantum group can act on local operators as well, however, it generically transforms them into non-local ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24142v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barak Gabai, Victor Gorbenko, Jiaxin Qiao, Bernardo Zan, Aleksandr Zhabin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-commuting SYK model: building quantum chaos from integrable blocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a new family of quantum chaotic models by combining multiple copies of integrable commuting SYK models. As each copy of the commuting SYK model does not commute with others, this construction breaks the integrability of each commuting SYK and the family of models demonstrates the emergence of quantum chaos. We study the spectrum of this model analytically in the double-scaled limit. As the number of copies tends to infinity, the spectrum becomes compact and equivalent to the regular SYK model. For finite $d$ copies, the spectrum is close to the regular SYK model in UV but has an exponential tail $e^{E/T_c}$ in the IR. We identify the reciprocal of the exponent in the tail as a critical temperature $T_c$, above which the model should be quantum chaotic. $T_c$ monotonically decreases as $d$ increases, which expands the chaotic regime over the non-chaotic regime. We propose the existence of a new phase around $T_c$, and the dynamics should be very different in two phases. We further carry out numeric analysis at finite $d$, which supports our proposal.
  Given any finite dimensional local Hamiltonian, by decomposing it into $d$ groups, in which all terms in one group commute with each other but terms from different groups may not, our analysis can give an estimate of the critical temperature for quantum chaos based on the decomposition. We also comment on the implication of the critical temperature to future quantum simulations of quantum chaos and quantum gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12806v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ping Gao, Han Lin, Cheng Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peierls substitution and Hall motion in exotic Carroll dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14329v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The particle with first-order dynamics proposed by Dunne, Jackiw and Trugenberger (DJT) to justify the ``Peierls substitution" is obtained by reduction from both of the planar two-parameter centrally extended Galilean and Carroll systems. In the latter case the extension parameters $\kappa_{exo}$ and $\kappa_{mag}$ generate non-commutativity of the coordinates resp. behave as an internal magnetic field. The position and momentum follow uncoupled anomalous Hall motions. Consistently with partial immobility, one of the Carroll boost generators is broken but the other remains a symmetry. Switching off $\kappa_{exo}$, the immobility of unextended Carroll particles is recovered. The Carroll system is dual to an uncharged anyon on the horizon of a black hole which exhibits the spin-Hall effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14329v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. -X. Zeng, Q. -L. Zhao, P. -M. Zhang, P. A. Horvathy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derivation of the GKP-Witten relation by symmetry without Lagrangian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16269v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive the GKP-Witten relation in terms of correlation functions by symmetry without referring to a Lagrangian or the large $N$ expansion. By constructing bulk operators from boundary operators in conformal field theory (CFT) by the conformal smearing, we first determine bulk-boundary 2-pt functions for an arbitrary spin using both conformal and bulk symmetries, then evaluate their small $z$ behaviors, where $z$ is the $(d+1)$-th coordinate in the bulk. Next, we explicitly determine small $z$ behaviors of bulk-boundary-boundary 3-pt functions also by the symmetries, while small $z$ behaviors of correlation functions among one bulk and $n$ boundary operators with $n\ge 3$ are fixed by the operator product expansion (OPE). Combining all results, we construct the GKP-Witten relation in terms of these correlation functions at all orders in an external source $J$. We compare our non-Lagrangian approach with the standard approach employing the bulk action. Our results indicate that the GKP-Witten relation holds not only for holographic CFTs but also for generic CFTs as long as certain conditions are satisfied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16269v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sinya Aoki, Janos Balog, Kengo Shimada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Adler zeros and soft theorems for inflationary perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17591v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive soft theorems for on-shell scattering amplitudes from non-linearly realised global space-time symmetries, arising from the flat space and decoupling limits of the effective field theories (EFTs) of inflation, while taking particular care of on-shell limits, soft limits, time-ordered correlations, momentum derivatives, energy-momentum conserving delta functions and $i\varepsilon$ prescriptions. Intriguingly, contrary to common belief, we find with a preferred soft hierarchy among the soft momentum $q$, on-shell residue $p_a^0 \pm E_a$, and $\varepsilon$, the soft theorems do not have dependence on off-shell interactions, even in the presence of cubic vertices. We also argue that the soft hierarchy is a natural choice, ensuring the soft limit and on-shell limit commute. Our soft theorems depend solely on on-shell data and hold to all orders in perturbation theory. We present various examples including polynomial shift symmetries, non-linear realisation of Lorentz boosts and dilatations on how the soft theorems work. We find that the collection of exchange diagrams, where the soft momentum is associated with a cubic vertex, exhibits an enhanced soft scaling. The enhanced soft scaling explains why the sum of such diagrams do not enter the soft theorems non-trivially. We further apply the soft theorems to bootstrap the scattering amplitudes of the superfluid and scaling superfluid EFTs, finding agreement with the Hamiltonian analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17591v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zong-Zhe Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the Pre-Big Bang scenario from a cosmological interpretation of the NANOGrav data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01734v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss a recently proposed fit of the 15-year data set obtained from the North American Nanohertz Observatory for Gravitational Waves (NANOGrav) in terms of a relic stochastic background of primordial gravitons, produced in the context of the string cosmology pre-big bang scenario. We show that such interpretation cannot be reconciled with a phenomenologically viable minimal version of such scenario, while it can be allowed if one considers an equally viable but generalised, non-minimal version of pre-big bang evolution. Maintaining the $S$-duality symmetry throughout the high-curvature string phase is possible although somewhat disfavoured. The implications of this non-minimal scenario for the power spectrum of curvature perturbations are also briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01734v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Conzinu, G. Fanizza, M. Gasperini, E. Pavone, L. Tedesco, G. Veneziano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restricted Phase Space Thermodynamics of 4D Dyonic AdS Black Holes: Insights from Kaniadakis Statistics and Emergence of Superfluid $\lambda$-Phase Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04375v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the thermodynamics of $4D$ dyonic AdS black hole in the Kaniadakis statistics framework using the Restricted Phase Space (RPST) formalism. This framework provides a non-extensive extension of classical statistical mechanics, drawing inspiration from relativistic symmetries and presenting a fresh perspective on black hole thermodynamics. Our study analyzes how including Kaniadakis entropy modifies the phase transition of the dyonic black holes. We consider the central charge $C$ and its conjugate chemical potential $\mu$ as the thermodynamic variable along with others except the pressure and volume. Due to the addition of the magnetic charge $\tilde{Q}_m$, the study of the phase transition becomes much richer by obtaining a non-equilibrium phase transition from an unstable small black hole to a stable large black hole along with the Van der Waals phase transition in the $T-S$ processes. In the $F-T$ plot, we get an extra Hawking-Page phase transition. Including the deformation parameter $\kappa$ introduces an unstable (ultra-large BH) branch seen in almost all the plots. Turning off the magnetic charge flips the direction of the phase transition seen during its presence. We observe a novel phenomenon that is the superfluid $\lambda$ phase transition in the mixed $(\tilde{\Phi}_e,\tilde{Q}_m)$ which is due to the additional $\tilde{Q}_m$ inclusion. Also, in the plots varying $\kappa$ match with the plot varying $C$ which underlines some sort of correspondence in its meaning which is not possible to observe in Gibbs-Boltzmann statistics. As the entropy models change the homogeneity is not lost where mass is of the first order and the rest is zeroth order. Finally, the $\mu-C$ processes in quite similar across black hole systems and entropy formulation marking some kind of universality of this process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04375v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Baruah, Prabwal Phukon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong-field magnetohydrodynamics for neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.01636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.01636v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a formulation of magnetohydrodynamics which can be used to describe the evolution of strong magnetic fields in neutron star interiors. Our approach is based on viewing magnetohydrodynamics as a theory with a one-form global symmetry and developing an effective field theory for the hydrodynamic modes associated with this symmetry. In the regime where the local velocity and temperature variations can be neglected, we derive the most general constitutive relation consistent with symmetry constraints for the electric field in the presence of a strong magnetic field. This constitutive relation not only reproduces the phenomena of Ohmic decay, ambipolar diffusion, and Hall drift derived in a phenomenological model by Goldreich and Reisenegger, but also reveals new terms in the evolution of the magnetic field which cannot easily be seen from such microscopic models. This formulation gives predictions for novel diffusion behaviors of small perturbations around a constant background magnetic field, and for the two-point correlation functions among various components of the electric and magnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.01636v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, L042050 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shreya Vardhan, Sa\v{s}o Grozdanov, Samuel Leutheusser, Hong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aschenbach effect and circular orbits in static and spherically symmetric black hole backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11883v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Aschenbach effect, the increasing behavior of the angular velocity of a timelike circular orbit with its radius coordinate, is found to extensively exist in rapidly spinning black holes to a zero-angular-momentum observer. It also has potential observation in the high-frequency quasi-periodic oscillations of X-ray flux. However, observing such effect remains to be a challenge in static and spherically symmetric black hole backgrounds. In this paper, we mainly focus on such issue. Starting with the geodesics, we analytically study the underlying properties of the timelike circular orbits, and show the conditions under which the Aschenbach effect survives. It is shown that the presence of the static point orbits and stable photon spheres would be the indicator of the Aschenbach effect. We then apply it to three characteristic black holes exhibiting different features. The results state that this effect is absent for both the Schwarzschild and Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m black holes. While, for the dyonic black hole in quasi-topological electromagnetics, there indeed exists the Aschenbach effect. This provides a first example that such effect exists in a non-spinning black hole background. Moreover, it also uncovers an intriguing property for understanding the black holes in nonlinear electrodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11883v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2023.101409</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Dark Univ. 43, 101409 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shao-Wen Wei, Yu-Xiao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic nature of black holes in coexistence region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11886v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Studying the system state of coexistence regions will peek into to reveal microscopic interactions between different phases of a thermodynamic system. However, there is no effective method to study thermodynamic nature of the coexistence black hole regions for the failure of the equation of state. Aiming at these coexistence states, in this work, we develop a general approach by introducing two new ratio parameters. The first one is the ratio of the horizon radii of the saturated coexistence small and large black holes, and the second one measures that of the small black hole molecule number to the total molecule number. We demonstrate that the first parameter can serve as an order parameter to characterize the first-order phase transition. The study also shows that the black hole state in the coexistence region is uniquely determined by these two introduced parameters bounded between 0 and 1. These results are quite significant in the analytical study of phase transition and the microscopic nature of black hole in the coexistence regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11886v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci.China Phys.Mech.Astron. 67, 250412 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shao-Wen Wei, Yu-Xiao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unifying Ordinary and Null Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05936v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Based on a recently proposed reinterpretation of gravitational wave memory that builds up on the definition of gravitational waves pioneered by Isaacson, we provide a unifying framework to derive both ordinary and null memory from a single well-defined equation at leading order in the asymptotic expansion. This allows us to formulate a memory equation that is valid for any unbound asymptotic energy-flux that preserves local Lorentz invariance. Using Horndeski gravity as a concrete example metric theory with an additional potentially massive scalar degree of freedom in the gravitational sector, the general memory formula is put into practice by presenting the first account of the memory correction sourced by the emission of massive field waves. Throughout the work, physical degrees of freedom are identified by constructing manifestly gauge invariant perturbation variables within an SVT decomposition on top of the asymptotic Minkowski background, which will in particular prove useful in future studies of gravitational wave memory within vector tensor theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05936v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lavinia Heisenberg, Guangzi Xu, Jann Zosso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter production during Warm Inflation via Freeze-In</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17371v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a novel perspective on the role of inflation in the production of Dark Matter (DM). Specifically, we explore the DM production during Warm Inflation via ultraviolet Freeze-In (WIFI). We demonstrate that in a Warm Inflation (WI) setting the persistent thermal bath, sustained by the dissipative interactions with the inflaton field, can source a sizable DM abundance via the non-renormalizable interactions that connect the DM with the bath. Compared to the (conventional) radiation-dominated (RD) UV freeze-in scenario for the same reheat temperature (after inflation), the resulting DM yield in WIFI is always enhanced showing a strongly positive dependence on the mass dimension of the non-renormalizable operator. Of particular interest, for a sufficiently large mass dimension of the operator, the entirety of the DM abundance of the Universe can be created during the inflationary phase. For the specific models we study, we find that the enhancement in DM yield, relative to RD UV freeze-in, is at least an order of magnitude for an operator of mass dimension 5, and as large as 18 order of magnitudes for an operator of mass dimension 10. Our findings also suggest a broader applicability for producing other cosmological relics, which may have a substantial impact on the evolution of the early Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17371v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.211001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 211001 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Katherine Freese, Gabriele Montefalcone, Barmak Shams Es Haghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Walking behavior induced by $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry breaking in a non-Hermitian $\rm XY$ model with clock anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17373v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A quantum system governed by a non-Hermitian Hamiltonian may exhibit zero temperature phase transitions that are driven by interactions, just as its Hermitian counterpart, raising the fundamental question how non-Hermiticity affects quantum criticality. In this context we consider a non-Hermitian system consisting of an $\rm XY$ model with a complex-valued four-state clock interaction that may or may not have parity-time-reversal ($\mathcal{PT}$) symmetry. When the $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry is broken, and time-evolution becomes non-unitary, a scaling behavior similar to the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless phase transition ensues, but in a highly unconventional way, as the line of fixed points is absent. From the analysis of the $d$-dimensional RG equations, we obtain that the unconventional behavior in the $\mathcal{PT}$ broken regime follows from the collision of two fixed points in the $d\to 2$ limit, leading to walking behavior or pseudocriticality. For $d=2+1$ the near critical behavior is characterized by a correlation length exponent $\nu=3/8$, a value smaller than the mean-field one. These results are in sharp contrast with the $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric case where only one fixed point arises for $2&lt;d&lt;4$ and in $d=1+1$ three lines of fixed points occur with a continuously varying critical exponent $\nu$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17373v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.224505</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 224505 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eduard Naichuk, Jeroen van den Brink, Flavio S. Nogueira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Size Matters: Lorentz Boosted Casimir Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01401v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many evidences appear in the past decades and show that the negativity of Casimir energy is responsible for exotic mechanical and gravitational effects. We study in this work the Lorentz boost of a Casimir cavity, on which little attention is paid to its momentum in historical works. We find that the vacuum energy and momentum carried by the cavity transform differently from those of point particles due to the cavity's extension feature. However, the mass-shell condition of the two are identical as long as the cavity is finite along the moving direction only.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01401v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Song Cao, YanXia Liu, Ding-Fang Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generalized uncertainty-inspired quantum black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03909v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive the full spacetime metric of a generalized uncertainty-inspired quantum black hole. We examine a previous model of the interior in this approach and show that extending its metric to the full spacetime leads to serious issues in the asymptotic region. To remedy this, we introduce an ``improved scheme'' mimicking a similar prescription used in loop quantum gravity, where the quantum parameters are made momentum-dependent. Under this scheme, we rework the interior of the black hole and extend it to the full spacetime. We find that the resulting metric is asymptotically flat and its associated Kretschmann scalar is regular everywhere. We also show that the null expansion and Raychaudhuri equation are regular everywhere in this spacetime, implying that the classical singularity is resolved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03909v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federica Fragomeno, Douglas M. Gingrich, Samantha Hergott, Saeed Rastgoo, Evan Vienneau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Managing Singular Kernels and Logarithmic Corrections in the Staggered Six-Vertex Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09889v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the spectral properties of the staggered six-vertex model with ${\cal Z}_2$ symmetry for arbitrary system sizes $L$ using non-linear integral equations (NLIEs). Our study is motivated by two key questions: what is the accuracy of results based on the ODE/IQFT correspondence in the asymptotic regime of large system sizes, and what is the optimal approach based on NLIE for analyzing the staggered six-vertex model?
  We demonstrate that the quantization conditions for low-lying primary and descendant states, derived from the ODE/IQFT approach in the scaling limit, are impressively accurate even for relatively small system sizes. Specifically, in the anisotropy parameter range $\pi/4 &lt; \gamma &lt; \pi/2$, the difference between NLIE and ODE/IQFT results for energy and quasi-momentum eigenvalues is of order $\mathcal{O}(L^{-2})$.
  Furthermore, we present a unifying framework for NLIEs, distinguishing between versions with singular and regular kernels. We provide a compact derivation of NLIE with a singular kernel, followed by an equivalent set with a regular kernel. We address the stability issues in numerical treatments and offer solutions to achieve high-accuracy results, validating our approach for system sizes ranging from $L=2$ to $L=10^{24}$.
  Our findings not only validate the ODE/IQFT approach for finite system sizes but also enhance the understanding of NLIEs in the context of the staggered six-vertex model. We hope the insights gained from this study have significant implications for resolving the spectral problem of other lattice systems with emergent non-compact degrees of freedom and provide a foundation for future research in this domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09889v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)040</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP, Volume 2024, article number 40, (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mouhcine Azhari, Andreas Kl\"umper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covariant quantum field theory of tachyons is unphysical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14225v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tachyons have fascinated generations of physicists due to their peculiar behavior, but they did not solve any real physical problem. This may have changed with the recent works of Dragan et al., who have shown that superluminal observers may be related to the foundations of quantum mechanics (QM) because they require introducing non-determinism and wave-like behavior at the fundamental level. Unfortunately, we show that the tachyon quantum field theory proposed as a part of this program is not quantum since the tachyon field commutes at all points and the canonical commutations relations of a quantum scalar field are not satisfied. We also discuss other authors' theories, e.g., we show that the Dhar-Sudarshan's formula for the Feynman propagator violates unitarity, and we apply the LSZ formalism to tachyons for the first time, where we find that one cannot prove the LSZ asymptotic condition just by replacing plane waves with wavepackets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14225v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Jod{\l}owski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified Compton Effect and CMB Anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04735v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent satellite observations have revealed significant anisotropy in the cosmic microwave background (CMB) radiation, a phenomenon that had previously been detected but received limited attention due to its subtlety. With the advent of more precise measurements from satellites, the extent of this anisotropy has become increasingly apparent. This paper examines the CMB radiation by reviewing past research on the causes of CMB anisotropy and presents a new model to explain the observed temperature anisotropy and the anisotropy in the correlation function between temperature and E-mode polarization in the CMB radiation. The proposed model is based on a modified-generalized Compton scattering approach incorporating Loop Quantum Gravity (LQG). We begin by describing the generalized Compton scattering and then discuss the CMB radiation in the context of processes occurring at the last scattering surface. Our findings are derived from the latest observational data from the Planck satellite (2018). In our model, besides the parameters available in the Planck data for the standard model ($\Lambda$CDM), we introduce two novel parameters: $\delta_{L}$, the density of cosmic electrons, and $M^2$, a parameter related to the modified-generalized Compton scattering effects. The results indicate that, based on the 2018 Planck data, small values were obtained for $\delta_{L}$ and $M^{2}$, $\delta_{L}=1.63\pm0.08(10^{-13})$ and $M^2=2.28\pm0.34(10^{-4})$, showing no significant deviation from the standard model. Moreover, increasing the values of $\delta_{L}$ and $M^{2}$ leads to an increase in the range of fluctuations in the CMB temperature anisotropy power spectrum and the correlation function between temperature and E-mode polarization for multipoles $l&lt;500$ until the first peak.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04735v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Davood Sadatian, Amir Sabouri, Zahra Davari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic Varieties for Massless Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16711v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study algebraic varieties that encode the kinematic data for $n$ massless particles in $d$-dimensional spacetime subject to momentum conservation. Their coordinates are spinor brackets, which we derive from the Clifford algebra associated to the Lorentz group. This was proposed for $d=5$ in the recent physics literature. Our kinematic varieties are given by polynomial constraints on tensors with both symmetric and skew symmetric slices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16711v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Smita Rajan, Svala Sverrisd\'ottir, Bernd Sturmfels</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of cosmologically coupled black holes for pulsar timing arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01801v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been argued that realistic models of (singularity-free) black holes (BHs) embedded within an expanding Universe are coupled to the large-scale cosmological dynamics, with striking consequences, including pure cosmological growth of BH masses. In this pilot study, we examine the consequences of this growth for the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) produced by inspiraling supermassive cosmologically coupled BHs. We show that the predicted SGWB amplitude is enhanced relative to the standard uncoupled case, while maintaining the $\Omega_{\text{gw}} \propto f^{2/3}$ frequency scaling of the spectral energy density. For the case where BH masses grow with scale factor as $M_{\text{bh}} \propto a^3$, thus contributing as a dark energy component to the cosmological dynamics, $\Omega_{\text{gw}}$ can be enhanced by more than an order of magnitude. This has important consequences for the SGWB signal detected by pulsar timing arrays, whose measured amplitude is slightly larger than most theoretical predictions for the spectrum from inspiraling binary BHs, a discrepancy which can be alleviated by the cosmological mass growth mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01801v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Calz\`a, Francesco Gianesello, Massimiliano Rinaldi, Sunny Vagnozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truncation-Free Quantum Simulation of Pure-Gauge Compact QED Using Josephson Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11413v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum simulation is one of the methods that have been proposed and used in practice to bypass computational challenges in the investigation of lattice gauge theories. While most of the proposals rely on truncating the infinite dimensional Hilbert spaces that these models feature, we propose a truncation-free method based on the exact analogy between the local Hilbert space of lattice QED and that of a Josephson junction. We provide several proposals, mostly semi-analog, arranged according to experimental difficulty. Our method can simulate a quasi-2D system of up to $2\times N$ plaquettes, and we present an approximate method that can simulate the fully-2D theory, but is more demanding experimentally and not immediately feasible. This sets the ground for analog quantum simulation of lattice gauge theories with superconducting circuits, in a completely Hilbert space truncation-free procedure, for continuous gauge groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11413v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guy Pardo, Julian Bender, Nadav Katz, Erez Zohar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationary BTZ space-time in Ricci-Inverse and $f(\mathcal{R})$ gravity theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11922v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore a stationary BTZ space-time within the framework of modified gravity theory, specifically focusing on Ricci-inverse gravity. It is important to clarify that ``Ricci-inverse" refers to the inverse of the Ricci tensor, not the Ricci scalar. We consider a general class of this gravity theory, where the function $f$ is defined by $f(\mathcal{R}, \mathcal{A}, A^{\mu\nu}\,A_{\mu\nu})$, with $\mathcal{R}$ and $\mathcal{A}$ representing the Ricci and anti-curvature scalars, respectively and $A^{\mu\nu}$ is the anti-curvature tensor. We demonstrate that stationary BTZ space-time is a valid solution in this gravity theory, wherein the cosmological constant undergoes modifications due to the coupling constants. Moreover, we study another modified gravity theory known as $f(\mathcal{R})$-gravity and analyze the stationary BTZ space-time. Subsequently, we fully integrate the geodesic equations for BTZ space-time constructed within the Ricci-Inverse gravity, expressing the solutions in terms of elementary functions and compared with the GR result. We classify different types of geodesics, including null and time-like geodesics, under three conditions: (i) nonzero mass and angular momentum, $M \neq 0, J\neq 0$, (ii) massless BTZ space-time, $M=0$ and $J=0$, and (iii) $M=-1, J=0$, that is $AdS_3$-type, and analyze the results in modified gravity theories and compare with the general relativity case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11922v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-13637-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>EPJC 84, 1271 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Faizuddin Ahmed, Abdelmalek Bouzenada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice gradient flows (de-)stabilizing topological sectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14812v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the stability of topological charge under gradient flow taking the admissibility condition into account. For the $SU(2)$ Wilson gauge theory with $\beta=2.45$ and $L^4=12^4$, we numerically show that the gradient flows with the Iwasaki and DBW2 gauge actions stabilize the topological sectors significantly, and they have qualitatively different behaviors compared with the Wilson and tree-level Symanzik flows. By considering the classical continuum limit of the flow actions, we discuss that the coefficient of dimension-$6$ operators has to be positive for stabilizing the one-instanton configuration, and the Iwasaki and DBW2 actions satisfy this criterion while the Wilson and Symanzik actions do not. Moreover, we observe that the DBW2 flow stabilizes the topological sectors at the very early stage of the flow ($\hat{t}\approx 0.5$--$1$), which suggests that the use of the DBW2 action for the gradient flow is computationally efficient to determine the gauge topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14812v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuya Tanizaki, Akio Tomiya, Hiromasa Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inner horizon instability via the trace anomaly effective action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14964v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In quantum field theory applied to black hole spacetimes, substantial evidence suggests that the Unruh and Hartle-Hawking vacuum states become singular at Cauchy horizons. This raises essential questions regarding the impact of quantum field backreaction on the stability of Cauchy horizons in static scenarios and inner horizons in evolving spacetimes. To approach this problem, we employ analytic approximations to the renormalized stress-energy tensor (RSET) of quantum fields in four dimensions. Specifically, we utilize the anomaly-induced effective action, which generates four-dimensional approximate RSETs through a pair of auxiliary scalar fields that satisfy higher-order equations of motion. The boundary conditions imposed on these auxiliary fields yield RSETs with leading-order terms that mimic the behaviour of different vacuum states. This study presents the first application of the anomaly-induced effective action method to Reissner-Nordstr\"om black hole interiors, evaluating its accuracy, applicability, and connections with prior RSET approximations. Among the range of possible states accessible through this method, we found none that remain regular at both the event and Cauchy horizons, aligning with theoretical expectations. The method shows strong agreement with exact four-dimensional RSET results for the Hartle-Hawking state but does not fully capture the unique characteristics of the Unruh state in Reissner-Nordstr\"om spacetimes. We conclude by suggesting possible extensions to address these limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14964v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julio Arrechea, Giulio Neri, Stefano Liberati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying Logical Gates in Quantum Codes via Cohomology Operations and Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15848v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically construct and classify fault-tolerant logical gates implemented by constant-depth circuits for quantum codes using cohomology operations and symmetry. These logical gates are obtained from unitary operators given by symmetry-protected topological responses, which correspond to generators of group cohomology and can be expressed explicitly on the lattice using cohomology operations including cup product, Steenrod squares and new combinations of higher cup products called higher Pontryagin powers. Our study covers most types of the cohomology operations in the literature. This hence gives rise to several new classes of diagonal and non-diagonal logical gates in increasing Clifford hierarchies beyond the usual color code paradigm corresponding to an $n$-fold cup product, including the logical $R_k$ and multi-controlled $C^m R_k$ gates for codes defined in projective spaces. Implementing these gates could make it more efficient to compile specific types of quantum algorithms such as Shor's algorithm. We further extend the construction to quantum codes with boundaries, which generalizes the folding approach in color codes. We also present a formalism for addressable and parallelizable logical gates in LDPC codes via higher-form symmetries and apply it to construct addressable logical Clifford gates in expander-based codes including the asymptotically good LDPC codes and hypergraph-product codes. As a byproduct, we find new topological responses of finite higher-form symmetries using higher Pontryagin powers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15848v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Po-Shen Hsin, Ryohei Kobayashi, Guanyu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A long freeze is hard to achieve in the presence of matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16344v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Certain holographic dark energy (HDE) models allow for the possibility of a ``long freeze,'' in which the scale factor evolves to a constant in the long-time limit. Here we extend previous calculations by adding a nonrelativistic matter component. The addition of a matter component tends to destroy the long freeze behavior, driving the universe to recollapse. Long freeze evolution is still possible, but only for a limited set of HDE models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16344v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Blitz, Robert J. Scherrer, Oem Trivedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal microscopic descriptions for statistics of particles and extended excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01886v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Statistics of excitations play an essential role in understanding phases of matter. In this paper, we introduce a universal method for studying the generalized statistics of Abelian particles and extended excitations in lattices of any dimension. We compute the statistics using the Berry phase of a sequence of unitary operators that transports the excitations while canceling local ambiguities at each step. The sequence is derived from locality, using the Smith normal form. We show that the statistics are quantized invariants. Our method unifies the statistics for the braiding and fusion of particles and loops, and leads to the discovery of novel statistics for membrane excitations. The statistics can be interpreted as the quantum anomaly of a generalized global symmetry, which manifests as an obstruction to gauging the symmetry on lattices. Furthermore, we show that non-trivial statistics forbid short-range entangled states, establishing the dynamical consequence of anomalies in microscopic lattice models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01886v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryohei Kobayashi, Yuyang Li, Hanyu Xue, Po-Shen Hsin, Yu-An Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Big Bang as spacetime defect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03538v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We review the suggestion that it is possible to eliminate the Big Bang curvature singularity of the Friedman cosmological solution by considering a particular type of degenerate spacetime metric. Specifically, we take the 4-dimensional spacetime metric to have a 3-dimensional defect with a vanishing determinant of the metric. This new solution suggests the existence of another "side" of the Big Bang (perhaps a more appropriate description than "pre-big-bang" phase used in our original paper). The corresponding new solution for defect wormholes is also briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03538v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. R. Klinkhamer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New analysis of SNeIa Pantheon Catalog: Variable speed of light as an alternative to dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05262v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In A&amp;A 412, 35 (2003) Blanchard, Douspis, Rowan-Robinson, and Sarkar (BDRS) slightly modified the primordial fluctuation spectrum and produced an excellent fit to WMAP's CMB power spectrum for an Einstein-de Sitter (EdS) universe, bypassing dark energy. Curiously, they obtained a Hubble value of $H_0\approx46$, in sharp conflict with the canonical range $H_0\sim67-73$. However, we will demonstrate that the reduced value of $H_0\approx46$ achieved by BDRS is fully compatible with the use of variable speed of light in analyzing the late-time cosmic acceleration observed in Type Ia supernovae (SNeIa). In arXiv:2412.04257 [gr-qc] we uncovered a hidden aspect in a generic class of scale-invariant actions: the dynamics of the dilaton can induce a variation in the speed of light as $c\propto\chi^{1/2}$, causing $c$ to vary alongside $\chi$ across spacetime. For an EdS universe with varying $c$, besides the effects of cosmic expansion, light waves emitted from distant SNeIa are further subject to a refraction effect, which alters the Lemaitre redshift relation to $1+z=a^{-3/2}$. Based on this new formula, we achieve a fit to the SNeIa Pantheon Catalog exceeding the quality of the $\Lambda$CDM model. Crucially, our approach does not require dark energy and produces $H_0=47.2$ in strong alignment with the BDRS finding of $H_0\approx46$. Hence, BDRS's analysis of the (early-time) CMB power spectrum and our variable-$c$ analysis of the (late-time) Hubble diagram of SNeIa fully agree on two counts: (i) the dark energy hypothesis is avoided, and (ii) $H_0$ is reduced to $\sim47$, which also yields an age $t_0=2/(3H_0)=13.8$ Gy for an EdS universe, without requiring dark energy. Most importantly, we will demonstrate that the late-time acceleration can be attributed to the declining speed of light in an expanding EdS universe, rather than to a dark energy component.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05262v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoang Ky Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
