<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Circles and Triangles, the NLSM and Tr($\Phi^3$)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A surprising connection has recently been made between the amplitudes for Tr($\Phi^3$) theory and the non-linear sigma model (NLSM). A simple shift of kinematic variables naturally suggested by the associahedron/stringy representation of Tr$(\Phi^3$) theory yields pion amplitudes at all loops. In this note we provide an elementary motivation and proof for this link going in the opposite direction, starting from the non-linear sigma model and discovering its formulation as a sum over triangulations of surfaces with simple numerator factors. This uses an ancient connection between "circles" and "triangles", interpreting the equation $y = \sqrt{1 - x^2}$ both as parametrizing points on a circle as well as generating the number of triangulations of polygons. A further simplification of the numerator factors exposes them as arising from the kinematically shifted Tr($\Phi^3$) theory, and gives rise to novel tropical representations of NLSM amplitudes. The connection to Tr$(\Phi^3)$ theory defines a natural notion of "surface-soft limit" intrinsic to curves on surfaces. Remarkably, with this definition, the soft limit of pion amplitudes vanishes directly at the level of the integrand, via obvious pairwise cancellations. We also give simple, explicit expressions for the multi-soft factors for tree and loop-level integrands in the limit as any number of pions are taken "surface-soft".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04826v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nima Arkani-Hamed, Carolina Figueiredo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loop Blow-up Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04831v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new model of string inflation driven by a blow-up K\"ahler modulus of type IIb compactifications with a potential generated by string loops. Slow-roll is naturally realized thanks to the fact that the blow-up mode is a leading-order flat direction lifted by string loops which are unavoidable and generate a plateau at large field values. We check that throughout the whole inflationary dynamics the effective field theory is under control. We perform a phenomenological analysis determining the exact number of efoldings by studying the post-inflationary evolution. We determine the values of the microscopic parameters which lead to agreement with CMB data, together with the prediction of a tensor-to-scalar ratio of order $r\sim 10^{-5}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04831v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suk\c{r}ti Bansal, Luca Brunelli, Michele Cicoli, Arthur Hebecker, Ruben Kuespert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Invertible Symmetries, Anomalies and Scattering Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04835v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that crossing symmetry of S-matrices is modified in certain theories with non-invertible symmetries or anomalies. Focusing on integrable flows to gapped phases in two dimensions, we find that S-matrices derived previously from the bootstrap approach are incompatible with non-invertible symmetries along the flow. We present consistent alternatives, which however violate standard crossing symmetry and obey modified rules dictated by fusion categories. We extend these rules to theories with discrete anomalies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04835v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Copetti, Lucia Cordova, Shota Komatsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local-in-time Conservative Binary Dynamics at Fourth Post-Minkowskian Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Leveraging scattering information to describe binary systems in generic orbits requires identifying local- and nonlocal-in-time tail effects. We report here the derivation of the universal (non-spinning) local-in-time conservative dynamics at fourth Post-Minkowskian order, i.e. ${\cal O}(G^4)$. This is achieved by computing the nonlocal-in-time contribution to the deflection angle, and removing it from the full conservative value in [2112.11296,2210.05541]. Unlike the total result, the integration problem involves two scales, velocity and mass ratio, and features multiple polylogarithms, complete elliptic and iterated elliptic integrals, notably in the mass ratio. We reconstruct the local radial action, center-of-mass momentum and Hamiltonian, as well as the exact logarithmic-dependent part(s), all valid for generic orbits. We incorporate the remaining nonlocal terms for elliptic-like motion to sixth Post-Newtonian order. The combined Hamiltonian is in perfect agreement in the overlap with the Post-Newtonian state of the art. The results presented here provide the most accurate description of gravitationally-bound binaries harnessing scattering data to date, readily applicable to waveform modelling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04853v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Dlapa, Gregor K\"alin, Zhengwen Liu, Rafael A. Porto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrically Constrained Localized Configurations: First-Order Framework and Analytical Solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04953v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work deals with the presence of topological structures in models of two real scalar fields in the two-dimensional spacetime. The subject concerns the presence of a geometric constriction, which appears with a modification of the kinetic term of one of the two fields. We elaborate on the construction of a first-order framework, which directly contributes to find analytical solutions. We describe several distinct possibilities, in particular, the case where the first-order equations do not separate. This is much harder, but we use the integrating factor to deal with analytical configurations. The proposed methodology help us deal with localized structures of both the N\'eel and Bloch type very naturally, and we end the work suggesting some possibilities of applications in distinct areas of nonlinear science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04953v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aop.2024.169638</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Annals Physics 463 (2024) 169638</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. Bazeia, M. A. Feitosa, R. Menezes, G. S. Santiago</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Celestial $w_{1+\infty}$ charges and the subleading structure of asymptotically-flat spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the subleading structure of asymptotically-flat spacetimes and its relationship to the $w_{1+\infty}$ loop algebra of higher spin charges. We do so using both the Bondi-Sachs and the Newman-Penrose formalism, via a dictionary built from a preferred choice of tetrad. This enables us to access properties of the so-called higher Bondi aspects, such as their evolution equations, their transformation laws under asymptotic symmetries, and their relationship to the Newman-Penrose and the higher spin charges. By studying the recursive Einstein evolution equations defining these higher spin charges, we derive the general form of their transformation behavior under BMSW symmetries. This leads to an immediate proof that the spin 0,1 and spin $s$ brackets reproduce upon linearization the structure expected from the $w_{1+\infty}$ algebra. We then define renormalized higher spin charges which are conserved in the radiative vacuum at quadratic order, and show that they satisfy for all spins the $w_{1+\infty}$ algebra at linear order in the radiative data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05195v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Geiller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-loop Double Copy Relation from Twisted (Co)homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a geometric relation between closed and open string amplitudes at one-loop. After imposing a homological splitting on the world-sheet torus twisted intersection theory is used to establish a one-loop double copy relation. The latter expresses a closed string amplitude by a pair of open string amplitudes and twisted intersection numbers. These inner products on the vector space of allowed differential forms are related to the twisted homology and cohomology groups associated with the Riemann-Wirtinger integral.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05208v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pouria Mazloumi, Stephan Stieberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Holes and Marchenko-Pastur distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05241v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The universal eigenvalue distribution characterizing the Gram matrix of semiclassical ensembles of black hole microstates is recognized as the Marchenko-Pastur distribution, which plays a prominent role as the universal limit distribution in a large class of random matrix and vector models. It is proposed that this distribution also universally determines the energy spectral density of black holes, which allows to construct a Krylov space for the time evolution of typical black hole states and calculate their state complexity. It is checked that the state complexity growth at late times saturates Lloyd's bound. Some implications of the proposed spectral density for the generation of Hawking radiation and black hole evaporation are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05241v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang M\"uck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inversion and Integral Identities in dCFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work derives an application from the identities of arXiv:hep-th/0602028 in order to invert four point functions in defect conformal field theories. For this, a recursion relation is established and the O(N) model with a line defect is considered as a testing ground of this application. Specifically, the CFT data are calculated from inversion of tilt and displacement four point functions. The recursion relation enables efficient computation of hypergeometrics at order $\epsilon$ in the $\epsilon$-expansion, leading to the inversion of four point functions and the derivation of CFT data. The inversion method presented offers a faster alternative to traditional approaches using arXiv:hep-ph/0507094v2, arXiv:0708.2443v2. The study also explores a general ansatz approach, assessing the algorithm's restrictiveness, and concludes by examining implications for the integral identity constraint of arXiv:2203.17157v2, predicting corrections to OPE coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05243v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Sakkas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Goldstone Boson Equivalence for Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The effective field theory of single-field inflation characterizes the inflationary epoch in terms of a pattern of symmetry breaking. An operator acquires a time-dependent vacuum expectation value, defining a preferred spatial slicing. In the absence of dynamical gravity, the fluctuations around the time-dependent background are described by the Goldstone boson associated with this symmetry breaking process. With gravity, the Goldstone is eaten by the metric, becoming the scalar metric fluctuation. In this paper, we will show that in general single-field inflation, the statistics of scalar metric fluctuations are given by the statistics of this Goldstone boson it decoupled from gravity up to corrections that are controlled as an expansion in slow-roll parameters. This even holds in the presence of additional parameters, like the speed of sound, that naively enhance the impact of the gravitational terms. In the process, we derive expressions for leading and sub-leading gravitational corrections to all-orders in the Goldstone boson.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05274v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Green, Kshitij Gupta, Yiwen Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modularity in Argyres-Douglas Theories with $a=c$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05323v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a family of Argyres-Douglas theories, which are 4D $\mathcal N=2$ strongly coupled superconformal field theories (SCFTs) but share many features with 4D $\mathcal N=4 $ super-Yang-Mills theories. In particular, the two central charges of these theories are the same, namely $a=c$. We derive a simple and illuminating formula for the Schur index of these theories, which factorizes into the product of a Casimir term and a term referred to as the Schur partition function. While the former is controlled by the anomaly, the latter is identified with the vacuum character of the corresponding chiral algebra and is expected to satisfy the modular linear differential equation. Our simple expression for the Schur partition function, which can be regarded as the generalization of MacMahon's generalized sum-of-divisor function, allows one to numerically compute the series expansions efficiently, and furthermore find the corresponding modular linear differential equation. In a special case where the chiral algebra is known, we are able to derive the corresponding modular linear differential equation using Zhu's recursion relation. We further study the solutions to the modular linear differential equations and discuss their modular transformations. As an application, we study the high temperature limit or the Cardy-like limit of the Schur index using its simple expression and modular properties, thus shedding light on the 1/4-BPS microstates of genuine $\mathcal N=2$ SCFTs with $a=c$ and their dual quantum gravity via the AdS/CFT correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05323v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongliang Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft Theorems for Boostless Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider effective field theories (EFTs) of scalar fields with broken Lorentz boosts, which arise by taking the decoupling and flat-space limits of the EFT of inflation, and derive constraints that must be satisfied by the corresponding scattering amplitudes if there is an underlying non-linearly realised symmetry. We primarily concentrate on extended shift symmetries which depend on the space-time coordinates, and find that combinations of scattering amplitudes obey enhanced Adler zeros. That is, such combinations vanish as one external momentum is taken soft, with the rate at which they vanish dictated by the corresponding symmetry. In our soft theorem derivation, we pay particular care to the energy and momentum-conserving delta functions that arise due to space-time translations, and show that when acted upon by derivatives with respect to spatial momenta, they yield a tower of soft theorems which are ultimately required for closure of the underlying symmetry algebra. All of our soft theorems correspond to constraints that must be satisfied by on-shell amplitudes and, even for symmetries that depend on the time coordinate, our soft theorems only require derivatives to be taken with respect to spatial momenta. We perform a soft bootstrap procedure to find solutions to our soft theorems, and compare these solutions to what we find from an off-shell analysis using the coset construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05459v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongzhe Du, David Stefanyszyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinning Particle Geometries in AdS$_3$/CFT$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05524v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study spinning particle/defect geometries in the context of AdS$_3$/CFT$_2$. These solutions lie below the BTZ threshold, and can be obtained from identifications of AdS$_3$. We construct the Feynman propagator by solving the bulk equation of motion in the spinning particle geometry, summing over the modes of the fields and passing to the boundary. The quantization of the scalar fields becomes challenging when confined to the regions that are causally well-behaved. If the region containing closed timelike curves (CTCs) is included, the normalization of the scalar fields enjoys an analytical simplification and the propagator can be expressed as an infinite sum over image geodesics. In the dual CFT$_2$, the propagator can be recast as the HHLL four-point function, where by taking into account the $PSL (2,\mathbb{Z})$ modular images, we recover the bulk computation. We comment on the casual behavior of bulk geometries associated with single-trace operators of spin scaling with the central charge below the BTZ threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05524v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New quasi-Einstein metrics on a two--sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct all axi-symmetric non--gradient $m$--quasi--Einstein structures on a two--sphere. This includes the spatial cross-section of the extreme Kerr black hole horizon corresponding to $m=2$, as well as a family of new regular metrics with $m\neq 2$ given in terms of hypergeometric functions. We also show that in the case $m=-1$ with vanishing cosmological constant the only orientable compact solution in dimension two is the flat torus, which proves that there are no compact surfaces with a metrisable affine connection with skew Ricci tensor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04117v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Colling, Maciej Dunajski, Hari Kunduri, James Lucietti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a series of simple affine VOAs at non-admissible level arising from rank One 4D SCFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the representations of the simple affine vertex algebras at non-admissible level arising from rank one 4D SCFTs. In particular, we classify the irreducible highest weight modules of $L_{-2}(G_2)$ and $L_{-2}(B_3)$. It is known by the works of Adamovi\'{c} and Per\v{s}e that these vertex algebras can be conformally embedded into $L_{-2}(D_4)$. We also compute the associated variety of $L_{-2}(G_2)$, and show that it is the orbifold of the associated variety of $L_{-2}(D_4)$ by the symmetric group of degree 3 which is the Dynkin diagram automorphism group of $D_4$. This provides a new interesting example of associated variety satisfying a number of conjectures in the context of orbifold vertex algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04472v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoyuki Arakawa, Xuanzhong Dai, Justine Fasquel, Bohan Li, Anne Moreau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regular Black Holes From Pure Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04827v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show via an explicit construction how an infinite tower of higher-curvature corrections generically leads to a resolution of the Schwarzschild singularity in any spacetime dimension $D \ge 5$. The theories we consider have two key properties that ensure the results are general and robust: (1) they provide a basis for (vacuum) gravitational effective field theory in five and higher-dimensions, (2) for each value of the mass, they have a unique static spherically symmetric solution. We present several exact solutions of the theories that include the Hayward black hole and metrics similar to the Bardeen and Dymnikova ones. Unlike previous constructions, these regular black holes arise as vacuum solutions, as we include no matter fields whatsoever in our analysis. We show how the black hole thermodynamics can be studied in a completely universal and unambiguous way for all solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04827v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Bueno, Pablo A. Cano, Robie A. Hennigar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase structures and critical behaviour of rational non-linear electrodynamics AdS black holes in Rastall gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This research paper presents a black hole solution with a rational non-linear electrodynamics source in the Rastall gravity framework. The paper analyzes the thermodynamic properties of the solution in normal phase space and explores its critical behavior. The phase structure is examined using the extended first law of thermodynamics, with the cosmological constant $\Lambda$ serving as pressure $P$. The isotherms exhibit van der Waals behavior at small values of horizon $r_+$. The paper also investigates the Gibbs free energy behavior and finds two critical points with two pressures where the reentrant phase transition occurs and disappears. On the other hand, we explore the prevalent microstructure of black holes in Ruppeiner geometry, uncovering significant deviations in the nature of particle interactions from conventional practice. Moreover, the thermodynamic geometry is analyzed using the Ruppeiner formalism, with the normalized Ricci scalar indicating possible point-phase transitions of the heat capacity, and the normalized extrinsic curvature having the same sign as the normalized Ricci scalar. The three-phase transitions of the heat capacity are those that we find for the normalized Ruppeiner curvatures. Thus, there is an absolute correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04888v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1572-9494/ad30f4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Theoretical Physics (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yassine Sekhmani, Dhruba Jyoti Gogoi, Ratbay Myrzakulov, Javlon Rayimbaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic ETH: Eigenstate Thermalization beyond the Microcanonical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05197v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis (ETH) has played a key role in recent advances in the high energy and condensed matter communities. It explains how an isolated quantum system in a far-from-equilibrium initial state can evolve to a state that is indistinguishable from thermal equilibrium, with observables relaxing to almost time-independent results that can be described using traditional statistical mechanics ensembles. In this work we probe the limits of ETH, pushing it outside its prototypical applications in several directions. We design a qutrit lattice system with conserved quasilocal charge, in which we verify a form of generalized eigenstate thermalization. We also observe signatures of thermalization in states well outside microcanonical windows of both charge and energy, which we dub `generic ETH.'</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05197v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena C\'aceres, Stefan Eccles, Jason Pollack, Sarah Racz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proton Helicity GPDs from Lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05282v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: First lattice QCD calculations of $x$-dependent GPD have been performed in the (symmetric) Breit frame, where the momentum transfer is evenly divided between the initial and final hadron states. However, employing the asymmetric frame, we are able to obtain proton GPDs for multiple momentum transfers in a computationally efficient setup. In these proceedings, we focus on the helicity twist-2 GPD at zero skewness that gives access to the $\widetilde{H}$ GPD. We will cover the implementation of the asymmetric frame, its comparison to the Breit frame, and the dependence of the GPD on the squared four-momentum transfer, $-t$. The calculation is performed on an $N_f = 2+1+1$ ensemble of twisted mass fermions with a clover improvement. The mass of the pion for this ensemble is roughly 260 MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05282v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Miller, Shohini Bhattacharya, Krzysztof Cichy, Martha Constantinou, Xiang Gao, Andreas Metz, Swagato Mukherjee, Peter Petreczky, Fernanda Steffens, Yong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeley-DeWitt Coefficients in $\mathcal{N}=2$ Einstein-Maxwell Supergravity Theory and Logarithmic Corrections to $\mathcal{N}=2$ Extremal Black Hole Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.13058</link>
      <description>arXiv:1905.13058v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the heat kernel method for one-loop effective action following the Seeley-DeWitt expansion technique of heat kernel with Seeley-DeWitt coefficients. We also review a general approach of computing the Seeley-DeWitt coefficients in terms of background or geometric invariants. We, then consider the Einstein-Maxwell theory embedded in minimal $\mathcal{N}=2$ supergravity in four dimensions and compute the first three Seeley-DeWitt coefficients of the kinetic operator of the bosonic and the fermionic fields in an arbitrary background field configuration. We find the applications of these results in the computation of logarithmic corrections to Bekenstein-Hawking entropy of the extremal Kerr-Newman, Kerr and Reissner-Nordstrom black holes in minimal $\mathcal{N}=2$ Einstein-Maxwell supergravity theory following the quantum entropy function formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1905.13058v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP08(2019)056</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Physics 08(2019)056</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sudip Karan, Gourav Banerjee, Binata Panda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Landau and leading singularities in arbitrary space-time dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.09872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.09872v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using the decomposition of the $D$-dimensional space-time into parallel and perpendicular subspaces, we study and prove a connection between Landau and leading singularities for $N$-point one-loop Feynman integrals by applying multi-dimensional theory of residues. We show that if $D=N$ and $D=N+1$, the leading singularity corresponds to the inverse of the square root of the leading Landau singularity of the first and second type, respectively. We make use of this outcome to systematically provide differential equations of Feynman integrals in canonical forms and the extension of the connection of these singularities at multi-loop level by exploiting the loop-by-loop approach. Illustrative examples with the calculation of Landau and leading singularities are provided to supplement our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.09872v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech Flieger, William J. Torres Bobadilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sen's Mechanism for Self-Dual Super Maxwell theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.13856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.13856v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In several elementary particle scenarios, self-dual fields emerge as fundamental degrees of freedom. Some examples are the $D = 2$ chiral boson, $D = 10$ Type IIB supergravity, and $D = 6$ chiral tensor multiplet theory. For those models, a novel variational principle has been proposed in the work of Ashoke Sen. The coupling to supergravity of self-dual models in that new framework is rather peculiar to guarantee the decoupling of unphysical degrees of freedom. We generalize this technique to the self-dual super Maxwell gauge theory in $D = 4$ Euclidean spacetime both in the component formalism and the superspace. We use the geometric tools of rheonomy and integral forms since they are very powerful geometrical techniques for the extension to supergravity. We show the equivalence between the two formulations by choosing a different integral form defined using a Picture Changing Operator. That leads to a meaningful action functional for the variational equations. In addition, we couple the model to a non-dynamical gravitino to extend the analysis slightly beyond the free case. A full-fledged self-dual supergravity analysis will be presented elsewhere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.13856v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Barbagallo, Pietro Antonio Grassi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A two-tensor model with order-three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.06046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.06046v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a two-tensor model with order-3 and present its $W$-representation. Moreover we derive the compact expressions of correlators from the $W$-representation and analyze the free energy in large $N$ limit. In addition, we establish the correspondence between two colored Dyck walks in the Fredkin spin chain and tree operators in the ring. Based on the classification Dyck walks, we give the number of tree operators with the given level. Furthermore, we show the entanglement scaling of Fredkin spin chain beyond logarithmic scaling in the ordinary critical systems from the viewpoint of tensor model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.06046v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84 (2024) 239</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bei Kang, Lu-Yao Wang, Ke Wu, Wei-Zhong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Edge Mode in Asymptotically AdS$_2$: JT Gravity Revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.06088v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the gravitational edge mode of the Jackiw-Teitelboim (JT) gravity and its $sl(2,\mathbb{R})$ BF theory description with the asymptotic AdS$_2$ boundary condition. We revisit the derivation of the Schwarzian theory from the wiggling boundary as an action for the gravitational edge mode. We present an alternative description for the gravitational edge mode from the metric fluctuation with the fixed boundary, which is often referred as "would-be gauge mode". We clarify the relation between the wiggling boundary and the would-be gauge mode. We demonstrate a natural top-down derivation of $PSL(2,\mathbb{R})$ gauging and the path integral measure of the Schwarzian theory. In the $sl(2,\mathbb{R})$ BF theory, we incorporate the gravitational edge mode and derive the Schwarzian theory with $PSL(2,\mathbb{R})$ gauging. We also discuss the path integral measure from the Haar measure in the Iwasawa decomposition of $PSL(2,\mathbb{R})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.06088v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Euihun Joung, Prithvi Narayan, Junggi Yoon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massless Rarita-Schwinger equations: Half and three halves spin solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.00106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.00106v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Counting the degrees of freedom of the massless Rarita-Schwinger theory is revisited using Behrends-Fronsdal projectors. The identification of the gauge invariant part of the vector-spinor is thus straightforward, consisting of spins 1/2 and 3/2. The validity of this statement is supported by the explicit solution found in the standard gamma-traceless gauge. Since the obtained systems are deterministic -- free of arbitrary functions of time -- we argue that the often-invoked residual gauge symmetry lacks fundamental grounding and should not be used to enforce new external constraints. The result is verified by the total Hamiltonian dynamics. We conclude that eliminating the spin-12 mode \textit{via} the extended Hamiltonian dynamics would be acceptable if the Dirac conjecture was assumed; however, this framework does not accurately describe the original Lagrangian system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.00106v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhys.16.3.065</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. 16, 065 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio Valenzuela, Jorge Zanelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent symmetries of relativistic fluid dynamics from local ergodicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07021v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that volume-preserving diffomorphisms and the chemical shift symmetry defining relativistic lagrangian ideal fluid dynamics can be derived as an emerging symmetry when ergodicity is assumed to apply locally in a way that is invariant under smooth spacetime foliations. This can be used as a way to derive the ideal hydrodynamic limit in a strongly coupled but strongly fluctuating medium.
  We comment on the connection with thermalization in small systems, the Eigenstate thermalization hypothesis and deviations from the ideal limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07021v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Torrieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-duality/plurality of BTZ black hole metric coupled to two fermionic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14543v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We ask the question of classical super (non-)Abelian T-duality for BTZ black hole metric coupling to two fermionic fields. Our approach is based on super Poisson-Lie (PL) T-duality in the presence of spectator fields. In order to study the Abelian T-duality of the metric we dualize over the Abelian Lie supergroups of the types $(1|2)$ and $(2|2)$, in such a way that it is shown that both original and dual backgrounds of the models are conformally invariant up to one-loop order in the presence of field strength. Then, we study the non-Abelian T-duality of the BTZ vacuum metric coupling to two fermionic fields. The dualizing is performed on some non-Abelian Lie supergroups of the type $(2|2)$, in such a way that we are dealing with semi-Abelian superdoubles which are non-isomorphic as Lie superalgebras in each of the models. In the non-Abelian T-duality case, it is interesting to mention that the models can be conformally invariant up to one-loop order in both cases of the absence and presence of field strength. In addition, starting from the decomposition of semi-Abelian Drinfeld superdoubles generated by some of the ${\cal C}^3 \oplus {\cal A}_{1,1}$ Lie superbialgebras we study the super PL T-plurality of the BTZ vacuum metric coupled to two fermionic fields. However, our findings are interesting in themselves, but at a constructive level, can prompt many new insights into supergravity and manifestly have interesting mathematical relationships with double field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14543v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2024)040</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 03 (2024) 040</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ali Eghbali, Meysam Hosseinpour-Sadid, Adel Rezaei-Aghdam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular transform of free fermion generalised Gibbs ensembles and generalised power partitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07601v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In [1] a conjecture for the modular transformation of the free fermion generalised Gibbs ensemble (GGE) was given where only the KdV charge associated to the weight four quasi primary field was inserted. In this paper we first generalise this conjecture to the case with an arbitrary, finite collection of KdV charges in the GGE. These GGEs are generalisations of the generating function of power partitions. We prove the conjectured transformation for the case with a finite number of charges inserted and discuss the case with an infinite number of charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07601v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Downing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remarks on effects of projective phase on eigenstate thermalization hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The existence of $p$-form symmetry in $(d+1)$-dimensional quantum field is known to always lead to the breakdown of the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis (ETH) for certain $(d-p)$-dimensional operators other than symmetry operators under some assumptions. The assumptions include the mixing of symmetry sectors within a given energy shell, which is rather challenging to verify because it requires information on the eigenstates in the middle of the spectrum. We reconsider this assumption from the viewpoint of projective representations to avoid this difficulty. In the case of $\mathbb{Z}_N$ symmetries, we can circumvent the difficulty by considering $\mathbb{Z}_N\times\mathbb{Z}_N$-symmetric theories with nontrivial projective phases, and perturbing the Hamiltonian while preserving one of the $\mathbb{Z}_N$ symmetries of our interest. We also perform numerical analyses for $(1+1)$-dimensional spin chains and the $(2+1)$-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11425v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osamu Fukushima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The origin of the cosmological constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16522v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is well-known that in unimodular gravity the cosmological constant is not sourced by a constant energy density, but rather appears as some sort of integration constant. In this work we try to flesh this out by studying in some detail a couple of examples, one from cosmology and the other from gravitational collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16522v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique \'Alvarez, Jes\'us Anero, Irene S\'anchez-Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confinement from Distance in Metric Space and its Relation to Cosmological Constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17000v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We argue that, in a theory of quantum gravity, the gauge coupling and the confinement scale of a gauge theory are related to distance in the space of metric configurations, and in turn to the cosmological constant. To support the argument, we compute the gauge kinetic functions in variuos supersymmetric Heterotic and type II string compactifications and show that they depend on distance. According to the swampland program, the distance between two (anti) de Sitter vacua in the space of metric configurations is proportional to the logarithm of the ratio of cosmological constants and thus the confinement scale depends on the value of the cosmological constant. In this framework, for de Sitter space, we revisit the swampland Festina Lente bound and gauge theories in the dark dimension scenario. We show that if the Festina Lente bound is realized in a de Sitter vacuum and dependence on distance is strong enough, it will be realized in vacua with higher cosmological constants. In dark dimension scenario, as the value of cosmological constant is related to the decompactifying dimension, we find that the confinement scale is indeed related to radius of dark dimension. We show that in this scenario the Festina Lente bound holds for the standard model QCD, as well as all confining gauge groups with $N_c\lesssim 10^3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17000v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2024)043</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Amineh Mohseni, Mahdi Torabian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unravelling the Holomorphic Twist: Central Charges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.04304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.04304v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The holomorphic twist provides a powerful framework to study minimally protected sectors in supersymmetric quantum field theories. We investigate the algebraic structure underlying the holomorphic twist of $\mathcal{N} = 1$ superconformal field theories in four dimensions. In particular, in holomorphically twisted theories the flavour and conformal symmetry algebras are enhanced to infinite-dimensional higher Kac Moody and higher Virasoro symmetry algebras respectively. We explicitly compute the binary and ternary $\lambda$-brackets and clarify their relation with the underlying infinite-dimensional symmetry algebra. Doing so we show that the central extensions of said symmetry algebras precisely encode the conformal anomalies $a$ and $c$ as well as the flavour central charges of the physical four-dimensional theory. This parallels the familiar story in two dimensions where the conformal anomaly $c$ is encoded in the central extension of the Virasoro algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.04304v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pieter Bomans, Jingxiang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak Coupling Regime in Dilatonic f(R,T) Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14899v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider $f(R,T)$ modified theories of gravity in the context of string theory inspired dilaton gravity. We deal with a specific model that under certain conditions describes the late time Universe in accord with observational data in modern cosmology and addresses the $H_0$ tension. This is done by exploring the space of parameters made out of those coming from the modified gravity and dilatonic charge sectors. We employ numerical methods to obtain several important observable quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14899v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe1010000</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>F. A. Brito, C. H. A. B. Borges, J. A. V. Campos, F. G. Costa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field theory expansions of string theory amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05733v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by quantum field theory (QFT) considerations, we present new representations of the Euler-Beta function and tree-level string theory amplitudes using a new two-channel, local, crossing symmetric dispersion relation. Unlike standard series representations, the new ones are analytic everywhere except at the poles, sum over poles in all channels and include contact interactions, in the spirit of QFT. This enables us to consider mass-level truncation, which preserves all the features of the original amplitudes. By starting with such expansions for generalized Euler-Beta functions and demanding QFT like features, we single out the open superstring amplitude. We demonstrate the difficulty in deforming away from the string amplitude and show that a class of such deformations can be potentially interesting when there is level truncation. Our considerations also lead to new QFT-inspired, parametric representations of the Zeta function and $\pi$, which show fast convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05733v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Priya Saha, Aninda Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Surprises in the Python's Lunch Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06678v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A bulge surface, on a time reflection-symmetric Cauchy slice of a holographic spacetime, is a non-minimal extremal surface that occurs between two locally minimal surfaces homologous to a given boundary region. According to the python's lunch conjecture of Brown et al., the bulge's area controls the complexity of bulk reconstruction, in the sense of the amount of post-selection that needs to be overcome for the reconstruction of the entanglement wedge beyond the outermost extremal surface. We study the geometry of bulges in a variety of classical spacetimes, and discover a number of surprising features that distinguish them from more familiar extremal surfaces such as Ryu-Takayanagi surfaces: they spontaneously break spatial isometries, both continuous and discrete; they are sensitive to the choice of boundary infrared regulator; they can self-intersect; and they probe entanglement shadows, orbifold singularities, and compact spaces such as the sphere in AdS$_p\times S^q$. These features imply, according to the python's lunch conjecture, novel qualitative differences between complexity and entanglement in the holographic context. We also find, surprisingly, that extended black brane interiors have a non-extensive complexity; similarly, for multi-boundary wormhole states, the complexity pleateaus after a certain number of boundaries have been included.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06678v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gurbir Arora, Matthew Headrick, Albion Lawrence, Martin Sasieta, Connor Wolfe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Large to Small $\mathcal{N}=(4,4)$ Superconformal Surface Defects in Holographic 6d SCFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11745v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2d) $\mathcal{N}=(4,4)$ Lie superalgebras can be either "small" or "large", meaning their R-symmetry is either $\mathfrak{so}(4)$ or $\mathfrak{so}(4) \oplus \mathfrak{so}(4)$, respectively. Both cases admit a superconformal extension and fit into the one-parameter family $\mathfrak{d}\left(2,1;\gamma\right)\oplus \mathfrak{d}\left(2,1;\gamma\right)$, with parameter $\gamma \in (-\infty,\infty)$. The large algebra corresponds to generic values of $\gamma$, while the small case corresponds to a degeneration limit with $\gamma \to -\infty$. In 11d supergravity, we study known solutions with superisometry algebra $\mathfrak{d}\left(2,1;\gamma\right)\oplus \mathfrak{d}\left(2,1;\gamma\right)$ that are asymptotically locally AdS$_7 \times S^4$. These solutions are holographically dual to the 6d maximally superconformal field theory with 2d superconformal defects invariant under $\mathfrak{d}\left(2,1;\gamma\right)\oplus \mathfrak{d}\left(2,1;\gamma\right)$. We show that a limit of these solutions, in which $\gamma \to -\infty$, reproduces another known class of solutions, holographically dual to small $\mathcal{N}=(4,4)$ superconformal defects. We then use this limit to generate new small $\mathcal{N}=(4,4)$ solutions with finite Ricci scalar, in contrast to the known small $\mathcal{N}=(4,4)$ solutions. We then use holography to compute the entanglement entropy of a spherical region centered on these small $\mathcal{N}=(4,4)$ defects, which provides a linear combination of defect Weyl anomaly coefficients that characterizes the number of defect-localized degrees of freedom. We also comment on the generalization of our results to include $\mathcal{N}=(0,4)$ surface defects through orbifolding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11745v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Capuozzo, John Estes, Brandon Robinson, Benjamin Suzzoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-loop quantization of Euclidean D3-branes in holographic backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16779v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note we analyze the semi-classical quantization of D3 branes in three different holographic backgrounds in type IIB string theory. The first background is Euclidean AdS$_5$ with $S^1\times S^3$ boundary accompanied with a twist to preserve supersymmetry. We work out the spectrum of fluctuations around the classical D3-brane configuration, compute its one-loop partition function, and match to the non-perturbative correction to the superconformal index of ${\cal N}=4$ SYM. We then study Euclidean D3-branes in the Pilch-Warner geometry dual to the IR Leigh-Strassler fixed point of ${\cal N}=1^*$ with the aim to find non-perturbative corrections to its index. Finally we study Euclidean D3-branes in the non-geometric ${\cal N}=2$ J-fold background which is dual to the gauging of the 3D Gaiotto-Witten SCFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16779v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fridrik Freyr Gautason, Jesse van Muiden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasinormal Modes and Greybody factors of de Sitter Black holes surrounded by Quintessence in Rastall gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09976v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we have studied the quasinormal mode, greybody factors, and absorption cross section of de Sitter Reissner-Nordstr\"om black hole surrounded by quintessence field in Rastall gravity. The violation of energy-momentum conservation has a non-linear effect on the quasinormal modes. With an increase in the black hole charge, both real parts of quasinormal modes i.e. oscillation frequency of ring-down Gravitational Waves (GWs) and damping or decay rate of GWs increase non-linearly. A similar observation is made for the black hole structural parameter also, however in this case the variation is almost linear. The remnant mass of a black hole depends on different physical parameters of a black hole. In the case of greybody factors also, we observed that both parameters have similar impacts. With an increase in these parameters, greybody factors decrease. Moreover, the null geodesics and the impact of Rastall gravity on the light trajectory are also investigated. Our study suggests that the presence of a surrounding quintessence field may shadow the existence of black hole charges in such black hole configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09976v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/prop.202300245</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Fortschritte der Physik 72, 2300245 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dhruba Jyoti Gogoi, N. Heidari, J. K\v{r}\'i\v{z}, H. Hassanabadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On counterexamples to unique continuation for critically singular wave equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.03525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.03525v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider wave equations with a critically singular potential $\xi \cdot \sigma^{-2}$ diverging as an inverse square at a hypersurface $\sigma = 0$. Our aim is to construct counterexamples to unique continuation from $\sigma = 0$ for this equation, provided there exists a family of null geodesics trapped near $\sigma = 0$. This extends the classical geometric optics construction of Alinhac-Baouendi (i) to linear differential operators with singular coefficients, and (ii) over non-small portions of $\sigma = 0$ - by showing that such counterexamples can be further continued as long as this null geodesic family remains trapped and regular. As an application to relativity and holography, we construct counterexamples to unique continuation from the conformal boundaries of asymptotically Anti-de Sitter spacetimes for some Klein-Gordon equations; this complements the unique continuation results of the second author with Chatzikaleas, Holzegel, and McGill and suggests a potential mechanism for counterexamples to the AdS/CFT correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.03525v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Guisset, Arick Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Induced Gravitational Wave interpretation of PTA data: a complete study for general equation of state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18965v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We thoroughly study the induced gravitational wave interpretation of the possible gravitational wave background reported by PTA collaborations, considering the unknown equation of state $w$ of the early universe. We perform a Bayesian analysis of the NANOGrav data using the publicly available \textsc{PTArcade} code together with \textsc{SIGWfast} for the numerical integration of the induced gravitational wave spectrum. We focus on two cases: a monochromatic and a log-normal primordial spectrum of fluctuations. For the log-normal spectrum, we show that, while the results are not very sensitive to $w$ when the GW peak is close to the PTA window, radiation domination is out of the $2\sigma$ contours when only the infra-red power-law tail contributes. For the monochromatic spectrum, the $2\sigma$ bounds yield $0.1\lesssim w\lesssim0.9$ so that radiation domination is close to the central value. We also investigate the primordial black hole (PBH) counterpart using the peak formalism. We show that, in general terms, a larger width and stiffer equation of state alleviates the overproduction of PBHs. No PBH overproduction requires $w\gtrsim0.42$ up to 2-$\sigma$ level for the monochromatic spectrum. Furthermore, including bounds from the cosmic microwave background, we find in general that the mass range of the PBH counterpart is bounded by $10^{-5} M_\odot\lesssim M_{\rm PBH}\lesssim10^{-1} M_\odot$. Lastly, we find that the PTA signal can explain the microlensing events reported by OGLE for $0.42\lesssim w\lesssim 0.50$. Our work showcases a complete treatment of induced gravitational waves and primordial black holes for general $w$ for future data analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18965v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillem Dom\`enech, Shi Pi, Ao Wang, Jianing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical tidal response of non-rotating relativistic stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03254v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurately modeling the tidal response of neutron stars is crucial to connecting gravitational wave observations of binaries to ultra-dense nuclear physics. Most current models of the tidal response of relativistic stars either assume a static response model, or use phenomenological models inspired by Newtonian gravity. In this work, we present a general formalism for computing the linear dynamical tidal response function of relativistic, spherically symmetric stars. Our formalism incorporates stratification due to thermal and chemical imbalances, allowing one to study the effects of g modes on the tidal response function. We also describe how to incorporate sources of dissipation due to shear and bulk viscosity. To showcase the utility of our approach, we present several applications for polytropic stars in general relativity. We show how our formalism can capture the dynamical tidal resonance due to the f and g modes of inviscid stars and explore the sensitivity of the dynamical tidal response to the compactness of the star. We also compute the dissipative tidal deformability due to bulk and shear viscous dissipation. We find that, for the same viscous profile, the shear viscous tidal lag parameter is 100-1000 times larger than the dimensionless bulk viscous tidal lag parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03254v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Hegade K. R., Justin L. Ripley, Nicol\'as Yunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
