<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 04:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted Baker-Akhiezer function from determinants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: General description of eigenfunctions of integrable Hamiltonians associated with the integer rays of Ding-Iohara-Miki (DIM) algebra, is provided by the theory of Chalykh Baker-Akhiezer functions (BAF) defined as solutions to a simply looking linear system. Solutions themselves are somewhat complicated, but much simpler than they could. It is because of simultaneous partial factorization of all the determinants, entering Cramer's rule. This is a conspiracy responsible for a relative simplicity of the Macdonald polynomials and of the Noumi-Shirashi functions, and it is further continued to all integer DIM rays. Still, factorization is only partial, moreover, there are different branches and abrupt jumps between them. We explain this feature of Cramer's rule in an example of a matrix that defines BAF and exhibits a non-analytical dependence on parameters. Moreover, the matrix is such that there is no natural expansion around non-degenerate approximations, which causes an unexpected complexity of formulas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02022v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Mironov, A. Morozov, A. Popolitov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noninvertible symmetries in the B model TFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02023v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we explore noninvertible symmetries in general (not necessarily rational) SCFTs and their topological B-twists for Calabi-Yau manifolds. We begin with a detailed overview of defects in the topological B model. For trivial reasons, all defects in the topological B model are topological operators, and define (often noninvertible) symmetries of that topological field theory, but only a subset remain topological in the physical (i.e., untwisted) theory. For a general target space Calabi-Yau X, we discuss geometric realizations of those defects, as simultaneously A- and B-twistable complex Lagrangian and complex coisotropic branes on X \times X, and discuss their fusion products. To be clear, the possible noninvertible symmetries in the B model are more general than can be described with fusion categories. That said, we do describe realizations of some Tambara-Yamagami categories in the B model for an elliptic curve target, and also argue that elliptic curves can not admit Fibonacci or Haagerup structures. We also discuss how decomposition is realized in this language.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02023v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Caldararu, T. Pantev, E. Sharpe, B. Sung, X. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spinning self-force EFT: 1SF waveform recursion relation and Compton scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Building on recent approaches, we develop an effective field theory for the interaction of spinning particles modeling Kerr black holes within the gravitational self-force expansion. To incorporate dimensional regularization into this framework, we analyze the Myers-Perry black hole and its particle description, obtaining a novel exponential form of the corresponding linearized stress tensor. We then derive the 1SF self-force effective action up to quadratic order in the spin expansion, identifying a new type of spinning recoil term that arises from integrating out the heavy dynamics. Next, we study the 1SF metric perturbation both from the traditional self-force perspective and through the diagrammatic background field expansion, making contact with the radiative waveform. This leads us to consider a novel recursion relation for the curved space 1SF Compton amplitude, which we study up to one-loop in the wave regime and compare with the flat space one-loop Compton amplitude for Kerr up to quadratic order in spin. Finally, we investigate the 1SF spinning Compton amplitude in the eikonal regime, clarifying how strong-field effects -- such as the location of the separatrix -- emerge from the resummation of the perturbative weak-field expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02025v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dogan Akpinar, Vittorio del Duca, Riccardo Gonzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tri-vector symmetry of 11 dimensional supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02029v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kaluza-Klein reductions of 11-dimensional supergravity lead to exceptional global symmetries in lower dimensions. Certain non-geometric elements of these symmetries, parameterized by a tri-vector $\gamma$, are not inherited from the higher-dimensional local symmetries, but represent instead a symmetry enhancement produced by the isometries of the background. Here, we demonstrate how to realize this enhancement in 11 dimensions, as a symmetry principle with constrained parameters. We show that $\gamma$ transformations exchange the equations of motion of the metric and the three-form with their Bianchi identities, in a closed form, structuring them into tri-vector multiplets. Implementing this principle as an off-shell symmetry of the theory requires the introduction of a hierarchy of dual fields, including a six-form and a dual graviton in the initial levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02029v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Walter H. Baron, Diego Marques, Carmen A. Nunez, Nahuel Yazbek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization of massive fermions in vacuum and external fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study massive Majorana neutrinos in background matter. Representing these particles in terms of Weyl spinors, we carry out their quantization. The propagators of these fields are also constructed. Then, we apply the Hamilton dynamics based formalism to describe massive Majorana neutrinos in matter on the classical level. Finally, we study a classical Dirac particle in vacuum, described with $c$-number variables, within the Hamiton formalism. Such a Dirac field is also canonically quantized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02365v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxim Dvornikov (IZMIRAN)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-loop effective potential for arbitrary scalar models in curved space-time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we calculate the leading divergences of the effective potential for an arbitrary scalar theory on a curved spacetime background. Based on the recurrence relation between the leading poles following from the locality condition, we obtain a system of generalised renormalisation-group equations that can be studied numerically or analytically in some special cases. We study the simplest effective potentials for power-like models and give a comparison of them in the framework of cosmological phenomenology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02418v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Filippov, R. M. Iakhibbaev, D. M. Tolkachev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating Function of Loop Reduction by Baikov Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02573v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we study the computation of reduction coefficients for multi loop Feynman integrals using generating functions constructed within the Baikov representation. Compared with traditional Feynman rules, the Baikov formalism offers a more structured and transparent framework, especially well suited for analyzing the reduction problem. We emphasize that, in a variety of nontrivial cases including several one loop and selected multi loop examples the generating functions can be explicitly computed in closed form, often involving hypergeometric or elementary functions. These analytic expressions signifi cantly simplify the determination of reduction coefficients and enhance their interpretability. The results demonstrate the practicality and potential of this approach, suggesting that the use of generating functions within the Baikov representation can serve as a powerful and flexible tool in modern Feynman integral reduction, even though its full scope for generic multi-loop topologies remains to be explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02573v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Hu, Wen-Di Li, Xiang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Equation for Massless Spin Particles and New Spin Coefficient Definitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new definition for the spin coefficients $\rho$, $\mu$, $\tau$, and $\pi$, which are defined as the directional derivatives of the logarithm of a generating function along the null tetrad ($l^{\mu}$, $n^{\mu}$, $m^{\mu}$, $\bar{m}^{\mu}$), respectively. This is the first discovery that these spin coefficients are interconnected through a generating function. Using the newly defined spin coefficients, we find that the field equations for massless particles with spins 0, 1/2, 1, 3/2, and 2 in arbitrary black hole spacetimes can be described by a single unified equation. This finding is particularly surprising, as unifying these field equations is already a significant challenge in flat spacetime, let alone in the intricate spacetime around black holes. Consequently, this work will inevitably prompt a re-examination of the shared characteristics among various types of particles in black hole spacetimes. Meanwhile, we verify the correctness of the new definition for the spin coefficients, and provide the explicit form of the unified equation for nearly all known black hole backgrounds. This lays a solid foundation for studying the behavior of massless spin particles in any black hole background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02592v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Heng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Holes, Moduli Stabilisation and the Swampland</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02645v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In theories with moduli, extremal black holes behave such that for generic initial conditions, the distance traveled by the scalars from infinity to the horizon can grow with the size of the black hole. This, in turn, implies that larger black holes can probe more of the UV ingredients of the theory, in contrast with (naive) EFT expectations. We relate this discrepancy to the lack of cosmological moduli stabilisation. Indeed, for would-be scale-separated string vacua with parametrically heavy stabilised scalars -- dubbed \emph{rigid} compactifications -- one recovers the EFT intuition where only small black holes probe the UV. We make this explicit in a toy model and then turn to top-down models and construct near-horizon solutions in IIA scale-separated compactifications with stabilised moduli. In these top-down models we still observe large field variations for large black holes which can be traced back to the absence of parametrically heavy moduli. We are led to speculate that needing UV physics to allow for non-local effects near the horizon of large black holes is at odds with having a rigid compactification, hinting to the possibility that such compactifications are in the Swampland.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02645v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matilda Delgado, S\'ebastien Reymond, Thomas Van Riet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The early universe is $\textit{ACT}$-ing $\textit{warm}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recently released data from the $\textit{Atacama Cosmology Telescope}$ (ACT) confirms that the primordial scalar spectrum is extremely flat. This, together with current upper bounds on the tensor-to-scalar ratio, implies that the simplest models of inflation coming from particle physics (for instance, a minimally-coupled scalar with monomial potentials) need additional ingredients in order to make them compatible with observations. Instead of invoking arbitrary new couplings or new interactions that are not protected symmetries, we argue that dissipation of the inflaton field with the radiation bath should be added as a new physical principle. Accordingly, we show that warm inflation provides the correct paradigm to explain the current observations, given very natural choices of dissipative terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02655v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Berera, Suddhasattwa Brahma, Zizang Qiu, Rudnei O. Ramos, Gabriel S. Rodrigues</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on the Gell-Mann--Low functions in quantum electrodynamics and in the Wess-Zumino model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01514v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive bounds $ |\frac{d\psi(\alpha)}{d\alpha}| \leq 1 $, $ \frac{d(\frac{d\psi(\alpha)}{d\alpha}\psi(\alpha))}{d\alpha} \leq 1 $ on the GL (Gell-Mann--Low) function $\psi(\alpha)$ from the Kallen-Lehmann dispersion representation in quantum electrodynamics. We also derive analogous bounds for the GL function in the Wess-Zumino model. The implications of the obtained inequalities are discussed. In particular, we obtain bounds on coupling constants in dark photon model and in dark matter model with vector $(B-L)$ messenger.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01514v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. V. Krasnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self Consistent Thermal Resummation: A Case Study of the Phase Transition in 2HDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02024v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An accurate description of the scalar potential at finite temperature is crucial for studying cosmological first-order phase transitions (FOPT) in the early Universe. At finite temperatures, a precise treatment of thermal resummations is essential, as bosonic fields encounter significant infrared issues that can compromise standard perturbative approaches. The Partial Dressing (or the tadpole resummation) method provides a self consistent resummation of higher order corrections, allowing the computation of thermal masses and the effective potential including the proper Boltzmann suppression factors and without relying on any high-temperature approximation. We systematically compare the Partial dressing resummation scheme results with the Parwani and Arnold Espinosa (AE) ones to investigate the thermal phase transition dynamics in the Two-Higgs-Doublet Model (2HDM). Our findings reveal that different resummation prescriptions can significantly alter the nature of the phase transition within the same region of parameter space, confirming the differences that have already been noticed between the Parwani and AE schemes. Notably, the more refined resummation prescription, the Partial Dressing scheme, does not support symmetry non-restoration in 2HDM at high temperatures observed using the AE prescription. Furthermore, we quantify the uncertainties in the stochastic gravitational wave (GW) spectrum from an FOPT due to variations in resummation methods, illustrating their role in shaping theoretical predictions for upcoming GW experiments. Finally, we discuss the capability of the High-Luminosity LHC and proposed GW experiments to probe the FOEWPT-favored region of the parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02024v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Bittar, Subhojit Roy, Carlos E. M. Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing axion-like particles with multimessenger observations of neutron star mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02032v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Axion-like particles (ALPs) can be copiously produced in binary neutron star (BNS) mergers through nucleon-nucleon bremsstrahlung if the ALP-nucleon couplings $g_{a N}$ are sizable. Furthermore, the ALP-photon coupling $g_{a\gamma}$ may trigger conversions of ultralight ALPs into photons in the magnetic fields of the merger remnant and of the Milky Way. This effect would lead to a potentially observable short gamma-ray signal, in coincidence with the gravitational-wave signal produced during the merging process. This event could be detected through multi-messenger observation of BNS mergers employing the synergy between gravitational-wave detectors and gamma-ray telescopes. Here, we study the sensitivity of current and proposed MeV gamma-ray experiments to detect such a signal. We find that the proposed instruments can reach a sensitivity down to $g_{a\gamma}\gtrsim \textrm{few} \times 10^{-13}\,\text{GeV}^{-1}$ for $m_a \lesssim 10^{-9}~\mathrm{eV}$, comparable with the SN 1987A limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02032v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Lecce, Alessandro Lella, Giuseppe Lucente, Vimal Vijayan, Andreas Bauswein, Maurizio Giannotti, Alessandro Mirizzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Instantons and the Post-Inflationary QCD Axion in a Special Product GUT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02033v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new framework of grand unification that is equipped with an axion solution to the strong CP problem without a domain wall problem when the Peccei-Quinn (PQ) symmetry is spontaneously broken after inflation. Our grand unified theory (GUT) is based on a symmetry breaking pattern, $SU(10) \times SU(5)_1 \rightarrow SU(5)_V \supset SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, where $SU(5)_1$ and a special embedding of $SU(5)_2\subset SU(10)$ are broken to a diagonal subgroup $SU(5)_V$. The model contains a vector-like pair of PQ-charged fermions that transform as (anti-)fundamental representations under $SU(10)$, so that the domain wall number is one. However, after the GUT symmetry breaking, the number of vector-like pairs of PQ-charged colored fermions is larger than one, which seems to encounter the domain wall problem. This apparent inconsistency is resolved by small instanton effects on the axion potential which operate as a PQ-violating bias term and allow the decay of domain walls. We propose a domain-wall-free UV completion for an IR model where the domain wall number appears larger than one. The model gives a prediction for a dark matter axion window, which is different from that of the ordinary post-inflationary QCD axion with domain wall number one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02033v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shihwen Hor, Yuichiro Nakai, Motoo Suzuki, Junxuan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F-Term Hybrid Inflation and SUSY Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02121v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider F-term hybrid inflation and supersymmetry breaking in the context of a model which largely respects a global U(1) R symmetry. The Kaehler potential parameterizes the Kaehler manifold with an enhanced U(1)_Rx(SU(1,1)/U(1)) symmetry, where the scalar curvature of the second factor is determined by the achievement of a supersymmetry-breaking de Sitter vacuum without ugly tuning. The magnitude of the emergent soft tadpole term for the inflaton can be adjusted in the range (1.2-460) TeV -- increasing with the dimensionality of the representation of the waterfall fields -- so that the inflationary observables are in agreement with the observational requirements. The mass scale of the supersymmetric partners turns out to lie in the region (0.09-253) PeV which is compatible with high-scale supersymmetry and the results of LHC on the Higgs boson mass. The mu parameter can be generated by conveniently applying the Giudice-Masiero mechanism and assures the out-of-equilibrium decay of the R saxion at a low reheat temperature Trh&lt;163 GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02121v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Pallis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Braided Majorana qubits as a minimal setting for Topological Quantum Computation?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02125v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I point out that a possible minimal setting to realize Kitaev's proposal of a Topological Quantum Computation which offers topological protection from decoherence could in principle be realized by braided Majorana qubits. Majorana qubits and their braiding were introduced in Nucl. Phys. B 980, 115834 (2022) and further analyzed in J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 57, 435203 (2024). Braided Majorana qubits implement a Gentile-type parastatistics with at most $s-1$ excited states accommodated in a multiparticle sector (the integer $s=2,3,4,\ldots$ labels quantum group reps at roots of unity). It is argued that braided Majorana qubits could play, for topological quantum computers, the same role as standard bits for ordinary computers and as qubits for "ordinary" quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02125v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Toppan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An exact five dimensional Weyl-Geometry Gauss-Bonnet Black Hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02230v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new exact black hole solution of a 5-dimensional Weyl-geometry Gauss-Bonnet theory of gravity. The Euclidean sector defines a fully regular metric coupled to the Weyl vector field. The Euclidean action and entropy are computed, with the latter following the simple $A/4$ form plus a term linear in the horizon radius, characteristic of Gauss-Bonnet couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02230v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Bahamonde, M\'aximo Ba\~nados</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigorous results for timelike Liouville field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Liouville field theory has long been a cornerstone of two-dimensional quantum field theory and quantum gravity, which has attracted much recent attention in the mathematics literature. Timelike Liouville field theory is a version of Liouville field theory where the kinetic term in the action appears with a negative sign, which makes it closer to a theory of quantum gravity than ordinary (spacelike) Liouville field theory. Making sense of this "wrong sign" requires a theory of Gaussian random variables with negative variance. Such a theory is developed in this paper, and is used to prove the timelike DOZZ formula for the $3$-point correlation function when the parameters satisfy the so-called "charge neutrality condition". Expressions are derived also for the $k$-point correlation functions for all $k\ge 3$, and it is shown that these functions approach the correct semiclassical limits as the coupling constant is sent to zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02348v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave with Domain Wall Dominance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02462v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Domain walls (DWs) can be produced when a discrete symmetry is spontaneously broken, and long-lived DWs can dominate the energy density of the universe. In this work, we explore the possibility that a "domain wall dominant (DWD)" phase existed in the early universe and ended with DW decay. During the DWD phase, the universe undergoes a power-law accelerated expansion of the scale factor and exhibits temporal superhorizon evolution of the relevant frequency modes. We show that this can lead to distinct features imprinted on the stochastic gravitational wave (GW) background. Our findings provide a comprehensive framework for evaluating GW emission associated with DWD, leading to distinguishable long-lived DW-induced GWs from other cosmological sources, with significant implications for future GW observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02462v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sungwoo Hong, Sung Mook Lee, Qiuyue Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-loop correction to primordial tensor modes during radiation era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02609v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The ability to infer properties of primordial inflation relies on the conservation of the superhorizon perturbations between their exit during inflation, and their re-entry during radiation era. Any considerable departure from this property would require reinterpreting the data. This is why it is important to understand how superhorizon perturbations interact with the thermal plasma driving the radiation dominated Universe. We model the plasma by free photons in a thermal state and compute the one-loop correction to the power spectrum of primordial tensor perturbations. This correction grows in time and is not suppressed by any small parameter. While one-loop result is not reliable because it invalidates perturbation theory, it signals potentially interesting effects that should be investigated further.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02609v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus B. Fr\"ob, Dra\v{z}en Glavan, Paolo Meda, Ignacy Sawicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Langevin Simulations of Supersymmetric Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This review explores the Complex Langevin Method (CLM), a stochastic quantization technique designed to address the sign problem in quantum field theories with complex actions. Beginning with foundational principles, the review examines the applications of CLM across a range of models, including zero- and two-dimensional systems, supersymmetric quantum mechanics, and the IKKT matrix model, a candidate for non-perturbative string theory. Key advancements, such as stabilization techniques and mass deformations, are highlighted as solutions to challenges like numerical instability and singular drift terms. The review emphasizes the capacity of CLM to simulate complex systems and reveal non-perturbative phenomena, positioning it as a powerful tool for exploring quantum field theory and string theory. Future directions, including higher-dimensional applications and benchmarking against quantum simulations, underscore the potential of CLM to advance both theoretical understanding and computational methodologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02660v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anosh Joseph, Arpith Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parity violation as enforced symmetry breaking in 3D fermionic topological order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02736v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Symmetry can be intrinsically broken in topological phases due to inherent incompatibilities, a phenomenon known as enforced symmetry breaking (ESB) in the framework of topological order. In our previous work, we developed a systematic framework to understand ESB within 2D invertible topological order. Meanwhile, the origin of parity violation in the Standard Model remains one of the most profound mysteries in physics, with no clear explanation to date. In this study, we explore the ESB of parity symmetry by three-dimensional fermionic topological order (fTO), offering potential insights into the origins of parity violation. As the simplest example, here we consider an fTO related to the intrinsic interacting fermionic SPT phase protected by $Z_2^f\times Z_2\times Z_8$ symmetry in three dimensions. We show that time-reversal symmetry (TRS) with ${T}^2=1$ on physical fermions is incompatible with such fTO; then, through the so-called crystalline equivalence principle, we show that the parity symmetry is also incompatible with it. In comparison, conventional TRS with ${T}^2={P}_f$ remains compatible to this fTO. We also discuss a general framework to study the ESB phenomenon for 3D fTO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02736v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shang-Qiang Ning, Yang Qi, Chenjie Wang, Zheng-Cheng Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry protected topological wire in a topological vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02745v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Symmetry-protected topological phases host gapless modes at their boundary with a featureless environment of the same dimension or a trivial vacuum. In this study, we explore their behavior in a higher-dimensional environment, which itself is non-trivial - a topological vacuum. In particular, we embed a one-dimensional topological wire within a two-dimensional Chern insulator, allowing the zero-dimensional edge modes of the wire to interplay with the surrounding chiral boundary states created by the environment. In contrast to a trivial vacuum, we show depending on the nature of low energy modes, the topology of the environment selectively influences the topological phase transitions of the wire. Interestingly, such selectivity leads to scenarios where the environment trivializes the wire and even induces topological character in an otherwise trivial phase - an example of `proximity-induced topology'. Using both numerical and analytical approaches, we establish the general framework of such embedding and uncover the role of symmetries in shaping the fate of low-energy theories. Our findings will provide a deeper understanding of heterostructural topological systems, paving the way for their experimental exploration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02745v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subrata Pachhal, Adhip Agarwala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the CMB revealing signs of pre-inflationary physics?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02746v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given the latest observational constraints coming from the joint analyses of the Atacama Cosmology Telescope, the Planck Satellite and other missions, we point out the possibility of reconciling fundamental particle-physics models of inflation with data by considering non-Bunch-Davies initial conditions for primordial density perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02746v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suddhasattwa Brahma, Jaime Calder\'on-Figueroa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting gravitational fields of Topologically Massive Gravity using geodesic deviation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02772v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study relative motion of nearby test particles in Topologically Massive Gravity (TMG) in three spacetime dimensions, using the equation of geodesic deviation. We show that, in a suitable reference frame, the influence of any gravitational field can be decomposed into transverse, longitudinal, and Newtonian components, which are directly related to the Cotton scalars of the Newman-Penrose-type. In particular, we prove that Cotton type N spacetimes exhibit a purely transverse gravitational effect on test particles, and can thus be reasonably interpreted as specific gravitational waves with a single polarization mode in TMG. The influence of the cosmological constant manifests itself as an isotropic effect. We also discuss the physical interpretation of spacetimes of specific algebraic types, as well as the influence of various matter fields, namely pure radiation, perfect fluid, and electromagnetic field. As an example, we provide an explicit analysis of TN-waves and pp-waves in three-dimensional TMG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02772v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matus Papajcik, Jiri Podolsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum maximally symmetric space-times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that 4-dimensional maximally symmetric spacetimes can be obtained from a coherent state quantisation of gravity, always resulting in geometries that approach the Minkowski vacuum exponentially away from the radius of curvature. A possible connection with the central charge in the AdS/CFT correspondence is also noted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02786v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Meert, Andrea Giusti, Roberto Casadio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubbles in a box: Eliminating edge nucleation in cold-atom simulators of vacuum decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02829v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The decay of metastable 'false vacuum' states via bubble nucleation plays a crucial role in many cosmological scenarios. Cold-atom analog experiments will soon provide the first empirical probes of this process, with potentially far-reaching implications for early-Universe cosmology and high-energy physics. However, an inevitable difference between these analog systems and the early Universe is that the former have a boundary. We show, using a combination of Euclidean calculations and real-time lattice simulations, that these boundaries generically cause rapid bubble nucleation on the edge of the experiment, obscuring the bulk nucleation that is relevant for cosmology. We demonstrate that implementing a high-density 'trench' region at the boundary completely eliminates this problem, and recovers the desired cosmological behavior. Our findings are relevant for ongoing efforts to probe vacuum decay in the laboratory, providing a practical solution to a key experimental obstacle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02829v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander C. Jenkins, Hiranya V. Peiris, Andrew Pontzen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic thin wall false vacuum decay rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.04498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.04498v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive a closed-form false vacuum decay rate at one loop in the thin wall limit, where the true and false vacua are nearly degenerate. We obtain the bounce configuration in $D$ dimensions, together with the Euclidean action with a higher order correction, counter-terms and renormalization group running. We extract the functional determinant via the Gel'fand-Yaglom theorem for low and generic orbital multipoles. The negative and zero eigenvalues appear for low multipoles and the translational zeroes are removed. We compute the fluctuations for generic multipoles, multiply and regulate the orbital modes. We find an explicit finite renormalized decay rate in $D = 3, 4$ and give a closed-form expression for the finite functional determinant in any dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.04498v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2022)209</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2022, 209 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandar Ivanov, Marco Matteini, Miha Nemev\v{s}ek, Lorenzo Ubaldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The free energy of the large-$N$ fermionic Chern$\small-$Simons theory in the 'temporal' gauge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.11020v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Most of the computational evidence for the Bose$\small-$Fermi duality of fundamental fields coupled to $U(N)$ Chern$\small-$Simons theories originates in large-$N$ calculations performed in the light-cone gauge. This gauge is ill-suited to computations in curved spacetimes, like the evaluation of the partition function on $\Sigma_g\times S^1$ for arbitrary genus $g$. In this paper, we use another gauge, the 'temporal' gauge, to set up the computation of this partition function. In the large-$N$ limit, and the special case $\Sigma_g=\mathbb{R}^2$, we take the computation through to the end by setting up and solving the gap equations, generalizing tricks explored in arXiv:1410.0558 to finite temperature. Our final results are in perfect agreement with earlier light-cone gauge results, providing a consistency check of both the formalism developed in this paper as well as previously performed light-cone gauge computations. In a follow-up paper, we will report on using our formalism to explicitly compute the partition function on $S^2 \times S^1$ for a finite-sized sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.11020v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiraz Minwalla, Souparna Nath, Nikhil Tanwar,  Vatsal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed string amplitudes around tachyon vacuum solution in Kaku theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14308v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We incorporate closed string field into Kaku's open string field theory which is defined by using Kaku vertex, and we construct open-closed string field theory. To do this, we define new consistent open-closed vertex and open-open-closed vertex with the Kaku vertex. Because these vertices depend on Chan-Paton parameter such as the Kaku vertex, the open-closed string field theory action that we construct depends on the Chan-Paton parameter such as the Kaku's theory action. However, we can show that an infinitesimal change of $l$ corresponds to a field redefinition. Furthermore, we compute closed string amplitudes around tachyon vacuum solution in this theory. As a result, we confirm that these are conventional pure closed string amplitudes on surfaces without boundaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14308v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP04(2025)029</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 04 (2025) 029</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuji Ando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\beta$ symmetry in type II Supergravities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15061v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A non geometric sector of the duality group emerging in Kaluza-Klein reductions is realized as an effective symmetry in the low energy action of uncompactified type II theories. This is achieved by extending the so called $\beta$ symmetry of the universal NS-NS sector to the R-R sector of type IIA, IIB and massive type IIA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15061v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Walter H. Baron, Nahuel A. Yazbek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>False Vacuum Decay Rate From Thin To Thick Walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17632v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a single real scalar field in flat spacetime with a polynomial potential up to $\phi^4$, that has a local minimum, the false vacuum, and a deeper global minimum, the true vacuum. When the vacua are almost degenerate we are in the thin wall regime, while as their difference in potential energy increases, we approach the thick wall regime. We give explicit simple formulae for the decay rate of the false vacuum in 3 and 4 spacetime dimensions. Our results include a careful treatment both of the bounce action, which enters at the exponent of the decay rate, and of the functional determinant at one loop, which determines the prefactor. The bounce action is computed analytically as an expansion in the thin wall parameter in generic $D$ dimensions. We find that truncating such an expansion at second order we obtain a remarkably accurate bounce action also deep into thick wall regimes. We calculate the functional determinant numerically in 3 and 4 dimensions and fit the results with simple polynomials of the same thin wall parameter. This allows us to write the complete one-loop decay rate as a compact expression, which works accurately from thin to thick wall regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17632v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Matteini, Miha Nemev\v{s}ek, Yutaro Shoji, Lorenzo Ubaldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinning Black Hole Scattering at $\mathcal{O}(G^3 S^2)$: Casimir Terms, Radial Action and Hidden Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19005v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We resolve subtleties in calculating the post-Minksowskian dynamics of binary systems, as a spin expansion, from massive scattering amplitudes of fixed finite spin. In particular, the apparently ambiguous spin Casimir terms can be fully determined from the gradient of the spin-diagonal part of the amplitudes with respect to $S^2 = -s(s+1)\hbar^2$, using an interpolation between massive amplitudes with different spin representations. From two-loop amplitudes of spin-0 and spin-1 particles minimally coupled to gravity, we extract the spin Casimir terms in the conservative scattering angle between a spinless and a spinning black hole at $\mathcal{O}(G^3 S^2)$, finding agreement with known results in the literature. This completes an earlier study [Phys. Rev. Lett. 130 (2023), 021601] that calculated the non-Casimir terms from amplitudes. We also illustrate our methods using a model of spinning bodies in electrodynamics, finding agreement between scattering amplitude predictions and classical predictions in a root-Kerr electromagnetic background up to $\mathcal{O}(\alpha^3 S^2)$. For both gravity and electrodynamics, the finite part of the amplitude coincides with the two-body radial action in the aligned spin limit, generalizing the amplitude-action relation beyond the spinless case. Surprisingly, the two-loop amplitude displays a hidden spin-shift symmetry in the probe limit, which was previously observed at one loop. We conjecture that the symmetry holds to all orders in the coupling constant and is a consequence of integrability of Kerr orbits in the probe limit at the first few orders in spin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19005v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2025)126</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 03 (2025) 126</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dogan Akpinar, Fernando Febres Cordero, Manfred Kraus, Michael S. Ruf, Mao Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic helicity flux operators in higher dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20077v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The helicity flux operator is a fascinating quantity that characterizes the angular distribution of the helicity of radiative photons or gravitons and it has many interesting physical consequences. In this paper, we construct the electromagnetic helicity flux operators which form a non-Abelian group in general dimensions, among which the minimal helicity flux operators form the massless representation of the little group, a finite spin unitary irreducible representation of the Poincar\'e group. As in four dimensions, they generate an extended angle-dependent transformation on the Carrollian manifold. Interestingly, there is no known corresponding bulk duality transformation in general dimensions. However, we can construct a topological Chern-Simons term that evaluates the minimal helicity flux operators at $\mathcal{I}^+$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20077v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Bin Liu, Jiang Long, Xin-Hao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New aspects of gauge-gravity relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20021v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The relation between four-dimensional $SO(4)$ pure Yang-Mills theory and the gravity is discussed. The functional integral for Yang-Mills theory is rewritten in terms of the gravity metric and Riemann tensors. This relation is shown to also provide a simple way to derive the linear potential resulting from the average Wilson loop in pure Yang-Mills theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20021v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Shuvaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back to the origins of brane-antibrane inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00097v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a new framework for brane-antibrane inflation where moduli stabilisation relies purely on perturbative corrections to the effective action. This guarantees that the model does not suffer from the eta-problem. The inflationary potential has two contributions: the tension of an antibrane at the tip of a warped throat, and its Coulomb interaction with a mobile brane. This represents the first realisation of the original idea of brane-antibrane inflation, as opposed to inflection point inflation which arises when the moduli are fixed with non-perturbative effects. Moreover, we formulate the brane-antibrane dynamics as an F-term potential of a nilpotent superfield in a manifestly supersymmetric effective theory. We impose compatibility with data and consistency conditions on control over the approximations and find that slow-roll inflation can occur in a large region of the underlying parameter space. The scalar spectral index is in agreement with data and the tensor-to-scalar ratio is beyond current observational reach. Interestingly, after the end of inflation the volume mode can, but does not need to, evolve towards a late-time minimum at larger values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00097v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-13982-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 85, 315 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michele Cicoli, Christopher Hughes, Ahmed Rakin Kamal, Francesco Marino, Fernando Quevedo, Mario Ramos-Hamud, Gonzalo Villa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manifestations of $(2+1)d$ chiral anomaly in a graphene plate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22843v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inspired by the Dirac model model of graphene, we consider a $(2+1)$-dimensional fermionic system in which fermions are described by four-component spinors. These fermions are proposed to interact with an electromagnetic field originating from a four-dimensional setting, as the graphene plate is embedded in 4d Minkowski spacetime. In this framework, a chiral anomaly arises at the boundary of the plate, stemming from a non-local anomaly action that depends on both the electromagnetic and chiral gauge fields when the chiral transformation is localized. This results in boundary chiral and electric currents, and we explore potentially observable effects when external magnetic or electric fields are applied to the fermionic system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22843v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey N. Solodukhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Celestial decomposition of Wigner's particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19219v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a detailed decomposition of Wigner's particles, defined as unitary irreducible representations of the Poincar\'e group, in terms of unitary representations of its Lorentz subgroup. As pointed out before us, this decomposition only involves Lorentz representations belonging to the principal continuous series, and further underpins the connection between scattering amplitudes and conformal correlation functions discussed in the context of celestial holography. We provide very explicit formulae for the decomposition of particles of arbitrary mass and (half-)integer spin and for any spacetime dimension. We emphasise that this decomposition is unique and comes with a specific inner product on the corresponding Hilbert space. We also confirm that unitary translations mix Lorentz representations within the principal continuous series only, as required. Implications to the celestial holography program are indicated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19219v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Iacobacci, Kevin Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical edge modes in Maxwell theory from a BRST perspective, with an application to the Casimir energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04270v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, dynamical edge modes (DEM) in Maxwell theory have been constructed using a specific local boundary condition on the horizon. We discuss how to enforce this boundary condition on an infinite parallel plate in the QED vacuum by introducing Lagrange multiplier fields into the action. We carefully introduce appropriate boundary ghosts to maintain BRST invariance. Explicit correspondence of this BRST extended theory with the original DEM formulation is discussed, both directly, and through the correspondence between edge modes and Wilson lines attached to the boundary surface. We then use functional methods to calculate the Casimir energy for the first time with DEM boundary conditions imposed on two infinite parallel plates, both in generalized Coulomb and linear covariant gauge. Depending on the gauge, different fields are contributing, but, after correctly implementing the BRST symmetry, we retrieve the exact same Casimir energy as for two perfectly conducting parallel plates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04270v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2025)161</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Physics, 161 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Canfora, David Dudal, Thomas Oosthuyse, Luigi Rosa, Sebbe Stouten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle production in a light-cone gauge fixed Jordanian deformation of $AdS_5\times S^5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08411v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a string on a Jordanian deformation of the $AdS_5\times S^5$ spacetime. This model belongs to the larger class of Homogeneous Yang-Baxter deformations, which preserve classical integrability in the sense that one can construct an explicit Lax connection. To study the scattering of bosonic worldsheet excitations, we fix light-cone gauge and expand around a pointlike classical solution that reduces to the BMN vacuum in the undeformed limit. Our analysis shows that the light-cone gauge-fixed Hamiltonian, under a perturbative field expansion, includes cubic terms that give rise to non-trivial cubic processes for physical particles. We discuss this unexpected result in relation to the property of Lax integrability of the sigma-model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08411v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Borsato, Sibylle Driezen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum vorticity: a not so effective field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10344v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a comprehensive picture for the formulation of the perfect fluid in the modern effective field theory formalism at both the classical and quantum level. Due to the necessity of decomposing the hydrodynamical variables $(\rho, p, u^\mu)$ into other internal degrees of freedom, the procedure is inherently not unique. We discuss and compare the different inequivalent formulations. These theories possess a peculiarity: the presence of an infinite dimensional symmetry implying a vanishing dispersion relation $\omega = 0$ for the transverse modes. This sets the stage for UV-IR mixing in the quantum theory, which we study in the different formulations focussing on the incompressible limit. We observe that the dispersion relation gets modified by quantum effects to become $\omega \propto \mathbf{k}^2$, where the fundamental excitations can be viewed as vortex-anti-vortex pairs. The spectrum exhibits infinitely many types of degenerate quanta. The unusual sensitivity to UV quantum fluctuations renders the implementation of the defining infinite symmetry somewhat subtle. However we present a lattice regularization that preserves a deformed version of such symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10344v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Cuomo, Fanny Eustachon, Eren Firat, Brian Henning, Riccardo Rattazzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rademacher expansion of modular integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13827v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a method to evaluate integrals of non-holomorphic modular functions over the fundamental domain of the torus with modular parameter $\tau$ analytically. It proceeds in two steps: first the integral is transformed to a Lorentzian contour by the same strategy that leads to the Lorentzian inversion formula in CFT, and then we apply a two-dimensional version of the Rademacher expansion. This computes the integral in terms of an expansion sensitive to the singular behaviour of the integrand near all the Lorentzian cusps $\tau \to i \infty$, $\bar{\tau} \to x \in \mathbb{Q}$. We apply this technique to a variety of examples such as the evaluation of string one-loop partition functions, where it leads to the first analytic formula for the cosmological constants of the bosonic string and the $\mathrm{SO}(16) \times \mathrm{SO}(16)$ string.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13827v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Maria Baccianti, Jeevan Chandra, Lorenz Eberhardt, Thomas Hartman, Sebastian Mizera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S-duality in higher-derivative corrections of heterotic supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00357v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study investigates the consistency of heterotic supergravity, where the $B$-field gauge transformation becomes anomalous due to the Green-Schwarz mechanism, under T-duality transformations. We establish that preserving T-duality necessitates an infinite tower of higher-derivative couplings proportional to $e^{-2\Phi}$. For spacetimes featuring a Killing self-dual circle, these couplings remain immune to quantum corrections. Leveraging S-duality in heterotic/type I string theory, we then identify the corresponding couplings in type I theory. Notably, our analysis reveals that standard S-duality transformations do not involve higher-derivative corrections. Moreover, field redefinitions in heterotic theory do not typically correspond directly, under S-duality, to analogous field redefinitions in type I theory, and vice versa. Building on these insights, we derive the explicit form of the effective action for type I theory at the $\alpha'$ order, adhering to a scheme that omits derivatives of the dilaton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00357v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad R. Garousi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipartite Entanglement Structure of Fibered Link States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19466v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the patterns of multipartite entanglement in Chern-Simons theory with compact gauge group $G$ and level $k$ for states defined by the path integral on ``link complements'', i.e., compact manifolds whose boundaries consist of $n$ topologically linked tori. We focus on link complements which can be described topologically as fibrations over a Seifert surface. We show that the entanglement structure of such fibered link complement states is controlled by a topological invariant, the monodromy of the fibration. Thus, the entanglement structure of a Chern-Simons link state is not simply a function of the link, but also of the background manifold in which the link is embedded. In particular, we show that any link possesses an embedding into some background that leads to GHZ-like entanglement. Furthermore, we demonstrate that all fibered links with periodic monodromy have GHZ-like entanglement, i.e., a partial trace on any link component produces a separable state. These results generalize to any three dimensional topological field theory with a dual chiral rational conformal field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19466v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vijay Balasubramanian, Charlie Cummings</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite group gauge theory on graphs and gravity-like modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17301v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study gauge theory with finite group $G$ on a graph $X$ using noncommutative differential geometry and Hopf algebra methods with $G$-valued holonomies replaced by gauge fields valued in a `finite group Lie algebra' subset of the group algebra $\C G$ corresponding to the complete graph differential structure on $G$. We show that this richer theory decomposes as a product over the nontrivial irreducible representations $\rho$ with dimension $d_\rho$ of certain noncommutative $U(d_\rho)$-Yang-Mills theories, which we introduce. The Yang-Mills action recovers the Wilson action for a lattice but now with additional terms. We compute the moduli space $\CA^\times / \CG$ of regular connections modulo gauge transformations on connected graphs $X$. For $G$ Abelian, this is given as expected by phases associated to fundamental loops but with additional $\R_{&gt;0}$-valued modes on every edge resembling the metric for quantum gravity models on graphs. For nonAbelian $G$, these modes become positive-matrix valued modes. We study the quantum gauge field theory in the Abelian case in a functional integral approach, particularly for $X$ the finite chain $A_{n+1}$, the $n$-gon $\Z_n$ and the single plaquette $\Z_2\times \Z_2$. We show that, in stark contrast to usual lattice gauge theory, the Lorentzian version is well-behaved, and we identify novel boundary vs bulk effects in the case of the finite chain. We also consider gauge fields valued in the finite-group Lie algebra corresponding to a general Cayley graph differential calculus on $G$, where we study an obstruction to closure of gauge transformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17301v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahn Majid, Francisco Sim\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simple scenario for the last ACT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21030v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the simplest generalization of the chaotic inflation model $\tfrac12 {m^{2}\phi^{2}}$ with nonminimal coupling to gravity $(1+\phi) R$ provides a good match to the results of the latest data release of the Atacama Cosmology Telescope, with $r \approx10^{-2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21030v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renata Kallosh, Andrei Linde, Diederik Roest</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on the $q=2$ $R$-para-fermionic SYK model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23967v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the $q=2$ SYK model with $R$-para-particles ($R$-PSYK$_2$), analyzing its thermodynamics and spectral form factor (SFF) using random matrix theory. The Hamiltonian is quadratic, with coupling coefficients randomly drawn from the Gaussian Unitary Ensemble (GUE).The model exhibits self-averaging behavior and shows a striking transition in SFF dynamics: while the fermionic SYK$_2$ displays a ramp behavior $\mathcal{K}(t) \sim e^{C_0 t}$ with $C_0 \sim \ln N$, the $R$-para-particle cases exhibit $C_0 \sim \mathcal{O}(1)$. These findings offer new insights into quantum systems with exotic statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23967v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tingfei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards the finite quantum field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.07195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2009.07195v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we propose a novel regularization/renormalization scheme that utilizes an auxiliary Feynman parameterization. This approach is employed to align a specified loop diagram with a designated unit of the form $1=\lambda/\lambda$. Within the proposed regularization technique, we formulate the standard renormalization scheme and demonstrate conditions under which it yields symmetry preserving results. It is demonstrated that its minimal form yields renormalized diagrams that are equivalent to those of the dimensional renormalization scheme, with the exception of their counterterms. Furthermore, a novel procedure for taking the soft limit $\lambda\rightarrow 0$, where a properly defined order of computational actions provides the field theory completely finite, is presented.The qualitative and quantitative distinctions between this approach and the standard scheme are highlighted. Both schemes are elucidated in the scalar model in 3+1D for pedagogical reasons. Subsequently, the proposed schemes are applied to the Standard Model at one loop level, e.g. we calculate photon and gluon polarizations. In the final section, we offer a concise discussion on the softening of anomalies and the treatment of overlapping divergences, accompanied by illustrative examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2009.07195v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Sauli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R\'enyi entropies for one-dimensional quantum systems with mixed boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.02124v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a general method for calculating R\'enyi entropies in the ground state of a one-dimensional critical system with mixed open boundaries, for an interval starting at one of its ends. In the conformal field theory framework, this computation boils down to the evaluation of the correlation function of one twist field and two boundary condition changing operators in the cyclic orbifold. Exploiting null-vectors of the cyclic orbifold, we derive ordinary differential equations satisfied by these correlation functions. In particular, we obtain an explicit expression for the second R\'enyi entropy valid for any diagonal minimal model, but with a particular set of mixed boundary conditions. In order to compare our results with numerical data for the Ising and three-state Potts critical chains, we also identify and compute the leading finite size corrections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.02124v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benoit Estienne, Yacine Ikhlef, Andrei Rotaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flops and Hilbert schemes of space curve singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.17154v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using pagoda flop transitions between smooth projective threefolds, a relation is derived between the Euler numbers of moduli spaces of stable pairs which are scheme-theoretically supported on a fixed singular space curve and Euler numbers of Flag Hilbert schemes associated to a plane curve singularity. When the space curve singularity is locally complete intersection, one obtains a relation between the latter and Euler numbers of Hilbert schemes of the space curve singularity. It is also shown that this relation yields explicit results for a class of torus-invariant locally complete intersection singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.17154v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duiliu-Emanuel Diaconescu, Mauro Porta, Francesco Sala, Arian Vosoughinia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for cosmological constraints using gravitational wave memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18083v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The {\Lambda}CDM model has long served as a robust and predictive framework for cosmology, successfully explaining a wide range of observations, including the accelerated expansion of the Universe. However, discrepancies in cosmological parameter estimates and recent findings, such as those from DESI, hint at potential deviations from {\Lambda}CDM. Gravitational wave (GW) observations offer an independent method to probe the nature of dark energy, leveraging GWs from compact binary mergers as standard candles. In this study, we demonstrate that the integrated GW memory over cosmological distances encodes a unique imprint of the background spacetime. Unlike previous analyses, our approach captures non-linear dependencies on cosmological quantities, resulting in an enhancement of the integrated GW memory by a factor of 100 for high-redshift sources well within the sensitivity range of next-generation detectors like Cosmic Explorer and the Einstein Telescope. We find that despite the diminishing strength of individual GWs at high redshifts, their cumulative effect leads to a significant amplification, akin to the integrated Sachs-Wolfe effect, offering a potential new avenue for cosmological studies. By examining a range of dark energy models, we reveal that GW memory is potentially highly sensitive to the underlying cosmological framework, making it a promising probe of dark energy. This novel approach presents the possibility of a fresh perspective to address persistent cosmological tensions, and the nature of dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18083v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Chakraborty (IIT Bombay), Susmita Jana (IIT Bombay), S. Shankaranarayanan (IIT Bombay)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Scale SUSY from Sgoldstino Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10039v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We review a number of unimodular no-scale supergravity models with F-term SUSY breaking which support technically natural de Sitter vacua. A variant of these models develops a stage of inflection-point inflation which can be realized for subplanckian field values consistently with the observational data. For central value of the spectral index ns, the necessary tuning is of the order of 10^-6, the tensor-to-scalar ratio is tiny whereas the running of ns is around -3x10^-3. Our proposal is compatible with high-scale SUSY and the results of LHC on the Higgs boson mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10039v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Pallis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar Dark Matter Production through the Bubble Expansion Mechanism:The Role of the Lorentz factor and Non-Renormalizable Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14592v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a Bubble Expansion mechanism for the production of scalar dark matter during a first-order phase transition in the very early Universe. Seeking for a dark matter energy density in agreement with observations, we study different renormalizable and non-renormalizable interactions between the dark matter species and the field undergoing the transition, considering all possible regimes for the Lorentz boost factor associated with the motion of the bubble wall. By employing a combination of analytical and numerical techniques, we demonstrate that sufficient dark matter production is achievable even in the previously unexplored low-velocity bubble expansion regime, enlarging the parameter space and possibilities of the scenario. Notably, for the non-renormalizable interactions it is found that the produced dark matter abundances exhibit a similar qualitative behavior to the renormalizable case, even for low Lorentz boost factors. Furthermore, for a transition around the electroweak scale, the associated gravitational wave spectrum is within the reach of future detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14592v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14064-6a</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 85, 368 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. R. Cembranos, Jes\'us Luque, Javier Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of the Mixmaster Universe in a non-commutative Generalized Uncertainty Principle framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20476v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we examine the dynamical aspects of the cosmological Mixmaster model within the framework of non-commutative generalized uncertainty principle (GUP) theories. The theory is formulated classically by introducing a well-defined symplectic form that differs from the ordinary one, thereby inducing a general deformation of the Poisson brackets describing a precise class of GUP theories. In this general setting, we first investigate the behavior of the Bianchi I and Bianchi II models using Misner variables. Then, we study the Bianchi IX model in the Mixmaster approximation, which is well-known for accurately reproducing the dynamics of the point-particle Universe approaching the cosmological singularity. We derive the corresponding Belinsky-Khalatnikov-Lifshitz (BKL) map and then, by selecting a specific GUP model associated with string theory, we explicitly investigate its resulting features shaped by the non-commutative GUP scheme. Our findings reveal that the chaotic and ergodic behavior typically observed in the standard BKL map, which characterizes the point-Universe's approach to the singularity, is replaced by quasi-periodic orbits in the parameter space of the theory. This corresponds to an oscillatory behavior of the Universe's scale factors, dependent on the initial conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20476v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/03/061</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 03, 061 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Segreto, Giovanni Montani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Komar charges and Smarr formulas for black holes and boson stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08268v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The standard Komar charge is a $(d-2)$-form that can be defined in spacetimes admitting a Killing vector and which is closed when the vacuum Einstein equations are satisfied. Its integral at spatial infinity (the Komar integral) gives the conserved charge associated to the Killing vector, and, due to its on-shell closedness, the same value (expressed in terms of other physical variables) is obtained integrating over the event horizon (if any). This equality is the basis of the Smarr formula. This charge can be generalized so that it still is closed on-shell in presence of matter and its integrals give generalizations of the Smarr formula. We show how the Komar charge and other closed $(d-2)$-form charges can be used to prove non-existence theorems for gravitational solitons and boson stars. In particular, we show how one can deal with generalized symmetric fields (invariant under a combination of isometries and other global symmetries) and how the geralized symmetric ansatz permits to evade the non-existence theorems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08268v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romina Ballesteros, Tomas Ortin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing dark matter halo profiles with multi-band observations of gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14063v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we evaluate the potential of multiband gravitational wave observations from a deci-Hz space-based detector and third-generation ground-based gravitational wave detectors to constrain the properties of dark matter spikes around intermediate-mass ratio inspirals. The presence of dark matter influences the orbital evolution of the secondary compact object through dynamic friction, which leads to a phase shift in the gravitational waveform compared to the vacuum case. Our analysis shows that the proposed Indian space-based detector GWSat, operating in the deciHz frequency band, provides the most stringent constraints on the dark matter spike parameters, as IMRIs spend a significant portion of their inspiral phase within its sensitivity range. While third-generation ground-based detectors such as the Einstein Telescope and Cosmic Explorer offer additional constraints, their contribution is somewhat limited, particularly for higher-mass systems where the signal duration in their frequency bands is shorter. However, for systems with detector-frame total masses $M_z &lt; 400 \rm M_{\odot}$, Cosmic Explorer and Einstein Telescope could improve the estimation of the chirp mass, symmetric mass ratio, luminosity distance, and dark matter spike power-law index by more than $15\%$. Nonetheless, their impact on the constraint of spike density is minimal. These results highlight the crucial role of deciHz space-based detectors in probing dark matter interactions with gravitational wave sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14063v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Divya Tahelyani, Arpan Bhattacharyya, Anand S. Sengupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighing the curvature invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12242v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove several inequalities between the curvature invariants, which impose constraints on curvature singularities. Some of the inequalities hold for a family of spacetimes which include static, Friedmann--Lema\^itre--Robertson--Walker, and Bianchi type I metrics, independently of whether they are solutions of some particular field equations. In contrast, others hold for solutions of Einstein's gravitational field equation and a family of energy-momentum tensors (featuring ideal fluids, scalar fields and nonlinear electromagnetic fields), independently of the specific form of the spacetime metric. We illustrate different behaviour of the basic curvature invariants with numerous examples and discuss the consequences and limitations of the proven results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12242v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Draga\v{s}evi\'c, Ina Moslavac, Ivica Smoli\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new study of the interactions of the axion with mesons and photons using a chiral effective Lagrangian model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13615v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend the results obtained in a previous work and investigate the most interesting decay processes involving axions, photons and the lightest pseudoscalar mesons in the more general case in which the quarks (and, therefore, the mesons) may be charged under the $U(1)$ Peccei-Quinn symmetry, making use of a chiral effective Lagrangian model with $N_f=3$ light quark flavors, which also includes the flavor-singlet pseudoscalar meson and implements the $U(1)$ axial anomaly of the fundamental theory. In particular, we compute the axion mass, the electromagnetic coupling of the axion to photons, and the amplitudes and widths of the decay processes $\eta/\eta'\rightarrow \pi\pi a$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13615v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Meggiolaro, Mirko Tamburini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional Determinants for False Vacuum Decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15878v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive simple expressions to regularise functional determinants from fluctuations of fields with spin 0, 1/2, and 1. These are important for the precise dimensionful determination of false vacuum decay rates. We work in $D = 4$ Euclidean dimensions and use familiar Feynman diagrammatic techniques with a double expansion in interactions and masses, together with dimensional regularisation in momentum space. We Fourier transform to coordinate space and end up with a simple regularisation prescription in terms of single integrals over the Euclidean radius of field-dependent masses and their derivatives. Our results apply to models with an arbitrary scalar potential and with any number of scalars, fermions, gauge bosons and associated ghosts. We exemplify this approach on the Standard Model with a streamlined calculation of the renormalisation and isolation of divergences in fluctuation determinants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15878v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Baratella, Miha Nemev\v{s}ek, Yutaro Shoji, Katarina Trailovi\'c, Lorenzo Ubaldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum decoherence in the Caldeira-Leggett model by the real-time path integral on a computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20699v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose first-principle calculations of an open system based on the real-time path integral formalism treating the environment as well as the system of our interest together on a computer. The sign problem that occurs in applying Monte Carlo methods can be overcome in general by using the so-called Lefschetz thimble method, which has been developed over the past decade. Here we focus on the Caldeira-Leggett model, which is well known, in particular, as a model of quantum decoherence. In this case, the calculation simplifies drastically since the path integral becomes Gaussian for typical initial conditions. The relevant saddle point, which is unique and complex, can be determined by solving a linear equation with a huge but sparse coefficient matrix, and the integration over the Lefschetz thimble can be performed analytically. Thus we obtain, without assumptions or approximations, the reduced density matrix after a long-time evolution, tracing out a large number of harmonic oscillators in the environment. In particular, we confirm the dependence of the decoherence time on the coupling constant and the temperature that has been predicted from the master equation in a certain parameter regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20699v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Nishimura, Hiromasa Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Lorentz invariance violation found?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01830v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Lorentz invariance violation (LIV) has long been recognized as an observable low-energy signature of quantum gravity. In spite of a great effort to detect LIV effects, so far only lower bounds have been derived. The high energy photons from the gamma ray burst GRB 221009A have been detected by the LHAASO collaboration and one at ${\cal E} \simeq 251 \, \rm TeV$ by the Carpet collaboration using a partial data set. Very recently, the Carpet collaboration has completed the full data analysis, reporting further support for their previously detected photon now at ${\cal E} = 300^{+ 43}_{- 38} \, {\rm TeV}$, which manifestly clashes with conventional physics. Taking this result at face value, we derive the first evidence for LIV and we show that such a detection cannot be explained by axion-like particles (ALPs), which allow for the observation of the highest energy photons detected by LHAASO. We also outline a scenario in which ALPs and LIV naturally coexist. If confirmed by future observations our finding would represent the first positive result in quantum gravity phenomenology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01830v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Galanti, Marco Roncadelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
