<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Super Covering Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12302v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define analytic maps between super Riemann surfaces which extend the notion of branched covering maps to a supersymmetric setting. We show that these super covering maps appear naturally both in symmetric product orbifolds of superconformal field theories, as well as in the hybrid formalism for tensionless string theory on $\text{AdS}_3\times S^3\times\mathbb{T}^4$. In the former, they can be used to calculate correlators in a manifestly supersymmetric way, while in the latter they solve Ward identities of correlators with space-time supersymmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12302v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beat Nairz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$T\bar{T}$ and root-$T\bar{T}$ deformations in four-dimensional Chern-Simons theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The four-dimensional Chern-Simons (CS) theory provides a systematic procedure for realizing two-dimensional integrable field theories. It is therefore a natural question to ask whether integrable deformations of the theories can be realized in the four-dimensional CS theory. In this work, we study $T\bar{T}$ and root-$T\bar{T}$ deformations of two-dimensional integrable field theories, formulated in terms of dynamical coordinate transformations, within the framework of four-dimensional CS theory coupled to disorder defects. We illustrate our procedure in detail for the degenerate $\mathcal{E}$-model, a specific construction that captures and unifies a broad range of integrable systems, including the principal chiral model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12303v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-ichi Sakamoto, Roberto Tateo, Masahito Yamazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phases of 2d Gauge Theories and Symmetric Mass Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12305v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamics and phase structure of Abelian gauge theories in $d=1+1$ dimensions. These include $U(1)$ gauge theory coupled to a scalar and a fermion, as well as the two-flavour Schwinger model with different charges. Both theories exhibit a surprisingly rich phase diagram as masses are varied, with both $c=1$ and $c=1/2$ critical lines or points. We build up to the study of 2d chiral gauge theories, which hold particular interest because they provide a mechanism for symmetric mass generation, a phenomenon in which fermions become gapped without breaking chiral symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12305v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishi Mouland, David Tong, Bernardo Zan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trombone gaugings of five-dimensional maximal supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The maximal gauged supergravities in five spacetime dimensions with gauge groups contained in $\mathbb{R}^+ \times \textrm{E}_{6(6)}$ are described. The $\textrm{E}_{6(6)}$ factor is the duality group of ungauged maximal supergravity and $\mathbb{R}^+$ is the scaling symmetry of the five-dimensional metric, usually called the \textit{trombone} symmetry. The equations of motion and supersymmetry variations for these supergravities are given to lowest order in fermions, and the mass matrices are provided. Then, the theories with gauge groups contained in a maximal subgroup of $\mathbb{R}^+ \times \textrm{E}_{6(6)}$ are classified, and a new family of such supergravities uncovered. For a concrete theory in this class, some supersymmetric anti-de Sitter vacua are found and their mass spectra computed within the gauged supergravity. These vacua are argued to be related to superconformal phases of the M5-brane field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12391v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Varela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a long exact sequence of groups of equivalence classes of 2d $\mathcal{N}{=}(0,1)$ SQFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strongly motivated by a mathematical result by Lin and Yamashita (arXiv:2412.02298), we describe a long exact sequence formed by groups of equivalence classes of two-dimensional $\mathcal{N}{=}(0,1)$ supersymmetric quantum field theories (SQFTs) with and without $SU(2)$ symmetry. As an application, we study chiral fermions in heterotic compactifications with $SU(2)$ symmetry of level one to four dimensions, and show that each even-dimensional irreducible representation of $SU(2)$ appears even times, assuming the conjectural relation between topological modular forms and SQFTs. This implies the absence of the Witten anomaly, but contains more information than that.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12481v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuji Tachikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher genus twistor spaces and the celestial torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies novel four-dimensional integrable field theories that are deformations of self-dual Yang-Mills. They are engineered by considering holomorphic Chern-Simons and BF type theories on covers of twistor space obtained by pulling back the vector bundle $\mathcal{O}(1)^2\to\mathbb{CP}^1$ to hyperelliptic or elliptic curves. Compactifying to 4d yields an integrable theory, which in the examples I study, are determined to leading order. The form of the higher-order corrections are bootstrapped, and I argue that the index structure and coefficients of these terms are fixed by integrability. The celestial chiral algebras of these theories are shown to live on hyper-elliptic and elliptic curves, respectively. Symmetry reducing these integrable deformations to 2d yields an example of a hyperelliptic and elliptic integrable model governing a deformation of Hitchin's equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12486v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seraphim Jarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$2$-Split of Form Factors via BCFW Recursion Relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, \cite{Cao:2025hio} demonstrated the $2$-split for form factor under specific kinematic constraints. This factorization is analogous to that observed in scattering amplitudes. A key consequence of this structure is the presence of hidden zeros, where the form factors vanish on specific kinematic loci. We first establish these zeros and a new zero for the form factors of the composite operators ${\cal O} =\frac{1}{2}\Tr((\partial \phi)^2) + \Tr(\phi^3)$ and ${\cal O} = \Tr(F^2)$, and then employ an inductive proof based on the BCFW recursion relation to prove the $2$-split factorization for any number of external particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12564v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superluminal Liouville walls in 2d String Theory and space-like singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12778v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An interesting class of time dependent backgrounds in $1+1$ dimensional string theory involves worldsheet Liouville walls which move in (target space) time. When a parameter in such a background exceeds a certain critical value, the speed of the Liouville wall exceeds the speed of light, and there is no usual S-Matrix. We examine such backgrounds in the dual $c=1$ matrix model from the point of view of fluctuations of the collective field, and determine the nature of the emergent space-time perceived by these fluctuations. We show that so long as the corresponding Liouville wall remains time-like, the emergent space time is conformal to full Minkowski space with a time-like wall. However, for the cases where the Liouville wall is superluminal, the emergent space-time has a {\em space-like boundary} where the collective field couplings diverge. This appears as a space-like singularity in perturbative collective field theory. We comment on the necessity of incorporating finite $N$, as well as finite (double-scaled) coupling, effects to understand the behavior of the exact theory near this boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12778v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumit R. Das, Shaun D. Hampton, Sinong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-dualities and scale-separated AdS$_3$ in type I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform three T-dualities on previously found, classical $\mathcal{N}=1$ scale-separated AdS$_3$ solutions of massive type IIA supergravity. These solutions arose from a compactification on a toroidal $G_2$-holonomy space with smeared O2/D2 and O6/D6 sources. The T-dual backgrounds are classical $\mathcal{N}=1$ AdS$_3$ solutions of type IIB supergravity with O5/D5 and O9/D9 sources (type I) compactified on a space with $G_2$-structure and non-vanishing Ricci scalar. We generalize the original solutions in IIA in the T-dual picture and present on the type IIB side fully classical solutions with parametric control, scale separation, and integer conformal dimensions for the dual operators in the corresponding CFT. We also obtain strongly coupled solutions with the same properties. These are S-dual to parametrically controlled classical solutions of the heterotic SO(32) string theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12801v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Miao, Muthusamy Rajaguru, George Tringas, Timm Wrase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Entropy in Jackiw-Teitelboim de Sitter gravity with Timelike Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The consideration of timelike boundaries in de Sitter static patches has a broad motivation, such as the formulation of a well-defined canonical ensemble and the realization of a natural framework for static patch holography. In this work we study Jackiw-Teitelboim de Sitter gravity with symmetric timelike reflecting boundaries, which, in the presence of both cosmological and "black hole" horizons, naturally separate the spacetime into a "black hole system" and a "cosmological system". We apply the island formula to compute the entanglement entropy of conformal matter in both systems. In the "black hole system" an island appears, causing the entanglement entropy to saturate at the horizon value and preventing late-time growth. In the "cosmological system" no island appears, and the entanglement entropy can become arbitrarily large depending on the position of the boundaries, indicating a tension with unitarity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12975v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timofei Rusalev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-Resolved Spread Complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the impact of conserved charges on the dynamics of spread complexity of quantum states. Building on the notion of symmetry-resolved Krylov complexity [1], we extend the framework to general quantum states and analyze the relation between the total spread complexity and its decomposition into fixed-charge sectors. After exploring a range of analytical examples and using orthogonal polynomial approach, we identify conditions under which spread complexity exhibits equipartition across sectors. Finally, we discuss quantum speed limits that constrain the growth of complexity in the presence of conserved charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12992v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawel Caputa, Giuseppe Di Giulio, Tran Quang Loc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubbles in AdS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13036v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate loop corrections to the four-point function of identical scalar operators in a four-dimensional large $N$ conformal field theory, holographically dual to AdS with a quartic interaction. We focus on the universal part of the correlator that, at any order in $1/N$, is completely determined by tree-level data. We show how this contribution controls the part of the anomalous dimensions of double-trace operators, that exhibits a characteristic $\log \ell$ dependence at large spin $\ell$. We resum these effects to all orders in $1/N$ and show that they admit a natural effective description in AdS. Finally, by reformulating the problem in Mellin space, we demonstrate that the same contribution corresponds to consecutive unitarity cuts of bubble diagrams in the flat space limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13036v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agnese Bissi, Giulia Fardelli, Mohammad Reza Khansari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sigma model renormalisation group flows, singularities and some remarks on cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13092v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the properties of the renormalisation group (RG) flow of two-dimensional sigma models with a generic metric coupling by utilising known results for the Ricci flow. We point out that on many occasions the RG flow develops singularities, due to strong coupling behaviour, before it reaches a UV or an IR fixed point. We illustrate our analysis with several examples. We give particular emphasis to type I singularities, where the length of the curvature of the sigma model target space grows at most as $|t-T|^{-1}$ as the flow parameter $t$ approaches the singularity at $T$. For these, the geometry near the singularity is described in terms of a shrinking Ricci soliton that exhibits a cosmological constant even though the original RG flow does not.
  Assuming that the spacetime satisfies an RG flow equation, we use the Ricci solitons to introduce a cosmological constant in a string theory setting. This can allow for different cosmological constants at different regions of spacetime. In particular, we point out how the de-Sitter space is a solution of the theory. We also raise the question on whether the techniques used to prove the geometrisation conjecture can be applied to prove the homogeneity and isotropy of the universe at large scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13092v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Papadopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categorical Continuous Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define the symmetry category in 1+1d for continuous 0-form $G$-symmetry to be $\textbf{Sky}^\tau(G)$, the category of skyscraper sheaves of finite dimensional vector spaces with finite support on the group manifold of $G$, where $\tau \in H^4(BG,\mathbb{Z})$ is the anomaly. We propose that the corresponding 2+1d SymTFT is described by the Drinfeld center of $\textbf{Sky}^\tau(G)$. We show explicitly the way that $\tau$ twists the convolution tensor product of the objects of $\textbf{Sky}^\tau(G)$. As a concrete example, we present the $S$ and $T$-matrices for the simple anyons of the resulting $Z(\textbf{Sky}^\tau(G))$ category for $G = U(1)$, both for the cases without or with anomaly and discuss the topological boundary conditions as Lagrangian algebra of $Z(\textbf{Sky}^{\tau}(U(1)))$. We also present the definition of $\textbf{Sky}^\tau(G)$ and $Z(\textbf{Sky}^\tau(G))$ for the non-abelian case of $G=SU(2)$, as well as the speculated modular data. We point out that in order to have a physically relevant center and Lagrangian algebras it is necessary to generalize $\textbf{Sky}^\tau(G)$ to a larger category, which we argue to be closely related to the category of quasi-coherent sheaves on $G_\mathbb{C}$ with convolution tensor product twisted by $\tau$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13170v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Jia, Ran Luo, Jiahua Tian, Yi-Nan Wang, Yi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistics of Base Polytopes in F-theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a new statistical ensemble of toric bases for elliptic Calabi-Yaus used in F-theory models, by focusing on only the convex hull of the base, i.e., the base polytope. This physically motivated coarse-graining greatly simplifies the combinatorial complexity of the part of the 4D F-theory landscape with toric bases. We develop a Monte Carlo approach that randomly samples the base polytopes within fixed boxes, with proper statistical weights. We first apply the algorithm to the set of 2d base polytopes, generating an enlarged set of toric 2d bases that include certain types of codimension-two (4,6) points, and we validate our approach against exact numbers. We then explore the set of 3d base polytopes which fit in a set of ``maximal'' 3d boxes, and estimate the total number of inequivalent 3d base polytopes to be $\sim 10^{85}$--$10^{90}$. We provide statistical data such as the distribution of non-Higgsable gauge groups on these bases. Amusingly, a similar method can also be applied to generate reflexive polytopes in various dimensions. In both the reflexive and base polytope cases, the number of relevant polytopes obeys a Gaussian distribution as a function of the number of vertices, which can be understood in terms of other results on random polytopes in the math literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13252v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Washington Taylor, Yi-Nan Wang, Yihang Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent structures in open EFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Open effective field theories (EFTs) provide a systematic framework for describing systems coupled to an environment, where dissipation, noise, and modified conservation laws naturally arise. Working within the Schwinger-Keldysh formalism, we examine open extensions of well-studied theories describing a spontaneous symmetry breaking phase in the higher-form sense: the superfluid, Maxwell theory, and Einstein's gravity. We demonstrate that to leading order breaking advanced symmetries while preserving the physical ones leads to (i) deformed conservation laws that hold at the level of expectation values for global symmetries and (ii) deformed noise constraints in gauge or gravitational theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13284v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Perseas Christodoulidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum spread complexity as a probe of NSI, $CP$ Violation, and mass ordering in neutrino oscillations in matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09854v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum spread complexity characterizes how a quantum state evolves and becomes distributed over the Hilbert space under unitary dynamics. In this work, we employ a cost function as a quantitative measure of spread complexity. We investigate this cost function within the framework of three-flavor neutrino oscillations in vacuum and matter, incorporating the $CP$-violation phase and Non-Standard Interaction (NSI) effects, under both normal and inverted mass ordering scenarios. The cost function is evaluated for each scenario and analyzed with the corresponding neutrino transition probabilities for both initial muon neutrino and muon antineutrino flavor states. The results are presented using the energy where the first oscillation is maximum and baseline lengths of ongoing long-baseline accelerator neutrino experiments, including T2K and NOvA, as well as upcoming experiments such as DUNE and P2O. Our findings indicate that the difference in the cost function between normal and inverted mass orderings during neutrino propagation in matter is sensitive to these experiments, with the appropriate choice of NSI parameters and the best-fit $CP$-violation phase values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09854v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Kumar Jha, Govind Krishna G, Anandbhai Pravinbhai Prajapati, Subhashish Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of test particles, QPOs and thermodynamics of charged Euler-Heisenberg AdS black holes with a cloud of strings and dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12264v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the geodesic motion of test particles around a charged Euler-Heisenberg Anti-de Sitter black hole (CEH-AdS-BH) with a cloud of strings (CoS) and surrounded by perfect fluid dark matter (PFDM). Our analysis examines how the interplay between Euler-Heisenberg nonlinear electrodynamic corrections, string cloud, and PFDM distributions modifies fundamental BH properties. We study dynamics of both massless photons and massive neutral test particles, deriving the effective potentials and trajectory equations that govern particle motion in this exotic spacetime. The photon sphere analysis shows systematic increases in shadow radii with string cloud parameter variations, while innermost stable circular orbit (ISCO) calculations demonstrate competing effects between string-induced gravitational weakening and electromagnetic charge contributions. We examine scalar and electromagnetic field perturbations using the Klein-Gordon and Maxwell equations, establishing the perturbative potentials that characterize wave propagation in the modified background. The scalar perturbative potential exhibits characteristic barrier structures influenced by all exotic matter components, while electromagnetic perturbations show fundamental differences due to their vector nature. Our thermodynamic investigation extends the conventional framework by incorporating additional intensive variables corresponding to cosmic string and perfect fluid dark matter contributions. The specific heat capacity analysis reveals divergence points that demarcate thermodynamically stable and unstable regions, while the Gibbs free energy exhibits modified profiles that extend Anti-de Sitter black hole thermodynamics into new parameter regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12264v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faizuddin Ahmed, Ahmad Al-Badawi, \.Izzet Sakall{\i}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical symmetry breaking described by cubic nonlinear Klein-Gordon equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12272v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dynamical symmetry breaking associated with the existence and non-existence of breather solutions is studied. Here, nonlinear hyperbolic evolution equations are calculated using a high-precision numerical scheme. %%% First, for clarifying the dynamical symmetry breaking, it is necessary to use a sufficiently high-precision scheme in the time-dependent framework. Second, the error of numerical calculations is generally more easily accumulated for calculating hyperbolic equations rather than parabolic equations. Third, numerical calculations become easily unstable for nonlinear cases. Our strategy for the high-precision and stable scheme is to implement the implicit Runge-Kutta method for time, and the Fourier spectral decomposition for space. %%% In this paper, focusing on the breather solutions, the relationship between the velocity, mass, and the amplitude of the perturbation is clarified. As a result, the conditions for transitioning from one state to another are clarified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12272v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasuhiro Takei, Yoritaka Iwata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-Form Anomalies on Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Higher-form symmetry in a tensor product Hilbert space is always emergent: the symmetry generators become genuinely topological only when the Gauss law is energetically enforced at low energies. In this paper, we present a general method for defining the 't Hooft anomaly of higher-form symmetries in lattice models built on a tensor product Hilbert space. In (2+1)D, for given Gauss law operators realized by finite-depth circuits that generate a finite 1-form $G$ symmetry, we construct an index representing a cohomology class in $H^4(B^2G, U(1))$, which characterizes the corresponding 't Hooft anomaly. This construction generalizes the Else-Nayak characterization of 0-form symmetry anomalies. More broadly, under the assumption of a specified formulation of the $p$-form $G$ symmetry action and Hilbert space structure in arbitrary $d$ spatial dimensions, we show how to characterize the 't Hooft anomaly of the symmetry action by an index valued in $H^{d+2}(B^{p+1}G, U(1))$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12304v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yitao Feng, Ryohei Kobayashi, Yu-An Chen, Shinsei Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the fate of spacetime singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12314v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I investigate spacetime singularities from the point of view of the wavefunction of the universe. In order to extend the classical notion of geodesic incompleteness one has to include the proper time of an observer as a degree of freedom in the Wheeler DeWitt equation. This leads to a Schr\"odinger equation along the observer worldline. Near the singularity, as in the classical BLK treatment, I ignore spatial gradients and effectively describe the spacetime around the worldline in the mini-superspace approximation. The problem proves identical to a spherically symmetric scattering of a quantum particle off a central potential and singularity avoidance is tantamount to the unitary evolution of this system. Standard types of matter (dust, radiation) correspond to regular potentials and thus lead to a bounce. The most singular component, spatial anisotropy, is associated to a conserved charge and yields a negative inverse-square potential-like standard angular momentum, but with opposite sign. This potential is critical, in that the unitarity of the evolution depends on the actual numerical factor in front of it, i.e., on the anisotropy charge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12314v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Piazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous Kolmogorov-Arnold Geometry in Shallow MLPs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12326v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Kolmogorov-Arnold (KA) representation theorem constructs universal, but highly non-smooth inner functions (the first layer map) in a single (non-linear) hidden layer neural network. Such universal functions have a distinctive local geometry, a "texture," which can be characterized by the inner function's Jacobian $J({\mathbf{x}})$, as $\mathbf{x}$ varies over the data. It is natural to ask if this distinctive KA geometry emerges through conventional neural network optimization. We find that indeed KA geometry often is produced when training vanilla single hidden layer neural networks. We quantify KA geometry through the statistical properties of the exterior powers of $J(\mathbf{x})$: number of zero rows and various observables for the minor statistics of $J(\mathbf{x})$, which measure the scale and axis alignment of $J(\mathbf{x})$. This leads to a rough understanding for where KA geometry occurs in the space of function complexity and model hyperparameters. The motivation is first to understand how neural networks organically learn to prepare input data for later downstream processing and, second, to learn enough about the emergence of KA geometry to accelerate learning through a timely intervention in network hyperparameters. This research is the "flip side" of KA-Networks (KANs). We do not engineer KA into the neural network, but rather watch KA emerge in shallow MLPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12326v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Freedman, Michael Mulligan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lowering the Horizon on Dark Energy: A Late-Time Response to Early Solutions for the Hubble Tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12331v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a model-independent null test of the late-time cosmological response to a reduced sound horizon, as typically required by early-universe solutions to the Hubble tension. In this approach, we phenomenologically impose a shorter sound horizon without modeling early-universe physics to isolate its impact on late-time dark energy inference. Using baryon acoustic oscillations (BAO), supernovae (SN), big bang nucleosynthesis (BBN), and local $H_0$ data, while explicitly avoiding CMB anisotropies, we examine how this calibration shift propagates into constraints on the dark energy equation of state. We find that lowering $r_d$ systematically drives the $w_0$-$w_a$ posterior toward less dynamical, quintessence-like behavior, bringing it closer to $\Lambda$CDM. This result underscores that some of the apparent evidence for evolving or phantom-like dark energy may reflect early-universe assumptions rather than genuine late-time dynamics. More broadly, our analysis highlights the importance of carefully disentangling calibration effects from physical evolution in interpreting forthcoming results from DESI and future surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12331v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tal Adi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distorted black ring with rotation on the two-sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12332v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct a stationary black ring spacetime with rotation only along the $S^2$ direction that is free of conical singularities. We use a solution-generating technique to add external gravitational fields and show these can be used to remove conical singularities from an asymptotically flat black ring with a rotating $S^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12332v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matin Tavayef, Shohreh Abdolrahimi, Ivan Booth, Hari Kunduri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Mass Generation in QED: Miransky scaling and Schr\"odinger-like infinite well and barrier potentials supporting a bound state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12366v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we revisit the Schwinger-Dyson equation for the electron propagator in QED in three and four space-time dimensions. Our analysis addresses the non-perturbative phenomenon of dynamical chiral symmetry breaking, which requires a critical value of the coupling for the dynamical generation of electron masses, encoded in the infrared behavior of the corresponding Green function. With a minimalistic truncation of the infinite tower of equations and adopting standard assumptions, the resulting gap equation is linearized and transformed into a Schr\"odinger-like equation with an auxiliary potential barrier (or well) subjected to boundary conditions for both high and low momenta. The dynamical mass is then associated with the zero mode of the corresponding Schr\"odinger-like operator and follows the Miransky scaling law, as expected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12366v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan D. Garc\'ia-Mu\~noz, A. Alfaro, L. X. Guti\'errez-Guerrero, A. Raya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new approach to (3+1)-dimensional TQFTs via topological modular forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12402v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a construction toward a new type of TQFTs at the crossroads of low-dimensional topology, algebraic geometry, physics, and homotopy theory. It assigns TMF-modules to closed 3-manifolds and maps of TMF-modules to 4-dimensional cobordisms. This is a mathematical proposal for one of the simplest examples in a family of ${\pi}_*({\rm TMF})$-valued invariants of 4-manifolds which are expected to arise from 6-dimensional superconformal field theories. As part of the construction, we define TMF-modules associated with symmetric bilinear forms, using (spectral) derived algebraic geometry. The invariant of unimodular bilinear forms takes values in ${\pi}_*({\rm TMF})$, conjecturally generalizing the theta function of a lattice. We discuss gluing properties of the invariants. We also demonstrate some interesting physics applications of the TMF-modules such as distinguishing phases of quantum field theories in various dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12402v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Gukov, Vyacheslav Krushkal, Lennart Meier, Du Pei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the non-zero Love numbers of magnetic black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12418v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Black holes are believed to possess vanishing Love numbers, which implies that they do not deform in the presence of external tides. This fact has been verified in a number of scenarios, that involve tides of bosonic fields of various natures (e.g. scalar, electromagnetic and gravitational), and has triggered active research in trying to identify the underlying reason. Surprisingly, two counterexamples have been found recently. The first, concerns charged-field tides on electrically-charged black holes. In that case, however, the response cannot be disentangled from dissipative effects, and might thus be argued to not consist of a truly conservative deformation. The second concerns fermionic tides on neutral holes. While these yield a purely conservative response, they lack a classical interpretation, which is the physical regime where black hole deformability is understood. Here, we consider magnetic Reissner-Nordstrom black holes and show that electrically-charged, scalar-field tides induce non-vanishing tidal Love numbers. We prove that this is a purely non-dissipative effect, in contrast to the cases of rotating or electrically-charged black holes, and hence consists of a genuine deformation. In addition, the magnetic charge resolves common ambiguities in defining Love numbers, so our result does not rely on any regularisation scheme. This constitutes a clear realisation of how new physics can influence black hole tidal deformability, and offers new perspectives on the study of black hole Love numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12418v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Pere\~niguez, Edgars Karnickis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regular Black Holes from Proper-Time flow in Quantum Gravity and their Quasinormal modes, Shadow and Hawking radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12469v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive a class of regular black holes from the proper-time renormalization group approach to asymptotically safe gravity. A central challenge is the robustness of physical predictions to the regularization scheme. We address this by computing key observables for our quantum-corrected black holes, which are non-singular and asymptotically Schwarzschild. We calculate the quasinormal mode spectrum, finding significant deviations from the classical case. The Hawking radiation spectrum is strongly suppressed, implying a slower evaporation rate and relaxed constraints on primordial black holes as dark matter. Shadows and ISCO radii remain consistent with observations. Our results demonstrate that the singularity resolution and its primary observational implications are robust physical outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12469v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alfio Bonanno, Roman A. Konoplya, Giovanni Oglialoro, Andrea Spina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Lema\^itre time for rotating and charged black holes and its near-horizon properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12485v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the behavior of the analogue of the Lemaitre time when a particle approaches the horizon of a rotating black hole. For the Kerr metric, the aforementioned time coincides with the Doran or Natario time but we consider a more general class of metrics. We scrutiny relationship between (i) its finiteness or divergence, (ii) the forward-in-time condition, (iii) the sign of a generalized momentum/energy, (iv) the validity of the principle of kinematic censorship. The latter notion means impossibility to release in any event an energy which is literally infinite. As a consequence, we obtain a new explanation, why collisions of two particles inside the horizon do not lead to infinite energy in their center of mass frame. The same results are also obtained for the Reissner-Nordstr\"om metric</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12485v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Toporensky, O. B. Zaslavskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the (Im)possibility of Electrically Charged Planck Relics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12520v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I revisit whether black-hole remnants, from sub-Planckian compact objects to Planck relics and up to (super)massive black holes, can preserve Standard-Model (SM) electric charge. Two exterior-field mechanisms -- Coulomb-focused capture from ambient media and QED Schwinger pair production -- robustly neutralize such objects across cosmic history. I first derive the general capture rate including both Coulomb and gravitational focusing, and sum the stepwise discharge time in closed form via the trigamma function, exhibiting transparent Coulomb- and gravity-dominated limits. I then integrate the Schwinger rate over the near-horizon region to obtain an explicit $\dot Q(Q)$ law: discharge proceeds until the horizon field falls below $E_{\rm crit}$, leaving a residual charge $Q_{\rm stop}^{(e)}\!\propto\! r_h^2$ that is $\ll e$ for Planck radii. Mapping the mass dependence from sub-Planckian to astrophysical scales, I also analyze dark-sector charges with heavy carriers (including kinetic mixing and massive mediators). In a conservative ``no-Schwinger'' limit where vacuum pair creation is absent, cumulative ambient exposures alone force discharge of any integer SM charge. Three possible loopholes remain. (i) A fine-tuned SM corner in which the relic sits arbitrarily close to Reissner-Nordstr\"om extremality so greybody factors suppress charged absorption, while Schwinger pair creation is absent due to Planck-scale physics. (ii) Charge relocated to a hidden $U(1)_D$ with no light opposite carriers, e.g. if the lightest state is very heavy and/or kinetic mixing with $U(1)_{\rm EM}$ is vanishingly small. (iii) Discrete or topological charges rather than ordinary SM electric charge. Outside these cases, the conclusion is robust: within SM electromagnetism, charged black-hole relics neutralize efficiently and cannot retain charge over cosmological times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12520v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Profumo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-horizon polarized images of rotating hairy Horndeski black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, Hou et al. [Astrophys. J. Lett. 988, L51 (2025)] revealed that the EVPA (Electric Vector Position Angle) of polarization vectors in the near-horizon images is governed solely by spacetime geometry and is irrespective of the plasma flows. Here, we generalize the study to the scenario of a rotating hair black hole within Horndeski gravity and probe the effects of the hairy parameter on the EVPA. For a fixed inclination, the hairy parameter enhances the observed EVPA in the slowly rotating case, but decreases it in the rapidly rotating case. For a fixed black hole spin, the influence of the hairy parameter on the observed EVPA under different observer inclinations is further modulated by the azimuthal angle of the observed polarization vector. The hairy parameter's impact is more distinct in the low inclination case as the azimuthal angle lies within a specific range, but is almost independent of the observer inclination as the azimuthal angle is beyond this specific range. Furthermore, the dependence of the hairy parameter's impact on the EVPA is stronger with respect to the black hole spin than to the inclination angle. These results could help to further understand the near-horizon polarized images and Horndeski gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12526v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chekiang Chen, Qiyuan Pan, Jiliang Jing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strangeness production in $p$Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}} = 5.02$ TeV in the PACIAE model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a study of the single- and multi-strange particle productions in $p$Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}} = 5.02$ TeV using the PACIAE 4.0 model. The effects of the color reconnection (CR), rope hadronization (RH) as well as the partonic and hadronic rescatterings (PRS and HRS) on their productions are investigated, respectively. There are two kinds of CR considered: the multiparton interactions-based CR (MPI-CR) and the quantum chromodynamics-based CR (QCD-CR). The four mechanisms studied have little effect on kaon production. However, the QCD-CR scheme incorporating the junction topology gives an enhanced baryon production, but it is still not enough to describe the integrated yields of strange baryons. The combination of QCD-CR and RH scheme together with the flavor ropes (FR) and the string shoving (SS), i.e., QCD-CR+FR+SS, provides a good description of the production of strange baryons. PRS has a weak effect but HRS exerts a promoting effect on the production of multi-strange baryons ($\Xi$ and $\Omega$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12575v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Lei, Qiang Wang, An-Ke Lei, Zhi-Lei She, Jia-Xin Gao, Dai-Mei Zhou, Yu-Liang Yan, Hua Zheng, Wen-Chao Zhang, Ben-Hao Sa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nambu Non-equilibrium Thermodynamics III: Application to specific phenomena</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12641v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We apply Nambu non-equilibrium thermodynamics (NNET)-a dynamics with multiple Hamiltonians coupled to entropy-induced dissipation-to paradigmatic far-from-equilibrium systems. Concretely, we construct NNET realizations for the Belousov-Zhabotinsky (BZ) reaction (oscillatory), the Hindmarsh-Rose neuron model (spiking), and the Lorenz and Chen systems (chaotic), and analyze their dynamical and thermodynamic signatures. Across all cases the velocity field cleanly decomposes into a reversible Nambu part and an irreversible entropygradient part, anchored by a model-independent quasi-conserved quantity. This construction reproduces cycles, spikes, and strange-attractor behavior and clarifies transitions among steady, periodic, and chaotic regimes via cross-model diagnostics. These results demonstrate that NNET provides a unified, quantitatively consistent framework for oscillatory, spiking, and chaotic non-equilibrium systems, offering a systematic description beyond the scope of linear-response theories such as Onsager's relations or GENERIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12641v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>So Katagiri, Yoshiki Matsuoka, Akio Sugamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nichols algebras, tensor categories and Kazhdan-Lusztig correspondences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12909v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There is a very general picture emerging that conjecturally describes what happens to the representation theory of a vertex algebra $\mathcal{V}$ if we pass to the kernel $\mathcal{W}$ of a set of screening operators. Namely, the screening operators generate a Nichols algebra $H$ inside $\mathrm{Rep}(\mathcal{V})$ and in many cases $\mathrm{Rep}(\mathcal{W})$ coincides with the relative Drinfeld center of $\mathrm{Rep}(H)$. This vastly generalizes the construction of a quantum group as the Drinfeld double of a Nichols algebra over the Cartan part. In this example, the conjectural category equivalence has been studied since around $20$ years as logarithmic Kazhdan Lusztig correspondence.
  The present survey was part of my habilitation thesis about my work in this area. I want to make it available as an introductory text, intended for readers from a pure algebra background as well as from a physics background. I motivate and explain gently and informally the different topics involved (quantum groups, Nichols algebras, vertex algebras, braided tensor categories) with a distinct categorical point of view, to the point that I can explain my general expectation. Then I explain some previous results and explain the main techniques in my recent proof of the conjectured category equivalence in case $\mathcal{V}$ is a free field theory and under technical assumptions on the analysis side.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12909v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon D. Lentner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Velocity Domination in quantized polarized Gowdy Cosmologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13162v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Asymptotic velocity domination (AVD) posits that when back-propagated to the Big Bang generic cosmological spacetimes solve a drastically simplified version of the Einstein field equations, where all dynamical spatial gradients are absent (similar as in the Belinski-Khalatnikov-Lifshitz scenario). Conversely, a solution can in principle be reconstructed from its behavior near the Big Bang. This property has been rigorously proven for the Gowdy class of cosmologies, both polarized and unpolarized. Here we establish for the polarized case a quantum version of the AVD property formulated in terms of two-point functions of (the integrands of) Dirac observables: these correlators approach their much simpler velocity dominated counterparts when the time support is back-propagated to the Big Bang. Conversely, the full correlators can be expressed as a uniformly convergent series in averaged spatial gradients of the velocity dominated ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13162v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Niedermaier, Mahdi Sedighi Jafari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smallness of neutrino masses and leptogenesis in 331 composite Higgs model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13245v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider 331 composite Higgs model (CHM3) in which the Lagrangian of the strongly coupled sector is invariant with respect to global SU(3)_C \times SU(3)\times U(1)_6 symmetry that can originate from SU(6) subgroup of E_6 and contains the gauge group of the standard model (SM) as a subgroup. The breakdown of the approximate SU(3)\times U(1)_6 symmetry down to SU(2)_W\times U(1)_Y subgroup around the scale f\sim 10 TeV results in a set of pseudo--Nambu--Goldstone bosons (pNGBs) that, in particular, involves Higgs doublet. The generation of the masses of the SM fermions in the CHM3 is discussed. We argue that an approximate discrete Z_2 symmetry may give rise to tiny masses of the left-handed neutrinos and several composite fermions with masses 1-2 TeV. The lepton and baryon asymmetries can be generated within the CHM3 via the out--of equilibrium decays of extra Majorana particle into the Higgs doublet and these composite fermions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13245v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Nevzorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Minimal and Non-Minimal Quintessence Models to 2025 DESI Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13302v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we examine the 2025 DESI analysis of dark energy, which suggests that dark energy is evolving in time with an increasing equation of state $w$. We explore a wide range of quintessence models, described by a potential function $V(\varphi)$, including: quadratic potentials, quartic hilltops, double wells, cosine functions, Gaussians, inverse powers. We find that while some provide improvement in fitting to the data, compared to a cosmological constant, the improvement is only modest. We then consider non-minimally coupled scalars which can help fit the data by providing an effective equation of state that temporarily obeys $w&lt;-1$ and then relaxes to $w&gt;-1$. Since the scalar is very light, this leads to a fifth force and to time evolution in the effective gravitational strength, which are both tightly constrained by tests of gravity. For a very narrow range of carefully selected non-minimal couplings we are able to evade these bounds, but not for generic values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13302v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Husam Adam, Mark P. Hertzberg, Daniel Jim\'enez-Aguilar, Iman Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Configurational Temperature as a Diagnostic for Complex Langevin Dynamics in the 3D XY Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13314v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the applicability of complex Langevin dynamics to the three-dimensional XY model at finite chemical potential. To assess correctness, we introduce a new diagnostic based on the configurational temperature (or configurational coupling) estimator, recently proposed as a thermodynamic consistency check. We compare this criterion with the established Nagata-Nishimura-Shimasaki drift-decay test across a range of couplings and chemical potentials. Our results show that complex Langevin dynamics yields reliable results in the ordered phase (large $\beta$), but fails in the disordered phase (small $\beta$), even when the sign problem is mild. The configurational estimator provides a clear and physics-driven reliability test that complements drift-based diagnostics. These findings establish the estimator as a practical tool for identifying incorrect convergence, and highlight its potential for broader applications in lattice field theories with complex actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13314v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anosh Joseph, Arpith Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrable Wilson loops in ABJM: a $Y$-system computation of the cusp anomalous dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01924v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the integrability properties of Wilson loops in the ${\cal N}=6$ three-dimensional Chern-Simons-matter (ABJM) theory. We begin with the construction of an open spin chain that describes the anomalous dimensions of operators inserted along the contour of a 1/2 BPS Wilson loop. Moreover, we compute the all-loop reflection matrices that govern the interaction of spin-chain excitations with the boundary, including their dressing factors, and we check them against weak- and strong-coupling results. Furthermore, we propose a $Y$-system of equations for the cusped Wilson line of ABJM, and we use it to reproduce the one-loop cusp anomalous dimension of ABJM from a leading-order finite-size correction. Finally, we write a set of BTBA equations consistent with the $Y$-system proposal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01924v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP06(2023)179</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Diego H. Correa, Victor I. Giraldo-Rivera, Mart\'in Lagares</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry Operators and Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We argue that topological operators for continuous symmetries written in terms of currents need regularization, which effectively gives them a small but finite width. The regulated operator is a finite tension object which fluctuates. In the zero-width limit these fluctuations freeze, recovering the properties of a topological operator. When gravity is turned on, the zero-width limit becomes ill-defined, thereby prohibiting the existence of topological operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08858v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ibrahima Bah, Patrick Jefferson, Konstantinos Roumpedakis, Thomas Waddleton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation hypergraph: a new representation of a quantum marginal independence pattern</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18018v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We continue the study of the quantum marginal independence problem, namely the question of which faces of the subadditivity cone are achievable by quantum states. We introduce a new representation of the patterns of marginal independence (PMIs, corresponding to faces of the subadditivity cone) based on certain correlation hypergraphs, and demonstrate that this representation provides a more efficient description of a PMI, and consequently of the set of PMIs which are compatible with strong subadditivity. We then show that these correlation hypergraphs generalize to arbitrary quantum systems the well known relation between positivity of mutual information and connectivity of entanglement wedges in holography, and further use this representation to derive new results about the combinatorial structure of collections of simultaneously decorrelated subsystems specifying SSA-compatible PMIs. In the context of holography, we apply these techniques to derive a necessary condition for the realizability of entropy vectors by simple tree graph models, which were conjectured in arXiv:2204.00075 to provide the building blocks of the holographic entropy cone. Since this necessary condition is formulated in terms of chordality of a certain graph, it can be tested efficiently.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18018v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Veronika E. Hubeny, Massimiliano Rota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scale separation from O-planes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15436v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Orientifold planes play a crucial role in flux compactifications of string theory, and we demonstrate their deep connection to achieving scale-separated solutions. Specifically, we show that when an orientifold plane contributes at leading order to the non-zero value of the scalar potential, then either the weak coupling limit or the large volume limit implies scale separation, meaning that the Kaluza-Klein tower mass decouples from the inverse length scale of the lower-dimensional theory. Notably, in the supergravity limit such solutions are inherently scale-separated. This result is independent of the spacetime dimension and the dimensionality of the O$p$-plane as long as $p&lt;7$. Similarly, we show, extending previous results, that parametric scale separation is not possible for isotropic compactifications with a leading curvature term that generically arise in the AdS/CFT context. We classify all possible flux compactification setups in both type IIA and type IIB string theory for O$p$-planes with $2\leq p\leq 6$ and present their universal features. While the parametrically controlled scale-separated solutions are all AdS, we also find setups that allow for dS vacua. We prove that flux quantization prevents these dS vacua in isotropic compactifications from arising in a regime of parametric control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15436v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Tringas, Timm Wrase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the relaxation of constraints in gauge theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02468v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, there were works claiming that path integral quantisation of gauge theories necessarily requires relaxation of Lagrangian constraints. As has also been noted in the literature, it is of course wrong since there perfectly exist gauge field quantisations respecting the constraints, and at the same time the very idea of changing the classical theory in this way has many times appeared in other works. On the other hand, what was done in the path integral approach is fixing a gauge in terms of zero-momentum variables. We would like to show that this relaxation is what normally happens when one fixes such a gauge at the level of action principle in a Lagrangian theory. Moreover, there is an interesting analogy to be drawn. Namely, one of the ways to quantise a gauge theory is to build an extended Hamiltonian and then add new conditions by hand such as to make it a second class system. The constraints' relaxation occurs when one does the same at the level of the total Hamiltonian, i.e. a second class system with the primary constraints only.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02468v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Golovnev, Kirill Russkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular chaos, operator algebras, and the Berry phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04682v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modular Berry transport associates a geometric phase to a zero mode ambiguity in a family of modular operators. In holographic settings, this phase was shown to encode nontrivial information about the emergent spacetime geometry. We reformulate modular Berry transport for arbitrary von Neumann algebras, including giving a precise definition of the zero mode projection in terms of a conditional expectation. For a certain class of state perturbations, we demonstrate that the modular Berry phase gives rise to an emergent symplectic form in the large $N$ limit, extending related results in the context of subregion/subalgebra duality. We also show that the vanishing of the Berry curvature for modular scrambling modes signals the emergence of a local Poincar\'e algebra, which plays a key role in the quantum ergodic hierarchy. These results provide an intriguing relation between geometric phases, modular chaos and the local structure of spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04682v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan de Boer, Bahman Najian, Jeremy van der Heijden, Claire Zukowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Root-$T\overline{T}$ deformed CFT partition functions at large central charge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12093v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the partition function of 2d CFT under root-$T\bar{T}$ deformation. We demonstrate that the deformed partition function satisfies a flow equation. At large central charge sector, the deformed partition function reduces to a redefinition of the modular parameters, which preserves modular invariance under the deformed parameters. We then derive a Cardy-like formula for the asymptotic density of states using modular bootstrap trick. In the context of AdS/CFT, it was proposed the root-$T\bar{T}$ deformed CFT corresponds to the AdS$_3$ with certain deformed boundary condition. We show the deformed BTZ black hole is a quotient of hyperbolic space. In terms of Chern-Simons formulation, we compute the root-$T\bar{T}$ deformed BTZ black hole entropy and find that it obeys a Cardy-like formula, which is consistent with the modular bootstrap result. Furthermore, employing the Wilson spool technique, we compute the one-loop partition functions for the root-$T\bar{T}$ deformed AdS$_3$ geometry. Our results reveal an exact match between one-loop gravitational partition function and the large $c$ expansion of root-$T\bar{T}$ deformed CFT partition function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12093v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A basis of the gradient flow exact renormalization group for gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23567v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The gradient flow exact renormalization group (GFERG) is a variant of the exact renormalization group (ERG) for gauge theory that is aimed at preserve gauge invariance as manifestly as possible. It achieves this goal by utilizing the Yang--Mills gradient flow or diffusion for the block-spin process. In this paper, we formulate GFERG by the Reuter equation in which the block spinning is done by Gaussian integration. This formulation provides a simple understanding of various points of GFERG, unresolved thus far. First, there exists a unique ordering of functional derivatives in the GFERG equation that remove ambiguity of contact terms. Second, perturbation theory of GFERG suffers from unconventional ultraviolet (UV) divergences if no gauge fixing is introduced. This explains the origin of some UV divergences we have encountered in perturbative solutions to GFERG. Third, the modified correlation functions calculated with the Wilson action in GFERG coincide with the correlation functions of diffused or flowed fields calculated with the bare action. This shows the existence of a Wilson action that reproduces precisely the physical quantities computed by the gradient flow formalism (up to contact terms). We obtain a definite ERG interpretation of the gradient flow. The formulation given in this paper provides a basis for further perturbative/nonperturbative computations in GFERG, preserving gauge invariance maximally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23567v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidenori Sonoda, Hiroshi Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gluon scattering amplitudes with instantons and minimal surfaces with topology change</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10865v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the instanton effect on the gluon scattering amplitudes at strong coupling and large $N$ for the ${\cal N}=4$ supersymmetric Yang-Mills theory. According to Alday and Maldacena, the gluon scattering amplitude corresponds holographically to the area of a worldsheet minimal surface in the T-dual AdS${}_5$ geometry. The Yang-Mills instanton introduces an instanton D-brane in the geometry, with which a particular boundary condition for the minimal surface is imposed. We show that the minimal surface undergoes a topology change depending on the size and the gluon momenta, and that the instanton amplitude exhibits a characteristic dependence on gluon momenta. More specifically, we find that when the fixed instanton size modulus $\rho$ is larger than ${\cal O}(\sqrt{\lambda}/E)$ where $\lambda$ is the 't Hooft coupling and $E$ is the typical momentum of the scattering gluon, due to the topology change of the worldsheet minimal surface, the instanton amplitude is exponentially enhanced as $\exp(\rho E)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10865v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koji Hashimoto, Koichi Kyo, Masaki Murata, Gakuto Ogiwara, Norihiro Tanahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed neural network solves minimal surfaces in curved spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10866v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a flexible framework based on physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) for solving boundary value problems involving minimal surfaces in curved spacetimes, with a particular emphasis on singularities and moving boundaries. By encoding the underlying physical laws into the loss function and designing network architectures that incorporate the singular behavior and dynamic boundaries, our approach enables robust and accurate solutions to both ordinary and partial differential equations with complex boundary conditions. We demonstrate the versatility of this framework through applications to minimal surface problems in anti-de Sitter (AdS) spacetime, including examples relevant to the AdS/CFT correspondence (e.g. Wilson loops and gluon scattering amplitudes) popularly used in the context of string theory in theoretical physics. Our methods efficiently handle singularities at boundaries, and also support both "soft" (loss-based) and "hard" (formulation-based) imposition of boundary conditions, including cases where the position of a boundary is promoted to a trainable parameter. The techniques developed here are not limited to high-energy theoretical physics but are broadly applicable to boundary value problems encountered in mathematics, engineering, and the natural sciences, wherever singularities and moving boundaries play a critical role.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10866v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koji Hashimoto, Koichi Kyo, Masaki Murata, Gakuto Ogiwara, Norihiro Tanahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs Phases and Boundary Criticality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17001v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by recent work connecting Higgs phases to symmetry protected topological (SPT) phases, we investigate the interplay of gauge redundancy and global symmetry in lattice gauge theories with Higgs fields in the presence of a boundary. The core conceptual point is that a global symmetry associated to a Higgs field, which is pure-gauge in a closed system, acts physically at the boundary under boundary conditions which allow electric flux to escape the system. We demonstrate in both Abelian and non-Abelian models that this symmetry is spontaneously broken in the Higgs regime, implying the presence of gapless edge modes. Starting with the U(1) Abelian Higgs model in 4D, we demonstrate a boundary phase transition in the 3D XY universality class separating the bulk Higgs and confining regimes. Varying the boundary coupling while preserving the symmetries shifts the location of the boundary phase transition. We then consider non-Abelian gauge theories with fundamental and group-valued Higgs matter, and identify the analogous non-Abelian global symmetry acting on the boundary generated by the total color charge. For SU($N$) gauge theory with fundamental Higgs matter we argue for a boundary phase transition in the O($2N$) universality class, verified numerically for $N=2,3$. For group-valued Higgs matter, the boundary theory is a principal chiral model exhibiting chiral symmetry breaking. We further demonstrate this mechanism in theories with higher-form Higgs fields. We show how the higher-form matter symmetry acts at the boundary and can spontaneously break, exhibiting a boundary confinement-deconfinement transition. We also study the electric-magnetic dual theory, demonstrating a dual magnetic defect condensation transition at the boundary. We discuss some implications and extensions of these findings and what they may imply for the relation between Higgs and SPT phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17001v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristian Tyn Kai Chung, Rafael Flores-Calder\'on, Rafael C. Torres, Pedro Ribeiro, Sergej Moroz, Paul McClarty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creation of domain-wall Skyrmions in chiral magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19056v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the capture of a magnetic Skyrmion into a domain wall (DW) structure in chiral magnets and find that in the respective ground states of the DW and the Skyrmion, they repel each other. This means that an isolated magnetic Skyrmion cannot a priori enter the DW and become a DW-Skyrmion. However, rotating the DW's phase away from the stable phase may cause the successful capture and hence creation of a stable bound state of a magnetic Skyrmion and a DW: the DW-Skyrmion. At certain distances, the DW may also destroy the magnetic Skyrmion by inducing shrinkage of the latter. This happens as the isolated magnetic Skyrmion has negative DMI energy, whereas the DW-Skyrmion has positive DMI energy; in a finite range from the DW, the magnetic Skyrmion can be pushed to have vanishing DMI energy, for which it collapses to a point. En passant, we find the possibility of pair creation of a Skyrmion anti-DW-Skyrmion pair and a creation of more than one DW-Skyrmions by a Kibble-like mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19056v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.117106</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl. Phys. B 1019, 117106 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sven Bjarke Gudnason, Yuki Amari, Muneto Nitta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localized Chiral Magnetic Effect in equilibrium QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17616v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the impact of a non-uniform magnetic background field on the Chiral Magnetic Effect (CME) in equilibrium QCD using lattice simulations with 2+1 flavors of dynamical staggered quarks at the physical point. We show that in the presence of a non-uniform magnetic field the CME manifests itself via a localized electromagnetic current density along the direction of the field, which integrates to zero over the full volume. Our primary observable is the leading-order coefficient of the current in a chiral chemical potential expansion, which we compute for various lattice spacings and extrapolate to the continuum limit. Our findings demonstrate that, even though the global spatial average of the CME conductivity vanishes in equilibrium, steady currents still exist locally. Thus, spatially modulated magnetic fields provide a possible way of generating a non-trivial CME signal in equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17616v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dwx4-5rmy</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>B. B. Brandt, G. Endr\H{o}di, E. Garnacho-Velasco, G. Mark\'o, A. D. M. Valois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circumventing Cosmic Variance via Remote Quadrupole Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07412v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A number of important cosmological questions can be addressed only by probing perturbation modes on the largest accessible scales. One promising probe of these modes is the Kamionkowski-Loeb effect, i.e., the polarization induced in the cosmic microwave background (CMB) by Thomson scattering in galaxy clusters, which is proportional to the CMB quadrupole measured at the cluster's location and look-back time. We develop a Fisher formalism for assessing the amount of new information that can be obtained from a future remote quadrupole survey. To demonstrate the constraining power of such a survey, we apply our formalism to a model that suppresses the primordial power spectrum on large scales but is poorly constrained with existing CMB data. We find that the constraints can be improved by over $3\sigma$ for a survey that measures around 100 clusters over $20\%$ of the sky with a signal-to-noise ratio of $3$. In the most optimistic case with a low-noise survey with dense full-sky coverage and only a single degree of freedom in the theory, the constraint improves to over $7\sigma$ beyond local CMB data. Our formalism, which is based in real space rather than harmonic space, can be used to explore a wide range of survey designs, and our results paint an optimistic picture for the utility of remote quadrupole measurements to probe physics on the largest observable scales in the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07412v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dxzl-fcyx</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Arsalan Adil, Reid Koutras, Emory F. Bunn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality defect in a deformed transverse-field Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17317v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Physical quantities with long lifetimes have both theoretical significance in the study of quantum many-body systems and practical implications for quantum technologies. In this manuscript, we investigate the roles played by topological defects in the construction of quasi-conserved quantities, using as a prototypical example the Kramers-Wannier duality defect in a deformed 1d quantum transverse field Ising model. We construct the duality defect Hamiltonian in three different ways: half-chain Kramers-Wannier transformation, utilization of techniques in the Ising fusion category, and defect-modified weak integrability breaking deformation. The third method is also applicable for the study of generic integrable defects under weak integrability breaking deformations. We also work out the deformation of defect-modified higher charges in the model and study their slower decay behavior. Furthermore, we consider the corresponding duality defect twisted deformed Floquet transverse field Ising model, and investigate the stability of the isolated zero mode associated with the duality defect in the integrable Floquet Ising model, under such weak integrability breaking deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17317v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ctxg-k3b6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 033198, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fei Yan, Robert Konik, Aditi Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Computational Complexity of Unitary and State Design Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23353v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate unitary and state $t$-designs from a computational complexity perspective. First, we address the problems of computing frame potentials that characterize (approximate) $t$-designs. We present a quantum algorithm for computing frame potentials and establish the following: (1) exact computation can be achieved by a single query to a $\# \textsf{P}$-oracle and is $\# \textsf{P}$-hard; (2) for state vectors, deciding whether the frame potential is larger than or smaller than certain values is $\textsf{BQP}$-complete, provided the promise gap between the two values is inverse-polynomial in the number of qubits; and (3) for both state vectors and unitaries, this promise problem is $\textsf{PP}$-complete if the promise gap is exponentially small. Second, we address the promise problem of deciding whether or not a given set is a good approximation to a design. Given a certain promise gap that could be constant, we show that this problem is $\textsf{PP}$-hard, highlighting the inherent computational difficulty of determining properties of unitary and state designs. We further identify the implications of our results across diverse areas, including variational methods for constructing designs, diagnosing quantum chaos through out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs), and exploring emergent designs in Hamiltonian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23353v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/21vm-bz3t</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 6, 030345 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yoshifumi Nakata, Yuki Takeuchi, Martin Kliesch, Andrew Darmawan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volume-law entanglement fragmentation of quasiparticles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12379v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the entanglement entropy in quantum states featuring repeated sequential excitations of unit patterns in momentum space. In the scaling limit, each unit pattern contributes independently and universally to the entanglement entropy, leading to a characteristic volume-law scaling. Crucially, this universal contribution remains identical for both free and interacting models, enabling decomposition of the total entanglement into pattern-specific components. Numerical verification in fermionic and bosonic chains confirms this volume-law fragmentation phenomenon. For fermionic systems, we derive analytical expressions where many-body entanglement becomes expressible through few-body entanglement components. Notably, this analytical framework extends to spin-1/2 XXZ chains through appropriate identifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12379v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1572-9494/adf79d</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun. Theor. Phys. 78, 015002 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiaju Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bell Inequalities and Unitary Dynamics in Quantum Field Theory: Scalar and Proca Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03840v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We examine the role of unitary transformations in enhancing violations of the Bell-CHSH inequality in relativistic quantum field theory. In quantum systems, all relevant observables can be expressed via unitary rotations of reference operators. We extend this perspective to a real massive free scalar field and to the Proca vector field in $(1+1)$ Minkowski spacetime. In two dimensions, the Proca theory carries only one degree of freedom and is known to be equivalent to the scalar theory, implying that both yield identical Bell-CHSH violations. After introducing suitable Hermitian operators, we employ Tomita-Takesaki modular theory to construct spacelike separated observables in the vacuum. We demonstrate that unitary deformations significantly increase the Bell-CHSH violation, approaching the Tsirelson bound, and we report the first explicit evaluation of such violation in a vector-field vacuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03840v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. O. R. Azevedo, F. M. Guedes, M. S. Guimaraes, I. Roditi, S. P. Sorella, A. F. Vieira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Manifestly Causal Approach to Particle Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18551v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new, probability-level approach to calculations in scalar field particle scattering. The approach involves the implicit summation over final states, which makes causality manifest since retarded propagators emerge naturally. Novel diagrams represent algebraic terms at the probability level, akin to Feynman diagrams at the amplitude level. We conjecture a list of rules that generate all probability-level diagrams for particle scattering processes in which one is fully inclusive over final states that contain no initial-state particles. These rules are confirmed using some fixed-order examples. The inclusivity and causal structure of this formalism may offer insights into the cancellation of infrared divergences if applied to gauge theory calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18551v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Dickinson, Jeff Forshaw, Ross Jenkinson, Peter Millington</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Work Statistics via Real-Time Effective Field Theory: Application to Work Extraction from Thermal Bath with Qubit Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18812v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum thermal states are known to be passive, as required by the second law of thermodynamics. This paper investigates the potential for work extraction by coupling a thermal bath to a qubit of either spin, fermionic, or topological type, which acts as a quantum thermal state at different temperatures. The amount of work extraction is derived from the work statistics under a cyclic nonequilibrium process. Although the work statistics of many-body systems are known to be challenging to calculate explicitly, we propose an effective field theory approach to tackle this problem by assuming the externally driven source couples to a specific quasiparticle operator of the thermal state. We show that the work statistics can be expressed succinctly in terms of this quasiparticle's thermal spectral function. We obtain the non-perturbative work distribution function (WDF) for the pure thermal bath without the qubit coupling. With qubit coupling, we get the second-order WDF, from which the physical regime of work extraction can be pinned down precisely to help devise quantum heat engines or refrigerators. Their efficiency or coefficient of performance (COP) can be inferred from the combination of the fluctuation theorem and the first law, and we find that the spin/topological qubit-bath system generally yields a far better heat engine/refrigerator than the other two alternatives due to the underlying quantum statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18812v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jhh-Jing Hong, Feng-Li Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin of fractional quantum Hall neutral modes and "missing states" on a sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06914v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A low-energy neutral quasiparticle in a fractional quantum Hall system appears in the latter's energy spectrum on a sphere as a series of many-body excited states labeled by the angular momentum $L$ and whose energy is a smooth function of $L$ in the limit of large sphere radius. We argue that the signature of a nonvanishing spin (intrinsic angular momentum) $s$ of the quasiparticle is the absence, in this series, of states with total angular momentum less than $s$.We reinterpret the missing of certain states, observed in an exact-diagonalization calculation of the spectrum of the $\nu=7/3$ FQH state in a wide quantum well as well as in many proposed wave functions for the excited states as a consequence of the spin-2 nature of the zero-momentum magnetoroton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06914v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dung Xuan Nguyen, Dam Thanh Son</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge invariance and color charge fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02102v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The nature of confinement is connected with color charge. Unfortunately, the color charge densities in QCD, the Noether charge densities associated with the global color invariance, are not invariant under local color rotations. This implies that the expectation values of the net color charge in any region of any physical state in QCD, states that satisfy the color Gauss law, are automatically zero for all components of color. In this paper it is shown that the expectation value of the square of the net color charge in a region, a measure of the color charge fluctuations, is necessarily nonzero when evaluated in physical states and the result, while depending on the scheme and scale by which the theory is regulated, is gauge invariant. This holds despite the formal lack of gauge invariance of the operator. Moreover, there is a particular combination of the color charge fluctuations for the vacuum and for a system describable by a non-trivial density matrix that is independent that has a well-defined continuum limit</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02102v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas D. Cohen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Core of Double Field Theory: Lecture Notes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10163v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Double Field Theory (DFT) has emerged as a comprehensive framework for gravity, presenting a testable and robust alternative to General Relativity (GR), rooted in the $\mathbf{O}(D,D)$ symmetry principle of string theory. These lecture notes aim to provide an accessible introduction to DFT, structured in a manner similar to traditional GR courses. Key topics include doubled-yet-gauged coordinates, Riemannian versus non-Riemannian parametrisations of fundamental fields, covariant derivatives, curvatures, and the $\mathbf{O}(D,D)$-symmetric augmentation of the Einstein field equation, identified as the unified field equation for the closed string massless sector. By offering a novel perspective, DFT addresses unresolved questions in GR and enables the exploration of diverse physical phenomena, paving the way for significant future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10163v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeong-Hyuck Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum harmonic oscillator, index theorem and anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21348v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report a bosonic anomaly emerging in the quantum harmonic oscillator, whose partition function is rigorously identified as the Chern character via the Grothendieck-Riemann-Roch theorem, establishing a new connection among statistical mechanics, anomaly, Atiyah-Singer index theorem and Gromov-Witten theory. We investigate how its internal energy relates to the Atiyah-Singer index theorem, showing that the partition function can be interpreted as the Chern character of "physical sheaf" over Eucildean spacetime by using Grothentic-Riemann-Roch theorem. This correspondence reveals the internal energy of oscillator as a concrete non-SUSY manifestation of the index theorem. Moreover, we show that this connection naturally leads to the emergence of a quantum anomaly. Furthermore, we arrive at Gromov-Witten theory through a more direct and physically intuitive approach. As a result, the internal energy of the quantum harmonic oscillator serves as a bridge linking two key concepts in physics -- statistical mechanics and anomalies -- with three fundamental mathematical frameworks: the Atiyah-Singer index theorem, the Grothendieck-Riemann-Roch theorem, and Gromov-Witten theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21348v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunrui Li, Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subsystem Symmetry-Protected Topological Phases from Subsystem SymTFT of 2-Foliated Exotic Tensor Gauge Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22261v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Symmetry topological field theory (SymTFT), or topological holography, posits a correspondence between symmetries in a $d$-dimensional theory and topological order in a $(d+1)$-dimensional theory. In this work, we extend this framework to subsystem symmetries and develop subsystem SymTFT as a systematic tool to characterize and classify subsystem symmetry-protected topological (SSPT) phases. For $(2+1)$D gapped phases, we introduce a 2-foliated $(3+1)$D exotic tensor gauge theory (which is equivalent to 2-foliated $(3+1)$D BF theory via exotic duality) as the subsystem SymTFT and systematically analyze its topological boundary conditions and linearly rigid subsystem symmetries. Taking subsystem symmetry groups $G = \mathbb{Z}_N$ and $G=\mathbb{Z}_N \times \mathbb{Z}_M$ as examples, we demonstrate how to recover the classification scheme $\mathcal{C}[G] = H^{2}(G^{\times 2}, U(1)) / \left( H^2(G, U(1)) \right)^3$, which was previously derived by examining topological invariant under linear subsystem-symmetric local unitary transformations in the lattice Hamiltonian formalism. To illustrate the correspondence between field-theoretic and lattice descriptions, we further analyze $\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2$ and $\mathbb{Z}_N \times \mathbb{Z}_M$ cluster state models as concrete examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22261v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Jia, Zhian Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parity violation in photon quasinormal modes of black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04149v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given that black holes are ubiquitous in the universe and axion-like scalar fields are potential candidates for dark energy and/or dark matter, it is natural to consider cosmological black holes endowed with axion hair. We investigate the photon quasinormal modes of a Schwarzschild black hole with axion hair where the electromagnetic field is coupled to the axion field via a Chern-Simons interaction. We derive the master equations for the electromagnetic field as a set of coupled equations for parity-even and parity-odd modes and numerically compute quasinormal modes by using Leaver's continued fraction method. We find parity violation in the polarization of photons within the quasinormal mode spectrum. This parity violation in electromagnetic signals could serve as a new probe to explore the nature of the dark sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04149v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sugumi Kanno, Jiro Soda, Akira Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driven Collisionless Reconnection of Force-free Flux Tubes: From Onset to Coalescence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06059v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the onset of driven collisionless reconnection and plasmoid formation in a magnetically dominated pair plasma, using 2D Particle-in-Cell simulations. Two force-free flux tubes of radius $R$ are initially pushed together with a prescribed velocity, forming a current sheet whose width shrinks until reconnection sets in. % Even in our largest simulation with $R\approx 1600$ plasma skin depths, the sheet thickness at reconnection onset is comparable to the skin depth. Plasmoid chains develop when the sheet length-to-width aspect ratio $A\gtrsim30$. In the strongly magnetized limit, the onset of reconnection occurs in roughly 2--6 light-crossing times, depending on the imposed driving timescale, which controls the duration of the thinning phase. In the subsequent nonlinear merging phase, the evolution becomes effectively independent of the initially imposed velocity, leading to magnetic-energy dissipation consistent with a normalized reconnection rate $\sim 0.1$. Our results have important implications for explosive release of magnetic energy in magnetospheres of astrophysical compact objects and their surroundings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06059v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camille Granier, Daniel Groselj, Luca Comisso, Fabio Bacchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasibound states of massive charged scalars around dilaton black holes in $2+1$ dimensions: Exact frequencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18740v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate massive charged scalar perturbations in the background of three-dimensional dilaton black holes with a cosmological constant. We demonstrate that the wave equations governing the dynamics of these perturbations are exactly solvable, with the radial part expressible in terms of confluent Heun functions. The quasibound state frequencies are computed analytically, and we examine their dependence on the scalar field's mass and charge, as well as on the black hole's mass and electric charge. Our analysis also underscores the crucial role played by the cosmological constant in shaping the behavior of these perturbations. This specific black hole metric arises as a solution to the low-energy effective action of string theory in $2+1$ dimensions, and it holds potential for experimental realization in analog gravity systems due to the similarity between its surface gravity and that of acoustic analogs. Moreover, the analytic tractability of this system offers a valuable testing ground for exploring aspects of black hole spectroscopy, stability, and quantum field theory in curved spacetime. The exact solvability facilitates deeper insights into the interplay between geometry and matter fields in lower-dimensional gravity, where quantum gravitational effects can be more pronounced. Such studies not only enrich our understanding of dilaton gravity and its string-theoretic implications but also pave the way for potential applications in simulating black hole phenomena in laboratory settings using analog models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18740v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. S. Vieira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral and deconfinement transitions in spin-polarized quark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08130v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the influence of spin polarization in strongly interacting matter by introducing a finite spin potential, $\mu_\Sigma$, which effectively controls the spin density of the system without requiring rotation or specific boundary conditions. Inspired by recent lattice QCD simulations that incorporated such a potential, we implement this approach within an effective QCD framework. Our results show that increasing spin polarization leads to a simultaneous decrease in both the chiral and deconfinement restoration temperatures. The resulting phase structure is qualitatively consistent with lattice findings, and notably, we observe the emergence of a first-order chiral phase transition at low temperature. These results suggest that spin-polarized environments can significantly impact the QCD phase diagram and offer a controlled route for studying spin effects in hot and dense matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08130v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5znc-7ztg</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, L051902 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo L. S. Farias, William R. Tavares</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular families of elliptic long-range spin chains from freezing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13104v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the construction of quantum-integrable spin chains with q-deformed long-range interactions by `freezing' integrable quantum many-body systems with spins. The input is a (quantum) spin-Ruijsenaars system along with an equilibrium configuration of the underlying spinless classical Ruijsenaars-Schneider system. For a distinguished choice of equilibrium, the resulting long-range spin chain has a real spectrum and admits a short-range limit, providing an integrable interpolation from nearest-neighbour to long-range interacting spins. We focus on the elliptic case. We first define an action of the modular group on the spinless elliptic Ruijsenaars-Schneider system to show that, for a fixed elliptic parameter, it has a whole modular family of classical equilibrium configurations. These typically have constant but nonzero momenta. Then we use the setting of deformation quantisation to provide a uniform framework for freezing elliptic spin-Ruijsenaars systems at any classical equilibrium whilst preserving quantum integrability. As we showed in previous work, the results include the Heisenberg, Inozemtsev and Haldane-Shastry chains along with their xxz-like q-deformations (face-type), or the antiperiodic Haldane-Shastry chain of Fukui-Kawakami, its elliptic generalisation of Sechin-Zotov, and their completely anisotropic q-deformations due to Matushko-Zotov (vertex type). Finally, we show how freezing fits in the setting of 'hybrid' integrable systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13104v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rob Klabbers, Jules Lamers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Generalized Crystalline Equivalence Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10978v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a general version of the crystalline equivalence principle which gives an equivalence of categories between a category of TQFTs defined on a generic space with $G$-symmetry, and a category of TQFTs with internal symmetry. We give a definition and classification of anomalies associated to TQFTs in the presence of spatial symmetry, which we then generalize to a definition of an anomaly for a categorical symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10978v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Devon Stockall, Matthew Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Big bounce and black bounce in quasi-topological gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00137v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the framework of quasi-topological (QT) gravity, we propose a novel model which is characterized by a bounce of the spacetime such that the singularity in standard general relativity can be avoided in both cosmological and black hole setups. Specifically, in the cosmological background, this model reproduces the modified Friedmann equation proposed in loop quantum cosmology, while in a black hole background, it produces a black bounce metric identical to that of the quantum Oppenheimer-Snyder (qOS) model. This model resolves the singularity presented in the qOS model and provides a unified, manifestly covariant framework for general spacetimes, from which both the modified Friedmann equation and the qOS black hole metric can be derived. Furthermore, it establishes a profound correspondence between the effective dynamics of loop quantum cosmology and the QT gravity theory, suggesting that certain quantum gravitational effects in loop quantum gravity can be captured by adding an infinite tower of higher-curvature corrections to the Einstein-Hilbert action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00137v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Ling, Zhangping Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
