<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 13:22:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Principle of Diminishing Potentialities in Large N Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A connection between the completion of quantum mechanics featuring events and the theory of emergent spacetime in quantum gravity where von Neumann algebra plays a vital role is established. In thermal equilibrium, we show that the Principle of Diminishing Potentialities (PDP) holds for the large $N$ algebra of $\mathcal{N}=4$ Super Yang-Mills (SYM) theory with gauge group $SU(N)$ when the temperature is higher than Hawking-Page temperature. Below Hawking-Page transition and for the case of zero temperature, PDP does not hold. Since the centralizer of thermofield double state on the large $N$ algebra of $\mathcal{N}=4$ SYM theory coincides with the center of the large $N$ algebra which is trivial, we extend the large $N$ algebra by performing crossed product by the maximal abelian subgroup $H $ of the compact symmetry group $G$ of the two-sided eternal black hole. In this case, the centralizer of thermofield double state is non-trivial and it is given by the action of the maximal abelian subgroup $H$ on the Hilbert space $\mathcal{H}_{TFD} \otimes L^{2} (H)$. This centralizer is by itself commutative and it coincides with its own center. This implies that the first actual event that initiate the ``Events-Trees-Histories'' dynamical evolution in this framework is given by the spectral projectors associated to the action of the Cartan subalgebra $\mathfrak{h}$ of the Lie algebra $\mathfrak{g}$ associated to the group $G$ on the Hilbert space $\mathcal{H}_{TFD} \otimes L^{2} (H)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11688v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bik Soon Sia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Line Operators in 3d Holomorphic QFT: Meromorphic Tensor Categories and dg-Shifted Yangians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study line operators and their OPE's in perturbative 3d holomorphic-topological QFT's, including holomorphic-topological twists (quarter-BPS sectors) of 3d $N=2$ theories. In particular, we develop the representation theory of the category $C$ of perturbative line operators and its chiral tensor product, by generalizing techniques introduced by Costello and collaborators. We argue that lines are equivalent to modules for an $A_\infty$ algebra $A^!$ that's Koszul-dual to bulk local operators. We further establish a non-renormalization theorem for the OPE's of lines in a large class of theories (dubbed quasi-linear), allowing an exact resummation of quantum corrections. Based on physics arguments, we propose axioms for the full algebraic structure on $A^!$, calling it a "dg-shifted Yangian," which controls the OPE of lines. A key part of the structure is a Maurer-Cartan element $r(z)\in A^!\otimes A^!(\!(z^{-1})\!)$ that satisfies an $A_\infty$ generalization of the Yang-Baxter equation. As examples, we consider 3d $N=2$ gauge theories with arbitrary Chern-Simons levels, linear matter, and superpotential, and explicitly compute 1) perturbative bulk local operators (as $A_\infty$-chiral algebras); and 2) the Koszul-duals $A^!$ (proving they are dg-shifted Yangians).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11749v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tudor Dimofte, Wenjun Niu, Victor Py</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Double Copy of Maximal Supersymmetry in $D=10$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We continue the program of using homotopy algebras to obtain off-shell, local and gauge redundant derivations of the double copy relations between gauge theory and gravity. We apply it to $N=1$ super-Yang-Mills theory in $D=10$ in order to obtain type IIA or type IIB supergravity, at least to cubic order in fields. Furthermore, we show how the super-Lie algebra of global supersymmetries, acting on the homotopy algebra of $N=1$ super-Yang-Mills theory, double copies to the maximal supersymmetry of supergravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11753v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Bonezzi, Giuseppe Casale, Olaf Hohm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hilbert Space of Finite $N$ Multi-matrix Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Hilbert space structure of gauge-invariant operators emergent in large-$N$ multi-matrix quantum mechanics. Building on the framework of \cite{deMelloKoch:2025ngs}, we identify a class of light single-trace operators that behave like free creation operators at low energy but saturate beyond a critical excitation level, ceasing to generate new states. This $q$-reducibility is a direct consequence of finite N trace identities and leads to a dramatic truncation of the high-energy spectrum of the emergent theory. The resulting number of independent degrees of freedom is far smaller than na\"ive semiclassical expectations, providing a concrete mechanism for how nonperturbative constraints shape the ultraviolet behaviour of emergent theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11986v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert de Mello Koch, Antal Jevicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Instantons in Gross-Neveu and Gross-Neveu-Yukawa models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study fermionic instantons of the Gross-Neveu and the Gross-Neveu-Yukawa models. We derive solutions for both models and examine the corresponding actions at the fixed points. We further map the solutions on to the sphere and discuss the relation to the Hubbard-Stratonovich approach. Close to the fixed points we compare and identify the results with those obtained in the large $N$ computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12080v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Imaanpur, S. E. Sadati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge origami and quiver W-algebras IV: Pandharipande--Thomas $qq$-characters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a contour integral formalism for computing the K-theoretic equivariant 3-vertex. Within the Jeffrey--Kirwan (JK) residue framework, we show that, by an appropriate choice of the reference vector, both the equivariant Donaldson--Thomas (DT) and Pandharipande--Thomas (PT) 3-vertices can be extracted from the same integrand. We analyze three distinct limits of the PT 3-vertex, recovering the unrefined topological vertex, the refined topological vertex, and the Macdonald refined topological vertex. Higher-rank extensions of PT counting and the DT/PT correspondence are also explored. From a quantum algebraic perspective, we construct an operator version of the equivariant PT 3-vertex and term it the Pandharipande--Thomas $qq$-character. We then discuss its connection with the quantum toroidal $\mathfrak{gl}_{1}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12125v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taro Kimura, Go Noshita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 4-fold Pandharipande--Thomas vertex and Jeffrey--Kirwan residue</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a contour integral formalism for computing the K-theoretic equivariant Pandharipande--Thomas (PT) 4-vertex. Within the Jeffrey--Kirwan (JK) residue framework, we show that the PT 4-vertex can be obtained from the same integrand as the Donaldson--Thomas (DT) 4-vertex by choosing a different reference vector. We illustrate the formalism through examples involving curves and surfaces on the 4-fold. Furthermore, we investigate the DT/PT correspondence for the 4-fold setting together with its higher rank and supergroup-like generalizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12128v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taro Kimura, Go Noshita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instability of sphalerons in $\phi^4$ models with a false vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A one-parameter family of nonlinear (quartic) Klein-Gordon models having a sphaleron solution is studied. The sphaleron arises from a saddle point between true and false vacua in the energy functional. Its instability is shown be governed by a Heun differential equation after a change of variable. This allows an explicit formulation of the eigenfunctions and eigenvalues to be obtained in terms of local Heun functions. Good approximations are found for certain ranges of the parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12150v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen C. Anco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Corner Polynomials: A Generalization of Super Macdonald Polynomials and Their VOA Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12267v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a family of partially symmetric polynomials, which we call quantum corner polynomials, as a generalization of the Sergeev-Veselov super Macdonald polynomials. We show that these quantum corner polynomials are precisely the partially symmetric polynomials corresponding to the quantum corner VOAs. Furthermore, we provide a detailed proof of the partial symmetricity of these polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12267v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panupong Cheewaphutthisakun, Jun'ichi Shiraishi, Keng Wiboonton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holography for stress-energy tensor flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12275v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the holographic description for general stress-energy tensor deformations in arbitrary dimensions using the metric flow approach. Mixed boundary conditions corresponding to these deformations emerge from solutions to the metric flow equations. To test this proposal, we analyze planar AdS black holes with such boundary conditions and find that the deformed energies satisfy flow equations consistent with the field theory interpretation. We further derive the commuting condition for stress-energy tensor deformations and extend the mixed boundary condition description to accommodate families of commuting deformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12275v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi-Yang Ran, Feng Hao, Hao Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdS3 integrability, Sine-Gordon and fractional supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12316v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The massless S-matrix of the pure RR AdS3 X S3 X T4 theory is very similar but not quite the same as Fendley-Intriligator's N=2 S-matrix, in turns related to Sine-Gordon taken at a special coupling. In this short note we review the reason why supersymmetry emerges but with a fractional statistics of the particles. We then use this to obtain a very simple interpolating S-matrix between massless AdS3 and Sine-Gordon, and further find two interpolating S-matrices between these and the mixed-flux relativistic S-matrix, solving the Yang-Baxter equation all the way in-between. They are all relativistic invariant and braiding unitary, can be written in terms of particles with fractional statistics, and they might serve the purpose to embed into a parent integrable system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12316v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Torrielli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CUDA Assisted Swampland and Black Hole Thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by string theory activities, we investigate the swampland program in the black hole context via CUDA numerical computations. Precisely, we study charged black hole solutions submerged in a hypergeometric inflationary potential extracted from Gauss-Bonnet scalar couplings to the Einstein-Maxwell-Hilbert action. Exploiting CUDA enabled parallel programming techniques, we examine the scalar potential behaviors permitting to derive the physically relevant roots of the black hole metric function. Equipped with more powerful CUDA techniques, we explore the effects of the parametric quantities on such roots supporting a swampland investigation. Accordingly, we establish a relationship between the charge $Q$ and the mass $M$ of a charged black hole allowing to approach the extremal limit and the cosmic horizon behaviors. Furthermore, we highlight the implications of the scalar field related to swampland conjectures including the moduli distance. Employing certain developed CUDA techniques to extract criticality conditions via black hole thermodynamics, we establish a relationship between the scalar moduli and the charge $Q$, enabling to show at what stage black holes can become unstable disintegrating into light states associated with the ratio $\frac{Q}{M}&gt;2\sqrt{\pi}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12378v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saad Eddine Baddis, Adil Belhaj, Hajar Belmahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement harvesting and curvature of entanglement: A modular operator approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12497v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An operator-algebraic framework based on Tomita-Takesaki modular theory is used to study aspects of quantum entanglement via the application of the modular conjugation operator $J$. The entanglement structure of quantum fields is studied through the protocol of entanglement harvesting whereby by quantum correlations evolve through the time evolution of qubit detectors coupled to a Bosonic field. Modular conjugation operators are constructed for Unruh-Dewitt type qubits interacting with a scalar field such that initially unentangled qubits become entangled. The entanglement harvested in this process is directly quantified by an expectation value involving $J$ offering a physical application of this operator. The modular operator formalism is then extended to the Markovian open system dynamics of coupled qubits by expressing entanglement monotones as functionals of a state $\rho$ and its modular reflection $J\rho J$. The second derivative of such functionals with respect to an external coupling parameter, termed the curvature of entanglement, provides a natural measure of entanglement sensitivity. At points of modular self-duality, the curvature of entanglement coincides with the quantum Fisher information measure. These results demonstrate that the modular conjugation operator $J$ captures both the harvesting of entanglement from quantum fields and the curvature of entanglement in coupled qubit dynamics providing parallel modular structures that connect these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12497v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rupak Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement entropy of particles in a perturbative scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The entanglement among scattering particles in an exemplary quantum electrodynamics (QED) process is studied perturbatively. To increase the computational accuracy, we need to consider virtual photon loop diagrams, which lead to infrared divergence. Therefore, when including higher-order corrections in perturbative theory, we use the dressed state formalism proposed by Chuang and Faddeev-Kulish, which provides a finite S-matrix element. The entanglement entropy calculation shows that the entanglement is distributed linearly over the scattering cross section under the perturbation approximation</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12612v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinbo Fan, Xuanting Ji, Xi-Jun Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite-dimensional symmetries in plane wave spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic symmetries of the Nappi-Witten spacetime in four dimensions, a plane wave arising as the Penrose limit of AdS$_2\times S^2$. Imposing suitable boundary conditions at large transverse distance, we uncover a new infinite-dimensional symmetry algebra allowing for non-trivial central extensions. The corresponding phase space encompasses the most general four-dimensional pp-wave metric, including in particular the Penrose limit of Kerr black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12760v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Despontin Emilie, Detournay St\'ephane, Fontaine Dima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interact or Twist: Cosmological Correlators from Field Redefinitions Revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In cosmology, correlation functions on a late-time boundary can arise from both field redefinitions and bulk interactions, which are usually believed to generate distinct results. In this letter, we propose a counterexample showcasing that correlators from local field redefinitions can be identical to the ones from bulk interactions. In particular, we consider a two-field model in de Sitter space, where the field space gets twisted by field redefinitions to yield a nontrivial reheating surface. We then exploit conformal symmetry to compute the three-point function, and show that the result takes the form of contact correlators with a total-energy singularity. Our finding suggests that in the effective field theory, a class of lower-dimensional operators, which were overlooked previously, may lead to nontrivial signals in cosmological correlators. As an illustration, we apply our result to cosmic inflation and derive a possibly leading signature of the Higgs in the primordial bispectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12856v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donggang Wang, Xiangwei Wang, Yi Wang, Wenqi Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Form factors of composite branch-point twist operators in the sinh-Gordon model on a multi-sheeted Riemann surface: semiclassical limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum sinh-Gordon model in 1+1 dimensions is one of the simplest and best-studied massive integrable relativistic quantum field theories. We consider this theory on a multi-sheeted Riemann surfaces with a flat metric, which can be seen as a pile of planes connected to each other along cut lines. The cut lines end at branch points, which are represented by a twist operator ${\cal T}_n.$ Operators of such kind are interesting in the framework of the problem of computing von Neumann and Renyi entanglement entropies in the original model on the plane. The composite branch-point twist operators (CTO) are a natural generalization of the twist operators, obtained by placing a local operator to a branch point by means of a certain limiting procedure.
  Correlation function in quantum field theory can be, in principle, found by means of the spectral decomposition. It allows one to express them in terms of form factors of local operators, i.e. their matrix elements in the basis of stationary states. In integrable models complete sets of exact form factors of all operators can be found exactly as solutions of a system of bootstrap equations. Nevertheless, identification of these solution to the operators in terms of the basic fields remains problematic. In this work, we develop a technique of computing form factors of a class of CTO determined in terms of the basic field in the semiclassical approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12878v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Lashkevich, Amir Nesturov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new recursion relation for tree-level NLSM amplitudes based on hidden zeros</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12894v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this note, we propose a novel BCFW-like recursion relation for tree-level non-linear sigma model (NLSM) amplitudes, which circumvents the computation of boundary terms by exploiting the recently discovered hidden zeros. Using this recursion, we reproduce three remarkable features of tree-level NLSM amplitudes: (i) the Adler zero, (ii) the $\delta$-shift construction, which generates NLSM amplitudes from ${\rm Tr}(\phi^3)$ amplitudes, and (iii) the universal expansion of NLSM amplitudes into bi-adjoint scalar amplitudes. Our results demonstrate that the hidden zero, combined with standard factorization on physical poles, uniquely determines all tree-level NLSM amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12894v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodi Li, Kang Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic force in matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the entropic force in matrix theory. We find the Newton's law of gravitation in bulk can be emergent from the entropic force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12921v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-shui Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical Non-Abelian Vortex String and 2D N=2 Black Hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been shown that the non-Abelian vortex string in 4D $\mathcal{N}=2$ SQCD with the U(2) gauge group and $N_f=4$ flavors becomes a critical superstring. Its 10D target space is a product of the flat 4D space and an internal noncompact Calabi-Yau threefold, namely, the conifold. It was also shown that the Coulomb branch of the associated string sigma model, which opens up at strong coupling, can be described by $\mathcal{N}=2$ Liouville theory. We continue here the study of the recently proposed mass deformation of the U(2) theory with $N_f=4$, interpolating to SQCD with the U(4) gauge group and $N_f=8$ quarks, by analyzing the mass-deformed $\mathcal{N}=2$ Liouville theory on the string world sheet, and show that it is always described by the trumpet geometry of the target space, which is $T$-dual to the 2D $\mathcal{N}=2$ supersymmetric black hole. We use this correspondence to find the low-lying hadron spectrum in the deformed SQCD, and explain the expected increase in the number of hadronic states in the theory with more gauge fields and quarks by considering the near-Hagedorn behavior of the 2D black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12972v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Ievlev, A. Marshakov, G. Sumbatian, A. Yung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mastering Cosmological Amplitudes Using Generalized Ramanujan's Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13126v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a systematic method for computing cosmological amplitudes, including in-in correlators and wavefunction coefficients, in FRW spacetime. Specializing to cases with conformally-coupled external scalars and massive scalar exchanges, we introduce a decomposition into massive family trees, which capture the nested time structure common to these observables. We then evaluate these building blocks using the Method of Brackets (MoB), a multivariate extension of Ramanujan's master theorem that operates directly on the integrand, translating integrals into discrete summations via a compact set of algebraic rules. This yields infinite series representations valid across the full space of external momenta and internal energies. We also develop Feynman-like diagrammatic rules that map interaction graphs to summand structures, enabling efficient and scalable computation. The resulting expressions make time evolution manifest, smoothly interpolate to the conformal limit, and are well suited for both numerical evaluation and analytic analysis of massive field effects in cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13126v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prashanth Raman, Qinglin Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black hole destabilization via trapped quasi-normal modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04779v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the presence of non-minimal gravitational couplings, matter field perturbations on a static black hole spacetime may develop unphysical poles in their linearized equations. Physical solutions confined in the domain between the event horizon and a pole satisfy a boundary value problem, although with boundary conditions which are different from standard quasi-normal modes. We refer to them as "trapped quasi-normal modes". Focusing on a Schwarzschild black hole in Einstein-Proca theory, we find that trapped quasi-normal modes accurately capture the behavior of perturbations under time evolution. In particular, axial-vector modes are unstable, with a growth rate that increases with multipole number. More interestingly, we uncover a new instability that affects monopole perturbations. These results confirm the existence of a novel destabilization mechanism of black holes by non-minimally coupled vector fields, with potential implications to well-studied models of modified gravity and cosmology based on vector particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04779v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ksyy-wdls</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 024017 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hsu-Wen Chiang, Sebastian Garcia-Saenz, Aofei Sang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of the short-range dynamics in simultaneous interpretation of $P_{cs}$ pentaqurks via $\Xi_c^{(\prime,*)}\bar{D}^{(*)}$ molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02601v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate hidden-charm molecular states in $\Xi_c^{(\prime,*)}\bar{D}^{(*)}$ systems using the one-boson exchange model. By regulating the short-range interactions with parameter $a$ and cutoff $\Lambda$, we found ten bound states in isoscalar systems. Our analysis reveals that if the LHCb's $P_{cs}(4459)$ and Belle's $P_{cs}(4472)$ pentaqurks are indeed distinct states, their mass splitting can be resolved through $\Xi_c^{\prime}\bar{D}$-$\Xi_c\bar{D}^*$ coupled-channel dynamics using consistent model parameters. This framework assigns $3/2^-$ and $1/2^-$ spin-parity quantum numbers to $P_{cs}(4459)$ and $P_{cs}(4472)$, respectively. With this consistent model parameter, we predict several new molecular candidates in the 4.3-4.7 GeV mass region, demonstrating the crucial interplay between coupled-channel effects and short-range dynamics in understanding hidden-charm pentaquarks as hadronic molecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02601v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziye Wang, Nijiati Yalikun, Yakefu Reyimuaji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of fermionic excitations in heavy-quark QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09927v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the thermodynamic properties of fermionic excitations in heavy-quark QCD on the lattice with Wilson fermions. The grand potential is calculated analytically in the hopping parameter expansion (HPE) on the basis of the cumulant expansion. Using the grand potential, we compute the quark number susceptibilities and their ratios up to next-to-leading order in the HPE. The ratio of fourth- to second-order susceptibilities is shown to be unity (nine) in the deconfined (confined) phase at the leading order. Excitation properties of baryonic and quark modes in each phase are also investigated utilizing the Boltzmann statistics. We obtain an analytic formula for the quark excitation energy in the deconfined phase, while that for baryonic excitations in the confined phase is decomposed into flavor multiplets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09927v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kei Tohme, Takahiro M. Doi, Masakiyo Kitazawa, Krzysztof Redlich, Chihiro Sasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observational constraints on holography in $(2 + 1)$-dimensional cosmology with a generalized equation of state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11701v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study we explore the cosmic holographic principle, as proposed by Fischler and Susskind~\cite{Fischler}, within the framework of $(2 + 1)$-dimensional cosmological models. A generalized equation of state is employed, given by $p = (\zeta - 1)(\rho + \rho_0)$, where $\zeta$ and $\rho_0$ are treated as two free parameters. The analysis confirms the validity of the holographic principle in all flat and open universes. However, for a $(2 + 1)$-dimensional closed universe, we apply the method proposed by Kaloper and Linde~\cite{Kaloper}, and observe that the holographic principle is generally not satisfied. Furthermore, we examine the stability of the proposed model using the Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) method, and estimate the best-fit values for the model parameters based on observational Hubble data sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11701v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Praveen Kumar Dhankar, Safiqul Islam, Saibal Ray, Aritra Sanyal, S. K. Maurya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acceleration Radiation from Derivative-Coupled Atoms Falling in Modified Gravity Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interaction of quantum detector models with fields in curved spacetimes provides fundamental insights into phenomena such as Hawking and Unruh radiation. While standard models typically assume a minimal coupling between the detector and the field, physically motivated derivative couplings, which are sensitive to field gradients, have been less explored, particularly in the context of modified gravity theories. In this paper, we develop a general framework to analyze the acceleration radiation from a two-level atomic detector with a derivative coupling undergoing a radial geodesic infall into a generic static, spherically symmetric black hole. We derive a general integral expression for the excitation probability and apply it to two distinct spacetimes. For an extended uncertainty principle (EUP) black hole, we demonstrate that the detector radiates with a perfect thermal spectrum at the precise Hawking temperature, reinforcing the universality of this phenomenon. For a black hole solution in a Ricci-coupled Bumblebee gravity model, the radiation is also thermal. Still, its temperature is modified in direct correspondence with the theory's Lorentz-violating parameters, consistent with the modified Hawking temperature. Furthermore, we demonstrate that derivative coupling results in a significantly enhanced entropy flux compared to minimal coupling models. Our results establish acceleration radiation as a sensitive probe of near-horizon physics and demonstrate that this phenomenon can provide distinct observational signatures to test General Relativity (GR) and alternative theories of gravity in the strong-field regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11734v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reggie C. Pantig, Ali \"Ovg\"un</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbations of Solitonic Boson Stars: Nonlinear Radial Stability and Binding Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11757v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the nonlinear radial stability of boson stars with a solitonic potential across the entire parameter space, focusing especially on families of solutions that support ultracompact models on the perturbatively stable branch. Using a dimensional reduction of the CCZ4 formulation of numerical relativity, we dynamically evolve these models with both internal and external perturbations. We find in particular that there are perturbatively stable models with positive binding energy that do not effectively disperse even under explicit perturbations, challenging the conventional wisdom that negative binding energy is a necessary condition for the dynamical stability of boson stars and other compact objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11757v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gareth Arturo Marks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Inference of Gravity through Realistic 3D Modeling of Wide Binary Orbits: General Algorithm and a Pilot Study with HARPS Radial Velocities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: When 3D relative displacement $\mathbf{r}$ and velocity $\mathbf{v}$ between the pair in a gravitationally-bound system are precisely measured, the six measured quantities at one phase can allow elliptical orbit solutions at a given gravitational parameter $G$. Due to degeneracies between orbital-geometric parameters and $G$, individual Bayesian inferences and their statistical consolidation are needed to infer $G$ as recently suggested by a Bayesian 3D modeling algorithm. Here I present a fully general Bayesian algorithm suitable for wide binaries with two (almost) exact sky-projected relative positions (as in the Gaia data release 3) and the other four sufficiently precise quantities. Wide binaries meeting the requirements of the general algorithm to allow for its full potential are rare at present, largely because the measurement uncertainty of the line-of-sight (radial) separation is usually larger than the true separation. As a pilot study, the algorithm is applied to 32 Gaia binaries for which precise HARPS radial velocities are available. The value of $\Gamma \equiv \log_{10}\sqrt{G/G_{\rm N}}$ (where $G_{\rm N}$ is Newton's constant) is $-0.002_{-0.018}^{+0.012}$ supporting Newton for a combination of 24 binaries with Newtonian acceleration $g_{\rm N}&gt;10^{-9}$m s$^{-2}$, while it is $\Gamma=0.063_{-0.047}^{+0.058}$ or $0.134_{-0.040}^{+0.050}$ for $7\text{ or }8$ binaries with $g_{\rm N}&lt;10^{-9}$m s$^{-2}$ (depending on one system) showing tension with Newton. The Newtonian ``outlier'' is at the boundary set by the Newtonian escape velocity, but can be consistent with modified gravity. The pilot study demonstrates the potential of the algorithm in measuring gravity at low acceleration with future samples of wide binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11996v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyu-Hyun Chae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Behaviors in Active Model B+ via the Functional Renormalization Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12065v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the scaling behaviors of the Active Model B+ using the functional renormalization group (FRG) approach, based on the nonequilibrium effective action formulated via the Martin-Siggia-Rose path-integral formalism. We derive the $\beta$ functions for all couplings of the system in generic $d$ dimensions, revealing regulator independence in various contributions to the RG flow at specific values for $d$. After identifying specific regions of the parameter space that define submodels closed under RG transformations, we determine all fixed points of potential physical relevance. We confirm the existence of a bicritical fixed point, which was conjectured within the perturbative momentum-shell RG method for being responsible for the transition from bulk phase separation to microphase separation in active systems. We argue that, within the FRG approach, global flows significantly differ from those obtained in its perturbative counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12065v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gergely Fej\H{o}s, Zsolt Sz\'ep, Naoki Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pomeron evolution, entanglement entropy and Abramovskii-Gribov-Kancheli cutting rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12102v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use Pomeron evolution equation in zero transverse dimension based on the Abramovskii-Gribov-Kancheli~(AGK) cutting rules to calculate the von Neumann entropy and $q$-moments that used as an experimental test for the Koba-Nielsen-Olesen~(KNO) scaling. In order to avoid the negative probabilities that emerge from the negative AGK weights in the Minkowski space, we reformulate
  the Pomeron evolution in the Euclidean space. The resulting positive definite probabilities for cut and uncut Pomerons are used in calculating the $q$-moments.
  The comparison to the experimental data shows that our AGK based model successfully describes $q$-moments dependence on the mean multiplicity without any adjustable parameter in the experimental data of the $\mathtt{p-p}$ collisions by $\mathtt{ALICE}$ Collaboration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12102v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustapha Ouchen, Alex Prygarin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolution of spin crisis, and notes on the Bjorken sum rule, anomaly and constituent quark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12156v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is shown that the widely used parton model expression for $ g_1$ in polarized proton-lepton scattering is incorrect as it ignores gluon-quark spin entanglement. Therefore, there is no spin crisis. A brief summary of results of the theoretical evaluation of non-octet axial vector current renormalization constants and anomaly -anomaly vacuum correlator is given. It suggests that anomaly plays an important role in the transformation of current quarks to constituent quarks and chiral symmetry breaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12156v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Pasupathy, Janardhan P. Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for $P$ and $C\!P$ violation in $\Lambda_{c}^{+}$ decays with polarized beam at Super Tau-Charm Facility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12217v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Weak decays of the charmed baryons offer an ideal platform to study parity ($P$) and charge conjugation-parity ($C\!P$) violation in quark sector, to stringently test the Standard Model and search for new physics. It is a key goal in the next-generation positron-electron collider, such as the Super Tau-Charm Facility (STCF). Thanks to the quantum-entangled pair production with super high luminosity and the possibility of beam polarization, STCF provides a unique environment to probe such symmetry violations with unprecedented sensitivity. In this paper, we evaluate the precisions of the $P$-violating parameters and subsequently obtain the expected sensitivity of the $C\!P$-violating parameters in charmed baryon decays of $\Lambda_{c}^{+}\to p\pi^0$, $p\eta$, $\Lambda K^+$, $\Sigma^0 K^+$, and $\Sigma^+ K^0_S$, regarding to different polarization setups in STCF. The study suggests that the implementation of longitudinal beam polarization in STCF would greatly enhance the experimental capability in studying $P$ and $C\!P$ violation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12217v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Jian Wang, Cheng Wang, Hao Sun, Pei-Rong Li, Xiao-Rui Lyu, Rong-Gang Ping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-invertible Symmetry as a Solution to the Strong CP Problem in a GUT-inspired Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12287v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a three-zero texture for the down-quark mass matrix within a $SU(5)$ GUT-inspired Standard Model, enforced by a non-invertible selection rule originating from $\mathbb{Z}_2$ gauging of $\mathbb{Z}_N$ symmetries. Assuming CP invariance at the high-energy scale, our framework solves the strong CP problem while reproducing a realistic quark mass matrix. The CP symmetry is spontaneously broken down at an intermediate scale via complex vacuum expectation values of new scalar fields $\eta_i$, which generate the CP phase in the CKM matrix without inducing the QCD $\bar{\theta}$ term. The present model incorporates three generations of matter, Higgs, and additional scalars with a common structure under the non-invertible symmetry, which may be naturally embedded into $SO(10)$ GUTs at high energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12287v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuo Kobayashi, Hajime Otsuka, Tsutomu T. Yanagida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics and Joule-Thomson Expansion for Schwarzschild-AdS Black Holes with Cloud of Strings and Quintessential-like Fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12318v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we explore the thermodynamic properties of a Schwarzschild black hole (BH) embedded in an anti-de Sitter (AdS) background, which is further coupled with a cloud of strings and surrounded by a quintessence-like fluid. Beginning with the formulation of BH mass in terms of the event horizon radius, we incorporate the concept of pressure as related to the AdS curvature radius within the framework of extended phase space thermodynamics. Using this setup, we derive key thermodynamic quantities, including the Gibbs free energy and internal energy, to characterize the energetic behavior of the black hole system. To assess the stability of the black hole, we compute the specific heat capacity and analyze how it is influenced by external parameters, such as the string cloud and the quintessence-like fluid. These geometric and matter fields are shown to significantly modify the thermal response of the BH. Furthermore, we examine the inversion temperature associated with the black hole and highlight its distinction from the standard Hawking temperature, providing deeper insight into the phase structure. Additionally, we investigate the Joule-Thomson expansion process and demonstrate how the aforementioned parameters affect this thermodynamic phenomenon, showing important aspects of BH cooling and heating behavior in an extended thermodynamic context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12318v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faizuddin Ahmed, Saeed Noori Gashti, Behnam Pourhassan, Abdelmalek Bouzenada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stringy Constraints on Modular Flavor Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12392v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate stringy constraints on moduli spaces in modular flavor models by analyzing moduli-dependent threshold corrections in heterotic string vacua. While moduli play a crucial role in determining the flavor structure of fermions predicted by modular flavor models, the parameter space in which their vacuum expectation values are allowed has not been fully explored. In this work, within the framework of perturbative heterotic string theory on toroidal orbifolds, we derive constraints on the moduli space and study their systematic behavior. We characterize the stringy constraints in terms of the dilaton, the beta-function coefficients, and the ratio between a complex-structure modulus and a K\"ahler modulus. It is found that the large value of the modulus controlling the flavor structure, i.e., $\tau\simeq i \infty$, lies in the Swampland, and the self-dual point $\tau=i$ is also disfavored in the large volume regime of toroidal backgrounds. In addition, we discuss the phenomenological implications of these stringy constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12392v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keiya Ishiguro, Takafumi Kai, Tatsuo Kobayashi, Hajime Otsuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical r-matrix structure for elliptic Ruijsenaars chain and 1+1 field analogue of Ruijsenaars-Schneider model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12656v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The classical dynamical $r$-matrix structure for the periodic elliptic Ruijsenaars chain is described. The Poisson brackets for the monodromy matrix are calculated as well, thus providing Liouville integrability of the model. Next, we study its continuous non-relativistic limit and reproduce the Maillet type non-ultralocal $r$-matrix structure for the field analogue of the elliptic Calogero-Moser model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12656v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Murinov, A. Zotov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum nature of gravity in self-bound quantum droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the possibility of testing the quantum nature of the gravitational field with an ultracold self-bound quantum droplet of one-dimensional Bose-Bose mixtures. To this end, we solve variationally and numerically the underlying generalized Gross-Pitaevskii equation which includes the effects of quadratic and cubic nonlinearities. We derive the associated generalized uncertainty principle and its corresponding minimal length. The obtained modified uncertainty relation enables us to search for the quantum gravity signatures in both small and large droplets. We place bounds on the parameter using existing experimental data from recent experiment of dilute droplets of potassium. Improved upper bounds on the generalized uncertainty principle parameters are found from our analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12838v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asma Tahar Taiba, Abdelaali Boudjemaa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward extracting scattering phase shift from integrated correlation functions V: complex $\phi^4$ field model in $3+1$ dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12881v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In Ref.~\cite{Guo:2024zal} and associated studies, a relativistic finite-volume formalism in $1+1$ dimensions is proposed to extract infinite-volume scattering phaseshift.
  It is based on the difference of integrated correlation functions (ICF) rather than energy spectrum in the finite volume, and can be regarded as complementary to the well-known L\"{uscher} formalism.
  In the present work, the formalism is further extended into $3+1$ dimensional spacetime. The aim is to explore and demonstrate the challenges in applying the formalism to more practical settings. Specifically, Monte Carlo simulations of a complex $\phi^4$ relativistic field model are carried out in both 2+1 and 3+1 dimensions on lattices of varying sizes, and phaseshifts for the contact interaction are extracted from the formalism using modest computing resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12881v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Guo, Frank X. Lee, Andrei Alexandru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black holes in the external Bertotti-Robinson-Bonnor-Melvin electromagnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12908v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An exact and analytical solution, in four-dimensional general relativity coupled with Maxwell electromagnetism, is built by means of a Lie point symmetry of the Ernst equations, the Harrison transformation. The new spacetime describes a Schwarzschild-like black hole embedded into a general external back-reacting electromagnetic field, which is the superposition of the Levi-Civita-Bertotti-Robinson and the Bonnor-Melvin ones. Conserved charges and the first law of thermodynamics are analysed. Swirling generalisations are also considered. Limits to the known metrics such as Schwarzschild-Bertotti-Robinson, Schwarzschild-Bonnor-Melvin and Bertotti-Robinson-Bonnor-Melvin are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12908v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Astorino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Black holes in $f(\mathbb{Q})$ gravity"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12912v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the work [Phys.Rev.D 105 (2022) 2, 024042], D'Ambrosio et al. investigated spherically symmetric black hole solutions in $f(\mathbb{Q})$ gravity, where several solutions satisfy the condition: $g_{tt}g_{rr} = \mathrm{const}$. This condition is characteristic of many black holes, including the Schwarzschild spacetime. In this Comment, we argue that no nontrivial vacuum black hole solutions satisfy this condition in $f(\mathbb{Q})$ gravity. We demonstrate our claim by reexamining the field equations under the "Set 2" connection called by D'Ambrosio et al., which is necessary for obtaining solutions distinct from those of general relativity (GR). For the case where the free parameters $c$ and $k$ are zero, i.e., Option 2 in their work, we show that any attempt to find a solution beyond GR forces the non-metricity scalar to vanish ($\mathbb{Q}=0$), which trivializes the field equations and does not describe a valid black hole solution. Our findings indicate that the condition, $g_{tt}g_{rr} = \mathrm{const.}$, is overly restrictive for finding new, static and spherically symmetric vacuum black holes in $f(\mathbb{Q})$ gravity. This conclusion does not depend on the specific form of $f(\mathbb{Q})$. We also briefly discuss Option 1 that was not addressed in D'Ambrosio et al.'s work, and give new constraints for the selection of parameters $c$ and $k$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12912v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Xiao Zhang, Chen Lan, Yan-Gang Miao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correspondence between quasinormal modes and grey-body factors in five-dimensional black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12989v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the correspondence between quasinormal modes and grey-body factors for the five-dimensional Schwarzschild--Tangherlini black hole. The quasinormal modes of gravitational perturbations are computed numerically using the continued fraction method. Particularly, we analyze the scalar, vector, and tensor types of perturbations, noting that the tensor type only exists in spacetimes with more than four dimensions. The grey-body factors are then calculated analytically via the correspondence, using data from the fundamental quasinormal mode and the first overtone. We then compute the grey-body factors independently using a numerical method and find that the results from the two methods coincide. This demonstrates that the correspondence holds with high accuracy for all three types of gravitational perturbations. Furthermore, our results extend the validity of the correspondence to the tensor type, which can only be tested in spacetimes with more than four dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12989v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyewon Han, Bogeun Gwak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Symmetries From Fusion Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13063v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $A$ be a condensable algebra in a modular tensor category $\EuScript{C}$. We define an action of the fusion category $\EuScript{C}_A$ of $A$-modules in $\EuScript{C}$ on the morphism space $\mbox{Hom}_{\EuScript{C}}(x,A)$ for any $x$ in $\EuScript{C}$, whose characters are generalized Frobenius-Schur indicators. This fusion action can be considered on $A$, and we prove a categorical generalization of Schur-Weyl duality for this action. For any fusion subcategory $\EuScript{B}$ of $\EuScript{C}_A$ containing all the local $A$-modules, we prove the invariant subobject $B=A^\EuScript{B}$ is a condensable subalgebra of $A$. The assignment of $\EuScript{B}$ to $A^\EuScript{B}$ defines a Galois correspondence between this kind of fusion subcategories of $\EuScript{C}_A$ and the condensable subalgebras of $A$. In the context of VOA, we prove for any nice VOAs $U \subset A$, $U=A^{\EuScript{C}_A}$ where $\EuScript{C}=\EuScript{M}_U$ is the $U$-module category. In particular, if $U = A^G$ for some finite automorphism group $G$ of $A,$ the fusion action of $\EuScript{C}_A$ on $A$ is equivalent to the $G$-action on $A.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13063v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chongying Dong, Siu-Hung Ng, Li Ren, Feng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primary hairs may create echoes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13069v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In most scenarios studied so far, the appearance of echoes in the ringdown signal requires modifications external to the black hole itself, such as the presence of matter in the near-horizon region, quantum field clouds, or exotic compact objects like wormholes that effectively introduce additional peaks in the effective potential. In this work we show that echoes can naturally arise in a different setting: black holes endowed with primary Proca-Gauss-Bonnet hair. We demonstrate that the primary hair modifies the effective potential in such a way that a second peak is formed, giving rise to late-time echoes without invoking any external environment or exotic horizon-scale physics. Using both the higher-order WKB method with Pad\'e resummation and time-domain integration, we compute the quasinormal spectrum for scalar and Dirac test fields and show the appearance of these echoes. Our results highlight a novel mechanism by which primary hairs alone can leave observable imprints on the ringdown signal of black holes in modified gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13069v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. A. Konoplya, A. Zhidenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SO(n) Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki states as conformal boundary states of integrable SU(n) spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct a class of conformal boundary states in the $\mathrm{SU}(n)_1$ Wess-Zumino-Witten (WZW) conformal field theory (CFT) using the symmetry embedding $\mathrm{Spin}(n)_2 \subset \mathrm{SU}(n)_1$. These boundary states are beyond the standard Cardy construction and possess $\mathrm{SO}(n)$ symmetry. The $\mathrm{SU}(n)$ Uimin-Lai-Sutherland (ULS) spin chains, which realize the $\mathrm{SU}(n)_1$ WZW model on the lattice, allow us to identify these boundary states as the ground states of the $\mathrm{SO}(n)$ Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki spin chains. Using the integrability of the $\mathrm{SU}(n)$ ULS model, we analytically compute the corresponding Affleck-Ludwig boundary entropy using exact overlap formulas. Our results unveil intriguing connections between exotic boundary states in CFT and integrable lattice models, thus providing deep insights into the interplay of symmetry, integrability, and boundary critical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13114v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueshui Zhang, Ying-Hai Wu, Meng Cheng, Hong-Hao Tu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Laue pattern and the Rydberg formula in classical soliton models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/0903.5502</link>
      <description>arXiv:0903.5502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent researches of the dynamics of solitons, it is gradually revealed that oscillation modes play a crucial role when we analyze the dynamics of solitons. Some dynamical properties of solitons on external potentials are studied with both numerical methods and analytical methods. In this paper, we propose a method to deal with such oscillation modes of solitons in potential wells. We show that oscillations of a soliton is described by the Klein-Gordon equation with an external potential. Although this analysis does not seems to give quantitative scattering amplitude of a soliton itself, it explains qualitative pictures of scattering. As a result of our analysis, when a soliton is scattered in a cyclic potential, the Laue pattern emerges. Furthermore, since our analysis is based on the Klein-Gordon equation, a discrete frequency spectrum of a soliton is obtained when it is bounded by some potentials. What is especially important is that this analysis predicts a frequency spectrum of a soliton in the Coulomb potential and then we find that this system absorbs external waves with specific frequencies described by the Rydberg formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:0903.5502v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinichiro Yamato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fusion rule in conformal field theories and topological orders: A unified view of correspondence and (fractional) supersymmetry and their relation to topological holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05178v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The algebraic or ring structure of anyons, called the fusion rule, is one of the most fundamental research interests in contemporary studies on topological orders (TOs) and the corresponding conformal field theories (CFTs). Recently, the algebraic structure realized as generalized symmetry, including non-invertible and categorical symmetry, captured attention in the fields. Such non-abelian anyonic objects appear in a bulk CFT or chiral CFT (CCFT), but it has been known that the construction of a CCFT contains theoretical difficulties in general. In this work, we study the structure of the fusion rules in $Z_{N}$ symmetric chiral and bulk conformal field theories and the corresponding TOs. We propose a nontrivial expression of subalgebra structure in the fusion rule of a bulk CFT. We name this subalgebra ``bulk semion". This corresponds to the fusion rule of the CCFT and categorical symmetry of the TO or symmetry topological field theory (SymTFT). This gives a bulk-edge correspondence based on the symmetry analysis and corresponds to an anyon algebraic expression of topological holography in the recent literature. The recent topological holography is expected to apply to systems in general space-time dimensions. Moreover, we present a concise way of unifying duality (or fractional supersymmetry), generalized or categorical symmetry, and Lagrangian subalgebra. Our method is potentially useful to formulate and study general TOs, fundamentally only from the data of bulk CFTs or vice versa, and gives a clue in understanding CCFT (or ancillary CFT more generally).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05178v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Fukusumi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strings as Hyper-Fractons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11678v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically examine all possible Gauss laws obeying spatial rotation symmetry, characterising the corresponding conserved charges. In the case of conserved higher moments, this gives rise to fractonic behaviour. We show that many Gauss laws, including those arising from $p$-form electrodynamics, in fact, produce an infinite tower of conserved moments, which we dub hyper-fractonic. In hyper-fractonic systems, a finite number of charged particles cannot be mobile due to an inability of fulfilling the infinite number of conservation laws with a finite number of degrees of freedom. Instead, mobile charged objects must have an infinite number of degrees of freedom. In particular, the strings and branes naturally coupling to $p$-form potentials provide an example of hyper-fractonic matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11678v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erica Bertolini, Hyungrok Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Max-Focusing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18192v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Quantum Focusing Conjecture (QFC) lies at the foundation of holography and semiclassical gravity. The QFC implies the Bousso bound and the Quantum Null Energy Condition (QNEC). The QFC also ensures the consistency of the quantum extremal surface prescription and bulk reconstruction in AdS/CFT.
  However, the central object in the QFC -- the expansion of lightrays -- is not defined at points where geodesics enter or leave a null congruence. Moreover, the expansion admits three inequivalent quantum extensions in terms of the conditional max, min, and von Neumann entropies.
  Here we formulate a discrete notion of nonexpansion that can be evaluated even at non-smooth points. Moreover, we show that a single conjecture, the discrete max-QFC, suffices for deriving the QNEC, the Bousso bound, and key properties of both max and min entanglement wedges. Continuous numerical values need not be assigned, nor are the von Neumann or min-versions of the quantum expansion needed. Both our new notion of nonexpansion, and also the properties of conditional max entropies, are inherently asymmetric and outward directed from the input wedge. Thus the framework we develop here reduces and clarifies the axiomatic structure of semiclassical gravity, eliminating redundancies and fixing ambiguities.
  We also derive a new result: the strong subadditivity of the generalized smooth conditional max and min entropies of entanglement wedges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18192v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raphael Bousso, Elisa Tabor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement R\'{e}nyi entropies in celestial holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09485v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Celestial holography is the conjecture that scattering amplitudes in $(d+2)$-dimensional asymptotically Minkowski spacetimes are dual to correlators of a $d$-dimensional conformal field theory (CFT) on the celestial sphere, called the celestial CFT (CCFT). In a CFT, we can calculate sub-region entanglement R\'{e}nyi entropies (EREs), including entanglement entropy (EE), from correlators of twist operators, via the replica trick. We argue that CCFT twist operators are holographically dual to cosmic branes in the $(d+2)$-dimensional spacetime, and that their correlators are holographically dual to the $(d+2)$-dimensional partition function (the vacuum-to-vacuum scattering amplitude) in the presence of these cosmic branes. We hence compute the EREs of a spherical sub-region of the CCFT's conformal vacuum, finding the form dictated by conformal symmetry, including a universal contribution determined by the CCFT's sphere partition function (odd $d$) or Weyl anomaly (even $d$). We find that this universal contribution vanishes when $d=4$ mod $4$, and otherwise is proportional to $i$ times the $d^{\textrm{th}}$ power of the $(d+2)$-dimensional long-distance cutoff in Planck units.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09485v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhys.19.2.042</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. 19, 042 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Federico Capone, Andy O'Bannon, Ronnie Rodgers, Somyadip Thakur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$T_c$, Photoproduction, Paramagnetic Anisotropic Plasma, IR Log-Gravitational-DBI Renormalization and $G_2$-Structure Induced (Almost) Contact 3-Structures in Hot Strongly Magnetic MQCD at Intermediate Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07732v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: After obtaining the flavor $D6$-brane gauge fields/their fluctuations in the type IIA dual of T&gt;T_c QCD-like theories at intermediate coupling (via the ${\cal M}$-theory uplift's ${\cal O}(R^4)$ corrections) in the absence/presence of a strong magnetic field, we compute the photoproduction spectral function and get a nice agreement with gauged supergravity backgrounds arXiv:2204.00024 [hep-th]. We demonstrate from the EoS that the holographic dual, in principle, could correspond to several $T&gt;T_c$ scenarios: anisotropic paramagnetic plasma transitioning via a smooth crossover to exotic matter as the universe cools, the stable wormhole, and a paramagnetic pressure/energy-anisotropic plasma. Given that $T&gt;T_c$ QGP is expected to be paramagnetic, see Bali et al '14, the third possibility appears to be the preferred one. We also show that it is not possible that the anisotropic plasma leads to the formation of a compact star. IR renormalization of the DBI action requires a boundary Log-det-Ricci-tensor counter term. {\it Noting (i) photoproduction spectral function determined from gauge field fluctuations receiving ${\cal O}(R^4)$-corrections, if complexified, include a non-analytic-complexified gauge-coupling dependence, and correspond to Contact 3-Structures; (ii) pressure/energy density, etc. determined from world-volume gauge fields and not ${\cal O}(R^4)$-corrected, if complexified, are analytic in the complexified gauge coupling, and correspond to Almost Contact 3-Structures (AC3S) both induced from the $G_2$ structure of a closed seven-fold, we conjecture (i) the lack of $N$-path connectedness in the parameter space associated with AC3S and C3S arXiv:2211.13186[hep-th] to be equivalent to that gauge field fluctuations can not be finite, and (zero-instanton sector) ${\cal O}(R^4)$ non-renormalized gauge fields produce ${\cal O}(R^4)$-corrected gauge fluctuation; (ii) C3S--UV--&gt; AC3S.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07732v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Singh Kushwah, Aalok Misra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microstates of Non-extremal Black Holes: A New Hope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13589v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a new roadmap for constructing microstates of non-extremal black holes in supergravity. First, we review the non-linear sigma model of five-dimensional supergravity governing stationary solutions with a U(1) isometry and present the first generalized Ernst formulation of this model. We then revisit solution-generating techniques associated to the coset model symmetry, Ernst formalism and inverse scattering method. While some of these techniques have been extensively used to generate non-extremal black holes and black rings in supergravity, we demonstrate how they can be adapted to construct systematically non-BPS smooth horizonless geometries that have the same mass and charges as non-extremal black holes. To illustrate these methods, we construct novel static solutions of this type, including a non-BPS generalization of the $\frac{1}{2}$-BPS Gibbons-Hawking center, which has served as the fundamental building block of multicenter microstates of BPS black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13589v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumangsu Chakraborty, Pierre Heidmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Signatures of Chaos from Free Probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20338v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A classical dynamical system can be viewed as a probability space equipped with a measure-preserving time evolution map, admitting a purely algebraic formulation in terms of the algebra of bounded functions on the phase space. Similarly, a quantum dynamical system can be formulated using an algebra of bounded operators in a non-commutative probability space equipped with a time evolution map. Chaos, in either setting, can be characterized by statistical independence between observables at $ t = 0 $ and $ t \to \infty $, leading to the vanishing of cumulants involving these observables. In the quantum case, the notion of independence is replaced by free independence, which only emerges in the thermodynamic limit (asymptotic freeness). In this work, we propose a definition of quantum chaos based on asymptotic freeness and investigate its emergence in quantum many-body systems including the mixed-field Ising model with a random magnetic field, a higher spin version of the same model, and the SYK model. The hallmark of asymptotic freeness is the emergence of the free convolution prediction for the spectrum of operators of the form $ A(0) + B(t) $, implying the vanishing of all free cumulants between $A(0)$ and $B(t)$ in the thermodynamic limit for an infinite-temperature thermal state. We systematically investigate the spectral properties of $ A(0) + B(t) $ in the above-mentioned models, show that fluctuations on top of the free convolution prediction follow universal Wigner-Dyson statistics, and discuss the connection with quantum chaos. Finally, we argue that free probability theory provides a rigorous framework for understanding quantum chaos, offering a unifying perspective that connects many different manifestations of it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20338v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo A. Camargo, Yichao Fu, Viktor Jahnke, Kuntal Pal, Keun-Young Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capacity of Entanglement in Lifshitz Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08297v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the capacity of entanglement in certain integrable scale-invariant theories which exhibit Lifshitz scaling symmetry with a generic dynamical exponent z at the critical point. This measure characterizes the width of the eigenvalue spectrum of the reduced density matrix and is a quantum informational counterpart of heat capacity. We explore various aspects of capacity of entanglement, such as the corresponding universal terms for the ground state, its z-dependence and also its temporal evolution after a global quantum quench in two dimensions. We carefully examine the existence of a convenient entropic c-function based on this quantity both in bosonic and fermionic theories. While in the relativistic case the corresponding c-function displays a monotonic behavior under the RG flow, this is not the case for the nonrelativistic theories. We also investigate the dynamics of capacity of entanglement after a mass quench and show that it follows the quasiparticle interpretation for the spreading of entanglement. Finally, we discuss how these results are consistent with the behavior of other entanglement measures including the entanglement entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08297v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sare Khoshdooni, Komeil Babaei Velni, M. Reza Mohammadi Mozaffar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous quantization of the Yang-Mills gradient flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20514v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate a nonsingular loop-space calculus for the Yang-Mills (YM) gradient flow, in which all variations act within the manifold of smooth loops via ``dot derivatives'' that are finite, parametrization-invariant, and free of cusp or backtracking singularities. This yields an exact momentum-loop representation and a universal trilinear loop-space diffusion equation, valid for any non-Abelian gauge group. We identify two distinct classes of exact solutions. The first is a self-dual (Hodge-dual) matrix-valued minimal surface whose area functional, when exponentiated, solves the fixed-point loop equation exactly, without contact terms or ambiguities; for planar loops the dual area equals $2\sqrt{2}$ times the Euclidean minimal area, providing a geometrically grounded confinement mechanism. We also prove that the ordinary minimal surface in $\mathbb{R}^4$ fails to satisfy the fixed-point loop equation, due to a singular nonvanishing contribution from the loop operator. The second is a decaying-flow solution in which the momentum loop performs a periodic random walk on regular star polygons -- the ``Euler ensemble'' previously found in Navier-Stokes turbulence -- realizing a form of \emph{spontaneous quantization} in the YM gradient flow. We discuss the emergence of quantum-like Wilson-loop statistics from deterministic classical dynamics, potential implications for confinement in QCD, and the role of these fixed points as attractors in the space of YM gradient-flow trajectories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20514v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Migdal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation for massive particles: transport and causality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15531v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Correlators at finite density and temperature encode important information about a physical system, such as transport and causality. For a massive gas of particles in the relaxation time approximation of kinetic theory, we provide complete analytic results for all first order transport coefficients, including thermoelectric coefficients. We demonstrate the first complete picture of the complex structure of the correlators as a function of mass, providing an interpretation in terms of the causal structure of lightcones. We provide a simple criterion to extract the effective lightcone velocity from the cut of the retarded correlator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15531v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matej Bajec, Alexander Soloviev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open-closed 3d gravity as a random ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19817v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate an ensemble of boundary CFTs within the framework of a tensor model recently constructed to model 3d quantum gravity. The incorporation of CFT borders introduces new elements to the gravity theory. In particular, it leads to an open-closed extension of Virasoro TQFT, which in the classical limit gives rise to 3d gravity with tensionful end-of-the-world branes. It also provides predictions for off-shell manifolds with bordered asymptotic boundaries, such as the annulus wormhole. As an application, we construct a purely open variant of the tensor model to study a purely open bootstrap problem in the context of CFT triangulation. We also briefly discuss the extension to non-orientable CFTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19817v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel L. Jafferis, Liza Rozenberg, Diandian Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic inflation as an open quantum system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02070v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We reinterpret Starobinsky's stochastic inflation as an open quantum system, where short-wavelength modes act as the environment for long-wavelength modes. Using the Schwinger-Keldysh formalism, we systematically trace out the environment and derive an effective theory for the reduced density matrix, including deviations from exact de Sitter. The resulting master equation is a Lindblad equation, which reduces to a Fokker-Planck equation for the diagonal elements up to higher orders in the slow-roll expansion, while also yielding a more complete equation in phase space. Finally, we extend the formalism to global de Sitter, for which the associated Fokker-Planck equation lacks equilibrium solutions until the late-time regime $aH \gg 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02070v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue-Zhou Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Tracking Solutions for Asymptotic Scalar Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04161v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the dynamics of pure scalar fields rolling on an exponential potential in the absence of any additional background fluid and demonstrate the existence of self-tracking solutions in which the self-perturbations of the scalar field act as an effective radiation background. The validity of these solutions is demonstrated through both analytic techniques and numerical simulations using CosmoLattice. We discuss applications to string cosmologies with significant trans-Planckian field excursions between inflation and BBN, including the required initial level of scalar perturbations to avoid overshoot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04161v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Mosny, Joseph P. Conlon, Edmund J. Copeland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Confining Solution of the Planar QCD Loop Equation via a Matrix Ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05096v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct an exact solution to the planar QCD loop equation in four-dimensional Euclidean space using a novel matrix-valued momentum loop formalism. Central to this construction is a new loop calculus, in which functional derivatives act directly on the loop velocity $ \dot{C}(\theta) $. This framework yields finite, well-defined expressions for point and area derivatives in loop space and reveals the role of the loop-space Bianchi identity in ensuring gauge consistency.
  The Wilson loop is expressed as an average over matrix-valued momentum loops $ P(\theta) $ tracing closed paths in a compact complex manifold, constrained by self-duality and boundary conditions. Self-duality dynamically nullifies the classical Yang--Mills term in the loop equation, while the boundary constraints eliminate the contact terms in the planar ($ N \to \infty$)) limit. Thus, the full planar QCD loop equation is satisfied exactly and without modification.
  We further argue that these random walks define a self-dual minimal surface in an extended matrix space, and \textbf{prove} that the area of this matrix minimal surface scales proportionally to the Euclidean minimal area bounded by the same loop $ C $, thereby providing a sufficient condition for quark confinement. In the example of an circular loop, we construct the exact surface and compute its area analytically, finding that it equals the Euclidean area multiplied by a universal factor of $ 6 \sqrt{2}$.
  These results provide the first known explicit construction of a quark-confining minimal surface that solves the planar QCD loop equation exactly, and open a new path toward understanding gauge--string duality from first principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05096v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Migdal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2-loop scattering on superstring and supermembrane in flat space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09528v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the S-matrix of transverse scalar excitations on an infinite $D=10$ GS superstring and $D=11$ supermembrane in flat target space. We compute the 4-particle scattering amplitude in the 2-loop approximation and demonstrate that, like in the Nambu string case, the $D=10$ GS string S-matrix does not contain non-trivial 2d UV divergences (UV pole not accompanied by terms with logarithms of momenta is an artifact of dimensional regularization). This is consistent with underlying integrability of this model which is maintaining by adding appropriate local counterterms. In the supermembrane case there are no 1-loop divergences but we find a genuine 2-loop UV pole. This demonstrates non-renormalizability of the world-volume S-matrix of the M2 brane theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09528v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Beccaria, R. Roiban, A. A. Tseytlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbative on-shell multiplet structure of SU(N) Yang-Mills fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11449v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Color multiplets of the gauge fields and fermions on mass shell in SU(N) Yang-Mills theory are classified according to representations of the Weyl group W(SU(N)). The multiplet structure of quark and gluon multiplets has been studied in the framework of a non-perturbative approach by considering complete exact equations of motion of the SU(N) Yang-Mills theory with matter fields. An important case of singlet non-Abelian gluon solutions corresponding to one-dimensional singlet representations of the Weyl group is revised on a rigorous mathematical basis. We demonstrate that Weyl group as a finite color subgroup of SU(N) reveals an inherent color symmetry of quarks and gluons on mass shell which determines a universal color miltiplet structure of quark-gluon solutions in a pure SU(N) Yang-Mills theory and in Abelian projected Yang-Mills theories with quarks. The obtained results allow to introduce strict concepts of fundamental particles, quarks and gluons, which differ drastically from the particle definitions in the conventional perturbative Yang-Mills theory. Possible applications of our results in non-perturbative quantum chromodynamics and hadron physics are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11449v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitriy G. Pak, Takuya Tsukioka, Pengming Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel On-Shell Recursive Relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23510v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel framework for deriving on-shell recursion relations, with a specific focus on biadjoint and pure Yang-Mills theories. Starting from the double-cover CHY factorization formulae, we identify a suitable set of independent kinematic variables that enables the reconstruction of amputated currents from amplitudes. As a byproduct, this new recursive structure recasts the BCJ numerators into an explicitly on-shell factorized form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23510v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Humberto Gomez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic symmetry algebra for the MHV sector revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02098v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the holographic symmetry algebra in the MHV sector. We find an infinite dimensional Abelian symmetry algebra whose generators are the conformally soft negative helicity gravitons and gluons. So the complete symmetry algebra in the MHV graviton sector is a semideirect product of the $w_{1+\infty}$ algebra and the infinite dimensional Abelian algebra. Similarly in the MHV gluon sector the symmetry algebra is a semidirect product of the $S$ algebra and the infinite dimensional Abelian algebra. The extended symmetry algebra has some use. For example, it is known for sometime that an $n$ point MHV amplitude satisfies $(n-2)$ Knizhnik-Zamolodchikov (KZ) type equations. So two equations are missing. We show that the extended symmetry algebra has additional null states whose decoupling give rise to the two missing equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02098v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shamik Banerjee, Raju Mandal, Milan Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impurity screening by defects in (1+1)$d$ quantum critical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09519v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel mechanism of impurity screening in (1+1)$d$ quantum critical states described by conformal field theories (CFTs). An impurity can be screened if it has the same quantum numbers as some gapless degrees of freedom of the CFT. The common source of these degrees of freedom is the chiral primary fields of the CFT, but we uncover that topological defect lines of the CFT may also take this role. Theoretical analysis relies on the insight that the impurities can be interpreted as edge modes of certain symmetry-protected topological (SPT) states. By stacking a SPT state with a CFT, one or two interfaces on which the SPT edge modes reside are created. If screening occurs due to topological defect lines, a symmetry-enriched CFT with exotic boundary states are obtained. The boundary conditions that appear in these cases are difficult to achieve using previously known methods. As a concrete example, we consider a spin-1 chain whose bulk is described by the SU(3)$_{1}$ CFT and edges are coupled to spin-1/2 impurities. We demonstrate that both the low-energy eigenstates and the extracted Affleck-Ludwig entropy are in excellent agreement with our theoretical predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09519v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying-Hai Wu, Yueshui Zhang, Hong-Hao Tu, Meng Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kink dynamics in a high-order field model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.12957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.12957v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study various properties of topological solitons (kinks) of a field-theoretic model with a polynomial potential of the twelfth degree. This model is remarkable in that it has several topological sectors, in which kinks have different masses. We obtain asymptotic estimates for the kink-antikink and antikink-kink interaction forces. We also study numerically kink-antikink and antikink-kink collisions and observe a number of interesting phenomena: annihilation of a kink-antikink pair in one topological sector and the production in its place of a pair in another sector; resonance phenomena -- escape windows, despite the absence of vibrational modes in the kink excitation spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.12957v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00332-025-10196-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aliakbar Moradi Marjaneh, Vakhid A. Gani, Azam Ghaani, Kurosh Javidan, Alexander A. Malnev, Oleg V. Nagornov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projective path to points at infinity in spherically symmetric spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02128v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper proves that, in a four-dimensional spherically symmetric spacetime manifold, one can consider coordinate transformations expressed by fractional linear maps which give rise to isometries and are the simplest example of coordinate transformation used to bring infinity down to a finite distance. The projective boundary of spherically symmetric spacetimes here studied is the disjoint union of three points: future timelike infinity, past timelike infinity, spacelike infinity, and the three-dimensional products of half-lines with a 2-sphere. Geodesics are then studied in the projectively transformed (t',r',theta',phi') coordinates for Schwarzschild spacetime, with special interest in their way of approaching our points at infinity. Next, Nariai, de Sitter and Godel spacetimes are studied with our projective method. Since the kinds of infinity here defined depend only on the symmetry of interest in a spacetime manifold, they have a broad range of applications, which motivate the innovative analysis of Schwarzschild, Nariai, de Sitter and Godel spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02128v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0219887825502834</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Geometric Methods in Modern Physics, Vol. 22, article 2550283, year 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Donato Bini, Giampiero Esposito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant history of gravitational atoms in black hole binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03147v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Rotating black holes can produce superradiant clouds of ultralight bosons. When the black hole is part of a binary system, its cloud can undergo resonances and ionization. These processes leave a distinct signature on the gravitational waveform that depends on the cloud's properties. To determine the state of the cloud by the time the system enters the band of future millihertz detectors, we study the chronological sequence of resonances encountered during the inspiral. For the first time, we consistently take into account the nonlinearities induced by the orbital backreaction and we allow the orbit to have generic eccentricity and inclination. We find that the resonance phenomenology exhibits striking new features. Resonances can "start" or "break" above critical thresholds of the parameters, which we compute analytically, and induce dramatic changes in eccentricity and inclination. Applying these results to realistic systems, we find two possible outcomes. If the binary and the cloud are sufficiently close to counter-rotating, the cloud survives in its original state until the system enters in band; otherwise, the cloud is destroyed during a resonance at large separations, but leaves an imprint on the eccentricity and inclination. In both scenarios, we characterize the observational signatures, with particular focus on future gravitational wave detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03147v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Maria Tomaselli, Thomas F. M. Spieksma, Gianfranco Bertone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Analogue Dynamic Schwinger Effect and Non-Perturbative Light Sensing in Lead Halide Perovskites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05032v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dielectric breakdown of physical vacuum (Schwinger effect) is the textbook demonstration of compatibility of Relativity and Quantum theory. Although observing this effect is still practically unachievable, its analogue generalizations have been shown to be more readily attainable. This paper demonstrates that a gapped Dirac semiconductor, methylammonium lead-bromide perovskite (MAPbBr$_3$), exhibits analogue dynamical Schwinger effect. Tunneling ionization under deep sub-gap mid-infrared irradiation leads to intense photoluminescence in the visible range, in full agreement with quasi-adiabatic theory. In addition to revealing a gapped extended system suitable for studying the analogue Schwinger effect, this observation holds great potential for non-perturbative field sensing, i.e., sensing electric fields through non-perturbative light-matter interactions. First, this paper illustrates this by measuring the local deviation from the nominally cubic phase of a perovskite single crystal, which can be interpreted in terms of frozen-in fields. Next, it is shown that analogue dynamic Schwinger effect can be used for nonperturbative amplification of non-parametric upconversion process in perovskites driven simultaneously by multiple optical fields. This discovery demonstrates the potential for material response beyond perturbation theory in the Schwinger regime, offering extremely sensitive light detection and amplification across an ultrabroad spectral range not accessible by conventional devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05032v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsphotonics.5c01360</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dusan Lorenc, Artem G. Volosniev, Ayan A. Zhumekenov, Seungho Lee, Maria Ib\'a\~nez, Osman M. Bakr, Mikhail Lemeshko, Zhanybek Alpichshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The geometric phase transition of the three-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15123v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: After fifty years of lattice gauge theories (LGTs), the nature of the transition between their topological phases (confinement/deconfinement) remains challenging due to the absence of a local order parameter. In this work, we conduct a percolation analysis of Wegner's three-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge model using intensive Monte Carlo simulations and finite-size scaling, offering fresh insights into the topological phase transitions of gauge-invariant systems. We demonstrate that, regardless of the connection rules, geometrical loops, constructed by piercing excited plaquettes percolate precisely at the thermal critical point $T_{\rm c}$, with critical exponents coinciding with those of the loop representation of the dual 3D Ising model. Further, we construct Fortuin-Kasteleyn (FK) clusters in a random-cluster representation, showing that they also percolate at $T_{\rm c}$, enabling access to all thermal critical exponents. Strikingly, the Binder cumulants of the percolation order parameters for both loops and FK clusters reveal a pseudo-first-order transition. This work sheds new light on the critical behavior of pure LGTs, with potential implications for condensed matter systems and quantum error correction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15123v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ramgopal Agrawal, Leticia F. Cugliandolo, Lara Faoro, Lev B. Ioffe, Marco Picco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No-hair and almost-no-hair results for static axisymmetric black holes and ultracompact objects in astrophysical environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08128v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: No-hair theorems are uniqueness results constraining the form of the metric of black holes in general relativity. These theorems are typically formulated under idealized assumptions, involving a mixture of local (regularity of the horizon) and global aspects (everywhere vacuum spacetime and asymptotic flatness). This limits their applicability to astrophysical scenarios of interest such as binary black holes and accreting systems, as well as their extension to horizonless objects. A previous result due to G\"urlebeck constrains the asymptotic multipolar structure of static spacetimes containing black holes surrounded by matter although not revealing the possible structure of the metric itself. In this work, we disentangle some of these assumptions in the static and axisymmetric case. Specifically: i) we show that only a one-parameter family of black-hole geometries is compatible with a given external gravitational field, ii) we also analyze the case in which the central object is close to forming an event horizon but is still horizonless and show that the deviations from the natural black-hole shape have to die off as one approaches the black hole limit under the physical principle that curvatures are bounded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08128v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/adc233</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quant. Grav. 42 (2025) 7, 075020</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Barcel\'o, Ra\'ul Carballo-Rubio, Luis J. Garay, Gerardo Garc\'ia-Moreno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Space-borne Interferometers to Detect Thousands of Memory Signals Emitted by Stellar-mass Binary Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18053v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The gravitational memory effect manifests gravitational nonlinearity, degenerate vacua, and asymptotic symmetries; its detection is considered challenging. We propose using the space-borne interferometer to detect memory signals from stellar-mass binary black holes (BBHs), typically targeted by ground-based detectors. We use DECIGO detector as an example. Over 5 years, DECIGO is estimated to detect $\sim$2,036 memory signals (SNRs $&gt;$3) from stellar-mass BBHs. Simulations used frequency-domain memory waveforms for direct SNR estimation. Predictions utilized a GWTC-3 constrained BBH population model (Power Law + Peak mass, DEFAULT spin, Madau-Dickinson merger rate). The analysis used conservative lower merger rate limits and considered orbital eccentricity. The high detection rate stems from strong memory signals within DECIGO's bandwidth and the abundance of stellar-mass BBHs. This substantial, conservative detection count enables statistical use of the memory effect for fundamental physics and astrophysics. DECIGO exemplifies that space interferometers may better detect memory signals from smaller mass binaries than their typical targets. Detectors in lower frequency bands are expected to find strong memory signals from $\sim 10^4 M_\odot$ binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18053v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaoqi Hou, Zhi-Chao Zhao, Zhoujian Cao, Zong-Hong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The First Law and Weak Cosmic Censorship for de Sitter Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19535v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We apply Iyer-Wald's covariant phase space formalism to asymptotically de Sitter spacetimes and establish the thermodynamic first law, expressed in terms of the Abbott-Deser mass. Similar to Iyer-Wald's first law for asymptotically flat black holes, our first law applies to general asymptotically de Sitter perturbations around a Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m-de Sitter black hole, without imposing any symmetry for the perturbations. We explicitly derive the first law up to the second order in perturbation. Additionally, we apply this first law to a thought experiment involving the overcharging of a Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m-de Sitter black hole by injecting energy and charge sources. We find that asymptotically de Sitter black holes cannot be overcharged, provided that the null energy condition holds, thereby reinforcing the weak cosmic censorship conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19535v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/add787</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class.Quant.Grav. 42 (2025) 11, 115008</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daisuke Yoshida, Kaho Yoshimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating charged and rotating black holes in scalar multipolar universes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11807v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, Cardoso and Natario constructed an exact solution of Einstein-scalar field equations that describes a scalar counterpart of the Schwarzschild-Melvin Universe. In fact, this solution belongs to a more general class of solutions described by Herdeiro in [7]. In this work we show how to further generalize these solutions in presence of acceleration, rotation and various charges. More specifically, we describe general accelerating charged rotating black holes with NUT charge in scalar multipolar universes and present some of their properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11807v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian Stelea, Marina-Aura Dariescu, Vitalie Lungu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic and cosmological axion hybridization: entangled photons, (HBT) and quantum beats</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04533v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article it is argued that synthetic axions, emergent collective excitations in topological insulators or Weyl semimetals hybridize with the cosmological axion, a compelling dark matter candidate via a common two photon decay channel since they both couple to electromagnetic fields via a Chern-Simons term. We point out an analogy to a V-type three level system with the two upper levels identified with the synthetic and cosmological axions decaying into a two-photon state. The Weisskopf-Wigner theory of spontaneous decay in multi level atoms is complemented and extended to describe the dynamics of hybridization. The final two-photon state features both kinematic and polarization entanglement and displays quantum beats as a consequence of the interference between the decay paths. An initial population of either axion induces a population of the other via hybridization. Consequently, a dark matter axion condensate induces a condensate of the synthetic axion, albeit with small amplitude. We obtain a momentum and polarization resolved Hanbury- Brown Twiss (HBT) second order coherence describing coincident correlated two-photon detection. It exhibits quantum beats with a frequency given by the difference between the energies of the synthetic and cosmological axion and \emph{perhaps may be harnessed} to detect either type of axion excitations. The case of synthetic axions individually is obtained in the limit of vanishing coupling of the cosmological axion and features similar two-photon correlations. Hence second order (HBT) two-photon coherence \emph{may} provide an alternative detection mechanism for emergent condensed matter axionic collective excitations. Similarities and differences with parametrically down converted photons are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04533v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8bsv-2h9g</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 033164 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Boyanovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the Bogoliubov vs Boltzmann approaches in gravitational production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21877v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the spectral behavior of scalar fluctuations generated by gravity during inflation and the subsequent reheating phase. We consider a non-perturbative Bogoliubov treatment within the context of pure gravitational reheating. We compute both long and short-wavelength spectra, first for a massless scalar field, revealing that the spectral index in part of the infrared (IR) regime varies between $-6$ and $-3$, depending on the post-inflationary equation of state (EoS), $0\leq w_\phi\leq1$. Furthermore, we study the mass-breaking effect of the IR spectrum by including finite mass, $m_{\chi}$, of the daughter scalar field. We show that for $m_{\chi}/H_{\rm e} \gtrsim 3/2$, where $H_{\rm e}$ is the Hubble parameter during inflation, the IR spectrum of scalar fluctuations experiences exponential mass suppression, while for smaller masses, $m_{\chi}/H_{\rm e}&lt;3/2$, the spectrum remains flat in the IR regime regardless of the post-inflationary EoS. For any general EoS, we also compute a specific IR scale, $k_m$, of fluctuations below which the IR spectrum will suffer from this finite mass effect. In the UV regime, oscillations of the inflaton background lead to interference terms that explain the high-frequency oscillations in the spectrum. Interestingly, we find that for any EoS, $1/9 \lesssim w_\phi \lesssim 1$, the spectral behavior turns out to be independent of the EoS, with a spectral index $ -6$. We have compared this Bogoliubov treatment for the UV regime to perturbative computations with solutions to the Boltzmann equation and found an agreement between the two approaches for any EoS, $0 \lesssim w_\phi \lesssim 1$. We also explore the relationship between the gravitational reheating temperature and the reheating EoS employing the non-perturbative analytic approach, finding that reheating can occur for $w_\phi \gtrsim 0.6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21877v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayan Chakraborty, Simon Clery, Md Riajul Haque, Debaprasad Maity, Yann Mambrini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Dilaton Sum Rule for the Conformal Anomaly Form Factor in QCD at Order $\alpha_s$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01904v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an off-shell dispersive analysis of the graviton-gluon-gluon ($TJJ$) vertex, extending previous investigations carried out in both QED and QCD. Within the framework of a non-Abelian gauge theory, we extract the conformal anomaly form factor from the trace component of the correlator and demonstrate that it satisfies a one-loop sum rule, valid under the most general kinematic conditions. Analogously to the chiral and chiral-gravitational cases, a spectral flow emerges in which the exchanged intermediate state becomes localized at zero invariant mass along the graviton line as the quark mass approaches zero. The total integral of the spectral density precisely reproduces the anomaly. We examine how the behaviour of these spectral densities evolves as the system approaches the conformal limit with on-shell gluons. The perturbative analysis reveals that such sum rules are fundamental dynamical features of anomaly-induced interactions. In particular, the appearance or absence of associated dilaton poles is closely tied to whether the sum rule is saturated by a pole contribution or by a dispersive continuum. In the conformal, on-shell limit, the particle-pole interaction yields a nonlocal S-matrix element entirely supported on the light-cone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01904v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Corian\`o, Stefano Lionetti, Dario Melle, Leonardo Torcellini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regular BTZ black holes from an infinite tower of corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08565v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore $2+1$-dimensional scalar-tensor theories derived from well-defined dimensional regularizations of the Lovelock invariants. In the limit where an infinite series of corrections is included, we obtain theories that admit fully regular black hole solutions. We analyze the properties of these regular black holes, investigate geodesics in these spacetimes, and examine the tidal forces, finding they remain finite everywhere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08565v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139772</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 868, 139772, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pedro G. S. Fernandes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toroidal black holes in four dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16790v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: From a purely geometric (kinematic) perspective, black holes in four dimensional spacetimes can have event horizons with arbitrary topologies. It is only when energy conditions are imposed that the horizon's topology is constrained to be that of a sphere. Despite this, exploring exotic horizon topologies remains theoretically intriguing since it allows to unveil structural aspects of General Relativity and gain intuition on energy condition violations. In the axisymmetric case, besides the well-known spherical topology, only a toroidal topology is consistent with the symmetry. Complete solutions, describing the entire exterior region of such toroidal black holes without singularities, have not been reported yet. To the best of our knowledge, the construction we present here is the first explicit example of a toroidal black hole solution in four spacetime dimensions that is free of singularities in the external region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16790v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/adf0e1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quant. Grav. 42 (2025) 15, 155015</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Barcel\'o, Gerardo Garc\'ia-Moreno, Alejandro Jim\'enez Cano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic strings in the complex symmetron model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19830v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study cosmic strings in the complex symmetron model, a scalar-tensor theory with a spontaneously broken local $U(1)$ symmetry in low matter density regions. Using numerical simulations, we show that these strings preferentially attach to matter halos, leading to the stabilization of string loops. While the requirement for screening of fifth-force interactions in the solar system limits observable signatures in theories with universal coupling to matter, analogous topological defects in the dark sector may still influence cosmic structure formation, offering a novel avenue to constrain dark-sector interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19830v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Nezhadsafavi, Levon Pogosian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A pedagogical approach to the black hole information problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17164v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The semiclassical depiction of gravity has provided many important results, such as particle creation effects in expanding universes and in spacetimes containing black holes. However, many questions remain open, most notably concerning the final product of the black hole evaporation process and the conservation of information. From a pedagogical perspective, we review the concepts that lead to this state of affairs, also known as the black hole information problem, and discuss the assumptions and hypotheses necessary for its formulation. Stating the necessary conjectures and results that lead to the geometrical properties of black holes, we present the notion of black hole evaporation and the result that entanglement between causally complementary regions is an intrinsic feature of quantum field theory under the Hadamard condition. We then show that, under certain assumptions, formation and complete evaporation of a black hole can lead to information loss. Comparing such a result to the main alternatives to this non-unitary dynamical evolution, we formulate the black hole information problem and show that information loss is a genuine prediction if no deviations from the semiclassical picture occur at the Planck scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17164v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thiago T. Bergamaschi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the transverse spin sum rule in position space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20468v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss in detail the relativistic spatial distribution of transverse angular momentum, including both orbital and intrinsic spin contributions. Using the quantum phase-space formalism, we begin with the definition of the three-dimensional spatial distributions of transverse orbital angular momentum and intrinsic spin in a generic Lorentz frame. By integrating these three-dimensional spatial distributions over the longitudinal axis, we derive for the first time the relativistic spatial distributions of transverse orbital angular momentum, intrinsic spin, and total angular momentum for spin-0 and spin-1/2 targets in the transverse plane. We verify the transverse spin sum rule about the relativistic center of spin for spin-0 and spin-1/2 systems, and find that the transverse total angular momentum distribution is non-trivial, even for spin-0 targets. We also show how the distributions of transverse orbital angular momentum, intrinsic spin, and total angular momentum change with the target momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20468v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Lorc\'e, Asmita Mukherjee, Ravi Singh, Ho-Yeon Won</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure Scalars for Charged Dissipative Spherical Collapse in $f(R, T)$ Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23605v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We examine the structure scalars constructed from the orthogonal splitting of the Riemann tensor for the spacetime metric describing the interior of a charged matter configuration undergoing dissipative collapse in the framework of $f(R,T)$ gravity (where $R$ and $T$ are the Ricci scalar and the trace of energy-momentum tensor, respectively), and also the way these quantities influence the various physical parameters of the collapsing matter. In absence of dissipation, the energy density inhomogeneity is found to be influenced by the structure scalar $X_{TF}$ and the mass-function of the collapsing matter. Further, the presence of charge affects the structure scalars and the total mass-energy content. The dependence of the various physical parameters like heat dissipation, energy density inhomogeneity, evolution of the expansion scalar, the shear scalar, effective homogeneous energy density, and pressure anisotropy on the structure scalars, have been clearly indicated along with a discussion on the complexity factor of the collapsing configuration. The $f(R,T)$ junction conditions have been presented, showing the matching conditions for the matter Lagrangian and their derivatives at the boundary. The energy conditions are also presented and the possibility of violation of the Strong Energy Condition has been discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23605v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uttaran Ghosh, Sarbari Guha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clarifying the relation between covariantly conserved currents and Noether's second theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14454v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Proper conservation laws, that is, the existence of local functions of the fields whose divergence vanishes on-shell, are associated with global symmetries and are a consequence of Noether's first theorem. Covariant conservation laws, i.e., the same type of laws but featuring a covariant divergence, are associated with local symmetries and are a consequence (under certain conditions) of Noether's second theorem. In this paper, we clarify under which conditions Noether's second theorem, which is mostly known for providing relations between the equations of motion of a theory that possesses some local symmetries, can be used to generate covariantly conservation laws. We do it using mostly the tools of Calculus, in the fashion of Noether's original article, avoiding the somewhat complicated mathematical tools that plague much of the literature on this topic, thus making the article readable for the general physicist.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14454v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuno Barros e S\'a, Miguel A. S. Pinto, Tom\'as Trindade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tightening constraints on primordial oscillations with latest ACT and SPT data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17276v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The oscillation feature in primordial power spectrum (PPS), a fingerprint of not only a wide class of models of inflation but new physics, is of significant theoretical interest, and can be imprinted on the cosmic microwave background (CMB). In this work, we present constraints on periodic oscillations in the PPS using the latest ACT DR6 and SPT-3G D1 CMB data with the precise measurements at high multipoles beyond the Planck angular resolution and sensitivity. It is found that the combination of SPT and ACT with Planck CMB dataset significantly tightens the upper bound to $A_\mathrm{log,lin}\lesssim 0.029$ at $95\%$ C.L., showing no hint for primordial oscillations, where $A_\mathrm{log,lin}$ are the amplitudes of logarithmic and linear oscillation in the PPS, respectively. Our work presents state-of-the-art CMB constraints on primordial oscillations, highlighting the power of the ground-based CMB experiments in constraining physics beyond the simplest slow-roll models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17276v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ze-Yu Peng, Yun-Song Piao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new class of rotating charged black holes with non-aligned electromagnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04850v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a large family of twisting and expanding solutions to the Einstein-Maxwell equations of algebraic type D, for which the two double principal null directions (PNDs) of the Weyl tensor are not aligned with the null eigendirections of the Faraday tensor. In addition to systematically deriving this new class, we present its various metric forms and convenient parameterizations. We show that in Boyer-Lindquist-type coordinates these solutions depend on 7 parameters, namely the Kerr and NUT (Newman-Unti-Tamburino) twist parameters $a$ and $l$, mass parameter $m$, acceleration $\alpha$, strength of the Maxwell field $|c|$, and angular parameters $\beta, \gamma$ that represent two duality rotations of the Faraday tensor, which include the rotation between the electric and magnetic charges generating the aligned part of the Maxwell field. This coordinate parameterization, analogous to the Griffiths-Podolsk\'y form of the Pleba\'nski-Demia\'nski solutions, allows us to perform various limits, explicitly identify the subcases, and determine the physical interpretation of the new class. Interestingly, by considering the limit with no acceleration ($\alpha\to 0$), one obtains either the famous Kerr-Newman-NUT black holes (if the parameter $|c|$ remains constant) or the novel Kerr-Bertotti-Robinson black holes, announced recently in our work arXiv:2507.05199 (if $|c|\rightarrow \infty$ while $\alpha |c|=\mathrm{const.}$). We may thus conclude that this new class of spacetimes represents twisting charged accelerating black holes, immersed in an external magnetic (or electric) field. In the non-twisting subcase, we obtain the previously known solution of Van den Bergh-Carminati.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04850v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hryhorii Ovcharenko, Ji\v{r}\'i Podolsk\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Evolving Dark Energy from LRG1 and Low-$z$ SNe Ia Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10514v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present observational evidences indicating that dark energy may be evolving with time, thereby challenging the core assumptions of the standard $\Lambda$CDM model. Our investigation extends beyond the standard $\Lambda$CDM model by exploring a range of dynamical dark energy models. The analysis reveals that the matter density parameter, $\Omega_m$, changes with redshift, and this change is significantly influenced by the LRG1 datapoint from the DESI DR2 survey. We find that including LRG1 strongly affects the predictions of these models, especially for $\Omega_m$ and $\omega_0$, with the latter shifting from $-1$ to slightly higher values. This suggests that the evidence of evolving dark energy in the DESI DR2 data is driven by the LRG1 datapoint. When we exclude low-redshift supernovae data, particularly from the DES-SN5YR compilation, the model predictions are restored to the $\Lambda$CDM paradigm. This effect is particularly evident in the GEDE model, where removing low-redshift supernovae data leads to $\Delta = 0$, effectively recovering $\Lambda$CDM paradigm. Our analysis confirms that the evidence for dynamical dark energy is substantial, particularly at low redshift ($z \lesssim 0.3$). The reconstruction of $\omega(z)$ and $f_{DE}(z)$, using a combination of DESI DR2 BAO measurements, CMB distance priors, and supernovae datasets, further supports the evolving nature dark energy. These results favor a dynamical dark-energy scenario characterized by $\omega_0&gt;-1$, $\omega_a&lt;0$, and $\omega_0+\omega_a&lt;-1$ (Quintom-B). Bayesian analysis of model evidence reveals that the inclusion of low-redshift supernovae data significantly strengthens the support for evolving dark energy models such as JBP and Mirage, while models revert to inconclusive or weak support when low-redshift data are excluded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10514v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Chaudhary, Salvatore Capozziello, Vipin Kumar Sharma, Isidro G\'omez-Vargas, G. Mustafa</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
